<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. Cyril E. Black of Mr. Mark F. Ethridge’s
                        Staff
                    Transmitted in a memorandum of August 26, 1947, to
                        four officers of the Department by Harding F. Bancroft, Associate Chief of
                        the Division of International Security Affairs; the transmitting paper noted
                        that Mr. Black’s memorandum had been approved by Mr. Ethridge.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d607</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">607</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-21T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="607" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d607">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Greece/8–2647</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Cyril E. Black of Mr. Mark F. Ethridge’s
                        Staff</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d607fn1">Transmitted in a memorandum of August 26, 1947, to
                        four officers of the Department by Harding F. Bancroft, Associate Chief of
                        the Division of International Security Affairs; the transmitting paper noted
                        that Mr. Black’s memorandum had been approved by Mr. Ethridge.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-21">July 21,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Policies of Security Council Members as Reflected in
                    the Work of the Balkan Commission of Investigation</p>
                <p>[Here follow sections on Australia, Belgium, Brazil, China, Colombia, France,
                    Poland, and Syria.]</p>
                <pb facs="0887" n="873" xml:id="pg_873"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">USSR</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It was clear from the start that the aim of the Soviet Delegation was to keep the
                    work of the Commission focused on the Greek domestic situation and to take
                    advantage of every opportunity to use the Commission as a springboard for
                    propaganda directed against the Greek Government. This attitude was clear from
                    the insistence of the Soviet Delegate that the Commission remain at Athens for
                    the entire period of its work, including the writing of its report. The Soviets
                    objected from the start to the Commission’s moving to Salonika to hear Greek
                    witnesses and objected strenuously to the U.S. proposal that it visit Bulgaria
                    and Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>Once it had sensed the trend of Commission feeling, however, the Soviet
                    Delegation conceded the necessity that the Commission leave Athens and
                    concentrated its efforts on obtaining a maximum hearing of the <gloss target="#t_EAM1">EAM</gloss> case against the Greek Government. Also, once
                    it had accepted the principle of sending Commission teams out to make such
                    investigations, it took steps to assure that the number of visits made to
                    villages allegedly destroyed by the Greek <hi rend="italic">gendarmerie</hi>, or
                    other places connected with the alleged reactionary policy of the Greek
                    Government, be visited roughly in equal proportion to the trips requested by the
                    Greek Government to places connected with guerrilla attacks. In addition to
                    their efforts made in this direction through the regular Commission machinery,
                    the Soviet Delegation also went to considerable lengths to introduce into the
                    Commission’s work materials useful for <gloss target="#t_EAM1">EAM</gloss>
                    propaganda such as letters from captured guerrillas held in jail or sentenced to
                    death by the Greek Government.</p>
                <p>Of equal importance to these tactical efforts to direct the attention of the
                    Commission to domestic conditions in Greece was the strong opposition expressed
                    by the Soviet Delegation to the United States efforts to introduce the
                    Macedonian question into the Commission’s debates. While the Macedonian question
                    was introduced merely for the purpose of clarifying the political objectives of
                    the guerrillas, the Soviet Delegation declared that it did not come within the
                    competence of the Commission because it was a territorial question. The great
                    sensitivity of the Soviet Delegation on this point was generally regarded at the
                    time as a reflection of its deep concern lest the Commission pry further into
                    the propaganda directed by the Yugoslav and Bulgarian Governments with a view to
                    detaching the province of Macedonia from Greece. While the Soviet Delegation did
                    not succeed in its efforts to prevent the Commission from introducing the
                    Macedonian question, it prevented a fuller investigation on the part of the
                    Commission which might have uncovered a great deal more material than was
                    actually included in the Commission’s report.</p>
                <pb facs="0888" n="874" xml:id="pg_874"/>
                <p>The decisive evidence regarding the Soviet attitude toward the subject of the
                    Commission’s investigation, however, was its preparation of minority conclusions
                        (<hi rend="italic">Report</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 183–238), and its refusal to
                    subscribe to the proposals approved by nine members of the Commission. (For the
                    Soviet objections to these propposals, see <hi rend="italic">Report</hi>, Vol.
                    I. pp. 252–253.)</p>
                <p>[Here follows a section on the United Kingdom.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
