<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-17T01:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-17T01:30:00-05:00" n="622" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d622">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">891.7962/2–1747: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-17T10:00:00+03:30">February
                                    17, 1947—10 a. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>117. During conversation with Minister of Finance<note n="1" xml:id="d622fn1">Abdol Hosein Hajir.</note> concerning sale of
                            Abadan Airfield,<note n="2" xml:id="d622fn2">The Abadan Airfield was
                                sold by the United States to the Iranian Government on March 11,
                                1947, for $136,682. A copy of the contract is filed under 891.24
                                    <gloss target="#t_FLC1">FLC</gloss>/3–1147.</note> I took
                            occasion to stress once again our expectation that American airlines
                            would receive no less favorable treatment in Iran than lines of any
                            other foreign country. Minister asked if we had any reason to think this
                            would not be the case. I said we had very good reason to think that
                            planes of the Soviet Union would be treated better than ours if present
                            Iran practice continued.</p>
                        <p>I pointed out that Pan American Airways would soon extend its line from
                            Ankara to India. We had hopes that at least a branch or <pb facs="0909" n="895" xml:id="pg_895"/> alternate route might eventually come from
                            Ankara to Tehran and then on to Kabul and India. Stops might
                            occasionally have to be made at Tabriz and Meshed. I asked the Minister
                            whether we could assure Pan American that it would be permitted to carry
                            passengers between Tabriz, Tehran, Meshed; that it could bring in free
                            of duty or taxes its airplanes, parts and gasoline for this internal
                            traffic even though it competed with an Iranian line which paid high
                            duty and taxes on everything; whether he would permit Pan American to
                            establish radio and weather stations wherever it liked in Iran without
                            even notifying Iranian authorities; bring in its passengers, cargo and
                            personnel without any visa or customs formalities; and pay no attention
                            to the Iranian passport or customs or aeronautic authorities at Iranian
                            airports; and above all do all these things without any kind of air
                            transport agreement with Iran and without any reciprocal permission
                            being granted to Iranian planes to fly to the US under any
                            circumstances. I added that no American line would expect such
                            privileges but that under most favored nation treatment, we could demand
                            them since all of these privileges were being accorded planes of another
                            country.</p>
                        <p>The Minister, who is one of the strongest members of the Cabinet and a
                            patriotic Iranian, expressed appreciation for these remarks and said
                            they would materially strengthen his efforts to regularize Soviet air
                            operations in Iran. He said that after much difficulty he had succeeded
                            only last week in obtaining a written commitment from the Soviet
                            Ambassador in connection with trade negotiations, that the USSR would
                            henceforth respect Iranian customs in the importation of Soviet goods
                            into Iran. Minister hoped now to have further success in obtaining
                            respect by the Soviet Union for Iranian laws and regions [<hi rend="italic">regulations</hi>].</p>
                        <p>Whenever I have discussed aviation matters with Iran officials, I have
                            emphasized that the US as an air-minded nation has no desire to hamper
                            developments of air traffic between Iran and the USSR, but on the
                            contrary wishes to encourage such traffic all over the world, on an
                            equitable basis. I have expressed the hope, however, that the time would
                            come when Iran, while welcoming Soviet planes to Iran, would insist upon
                            reciprocal right for Iranian planes to fly to USSR. Without reciprocity
                            there should be no Soviet planes in Iran.</p>
                        <p>If this policy is eventually followed by all states bordering the USSR,
                            perhaps the USSR may gradually be persuaded to liberalize its aviation
                            policy.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department 117; repeated Moscow 12 and London 17.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>