<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Iran (
                        Allen
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d644</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">644</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-28T05:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-28T05:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-equipment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military supplies</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-28T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-28T05:30:00-05:00" n="644" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d644">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/6–2847: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allen</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-28T14:00:00+03:30">June 28, 1947—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>579. I conveyed contents of Department’s 337, June 21 to Qavam on June 25.
                    (Receipt of correct text was delayed by transmission difficulty.) While Qavam
                    showed regret that we were unable to accord the military supplies as a gift, he
                    appreciated Department’s reasoning and advice that he should appeal to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> if and when he has positive reason to believe
                    that Iran independence is threatened and he understands <pb facs="0933" n="919" xml:id="pg_919"/> our refusal to make representations to Soviet Government
                    at present time.</p>
                <p>He said that the occasion for representations to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> might well arise after the opening of the Majlis because he did
                    not propose to take any further action of any kind regarding Soviet oil
                    proposals and Soviet Government might react strongly against Iran on this count.
                    (Qavam’s attitude appears to be that he has put the Soviet Government on notice
                    that their existing oil proposals are inadequate and that the next move is up to
                    the Kremlin to make new proposals.)</p>
                <p>On the question of according arms free of charge, I pointed out that the present
                    Greek and Turkish Govts are regarded by the Kremlin as entirely objectionable
                    and that there is little pretence of any friendly negotiations between the USSR
                    and those two countries. I said that if President Truman had included Iran along
                    with Greece and Turkey in his message to Congress, we would have automatically
                    placed Iran in the same category vis-à-vis the USSR as the other two countries
                    are. I said we could not have taken this step without ascertaining in advance
                    whether the Iran Govt desired to be placed in this category. I recalled that
                    Iran was still negotiating with the USSR concerning many questions, including
                    the gold which he was endeavoring to recover from the Soviet State Bank.<note n="1" xml:id="d644fn1">The reference is to the Soviet-Iranian financial
                        agreement, which was signed at Tehran on March 18, 1943, and expired on
                        March 2, 1946. By the latter date, the Soviet State Bank owed the Bank Melli
                        Iran 11,196,070.30 grams of gold, equivalent to approximately $12,600,000,
                        and an additional sum of about $8,400,000 to balance exchange accounts. In
                        despatch 429, June 7, the Embassy in Tehran forwarded translations of two
                        notes on the matter, dated February 4 and May 26, 1947, as published in the
                        Tehran press, which had been delivered to the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                        of the Soviet Union, Molotov, by Iranian Ambassador Firouz. The text of the
                        agreement was forwarded at the same time (891.51/6–747). For contemporary
                        references to the agreement, see <ref target="frus1943v04#pg_345">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 345</ref>, <ref target="frus1943v04#pg_632">632</ref>.</note> Qavam agreed that Iran was
                    not yet ready to be placed in the same category as Greece and Turkey. He added,
                    however, that Iran might become in that category shortly after the Majlis opened
                    because of the oil question. He wanted to know whether we would treat Iran the
                    same as we are treating Greece and Turkey if the situation as regards Iran
                    should become identical with that of Greece and Turkey.</p>
                <p>I said that I had no instructions in this regard that situations would have to be
                    met as they arose, that situations were seldom identical and that, moreover,
                    identical action was not always possible or desirable anyway. I reiterated the
                    American position as set forth in Department’s 221, May 2.</p>
                <p>The conversation went off surprisingly satisfactorily and ended with expressions
                    of appreciation by Qavam for our continued interest and support. I am not
                    certain, however, that Qavam accepts as final our refusal to accord the arms as
                    a gift and he may delay presentation of <pb facs="0934" n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/> the credit agreement to Majlis for a while hoping that something will happen
                    outside Iran (either a definite agreement between the Western Powers and USSR or
                    a definite disagreement) which will somehow relieve him of the necessity of
                    fighting through Majlis an agreement calling for large appropriations for arms
                    which is certain to encounter opposition in the Majlis and which Qavam himself
                    does not genuinely like. While he recognizes that the agreement gives Iran an
                    excellent opportunity to acquire much needed military supplies at a most
                    favorable price, he still thinks Iran cannot afford to spend 30 to 40 million
                    dollars on arms at this time.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 579.</p>
                <p>Department pass London 75 and to Moscow 67.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
