<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Clark) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-08-19T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-19T07:00:00-05:00" n="659"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d659">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.91/8–1947: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clark</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-19T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 19, 1947—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4483. Thoughts Moscow’s 305, August 16<note n="1" xml:id="d659fn1">See footnote
                        1, <ref target="#pg_934">p. 934</ref>.</note> re latest Soviet move in Iran
                    were tried out informally August 18 on Pyman, Eastern Dept, who observed that in
                    his view whether or not Soviets have made diplomatic blunders depends upon
                    whether USSR is prepared to use open force against Iran. If not, Pyman regards
                    Soviet move as “blunder”.</p>
                <p>2. Pyman showed Embassy Le Rougetel’s August 17 telegraphic report re his latest
                    interview with Shah who expressed view on this occasion that there were dangers
                    in allowing Majlis to get down to work. When asked for his opinion Le Rougetel
                    reminded Shah that if Shah’s supporters block indefinitely opening of Majlis for
                    business Shah must be prepared to accept Soviet blame for delaying tactics of
                    his friends. Shah said he understood this and indicated that he would
                    immediately use his influence to stop obstructionism of anti-Qavam and pro-Shah
                    minority.</p>
                <p>3. Le Rougetel has reported to <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> without
                    comment call upon him by Nikpey during which later told same story reported
                    Tehran’s 90, August 15.</p>
                <p>4. Asked what advice Le Rougetel would be instructed to give Qavam if latter
                    should seek British Govt views, Pyman said that he thought an instruction to Le
                    Rougetel would be drafted in next few days. He was not sure how far his own
                    thinking would prevail with his superiors but he had in mind saying that the
                    sooner Qavam presents oil agreement to Majlis and the sooner Majlis rejects it
                    the better. Pyman reverted to his idea set forth in paragraph 3 Embtel 4154,
                    July 30 and it seems probable new instructions may contain this idea as
                    possibility for Iranian consideration. On this occasion Pyman phrased his
                    proviso as follows: northern area will be reserved for exploitation by Iranians
                    alone and if Iranians find oil there this oil will be offered to USSR at world
                    prices. Pyman said it seemed to him that if Majlis coupled with turn-down some
                    such formula it might meet to some extent Soviet strategic fears as well as take
                    care of Soviet fiction that oil from northern Iran is needed by USSR. It seemed
                    to him that if USSR continues to press Iran for oil agreement in the light of
                    such a proviso, outline of real Soviet policy towards Iran <pb facs="0953"
                        n="939" xml:id="pg_939"/> would be clearly apparent to world—in fact at
                    least five of seven Soviet veils will have disappeared.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d659fn2">According to telegram 4499, August 19, 8 p. m., from
                        London, the Iranian Ambassador called on Foreign Secretary Bevin on August
                        18 to inquire what help Iran might expect from friends, such as Great
                        Britain, in case of Soviet attack. After stating he would need time to study
                        the matter, Mr. Bevin expressed the view that the “Iranian Government ought
                        to make it known to world that it had not tried to back out of its
                        undertaking to USSR to present oil agreement to Majlis. Bevin said that he
                        had always envisaged negotiations between USSR and Iran as being conducted
                        freely whereas it seemed to him that at moment ‘USSR is behaving in a very
                        take it or leave it manner.’” (891.6363/8–1947) <p>Telegram 4499 also noted
                            that the Iranian Ambassador in Washington was going to ask an identical
                            question of the Department and expressed Mr. Pyman’s hope that neither
                            the United States nor the United Kingdom would say anything that might
                            be interpreted by the Iranians as indicative of diversity in American
                            and British attitudes.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Repeated Moscow 269, repeated Tehran 63.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Clark</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
