<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-01-31T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-01-31T12:00:00-05:00" n="718" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d718">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/1–3147: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gallman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-01-31T17:00:00+00:00">January
                                    31, 1946—5 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>690. Palestine Conference met yesterday for two hours. According Beeley
                            (Embtel 658, January 30) following took place: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Bevin opened meeting with prepared statement which dealt first
                                    with October Arab proposals, secondly, partition and thirdly,
                                    British obligations to UN. Bevin said that he did not propose to
                                    discuss Arab proposals in detail because they were open to great
                                    objection that they would meet with immediate Jewish armed
                                    resistance and he doubted whether Jews would ever consent to
                                    them. Bevin said that according to Jamal Husseini’s opening
                                    statement (Embtel 577, January 28) Arabs would resist any kind
                                    of Jewish expansion and thus partition suggestion was subject to
                                    same objection as Arab proposals. British Govt is faced
                                    consequently with unwelcome prospect of imposing some solution.
                                    Bevin said that he wished to make clear to Arab Delegation <pb facs="1036" n="1022" xml:id="pg_1022"/> that present belief
                                    British Govt is that in accord with its obligations to UN its
                                    next move after talks end would have to be, if agreement is
                                    reached, to refer agreed solution to UN for approval; if no
                                    agreement is reached, matter would also have to be referred to
                                    UN, either with or without a proposed solution suggested by
                                    British Govt in absence of agreement.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Continuing his statement, Bevin said British Delegation was
                                    reluctant to be forced to conclusion that only possible solution
                                    is one which British must impose. He asked Arab Delegation to
                                    consider, just as he had asked <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss>
                                    Delegation to consider, possibility of a bi-national central
                                    government combined with a large measure of local autonomy (see
                                    paragraph 6 below) for 2 communities.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Jamal Husseini said any solution would be difficult so long as
                                    Jews are armed. He asked whether British Govt is sincerely
                                    endeavoring to disarm Jews. Creech Jones expanded on
                                    difficulties of situation and said that it was almost impossible
                                    to disarm Jews. Husseini took up this point and asked whether
                                    British Govt is sincerely endeavoring to find a solution on
                                    basis of right and justice or whether it is following an
                                    appeasement policy under Jewish armed threats.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Arab Delegation reserved comment on Bevin’s statement and at
                                    end meeting it was agreed that Arab Delegation, when it had had
                                    time to prepare its comments on Bevin’s statement, would ask for
                                    next meeting—possibly on Monday.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Beeley said delegates from Syria and Iraq seemed especially
                                    depressed but all were gloomy.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Embassy mentioned to Beeley that it heard from outside sources
                                    (Embassy’s 677, January 30) that at January 29 meeting, Bevin
                                    had “dismissed” partition and urged Jews to consider some
                                    variant of Morrison plan. Beeley said that from what he had just
                                    told Embassy (see above) it would be clear that in carrying out
                                    Cabinet’s instructions to explore fully all possible lines of
                                    thought British Delegation was urging both sides, without in any
                                    sense having made up its mind, to consider carefully an
                                    intermediate proposal which was not strictly speaking, the
                                    Morrison plan although it had a number of features in common
                                    with Morrison plan. As an example of differences Beeley said the
                                    bi-national state British have in mind would involve two
                                    communities being actively associated with central govt from the
                                    outset, ultimate independence being goal. Purpose behind plan
                                    would be to “drive the two peoples in Palestine into a position
                                    of responsibility.” It was obviously desirable that Jews and
                                    Arabs should both have another look at possibilities inherent in
                                    a bi-national state since Cabinet is suspending final judgement
                                    until all avenues have been explored.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Asked whether British were sending <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss> Delegation latest edition <pb facs="1037" n="1023" xml:id="pg_1023"/> [“]Morrison plan” Beeley said
                                    Colonial Office is sending <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss>
                                    Delegation, in form of mimeographed conference papers, October
                                    Arab proposals and Morrison’s speech July 31, 1946,<note n="1" xml:id="d718fn1">For extract of speech, see British Cmd.
                                        7044, Palestine No. 1 (1947), p. 2.</note> in Commons which
                                    is also being sent to Arab Delegation. Dept has copy. British do
                                    not intend at this stage to show either Arabs or Jews detailed
                                    proposals worked out by Grady and Brook because (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) proposals are a “US-British document
                                    and not sole property of British Govt”; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) showing map might raise storm which could be
                                    obviated by negotiation and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) some of
                                    proposals are obviously open to negotiation. While British
                                    wanted both Arabs and Jews to think about a bi-national state
                                    they had no intention of going in writing beyond Morrison’s
                                    speech as a basis for their thinking.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Beeley emphasized that while <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss>
                                    Delegation has promised to comment on Morrison’s speech of July
                                    31 and while Arabs have promised to comment on Bevin’s statement
                                    of yesterday, in substance both will be commenting on
                                    bi-national state idea. It was impossible to keep two sets of
                                    negotiations exactly parallel.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Beeley said that British Govt’s efforts to get bi-national
                                    state considered had had interesting result of making Arab
                                    Delegation feel that it was being edged toward partition by
                                    gentle stages and of making <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss>
                                    Delegation feel that partition has been dismissed and that it is
                                    being urged toward Morrison plan. Both sides are indignant,
                                    their differing interpretations stemming from mutual
                                    distrust.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>Asked what move would be if both sides dismissed possibility
                                    bi-national state, Beeley said that British Delegation would
                                    have “to think again,” and consider desirability of laying
                                    before Cabinet a report showing complete absence of any basis
                                    for agreement and asking Cabinet to choose one of four
                                    alternatives: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) partition (i.e. Jewish
                                    state); (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Arab proposals; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) enforcement of some intermediate
                                    solution or (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) abandonment of mandate
                                    and putting problem without any suggestion to UN for solution.
                                    In this event British Delegation would be likely to put to
                                    Cabinet for decision at same time how and when Cabinet’s choice
                                    should be brought before UN.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>