<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        United States Representative at the United Nations (
                        Austin
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d856</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">856</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-11-06T18:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recGV5iJwHKxZYFEb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="financial-stability" lcsh-match="no_match">Financial stability</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-06T18:00:00-05:00" n="856" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d856">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/11–447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        United States Representative at the United Nations</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-06T18:00:00-05:00">November 6, 1947—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>546. For Hilldring from Henderson and McGuire.<note n="1" xml:id="d856fn1">Paul
                        F. McGuire, Associate Chief of the Division of Financial Affairs.</note>
                    Dept favors working group’s revision (<gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss>
                    1146, Nov 4<note n="2" xml:id="d856fn2">Not printed; the revision read as
                        follows: “After these obligations have been met in full, the surplus revenue
                        from the customs and other common services shall be divided in the following
                        manner: not less than 5 per cent and not more than 10 per cent to the City
                        of Jerusalem, and the residue in equal proportion to the Jewish and the Arab
                        States. <hi rend="italic">At the end, of the first year, and every two years
                            thereafter</hi>, the division shall be reviewable by the Joint Economic
                        Board, which shall make such modifications as may be deemed necessary.”
                        (501.BB Palestine/11–447)</note>) and feels strongly that this is only
                    wording <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> should vote favorably upon. If
                    rest of Subcommittee 1 accepts Guatemalan revision,<note n="3" xml:id="d856fn3">Telegram 1146 reported this revision was “proposed by Guatemala in
                        consultation with and to meet Jewish Agency’s views” and read the same as
                        the revision above through the distribution of revenues to the City of
                        Jerusalem. Thereafter it read: “and the residue shall be allocated to each
                        state by the Joint Economic Board in a proportion to be decided each year.
                        The Board shall take into account that no state shall receive a share higher
                        than approximately four million pounds in excess of its net contribution to
                        these revenues, but the amount granted may be adjusted by the board
                        according to the price level in relation to the prices prevailing at the
                        time of the establishment of the union.”</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> should reserve its position and
                    introduce working group’s wording in full committee. Reference last para <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d856fn4">This paragraph gave the text of a compromise
                        wording which was acceptable to the Jewish Agency.</note> Delegation should
                    not attempt to influence wording any alternative proposal.</p>
                <p>If necessary to defend position, <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> might
                    state: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>US Govt considers it an integral part of the <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> proposals that measures should be
                            taken to provide in so far as possible that both the Jewish and Arab
                            States have the means for financial stability and a reasonable
                            opportunity for economic progress. This conception was the basis for
                                <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP’s</gloss> recommendation that
                            there should be an economic union.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> did not provide a detailed
                            definition of economic union. The Jewish Agency has presented certain
                            proposals regarding currency and customs which define economic union in
                            a very limited way. In fact, the Agency proposals appear to be designed
                            to establish economic separation. While in order to avoid delay in the
                            submission of the whole report of the subcommittee, <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has tentatively approved the Jewish
                            Agency’s currency proposals, it intends to devote further study to them,
                            and reserves the right to suggest changes at a later time if it becomes
                            clear that the Agency’s proposals will endanger the financial stability
                            of either state. In the meantime, <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> is not prepared to approve any change whatever in the
                            specific <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> proposal for an equal
                            division of customs revenues, until such time as it becomes clear from
                            experience that some other division is compatible with accomplishment of
                            the objective of financial stability for both states.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1256" n="1242" xml:id="pg_1242"/>
                <p>Above position drafted in light of Dept’s understanding that <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has already tentatively approved certain
                    Jewish Agency currency proposals in modified form, and may not consider it
                    feasible to retract this approval. However, Dept would prefer that US position
                    on currency proposals also be formally reserved. If possible without serious
                    embarrassment, Dept suggests that <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> take
                    position that there is insufficient information available to permit any detailed
                    elaboration of <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP’s</gloss> recommended objective
                    of “a common currency”, and that such elaboration should be left to be worked
                    out during the course of negotiations for the treaty of Economic Union.</p>
                <p>Dept’s economic experts believe there is serious doubt that Arab State can be
                    financially stable if it has to depend solely upon its own tax resources for
                    governmental revenues and upon foreign exchange earnings from exports
                    originating in the Arab State for all import requirements of that State. It
                    would appear reasonable and compatible with <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> concepts to provide for pooling of taxes and foreign
                    exchange receipts and central import licensing for an initial period after
                    political separation. An exception for gift capital remittances could be
                    provided. If <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> feels it is incumbent upon
                    US Govt to recommend a detailed plan for economic union at this time, State and
                    Treasury will undertake to prepare such a plan in time for presentation to full
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee. However, State and Treasury would
                    be seriously handicapped by lack of info concerning economic effects of
                    partition. It is in fact probable that the answer as to what form of economic
                    union will be compatible with financial stability of both states can be derived
                    only from experience, and that initially there should be a minimum of change
                    from economic arrangements now in effect. I.e. the Joint Economic Board might
                    take over the economic functions and procedures of the present Government of
                    Palestine, but with instructions to work out procedures for a gradual transition
                    to greater economic independence for the two states over a reasonable period of
                    time. Dept would appreciate <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel’s</gloss> comments
                    on this approach. [Henderson and McGuire]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
