<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Jerusalem (
                        Macatee
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d917</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">917</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-12-17T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-12-17T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-17T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-17T10:00:00-05:00" n="917" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d917">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/12–1747: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Jerusalem</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Macatee</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerusalem</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-17T17:00:00+02:00">December 17, 1947—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>615. Myerson, <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss> political chief, called December
                    15, complained about Palestine Government.<note n="1" xml:id="d917fn1">Telegram
                        586, December 9, 1 p. m., from Jerusalem, reported that Mrs. Myerson,
                        accompanied by Mr. Ben-Gurion, informed Mr. Macatee on December 8 that the
                        Jewish Agency thought the Government of Palestine was unnecessarily lenient
                        in controlling the Arabs. She expressed distress at news of an Arab ambush
                        of a convoy on the Jerusalem–Tel Aviv road at which the Mukytar of Yagur, a
                        close friend, and a high-ranking Haganah officer had been killed.
                        (867N.01/12–947).</note> Said she saw sinister design in actions government
                    adding while Jews can take care of themselves against Arabs, British and Arabs
                    together too much. Cited several examples of “government discrimination” against
                    Jews, including prohibition against Jewish settlement police using armored
                    cars.</p>
                <p>After adding Jews may be forced to war with both government and Arabs she
                    wondered what outsiders would think if Jews remained quiet under “provocation”.
                    I remarked restraining on part of Jews will not be considered weakness but sign
                    of strength that so much had <pb facs="1329" n="1315" xml:id="pg_1315"/> been
                    attributed to Jews because of terrorism that exhibition of restraint could not
                    fail bring favorable reaction. Myerson wants UN committee here quickly, failing
                    that a UN observer “who could keep eye on government”. Asked that her remarks be
                    reported US Government.</p>
                <p>This frame of mind typical of <gloss target="#t_JA1">JA</gloss> these days as
                    their many difficulties increase. Having at first welcomed British handing over
                    Tel Aviv area to Jewish police, now sees sinister design here also, commenting
                    since British and Arabs remaining in Jaffa Jews will be compelled to fight them
                    both.</p>
                <p>Similar views expressed in <hi rend="italic">Palestine Post</hi> editorial
                    yesterday commenting upon which high government official said government felt if
                    Jews took over own defence same would have to apply Arabs. Jews were not willing
                    accept this therefore government feels their argument not valid.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Macatee</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
