<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-23T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-23T13:00:00-05:00" n="1005" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1005">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112EW/8–2344: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-23T21:00:00+03:00">August 23,
                                    1944—9 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received August 24—2:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3122. ReEmbs 2938, August 11, 10 a.m. [<hi rend="italic">p.m.</hi>] I
                            have received a letter from Molotov dated August 22 of which the
                            following is a paraphrase translation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I wish to inform you with respect to your letter of July 24 that
                                    the Soviet Government, taking note of the assurances of the
                                    American military authorities who are maintaining communications
                                    with England, has in mind that the export from Sweden of the
                                    ball bearings ordered for the Soviet Union should be effected
                                    not directly from Stockholm to Moscow but by the same route used
                                    for previous shipments of ball bearings, namely from Sweden to
                                    England and thence to the Soviet Union by sea.</p>
                                <p>M. A. Nikitin, the Soviet trade representative in Sweden, has
                                    been instructed to undertake measures connected with the
                                    organization of the export from Sweden of the ball bearings. I
                                    should be grateful, Mr. Ambassador, if you would advise me with
                                    which of the American representatives in Stockholm Mr. Nikitin
                                    should get in touch as well as when and where.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>A reply on this matter has been received after a month’s delay and only
                            after pressure from myself on the Foreign Office, from the Military
                            Mission on the Soviet military authorities, and from General Spalding on
                            the Commissariat for Foreign Trade. The Soviet attitude is doubtless due
                            to the fact that they do not want our planes to fly in the Soviet Union.
                            In view of the long delay in replying, it would appear that the need for
                            these bearings is not vital and, as a matter of principle in our
                            relations with the Soviets as well as from the standpoint of the proper
                            use of our planes, I recommend that we decline to transport the bearings
                            to England and that I be instructed promptly to inform Molotov to this
                            effect.</p>
                        <p>I suggest that the reply be made along the line that, as the Soviet
                            Government has had our offer under consideration since July 24 and is
                            now proposing a round-about route which would involve considerable
                            further delay, the American authorities have concluded that the need for
                            bearings is not sufficiently urgent to warrant the risk to the American
                            personnel and planes involved, particularly as it would appear that a
                            safe route may likely be available by the time the bearings could be
                            transported to the Soviet Union by the route proposed by the Soviet
                                Government.<note n="17" xml:id="d1005fn1">In telegram 2141,
                                September 5, 1944, 11 p.m., to Moscow, the Department replied it did
                                not desire any further approach to be made to the Foreign Office and
                                understood that General Deane was being informed by the War
                                Department of this decision (861.24/8–2144).</note> General Deane
                            concurs.</p>
                        <pb facs="1133" n="1123" xml:id="pg_1123"/>
                        <p>Sent to Department, repeated to London as my 152, August 23, 10 p.m.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>