<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1089</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1089</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-01-12T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-01-12T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-01-12T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-01-12T12:00:00-05:00" n="1089"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1089">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 European War/1244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-01-12T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 12, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 13—9 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>269. This refers to Embassy’s 39 of January 3, 9 p.m. Bucknell<note n="34"
                        xml:id="d1089fn1">Howard Bucknell, Jr., Counselor of Embassy in the United
                        Kingdom.</note> has received the following communication from Sir Orme
                        Sargent:<note n="35" xml:id="d1089fn2">British Deputy Under Secretary of
                        State for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“You will remember that at its meeting on 24 December<note n="36"
                                xml:id="d1089fn3">See telegram 8992, December 24, 1943, from London,
                                    <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_852">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 852</ref>.</note> the London
                            Political Warfare Coordinating Committee recommended that the United
                            States and British Governments should decide at once as to the
                            relationship of the Kharkov trials to the Moscow Declaration.</p>
                        <p>We have been considering this point and have reached the following
                            conclusion. The relevant passages of the Moscow Declaration seem to us
                            clearly to mean that, at the time of any armistice with Germany, those
                            Germans who have committed war crimes will be apprehended and sent to
                            the places where the crimes have been committed for trial. This can only
                            apply to those German war criminals who have not already fallen into the
                            hands of, and been tried by, the <pb facs="1211" n="1201"
                                xml:id="pg_1201"/> three powers making the Declaration or any of the
                            other 32 United Nations. It does not impose an obligation upon either
                            the three Allied powers or any of the other United Nations not to try,
                            at any place or at any time where the legal powers to do so exist,
                            German war criminals who may be captured before an Armistice is made
                            with Germany. Thus the Declaration in our view only dealt with those
                            German war criminals who will be handed over at the time of the
                            Armistice with Germany, and is a solemn pronouncement of the intention
                            of the powers concerned to try them and punish them in a certain
                            manner.</p>
                        <p>Our conclusion therefore is that it is not possible to argue that the
                            Kharkov trials are contrary to either the spirit or the wording of the
                            Moscow Declaration. Conversely we doubt whether the Russians are
                            entitled to claim that the trials are in accordance with the declaration
                            since, as indicated above, it seems to us that two different sets of
                            Germans are involved. None-the-less we are not in favor of raising the
                            issue with the Soviet Government, not only because there seems no actual
                            conflict between the Kharkov trials and the Declaration but also having
                            regard to earlier arguments with the Russians about war crimes and to
                            the present deadlock about their representation on the United Nations
                            Commission on War Crimes.<note n="37" xml:id="d1089fn4">Concerning the
                                establishment of the United Nations Commission for the Investigation
                                of War Crimes, see <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_402">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 402</ref> ff; for
                                correspondence on discussions regarding procedures and scope of this
                                Commission, see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_1265">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >i</hi>, pp. 1265</ref> ff.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>We are telegraphing on the above lines to His Majesty’s Embassy at
                            Washington and instructing them to communicate our view to the State
                            Department.</p>
                        <p>We are also instructing His Majesty’s Embassy to inform the State
                            Department that we agree with their view, expressed just before
                                Christmas,<note n="38" xml:id="d1089fn5">See telegram 8101, December
                                23, 1943, to London, <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_849">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 849</ref>.</note> that we
                            should not allow ourselves to be drawn by the Kharkov trials into
                            friction with the Russians. We also agree with them that, while
                            publicity should for the present be played down, the position will have
                            to be reconsidered if the Germans actually proceed to trials or if the
                            Russians show signs of staging new trials.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Winant spoke just after Christmas to Mr. Eden<note n="39"
                                xml:id="d1089fn6">Anthony Eden, British Secretary of State for
                                Foreign Affairs.</note> about a telegram which the State Department
                            had sent to the United States Minister at Bern<note n="40"
                                xml:id="d1089fn7">Leland Harrison.</note> on 24 December<note n="41"
                                xml:id="d1089fn8">Telegram 3222, December 24, 1943, <ref
                                    target="frus1943v01#pg_434">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 434</ref>.</note> instructing
                            him to inform the Swiss Government that the United States Government
                            were not proceeding against German prisoners of war along lines similar
                            to reports of German intentions but were strictly observing the
                            provisions of the Geneva Convention. There seems to us a danger that
                            these instructions might be interpreted as implying that the United
                            States Government regard the trial of prisoners of war as incompatible
                            with strict observance of the Convention. According to our view, the
                            position in this connection is as follows. The Geneva Convention to
                            which His Majesty’s Government, United States Government and the German
                            Government are parties, but not the Soviet Government, does not prohibit
                            the trial of prisoners of war for any war crimes they <pb facs="1212"
                                n="1202" xml:id="pg_1202"/> may have committed. What it does is to
                            lay down certain procedural provisions which must be applied
                            specifically the obligation to give due notification through the
                            protecting power of the trial and of the nature of the offence charges,
                            and the obligation not to carry out any death sentence until three
                            months after the sentence has been communicated to the protecting power.
                            His Majesty’s Embassy at Washington is being instructed to bring this
                            point also to the attention of the State Department.[”]</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The American members, pending such further instructions as the Department may
                    consider necessary, will be guided by the Department’s instructions in its 249
                    of January 10, 10 p.m. and in its 8267 of December 31, 7 p.m.,<note n="42"
                        xml:id="d1089fn9">For latter telegram, see <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_853">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 853</ref>.</note> and we will endeavor
                    to see to it that in any propaganda directive which may be adopted in the event
                    of further such trials any statement that the Kharkov trials either come within
                    or without the Moscow Declaration will be avoided. We will also endeavor to see
                    to it that comment on further trials will be held to a minimum.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
