<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="1127" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1127">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.01B11/156</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Eastern
                                European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bohlen</hi>)<note n="28" xml:id="d1127fn1">Addressed to the Deputy Director of the Office of
                                European Affairs, H. Freeman Matthews; the Legal Adviser, Green H.
                                Hackworth; and the Secretary of State.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-03">June 3, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Legal Adviser’s office has discussed the law and proceedings in the
                            Kravchenko case with officials of the Department of Justice and <pb facs="1244" n="1234" xml:id="pg_1234"/> the situation is described
                            in the underlying memorandum.<note n="29" xml:id="d1127fn2">Not
                                printed.</note> In brief the legal position is as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We have no extradition treaty with the Soviet Union nor any
                                    agreement for the return of deserters from our respective armed
                                    forces. It is, therefore, impossible to institute extradition
                                    proceedings against Kravchenko on the basis of the Soviet
                                    charges that he is a deserter from the armed forces.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>If you indicate to the Attorney General your approval of such
                                    action, deportation proceedings can be instituted against
                                    Kravchenko. There is, however, in accordance with our practice
                                    the real possibility that the Board of Immigration Appeals will
                                    permit Kravchenko to depart from the United States to any
                                    country of his choosing and will not uphold the request for his
                                    return to the Soviet Union. If the Board of Appeals, however,
                                    should support the order of deportation to Russia, Kravchenko’s
                                    lawyers could through a writ of habeas corpus contest the
                                    decision in the courts. Any action in court would obviously give
                                    rise to violent public controversy in which unquestionably
                                    statements or possibly documentary evidence derogatory of the
                                    Soviet Union and damaging to Soviet-U.S. relations would be made
                                    public.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>There is apparently no certainty under the law that the Soviet request
                            that he be returned to the Soviet Union can be granted, and in any case
                            the institution of deportation proceedings will certainly give rise to
                            very undesirable publicity.<note n="30" xml:id="d1127fn3">In
                                conversation on May 27 with Edward J. Shaughnessy, special assistant
                                to the Commissioner of the Immigration and Naturalization Service in
                                the Department of Justice, Richard W. Flournoy of the Legal
                                Adviser’s office explained that the Department of State “would like
                                to find some way to avoid having Kravchenko sent to Russia, and that
                                at the same time it would like to avoid having publicity given to
                                the case.” (861.01B11/156)</note> It is suggested, therefore, that
                            you may give consideration to calling in the Soviet Ambassador and
                            explaining to him orally the situation under our law and practice, and
                            asking him under the circumstances if his Government would not give
                            consideration to allowing their request for his return to the Soviet
                            Union to lapse.</p>
                        <p>At the same time you might care to explain to the Ambassador that if
                            Kravchenko should engage in any public or other activity in the United
                            States inimicable to the Soviet Union, he would be regarded by this
                            Government as an undesirable alien and possibly on that basis the
                            question of his deportation would be reopened. You might also care to
                            ask the Ambassador to transmit your observations to Molotov as a
                            personal message from you.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bohlen</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>