<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-22T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-22T16:00:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War 1939/2294:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-22T17:00:00-04:00">March
                                        22, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2146. In consideration of a request from the British Foreign Office
                                communicated through its Embassy here for an expression of the views
                                of this Government on the Rumanian proposals presented to the Allied
                                representatives by Prince Stirbey in Cairo on March 17 (see
                                Department’s immediately following telegram<note n="39" xml:id="d160fn1">No. 2147, March 22, 5 p.m., not printed; it
                                    repeated telegrams of March 17 and 18 from Cairo, <ref target="#pg_149">pp. 149</ref> and <ref target="#pg_151">151</ref>, respectively.</note>), the Department is
                                formulating a statement of such views in consultation with the Joint
                                Chiefs and will forward them to the British as soon as may be
                                possible.</p>
                            <p>Meanwhile, in as much as related events are moving rapidly and
                                valuable time may elapse before Prince Stirbey can be given a reply
                                representing the concerted view of the three Allied Governments, it
                                is believed that he should be advised accordingly and that he should
                                be afforded whatever facilities he may require in order to
                                communicate to his principals, should he so desire, the fact that
                                whereas such necessary delay may be expected the Rumanians must
                                realize that they alone will have to bear the responsibility if they
                                postpone action until too late.</p>
                            <p>Please communicate the foregoing to the Foreign Office.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>