<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-13T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-13T02:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW 1939/2665:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to the Yugoslav Government in
                                    Exile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-13T10:00:00+03:00">June
                                        13, 1944—10 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received June 13—8:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Yugos 120. Yesterday the Rumanian emissaries received from Maniu
                                through Cretzianu a message in the following sense: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Maniu agrees to conclude an armistice upon the conditions
                                        presented by the Allies. The means of putting the armistice
                                        into application are in process of being established in
                                        agreement with those responsible and will be communicated to
                                        you in a few days.</p>
                                    <p>The patriotic democratic bloc has been formed.</p>
                                    <p>In view of the fact that the conditions of the armistice have
                                        been accepted, we are convinced that we shall obtain an
                                        amelioration of these conditions when they are applied as
                                        repeatedly declared by the Allies.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Allied representatives are at a loss to understand the last
                                sentence above, since they have promised no amelioration of the
                                armistice terms but on the contrary have emphasized repeatedly the
                                statement in the terms themselves that these “can be changed for the
                                worse if Rumania does not accept them soon”.</p>
                            <p>Today the British received a radio message from Rumania asking for
                                safelanding at Aleppo of a plane bearing three more Rumanians who
                                wish to contact Prince Stirbey. The Allied representatives have
                                decided to permit this, as Novikov has not yet received Moscow’s
                                approval of the proposed statement in my Yugos 111, June 1 that
                                conversations are at an end.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Algiers for Murphy as number 8.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>