<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-08T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-08T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-08T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-08T09:00:00-05:00" n="237"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 E.W. 1939/9–844: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-08T17:00:00+03:00"
                            >September 8, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 8:22 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3383. ReEmbs 3343, September 6, 4 p.m. In the conferences on the Rumanian
                    armistice terms, full agreement has been reached on the wording of all of IDS
                        [<hi rend="italic">its</hi>] terms with the exception of the indemnity to be
                    paid by Rumania to the Soviet Union. (The new protocol has not been discussed,
                    reEmbs 3382, September 8, 4 p.m.) The changes in the language are in the nature
                    of clarification and practically all of the Department’s suggestions have in
                    substance been excluded [<hi rend="italic">included</hi>] with the exception of
                    the paragraph on contribution to general relief. Molotov objected to the
                    inclusion of this provision in the armistice but agreed that if occasion arose
                    when it was desired to have Rumania make a contribution to relief of other
                    countries, the subject could be a matter of consideration at that time, bearing
                    in mind Rumania’s capabilities in the light of the other obligations she assumes
                    under the armistice.</p>
                <p>The British Ambassador today proposed a redraft of the article on reparation to
                    the Soviet Union which excluded reference to the percentage which the
                    $300,000,000 bore to the total damage caused by Rumanian occupation of Soviet
                    territory and inserted the word “provisionally” in the clause that fixed the
                    sum. Molotov agreed to the first of these proposals but insisted on the
                    elimination of the word “provisionally”. The British Ambassador agreed to drop
                    the word <pb facs="0237" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/> “provisionally” provided a
                    separate protocol were concluded between the three Allied Governments which
                    would cover (1) a clause to the effect that the inclusion of the fixed sum of
                    $300,000,000 had been agreed to without prejudice to a revision if it developed
                    that this amount was beyond Rumania’s capacity to fulfill and (2) a provision
                    that while the British Government did not object to deliveries to the Soviet
                    Union alone within the amount of $300,000,000, it should be borne in mind that
                    other claimant countries should receive in the final settlement an equitable
                    proportion of the total reparations received from all enemy countries.</p>
                <p>The British Ambassador had been instructed to inform the Soviet Government that
                    it was the British opinion that $300,000,000 considering Rumania’s other
                    obligations would probably be beyond her capacity to pay. Molotov made it clear
                    that the Soviet Government would not agree to sign a separate protocol of this
                    character. Thus the British and Soviet Governments are again at an impasse and
                    the British Ambassador is cabling for further instructions.</p>
                <p>Sent to Department as 3383, September 8, 5 p.m. Repeated to London as 165,
                    September 8, 5 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
