<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-17T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-17T14:00:00-05:00" n="27" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/121a: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Minister in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-17T15:00:00-04:00">May
                                        17, 1944—3 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1389. Following from War Department: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Combined Chiefs of Staff have not yet taken final action
                                        on the matter mentioned in War Department’s message to the
                                        Military Attaché of April 29,<note n="57" xml:id="d27fn1">Not found in Department files.</note> and although some
                                        form of favorable action is expected we cannot further delay
                                        on this account before successfully concluding negotiations
                                        for additional airfield.</p>
                                    <p>The capacity of the single crowded Lagens Airport will be
                                        exceeded by War Department’s projected tremendously
                                        increased air loads. Projected operations of ATC<note n="58" xml:id="d27fn2">Air Transport Command.</note> alone
                                        (repeat alone) call for 1,350 landings monthly by September.
                                        This figure will have increased to more than 2,100 monthly
                                        by January, not including diversions from the southern
                                        route. Obviously such operations cannot be accommodated by
                                        the existing field. Furthermore, these figures do not
                                        include the expected substantial British operations.</p>
                                    <p>A restriction on the Allied war effort would result from
                                        attempting to operate with one field only, and it is
                                        important to understand that it is extremely hazardous now
                                        and will continue to be so, to operate without a suitable
                                        weather alternate. Loss of equipment and life will be
                                        inevitable in moving tactical aircraft over that route, and
                                        this reason alone renders an additional airport absolutely
                                        essential.</p>
                                    <p>Traffic already planned as above outlined plus diversions
                                        from Caribbean, South Atlantic, and Central African Wings of
                                        ATC can be adequately accommodated with the two fields. This
                                        is a further and pressing consideration. Upon completion of
                                        both airfields it will be possible to abandon these three
                                        Wings except for small housekeeping detachments enabling the
                                        War Department to reassign thousands of highly trained
                                        personnel. The abandonment of the long southern route will
                                        save millions of gallons of aviation gasoline and much
                                        critical war material, as well as thousands of pilot
                                        hours.</p>
                                    <p>Should the war in Europe end by the time these fields are
                                        completed Azores operations will diminish little if any as
                                        long as the Asiatic theater continues to engage us. The
                                        shortest and fastest channel to the Far East will continue
                                        to be provided by the Central Atlantic route, and the best
                                        route westward for tactical aircraft and cargo <pb facs="0034" n="24" xml:id="pg_24"/> from Europe will be
                                        provided by the same route destined for redeployment in the
                                        Pacific.</p>
                                    <p>It is absolutely imperative that by June 15 the survey be in
                                        progress and actual construction should commence immediately
                                        following the survey if the new field is to be ready to
                                        handle winter traffic. By autumn there will be rough weather
                                        in the Azores and a further delay of as much as one month in
                                        approval of this program will postpone for another year the
                                        construction of the airfield.</p>
                                    <p>Please seek an immediate interview with the Prime Minister on
                                        the subject of the additional airfield alone and insist upon
                                        approval, final and definite, for prompt survey of Santa
                                        Maria. Should you encounter further difficulty please advise
                                        at once and furnish your recommendations.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Department has asked the War Department whether you should
                                furnish the foregoing information to Dr. Salazar and it has replied
                                that the information is furnished for that specific purpose in order
                                to strengthen your appeal to the Prime Minister, to be used by you
                                in full or in part as you see fit. You are authorized to make the
                                desired approach.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>