<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-07T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-07T19:00:00-05:00" n="290" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d290">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Rumania)/10–2844:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-07T20:00:00-04:00">December 7, 1944—8 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2801. Reurtel 4584 November 30, 9 p.m.<note n="84" xml:id="d290fn1">Not printed.</note> You should address a communication to the
                                Commissariat for Foreign Affairs referring to Ambassador Harriman’s
                                letter of October 13 to Vyshinsky. The Embassy’s 4584 November 30
                                says that no reply to Ambassador Harriman’s letter of October 13,
                                which presumably stated the points set <pb facs="0288" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/> forth in Department’s 2418 October 12, has
                                been received. Your 4133 October 28, however, indicated a reply had
                                been received indicating Soviet agreement to the appointment of an
                                American political representative, stating that the Soviet
                                Government had in view the parallel with Italy. Kostylev, Soviet
                                representative in Italy, and Bogomolov, Soviet member of the
                                Advisory Council for Italy, have the privilege of direct
                                communication in code with the Soviet Government. It has been the
                                Department’s understanding that the Soviet Government had agreed,
                                either orally or in writing, to Berry’s having freedom of
                                communication in code. (See in this connection Molotov’s statement
                                to the Rumanian delegation on September 12 reported in your despatch
                                no. 1066 of October 7, enclosure no. 5th.<note n="85" xml:id="d290fn2">Not printed.</note>) Please inform the Soviet
                                Government of the Department’s position on this matter and request
                                that communication in code be immediately permitted between the
                                American Embassy in Moscow and the American mission in
                                Bucharest.</p>
                            <p>The Department has not yet received from Caserta or from Bucharest
                                any information in reply to the inquiries contained in your 42 to
                                AmPolAd Caserta repeated to the Department as 4584 November 30.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>