<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-16T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-16T23:00:00-05:00" n="379" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.52/422a: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)<note n="94" xml:id="d379fn1">Repeated on the same date to Madrid as
                                    1066.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>. <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-17T00:00:00-04:00">April 17,
                                        1944—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3073. For the Ambassador and the Under Secretary.<note n="95" xml:id="d379fn2">Under Secretary of State Stettinius was in
                                    London at this time for a series of conferences with the
                                    British.</note> As you are probably aware, the British
                                Ambassador called upon me last Saturday afternoon<note n="96" xml:id="d379fn3">April 15.</note> to convey a message from the
                                British Government giving its view that the latest proposal of the
                                Spanish Government, <pb facs="0397" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> as to
                                the shipment of wolfram to Germany at the rate of 60 tons between
                                now and July, and the balance of 240 tons to be shipped during the
                                rest of this year, should be accepted, and the shipments of
                                petroleum products to Spain be resumed forthwith. After giving
                                careful study to this situation over the weekend and making a survey
                                of the attitude of public opinion in the country with respect
                                particularly to the situation of the neutral countries furnishing
                                war supplies to the enemy, I asked the Ambassador to call upon me
                                this morning.<note n="97" xml:id="d379fn4">Secretary Hull’s
                                    memoranda of conversations of April 15 and 17, not
                                    printed.</note> I told Lord Halifax that this question of making
                                arrangements with neutral countries under which we agree that there
                                shall be shipped from these neutrals to our enemies war materials
                                which have the direct result of killing our soldiers, was a matter
                                upon which there was the strongest of public opinion especially in
                                view of the long continued propaganda activities against this
                                Government running back to 1937 during the Spanish Civil War. I said
                                to Lord Halifax that in view of the fact that the British, as they
                                say, must continue to procure a number of strategic war materials
                                from Spain, and for other reasons to which the British seem to
                                attach great importance, and as Great Britain therefore would seem
                                to have a special interest in the situation which we do not have,
                                just as in the case of Argentina the British had a special interest
                                which we did not have, it would seem to me entirely logical and
                                practicable for the British to sponsor the oil shipments which would
                                be a counterpart to the arrangements they might wish to make with
                                regard to the shipment to Germany of wolfram and other commodities
                                which are involved in the military situation. I therefore told the
                                Ambassador that I desired in all earnestness to urge that if the
                                British believe these shipments to be necessary they should
                                undertake the responsibility and sponsorship for the shipments of
                                oil from Shell Oil or other British facilities in the Caribbean for
                                carrying in Spanish tankers, and that this seemed to be the only
                                logical way out of both of our difficulties in meeting the situation
                                each from our own particular point of view.</p>
                            <p>The response from the press and the people generally throughout the
                                country in supporting the statements I made in my speech of April 9
                                with regard to our attitude toward the neutrals shows how clearly
                                and how strongly the American public feels in this matter. I regret
                                the necessity of taking this position, but I see no other
                                alternative in the face of the strength of public opinion here
                                against agreements with neutrals on the basis of which they supply
                                important war materials to the enemy.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>