<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-27T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-27T08:00:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.52/427: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hayes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-27T15:00:00+02:00">April
                                        27, 1944—3 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received April 28—6:45 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1451. My 1431, April 25, 6 p.m. I informed the British Ambassador
                                yesterday of my conversation with Jordana on Monday<note n="19" xml:id="d391fn1">April 24.</note> and said I thought there was
                                still a slight chance of our persuading the Spanish Government to
                                reach a prompt agreement with us on the basis of the proposal I had
                                then made, namely, no further export of wolfram before June 30 and
                                thereafter export of 50 tons a month. I explained Jordana while
                                expressing very great pessimism about the outcome had promised to
                                re-submit the proposal to the Government and to inform me of the
                                result as soon as possible. I also indicated that if Jordana’s reply
                                was unfavorable I would ask him to arrange for me an interview with
                                Franco. In the meantime I felt sure that the temporary embargo could
                                be maintained and thus carried into May.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador said that a good deal of water had gone over the dam
                                since my conversation with Jordana on Monday. On Tuesday he had
                                received a number of telegrams from London and Washington explaining
                                that our two Governments were finally agreed on accepting the
                                original Jordana proposal. I asked him if he had definite
                                instructions on the matter. He said he had, and outlined them as
                                follows: We would try to reach an agreement whereby 40 tons of
                                wolfram could be exported to Germany between now and June 30
                                although if the Spaniards objected to this we might increase the
                                allowable export to 60 tons between now and June 30 and then 40 tons
                                a month could be exported thereafter. Also he had been instructed to
                                support me earnestly in representations hoping towards the removal
                                of the Japanese military agency in Tangier though this was not to be
                                made a part of the wolfram agreement. He understood moreover that I
                                was receiving identic instructions.</p>
                            <p>I told the Ambassador instructions were just coming in to me, that I
                                too understood agreement had been reached between London and
                                Washington but inasmuch as all the messages had not been decoded as
                                yet I could not tell him precisely what my instructions were. I
                                would inform him, however, as soon as possible. He said he thought I
                                should seek an interview with Jordana at the earliest possible
                                moment and communicate to him the proposal on which the British and
                                American Governments were now agreed. I said it seemed much better
                                to await a summons from Jordana and ascertain whether he had been
                                able to obtain from’ the Spanish Government authorization to
                                conclude an agreement along the lines of my original proposal. At
                                any rate until <pb facs="0415" n="405" xml:id="pg_405"/> I knew
                                precisely what my latest instructions were, I was in no position to
                                seek an interview with Jordana.</p>
                            <p>As I was about to leave Beaulac transmitted to me the telephone
                                message he had just received from Dunn in Washington. I told the
                                British Ambassador about it and said this reinforced my conviction
                                that neither of us should talk with Jordana until the whole matter
                                was further clarified. He seemed to agree to this and said he was
                                going home to keep certain engagements he had made there. We
                                separated at 7:15 p.m.</p>
                            <p>I saw Hoare again this morning. He stated that after I had talked
                                with him yesterday afternoon he had received a message that Jordana
                                wished to see him. He had therefore called on Jordana. He found the
                                Minister greatly agitated at the prospect of facing the Council of
                                Ministers at an adjourned meeting this morning and very anxious to
                                receive some kind of assurance from the British Ambassador that a
                                wolfram agreement would be quickly reached. The Ambassador said he
                                told the Minister he had no communication to make but that he hoped
                                very much the Council of Ministers would delay taking any steps
                                which might imperil the reaching of an agreement. He counselled
                                Jordana to take Franco aside before the meeting and point out to him
                                the desirability of avoiding discussion in the Council of Ministers
                                on the matter and of postponing any decision for a week. The
                                Ambassador said he told the Minister that while he could make no
                                communication to him he [apparent omission] on to believe that
                                London and Washington were disposed with Spanish cooperation to
                                reach an agreement within the next very few days. It should be easy
                                because there was such very little difference remaining between
                                Spain and the Allies. According to Hoare the Minister seemed to be
                                heartened and better prepared to meet the Council of Ministers this
                                morning.</p>
                            <p>The Minister also expressed to Hoare his hope that any statement to
                                be issued from Washington or London would be couched in most general
                                terms simply saying that an agreement had been reached. Hoare
                                pointed out certain difficulties in the way of any such general
                                statement but expressed sympathy with Jordana’s subsequent proposal
                                that the statement should not give the impression that Spain was
                                being rubbed in the dust by the Allies but was completing and
                                perfecting her strict neutrality. Hoare told Jordana that he would
                                recommend to London and Washington compliance with the latter’s
                                wishes in this matter.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador said that until he had further clarification from
                                London he must assume that the British will take over the oil supply
                                from the Americans. My 1450, April 27, 2 p.m. He gave me a copy of
                                the proposed statement of Mr. Churchill and said it clearly <pb facs="0416" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/> indicated the belief in
                                London that Great Britain would assume responsibility for supplying
                                and supervising the distribution of petroleum products in Spain. I
                                explained that the telegrams I had recently received from Washington
                                clearly implied that the Americans would continue supplying the
                                petroleum after a mutually satisfactory agreement about wolfram and
                                other pending matters was reached.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to London.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayes</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>