<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Sweden ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d550</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">550</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-21T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-21T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-21T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-21T13:00:00-05:00" n="550"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d550">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/7–2144:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-21T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 21, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 9:32 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2718. My 2701 of July 20, 7 p.m., 723 to London. This afternoon Mr. Sohlman
                    requested British Minister and me to see him. He told <pb facs="0596" n="586"
                        xml:id="pg_586"/> us that he had been authorized by the Swedish Government
                    to give us the following reply to the request we had made of him yesterday.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In regard to trade for 1945, Mr. Sohlman stated that he could confirm what
                        Hägglöf had told Foot in London, that the Swedish Government has not entered
                        into any commitments for 1945 with enemy countries. The question regarding
                        any such commitments has for the present no actuality and is not expected to
                        arise until late this autumn. Before any consideration is given by the
                        Swedish Government to such a question, the American and British members of
                        the JSC in London will be informed in time to allow them to present their
                        views.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In regard to trade for 1944, Mr. Sohlman said he would like to explain
                        that the Swedish Government has for 1944 made a number of agreements
                        regarding trade between German and Axis Europe. Of this the American and
                        British Governments are aware. Full information in regard to these
                        agreements has been given in the JSC. Swedish commitments in these trade
                        agreements of course falls entirely within the framework of the
                        Anglo-American-Swedish War Trade Agreement which however also gives latitude
                        for further agreements. The question regarding any such further agreements
                        is expected to arise only with respect to Swedish trade with Norway and
                        Denmark during second half of this year. The Swedish Government does not
                        however intend to enter into any such further agreements with these two
                        countries. After the fulfilment of the commitments arising out of agreements
                        governing trade for the first 6 months of this year with these two
                        countries, trade with each will be carried on a barter basis without any
                        further agreements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In relation to Germany, the Swedish Government will only apply existing
                    agreements. They will decline any proposals for additional agreements. In other
                    words, Sweden will stick strictly to the quotas with Germany which have already
                    been established and will not entertain any proposals for increase of those
                    quotas within the ceiling limits.</p>
                <p>Both British Minister and I thanked Mr. Sohlman for the promptness of this reply
                    and said that we were confident it would be appreciated by our Governments. It
                    seems to both Mallet and me to be a most satisfactory response to our
                    request.</p>
                <p>My 728, July 21, 7 p.m. repeats this to London.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
