<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-08T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-08T13:00:00-05:00" n="589" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d589">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/9–844:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-08T19:00:00+01:00">September
                                    8, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received September 9—7:09 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3561. Swedish Foreign Office according to Grafström<note n="74" xml:id="d589fn1">Sven Grafström, Acting Director of the Department
                                of Political Affairs, Swedish Ministry for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                            informed Germans September 6 that effective September 9 all transit of
                            goods through Sweden for German use will be stopped. It will be recalled
                            that Mr. Boheman told me on September 4th (Legation’s 3476, September 4,
                            8 p.m.; 1002 to London) that the transit of all war material which
                            previously had come to German-occupied Finland had been stopped and that
                            the question of the cessation of the remaining traffic of the same kind
                            to Norway was under serious consideration by the Government.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Grafström described this stopping of all German transit traffic as
                            another step in Sweden’s rapid progress in the continuing breaking of
                            its commercial relations with Germany. He added that for all practical
                            purposes these relations had ceased.</p>
                        <p>He went on to say with reference to how the term “war criminals” might be
                            interpreted by the Swedish Government that he was certain that “war
                            criminals” would be construed as including looted property and that the
                            Swedish Government would actively cooperate in efforts to discover and
                            return such property (Legation’s 3542, September 7, 9 p.m., 1021 to
                                London<note n="75" xml:id="d589fn2">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                        <p>My 1028, September 8, 7 p.m. repeats this to London.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>