<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Portugal ( (Norweb) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-13T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-13T11:00:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/7–1344: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-13T18:00:00+02:00"
                            >July 13, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 7:16 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2162. We have read and digested contents of Department’s 1958, July 11, which we
                    now [<hi rend="italic">not</hi>?] only fully appreciate but with which we are in
                    agreement as to substance and feeling. It may have been difficult for us to
                    convey in telegrams with what urgency and stress we are viewing developments but
                    on other hand at no time do we feel we have given grounds for the note of
                    discouragement such as seems to color Department’s 1941, July 8 and 1951, July
                    10.</p>
                <p>On contrary although we are far from satisfied and are driven almost to point of
                    exasperation by tempo of developments they are not abnormal from Portuguese
                    point of view. For the past weeks the movement has been definitely progressive
                    and in the week since <pb facs="0059" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> survey was
                    completed and given to Salazar we have had further indications that matter is
                    moving forward in all its aspects. In dealing with the Prime Minister one has to
                    learn to read the signs and interpret the language endeavoring to draw correct
                    conclusions therefrom. At this point we do not doubt eventual attainment of our
                    long range objectives since we are confident that he himself not only is
                    attracted by the prospect of a first class trans-Atlantic airfield for Portugal
                    but also has in mind a contribution which will redound to Portugal’s advantage
                    in the Far East.</p>
                <p>He is wise and farsighted and at the same time a prudent man and there is
                    evidence that he is considering every angle on this project including Portuguese
                    neutrality in Europe even to the point of consulting with Spain as he did prior
                    to the British Azores Agreement.</p>
                <p>I saw Sampaio again yesterday who assured me that Salazar was giving his
                    attention to our Azores [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] and that as soon as his
                    mind was made up he would receive me. I said I was sure this was the case but
                    repeated that I was deeply disturbed at the time factor. Undoubtedly some
                    element unknown to us is incomplete the picture as Salazar sees it and this
                    would explain his delay in calling me. We know for instance that 2 days ago he
                    convoked the top military officials to discuss the plan with them. Only
                    yesterday General Lelloone of the inner circle spoke to me with evident
                    enthusiasm of the project for fine installation at Santa Maria.</p>
                <p>We are of course facing certain risks but these in our judgment do not include
                    backsliding on part of Salazar. Moreover the chain of events during last
                    fortnight strengthens this belief. Our main concern is lest he sacrifice this
                    unique opportunity by his constitutional in Cape City [<hi rend="italic"
                        >incapacity</hi>] to move fast.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Norweb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
