<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-10-05T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-10-05T13:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">858.248/10–544: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-10-05T19:00:00+01:00">October 5,
                                    1944—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received October 5—6:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>8372. ReEmbs 8205, September 30, 8 p.m.<note n="78" xml:id="d646fn1">Not
                                printed.</note> We have just been given by the Foreign Office the
                            following communication concerning the release of airmen interned in
                            Sweden.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Thank you for your letter of the 28th September last in which you
                                referred to the great importance which your military authorities
                                attach to the release from internment as soon as possible of all U.
                                S. air personnel in Sweden. I need hardly say that we fully
                                appreciate their point of view.</p>
                            <p>Since then events have developed most favorably of their own accord
                                in that, as you will no doubt have heard, the Swedish Cabinet have
                                decided to release immediately 300 Allied airmen ‘on account’.
                                Although the official intention is to release a corresponding number
                                of Germans we understand that the release of further batches of
                                Allied airmen may not in fact be held up until an equivalent number
                                of Germans have arrived and been set free, but that we may expect
                                further contingents of Allied airmen to be released ‘on account’ as
                                soon as these initial 300 men have left Swedish territory and a few
                                more Germans have arrived.</p>
                            <p>We have, however, been somewhat worried by the possible attitude of
                                the Soviet Government to this repatriation of Germans who have come
                                from the Eastern Front and may well return to fight there. We <pb facs="0707" n="697" xml:id="pg_697"/> feel that the Soviet
                                Minister in Stockholm<note n="79" xml:id="d646fn2">Mme. Alexandra
                                    Kollontay.</note> should at least be informed of these
                                arrangements and we have, therefore, instructed Mallet on the
                                following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <list>
                                        <item>‘1. While I could not have agreed to our doing a deal
                                            with the Swedes for the release to U. S. of British and
                                            American airmen against German military personnel who
                                            have fled from a Russian sphere of operations unless the
                                            Soviet Government had been informed, we have now been
                                            placed in the position not of being asked to agree to an
                                            exchange but of being informed that a release of
                                            internees has been decided upon by the Swedish
                                            Government.</item>
                                        <item>2. All the same it is reasonable that the Soviet
                                            Government should be given equally favorable treatment
                                            with us and the Americans, the more so as the Germans in
                                            question have been fighting on the Eastern Front and may
                                            well return to the Eastern Front. The Soviet Government
                                            will certainly resent it if we appear to be acting
                                            behind their backs.</item>
                                        <item>3. Report that Russian internees do not wish to return
                                            to Russia may well (to judge by experience here) prove
                                            to be largely, if not wholly, unfounded. In any case
                                            that is not an argument which we can use with the Soviet
                                            Government and I think it would be only reasonable that
                                            the Russian internees should be considered for inclusion
                                            in the next batch of Allied prisoners to be
                                            released.</item>
                                        <item>4. It is, of course, for your Soviet colleague to
                                            protect her own country’s interest in this matter, but
                                            you should keep her informed of developments. You should
                                            first inform your U.S. colleague of your instructions
                                            and give him the opportunity of taking similar action.
                                            If you think it necessary you may discuss matter first
                                            with Secretary General of Ministry of Foreign
                                            Affairs.’”</item>
                                    </list>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>When giving us this communication Foreign Office stressed orally that it
                            attaches greatest importance to keeping the Soviet Government informed
                            of any exchange which involves the release of Germans.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>