<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-24T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-24T11:00:00-05:00" n="655" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d655">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">858.79661/11–2144: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-24T17:00:00+01:00">November
                                    24, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:58 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>4821. For Department only. The reason in my opinion why it is of
                            importance not to insist on second condition mentioned in my 4774,
                            November 21, 10 p.m., as well as first condition (re Department’s 2355,
                            November 22, 9 p.m.) is that it requires an act by Swedish Government as
                            a prior condition for our making these planes available to the
                            Norwegians. If Swedes should decide that as matter of policy they are
                            unable to grant this permission on any conditions such as ones War
                            Department proposes, it would be the Norwegians not the Swedes who would
                            suffer. It is not the Swedes who have asked this service of us but the
                            Norwegians nor did initiative come from Swedes; the idea was one of
                            Foreign Minister Trygve Lie. Aside from practical considerations I do
                            not think it helps the United States position to use the need of one of
                            our Allies as leverage in forcing something out of Swedish Government.
                            They do not understand why Norwegian request cannot be decided on its
                            own merits and in light of our own military necessities and
                            possibilities. Mr. Günther has, moreover, consistently maintained
                            throughout my various discussions with him and Boheman on the release of
                            these aviators that their release would not be considered by his
                            Government on any basis of bargain. Releases so far secured by me have
                            been entirely on basis of Swedish good will to Allied cause. The good
                            will which produced release of our airmen still exists, but the Swedes
                            who are proud and sensitive under a stiff front of reserve feel that
                            there has been no real appreciation or understanding on our part for
                            what they have done. They are fully aware that Sweden has been under no
                            obligation to effect these releases. Even Boheman who has with great
                            loyalty and often with personal courage fought our battles with his slow
                            moving and obstinate Government remarked to me with a suggestion of
                            sarcasm that “it would be interesting to know how many of your interned
                            military personnel have been released by Switzerland and other neutral
                            countries”. Moreover, the treatment in every respect which the Swedes
                            have accorded our aviators has been humane <pb facs="0714" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/> and understanding to a high degree and beyond any
                            bounds of what are their obligations under international law and custom.
                            The aviators themselves are fully appreciative of this fact, as
                            testified to me by General Curtis on his recent visit here.</p>
                        <p>I have been reliably informed that Government Ministers in Cabinet
                            meeting have voiced bitter resentment at what they call the “American
                            way of treating Swedes as if they were slaves”. I am not in a position
                            as yet to report that Swedish Government will now immediately release
                            all our remaining aviators. I am convinced, however, that their release
                            will not be advanced one day through injecting any form of condition or
                            implied threat on our part.</p>
                        <p>I should also add as a practical matter that although the instructions in
                            this regard are sent by War Department to Colonel Hardison, action On
                            them has to be taken by me. Hardison has no place whatever in situation
                            beyond field of operations.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>