<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-02-01T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-02-01T23:00:00-05:00" n="950" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d950">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.51/3023: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-02-02T00:00:00-04:00">February
                                    2, 1944—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>211. The Department has submitted for the approval of the President a
                            program for the handling of the various problems referred to in your
                            253, January 26, 1 p.m. and previous telegrams on this subject.</p>
                        <pb facs="1053" n="1043" xml:id="pg_1043"/>
                        <p>As indicated in the Department’s 83, January 14, the Department’s
                            proposals are in general agreement with your suggestions that
                            discussions be initiated in Moscow in regard to postwar reconstruction.
                            However, the question of the 300 million dollars worth of goods under
                            Lend-Lease is being considered by Hopkins. Moreover, it is felt that
                            negotiations should be carried on through regular diplomatic channels
                            and that these discussions should form an integral part of our over-all
                            relations with the Soviet Union. If the President approves of these
                            proposals they will be incorporated in a telegram to you.</p>
                        <p>It has been learned on the basis of preliminary considerations given to
                            this matter that we cannot at this time make any definite arrangements
                            for the financing of postwar trade until certain legal limitations have
                            been removed. You should, therefore, in discussing credits with the
                            Soviet authorities limit yourself only to generalities.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>