<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union (
                    (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d998</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">998</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-05T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-05T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-05T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-05T20:00:00-05:00" n="998"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d998">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24/8–244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-05T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 5, 1944—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1869. ReDepts 1834 of August 2. Following is summary of the third talk we had
                    with Stepanov on August 2:</p>
                <p>1. After discussing the question with Treasury, Stepanov was advised that it
                    might be difficult for the United States Government to accept his suggested gold
                    clause providing for payments to be made in United States dollars or gold at the
                    rate of 35 dollars an ounce. Stepanov was told that it would be necessary for
                    him to discuss this question with Treasury. We have since learned that Treasury
                    officials think that it might be possible for them to work out a gold clause
                    somewhat similar to that suggested by the Soviets. We will report results of
                    these conversations as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>2. Considerable further discussion took place regarding the rate of interest.
                    Stepanov was assured that the amount of principal on which interest would be
                    charged would be based upon the aggregate cost of the various items furnished
                    under the agreement as calculated by cost formulae which are to be worked
                    out.</p>
                <p>In this connection he raised the following points: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Stepanov stated that after studying our proposals he still felt that
                            2½ percent was too high since this rate was the rate at which the U.S.
                            Government sells its taxable bonds and that roughly speaking one-half of
                            one percent is returnable to the Government as taxes.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>While the repayment of principal on U.S. 23–28 year, 2.4 [<hi
                                rend="italic">2.5?</hi>] percent bonds does not begin until at least
                            the 23rd year, the Soviet Government plans to start amortization
                            payments in 5 or 10 years and thus the average time of the outstanding
                            Soviet indebtedness would be shorter than 30 years and therefore
                            Stepanov felt the interest rate should be lower than that charged for
                            U.S. thirty-year bonds.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>We promised to give consideration to these points.</p>
                <p>3. While Stepanov admitted and agreed that of course the President, in the
                    agreement, has the discretion to determine the date upon which active military
                    operations against the common enemy have ceased, he nevertheless suggested that
                    he thought it would be advisable throughout the agreement to change the phrase
                    “active military operations” to read “military actions.” He explained that it
                    was felt some ambiguity might arise from the use of the present phrase and he
                    therefore hoped that a new phrase could be worked out. We promised to give
                    consideration to his suggestion and after studying the question, plan to suggest
                    that the phrase “military resistance of the common enemy has been overcome” be
                    used to replace “active military operations.”</p>
                <pb facs="1122" n="1112" xml:id="pg_1112"/>
                <p>4. A lengthy discussion took place on point 1 in the telegram under reference
                    regarding where the negotiations on the items to be included in each schedule
                    should take place.</p>
                <p>Acheson outlined the following suggested procedure for further talks: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>We would continue to discuss the textual provisions of the agreement
                            with Stepanov and endeavor to settle all questions therein.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In order to settle the question of what categories of goods should be
                            listed in schedule I or schedule II, we provisionally proposed that we
                            might give to the Soviet authorities as soon as possible our tentative
                            offerings under the Fourth Protocol indicating which items we consider
                            to be in schedule I and which in schedule II with the remainder falling
                            under straight lend-lease. The offerings with the indicated
                            classification would be transmitted by Stepanov and the Department to
                            Moscow in order that you and the Soviet authorities could study them and
                            thus ascertain whether, under the classifications which must of
                            necessity be decided by us, the Soviet authorities desire to obligate
                            themselves to take the supplies offered under the terms and conditions
                            to be worked out in the 3<hi rend="italic">c</hi> agreement.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Acheson explained that while it might be decided that a general category of goods
                    should fall within schedule I, there might be special items in this category
                    such as special presses which take a comparatively long time to produce and have
                    a long life, which have to be classified under schedule II despite the fact that
                    presses in general were classified under schedule I. Acheson further explained
                    that we should have the right to decide into which category any supplementary
                    requisitioned item should fall if such item had not been included in the
                    original Fourth Protocol offerings. In this connection, Stepanov suggested that
                    it might be possible to define carefully the categories in such a manner that
                    there would be no question about special items being transferred from schedule I
                    to schedule II. We feel this would unnecessarily complicate matters, might be
                    almost impossible to define and therefore are of the opinion that all such basic
                    decisions should be made in Washington where both the American and Purchasing
                    Commission technicians are familiar with all classification problems while in
                    Moscow neither any of your staff nor the Soviet staff has this knowledge.</p>
                <p>Stepanov argued at some length that you and General Spalding together with Soviet
                    officials should be the ones to decide in which schedule various items of the
                    Fourth Protocol should be placed and he indicated that he had already
                    telegraphed Moscow suggesting that these discussions should be carried on
                    simultaneously with the talks here. We again explained that while we felt that
                    discussions should take place in Moscow to determine what supplies the Soviet
                    Government desires to obligate themselves to take under the terms and conditions
                    of the 3<hi rend="italic">c</hi> agreement, we could not agree that the Soviet
                        <pb facs="1123" n="1113" xml:id="pg_1113"/> Government should have final
                    decision regarding the category in which various items should fall.</p>
                <p>As a tentative alternative, Mr. Acheson suggested that perhaps after reaching
                    provisional agreement on the textual part of the agreement, Stepanov could: 1)
                    either go to Moscow to discuss categories which the Soviet Government would
                    desire to obligate themselves to take under 3<hi rend="italic">c</hi>; 2) remain
                    here and have this question worked out by you with the Soviet authorities and
                    telegraphed here for final approval; or 3) reach an agreement here on as many
                    categories as possible and have Stepanov discuss the remaining categories after
                    returning to Moscow.</p>
                <p>5. After having made the above tentative proposals to the Soviet representatives
                    the lend-lease authorities have studied the question further and now plan to
                    propose the following arrangement to the Soviet representatives: instead of
                    submitting the full list of offerings under the Fourth Protocol they plan to
                    revise the third paragraph of schedule I submitted with the proposed agreement
                    to the Soviet authorities on May 24, 1944, and to submit a new schedule I
                    showing in greater detail the various items which we are prepared to offer under
                    the agreement. It is felt that the submission of a more detailed schedule I will
                    make it easier for Moscow to decide which items they are willing to obligate
                    themselves to pay for under schedule I and under the terms of the proposed
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>It is also proposed that in addition we will furnish to Stepanov a breakdown
                    detailed list of all items which we are also prepared to furnish under the
                    agreement, in order that the Soviet authorities, if they so desire, may make
                    additional requests for the inclusion of categories beyond those which we
                    propose in the revised schedule I.</p>
                <p>It is also planned to deliver to Stepanov a list of projects which the Soviet
                    authorities have already expressed an interest in and which we are willing to
                    consider under schedule II. This list would also contain the conditions which we
                    would have to impose before final approval could be obtained of projects under
                    schedule II.</p>
                <p>We are working on the revised schedule I and the rewording of the third paragraph
                    of schedule I and hope to get it to you as soon as possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
