<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-07-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="1074" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1074">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 882.00/565</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Curtis</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 112</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-07-09">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July 9, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report the receipt of
                            the program of reform in the administration of the Government of Liberia
                            proposed by Department, a copy of which was transmitted to General
                            Receiver of Customs.</p>
                        <p>A memorandum of said program was transmitted promptly to the Liberian
                            Government accompanied with a note, a copy of which is herewith enclosed
                            marked enclosure No. 1.</p>
                        <p>Before bringing the matter to the attention of the Liberian Government, I
                            invited the General Receiver and Major commanding the Liberian Frontier
                            Force to confer with me, the Secretary of Legation and the Military
                            Attaché.</p>
                        <p>All of the above-named were present at the said conference which was held
                            in the Legation and every detail of the said program was discussed and
                            each conferee was in accord as to the desirability of reform in
                            administration of the affairs of Liberia and of one mind as to his
                            willingness and determination to lend all possible aid in furtherance of
                            the adoption by Liberia of the suggestions and proposals of
                            Department.</p>
                        <p>There seems to be a disposition on the part of Liberia to act without
                            delay upon the said memorandum of reform, as evidenced by the <pb facs="1050" n="884" xml:id="pg_884"/> calling of the Legislature in
                            extra session for that purpose, for July 16.</p>
                        <p>The progress of the Legislature in the premises will be reported to
                            Department with all convenient despatch.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">James L. Curtis</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Curtis</persName>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Liberian Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-25">
                                        <hi rend="italic">June 25, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose herewith
                                for the information of the Government of Liberia, a memorandum of a
                                definite reform program suggested by the Department of State at
                                Washington for adoption by the Liberian Government.</p>
                            <p>I am instructed by the Department, in connection with said memorandum
                                of desirable reforms, to make known to the Government of Liberia its
                                keen interest in the growth, development and national well-being of
                                Liberia and its disappointment in the administration of Liberian
                                affairs, as it feels now that the time has arrived when the
                                Government of the United States, as next friend of Liberia, must
                                insist upon a radical change of policy or continue to be subjected
                                to criticism from other foreign Powers as regards the loan
                                agreement, which it is not disposed to do.</p>
                            <p>The temper of the Department as disclosed in said instruction is such
                                as calls for immediate action on the part of the Liberian Government
                                with respect to the advice and suggestions set out in the enclosed
                                memorandum, if it would escape the consequences of the withdrawal of
                                the friendly support that purely altruistic considerations have
                                hitherto prompted the Government of the United States to extend.</p>
                            <p>The manifest determination of the Department, on the other hand, not
                                only to maintain, but to enlarge upon, the historic attitude of the
                                friendly interest of the Government of the United States in
                                Liberia’s welfare, in the proportion of Liberia’s prompt and honest
                                cooperation in carrying out the said suggested reforms, is just as
                                unmistakable.</p>
                            <p>Increased success and prosperity for the Republic of Liberia will, I
                                am sure, result from the closer and more friendly relations between
                                the two Governments, which will follow in the wake of the adoption
                                by Liberia of said suggested reforms, while the absence of tangible
                                and permanent results in this regard, will doubtless cause the
                                Department to reach the conclusion, that the failure to thus
                                translate promise into performance represents the bent of the
                                Republic as to the need or desirability of reforms.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">James L. Curtis</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>