<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Fletcher to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1241</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1241</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="1241"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1241">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.63/414</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Fletcher</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 23</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico City</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 14, 1917</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my telegram No. 14 of March 10, 2
                    p.m., I have the honor to report in more complete detail the procedure
                    prescribed by the Department of Fomento, Colonization and Industry to be
                    followed by owners of mines in Mexico who, being unable to resume or begin
                    operations, have not applied for an extension of time in which to resume
                    operations, or, having applied for such extension, have not put their petitions
                    in proper form.</p>
                <p>These petitions must be in the Spanish language, addressed and sent directly to
                    the Secretary of Fomento, Colonization and Industry, signed by the owner of the
                    property in question, or his legal representative, and stamped with a fifty
                    centavo Mexican documentary stamp.</p>
                <p>The petition should enumerate the name, title number, exact location and number
                    of pertenencias in the property, the reasons which the owner alleges for his
                    failure to operate the property, and a request that extension of time be granted
                    in which to begin or resume operations. The last mining tax receipt (boleta)
                    should accompany the petition to show that taxes are paid up to date.</p>
                <p>I enclose a copy of the memorandum of information I am sending mine owners who
                    write this Embassy inquiring for information in this matter. I also enclose a
                    translation of a circular issued by the Department of Fomento, Colonization and
                    Industry February 21, 1917, which contains the most recently published
                    regulations and <pb facs="1214" n="1048" xml:id="pg_1048"/> instructions on the
                    subject of ownership and operation of mines in Mexico.</p>
                <p>As I have elsewhere reported, both the First Chief and the Minister of Foreign
                    Affairs have assured me that extensions will be granted mine owners in all
                    proper cases, and that they prefer to deal with each case individually upon its
                    merits, rather than adopt the plan suggested in your telegram No. 8, February
                    24, 1 p.m.</p>
                <p>The action taken by the Department of Fomento, and the declarations of the
                    Minister of Fomento, when certain cases of non-operation of mines have been
                    presented to him personally are in conformity with this reasonable attitude of
                    the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> Government of Mexico.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry P. Fletcher</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">circular issued by the department of fomento,
                            colonization and industry, february 21, 1917</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The decree of September 14, 1916, issued by the First Chief of the
                        Constitutionalist Army charged with the Executive Power of the Nation,
                        established the penalty of forfeiture for those mining concessions whose
                        owners should not develop their properties in accordance with the
                        requirements of the decree, specifying to this effect a period of two months
                        for resuming work in the mines, which period was extended until the 14th of
                        the present month by circular No. 22 of this Department, issued by the
                        Bureau of Mines and Petroleum.</p>
                    <p>Various concessionaires have complied with this decree, and have begun work
                        in their mines; others have requested an extension of time in order to
                        comply with it, and another group has incurred the penalty of forfeiture
                        referred to; the properties of this last-mentioned group, with the approval
                        of the First Chief, are therefore subject to intervention by the Department
                        of Hacienda and Public Credit after the Department of Fomento declares the
                        forfeiture of the respective concessions.</p>
                    <p>In order to comply with the resolutions of the Executive of the 16th of the
                        present month, and in order to proceed with entire justice, this Department
                        has resolved as follows with respect to each of the before-mentioned groups: <list>
                            <item>First Group.—Concessionaires whose properties are being worked: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Concessionaires of mining properties now being worked are
                                        required to verify before the first day of next April, in
                                        this Department, with the respective receipts or
                                        certificates, if they have not already done so, that they
                                        are up to date in the payment of the mining tax.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>They are required to render before the first day of next
                                        April, either directly to this Department, or to the agency
                                        in their district, a detailed report for each one of their
                                        properties, which shall contain the description of
                                        operations, both above and below ground, giving the
                                        following general data: <list>
                                            <label>A.</label>
                                            <item>Name of the property, name of the original
                                                concessionaire, name of the present owner, situation
                                                of the mine, boundaries, area, number of the title,
                                                number of the registry, principal ore which is
                                                exploited, and metals or metalloids that it is
                                                desired to exploit.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>These data will be accompanied by a true copy of
                                                the original plan of the property.</item>
                                            <label>B.</label>
                                            <item>A clear and detailed explanation of each of the
                                                explorations or developments that is being made at
                                                the present time. In case of a group of mines, where
                                                work of exploration is being done, the development
                                                of which extends over two or more properties, the
                                                written report of this work will be accompanied by a
                                                plan which gives a complete idea of the project, in
                                                order that this Department may determine which
                                                properties are included in the work referred
                                                to.</item>
                                            <label>C.</label>
                                            <item>The number of employees and operators, hours of
                                                labor, salaries and day wages, centers of population
                                                which furnish laborers for this work.</item>
                                            <label>D.</label>
                                            <item>Motors employed: man power, steam, hydraulic, gas,
                                                electric, etc.</item>
                                            <label>E.</label>
                                            <item>The machinery used in the work of development,
                                                ventilation and drainage, and in the preparation and
                                                treatment of the minerals.</item>
                                            <pb facs="1215" n="1049" xml:id="pg_1049"/>
                                            <label>F.</label>
                                            <item>System of development and treatment.</item>
                                            <label>G.</label>
                                            <item>Production of ore, stating the amount of ore
                                                exported and the amount treated; approximate
                                                percentage of the ore exported and of the ore
                                                treated.</item>
                                            <label>H.</label>
                                            <item>The supply of the principal materials employed in
                                                the development and treatment of the ores, such as
                                                steel, explosives, lubricants, carbides, wood
                                                cyanide, zinc, acetate of lead, fusing substances,
                                                combustibles, etc.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>They will also state their nationality. If companies, they
                                        will declare whether or not they are organized in accordance
                                        with the laws of the land.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>Second Group.—Concessionaires who request an extension of time in
                                order to comply with the decree of the 14th of September. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Concessionaires of mining properties who request an
                                        extension of time in order to comply with the decree of the
                                        14th of September are required to verify before the first
                                        day of next April, in this Department, with the respective
                                        receipts or certificates, if they have not already done so,
                                        that they are up to date in the payment of the mining
                                        tax.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>If, in the request presented by the concessionaires of
                                        this group, the properties referred to have not been
                                        specified, this should be done, accompanied by a report
                                        which contains for each one of them the following data: <list>
                                            <label>A.</label>
                                            <item>Name of the property, name of the original
                                                concessionaire, name of the present owner, situation
                                                of the mine, boundaries, area, number of the title,
                                                number of the registry, principal ore which is being
                                                developed, and the metal or metalloids produced by
                                                the development.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>These data will be accompanied by a true copy of
                                                the original plan of the property.</item>
                                            <label>B.</label>
                                            <item>A report of the work which was done before the
                                                suspension of operations, stating the number of
                                                employees and operators, hours of work, salaries and
                                                day wages, and the centers of population which
                                                furnish the labor.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>They will state their nationality; if companies, they will
                                        state whether or not they are organized in accordance with
                                        the laws of the land.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>After these requirements have been complied with, and
                                        after considering the reasons stated in the petition, and
                                        the general conditions of the zone in which the properties
                                        referred to are situated, this Department will fix the
                                        maximum extension of time for resuming or initiating
                                        work.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>Third Group.—Concessionaires who did not comply with the decree
                                referred to: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Since all of the concessionaires of mining properties
                                        belonging to this group have incurred the penalty of
                                        forfeiture, this Department will proceed immediately to
                                        forward to the Treasury, (Hacienda) a detailed list of said
                                        mining properties, in order that they may be
                                        intervened.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>During the period of intervention, before this Department
                                        declares corresponding confiscation, the interested parties
                                        may make representations to retain possession of their
                                        concessions, stating to this Department the reasons for
                                        their noncompliance with the decree; their decision to
                                        resume work on the mining property in question; the means at
                                        their disposal for this purpose, and the time fixed for
                                        doing so. In order to determine whether the reasons stated
                                        merit attention, and whether the securities they give for
                                        compliance with their proposals are sufficient, these will
                                        be presented by this Department to the consideration of the
                                        First Chief of the Constitutionalist Army, in charge of the
                                        Executive Power of the Nation, when the declaration of
                                        confiscation which should be issued for the properties
                                        referred to are presented for his approval.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>In order that this petition may be acted upon it must be
                                        accompanied by vouchers showing that the concessionaire has
                                        paid the mining tax to date.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The respective petition referring to properties should
                                        contain the following data: <list>
                                            <label>A.</label>
                                            <item>Name of the property and name of the first
                                                concessionaire, name of the present owner, location
                                                of the mine, boundaries, area, number of title,
                                                number of registry, principal ore being developed,
                                                and the metals or metalloids being produced.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>These data will be accompanied by a true copy of
                                                the original plan of the property.</item>
                                            <label>B.</label>
                                            <item>A report of the work done before the suspension of
                                                operations, stating the number of employees and
                                                operators, hours of work, salaries and day wages and
                                                centers of population which furnished
                                                laborers.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>They will state their nationality. If companies, they will
                                        declare whether or not they are organized in accordance with
                                        the laws of the country.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>Another group of mines exists which, in accordance with
                                        circular number 25, of April 29, 1914, given by the First
                                        Chief of the Constitutionalist Army in charge of the
                                        Executive Power of the Nation, and which has obtained
                                        permission <pb facs="1216" n="1050" xml:id="pg_1050"/> from
                                        this Department to develop its properties before issuing the
                                        corresponding title.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>The petitioners for these properties are required: <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>To submit, before the first day of April next, a
                                                report of the work undertaken by them, stating the
                                                number of employees and operators now engaged, the
                                                plan of work which they expect to follow, what force
                                                or energy they are using, what class of machinery
                                                they have installed, what ores they are developing,
                                                what is the present production of ore, what is the
                                                approximate percentage of ore obtained.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>To prove within the same period of time, to this
                                                Department, with the receipts or certificates, that
                                                they have paid the mining tax to date.</item>
                                            <label>3.</label>
                                            <item>The report shall contain the following general
                                                data: <list>
                                                  <label>A.</label>
                                                  <item>Name of the property, name of the
                                                  petitioner, location of the mine, boundaries,
                                                  area, number of corresponding document,
                                                  (expediente) number of the registry, ores and
                                                  metals of metalloids that are being
                                                  developed.</item>
                                                  <label>B.</label>
                                                  <item>Nationality of the petitioner. If companies,
                                                  they will state whether or not they are organized
                                                  in accordance with the laws of the land.</item>
                                                </list>
                                            </item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>The above is published for the information and guidance of
                                        the public and those interested.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">Constitution and Reforms</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-02-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 21, 1917</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pastor Rouaix</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum relative to petitions to be presented to the
                            ministry of fomento of the de facto government of mexico for extension
                            of time for operation of mines</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Ministry of Fomento, in response to various requests presented by the
                        American Embassy on behalf of American citizens for an extension of time in
                        which to resume or begin the operation of mining properties, has indicated
                        that the interested parties must make their petitions directly to the
                        Ministry.</p>
                    <p>Such petitions must be written in the Spanish language, bear a properly
                        canceled fifty centavo Mexican documentary stamp, be signed by the owner of
                        the property in question or his legal representative, and set forth the
                        following points: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The name, title number, exact location, and number of pertenencias
                                (area) of the mining property for which extension of time is
                                required.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The reasons which the owner alleges for the nonoperation of his
                                property.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>A request that extension of time be granted in which to begin or
                                resume operation.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>This petition should be accompanied by the last boleta or mining tax receipt,
                        in order to show that the taxes are paid up to date.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 10, 1917</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
