<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Jefferson to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-09-01T15:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-09-01T15:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-09-01T15:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-09-01T15:45:00-05:00" n="1377"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1377">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 817.51/896</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Jefferson</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-09-01T15:00:00-05:45">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 1, 1917, 3 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Nicaraguan Congress in extraordinary session after over a month of discussion of
                    financial plan approved it with some modifications and enacted it into law. The
                    Executive is authorized with power to execute formal contracts with the
                    interested parties in conformity with the bases of the plan which are
                    sufficiently broad so that no question can arise after the formal contracts are
                    signed on behalf of the Nicaraguan Government by its agent Ramón Enríquez.
                    Therefore it will only be necessary if the bankers so desire to later have the
                    contracts ratified by the Congress.</p>
                <p>In the paragraph after word “power” in lieu of “etc., etc.” insert “According to
                    the catalogue of fiscal accounts.” Not listed in catalogue are property, local
                    school and forestry taxes. National Bank now collects property tax as guaranty
                    of 500,000 dollars loan of which 236,000 dollars have been paid to June 30.
                    School and forestry taxes will be used for school and agricultural purposes and
                    collected and expended local school boards.</p>
                <pb facs="1303" n="1137" xml:id="pg_1137"/>
                <p>Also in the first paragraph is following change in phraseology: “If during a
                    period of three consecutive months the revenues are less than 180,000 dollars it
                    is understood to mean that the three months referred to will begin from the
                    first month which falls short of the 60,000 dollars except in case of unforeseen
                    circumstances and <hi rend="italic">force majeure</hi>.”</p>
                <p>In second paragraph insert after “legal fees, etc.” “Approved by the
                    Government”.</p>
                <p>In Subsection C insert after “legal fees,” etc. “Properly vouchered”.</p>
                <p>With reference to most important addition to plan see my August 18, 11 a.m.,
                    second and third paragraphs. Other slight additions to text do not change intent
                    of law.</p>
                <p>Copy of the law will be forwarded by first mail.</p>
                <p>I wish to report the amount of customs receipts retained will approximate about
                    1,000,000 dollars by September 16.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jefferson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
