<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="1419" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1419">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 819.77/261</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister of Panama</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 996</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Panama</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-12-26">
                                        <hi rend="italic">December 26, 1916</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: I have the honor to
                                acknowledge receipt of your excellency’s note No. 7 dated the 22d
                                instant, and in reply beg leave to express my satisfaction at
                                finding therein the Department of State’s opinion of the projected
                                construction of an 18-mile extension of the Chiriqui Railway which
                                will prove of great benefit to the Republic of Panama and at knowing
                                that the Department of State is disposed to approve an issue of 5%
                                bonds by my Government aggregating $400,000 provided that adequate
                                provision be made for the redemption of those bonds within thirty
                                years after the date of issue, that $200,000 of the issue be
                                delivered at not less than 97% of the face value and that the
                                remainder will be delivered, when needed, with the approval of the
                                Government of the United States.</p>
                            <p>This very important matter will, on this very day, be communicated to
                                the Government of my country for its further action; but, in the
                                meanwhile I will take the liberty of calling to your excellency’s
                                attention two probable errors in which your excellency’s Government
                                seems to me to have fallen in this case. The first is the idea that
                                the railway is to be extended eighteen miles in the direction of
                                Charco Azul from the city of David. I must say to your excellency
                                that the eighteen miles from the city of David in that direction
                                have already been built, that being one of the branches built in
                                Chiriqui with the three previous issues of the loan. The projected
                                extension is to be eighteen miles more or less and in the direction
                                of Charco Azul but not from David; it is from the city of Concepcion
                                which is the terminal of the railway branch under consideration.</p>
                            <pb facs="1348" n="1182" xml:id="pg_1182"/>
                            <p>The other probable error is that which deals with the hypothecation
                                required as a security for the issue. Your excellency speaks of the
                                sum of the six millions belonging to the Republic of Panama and
                                invested in mortgages in the city of New York by order of the
                                Panaman Government. Your excellency will remember that my Government
                                negotiated a three million dollar loan with the National City Bank
                                and the Farmers’ Trust Co. of New York City for the construction of
                                railways in the Republic of Panama, giving as security the annuity
                                of two hundred and fifty thousand dollars which your excellency’s
                                Government pays to my country under the Canal Treaty. Of that loan
                                there have been but three issues of seven hundred and fifty thousand
                                dollars, and now it is proposed to make a fourth issue of four
                                hundred thousand only, so that the surety for this last does not
                                bear on the six millions above mentioned, but is the same surety
                                pledged for the loan and the three issues already made which form
                                part of it.</p>
                            <p>I trust that, if your excellency concurs in this view, you will be so
                                good as to let me know in order that my Government be fully aware of
                                the obligations it is about to assume.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Belisario Porras</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>