<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Morris to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-11-27T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-11-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-11-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-11-27T10:00:00-05:00" n="338"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 793.94/628</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Morris</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-11-28T00:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 28, 1917, midnight</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Your telegram of November 5, 6 p.m. [November 6, 5 p.m.], and November 21, 6 p.m.
                    Following letter marked private and confidential received yesterday from
                    Viscount Motono.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My dear Ambassador</hi>: [By your] excellency’s private
                        and confidential note of the 8th instant you were so good as to communicate
                        to me the substance of a telegram from the Secretary of State calling my
                        attention to the premature publication of the notes recently exchanged
                        between Mr. Lansing and Viscount [Ishii] and you requested that an
                        investigation be made to determine if possible the responsibility for such
                        publication.</p>
                    <p>Being myself embarrassed as much as the Secretary of State by the disclosure
                        of the contents of the notes in question before the time agreed upon, I did
                        not fail to telegraph to the Japanese Minister to China and to cause
                        thorough inquiries to be made at Peking where the leakage appears to have
                        emanated.</p>
                    <p>Baron Hayashi now reports that on November 4 he confidentially communicated
                        the text of the notes to Premier Tuan and to Mr. [?] Vice Minister for
                        Foreign Affairs, in the absence of the Foreign Minister on an express
                        message that the whole subject should be kept strictly secret pending
                        official announcement of the documents at Tokyo on the afternoon of November
                        7. On the evening of November 4 Baron Hayashi received the call, of the
                        American Minister and in the course of the conversation with him referred to
                        the subject. He sent to Doctor [Reinsch], American Minister, at the latter’s
                        request, a copy of the notes early next morning. On the evening of November
                        5 Mr. Smith, correspondent of the Associated Press, called upon the Japanese
                        Legation and after having stated that both had learned of the recent
                        exchange of the notes at Washington respecting the Chinese questions he
                        asked for a copy of the correspondence, replying to the questions put to him
                        by the Secretary of the Japanese Legation who received him. He said that
                        private information had reached him from New York late at night on the
                        previous day to the effect that the United States had recognized the special
                        interests of Japan in China and that the Government of the United States and
                        Japan had selected the policy of the open door. The Secretary of Japanese
                        Legation admitted in strict confidence the accuracy of the report but
                        declined to give out the text of the notes.</p>
                    <p>Baron Hayashi states that prior to the time fixed for publication neither he
                        nor any member of his staff had ever divulged the fact of the exchange of
                        the notes, still less the contents of such documents, to any quarters except
                        to his American colleague and the Chinese Government as above explained. He
                        is unable to discover nor has he any reason to suspect that the revelation
                        originated from the Chinese authorities. He requested the cooperation of
                        Doctor [Reinsch], American Minister, in tracing the source of the
                        information which Mr. Smith had obtained but it now appears that Doctor
                        [Reinsch], American Minister’s, efforts in that direction have also proved
                        unsuccessful.</p>
                    <p>Such is the result of the inquiries made at Peking and while regretting as I
                        do the failure to determine the responsibility of the premature publication,
                        I do not think that any further steps could at this moment be usefully taken
                        to throw light on the mystery.</p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
