<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="355" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d355">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.21/357</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Colombian Minister</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 33</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Colombian Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-07">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March 7, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Convinced that at this momentous and
                            solemn hour in the history of humanity the supreme and clear duty of all
                            the countries of America is to secure the benefits of collective action
                            for the defense of their noble ideals of liberty within justice and the
                            economic interests of the continent, my Government has endeavored to
                            settle old boundary litigations with neighboring Republics in the
                            regions of the Orinoco and Amazonas, accomplishing to that end an
                            amicable settlement, in which, as I have already stated to your
                            excellency, Colombia has sacrificed valuable portions of her territory
                            for the sake of peace and concord.</p>
                        <p>Animated thusly, and for the selfsame aim of fostering harmony and
                            solidarity, my Government, fully alive to the urgency of unifying
                            continental interests, hopes to-day for the ratification of the pact
                            which, signed in Bogotá on April 6 of the year 1914, is to renew the
                            old-standing friendship between Colombia and the United States.</p>
                        <p>Admittedly the pact in itself comprises an act of justice and of
                            international value. That has been acknowledged by eminent men in this
                            country and in Latin America.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, filed in the archives of the Legation under my charge, there
                            are numerous letters that have been received from leading capitalists
                            and business men in such centers of progress as New York, Philadelphia,
                            Chicago and many other cities. In all of these letters is echoed a
                            lively interest in favor of the approval of the treaty <pb facs="0461" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> between Colombia and the United States, a
                            treaty which, submitted by the Executive branch of this Government to
                            the approval of the Senate, has lain in the councils of this body since
                            1914.</p>
                        <p>It is impossible to allow the pending question between our two countries
                            go on any longer without receiving a satisfactory solution. And all the
                            more so when that solution is pressingly urged by the demands of
                            justice, by potent reasons of international wisdom and by valuable
                            interests of the American people.</p>
                        <p>With pleasure I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Julio Betancourt</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>