<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Swenson to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="690"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d690">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Swenson</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 234</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-12-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 19, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your cablegram of the 17th instant, relative to the treaty for the cession of
                    the Danish West Indies, and to confirm mine of the 18th instant in reply
                    thereto, the true reading of which follows: Cipher cablegram received December
                    17, 1901, at 9:30 p.m. [Printed <hi rend="italic">ante.</hi>]</p>
                <p>The text of the treaty which had been scrutinized and approved by the Department
                    reached the Foreign Office Tuesday noon, the 17th instant. In the afternoon I
                    called on the Director General—the Minister was attending a meeting of the
                    Rigsdag—and urged the desirability of cabling Mr. Brun full power to sign the
                    treaty as soon as the Minister for Foreign Affairs had examined it. I was
                    informed that the formalities of finally laying the matter before the King would
                    have to be observed, and that the Finance Committee of the Folkething had
                    requested to have the treaty as agreed upon communicated to it before the
                    signature was authorized.</p>
                <p>This would require a few days. Yesterday morning I handed a copy of your
                    cablegram to Mr. Deuntzer; and in the afternoon I had an interview with him. He
                    said that it was quite impossible to expedite matters sufficiently to have the
                    treaty signed before the <pb facs="0668" n="502" xml:id="pg_502"/> adjournment
                    of the Senate. A Council of State was to be held on Friday; and the King could
                    not be asked to discuss the question earlier. The Folkething Finance Committee
                    could not meet before Thursday afternoon. There seemed to be one or two
                    discrepancies of minor importance, between the text of the treaty received and
                    that of the cablegrams exchanged with Mr. Brun, which would necessitate further
                    communication with him. No time limit for ratification had been inserted in the
                    treaty. This he thought was an oversight; and such a stipulation ought to be
                    added.</p>
                <p>He then told me that the Rigsdag was giving him trouble by raising the question
                    of a plebiscite at this stage in the negotiations, when an agreement between the
                    two Governments had practically been reached. I reserve my report on this point
                    for a separate dispatch, which will be mailed tomorrow.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Laurits S. Swenson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
