<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Reinsch to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-06-09T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-06-09T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-06-09T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-06-09T10:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/2601</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Reinsch</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegrams]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-09T23:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 9, 1917, 11 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The general situation is not unfavorable to compromise as there is discord among
                    the rebel generals and the wiser heads discountenancing violent measures; the
                    communication of the American Government adds to the conciliatory influences.
                    The war question has retired into the background giving way to the purely
                    factional and personal rivalries which from the beginning animated the
                    revolutionists. At present stage is occupied by General Chang Hsun. Upon the
                    invitation of the President who was led to expect assistance from him he has
                    come as far as Tientsin, 2,000 of his troops preceding him <pb facs="0226"
                        n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/> to Peking. Assuming role of arbiter in the last
                    resort he is demanding immediate dissolution of Parliament. The President
                    evidently shaken by his disappointment is weakening although he would appear to
                    have a chance of uniting northern generals against Chang who is universally
                    feared and hated. The latter proposes to come to Peking to-morrow.</p>
                <p>Presence of his notorious troops here is not reassuring and the question arises
                    whether the diplomatic corps should call on the Chinese Government to prohibit
                    bringing up more of these troops. Understand their presence is unnecessary and
                    threatens disturbances.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Reinsch</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
