<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-06-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="96" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/2663</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Sharp</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5456</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-20">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June 20, 1917</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Confirming my telegram No. 2190 of June
                            17, acquainting you with the reply of the French Government made in
                            answer to the communications which I presented in compliance with your
                            telegraphic instructions No. 2313 and 2338 of June 4 and 9 respectively,
                            relative to the identic representations which you proposed be made by
                            the Governments of the United States, France, Great Britain and Japan, I
                            have the honor to inclose herewith a copy and translation of a note from
                            the Foreign Office, the translation of which was transmitted in my said
                            telegram.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. G. Sharp</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                        Affairs</gloss> to Ambassador <persName type="to">Sharp</persName>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry for Foreign Affairs</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-06-14">
                                        <hi rend="italic">June 14, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: By a letter under date of
                                the 6th of this month your excellency was pleased to converse with
                                me of the opportunity which there would be for France, Great
                                Britain, Japan and the United States to make identic representations
                                to the Chinese Government expressing their regret at seeing fresh
                                discord arising in China and their hope of seeing a united and
                                responsible central Government reestablish and maintain harmony.</p>
                            <p>Returning to this question by your letter of the 13th of this month,
                                you were pleased to expound to me afresh the views with which the
                                Federal Government was inspired when it formulated the proposition
                                which I have just recalled.</p>
                            <p>Your Government estimates, in effect, that it is advisable that the
                                Allied Powers, to whom the military party at present in revolt in
                                China claims to belong dissociate their action from all idea of
                                revolt against the established <pb facs="0242" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/> Government in China, while the parliamentary party which today
                                mingles with the existing Government and which remains sympathetic
                                to the views of the Allies, desires only the establishment of a
                                Ministry favorable to the majority. It is to be feared that if the
                                military party triumph civil war will follow and that thus the cause
                                of the Allies will draw no benefit therefrom.</p>
                            <p>The Federal Government considers accordingly that identic
                                representations from the Allies would be able to have the happy
                                result of making all discord cease and of reuniting all the Chinese
                                factions into a grouping favorable to the cause of the Allies.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to make known to your excellency that as early as
                                the 9th of this month I invited the French Ambassador to the United
                                States to make known to Mr. Lansing that the French Government was
                                ready to associate itself with the Government of the United States
                                in making to the Chinese Government an overture recommending to it
                                not to neglect any effort for preventing all disorder and for
                                establishing the desirable harmony in the interior and exterior
                                situation of China.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Jusserand was charged, on the one hand, to add that if the other
                                Powers consulted by the Federal Government were of the same mind,
                                conformable instructions would be addressed to the French Minister
                                at Peking, on the other to present the following observations
                                concerning the meaning of the proposed overture.</p>
                            <p>It did not, in fact, appear happy, as proposed in your excellency’s
                                letter of the 6th of this month, to say to the Chinese Govenment
                                that we consider the entry of China into the war against Germany as
                                of entirely secondary importance. From this point of view, it would
                                seem preferable to say that “if the Powers continue to attach a real
                                importance to the entry of China into the war against the Central
                                Powers, they wish before everything else the reestablishment of
                                order and of harmony in China, because they consider this as a
                                necessity essentially preliminary to any action of the Chinese
                                Government abroad.”</p>
                            <p>Moreover, the French Ambassador was charged with pointing out to Mr.
                                Lansing that it would appear opportune if the overture were to be
                                made, that Italy should be invited to take part. This Power is in
                                fact an Ally in the Great War and it seems that her interests in
                                China give her the right to be associated with the suggested
                                action.</p>
                            <p>Since the communication which I addressed to the French Ambassador at
                                Washington, I have learned that the Japanese Government and the
                                British Government did not show themselves at all favorable to the
                                proposed action. Nevertheless, according to a telegram from Mr.
                                Jusserand, dated the 9th of this month, the United States Minister
                                at Peking is said, for his part, to have taken the identical step
                                proposed without waiting longer.</p>
                            <p>Under these conditions, while renewing the assurance that the French
                                Government is, on its part, disposed to join in a measure which
                                would meet with unanimous concurrence, I would be very much obliged
                                to your excellency to be good enough to confirm to your Government
                                the sense of the communication which the French Ambassador was
                                charged to make to it on the 9th of this month.</p>
                            <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Cambon</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>