<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Minister ( (Hall) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State (
                    (Acheson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-07-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-07-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="205"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">792.94/130</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hall</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-07-07">July 7,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Acheson</hi>: You will remember that at our recent
                    talk on the question of Thailand, the point was raised as to whether His
                    Majesty’s Government was still trying to obtain assurances from the Thai
                    Government that they would not enter into any agreement directed against us nor
                    allow Japan to secure a position of preponderance in Thai affairs. We told you
                    at the time that this political issue had been to some extent shelved in view of
                    the more immediate urgency of the tin and rubber question but that we felt that
                    the conditional offer of assistance which you were now making, altered the
                    position and should allow of the political point being again brought to the
                    fore.</p>
                <p>We now have heard from Sir J. Crosby that in his negotiations he is linking the
                    oil supplies with rubber and tin and is reserving financial credits for
                    discussion in connection with securing assurances from the Thai Government as
                    set out above. The Foreign Office have informed us that they are in agreement
                    with this procedure. You may like to keep this further objective in view when
                    your own negotiations arrive at a more detailed stage.</p>
                <p>May I take this opportunity of expressing to you my thanks for the help which the
                    U. S. Government has given indirectly to Sir J. Crosby by the information which
                    it gave immediately after our talk to the Thai Minister in Washington, It is my
                    personal opinion that <pb facs="0209" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> Sir J. Crosby
                    would not have felt justified in recommending the policy which is now being
                    followed had he not been conscious of some improvement in the general situation
                    as a result of your actions.</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Noel F. Hall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
