<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Thailand ( (Chapman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-09-02T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-09-02T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-02T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-02T04:00:00-05:00" n="298"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 (D)Regulations/4367: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Thailand</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chapman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bangkok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-02T16:00:00+07:00"
                            >September 2, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 3—9:54 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>442. During the course of the conversation today the Foreign Minister<note n="76"
                        xml:id="d298fn1">Nai Direck Jaiyanama.</note> expressed his satisfaction
                    over word received from the Thai Minister in Washington of the sympathetic
                    attitude of the American authorities in regard to the granting of export
                    licenses for American goods needed in Thailand. The Foreign Minister said that
                    his Government desired preference to be given to such needs in the following
                    sequence: (1) armaments; (2) requirements of government ministries and
                    departments; (3) civilian requirements. Referring to the Government’s recent
                    unequivocal public statements that Thailand would resist aggression, the Foreign
                    Minister remarked that in order to resist armaments were needed. He said
                    smilingly that, while the impression might have existed in Washington in the
                    past that there was no use furnishing armaments to Thailand because they might
                    be turned to the benefit of the Japanese, he hoped that impression no longer
                    prevailed.</p>
                <p>Referring to Minister Peck’s<note n="77" xml:id="d298fn2">Willys R. Peck,
                        Appointed Minister to Thailand.</note> impending arrival, the Foreign
                    Minister said that arrangements for the presentation of his credentials would be
                    made as soon as possible after he reaches Bangkok.</p>
                <p>While some misgivings were occasioned by the designation in August of Colonel
                    Prayoon and Luang Vichitr to act for the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    (Legation’s telegram No. 427, August 20, 5 p.m.<note n="78" xml:id="d298fn3">Not
                        printed.</note>), the subsequent elevation of Nai Direck Jaiyanama to the
                    post of Foreign Minister and other recent Cabinet changes have been taken by
                    experienced observers here to indicate a strengthening of the position of those
                    elements in the Thai Government which have all along been pro-democratic and
                    anti-Axis in sympathy and reflects a realistic appreciation on the part of both
                    government officials and the public of the Japanese menace to Thailand following
                    the occupation of southern Indochina.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Chapman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
