<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-28T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-28T22:00:00-05:00" n="44" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.92/220: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Thailand</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bangkok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-29T10:00:00+07:00">January
                                    29, 1941—10 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>51. In an hour’s conversation with Prince Varnvaidya, adviser to the
                            Foreign Office, who will head the Thai delegation to the mediation
                            conference at Tokyo regarding the dispute between Thailand and
                            Indochina, I elicited statements which seem to confirm the reports I
                            have previously submitted to the Department to the effect that there is
                            a plot formulated by Japan and aided by Thailand to oust the French
                            completely from Indochina. The French are going to be led to the
                            slaughter pen at Tokyo, it would appear. …</p>
                        <p>In reply to my inquiry as to whether he thought that Thailand would be
                            allowed to control this territory in the event it is awarded by mediator
                            Japan, Varnvaidya answered in the affirmative, explaining that Laos and
                            Cambodia were not attractive to Japan since they have little economic
                            value and Thailand is interested in acquiring these territories largely
                            for “sentimental reasons”. Japan, he added, is primarily interested in
                            Tonkin and Cochin-China which are important commercially. I suggested
                            that the acquisition of Laos and Cambodia with their population of
                            approximately 4,000,000 people who are very poor might prove to be a
                            liability rather than an asset to Thailand. Varnvaidya said he did not
                            think so since the administration of the territories by Thailand would
                            cost so much less than it is costing the French.</p>
                        <p>I asked the Prince if he thought Japan might ask for a reward for
                            awarding this territory to Thailand. The Prince replied in the negative,
                            stating that Thailand had “assurances from Japan that her independence
                            would be respected”. Furthermore, he added, Thailand was not included in
                            the Japanese program for greater East Asia but would be in the sphere
                            which the Japanese described as “co-prosperity”. Varnvaidya then
                            intimated that Japan might possibly ask Thailand for a military pact
                            which would be directed against Great Britain. When I terminated the
                            conversation with the remark that I <pb facs="0058" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> very sincerely hoped that in the coming days
                            Thailand’s complete independence would not be impaired Varnvaidya
                            thanked me most profusely.</p>
                        <p>The Thai delegation according to Varnvaidya will comprise 18 persons
                            including besides himself the Chief of Staff of the armed forces,
                            representatives of the army and navy, the air force, the Thai Minister
                            and the Naval and Military Attachés in Tokyo. He said he understood that
                            Matsuoka will play an important personal role in the mediation
                            conferences. The Thai delegation plans to fly to Tokyo on February 2 and
                            should be there for at least a fortnight he said.</p>
                        <p>Prince Varnvaidya has served his Government in both London and Paris and
                            is regarded as one of the most astute political leaders in Thailand.
                            …</p>
                        <p>Sent to Cavite for repetition to the Department, to Chungking, to Hong
                            Kong and to Shanghai. Shanghai please repeat to Tokyo all sections.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grant</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>