<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="482" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1115/5046: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Vice Consul at Dairen</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Richardson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dairen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-25T09:00:00+09:00">October 25,
                                1941—9 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received October 27—8:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Reference the Embassy’s telegram of October 23, 5 p.m. [to Dairen]. Police
                        interference with the Consulate has entirely stopped. From the viewpoint of
                        reciprocity, however, the treatment of Americans in the Kwantung leased
                        territory leaves much to be desired. An American citizen who is returning to
                        the United States applied for foreign exchange to the value of United States
                        dollars $250 but was allowed only $100, although Japanese leaving the United
                        States can take with them $500 without formalities.<note n="53" xml:id="d482fn1">Marginal notation by the Assistant Secretary of State
                            (Acheson): “$250 is the correct figure. D. A.”</note> (This difference
                        in treatment, in addition to causing more inconvenience to Americans than to
                        Japanese, reduces Japanese frozen credits in the United States more rapidly
                        than American credits in Japan are reduced.)</p>
                    <p>Another American citizen who is returning to the United States on a visit was
                        refused permission to take with him a ring, his watch, cuff links and
                        necktie pin until a local resident gave a written guarantee that the
                        traveler would bring the articles back with him when he returned.</p>
                    <pb facs="0447" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                    <p>Chase<note n="54" xml:id="d482fn2">Augustus S. Chase, Consul at Dairen, who
                            was ill.</note> and I are very anxious to ship to the United States our
                        household effects which include a considerable proportion of Chase’s total
                        effects and all of mine. On August 18 the Consulate reported to the Embassy
                        at Tokyo that the local authorities demanded a detailed list of the effects
                        to be shipped to be submitted with the application for permission to ship.
                        The Embassy took up the question with the Foreign Office at Tokyo and on
                        September 17 informed the Consulate that the Foreign Office had stated that
                        the Japanese Embassy at Hsinking had stated that while no special permit
                        from the Japanese Ambassador to Manchukuo (who is concurrently the chief
                        official of the Kwantung Government) was necessary for the shipment of our
                        effects, it would be advisable to request through the Embassy at Hsinking
                        “customs privileges.”</p>
                    <p>This was done on September 20. No answer, nor even an acknowledgement of the
                        request, has yet been received.<note n="55" xml:id="d482fn3">Marginal
                            notation by the Adviser on Political Relations (Hornbeck): “I think it
                            is time (high time) for retaliation—which would be easy. SKH.” To this
                            Mr. Acheson added: “I agree. DA.” On November 18, however, Mr. Hamilton
                            initialed a memorandum to Dr. Hornbeck which concluded that “there is no
                            need for Departmental action on the telegram under reference, at least
                            not until we hear that the Japanese in Dairen are not abiding by the
                            procedure governing departing Americans to be established by the
                            Japanese Government on a reciprocal basis.”</note> This was reported on
                        October 13 to the Embassy at Tokyo, which immediately made further
                        representations to the Foreign Office, which promised every assistance.</p>
                    <p>The Consulate has just been told informally and unofficially that it has been
                        decided by the authorities of the Kwantung bureau in Hsinking that we must
                        make application for permission to ship listing every individual article in
                        each packing case and giving the value of each article.</p>
                    <p>This would involve unpacking, listing and repacking of all articles in use in
                        two houses of medium size, which in addition to taking a long time would be
                        very expensive.</p>
                    <p>The Consulate has been unable up to the present to obtain written
                        confirmation of the above mentioned decision of the authorities in Hsinking
                        or even any indication that our request is being considered.</p>
                    <p>From the constant delay and the new demands continually brought forward it
                        appears obvious that Hsinking authorities, probably directed by the economic
                        section of the Kwantung army, which has ultimate control in Manchuria over
                        export and import permits are actuated not by a desire to enforce
                        regulations but by the wish to obstruct and if possible and [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] to prevent the shipment of our effects without
                        giving direct refusal.</p>
                    <p>Sent to Peiping, repeated to Tokyo.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Richardson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>