<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political Relations (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.94/123</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political
                        Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-02-01">February 1,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Netherlands Minister called me up late last evening and stated that he had
                    from his Government a telegram stating that his Government is making a statement
                    to the Japanese Government, in Tokyo, in writing, to the effect that the
                    Netherlands Government will take no part and be no party to the establishment of
                    a “new order in Asia” under the aegis of any foreign power.<note n="68"
                        xml:id="d50fn1">See telegram No. 158, February 3, 6 p.m., from the
                        Ambassador in Japan, <ref target="#pg_54">p. 54</ref>.</note> I asked
                    whether Mr. Loudon could tell me what was the occasion or the cause of this
                    action. Mr. Loudon replied that his Government stated that this was in reply to
                    a statement made by Mr. Matsuoka.<note n="69" xml:id="d50fn2">See telegram No.
                        135, January 28, midnight, from the Ambassador in Japan, <ref
                            target="#pg_46">p. 46</ref>.</note> Mr. Loudon inquired what was my
                    reaction. I said that I would wish to think the matter over; that I would assume
                    that we would receive some report on the subject from our Embassy in Tokyo; and
                    that I would not wish to express any opinion offhand. Mr. Loudon said that he
                    would like to talk the matter over with me at an early convenient moment.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
