<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-20T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-20T15:00:00-05:00" n="553" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/16703a: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-20T16:00:00-04:00">June 20,
                                    1941—4 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>342. 1. The American Legation at Bucharest has received information from
                            a reliable source as follows:<note n="97" xml:id="d553fn1">Omissions
                                indicated in the original.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“… military circles in Germany are greatly interested in the
                                    continuation of the Sino-Japanese war. They are indirectly
                                    encouraging China to resist and have also permitted various
                                    countries to send additional war material to China. While the
                                    Germans are using Japan as a threat against the United States, …
                                    the former have made a secret economic treaty with the Dutch
                                    authorities in occupied Holland which will become effective
                                    immediately after the end of the war. This treaty secures for
                                    Germany large concessions in Java, Sumatra, Celebes, Borneo and
                                    the Dutch part of New Guinea. These concessions cover large
                                    areas and include the Banka and Billiton tin mines as well as
                                    some oil properties. The price for these concessions has been
                                    fixed and will be met in part by reducing the cost assessed the
                                    Dutch for the upkeep of the German army of occupation. In the
                                    event that Japan attacks the Dutch East Indies and succeeds in
                                    gaining foothold there, Germany will immediately claim her
                                    rights.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. You may make discreet use of the foregoing in any conversations you
                            may have with influential Japanese without revealing the source of your
                            information.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>