<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="64" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 P. W./116</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                Division of Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-02-07">February 7, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In leaving with me the attached <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of
                            February 7<note n="82" xml:id="d64fn1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> marked “very confidential”, Mr.
                            Butler, Counselor of the British Embassy, said that the Embassy had just
                            received two telegrams from <pb facs="0071" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> the
                            British Foreign Office containing confidential information which the
                            Embassy was instructed to communicate to the American Government. Mr.
                            Butler said that the information was as follows:</p>
                        <p>The first telegram, dated February 6, was to the effect that according to
                            reliable information the Japanese Embassy in London on February 4
                            received instructions to reduce to a minimum its contacts with the
                            British and to be prepared to leave on short notice;<note n="83" xml:id="d64fn2">The Chargé in the United Kingdom in telegram No.
                                477, February 7, 10 p.m., reported similar information. In a
                                conversation on February 6, Anthony Eden, British Secretary of State
                                for Foreign Affairs, informed Harry Hopkins, Special Assistant to
                                President Roosevelt, and the American Chargé (Johnson) that the
                                British were “apprehensive lest Japan may be planning some direct
                                attack against Great Britain in the Far East”. Mr. Johnson noted
                                that they were “hoping for some positive move by the United States
                                which would act as a restraint on Japan.” (740.0011 European War
                                1939/8145 ²⁄₅)</note> that these instructions were discussed at the
                            Japanese Embassy in London; that some members of the Embassy were
                            dismayed by the instructions while others were not; that it was believed
                            at the Japanese Embassy that the instructions had reference to some
                            scheme of cooperation with Germany advocated by the Japanese military
                            party.</p>
                        <p>The second telegram, also dated February 6, was to the effect that the
                            notification date referred to in the first telegram was either February
                            9 or February 18 (the telegram as received by the British Embassy was
                            garbled and the Embassy had not yet worked out whether the correct date
                            was February 9 or February 18); that there was some indefinite reference
                            to the plan in question being linked up with the Soviet Government and
                            Chinese Communists; that the proposed action was being carefully planned
                            so as not to appear to affect United States interests; that the movement
                            of the United States Fleet was regarded as of a routine character; and
                            that there was a good deal of talk at the Japanese Embassy in London
                            about war.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Butler added that it was possible that the British Ambassador might
                            ask to talk to the Secretary of State and to the President in regard to
                            the information set forth in the two telegrams under reference.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>M[<hi rend="smallcaps">axwell</hi>] M. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">amilton</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>