<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-08-07T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-08-07T19:00:00-05:00" n="731" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d731">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.24/1143<hi rend="superscript">2/11</hi>:Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-08-07T20:00:00-04:00">August 7,
                                    1941—8 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3017. The Department desires that you seek an early opportunity to
                            discuss with the appropriate British authorities the question of the
                            transit duties now being levied by the Government of Burma on shipments
                            of American materials consigned to the Chinese Goverment or its agencies
                            and passing in transit through Burma. These shipments now consist almost
                            wholly of “lend-lease” materials and supplies purchased upon the basis
                            of credits extended by the Government of the United States.</p>
                        <p>The Department considers that the application of these duties to such
                            cargoes is inconsistent with the coordinated policies of the United
                            States, the British Empire and China in meeting Axis aggression in the
                            Orient as well as in the Occident. Although the transit duties are paid
                            by the Chinese the ultimate burden of their payment must be borne by the
                            United States Government because of the dependence of the Chinese
                            Government upon the United States for financial support being rendered
                            in the form of loans. The collection of these duties also results in
                            administrative delays in the clearance of such shipment at Rangoon and
                            at the border.</p>
                        <p>For the reasons stated above this Government considers that shipments of
                            American materials consigned to the Chinese Government should be totally
                            exempted from the Burma transit duties and requests that necessary steps
                            be taken to that end. In making your representations you may point out
                            that these duties constitute a recently developed and abnormal source of
                            revenue, the loss of which would not deprive Burma of other substantial
                            economic and financial benefits, such as greatly increased
                            Government-owned railway revenues, accruing from the newly developed
                            China transit trade.</p>
                        <p>Please report the results of your representations to the Department by
                            telegraph.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>