<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-01-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="2" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                    <head>2. Letter From the <persName type="from">Shah</persName> of Iran to
                        President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d2fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Special
                            Head of State Correspondence File, Iran—Presidential Correspondence. No
                            classification marking. The copy of the Shah’s letter in the Department
                            of State is attached to a covering memorandum indicating that the
                            original was delivered by the Iranian Embassy to the Department on
                            January 17. (Department of State, Central Files, POL 15–1
                            US/Johnson)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-01-07">January 7, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dear Mr. President,</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have been recalling with pleasure impressions of your memorable but short
                        visit to Teheran, in the company of Mrs. Johnson and your daughter. It was
                        indeed gratifying to have had the occasion to meet you again personally. For
                        the citizens of our capital it was a rare and cherished opportunity to have
                        a glimpse of a kind-hearted and affable personality of your stature, to show
                        their genuine admiration for you and to extend to you, as you no doubt
                        witnessed, their spontaneous and cordial welcome. Such personal contacts and
                        human relationships make for more sincere cooperation, still better
                        understanding and closer ties of friendship between our two countries.</p>
                    <p>Let me express the earnest hope that the United States, under your wise and
                        capable leadership will further succeed in her continued efforts to usher in
                        a new era of peace and prosperity for mankind.</p>
                    <p>I am quite confident, Mr. President, that your wisdom and high statesmanship,
                        as well as your long and intimate association with American politics and
                        extensive knowledge and experience of world affairs, will prove invaluable
                        assets in the successful discharge of the heavy responsibilities of your
                        high office both in the United States and abroad.</p>
                    <p>Since your visit, Mr. President, much has happened in Iran. A comprehensive
                        programme of far-reaching social, political and economic reforms, of which
                        you were then given a brief account, has now been fully implemented. These
                        reforms have transformed completely the entire structure of our society, and
                        placed its foundations firmly upon the enlightened and progressive
                        principles of our time. In their application, varying political slogans
                        which essentially cater for the interests of only a certain class of society
                        played no part. The guiding principle of our national policy is the
                        realization of that which is advantageous to the interests of a free and
                        independent society.</p>
                    <p>That the Iranian people wholeheartedly supported the cause of our
                        revolutionary reforms was amply manifested at the referendum of January
                        1963, and during our recent general elections. I am certain that you are
                        already familiar with these events.</p>
                    <p>Our position today, from the point of view of internal stability, national
                        prestige, and our people’s confident hope for a better life has <pb facs="0032" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/> reached a point where, if no external
                        dangers should threaten us, gives us reason to look to the future with
                        well-founded optimism and confidence.</p>
                    <p>Turning to conditions outside Iran, we are thankful that the firm and
                        far-sighted policy of the United States has led the world to the threshold
                        of a period of relaxation of international tension, and that the Soviet
                        Union seems, for the present at least, to have discarded the use of force as
                        an instrument of her foreign policy. In these circumstances, I believe, Mr.
                        President, co-existence with Russia, in the face of the Chinese peril to
                        universal peace, commends itself as the wisest course to adopt; bearing in
                        mind that until such time that complete and general disarmament with full
                        and precise control becomes a reality, the fundamental question of our time,
                        namely the preservation of peace, remains unsolved. Meanwhile, it is a
                        matter of course that we should be well-disposed to undertake any step or
                        action that would contribute to the realization of this goal, provided, of
                        course, that in so doing we do not compromise our principles.</p>
                    <p>Your illustrious predecessor, in a letter written to me just before his
                        tragic demise, had asked my opinion, in view of our past experiences with
                        the Soviet Union, on the question of the bruited non-aggression treaty
                        between <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and the Warsaw Pact
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>You are well aware, Mr. President, that in 1959 we were on the point of
                        signing with the Soviet Union a non-aggression treaty for a period of some
                        30 or even 50 years. Their rather ridiculous initial conditions, however,
                        delayed the negotiations for a few days. In the meantime, we received
                        messages from the Presidents of the United States, Turkey and Pakistan
                        warning us of the dangers of such a step. We were even reminded of the fate
                        of the Baltic States. The reason they advanced was that if any action of
                        this nature were to be taken, it would have to be on behalf of all the
                        countries of the free world; in other words, that such an action would have
                        to be collective, if the free world’s united front were to remain
                        intact.</p>
                    <p>This reasoning I found convincing, and I believe that it holds true even
                        today. There can be no objection, in principle, to the conclusion of a
                        non-aggression treaty between <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and the
                        Warsaw Pact countries; it may even be fruitful; but what, may in that case
                        be asked, will be the impact of such a treaty on the regional member nations
                        of the Central Treaty Organization? Where will American and British
                        obligations to <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss> stand? Will Russia,
                        then, be allowed to have a free hand to do as she pleases elsewhere? In such
                        a situation—should it arise—it is not unlikely that the countries thus
                        exposed will have to see how best they can arrive at a bilateral agreement
                        with the Soviet Union and that, certainly at a price.</p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/>
                    <p>It is, therefore, highly advisable that the non-aggression pact between
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and Warsaw Pact countries—if there
                        is to be one—should cover all member countries of <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss>, in particular those bordering on the Soviet Union and
                        not to leave them outside the agreement. We have also heard of a proposal
                        that all countries of the world should sign a treaty of non-aggression with
                        each other.</p>
                    <p>There are certain countries in the world, the preservation of whose
                        independence and territorial integrity, because of their characteristic
                        geographic position, does not only constitute a service to those countries
                        alone, but a service also to the stability and peace of an entire area. Iran
                        is an instance of such a country.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Brezhnev</persName> paid a visit to Iran about a couple of
                        months ago. In his talks with me he did his best to be friendly and to leave
                        formality aside. So much so, that on the last day of his stay he went as far
                        as confiding to me that, relations between Iran and the Soviet Union having
                        improved considerably, he would permit himself to express Russia’s dislike
                        of Iran’s participation in military agreements with the West. My immediate
                        reply, of course, was that one did not have to go too far to seek the
                        reasons for the existence of such regional defensive agreements. They would
                        automatically lose their force and validity as soon as the numerous military
                        pacts between countries of the world ceased to exist and the dangers of war
                        and aggression no longer posed a threat to the territorial integrity of
                        smaller nations; and that such an ideal situation could only be brought
                        about when general and complete disarmament with proper controls became a
                        reality.</p>
                    <p>Permit me to say a few words now about developments in some of the countries
                        around Iran. A matter to which I wish, Mr. President, to call your attention
                        is the danger which threatens this area of the world. I refer to the
                        stockpiles of weapons of aggression in the possession of Egypt and the ever
                        increasing delivery of offensive equipment to that country by the Soviet
                        Union, designed to serve, overtly or under cover, as instruments of Egyptian
                        intervention. Yemen, the Morocco-Algeria conflict and the arming of Somalia
                        for expansion are instances in point. Egypt, in fact, has already prepared
                        an “intervention force” of considerable size, equipped with long-range
                        bombers, missiles, heavy troop transport planes, submarines, ships, and
                        torpedo boats armed with missiles, so that if a “change” should happen to
                        occur in any Arab country and President Nasser be asked to “intervene” he
                        would willingly do so and let the world be faced with a fait accompli. I
                        should perhaps add that even Iran does not seem to be too distant for his
                        designs or immune from his subversive activities.</p>
                    <p>It is in consideration of these compelling reasons that the security of the
                        Persian Gulf poses for us a source of constant concern, not only in the
                        interest of our own country, but in the interest of the West as well.
                        Indeed, <pb facs="0034" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> the stakes involved are so
                        great that any lack of vigilance on our parts may have disastrous
                        consequences. To this situation, we have endeav-oured to draw the attention
                        of the United States Government.</p>
                    <p>Last year, the Pentagon prepared a Five Year Plan for Iran which was accepted
                        with some reservations and for want of a more satisfactory alternative.<note n="2" xml:id="d2fn2">For text of the U.S. Five-Year Military Program for
                            Iran, accepted by Iran on September 19, 1962, see <ref target="frus1961-63v18#pg_105">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1961–1963, vol. XVIII, pp.
                                105</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v18#pg_109">109</ref>.</note> This
                        Plan has already proved inadequate for the requirements of the changing
                        situation in this area. The Iranian Army is capable of serious combat
                        neither in the mountainous regions—for lack of adequate material
                        requirements and logistical support—nor in the plains—for being devoid of
                        the required mobility, and armour for such warfare. Our armoured equipment,
                        the M47 tanks, are of type not in current production whose replacement and
                        spare parts can be found with great difficulty. Now, if such is the
                        condition of our equipment in peace time, it is difficult to imagine how
                        they can be of any serious value at times of emergency. We have no military
                        stockpiles of any kind and no reserves, even of machine guns, automatic
                        rifles and ammunition to meet routine demands. Should unforeseen
                        circumstances require us to put our army in a state of mobilization, we
                        shall hardly be able to place ourselves in a state of readiness for the
                        emergency. All our supplies and equipment have been distributed to provide
                        for the army’s current requirements.</p>
                    <p>The responsibilities of the Iranian Air Force, moreover, have never been
                        equal to even the minimum of the Army requirements. Our airfields are
                        limited in number, and where they do exist we are there faced with
                        deficiencies in radar facilities and anti-aircraft protection.</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, ships and vessels presently in service with our navy, in number
                        as well as in military value, are hardly adequate to carry out their vital
                        responsibilities.</p>
                    <p>If our armed forces are to function effectively and to perform their alloted
                        duties, and if Iran, a staunch and steadfast ally of the United States, is
                        to play her full part in the changing political climate of the Middle East,
                        then obviously, Mr. President, these shortages have to be met. Otherwise, we
                        must consider as wasted the funds that are presently allocated for
                        maintaining our armed forces.</p>
                    <p>In my correspondence with you, Mr. President, I wish to be perfectly candid
                        in dealing with matters of mutual interest. If the United States is not in a
                        position to meet our clear and urgent military needs in addition to the Five
                        Year Plan, in order to be able to fulfil our duties, I thought that we might
                        advisedly arrange for the purchase of our additional needs, under favourable
                        conditions, from the United States of America or from elsewhere.</p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/>
                    <p>Of course, the question of <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss> strategy,
                        American engagements and a great many related topics will form the subject
                        of discussions by our representatives at the <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss> Ministerial Council. We hope that this forthcoming
                        meeting, due to be held in Washington, will provide a suitable opportunity
                        for clarifying all these points. In the meantime, it would be useful if you
                        should see fit to appoint someone to discuss with me urgent matters of
                        interest to our two countries and to report the result to you.</p>
                    <p>In the field of economic activity, it is a source of satisfaction that our
                        own potentials are so great that if we can devote all our planned resources
                        to the implementation of our Five Year Plan, we can envisage an annual
                        growth of 8 per cent, with every hope of raising considerably the material
                        welfare of our people. We have received a number of proposals for economic
                        assistance from Western and even Eastern European countries as well as from
                        the Soviet Union. Doubtless, we would be more than gratified to have offers
                        of loan from the A.I.D. with their very generous terms, and also from the
                        Export-Import Bank and its subsidiary organizations. We would welcome,
                        further, private American investors who would wish to participate in the
                        development of our economy.</p>
                    <p>To turn once again to the Middle East, the situation in Iraq seems uncertain.
                        With the fall of Kassem’s unwholesome regime, we welcomed with relief what
                        we hoped would be closer ties with Iraq, thinking that since the Baathists
                        at once began to purge their country of Communists, we had been rid of a
                        troublesome neighbour. Our optimism was shortlived however, for we soon
                        discovered in Southern Iran centres of Arab espionage, with their covetous
                        eyes on a certain integral part of our country, namely Khuzistan, the main
                        centre of our oil industry.</p>
                    <p>With the overthrow of the Baathist Government in Iraq, this danger seems to
                        have abated. Uncertainty however, still persists. For our information
                        indicates that Marshal Aref himself had been fully aware of the above
                        activities and had given them his full support.</p>
                    <p>I regret to say that already Marshal Aref has shown a tendency to turn
                        towards Egypt. If I lay emphasis on this question and express my concern, it
                        is because we are well aware of the developments in this area and the course
                        they are likely to take.</p>
                    <p>Here, I must state that our attitude towards Iraq has always been a friendly
                        one, and we have always hoped that Iraq will have a strong and stable
                        Government, capable of preserving its independence and of safeguarding its
                        national interests.</p>
                    <p>The Kurdish question is still unsettled. Agents of international communism
                        are making every endeavour to exploit the situation to their own advantage,
                        and Cairo is anxious to play its dubious role in any development in this
                        situation.</p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="8" xml:id="pg_8"/>
                    <p>If negotiations between the Government at Baghdad and the Kurds should fail
                        to reach an understanding, we have reason to expect that the fighting will
                        flare up again in the spring.</p>
                    <p>We have reports to the effect that President Nasser did try, and is still
                        making efforts to “mediate” between the Kurds and the Central Government of
                        Iraq. This, on the surface, sounds quite harmless, even perhaps commendable.
                        However, the contents of one of his messages to the Kurds fully reveals his
                        ill intentions towards Iran. He has said in effect, according to our
                        information, that it was a pity the Kurds were fighting the Arabs. He would
                        have given them full support if their force were directed against Iran.</p>
                    <p>Thus with the situation prevailing in Iraq and with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> adventures in Yemen and elsewhere likely to
                        erupt in other parts of the Middle East as well, my obligations to my
                        country and my people make it incumbent upon me to take all precautions for
                        the safety of the country and of our national interests. We cannot tolerate
                        Egypt’s subversive influence at our doorstep; nor fail to regard it
                        seriously. I think, as referred to above, upon the stability of Iran depends
                        the security of the entire Middle East. While we in Iran are seeking to
                        ensure the security and stability of our own country, and that of the
                        Persian Gulf, we are contributing also to the preservation of peace in this
                        entire area—an area in which the United States has vital interests.</p>
                    <p>Happily, on these as on other matters, we have always maintained close and
                        cordial contact, and our views have never been far apart.</p>
                    <p>Again, my best wishes for your happiness and success in the service of the
                        United States of America as well as in the cause of the free world.</p>
                    <p>With high esteem,</p>
                    <p>Sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="strong">
                                <persName corresp="#p_PMR1">M.R. Pahlavi</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>