<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>205. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern
                    and South Asian Affairs (Battle) to the Ambassador at Large () to the Ambassador
                    at Large (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recfgV5j0WMmONcRO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="205"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <head>205. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern
                    and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BLD2" type="from"
                        >Battle</persName>) to the Ambassador at Large (<persName corresp="#p_HWA2"
                        type="to">Harriman</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d205fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 ARAB–ISR. Secret; Exdis.
                        Drafted by <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> Country Director
                            <persName>Donald C. Bergus</persName> and cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-06-02">June 2, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Your Meeting with the Shah of Iran: Middle East Crisis</item>
                </list>
                <p>During your visit to Paris, I recommend that you meet with the Shah to discuss
                    the Middle East crisis and specifically to increase his understanding of and
                    support for our policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0406" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The current Arab/Israel crisis has had repercussions in Iran. At the same time
                    Nasser called for the evacuation of <gloss target="#t_UNEF1">UNEF</gloss>, he
                    also publicly requested Jordan and Saudi Arabia to intervene with the Shah to
                    stop sales of Iranian oil to Israel. (Iranian oil has been supplied to Israel
                    since 1957 and has been carried by tanker around the Arabian Peninsula through
                    the Gulf of Aqaba to Eilat.)</p>
                <p>In response, the Iranian Government issued an official denial that Iranian oil
                    was being sold to Israel. This is technically true, since the transactions are
                    made through third parties. At the same time, the Iranians became concerned
                    about their isolated position among the Islamic nations of the Middle East and
                    about the effects of Iran’s ties with Israel on Iran’s efforts to establish
                    closer relations with the moderate Arab states. On May 31, the Iranian
                    Government issued a statement supporting “the legitimate rights of Moslem
                    peoples” and saying that it regards “as necessary the securing of the legitimate
                    rights of the Palestinian people as mentioned in the U.N. resolutions.” The
                    statement also expressed the hope for a peaceful solution to the present crisis.
                    The Iranian press has from the first attacked Nasser for instigating the
                    crisis.</p>
                <p>Iran’s concern about its relations with the moderate Arab states has no doubt
                    been increased as a result of King <persName>Hussein</persName>’s flight to
                    Cairo to effect a grand reconciliation and to sign a military agreement with the
                        <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. At this writing King
                        <persName>Faisal</persName> is still in Europe, but we do not exclude the
                    possibility that he, too, may in some manner make a gesture toward improving his
                    relations with Nasser in the name of Arab solidarity against the Israel
                    threat.</p>
                <p>In their talks with us, Iranian officials have been expressing the hope that we
                    would take a firm line to keep the Gulf of Aqaba open. The Shah undoubtedly
                    believes that we bear much of the responsibility for the crisis for not having
                    acted vigorously to oppose Nasser long since. Some Iranian officials have
                    indicated a concern that we might resume aid to Nasser in order to end the
                    crisis.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Suggested talking points for use with the Shah:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The present crisis in the Middle East is grave and highly
                            dangerous.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The U.S. is doing its best to urge restraint on all parties to the
                            dispute.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We do not believe that Nasser wishes to be the first to shoot in the
                            present situation. Indeed, it would be against his interest to do so. He
                            has again proven his ability as an expert, albeit a malevolent one, in
                            exploiting and building upon the events of each day. He has been able to
                            create <pb facs="0407" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> circumstances in which
                            the very firmly held anti-Israel sentiments of most Arabs come to the
                            fore.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>For the past six months to a year, Nasser had been convincing himself
                            that the U.S. was determined to destroy him and to humiliate Egypt. He
                            viewed the cessation of significant U.S. aid to Egypt in the <gloss
                                target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s growing economic crisis, his failure
                            to achieve a victory in the Yemen, resistance to his designs by Kings
                                <persName>Faisal</persName> and <persName>Hussein</persName>, and
                            even the good relations between Iran and the United States in this
                            light.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Nasser, therefore, is trying to exploit the current crisis to his
                            advantage. He has consistently sought to identify publicly the U.S. with
                            Israel. He now believes he is in a position whereby the U.S. and Israel
                            face the painful choice of either accepting his “victory” (withdrawal of
                                <gloss target="#t_UNEF1">UNEF</gloss>, closure of the Straits of
                            Tiran) or committing “aggression” against Egypt. He strongly hopes for
                            the former. He believes, however, that if he is destroyed as a result of
                            Israel/U.S. military action, he can destroy with him a good many Western
                            interests in the area. He considers this a deterrent. There is some
                            speculation that among Nasser’s objectives is the resumption of U.S. aid
                            to the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. We have told the Iranians
                            that there is no possibility that we will resume aid to the <gloss
                                target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> in the foreseeable future.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>There is good reason to believe that the Soviets may have been
                            instrumental in touching off the present crisis by floating in mid-May
                            in Damascus and Cairo a report that a massive Israel attack on Syria was
                            imminent. Since then, they have attempted to reap full propaganda
                            advantage of the theme that Israel is the aggressor and has U.S.
                            support, that the Soviet Union is the protector of the Arabs and that
                            the Soviet Union hopes war can be avoided if only the U.S. will restrain
                            Israel. The Soviets seem to have been taken by surprise by Nasser’s
                            proclaimed closure of the Gulf of Aqaba and have thus far confined
                            themselves to general statements in support of the Arab position that
                            the Straits lie in Egyptian territorial waters.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>We certainly do not approve of <persName>Hussein</persName>’s early
                            public capitulation to Nasser. <persName>Hussein</persName> as a
                            sovereign independent ruler has to decide where his best interests lie.
                            He has assured us that this gesture was solely for the purpose of
                            insurance and that his attitude toward and intention to cooperate with
                            the United States is unchanged. Whether <persName>Hussein</persName>
                            will be able to maintain this position under the pressure of events
                            cannot be predicted with certainty.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>It would be helpful if the Shah were to let the Israelis know that his
                            attitude toward them is unchanged and that his intention is to maintain
                            the present relationship with them in all its aspects as circumstances
                            warrant. The Shah could also usefully counsel the Israelis to exercise
                            military restraint in order to give the fullest opportunity for
                            multilateral diplomacy to work. We would hope that Iran would take no
                            steps to interrupt the commercial relationships whereby Iran obtains
                            oil.</item>
                        <pb facs="0408" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>We would also hope that the Shah would get word to
                                <persName>Faisal</persName> and <persName>Hussein</persName>
                            indicating that the present crisis should not be allowed to impair the
                            close relationship which Iran has with both countries. This relationship
                            is based on a mutuality of interests which continues to endure.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The U.S. position in this crisis has been made clear by the President
                            in his statement of May 23. The United States is firmly committed to the
                            support of the political independence and territorial integrity of all
                            the nations of the area. The United States strongly opposes aggression
                            by anyone in the area, in any form, overt or clandestine. The United
                            States considers the Gulf of Aqaba to be an international waterway and
                            feels that a blockade of Israeli shipping is illegal and potentially
                            disastrous to the cause of peace. The United States is making vigorous
                            efforts to obtain effective United Nations action to resolve this
                            crisis. Concurrently, we are consulting urgently with the maritime
                            nations of the world with a view to multilateral action asserting our
                            right to use this international waterway.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
