<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Paraguay ( (Wheeler) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d236</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">236</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-04-10T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-04-10T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-04-10T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-04-10T16:00:00-05:00" n="236"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d236">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/3005: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Paraguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wheeler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Asunción</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-04-10T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >April 10, 1933—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received April 11—1:10 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>43. My telegram No. 42, April 7, 10 p.m. [<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.<hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi>.] On April 8, my Brazilian colleague received
                    instructions to make the representation “together with the Argentine and Chilean
                    Ministers” and to take the initiative in the affair. The Argentine and Chilean
                    Ministers also were on that date informed that I would join with them and with
                    the Brazilian Minister in the prospective action. Last night the Argentine
                    Minister sent me word that he had arranged a meeting within the hour with the
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs at whose house we met and made the joint
                    representation, my Brazilian colleague taking the lead. It appeared, however, at
                    this meeting that the instructions received by my colleagues had either lacked
                    clearness or had been in very general terms, the Argentine Minister appearing to
                    be most hazy as to what his Government was pressing. The Chilean Minister later
                    told me confidentially that he himself had not received any specific instruction
                    but was so certain from previous correspondence of what Cruchaga desired that he
                    had joined the representations without hesitation. As my personal understanding
                    with the President was complete and satisfactory I stated merely that my
                    instructions were to cooperate with <pb facs="0391" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> my
                    colleagues in behalf of the Mendoza formula. The Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    replied that the matter would be considered by the Cabinet and a communication
                    made to us as soon as practicable. After the meeting I went to the President’s
                    house and gave him its details. He had already been informed that the conference
                    had not shown complete unanimity and said that further consideration and
                    postponement by the neighbor powers seems inevitable. I suggested that he ask
                    that we four representatives confer with him today to see if the difficulty
                    could not be ironed out without delay. The Argentine Minister, however, sent
                    word that he had suddenly been taken ill and could not take part.</p>
                <p>This morning the President telegraphed me that he was not disposed to defer
                    longer to the backing and filling of Brazil and Argentine and that a note was
                    being sent me which was this Government’s separate reply to my own
                    representation. I asked him to withhold it till I could speak with him and went
                    to the Palace where I urged that it be made an identic note to all four
                    representatives and that it be so couched as to cover the points of my
                    representation without specifically referring to it. The result after a Cabinet
                    meeting was an identic memorandum which has now been handed to me and to my
                    three colleagues of which the following is a translation: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Government of Paraguay, desirous of putting an end to the war, as
                            soon as possible, in order to seek by appropriate means a legal solution
                            of the conflict with Bolivia, declares that it agrees to the withdrawal
                            of its second reservation to the formula of Mendoza, with the result
                            that the Bolivian troops should retire to Ballivian and Robore. It
                            likewise agrees that the other amendments and additions which it made in
                            its answer of the 27th of February shall be the object of consideration
                            later, upon the occasion of the negotiation of the arbitral <hi
                                rend="italic">compromise</hi>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>… The Peruvian Minister has received no communication whatever from his
                    Government touching the matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wheeler</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
