<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-02-15T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-02-15T18:00:00-05:00" n="509" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d509">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">721.23/1158a: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-02-15T18:00:00-05:00">February 15, 1933—6
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>26. Guzmán came in this afternoon to say that after the Peruvian attack
                            on the Colombian forces in Colombian and Brazilian waters yesterday the
                            situation had now developed into actual warfare. He said that he wanted
                            to explain, merely for the Department’s information, the situation in
                            which the Colombian forces find themselves and the “possibilities” that
                            Colombia might have to attack and occupy the Peruvian posts along the
                            Putumayo, such as Güepi and Puerto Arturo. He said that it was
                            absolutely necessary to keep the lines of communication open between the
                            Colombian advance base at Caucayá and the Colombian forces at Tarapacá
                            as otherwise these <pb facs="0568" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> latter
                            forces would be without supplies and could be isolated and destroyed by
                            Peru.</p>
                        <p>He was told that, of course, the question was one for the Colombian
                            Government to determine on its own responsibility. Mention was made of
                            the Colombian note to the League of Nations dated January 24 in which it
                            was stated that the Colombian flotilla “is, therefore, about to operate
                            within Colombian territory. It is no way threatening any Peruvian
                            territory nor does it propose to attack any foreign country or
                            government” and also of the League’s telegram of February 3 to the
                            Peruvian Government which stated that the League “has received formal
                            assurances from the Colombian Government that it has no intention to
                            violate or to threaten any Peruvian territory”. Guzmán said that the
                            situation had totally changed since the Peruvian attack yesterday and
                            that it was precisely because of this changed situation that he desired
                            to inform the Department (and that Colombia was also informing the
                            League) of the possibilities that Colombia in order to protect her own
                            forces and to reestablish her authority in Colombian territory might now
                            find it necessary to occupy the Peruvian positions mentioned. He stated
                            that Colombia, of course, would not hold such positions but would turn
                            them back to Peru once the question is finally settled.</p>
                        <p>The conversation brought out the possibilities of Colombia’s position
                            before world opinion being adversely affected in case she took the
                            initiative in attacking these Peruvian positions and also that attacking
                            the posts in question might extend the field of conflict and possibly
                            render more difficult a settlement than if the conflict were localized
                            in the Tarapacá-Leticia sector. However, Guzmán said that it was the
                            Colombian point of view that if Colombia occupied these posts it might
                            shorten the conflict and hasten a solution. As stated above, Guzmán was
                            told that the responsibility in the matter was, of course, for Colombia
                            to determine.</p>
                        <p>Guzmán did not make it clear whether he was acting under instructions in
                            informing the Department of the foregoing, or whether on his own
                            initiative he was anticipating probable developments.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>