<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Argentina ( (White) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-08-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="690"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d690">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/175</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">White</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2194</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-16">August 16,
                            1933</date>.<lb/>[Received August 28.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the memorandum of
                    the conversation between the Acting Secretary of State and the Argentine
                    Ambassador, as reported in the memorandum of July 6<note n="9" xml:id="d690fn9"
                        >Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State, <ref target="#pg_645">p.
                            645</ref>.</note> attached to Confidential Instruction No. 729 of July
                        27.<note n="10" xml:id="d690fn10">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In this there occurs the following passage: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I gathered that there was a veiled threat, although the Ambassador did
                            not convey it as such, that if there were no prospects of trade
                            negotiations with the United States, the United States would suffer the
                            consequences.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Ever since I have been in this country I have noticed the almost instinctive
                    tendency of Argentines—not necessarily of officials—to endeavor to play the
                    United States off against Great Britain, and vice versa, as such a competitive
                    spirit leads to the comforting sensation that foreign countries are falling over
                    each other in their endeavor to secure Argentine trade. Possibly deriving from
                    this tendency is a sentiment that the present balance of trade in favor of the
                    United States can be used as a club to extort favors for Argentine exports.
                    Presumably Dr. Espil is too well aware of the imperviousness of agricultural
                    interests in the United States to arguments of this nature to have made any
                    threat on his own initiative. But I can quite imagine that Dr. Saavedra
                        Lamas<note n="11" xml:id="d690fn11">Carlos Saavedra Lamas, Argentine
                        Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> might have sent instructions along such
                    lines, with a view to obtaining reactions from Washington that might be of
                    service in his negotiations with Great Britain or Italy.</p>
                <p>When the idea of clubbing the United States into reciprocity arises, measures
                    against the American automobile trade are the first to suggest themselves. Here,
                    however, the difficulty occurs that there are no other cars so suitable for
                    Argentine “camp” (i. e. rural) work as those from the United States. So that
                    endeavors to injure this branch of American trade would give little satisfaction
                    to the Argentine automobile public.</p>
                <p>In connection with the foregoing, I may refer to the Department’s telegraphic
                    instruction No. 50 of July 5, 6 p.m.,<note n="10" xml:id="d690fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> in which it is stated that the Argentine Ambassador had been
                    instructed by his Government to inquire whether the reclassification of
                    automobiles in <pb facs="0739" n="651" xml:id="pg_651"/> the Argentine tariff
                    now sought by the British Government would prejudice American autos, and I may
                    also refer to this Embassy’s despatch No. 2170 of July 28,<note n="12"
                        xml:id="d690fn12">Not printed.</note> page 2, confidential section, in which
                    it was stated that the Commission negotiating for the tariff clauses of the Roca
                    Agreement proposed to change the basis of valuation of automobiles so as to
                    favor cars with small cylinder space.</p>
                <p>The informant to whom I am indebted for the information contained in this
                    confidential section on page 2 of despatch No. 2170 of July 28 told me a day or
                    so ago that a fresh attempt had been made by the British to obtain advantages in
                    the automobile field in the course of the tariff discussions connected with the
                    Roca agreement. He stated to me that the British had threatened to abandon the
                    whole Roca agreement unless valuations upon imported cars should in future be
                    effected on the basis of weight, to the end that American cars, being heavier
                    than the British models, might pay a higher duty. My informant stated that such
                    an arrangement, if put into effect, would, however, also in certain cases create
                    unjust discrimination between different types of British cars. I told him I felt
                    sure that the threat to rescind the Roca agreement on this ground was a bluff as
                    the British would hardly spurn the Roca agreement at this late stage on such a
                    pretext.</p>
                <p>Enclosed herewith is further press comment<note n="12" xml:id="d690fn2">Not
                        printed.</note> in regard to negotiations for commercial agreements between
                    Argentina and various Powers.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. C. White</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
