<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Attorney General ( (Cummings))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d787</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">787</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recbWaHluS6u86H53" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038411"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diseases</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="787"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d787">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3556/110</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Attorney General</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cummings</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-07-27">July 27,
                            1933</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Attorney General</hi>: I have received your
                    letter of July 17,<note n="49" xml:id="d787fn49">Not printed.</note> with
                    reference to the inquiry addressed to you by the Secretary of Agriculture
                    requesting your opinion as to the proper interpretation of Section 306–A of the
                    Tariff Act of 1930 concerning the importation of meats and livestock from
                    countries infected with rinderpest and foot-and-mouth disease. You ask me to
                    supply you with any suggestions which may have a bearing upon the question
                    submitted to you.</p>
                <p>For several years Doctor Malbran and his successor, Doctor Espil, the Argentine
                    Ambassadors in Washington, have presented to this Department their Government’s
                    view that mutton originating in Patagonia, the most southern portion of
                    Argentina, could be imported into the United States under the provisions of the
                    foregoing section of the Tariff Act, basing their arguments on the statement
                    that Patagonia is, geographically considered, isolated from the remainder of
                    Argentina owing to the extreme scarcity of means of communication. They have
                    also stated that investigations made by the veterinarians of the Argentine
                    Ministry of Agriculture have failed to reveal the existence of foot-and-mouth
                    disease among the herds of sheep.</p>
                <pb facs="0871" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/>
                <p>This statement concerning the isolation of Patagonia would appear in the light of
                    the information at my disposal to be entirely correct. It is also the opinion of
                    this Department that the word “country” need not necessarily mean an entire
                    state in the political sense of that word. England and Scotland, for instance,
                    are usually referred to as separate countries, although they form part of the
                    same state.</p>
                <p>I should like in this connection to call your attention to the Convention of
                    January 16, 1930 [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>], between the United States and
                        Mexico<note n="50" xml:id="d787fn50">Convention of March 16, 1928
                        (proclaimed January 18, 1930), <ref target="frus1928v03#pg_317">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 317</ref>.</note> for the safeguarding
                    of livestock interests through the prevention of infectious and contagious
                    diseases. Articles 8 and 9 of this convention read as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“Article VIII. The livestock sanitary officials shall define the
                                specific territory in their respective countries in which any
                                contagious or infectious disease exists and shall indicate zones
                                which may be considered as exposed, in order to prevent the
                                propagation and dissemination of the infection of such
                                disease.</item>
                            <item>“Article IX. The High Contracting Parties shall not issue permits
                                for domestic ruminants or swine originating in any foreign countries
                                or zones where highly infectious and rapidly spreading diseases such
                                as foot-and-mouth disease and rinderpest appear frequently, until at
                                least sixty days have elapsed without any outbreak of the disease in
                                such countries or zones. When a disease of this kind occurs in any
                                part of a foreign country any other part of the same country shall
                                be considered as exposed until the contrary is positively shown,
                                that is, until it is shown that no communication exists between the
                                two parts by which the disease may be readily transmitted. When such
                                a disease occurs near the land border of a foreign country the
                                neighboring part of the adjacent country shall be considered as
                                exposed until the contrary is positively shown.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The text of these articles indicates that this convention provides definitely for
                    the dividing of a country, in the political meaning of that word, into zones for
                    the purpose of protection against animal diseases. It would thus appear that
                    Patagonia could properly be described as a zone of Argentina.</p>
                <p>In view of the foregoing, this Department is glad to concur with the views
                    expressed by the Department of Agriculture and hopes that you may find it
                    possible to give prompt consideration to this important matter owing to the
                    contemplated negotiations for the conclusion of a trade agreement between
                    Argentina and the United States.</p>
                <p>As of possible interest, I am enclosing a copy of my letter on this subject to
                    the Assistant Secretary of Agriculture.<note n="51" xml:id="d787fn51">Letter of
                        July 27, 1933, not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
