<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Senator Key Pittman</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="147"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.24/708</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to Senator
                            <persName type="to">Key Pittman</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-05-12">May 12,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr Dear Senator Pittman</hi>: I have received your letter
                    of May 3, 1938,<note n="59" xml:id="d147fn59">Not printed.</note> enclosing a
                    copy of S. J. Resolution 288 “repealing the Joint Resolution to prohibit the
                    export of arms, ammunition and implements of war from the United States to
                    Spain, approved January 8, 1937, and conditionally raising the embargo against
                    the Government of Spain”, and requesting my comment.</p>
                <p>In recent years this Government has consistently pursued a course calculated to
                    prevent our becoming involved in war situations. In August, 1936, shortly after
                    the beginning of the civil strife in Spain, it became evident that several of
                    the great powers were projecting themselves into the struggle through the
                    furnishing of arms and war materials and other aid to the contending sides, thus
                    creating a real danger of a spread of the conflict into a European war, with the
                    possible involvement of the United States. That there was such a real danger was
                    realized by every thoughtful observer the world over. Twenty-seven Governments
                    of Europe took special cognizance of that fact in setting up a committee
                    designed to carry out a concerted policy of non-intervention in the conflict. In
                    view of all these special and unusual circumstances, this Government declared
                    its policy of strict non-interference in the struggle and at the same time
                    announced that export of arms from the United States to Spain would be contrary
                    to such policy.</p>
                <p>The fundamental reason for the enactment of the Joint Resolution of January 8,
                    1937, was to implement this policy by legislation. This Joint Resolution was
                    passed in the Senate unanimously and in the House of Representatives by a vote
                    of 406 to 1.</p>
                <p>In the form in which it is presented, the proposed legislation, if enacted, would
                    lift the embargo, which is now being applied against both parties to the
                    conflict in Spain, in respect to shipments of arms to one party while leaving in
                    effect the embargo in respect to shipments to the other party. Even if the
                    legislation applied to both parties, its enactment would still subject us to
                    unnecessary risks we have so far avoided. We do not know what lies ahead in the
                    Spanish situation. The original danger still exists. In view of the continued
                    danger of international conflict arising from the circumstances of the struggle,
                    any proposal which at this juncture contemplates a reversal of our policy of
                    strict non-interference which we have thus far so scrupulously followed, and
                    under the operation of which we have kept <pb facs="0203" n="195"
                        xml:id="pg_195"/> out of involvements, would offer a real possibility of
                    complications. From the standpoint of the best interests of the United States in
                    the circumstances which now prevail, I would not feel justified in recommending
                    affirmative action on the Resolution under consideration.</p>
                <p>Our first solicitude should be the peace and welfare of this country, and the
                    real test of the advisability of making any changes in the statutes now in
                    effect should be whether such changes would further tend to keep us from
                    becoming involved directly or indirectly in a dangerous European situation.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, if reconsideration is to be given to a revision of our neutrality
                    legislation, it would be more useful to reconsider it in its broader aspects in
                    the light of the practical experience gained during the past two or three years,
                    rather than to rewrite it piecemeal in relation to a particular situation. It is
                    evident that there is not sufficient time to give study to such questions in the
                    closing days of this Congress.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
