<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="2" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751.60C/119</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Poland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Biddle</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 297</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-08">January 8, 1938</date>.<lb/>[Received January
                            20.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>:</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p>My confidential talks with Polish Government officials reveal in substance
                        the following: Although the French press had heralded a drastic
                        parliamentarian questioning of M. Delbos upon the results of his recent
                        voyage through Eastern and Central Europe, M. Delbos was in a position to
                        offer adequate defense. Subsequent to the London Anglo-French conversations,
                        in light of the previous Halifax–Hitler discussions, Polish official circles
                        had gained the impression that the French Government had agreed with the
                        British Government that the purpose of the Delbos tour would envisage
                        soundings on the broader issues looking to a general appeasement and
                        pacification settlement rather than looking to any specific questions.
                        Hence, realistically appraised, the value of the Delbos tour consisted of
                            (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) an enlightening realistic and useful
                        inventory of the attitudes of each of France’s allies in Eastern and Central
                        Europe, whereby France had learned that her allies were not to be expected
                        to carry on as in the past five or six years. The inventory should also show
                        France that her allies individually had become more powerful during the past
                        several years, and that not only had they less faith in the collective
                        system of security, but also that circumstances due to the turn of events
                        during the past two years throughout Europe had changed the political
                        complexion both of Eastern and Central Europe.</p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/>
                    <p>Moreover, Delbos had found out that reliance on the Little Entente was like
                        relying on the wind, except perhaps for Czechoslovakia. Realistically viewed
                        however, Czechoslovakia could not be regarded as an element of strength, but
                        rather as an element requiring protection. On the other hand, Delbos’
                        inventory had brought to light certain current swings, such as Rumania’s
                        present apparent swing to more of an “on-the-fence-position” as indicated by
                        her political change-over, and the Yugoslav apparent swing away from the
                        dominance of French influence. On the other hand, the inventory would show
                        Poland continuing her practice of “active neutrality” according to her
                        established policy.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, according to my informants’ views, French friendship, as well as
                        Polish loyalty to the Franco-Polish alliance in terms of Poland’s direct
                        obligations, could be depended upon. That is to say, Poland would march if
                        France were directly attacked by Germany. However, France had ascertained
                        that Poland refused to deviate from her established stand in respect to a
                        possible German-Soviet conflict. That is to say, France could not look for
                        Poland to maintain other than a neutral position in the event of a conflict
                        between Germany and Russia.</p>
                    <p>It is, moreover, my own opinion that M. Delbos undoubtedly came to the
                        conclusion that Poland might not be expected to march on Germany in the
                        event France attacked the latter as a result of a German thrust against
                        Czechoslovakia. I personally am still of the opinion that in such event,
                        Poland would “sit tight”.</p>
                    <p>Besides, in considering this question, one should bear in mind Poland’s
                        foreign policy as directed by Colonel Beck, in pursuance of the late Marshal
                        Pilsudski’s precepts: a determination to prevent the passage of foreign
                        troops over Polish territory. To my mind, this determination has an
                        important bearing on Poland’s past and present attitude in respect to
                        Czechoslovakia.</p>
                    <p>On the one hand, Minister Beck has been aware of Germany’s growing appetite
                        for Sudeten Deutsch; on the other, he is apprehensive lest in the event of a
                        conflict, France might march, and Russia might be called upon to discharge
                        her obligations under her pact with the Czechs. By constantly building up a
                        record of misunderstanding, despite correct official Polish-Czech relations,
                        Poland envisages the establishment of a moral defense against future League
                        or other foreign pressure towards urging her either to lend Czechoslovakia
                        military assistance or by permitting passage of a Soviet punitive expedition
                        over Polish territory in event of a German attack on Czechoslovakia.</p>
                    <p>France had found in fact that Poland would not and could not, according to
                        her established policy, play any part in a scheme envisaging <pb facs="0013" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> the encirclement of Germany. Indeed, Delbos’
                        inventory would show that France could no longer go forward with her
                        previously entertained illusion that she could maintain Germany’s
                        encirclement. Hence, France undoubtedly would have awakened to the fact,
                        that her position in relation to her allies in this part of Europe was not
                        as secure, in terms of a policy which France wished to impose, as she had
                        previously allowed herself to believe. In light of these revelations,
                        therefore, France was expected to become more desirous of joint action with
                        Britain towards bringing about a general appeasement and pacification
                        settlement.</p>
                    <p>In the eyes of my informants, moreover, the foregoing disclosures might be
                        expected to contribute to France’s making strenuous efforts to “do business”
                        directly with Germany—in other words, to do all possible to improve
                        Franco-German relations.</p>
                    <p>I suggest that the foregoing be read in connection with my despatch No.
                            298<note n="10" xml:id="d2fn10">January 8; not printed.</note> on the
                        subject of “Poland’s position in respect to the League”, which will go
                        forward by next week’s pouch.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer><signed>A. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Drexel Biddle,
                        Jr.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>