<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-04-26T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-04-26T15:00:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/372: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-04-26T21:00:00+01:00">April 26, 1938—9
                            p.m.</date><lb/>[Received April 26—7:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>658. Since March 1936 it has been said frequently that events in Europe were
                        at a crucial turning point. It seems to me that this has never been so true
                        as it is today. Great Britain and Italy have come to an agreement
                        facilitated by the German assault on Austria.<note n="77" xml:id="d23fn77">See <ref target="#pg_384">pp. 384</ref> ff.</note> A settlement between
                        France and Italy is now in sight. The Spanish conflict has ceased to be a
                        danger to European peace. It may be assumed that anyone possessing the
                        courage and determination which Chamberlain showed in tackling the Italian
                        question will now turn to the problem of a settlement with Germany. In this
                        effort Daladier and Bonnet may be counted upon to make a positive
                        contribution so long as there is any hope of reaching a reasonable
                        understanding with Germany. The question of whether Hitler’s aims in
                        Czechoslovakia can be reconciled with the views of other major powers
                        regarding central Europe will be an important factor. Ways and means of
                        approaching the problem of collaboration with Germany are apt to prove in
                        the long run the most important subject at the London meeting this week.</p>
                    <p>It seems, therefore, that before much longer the essential question which has
                        confronted Europe during the past 5 years may receive an answer: namely is
                        it possible for a regime such as Hitler’s to accept <pb facs="0055" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> in good faith the principle that Europe should be
                        organized on a basis of peaceful collaboration.</p>
                    <p>Failure this summer to reach an understanding with Germany will give a strong
                        indication it seems to me of a negative answer to this question.
                        Furthermore, an inconclusive result of efforts made to reach an
                        understanding with Germany will be about as bad as flat failure. Anything
                        short of a settlement of such nature as will make it possible to write finis
                        to this insane struggle for armaments may prove as disastrous in the long
                        run as no settlement at all.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>