<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-07-26T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-07-26T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-07-26T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-07-26T12:00:00-05:00" n="30"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d30">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00/430: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-07-26T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 26, 1938—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7:38 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1167. In the course of a conversation with Secretary Morgenthau<note n="93"
                        xml:id="d30fn93">Henry Morgenthau, Jr., Secretary of the Treasury.</note>
                    and myself today the Minister for Foreign Affairs gave a brief summary <pb
                        facs="0066" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> of his views on the present
                    international situation. He said that there were two points of danger to peace
                    in Europe at the present time. The first was Czechoslovakia. A few months ago
                    this situation had appeared to be desperate because the British had refused to
                    interest themselves in the fate of Central Europe. He had succeeded in
                    persuading the British to take the initiative with regard to the settlement of
                    the Czechoslovak-German dispute and he was most hopeful that the mission about
                    to be undertaken by Lord Runciman<note n="94" xml:id="d30fn94">Walter Runciman,
                        Lord President of the Council, 1938–39; for correspondence on his mission to
                        Czechoslovakia in connection with the Sudeten question, see telegram No.
                        699, July 29, 6 p.m., from the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, <ref
                            target="#pg_537">p. 537</ref>.</note> would produce an appeasement. It
                    would be impossible for Runciman to satisfy either party to the dispute
                    completely but all the weight of Great Britain would be thrown into the scale to
                    compel either the Germans or the Czechs as the case might be to accept
                    Runciman’s proposals.</p>
                <p>For the first time therefore he saw a ray of light. It was his personal opinion
                    that war during the next two months was no longer to be feared.</p>
                <p>He felt moreover that Germany and Italy were now at the peak of their military
                    strength. They had used their gold reserves and the personal reserves of the
                    people of Italy and Germany to build up immense armaments. It would be
                    exceedingly difficult for Germany, and impossible for Italy to continue to
                    replace these armaments.</p>
                <p>In France and England on the other hand although the governments might encounter
                    financial difficulties individual citizens were still immensely rich—with
                    investments both at home and abroad. These riches could be used to build up the
                    armaments of France and Great Britain to such an extent that if it should be
                    possible to preserve peace during the next 12 months Germany and Italy would be
                    unable to attack with any hope of success.</p>
                <p>He added parenthetically that he felt that the chief danger to peace at the
                    moment was Mussolini who was so completely aware that he would be unable to
                    maintain the present military strength of Italy that he desired war at once.</p>
                <p>With regard to the Soviet Union Bonnet said that he believed that the recent
                    “purges” of army officers and civilian leaders had so weakened the structure of
                    the Bed Army and the government that it would be impossible for the Soviet Union
                    to contemplate war beyond its frontiers. It was his policy to attempt to
                    strengthen the relations of France not with the Soviet Union but with Poland and
                    Rumania. To this end he was attempting to obtain assurances from the Soviet <pb
                        facs="0067" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/> Government that if war should come in
                    Central Europe the Soviet Union would positively not attempt to march armies
                    across the territories of Poland and Rumania and would not send airplanes across
                    those territories but would confine its assistance to the furnishing of
                    munitions and implements of war to the Polish and Rumanian Governments.</p>
                <p>With regard to the situation in the Far East Bonnet said that he felt the
                    Japanese were so deeply involved in China that there was no real danger that
                    Japan would dare to attack the Soviet Union or the Island of Hainan or any
                    French possession in Asia. China was proving to be such a formidable enemy that
                    the Japanese could not afford to take on new enemies.</p>
                <p>He read to us a telegram which he had received this morning from the French
                    Ambassador in Moscow recounting a conversation with Litvinov in which Litvinov
                    declared that the Red Army would remain in occupation of the positions recently
                    seized at Changkufeng and that the Soviet Government had no fear whatsoever that
                    the Japanese would dare to attack.</p>
                <p>In conclusion Bonnet said that he thought that the action of the British in
                    taking the lead in the settlement of the Czechoslovak-German dispute and the
                    recent action of the French Government in developing close relations with Turkey
                    marked the beginning of the end of the German thrust through Central and Eastern
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>With regard to Spain—the second danger point—Bonnet said that his position had
                    been peculiarly difficult because while France on the whole was most favorable
                    to the Barcelona Government the British on the whole were most favorable to
                    Franco. To maintain close collaboration with the British was the basis of French
                    foreign policy. It was therefore difficult to take a clear line with regard to
                    Spain. He felt that the policy of non-intervention unsatisfactory as it might be
                    was the only one to be. Franco had given categoric assurances to both Great
                    Britain and France that if he should be victorious neither the Italians nor the
                    Germans would be left in the possession of any strategic position whatsoever in
                    Spain. The British furthermore had promised the French to go to war if necessary
                    to eject the Italians and the Germans from any strategic position they might
                    have acquired, and might refuse to give up.</p>
                <p>Bonnet finally said that although he had been extremely pessimistic until
                    recently he was now definitely optimistic and did not expect war this
                    summer.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
