<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="459"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d459">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">863.00/1436½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-03-14">March 14,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The German Ambassador<note n="69" xml:id="d459fn69">Hans Heinrich
                        Dieckhoff.</note> came in to see me this evening immediately after leaving
                    the Secretary of State. The Ambassador told me that he had handed to the
                    Secretary in its German text a formal communication<note n="70"
                        xml:id="d459fn70">For translation of communication, see Department of State,
                            <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, March 19, 1938, p. 374, or <hi
                            rend="italic">Documents on German Foreign Policy, 1918–1945</hi>, series
                        D, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, document No. 378, p. 594.</note> he had
                    been instructed by his Government to make to the Government of the United States
                    quoting the texts of a German decree and of an Austrian decree promulgated
                    yesterday declaring the union of Austria with the German Reich. The Ambassador
                    remarked that these texts had been published by the press here and that he
                    supposed I had seen them. I said that I had and that I thought they also had
                    been telegraphed to the Department by our missions in Berlin and in Vienna. I
                    asked the Ambassador if there was anything further in the communication he had
                    delivered to this Government other than the text of these two decrees and he
                    said merely the further statement that the Austrian Legation and the Austrian
                    Consulates in the United States had been instructed to turn over their archives
                    and to subordinate themselves to the German Embassy in Washington and to the
                    nearest German consular officers. I made no comment.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador seemed to find my failure to make any further remark somewhat
                    exasperating and he gave me the impression of laboring under a very considerable
                    degree of nervous excitement and tension. He then broke out with the remark
                    “This is a great day, a wonderful day, for Germany”. I again made no
                    comment.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dieckhoff then embarked upon a tirade which lasted certainly for ten minutes
                    and which, in view of his usually extremely courteous and pleasant manner and in
                    view of the fifteen years I have known him and have maintained extremely
                    friendly personal relations with him, struck me as all the more extraordinary.
                    He commenced with the assertion that no matter what Germany did, the rest of the
                    world was always ready to inveigh against her, to question her good faith, <pb
                        facs="0451" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> to malign and maliciously to
                    misinterpret her actions and her purposes, and that the present moment was
                    another example of that phenomenon. He said Austria has always desired an <hi
                        rend="italic">Anschluss</hi> with Germany, and both the Weimar and the
                    Austrian constitutions provided for such amalgamation. Only through the inequity
                    of the Versailles<note n="71" xml:id="d459fn71">See article 80 of the Treaty of
                        Peace, signed June 28, 1919, <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_198">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris Peace Conference,
                            1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 198</ref>.</note> and the
                    Saint-Germain treaties, said the Ambassador, was such a union made impossible at
                    the end of the World War. He continued, saying that it was now evident to the
                    whole world that the Austrian people unanimously desired to become an integral
                    part of the German Reich.</p>
                <p>At that point I interjected and said that so far as the impression of the world
                    was concerned, it would seem to me that the impression created had been that the
                    Austrian people had not been given an opportunity of determining that question
                    and that the use of physical force must necessarily be considered as having
                    obscured any considered and expressed determination by the Austrian people of
                    what they themselves desired.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then went on to exclaim, “If you were in Vienna today you would
                    not feel that way. You would see for yourself that every Austrian wishes to
                    become a citizen of the German Reich”. To this I made no comment.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then continued by stating, “And if the Austrians are not permitted
                    to have a plebiscite, that would be nothing new. You will remember that when the
                    French occupied Alsace and Lorraine after the World War, Poinearé<note n="72"
                        xml:id="d459fn72">Raymond Poincaré, President of France, 1913–20.</note>
                    announced that the mere manner in which French troops had been received by the
                    populace in those two provinces was sufficient proof that the citizens of Alsace
                    and of Lorraine desired to become Frenchmen once more”. At this point I
                    mentioned that it seemed to me that the precedent selected by the Ambassador was
                    not a singularly happy one.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then went on to revile the press in the United States. He said
                    that the news columns and the editorials in all of the American newspapers were
                    filled with calumny and lies and that no effort was ever made to treat Germany
                    or German policy objectively or even to deal with the issues in an impartial
                    manner.</p>
                <p>I reminded the Ambassador that we had had many conversations in the past months
                    on the subject of the relations between our two countries and on the subject of
                    the press, both in the United States and in Germany. I reminded him that it was
                    absolutely impossible for the press or the people of the United States to take a
                    dispassionate point of view with regard to certain occurrences which had taken
                    place during recent years in Germany. I stated to him that there <pb facs="0452"
                        n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> was instinct in the spirit of every American
                    citizen two great principles upon which the United States had been founded and
                    had grown to its present stature. I said these two principles were the freedom
                    of religious worship and the right of free speech and of a free press. I told
                    the Ambassador that, as I had said to him frequently, so long as there were very
                    great elements in our population who saw the members of their own race or of
                    their own religion in Germany deprived of these rights which were considered
                    fundamental by every American citizen, that prejudice would persist and I was
                    sure that with his knowledge of human nature and with his long acquaintance with
                    this country, he must realize that that was the fact.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then remarked, “But the Jews here are only a small proportion of
                    your population. Why should you permit them to dominate the press and to
                    dominate public opinion?”</p>
                <p>I replied that while the Jewish element in the population of the United States
                    was, as he said, only a small percentage of our total population, nevertheless,
                    the people of the United States felt that that element among them was as much a
                    part of the United States as any other element of the population; that we felt
                    they had contributed greatly to the progress and to the well-being of the
                    nation; and that while I could under no conditions accept the Ambassador’s
                    statement that our press or our public opinion was dominated by the Jewish
                    element in our population, nevertheless, in view of the fact that most Americans
                    had Jewish friends whom they regarded highly and whom they admired as fellow
                    citizens, the feelings and the sufferings of this part of our people very
                    naturally necessarily had its effect upon the views and sentiments of the
                    non-Jewish part of our population. I reminded the Ambassador in as much as he
                    was undertaking to dissect the component parts of public opinion in the United
                    States, that the members of other churches, both Catholic and Protestant, felt
                    quite as strongly with regard to the two principles I had mentioned as the
                    Jewish element in the United States.</p>
                <p>I reminded the Ambassador that in previous conversations I had told him of my own
                    early friendships in Germany and of the great benefits I as an individual had
                    received from those friendships, and of the cultural benefits I had been
                    privileged to obtain from Germany, and that therefore he knew that as an
                    individual I was far from prejudiced and had always endeavored to see both sides
                    to the German contention since the War and had fully appreciated the fact that
                    in their dealings with Germany during the past twenty years injustices had been
                    committed by other powers which I had always hoped would some day be righted
                    through peaceful and reasonable negotiations such as those which Stresemann<note
                        n="73" xml:id="d459fn73">Gustav Stresemann, German Foreign Minister from
                        1923 until his death in 1929.</note> had endeavored to undertake. I <pb
                        facs="0453" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> stated, however, that in view of his
                    knowledge of the American people and of the way in which public opinion in the
                    “United States reacted, the Ambassador would realize that the feeling now
                    existing on the part of so large a proportion of our population would be very
                    greatly intensified if new acts of repression and persecution were undertaken by
                    the German authorities against Austrian citizens because of the latter’s
                    religious beliefs.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador concluded our conversation by stating in the most vehement manner
                    that the German Government as a result of its experience with the American press
                    during the past years from which it had never received anything except malignant
                    and malicious treatment would not be greatly concerned by any intensification of
                    that feeling on the part of the press in this country.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
