<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-08-27T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-08-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-08-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-08-27T10:00:00-05:00" n="752"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d752">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/659: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-08-27T11:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 27, 1938—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>592. For Taylor and Rublee. Your telegram 763 of August 15, noon, and the
                    memorandum enclosed with your despatch of August 13<note n="20"
                        xml:id="d752fn20">Despatch and its enclosure not printed.</note> have been
                    carefully studied. There is no need to emphasize to you the extreme difficulties
                    which will be involved in the negotiations with the German Government and that
                    any plans yet devised to bring about the transfer of Jewish property from
                    Germany are subject to serious objections. I therefore lay before you now
                    certain considerations for such guidance as is possible concerning broad lines
                    of approach. It is hoped to avoid a situation in which the German Government
                    makes proposals which cannot be accepted.</p>
                <pb facs="0783" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                <p>1. In the last analysis, the funds in question can be transferred from Germany
                    only through increased German exports. That is not in itself undesirable,
                    provided that such increased trade is not based on inequitable commercial
                    practices tending to divert the course of trade into artificial bilateral
                    channels. Unfortunately the systems heretofore used, particularly the Haavara
                    system, result not only in increased German exports but in giving them a very
                    great competitive advantage. Transactions of this character, insofar as the
                    transfer of Jewish funds is concerned, have hitherto been of minor importance
                    but if they were to be used for the transfer of even a small percentage of the
                    funds of several hundred thousand refugees the result would have a very
                    considerable effect on the course of international trade.</p>
                <p>You are familiar with the fact that the broad trade policies of this Government
                    are fundamental in our entire program. We cannot permit the German Government to
                    use our Government’s interest in the distress of German refugees as a lever to
                    break up this policy or create additional spheres of bilateral trade influence
                    through the medium of specially constructed currency or credit arrangements. In
                    consequence, any bilateral currency or credit proposals cannot even be
                    considered and this should be understood by the Germans at the outset.</p>
                <p>2. The German Government is of course aware of the competitive advantage which
                    systems such as the Haavara give its exports and we may assume that this will be
                    a not inconsiderable factor in whatever willingness the Germans may show to
                    enter into negotiations. In this connection an officer of the German Embassy
                    here recently referred in an informal conversation to the Haavara system as “the
                    only practicable method of dealing with the problem”. Incidentally, he
                    apparently took it for granted not only that Rublee would shortly go to Berlin
                    to discuss the problem but that the German authorities would be willing to
                    discuss it with him. We cannot consider the extension of that system to this
                    country or look with favor on its extension to other countries and must be on
                    guard against a German proposal along these lines.</p>
                <p>3. The German foreign exchange position appears particularly acute at this time
                    and we seriously doubt that that Government would be willing to permit
                    withdrawals by refugees in free foreign exchange now or at any time in the
                    comparatively near future.</p>
                <p>4. Preferably, of course, involuntary emigrants should be permitted to take free
                    foreign exchange out of the country. If, as seems likely, this is an
                    impossibility, conceivably the German Government might assent to permitting such
                    emigrants the use of marks convertible in some degree into free foreign exchange
                    along the lines of the sperrmark, and not limited to a medium for purchases of
                    German products. <pb facs="0784" n="776" xml:id="pg_776"/> As a last resort, the
                    German Government might grant such emigrants currency or obligations, not for
                    immediate use, which could be deposited in the Bank for International
                    Settlements, which, in turn, might issue to such emigrants an appropriate
                    receipt. In that case, the currency or credits so deposited would have to lie
                    dormant until circumstances offered possibility of its ultimate conversion into
                    free foreign exchange. In substance, this is merely suggesting that the refugees
                    take what the German Government offers, leaving this with the Bank to act as
                    holding agent in the hope that something may be eventually realized.
                    Conceivably, receipts for these deposits might be used by the emigrants as basis
                    for resettlement loans made by relief organizations or similar bodies, thereby
                    giving such organizations at least a chance of ultimately recouping part of
                    their expenditures. Naturally, this third suggestion is highly unsatisfactory
                    and should be resorted to only if all other means fail.</p>
                <p>In giving effect to such a proposal, thought would need to be given to the effect
                    of the Johnson Act,<note n="21" xml:id="d752fn21">Approved April 13, 1934; 48
                        Stat. 574.</note> which makes it unlawful for any person in the United
                    States to buy or sell obligations of governments in default. In any event the
                    obligations in question could be marketed in foreign centers such as London.</p>
                <p>5. The transfer problem, or in other words the working out in agreement with the
                    German Government of a practicable arrangement whereby some percentage of an
                    emigrant’s funds may be made available for his settlement and use elsewhere, is
                    of course the crux of the whole financial problem. If it can be satisfactorily
                    solved we believe that an attempt could be made, with some chance of success, to
                    have the special taxes upon emigrants reduced or abolished. In particular, an
                    attempt might be made to have the flight tax abolished or at least materially
                    reduced and the personal property tax abolished.</p>
                <p>6. It should be borne in mind throughout the negotiations that Rublee is
                    negotiating on behalf of the Committee rather than on behalf of this Government,
                    but I need hardly assure you both of our full and entire support.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
