<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-10-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="771" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d771">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/798½</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lindsay</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-10-07">October 7, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: I beg to enclose
                        herewith a message to the President from Mr. Neville Chamberlain, on the
                        subject of Refugees from Germany and I shall be grateful if you will forward
                        it to its destination.</p>
                    <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer><signed>R. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lindsay</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The British Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Chamberlain</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName></hi></head>
                        <p>I fully share your conviction of the importance both moral and practical
                            of the refugee problem and your anxiety that an early appeal should be
                            made to Herr Hitler concerning it. The German Government’s treatment of
                            emigrants is undoubtedly a serious obstacle in the way of a better
                            understanding between the German people and those of our own countries,
                            which is essential if we are to profit from this opportunity to create a
                            new and better order. Therefore it is our duty not only to do what we
                            can to alleviate the lot of the refugees but still more to endeavour to
                            bring about a realisation of the extent of the damage caused to friendly
                            international relations by the harsh treatment of German emigrants. I
                            hope as you do that it will prove possible to persuade the German
                            Government to make a practical contribution to the solution of the
                            problem and I warmly welcome your suggestion that the first suitable
                            opportunity should be taken of urging them to do so.</p>
                        <p>The Chairman of the Inter-Governmental Committee is now considering, in
                            consultation with the director, the possibility of a visit by the latter
                            to Berlin and we propose to consult our Ambassador in Berlin on this
                            point forthwith.</p>
                        <pb facs="0803" n="795" xml:id="pg_795"/>
                        <p>Meanwhile I suggest that our respective Ambassadors should be instructed
                            to take the first opportunity of speaking to the German Government on
                            the lines of your message on this question.</p>
                        <closer><dateline rendition="#left">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-10-07"><hi rend="smallcaps">October</hi> 7, 1938</date>.</dateline></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>