<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-10-18T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-10-18T11:00:00-05:00" n="777" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d777">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/829: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-10-18T17:00:00+01:00">October 18, 1938—5
                            p.m.</date><lb/>[Received October 18—2:06 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>555. My 549, October 15, 11 a.m. Ribbentrop as usual is out of town having
                        been almost continuously absent from Berlin since July 1st; I therefore
                        called on Weizsaecker and presented the matter of Rublee’s visit orally
                        along the lines suggested in your 179. As stated in my 549, I left a
                        memorandum.</p>
                    <p>Henderson also called this morning separately also leaving memorandum. I have
                        not been able to check with François-Poncet as he is in Berchtesgaden taking
                        leave of the Chancellor.</p>
                    <p>In presenting the matter to Weizsaecker I emphasized particularly the fact
                        that the German Government’s action has created a problem which affects the
                        outside states as well, that the Germans cannot consider this a purely
                        internal matter. I also emphasized the advantages to the Germans in making a
                        regular plan of emigration and facilitating the export of Jewish capital
                        both because of their desire to hasten emigration and because their present
                        attitude toward the <pb facs="0809" n="801" xml:id="pg_801"/> Jews was one
                        of the chief factors in the maintenance of the hostile sentiments against
                        Germany abroad.</p>
                    <p>Weizsaecker replied that he could not give me an official answer in this
                        matter, that he personally had been of a frame of mind some time ago to
                        discourage the visit, that they had followed the developments in the
                        Committee and had not been able to see that any particular headway had been
                        made for the absorption of Jewish emigrants. (Here I interrupted to point
                        out to him that the capacity of absorption depended on the amount of
                        securities Jews could take with them.) He then said he feared that if Mr.
                        Rublee came and nothing was worked out he would return and report to the
                        Committee that because of German obstinacy nothing could be accomplished. I
                        replied that this might well be the case unless the party members could
                        realize both that they had created a world problem of concern to many states
                        besides Germany and that it was to their own distinct advantage to work this
                        matter out with Rublee.</p>
                    <p>I then said that the specific question to which we wished an answer was
                        whether, in the event of Mr. Rublee’s arrival, the various German officials
                        who would have the decision on the question will be ready to receive him and
                        discuss the matter on the question of finding an arrangement. Weizsaecker
                        replied that he would lay this matter before the proper authorities and let
                        me know.</p>
                    <p>I intend, of course, to push this matter at every opportunity pending a reply
                        from the Foreign Office. I believe that pending such reply whatever hope of
                        success now exists will be jeopardized if publicity is given to the fact
                        that the various Ambassadors are discussing this matter with the German
                        Foreign Office.</p>
                    <p>Henderson’s memorandum and mine forwarded by mail.<note n="41" xml:id="d777fn41">Despatch No. 378, October 18, not printed.</note>
                        Telegram repeated to London for Rublee.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>