<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>116. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State (Sonnenfeldt)
                    and the Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research (Hyland) to
                    Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Kissinger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">CSCE</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >PNEs</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="compound-subject" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002599"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Environmental</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="chemical-and-bacteriological-warfare"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007509"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemical weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="116"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                <head>116. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State (Sonnenfeldt)
                    and the Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HWG_1">Hyland</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d116fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: In preparation for <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s upcoming meeting with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> in Geneva,
                                Sonnenfeldt and <persName corresp="#p_HWG_1">Hyland</persName>
                                reviewed several issues related to the Strategic Arms Limitation
                                Talks, arms control, the Conference on Security and Cooperation in
                                Europe, trade, and bilateral cooperation.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                                    >RG</gloss> 59, Records of the Office of the Counselor, Lot
                                81D286, Box 5, Soviet Union, January-March, 1975. Secret; Sensitive;
                                Eyes Only. The memorandum is mistakenly dated “2/7/74.” All brackets
                                are in the original except those indicating text omitted by the
                                editors. The memorandum is printed in full in <ref
                                    target="frus1969-76v16#d127">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, volume XVI,
                                    Soviet Union, August 1974–November 1976, as Document 127</ref>.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                                    corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> met in Geneva February
                                16–17. For the memoranda of conversation, see ibid., <ref
                                    target="frus1969-76v16#d128">Documents 128</ref>, <ref
                                    target="frus1969-76v16#d129">129</ref>, and <ref
                                    target="frus1969-76v16#d130">130</ref>.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-02-07">February 7, 1975</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Your Meeting With <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2"
                            >Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>[Omitted here are an introductory note and Section I. <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Security Arms Control Issues</p>
                <p>All of these issues are proceeding more or less on their merits with no overall
                    strategy.</p>
                <p>—Somewhat surprisingly <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> may be
                    accelerating, even though the Soviets are still intransigent, because the allies
                    are growing weary.</p>
                <p>—A <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> Summit in the late summer may not be
                    avoidable, if matters take their course.</p>
                <p>—The introduction of Option III in <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> will
                    take considerable time to work through the allies; any impact on the Soviets
                    will probably be lost through leaks, and, in any case, if this move is to break
                    the impasse, it almost certainly has to be introduced in your channel <hi
                        rend="italic">now</hi>.</p>
                <pb facs="0422" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/>
                <p>—Negotiations will resume this month on the Threshold Test Ban (<gloss
                        target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>) and environmental warfare, and the <gloss
                        target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> in Geneva will resume on March 4 where <gloss
                        target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> will be revived.</p>
                <p>We ought to work out a scheme for holding or moving these various issues. A
                    possibility might be:</p>
                <p>1. Make a <hi rend="italic">firm promise</hi> to <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2"
                        >Gromyko</persName> for a <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> Summit <hi
                        rend="italic">in September</hi> (if necessary we can make concessions on
                    CBMs because the allied position is collapsing).</p>
                <p>2. Foreshadow to <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> that we will
                    make a move on nuclear weapons in <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>,
                    without going into specifics, in return for which we expect agreement, in
                    principle before the summit, to a first stage <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >U.S.</gloss>-Soviet reduction that will also include air forces.</p>
                <p>3. Agree to try to work out an <hi rend="italic">environmental agreement before
                        the summit but ask <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> to hold
                        off on both environment and <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> in
                        Geneva</hi>, until we have had more time to consider how to respond to their
                        <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> draft agreement (you might want to
                    surface the idea of an interim moratorium on <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>
                    production, rather than a treaty).</p>
                <p>4. On the Threshold Test Ban, the real issue comes down to our toleration for
                    excavation <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> over 150 <gloss
                        target="#t_KT_1">kt</gloss> with non-firm guarantees. If this is not
                    supportable in Washington, can we strike a bargain to limit all <gloss
                        target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> to 150 <gloss target="#t_KT_1">kt</gloss>, if
                    we enter into a “cooperative arrangement” with the Soviets (which has strong
                    overtones of a nuclear condominium).</p>
                <p>—Since the outcome of this negotiation is bound to lead to a new controversy, <hi
                        rend="italic">there is no reason to force the pace</hi>. On the other hand,
                    it would be appropriate to announce at the summit that the issue is
                    resolved.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">A.</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>At <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss>, the Soviets have maintained their
                    inflexibility on both CBMs and the remaining Basket III issues while continuing
                    to argue that the major issues of the conference have been settled and that it
                    should end soon at the highest level. This Soviet intransigence can contribute
                    to your current strategy of stretching out the negotiations and delaying Stage
                    III and our final agreement to a summit until after <persName corresp="#p_BL_1"
                        >Brezhnev</persName>’s visit here, but it also depends on the allies not
                    giving in prematurely.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName> can be expected to complain that
                    we are not being active enough in pushing the allies toward more “realistic
                    positions,” and not carrying through on the <persName corresp="#p_BL_1"
                        >Brezhnev</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> agreement
                    at Vladivostok to work together to conclude the conference at the earliest
                    possible time.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">You should say</hi> the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    has accomplished a good deal since last fall—both in the Principles Declaration
                    and in Basket III—in moving <pb facs="0423" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> the allies
                    along, but that the Soviets must accept that further compromises will be
                    necessary on their part, especially on the peaceful change language, CBMs, and
                    the unresolved Basket III issues. (You have a detailed memo on <gloss
                        target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> issues in your briefing book.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">B.</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>You may decide to raise Option III, as follows:</p>
                <p>—It is our impression that if we included air and nuclear forces in our
                    proposals, the Soviets would be willing to include the withdrawal of a tank
                    army.</p>
                <p>—In the interest of moving the talks forward, we are considering certain
                    proposals on air and nuclear elements. In particular, we are considering an
                    offer to withdraw a significant number of nuclear weapons from the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Guidelines area (along with 29,000 ground
                    forces).</p>
                <p>—In return, we would have to have Soviet withdrawal of a tank army consisting of
                    68,000 men and 1,700 tanks in Phase I and agreement on the concept of a common
                    manpower ceiling within the area as the goal for reductions in Phase II.</p>
                <p>—However, we would be interested in obtaining the reaction of the Soviet side in
                    these channels as soon as possible.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">C.</hi> Environmental Warfare</p>
                <p>Our first series of talks in Moscow November 1–5 only pointed up the differences
                    between the Soviet catch-all approach, as set out in their draft convention
                    tabled earlier at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>, and our strictly
                    limited “Option II” position, which would not include limits on “tactical” uses
                    of environmental modification such as rainmaking. We will be meeting with the
                    Soviets again at the experts level in Washington on February 24, and are working
                    on a counter draft convention to give them at that time. Our immediate objective
                    is simply to maintain the dialogue and forestall tabling of a Soviet draft in
                    Geneva by extending the bilaterals into the period when the <gloss
                        target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> is in session. If you offer an agreement by
                    the summit, the Soviets might see it in their interest to subscribe to our more
                    limited approach (especially since it is not a serious issue).</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">D.</hi> Chemical Warfare</p>
                <p>The Soviets have been pressing us for bilateral talks on chemical weapons, citing
                    our agreement in the July 3, 1974, summit communiqué to consider a joint
                    initiative in the <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_VY_1">Vorontsov</persName> gave you a draft convention last
                    August which is too broad in scope, inadequate on verification, and by limiting
                        <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> agents above a certain level of
                    lethality, would catch all agents in our stockpile while leaving most of theirs
                    untouched. In the <gloss target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss> of January 27 you asked
                    for more work on the question of whether we should produce binary weapons. Until
                    these <pb facs="0424" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/> studies are completed and a
                    decision taken, we are not in a position to respond to the Soviets.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, however, <hi rend="italic">we should urge them not to table their
                        draft convention in the <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>,</hi> which
                    reconvenes March 4, pending bilateral discussion with us. You may want to
                    suggest that since a formal treaty is unverifiable, a moratorium for say 5 years
                    limiting stockpiles could be undertaken: a production ban may be inevitable if
                    we have no programs.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">E.</hi> Threshold Test Ban and PNEs</p>
                <p>The second session of the TTB/PNE talks will be in progress when you see
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2">Gromyko</persName>. There are <hi rend="italic"
                        >four key issues</hi> that will have to be worked out if—as the Soviets
                    wish—we are to have an agreement by the summit.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Yield Limit of Contained Explosions.</hi> We are proposing a
                    100-kiloton limit and on-site observers. However, we have some flexibility to
                    move the yield up or to drop the observers.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Verification of Excavation Shots.</hi> Here we have proposed a
                    yield limit of 150 kilotons (with a salvo limit of 500 <gloss target="#t_KT_1"
                        >kts</gloss>), observers and a very low limit on the fission yield of the
                    device (say one-half kiloton). Eventually our verification needs could be
                    satisfied either by the overall yield limit or, if the Soviets want explosions
                    over 150 kilotons, by limiting the fission yield of each shot. This is going to
                    be difficult for the Soviets either way, however, because a 150-kiloton
                    threshold may constrain to some extent the Pechora-Kama project while the
                    fission yield limit will require fairly intrusive on-site observer activity.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>.</hi> Any excavation program is
                    likely to violate the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>. The Soviets will
                    probably want explicit or tacit help from us in getting around this problem.
                    This will be very difficult for us to do because the Senate is unlikely to
                    ratify any TTB/PNE arrangement which looks to modification of the <gloss
                        target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> Cooperation.</hi> The Soviets want us
                    to conclude a broad cooperative agreement on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1"
                        >PNEs</gloss>. We can probably go along with a modest program of cooperation
                    covering domestic <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> applications, only on
                    condition that our verification concerns are fully met. However, we cannot
                    accept the Soviet idea of joint U.S./Soviet <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss>
                    services to third countries because of the overall political implications of
                    superpower condominium.</p>
                <p>The most valuable message you could leave with <persName corresp="#p_GAA_2"
                        >Gromyko</persName> is that verification is a very serious problem for us
                    which, if it is not solved, will make it impossible to obtain the needed
                    congressional support for ratification of the TTB.</p>
                <pb facs="0425" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">F.</hi> Non-proliferation</p>
                <p>The Soviets have agreed to attend a multilateral nuclear exporters meeting. On
                    the other hand, they are very strong supporters of universal <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> adherence and the closest possible links
                    between safeguards and the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss>. We are
                    concerned that a conspicuous and inflexible public posture on the <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> will make it very difficult for the French to
                    engage in meaningful cooperation on safeguards. Thus, if the Soviets are not
                    willing to tone down their <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> position, we
                    will lose both ways: the safeguards problem will get out of hand without French
                    cooperation and the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> rhetoric will not
                    succeed in gaining <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> adherence by France and
                    the other countries that matter.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here are Section III. <hi rend="italic">Trade/Emigration</hi> and
                    Section IV. <hi rend="italic">Bilateral Cooperation.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
