<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>188. Telegram 2926 From the Mission in Geneva to the Department of State and
                    the Embassy in the Soviet Union</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-04-15T06:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-04-15T06:50:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96004190"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Weapons of mass destruction</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="chemical-and-bacteriological-warfare"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007509"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemical weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038411"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diseases</term>
                    <term ref="recm0kKdhKGPVOMsn" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022963"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-04-15T06:50:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-04-15T06:50:00-05:00" n="188"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                <head>188. Telegram 2926 From the Mission in Geneva to the Department of State and
                    the Embassy in the Soviet Union<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d188fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The mission reported that the Conference of
                                the Committee on Disarmament had, at Soviet request, held three
                                informal meetings of experts in Geneva, April 7–8, concerning the
                                Soviet new weapons of mass destruction proposal. After summarizing
                                the three meetings, the Mission commented that the sense of the
                                Western and non-aligned groups was that the <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                                    >MDW</gloss> proposal “still lacked essential definition and
                                substance.”</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                                    >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D760143–0213.
                                Limited Official Use; Priority. Repeated to Bonn, London, New Delhi,
                                Ottawa, Rome, The Hague, Tokyo, <gloss target="#t_ERDA_1"
                                    >ERDA</gloss>, the Mission to the <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1"
                                    >IAEA</gloss> at Vienna, the Mission to <gloss
                                    target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                                    >U.S.</gloss> delegation to the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1"
                                    >SALT</gloss> II talks in Geneva, and <gloss target="#t_USUN_1"
                                    >USUN</gloss>. Telegram 81986 to Geneva, April 6, is ibid.,
                                D760128–0656.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1976-04-15T11:50:00+00:00">April 15, 1976, 1150Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>2926. Subject: <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>: Informal Meetings on New
                    Mass Destruction Weapons (<gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>) April 7–8, 1976.
                        <gloss target="#t_REFReftel_1">Ref</gloss>: State 81986 (<gloss
                        target="#t_Notal_1">Notal</gloss>).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> held three informal meetings on Soviet
                        <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> proposal in which experts from <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, Hungary and <gloss target="#t_GDR_1"
                        >GDR</gloss> participated. Western delegations including <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> raised questions about scope and content of
                    proposed <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> convention, some (especially
                    Canada and Italy) expressing strong skepticism and raising Soviet hackles.
                    Non-aligned delegations remained silent except India, which supported <pb
                        facs="0639" n="605" xml:id="pg_605"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> making efforts on question. Although a
                    number of possible “new” weapons applications based on various physical,
                    chemical and biological principles were suggested, scope and content of <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> proposal remained pretty much undefined.
                    Soviets contended repeatedly that other <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>
                    members had obligation to help sponsors put content into <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> concept. They mooted, but did not formally
                    propose, establishing experts group on definition. However, following meeting
                    they seemed uncertain as to what they wanted to do next regarding the proposal.
                    Soviets later inquired as to future <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    initiatives. <hi rend="italic">End summary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. At Soviet request, <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> held three informal
                    meetings with experts April 7–8 on question of banning new weapons of mass
                    destruction and new systems of such weapons. Soviets sent two experts, Hungary
                    and <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> one each. No other country was
                    represented outside of its regular <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>
                    delegation.</p>
                <p>2. After introduction by Soviet Rep <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2"
                        >Roshchin</persName>, primary <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> expert,
                    Academician Fokin of Academy of Sciences, led off discussion in April 7 a.m.
                    meeting. Turning first to question of specifying weapons to be covered in draft
                        <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> treaty, Fokin cautioned that listing
                    weapons ideas now in existence could omit even more threatening weapons that
                    might emerge in future. Nevertheless, he conceded, some kind of definition must
                    be arrived at.</p>
                <p>3. Fokin focused on definitions of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> in terms
                    of their objectives (mass destruction of people, loss of self-defense
                    capability, death), their methods of employment (physical, chemical, biological,
                    genetic), and their effects (on men, environment, productivity). He asserted
                    that certain <gloss target="#t_RD_1">R&amp;D</gloss> areas must be defined for
                    prohibition, but did not state what these were. New weapons of mass destruction
                    could be based on existing technology; on principles already developed (particle
                    annihilation); or on entirely new principles. As specific examples Fokin cited
                    transuranic fission weapons and laser fusion; the examples were drawn from
                    presentations at an open symposium in <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> in
                    1970, meeting without amplification or addition (Fokin made no direct attempt to
                    include for prohibition new systems for the employment of existing (e.g.,
                    nuclear or chemical) weapons).</p>
                <p>4. Fokin added that a basic definition of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>
                    would involve three aspects: (a) objects of use, e.g., human systems,
                    environment, energy systems; (b) method of operation; (c) realization of the
                    effect (i.e., losses suffered). Filling in this basic definition would give rise
                    to all-encompassing definition.</p>
                <p>5. Upon conclusion of Fokin’s statement, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ_1"
                        >Martin</persName> (<gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>) put forward
                    following questions pursuant to instructions contained <gloss
                        target="#t_REFReftel_1">reftel</gloss>:</p>
                <p>(A) What specific items would be included as examples of “new types” and “new
                    systems” in Article I, Paragraph 1, of the draft convention?</p>
                <p>(B) What “new types” of weapons of mass destruction do Soviet experts believe may
                    emerge in the foreseeable future?</p>
                <pb facs="0640" n="606" xml:id="pg_606"/>
                <p>(C) What physical principles do Soviet experts believe could eventually provide
                    the basis for a new type of mass destruction weapon?</p>
                <p>(D) Article I, Paragraph 2, of the Soviet draft provides for further negotiations
                    if new areas emerge in the development and manufacture of weapons of mass
                    destruction and systems of such weapons not covered by the agreement. What is
                    the meaning of the phrase “new areas”? How would agreement be reached as to
                    whether or not new areas or systems had emerged? (Questions had been handed to
                    SoviDel in advance.)</p>
                <p>6. Schlaich (<gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>) could not see how Soviet
                    proposal could achieve the praiseworthy aim of preventive arms control. He said
                    that authoritative interpretation of certain concepts was still lacking, e.g.,
                    it was unclear whether “new weapons” are completely new or embody development of
                    existing ABC weapons. Schlaich asked whether genetic engineering was not
                    actually covered by the Biological Weapons Convention. Commenting that
                    verification and proof in context of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> draft
                    treaty seemed insurmountable problem, he called the complaints procedure
                    involving Security Council “entirely inadequate.”</p>
                <p>7. Allen (<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>) was especially concerned regarding
                    the distinction between “new types” and “new systems” of <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>. He agreed with Schlaich’s suggestion that
                    genetic engineering was already covered by <gloss target="#t_BWC_1">BWC</gloss>
                    and added that in considering the <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> question
                    one must be careful to analyze what is and what is not covered by existing
                    international instruments.</p>
                <p>8. Di Bernardo (Italy) said “real life” definition of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                        >MDW</gloss> was needed, but doubted that such definition could be
                    developed. It was necessary, he said, to put content into any <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> agreement which at same time must not impede
                    the beneficial development of new scientific techniques. Di Bernardo concluded
                    that more specificity regarding proposal was needed in any case.</p>
                <p>9. Ericsson (Sweden) asked whether draft treaty referred to new weapons and new
                    systems of such new weapons or alternatively new systems of already extant
                        <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>. He proposed that if intention was
                    former, Article I be rephrased as “new weapons of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                        >MDW</gloss> and new systems of such new weapons.”</p>
                <p>10. Concluding morning’s discussion, <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2"
                        >Roshchin</persName> protested that Soviets wanted other countries to go
                    beyond “negative questions” that had been raised. <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                        >MDW</gloss> definition, he said, was not the sole responsibility of the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. This was why informal meeting with
                    experts had been called. <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2">Roshchin</persName> quite
                    impassionedly maintained that all other members of <gloss target="#t_CCD_1"
                        >CCD</gloss> had obligation to add content to Soviet proposal. Thus he
                    called on others to provide answers to <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    questions, as he assured Soviets would.</p>
                <pb facs="0641" n="607" xml:id="pg_607"/>
                <p>11. In April 7 afternoon meeting second Soviet expert, Col. Sourikov, said two
                    courses could be pursued: experts could develop definition of <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> and then move on to identifying specific
                    weapons, or, alternatively, they could follow a concept which had been put
                    forward earlier and establish a list of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> and
                    develop general prohibition from that. Definition, Sourikov said, should take
                    into account new physical, chemical, or biological principles that could be used
                    for military purposes, and measure these in terms of what they could do to
                    humans. Under term <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>, he continued, should be
                    considered new types of conduct of warfare that are being or may be found in
                    research or study stage, based on qualitatively new methods of action and meant
                    for new objectives of discussion.</p>
                <p>12. Hungarian maintained that banning <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> was
                    important because most such weapons are strategic in nature and if one country
                    develops them others will have to as well. He stated that Soviet experts alone
                    could not answer all questions put to them; answers could be found only after
                    lengthy consultations in committee.</p>
                <p>13. <persName corresp="#p_MBC_1">Mishra</persName> (India), the only non-aligned
                    representative to intervene, supported the idea of a <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                        >MDW</gloss> convention. He said the <gloss target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>
                    should pursue its consideration of this subject, which process could lead to
                    “significant developments.”</p>
                <p>14. Opening April 8 informal meeting, <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> Rep
                    Herder called it regrettable that other technologically advanced states had so
                    far only asked questions. They should, he said, have volunteered “positive
                    information.”</p>
                <p>15. Herder then introduced <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> expert, Prof.
                    Lohs, a chemical toxicologist. In quite thorough presentation, Lohs proposed
                    examples of new chemical weapons. These included new families of binary weapons
                    based on high-toxicity carbamates and nitrosamines, which are too unstable for
                    use in other than binary form. Synthetic toxins and pain-producing agents were
                    cited as another example of possible future binary technology. Synthetically
                    produced toxic peptides could undermine existing agreements.</p>
                <p>16. According to Lohs delayed toxic effects could become important, as could
                    highly toxic by-products of herbicides that can be produced as main components,
                    which compare with V-agents in toxicity but for which, in contrast to the
                    V-agents, there is no technically possible means of detoxification.
                    Contamination of a town with, e.g., dioxin, would render it uninhabitable
                    permanently without other damage. Effects of dioxin are long-lasting and can
                    exterminate large population groups through diseases of metabolism or cancer. An
                    additional example involved so-called “ethnic weapons,” specific in their
                    effects against certain ethnic groups due to the genetic disposition or
                    enzymatic polymorphism of those groups. Such weapons, Lohs maintained, could <pb
                        facs="0642" n="608" xml:id="pg_608"/> selectively exterminate specific
                    ethnic populations without damaging others.</p>
                <p>17. <persName corresp="#p_BWH_1">Barton</persName> (Canada) said his delegation
                    had found Soviet experts’ presentations “thought-provoking and illustrative of
                    the vast dimensions of the problems coming within the scope of the Soviet
                    initiative.” Nevertheless, <persName corresp="#p_BWH_1">Barton</persName> said,
                    procedures set forth in Article I of draft <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>
                    agreement seemed inadequate to provide necessary definitions of what weapons and
                    weapons types would be covered. <persName corresp="#p_BWH_1">Barton</persName>
                    said that as with <gloss target="#t_EnMod_1">EnMod</gloss> treaty it was
                    necessary to define what was being banned with enough specificity so there would
                    be no ambiguity about intentions and obligations being undertaken by treaty
                    parties.</p>
                <p>18. <persName corresp="#p_BWH_1">Barton</persName> raised another question
                    relating to implementation of an agreement on <gloss target="#t_MDW_1"
                        >MDW</gloss> prohibition. In view of the sweeping nature of such an
                    agreement he supposed it could not be implemented without adherence of all
                    technologically and militarily advanced nations. But, he said, he would
                    appreciate hearing Soviet views on this point which was “of some relevance in
                    the light of the approach of some governments to these matters.”</p>
                <p>19. Soviets then essayed response to questions raised by Western delegations,
                    especially <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> According to Fokin, “new types
                    of <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>” involved new means of waging war based
                    on a new effect, chemical, physical or other. “New systems” involved the carrier
                    and control mechanisms. Regarding specific “new types,” Fokin postulated, e.g.,
                    “ethnic war” based on biochemical characteristics of races, psychotropic
                    chemicals, use of infrasound and subsonic frequencies, acoustic and optical
                    principles (lasers?), and radiological weapons.</p>
                <p>20. Regarding “new areas” question, <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2"
                        >Roshchin</persName> said Fokin had pointed to three categories of <gloss
                        target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> “that seem achievable:” (a) those based on
                    already discovered scientific principles; (b) types for which there is
                    scientific basis in principle, but scientific-technical means to bring them into
                    being are lacking; (c) types based on entirely novel principles about which we
                    currently know nothing. <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2">Roshchin</persName>
                    maintained that draft treaty text answered question regarding agreement whether
                    or not new area or system had emerged. This was to be subject of negotiation, he
                    said.</p>
                <p>21. In reply to other Western questions, <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2"
                        >Roshchin</persName> (a) doubted that <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>
                    agreement would inhibit peaceful uses; (b) said not all technologically advanced
                    states would need to join agreement. On latter point, he noted that “big
                    majority” in <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>, including Canada, had voted
                    to refer <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> question to <gloss
                        target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss>; therefore he hoped that large number of
                    technologically advanced countries would in fact participate in eventual
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>22. Meeting concluded with expressions of appreciation to experts, and with
                    repeated <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2">Roshchin</persName> appeal to all <gloss
                        target="#t_CCD_1">CCD</gloss> members to participate fully in dealing with
                    “vitally important question.”</p>
                <pb facs="0643" n="609" xml:id="pg_609"/>
                <p>23. <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> General reaction among Western and
                    non-aligned groups seemed to be that notwithstanding creditable efforts by Fokin
                    and Lohs, <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss> proposal still lacked essential
                    definition and substance. Soviets seem somewhat uncertain where to go next with
                    their proposal. A week after meetings they have failed to respond to widespread
                    requests for English translations of Fokin’s presentations. (<gloss
                        target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss>, in contrast, provided Lohs’s statement
                    overnight).</p>
                <p>24. At April 9 co-chairmen’s luncheon <persName corresp="#p_RAA_2"
                        >Roshchin</persName> asked if <persName corresp="#p_MJJ_1">Martin</persName>
                    thought committee should carry on in summer with more informal meetings on
                        <gloss target="#t_MDW_1">MDW</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ_1"
                        >Martin</persName> said that he thought the present meetings had been very
                    general and that if future meetings were to be of the same nature he personally
                    had difficulty in seeing how the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> would be
                    able to make any substantive contribution which would justify sending experts.
                    If, however, the Soviets were prepared to designate specific areas or topics as
                    the subject for consideration, Washington would be better able to consider in
                    connection with its evaluation of the present meetings whether it would be
                    worthwhile to send experts to future meetings.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Abrams</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
