<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-09-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="77" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                    <head>77. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">David Elliott</persName>
                        of the National Security Council Staff to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d77fn1">
                            <p><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Elliott</persName> reviewed the current status of the
                                    Limited Test Ban Treaty and recommended that <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> approve a request
                                    for an interagency assessment of non-technical issues associated
                                    with amendment of the treaty.</seg></p>
                            <p><seg type="source">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Program Analysis Staff
                                    Files, Convenience Files, Box 45, Nuclear Testing (1). Secret.
                                    Sent for urgent action. <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Elliot</persName> sent the memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> under a September 5
                                    covering memorandum, noting: “Consideration of our position on
                                    the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> will be a background
                                    theme in the <gloss target="#t_VP_1">VP</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meetings on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>. It therefore seems highly
                                    desirable to get a quick fix on the problems, options, and pros
                                    and cons in this area as part of the preparation for these
                                    meetings and the Moscow talks.” <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> added the following at the bottom of
                                    the covering memorandum: “Went out Saturday [September 7]. B.”
                                    Tab A, an undated draft memorandum to the Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Under Secretaries Committee,
                                    is attached but not published. Tab B, the analysis, is <ref target="#d78">Document 78</ref>. The Interagency Study
                                    Group’s report is <ref target="#d82">Document
                                82</ref>.</seg></p>
                        </note>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-09-05">September 5, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Amendment of the Limited Test Ban Treaty (<gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>We have been carrying on technical talks for some years with the Soviets and
                        others regarding the benefits of peaceful nuclear explosions (<gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss>) for excavation purposes and the
                        possibilities for limiting the radioactive fallout to acceptably low levels.
                        Such excavation shots are almost all prohibited by the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>. The outcome of these talks would supply
                        the technical background for a possible future initiative to open the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> to amendment to allow de minimus
                        radioactivity levels to cross borders for legitimate <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> applications as long as no health risk
                        exists. Our own <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> program is practically
                        nonexistent and not constrained by the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> prohibition, but the Soviets have many excavation shots
                        planned and are most interested in amending the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>The political aspects of seeking to amend the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> have not been the subject of any explicit interagency
                        study, and no administration policy exists.</p>
                    <p>Our preparatory work for the negotiation of the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> agreement collateral to the <gloss target="#t_TTB_1">TTB</gloss> and for the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> review
                        conference could be more comprehensive and useful, if some policy
                        understanding could be reached on the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>
                        matter. In particular, the handling of excavation <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> above the threshold will be one of the major focuses of the
                        October Moscow talks, and Soviet willingness to be forthcoming on
                        verification procedures (including establishing the precedent of on-site
                        inspection) may well depend in part on our position on the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> amendment question. It is even
                        conceivable that some indication of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        support <pb facs="0291" n="257" xml:id="pg_257"/> for <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> amendment will be necessary to the
                        successful conclusion of the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> agreement.
                        However, there are several disadvantages to seeking to amend the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>, the most important being that the
                        majority of the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> Parties may well
                        demand a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> as a quid pro quo for amending
                        the treaty to allow excavation <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, and we
                        may, in any event, fail to gain international approval for the amendment by
                        raising it at this time. Further, Congress may defeat ratification of <hi rend="italic">both</hi> an <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>
                        amendment and the TTBT if the two issues are coupled directly or implicitly.
                        (Further analysis of the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> issues and
                        the pros and cons are at Tab B).</p>
                    <p>It would be useful to conduct a quick interagency assessment of the
                        non-technical issues associated with amendment of the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>. Based on this study, the President
                        would have the background for deciding whether the amendment liabilities
                        appear too great to indicate any <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        movement at this time or, conversely, that we can use some indication of
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> support to gain important
                        concessions from the Soviets in the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss>
                        talks. (Any action to seek amendment of the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss> would, of course, be predicated on technical agreement on
                        reducing radioactive release and standards of acceptable dose so that risk
                        to health would not be an issue.)</p>
                    <p>A memorandum to the Under Secretaries Committee (Tab A) requests a study of
                        the non-technical issues associated with seeking to amend the <gloss target="#t_LTBT_1">LTBT</gloss>. The study would be completed in time
                        for the <gloss target="#t_VP_1">VP</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> later this
                        month.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRT_1">Dick Kennedy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LJM_1">Jan Lodal</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CAD_1">Denis Clift</persName> concur.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation:</p>
                    <p>That you sign the memorandum to the <gloss target="#t_USC_1">USC</gloss> at
                        Tab A.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>