<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-01-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                        <head>129. Memorandum of Telephone Conversations, Washington, January 15,
                                1957<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d129fn1">Source: Department of
                                State, Central Files, 361/1–557. Official Use Only. No drafter is
                                indicated on the source text.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1957-01-15">January 15, 1957</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Costs Involved in U.S. Proposals for <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KSM1">Milton S.
                                Eisenhower</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_RPA1">RPA</gloss>—Amb. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In a telephone conversation with Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> on Tuesday, January 15, 1957, Dr.
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> stated that he had taken up with the
                            President and the Director of the Bureau of the Budget<note n="2" xml:id="d129fn2"><persName corresp="#p_BPF1">Percival E.
                                    Brundage</persName>.</note> the question of costs involved in
                            our proposals for the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. He had
                            explained that our proposals implied a cost to the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> of a little more than $5 million per
                            year, and that our share would be an increase of about $3.5 million in
                            our annual quotas. In addition, there would be certain non-recurring
                            costs such as for malaria eradication and atomic energy that would
                            amount to a total of a <pb facs="0503" n="469" xml:id="pg_469"/> little
                            over $40 million to be used over five years, or an average of $8 million
                            annually for five years.<note n="3" xml:id="d129fn3">These estimated
                                costs of the U.S. proposals for the Committee of Presidential
                                Representatives were tabulated and sent to <persName corresp="#p_EM1">Milton Eisenhower</persName> by <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> in a memorandum dated
                                January 10. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> wrote in
                                part: “Decisions will also have to be made at some point as to the
                                precise amount which the United States will be willing to contribute
                                to the special voluntary funds in support of the non-recurring
                                expenditures, and the relationship of our contribution to those of
                                other countries. It has been our thought so far in the Department
                                that the annual costs would be governed by the obligatory quota
                                systems of the various branches of the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> (U.S. paying up to two-thirds), but that in cases
                                of special programs where completion of a task is of great
                                importance to us, we might find it necessary and desirable to
                                contribute a larger share to the voluntary funds, without regard to
                                a fixed scale of contributions by all <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> member countries.” (Department of State, Central
                                Files, 361/1–1057)</note> Both the President and the Director of the
                            Bureau of the Budget said they considered Dr.
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s figure as all right, and that he
                            could go ahead with the proposals so far as the costs were
                            concerned.</p>
                        <p>Later, Dr. <persName>Eisenhower</persName> called Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BPF1">Brundage</persName> of the Bureau of the Budget on
                            the telephone, and reported to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BPF1">Brundage</persName> had already informed his staff of the
                            conversation with the President.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>