<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-08-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="148" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d148">
                        <head>148. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SWP1" type="from">Snow</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d148fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Cabinet Meetings: Lot 68 D 350, CP–7. Official
                                Use Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RAM2">Rosenson</persName>, cleared by <persName corresp="#p_THR1">Turkel</persName>, and concurred in by <persName corresp="#p_AWC1">Willis C. Armstrong</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-08-22"><hi rend="italic">August 22,
                                1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Inter-American Economic Conference at Buenos Aires</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Buenos Aires Conference is, in essence, a continuation of a
                            long-standing effort by the Latin American countries to obtain from the
                            United States special economic concessions which we are not prepared to
                            grant.</p>
                        <p>The main issues, in the probable order of their importance to most Latin
                            American countries, are as follows: <pb facs="0560" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Special regional facilities for financing economic
                                    development. We believe existing institutions and private
                                    investment provide ample sources of development capital.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Stabilization (at high levels) of prices of Latin American
                                    primary product exports. We oppose endorsement of the principle
                                    of commodity agreements.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>General inter-American economic agreement. The substantive
                                    differences that separate us from the Latins on many issues are
                                    so marked as to make agreement on a binding treaty of this kind
                                    almost out of the question. The Mexican delegation is attempting
                                    to line up the other Latin American delegations in favor of a
                                    declaration of general principles in place of a treaty. We might
                                    be able to approve such a declaration if our views are properly
                                    taken into account in it.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Regional trade arrangements. The European common market has
                                    given considerable impetus to the movement for some kind of
                                    Latin American economic regionalism. So far nothing concrete has
                                    been proposed, but some definite plan may emerge as a result of
                                    studies now being carried out by <gloss target="#t_ECLA1">ECLA</gloss>. We are willing to consider on its merits any
                                    definite proposal that is economically sound and consistent with
                                    our general trade principles. In this connection, the U.S.
                                    recently assisted Nicaragua in obtaining provisional approval at
                                        <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> of plans for the
                                    formation of a free trade area and eventual customs union among
                                    the five Central American states.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>U.S. surplus disposal. The force of the criticism on this
                                    score has been mitigated (a) by our demonstrated desire to
                                    protect the legitimate interests or other suppliers, and (b) by
                                    the fact that seven Latin American countries have entered into
                                        <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> 480 agreements with us,
                                    with others definitely interested.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Reduction or complete elimination of U.S. taxes on income
                                    earned by American business firms in Latin America. We oppose
                                    this and favor bilateral tax agreements to eliminate tax
                                    obstacles to the flow of capital. We have indicated our
                                    willingness to include “tax-sparing” provisions in such
                                    treaties.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Our position at the Conference has been made more difficult, first, by
                            recent or imminent actions affecting certain important Latin American
                            exports (petroleum, lead and zinc,<note n="2" xml:id="d148fn2">Reference
                                is to Congressional efforts to raise import fees on lead and zinc.
                                In Soaec 19 from Buenos Aires, August 19,
                                    <persName>Anderson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> state in part the following: “We strongly
                                urge that administration stand firm against alteration of lead zinc
                                bill [H.R. 6894]. In our efforts allay fears Mexicans, Peruvians and
                                Bolivians, who so far very friendly to US, we have stressed limited
                                amount of increase, fact that rates would be reduced and removed as
                                prices increase, and intentions US carry out its trade-agreement
                                obligations.” (Department of State, Central Files,
                                365/8–1957)</note> tung oil, long staple cotton) and secondly, by
                            the recent House action reducing the Economic Development and Technical
                            Cooperation funds and eliminating the special regional fund for Latin
                            America (<persName corresp="#p_SGA1">Smathers</persName> Fund).<note n="3" xml:id="d148fn3">For documentation, see <ref target="#d56">Documents 56</ref> ff.</note></p>
                        <p>As the Conference committees started their work only yesterday, it is too
                            early to forecast results.<note n="4" xml:id="d148fn4">An attached
                                agenda of the Conference is not printed.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>