<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-27T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-27T14:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <head>221. Memorandum of a Conversation, White Sulphur Springs, West
                            Virginia, March 27, 1956, 2 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d221fn1">Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File,
                                    <persName>Eisenhower</persName> Diaries. Secret. Drafted by
                                Walters.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-03-27T14:00:00-05:00">March 27, 1956, 2 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Ruiz Cortines</persName> of
                                Mexico</item>
                            <item>Lt. Colonel <persName>Vernon A. Walters</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The President opened the conversation by saying that he had been anxious
                            to be able to get together informally and talk with President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>. This was one of the main
                            reasons that had led him to suggest this conference.</p>
                        <p>There were on the North American continent three nations who had to live
                            together; President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>
                            interrupted to say “who were determined to live together.” President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> said that one of these nations, the
                            United States, had by a combination of circumstances reached a position
                            of great power and wealth and that it was anxious to do what it could to
                            be of assistance to Mexico, and could not in a patronizing way but as a
                            good friend. We wanted only prosperity, happiness and a better standard
                            of living for our friends in Mexico. We had achieved our present well
                            being largely through the assistance of foreign capital invested in the
                            United States. The President said that it was a fact that as late as
                            1910 the United States owed money to practically every nation in
                            Europe—England, France, Germany, etc. Foreign capital had helped develop
                            our railroads and the insurance business and that even in the
                            development of the West there had been extensive holdings by British
                            investment in the cattle ranches of our country. What we had been able
                            to achieve had been done in the framework of the free enterprise
                            system.</p>
                        <p>We knew that throughout the world there were in different countries
                            varying degrees of governmental control, but basically our people
                            believed that if a man invested his money he should be allowed, after
                            paying due taxes, to retain what he had been able to earn. We had
                            developed our economy in this free enterprise framework before the
                            spread of the ideas of socialization that were developed elsewhere. We
                            did not seek to convince others to do as we had, but our only desire was
                            for a prosperous, happy Mexico with an ever rising standard of
                            living.</p>
                        <p>The President said that if he were in President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>’ place, he would not wish to
                            see foreign capital come in and take charge of <pb facs="0745" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/> some major service in his country, but on the
                            other hand he did not feel that obstacles should be placed in the way if
                            certain Mexican business men felt that they needed additional capital to
                            further their own development. As far as the government was concerned,
                            they could undoubtedly secure loans (from the Export-Import Bank and the
                            World Bank and similar organizations) for those projects which they felt
                            the government itself would have to promote. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> broke in to cite the railroads
                            as an example, to say that this was an absolute necessity for
                            Mexico.</p>
                        <p>President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then went on to say that if he
                            were a Mexican he would be happy to have Mexican business in a position
                            where, if it needed help, they could get it by direct dealings with
                            American business men. He assured the President of Mexico that the
                            United States’ major interest was not in gaining additional allies
                            against Communism, though that played some part in our feelings, but
                            basically what we wanted was to see Mexico strong and prosperous with a
                            better life for her people.</p>
                        <p>President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then said that he welcomed this
                            opportunity to speak directly with the President of Mexico, the Chief of
                            State of an immediate and close neighbor, and to talk over with him some
                            of the problems and difficulties between these two friendly nations. He
                            felt that if Dr. <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> and
                            himself could agree on principles, the details could be worked out by
                            others. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> said
                            that he felt exactly the same way, and also felt that it was essential
                            that both of them agree on principles, that if they did so and good will
                            was shown by both sides it would not be difficult to overcome whatever
                            difficulties might remain.</p>
                        <p>The President said that he could assure President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> that the United States wished
                            only for a strong, free and democratic Mexico. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> thanked President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> for this expression and said that
                            the Mexicans sincerely believed this. He said that ever since his first
                            meeting with President <persName>Eisenhower</persName>, he felt that
                            they had established a direct personal and friendly contact. He said
                            that sometimes when people met they either did not get along together or
                            else they established an instant friendly contact. He was happy that the
                            latter situation had occurred between him and his great friend President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The President then said that the whole American people were concerned
                            with the threat of subversion by Communist infiltration of governments.
                            This was something on which the American people felt very strongly, as
                            they had had examples of it in the past and knew that Soviet Embassies
                            were not set up to do the normal and legitimate business of an Embassy,
                            but were centers of espionage, sabotage and other subversive activities,
                            and this was something that <pb facs="0746" n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/>
                            had to be watched. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> replied that he knew this and agreed with the
                            President.</p>
                        <p>The President said that he wanted President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> to know that he appreciated the difficult
                            problems which he had to face. He knew that the United States was a
                            close neighbor of Mexico, a large neighbor and sometimes an awkward one.
                            He knew that there was great desire in Mexico and impatience for
                            progress, and sometimes this made President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>’ task more difficult as there were those who
                            might say, “Why can we not achieve the same standard of living as the
                            ‘gringos’ right away?” He said this because he wanted President
                                <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> to know that he
                            appreciated his difficulties. He added that he had never had with
                            another chief of government such a frank and informal conversation.
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> expressed his
                            gratitude to President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> for this.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> thanked the
                            President for his understanding of his (Dr. <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>’) problems and said that Mexico had passed
                            through a difficult period. As late as 1938, they had still had military
                            rebellions. Since then, however, the democratic institutions of Mexico
                            and the authority of the state had become firmly established. First they
                            had had two military men as Presidents during this period, then a
                            lawyer, President Aleman,<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">Miguel Alemán
                                Valdes, President of Mexico, 1946–1952.</note> and finally a simple
                            citizen himself as President. He did not say this to cast any aspersions
                            on the military, but merely to indicate to President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> events that had occurred in Mexico’s
                            recent past. The Mexican people were driven by a burning desire for
                            progress and an improvement in their lot.</p>
                        <p>He said that his mention of the difficulties engendered by progress
                            earlier in the day had been an attempt to describe some of these very
                            difficulties. Mexico’s population was increasing at the rate of some 3%
                            per year which meant an annual increase in the population of 900,000 per
                            year. President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then said that if only
                            Mexico could increase her productive capacity by 6 or 7 percent per
                            year, this would compensate for the population increase and would also
                            provide an increase in the living standards of the Mexican population.
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> agreed that
                            this was so. He said that an increase in the productive capacity of the
                            nation had to be properly spread so that all parts of the population
                            would benefit therefrom. He felt that if they could achieve an annual
                            increase in production around 5%, this would be most helpful.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> said that he
                            did not want to take up the President’s time but that there were a few
                            matters that he would like to take up with him if he might. The
                            President said that this was the very reason that had brought him to
                            extend the invitation, <pb facs="0747" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> this
                            opportunity to talk frankly with the President of Mexico and the Prime
                            Minister of Canada.</p>
                        <p>First of all, he wanted to tell the President how grateful he and the
                            whole Mexican people were to the President for his personal intervention
                            that had made possible an agreement on the question of the “wetbacks.”
                            For years they had tried unsuccessfully to obtain a solution of this
                            problem, and finally, thanks to the personal action of President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>, this had been achieved. This was a
                            matter that affected the Mexican people in their deepest feelings and
                            they had therefore been extremely happy when the agreement had been
                            reached. Previously the migrants had been illegal entrants and had been
                            exposed to harsh treatment and sometimes injury and now this situation
                            had been cleared up. However, there was one aspect of the matter that
                            was still of some concern, and he would be most appreciative if the
                            President would look into the matter. It appeared that at the border
                            entry stations they were no longer demanding that the laborers entering
                            the United States show their work contract. If this were not done, the
                            value of the agreement would be lost. The President promised to look
                            into this matter. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> said that he would leave a number of small
                            cards with notes on them for the President as a sort of
                            aide-mémoire.</p>
                        <p>Next, there was the question of the Mexican difficulties in the matter of
                            cotton production and sales. In reply to a question by the President, he
                            indicated that cotton was produced in the northern part of Mexico. He
                            said that most of Mexico’s cotton production was sold abroad and only a
                            very small part of it was used within Mexico. He said that as a result
                            of the United States decision to sell surplus cotton, Mexican production
                            would be reduced by some 25%. They were planning to reduce the area
                            under cotton. The President then asked what else could be produced in
                            these areas and how the Mexicans planned to replace cotton production.
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> replied that
                            in some measure they were seeking to produce tropical products in these
                            areas but actually there was little else that could be advantageously
                            produced in these areas. He would be grateful if the President would
                            look into this matter also, and would likewise leave a card with the
                            President on this subject. He added that they were discussing this
                            matter with the Department of State and also through the Embassy in
                            Mexico City.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> said that there
                            was still one matter that he would like to mention to the President. He
                            apologized for taking up his time. This was the matter of fisheries.
                            There had been difficulties with regard to these fishing rights.
                            President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> inquired as to whether this
                            was on the East coast or on the Pacific coast. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> replied that this was
                            principally in the Gulf of Mexico area but also applied in lesser
                            measure to the Pacific Coast <pb facs="0748" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>
                            as well. President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then asked if the
                            trouble was with patrol boats or with regard to trespassing in coastal
                            waters, and President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>
                            indicated that there was some of both. President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then said that just as it had been
                            possible to create a regulatory body to handle problems relating to the
                            “wetback” agreement, it might also be possible to set up something
                            similar to handle this matter. President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> indicated agreement on this, and also indicated
                            that he would leave a note on this subject.</p>
                        <p>The President of Mexico then indicated that he did not wish to take up
                            any more of the President’s time, and the President said that there was
                            one more matter which he wished to mention briefly to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName>. This was the matter
                            of air routes. The only line authorized to fly between our largest city
                            and the capital of Mexico was a French airline. The President said that
                            he would like to see United States and Mexican carriers flying not only
                            on that route, but also on other routes between major United States
                            cities and Mexico. If the Mexicans needed help to set up their part, the
                            United States would see what could be done to assist them. The President
                            said that he had no favored company of any sort, but he felt that there
                            should be both United States and Mexican carriers on these routes. He
                            felt that everything should be done to provide the public with this
                            service, as that would help increase tourism in Mexico, and that would
                            result in numerous benefits to the country and would stimulate the
                            building of hotels, development of communications within Mexico, and so
                            forth.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> replied that he
                            had been working on this matter, and he felt that it should be settled
                            as it had been pending for a long time. He wondered if it would be
                            possible to send down some experts on this matter, not because the
                            United States Embassy in Mexico was not fully up-to-date on the matter,
                            but he felt that there were certain technical aspects which should be
                            ironed out. The President asked President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> if he meant experts on air routes, and the
                            Mexican President said that this was what he had meant. He concluded by
                            saying that, as the President had indicated at the outset of the
                            conversation, if they could only agree on principles, others could work
                            out the details of these matters. It was essential that this matter be
                            satisfactorily solved. The President said that he was happy to hear
                            this, and repeated that the United States would be willing to study the
                            matter and see what could be done to assist the Mexicans if they needed
                            such help to get their carriers prepared to operate these services
                            alongside the United States carriers. He felt that it was important that
                            such service be provided for the reasons he had mentioned before,
                            between major United States cities and Mexico.</p>
                        <pb facs="0749" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/>
                        <p>President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> then said that he understood
                            that the Mexican President was going out later in the afternoon with
                            Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> and
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EM1">Milton Eisenhower</persName> for a ride
                            around the countryside. He hoped that the President of Mexico would
                            enjoy the ride and he was happy that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> would have an opportunity to talk to Dr.
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> then repeated
                            his thanks for the President’s invitation and the opportunity it had
                            given him for this meeting with his great and good friend President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>. He then took his leave of the
                            President.</p>
                        <p>Addendum to Memorandum of Conversation prepared by Lt. Col. Vernon A.
                            Walters, of the President’s conversation with President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Ruiz Cortines</persName> of Mexico, March 27,
                            1956, at 2:00 P.M., in the President’s suite at the Greenbrier.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the subjects discussed, which are covered in this very
                            excellent memorandum from Colonel <persName>Walters</persName>,
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RCA1">Cortines</persName> brought up to
                            me the matter of the working conditions of Mexicans who come in legally
                            and on a temporary basis to work in the Southwestern United States. He
                            said that in many states they worked extremely long hours and under
                            other conditions that were not satisfactory. I told him I would see what
                            we could find out about this.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">DDE</hi><note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">Printed from a copy which bears these typed
                                initials.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>