<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="32" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                        <head>32. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1" type="from">Holland</persName>) to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_LCB1" type="to">Lyon</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d32fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 720.5/4–1156.
                            Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-13"><hi rend="italic">April 13,
                                1956</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Military Programs in Latin America</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I have read and returned to you your memorandum of April 11 on our
                            military programs in Latin America.<note n="2" xml:id="d32fn2">This
                                memorandum concerned the status of efforts by the Bureau of
                                Inter-American Affairs to obtain from the Department of Defense a
                                clear definition of U.S. military objectives in Latin America. In
                                the memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Lyon</persName> informed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> that the Navy had
                                completed a draft comprehensive naval program for Latin America and
                                was prepared to refer it to the Joint Chiefs of Staff for approval,
                                but that the Army and Air Force were still working on a review of
                                their respective programs. He also stated the following: “We are
                                still endeavoring to obtain agreement on criteria and procedures,
                                and to find a source of funds for credit sales of military
                                equipment. E has few objections to our proposals on how a credit
                                program should be operated if we are to have a credit program. E is
                                opposed to the established policy calling for credit and is
                                therefore unwilling to agree to proposals designed to obtain an
                                assured source of funds as Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> requested in May 1955.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</note> Attached also is the draft of letter from
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d32fn3">Not
                                found with the source text, but see <ref target="#d35">Document
                                    35</ref>.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0279" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/>
                        <p>I do not have the feeling after reading these papers that we ourselves
                            have a view as to the outer limits of the problem. Perhaps I am wrong
                            but I have the feeling that we are going directly to components of the
                            larger problem, and without defining their relationship to each
                            other.</p>
                        <p>I had hoped that this larger problem could be defined in conferences with
                            Defense. Apparently that is not possible. Perhaps the best substitute is
                            to submit to Defense our ideas as to the broad definition of the
                            problem. That might lead them to agree or disagree with our views, thus
                            eventually leading us to an accord.</p>
                        <p>The statement I have in mind could be worded somewhat as follows:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">General Objectives of Military
                                Programs in Latin America</hi>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Hemispheric defense</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Internal security</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>To orient military leaders in Latin American governments
                                    toward the United States (dubious)</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Standardization of Latin American military equipment
                                    (dubious)</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>If the foregoing are in fact the objectives of our military programs,
                            then we should define the hemisphere defense units that we actually want
                            from the Latin American countries and we should define the nature of the
                            units required for internal security. It would also be necessary to
                            reach a decision once and for all on how much military aid we are going
                            to put out for political purposes, and how far we are willing to go to
                            try to outbid other suppliers in order to achieve standardization of
                            arms.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Programs to Achieve Objectives of
                                Military Aid</hi>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Grant military assistance</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Sales of military equipment for credit</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Sales of military equipment for cash</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>U. S. military missions in Latin America</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Training of Latin American officers in the United
                                    States</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Under each of these programs, and any others that I have overlooked, we
                            should analyze just what contribution it is expected <pb facs="0280" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/> to make toward the achievement of the
                            basic objectives, we should also analyze just what can be done under
                            each program. In other words, what credit terms will be offered; what
                            prices on cash sales; what delivery dates; what types of equipment will
                            be made available; whether ships are to be lent, and all the other
                            things that we have been bickering about for the past two years.</p>
                        <p>Some such presentation as that outlined very roughly above would enable
                            us to consider each of the different things that we have had under
                            discussion, but to do it with some idea of the relationship of that
                            problem to all of the other problems that we have under discussion, and
                            an idea of its relationship to the basic objectives that we are trying
                            to achieve.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>