<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>107. Telegram 17 from Quito, July 11</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10-12mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-07-11T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-07-11T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recu8CRwmmn30dF6G" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic reform</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-11T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-11T21:00:00-05:00" n="107"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <head>107. Telegram 17 from Quito, July 11<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d107fn1"
                        >Announcement of five-man military junta ouster of <persName
                            corresp="#p_AMCJ_1">Arosemena</persName> government. Confidential. 9 pp.
                        Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Ecuador, July to
                        November, 1963.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Quito</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-07-11T21:00:00-05:00">July 11, 1963, 9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d107-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-1"/>
                <p>Emergency. Action Department 17; Information Bogota 3, Lima 2, Guayaquil
                    Unnumbered. Department please pass to US CINCSO for POLAD, also <gloss
                        target="#t_ACSI_1">ACSI</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_AFCIN_1"
                    >AFCIN</gloss>. RE telecons with Belcher.</p>
                <p>Pressure building in military for replacement <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1"
                        >Arosemena</persName> culminated today in announcement by chiefs three armed
                    services of <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1">Arosemena</persName>’s ouster and
                    formation of military junta. Five-man junta includes Navy Commander Captain
                    Ramon Castro Jijon, Army Commander Colonel Luis Cabrera Sevilla, Air Force
                    Commander Lt Colonel Guillermo Freile Posso, Armed Forces Senator Colonel Marcos
                    Gandara Enriquez who also head of War Academy, and Colonel Santiago Morochz,
                    Subsecretary of Defense. Proclamation, issued by junta at 3:30 PM, stated
                    objectives of change are to crush communism and end terrorism, carry out
                    constitutional and structural reforms, and put into effect social and economic
                    reforms. Proclamation also placed country under martial law, prohibited strikes
                    and demonstrations, and suspended constitutional guarantees. Text of
                    proclamation sent separately.</p>
                <p>Following a period of uncertainty, during which President holed up in
                    Presidential Palace with support of Presidential Guard, presumably awaiting the
                    effect popular pro-constitutional demonstrations in Guayaquil and hopefully in
                    Quito, President <pb facs="d107-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-2"/>
                    finally convinced, during visit of three armed services chiefs, to relinquish
                    his office to junta and leave for airport where he flown out at twilight to
                    either Cali or Panama.</p>
                <p>Info regarding pro-constitutional reaction sketchy and not yet clear. Reports
                    from Guayaquil indicate that large pro-constitutional rallies being led by Mayor
                    Bucaram. Also reported that various prominent citizens have issued an appeal for
                    return to constitutional government and that Vice-President Varea has called an
                    extraordinary meeting of the Congress to meet tomorrow afternoon. Junta reaction
                    has been announcement that extraordinary session will not be permitted and that
                    a constituent assembly will soon be called. Varea reportedly arrested and to be
                    deported.</p>
                <p>Curfew imposed as of 9:00 PM tonight.</p>
                <p>Events arose from incident at banquet given last night at Presidential Palace by
                        <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1">Arosemena</persName> in honor of Admiral
                    Wilfred McNeil, president of the Grace Lines. President most noticeably drunk
                    while reading <pb facs="0443" n="268" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_268"/> speech
                    during decoration Admiral McNeil. He made impromptu speech later at dinner in
                    which he said he liked American public but that American <gloss
                        target="#t_govt_1">Govt</gloss> was exploiting Ecuador and Latin America.
                    This naturally fell like a bombshell among official guests who were already
                    shocked and ashamed over President’s condition. In response to President’s
                    assurances to me that no personal offense was meant, I said that I could not
                    agree with what he had said, and that the American <gloss target="#t_govt_1"
                        >Govt</gloss> was the reflection of the American people. <persName
                        corresp="#p_AMCJ_1">Arosemena</persName> staggered from the dinner table
                    shortly thereafter and did not reappear.</p>
                <p>In accepting apologies on behalf of <gloss target="#t_GOE_1">GOE</gloss> from all
                    ministers present and other dignitaries after dinner, I attempted play down
                    incident, saying <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has no quarrel with
                    Ecuador or its people, and that President’s statement while drunk would not
                    affect my <pb facs="d107-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-3"/> attitude or
                    that of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> toward continued good relations
                    with Ecuador. The extreme concern over effect of incident to those with whom I
                    spoke was apparent, despite my assurances. I expressed the same assurances this
                    morning to MinPublic Works Salem who concerned that incident might effect
                    pending consortium road loan. According <gloss target="#t_FonMin_1"
                        >FonMin</gloss> Peralta, <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1"
                    >Arosemena</persName>’s blast due resent over UPI press article appearing same
                    day in which Felando of American Tunaboat Association quoted as saying at San
                    Diego that fishing negotiations failed due <gloss target="#t_GOE_1">GOE</gloss>
                    bad faith and recommending embargo on imports fish products from Ecuador.
                    Resentment also fed, according Peralta, by Panama hat problem.</p>
                <p>Rumor already circulating in Guayaquil that coup undertaken at my insistence due
                    insult <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_Dept_1"
                        >Dept</gloss> alerted to possibility that this may be used in commie
                    propaganda here and elsewhere.</p>
                <p>Junta objectives explained to Mil Att and to me during visit today by Colonel
                    Gandara. He said military disgusted by events last night and decided this
                    morning to put an end to “disgraceful situation.” Since preparations had already
                    been underway for such a move in armed services, it took little time to put them
                    into effect. Consideration given to <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1"
                        >Arosemena</persName> replace by Vice President Varea but idea discarded in
                    face almost unanimous opposition. Presenting a partial preview of later junta
                    proclamation, Gandara said junta proposed initiate new regime with revision laws
                    to outlaw communism and put teeth into anti-communist measures. Planned promptly
                    to call a constituent assembly to draft new constitution. Proposed take
                    advantage of opportunity to effect clean sweep of Ecuador’s outmoded social
                    structure through agrarian, administrative and fiscal reforms to extent
                    possible.</p>
                <pb facs="d107-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-4"/>
                <p>Gandara stated in response my query <gloss target="#t_re_1">re</gloss>
                    restoration constitutional <gloss target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> that current
                    Congress could not be relied upon to make necessary changes in view its
                    demonstrated incapacity, with result that job would have to be done by junta
                    with collaboration patriotic and competent civilians. Although constituent
                    assembly would be called promptly, he <pb facs="0444" n="269" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_269"/> estimated that elections could not be held before about
                    two years. He assured me that military sufficiently unified to feel satisfied
                    that junta could carry on for this period of time in face possible leftist,
                    anti-junta reactions.</p>
                <pb facs="d107-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-5"/>
                <p>He repeated junta would merely represent military facade over civilian <gloss
                        target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> which should be able count support people
                    through effective implementation reform measures while at same time controlling
                    communist subversion.</p>
                <p>I emphasized importance of an early return to constitutionality. I said US <gloss
                        target="#t_govt_1">Govt</gloss> wanted to help Ecuador and that assurance of
                    return to constitutionalism within reasonably prompt period of time would
                    facilitate always sticky problem of recognition, while determination of new
                        <gloss target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> to push social and economic reform
                    would facilitate collaboration under the Alliance for Progress. Gandara replied
                    he would not be honest if he said return to constitutionalism could be
                    accomplished in six months because of needed structural changes in social,
                    political and economic systems could not be effectively worked out in so short a
                    period. He said junta did not want to repeat mistake of Peruvian junta which
                    missed opportunity to institute widespread reforms required by Peru. Without
                    arguing, I repeated a few times my original point on the importance of
                    assurances of prompt return to constitutionality and implementation of social
                    and economic reforms. I drew his attention to successful results of <pb
                        facs="d107-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-6"/> forward-looking
                    attitude of Salvadoran military on constitutional and reform problems.</p>
                <p>Colonel McRochz, another member of junta, telephoned me later. He said decision
                    change <gloss target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> taken in belief it essential for
                    Ecuador’s well-being and honor, and that crack-down on commies would be amongst
                    first moves of junta. I repeated position told Gandara. I also noted wisdom of
                    reform program since purely negative position against communist would leave door
                    open communist-stimulated reaction, whereas immediately emphasized program of
                    reforms and prompt return to constitutionality could reassure public and gain
                    its confidence.</p>
                <p>Visit from Alfredo Albornoz, independent liberal ex-Min <gloss target="#t_govt_1"
                        >govt</gloss>, confirmed Gandara’s assurance of high level civilian cabinet
                    and understood that names various other well-known civilians being considered
                    and approached. Said had been assured of prompt return to constitutionalism
                    through near future convocation constituent assembly to reform outmoded
                    constitution and then elect new president. Albornoz agreed on importance
                    promptly announced guarantees of return to constitutionalism and said would push
                    this further talks. He optimistic over future and confident junta in control
                    situation. He discounted importance congressional reaction and thought political
                    parties would fall in line. Albornoz was hard hitting Min <gloss
                        target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> who left <gloss target="#t_govt_1"
                        >govt</gloss> last year due <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1"
                        >Arosemena</persName>’s refusal clean house in <gloss target="#t_govt_1"
                        >govt</gloss>.</p>
                <pb facs="0445" n="270" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_270"/>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] reaction to current
                    developments:</p>
                <p>1. Directorate of CTE meeting tonight 7:00 PM to consider calling general strike
                    July 12.</p>
                <p>2. Commie youth instructed to hold street demonstrations tonight after 9:00 PM
                    curfew. Slogan will be “poder al pueblo; abajo la dictadura militar.”</p>
                <pb facs="d107-7" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-7"/>
                <p>3. Junta has issued order to arrest all known communists.</p>
                <p>Comment: [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] junta
                    proclamations have in my opinion over-emphasized commie problem, [<hi
                        rend="italic">2 lines not declassified</hi>]. Aside from demonstrations in
                    Guayaquil led by Mayor Bucaram, we have not as yet heard from other elements
                    who, while opposed to <persName corresp="#p_AMCJ_1">Arosemena</persName>, may be
                    expected also to oppose a military junta. Vice-President Varea has apparently
                    been attempting to capitalize on this sentiment, particularly in Congress, in
                    hope that he would be logical beneficiary under constitution. He has apparently
                    been put out of the way. We should have some idea tomorrow of the congressional
                    reaction and that of the political parties. If strong enough, these could
                    conceivably influence a greater readiness for a prompt return to
                    constitutionality. We shall of course press this point in further conversations.
                    Strength of leftist reaction will undoubtedly be important factor for
                    future.</p>
                <p>Although US support clearly being solicited, question of recognition has not yet
                    arisen. We propose, as the opportunities present themselves, to continue
                    pressing for a prompt return to constitutional government, as well as guarantees
                    that the new <gloss target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> will honor its international
                    commitments, including obligations under the Alliance for Progress. No problem
                    anticipated with respect latter two points.</p>
                <p>Although initially the three armed services and their commanders in the junta
                    display high degree of unity and resolve, it is doubtful this unified facade
                    will persist indefinitely, and it seems likely that questions of personal and
                    service interest will eventually be divisive. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                <pb facs="d107-8" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-8"/>
                <pb facs="d107-9" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d107-9"/>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Bernbaum</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
