<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <head>133. Memorandum for the record, January 22<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Meeting at the White House to discuss the situation
                                in Guatemala and Arévalo’s candidacy. Top Secret. 2 pp. <gloss target="#t_DOS_1">DOS</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CF_1">CF</gloss>, 714.00/1–2263.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1963-01-22">January 22, 1963</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d133-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d133-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting at the White House, January 22, 1963</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEM_1">Martin</persName>,
                                <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> Administrator <persName corresp="#p_BJO_1">Bell</persName>, Mr. Graham Martin, Deputy
                            Coordinator Alliance for Progress; Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJH_2">John
                                Crimmins</persName>, Director of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs, and
                            I were present at a meeting at the White House January 22 to discuss
                            Guatemala and Haiti. Col. <persName corresp="#p_KCJC_1">J.C.
                                King</persName>, Chief of the Western Hemisphere Division, and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>, his immediate
                            superior from the Agency, were also present.</p>
                        <p>The President opened the meeting, asking about the situation in Guatemala
                            and the candidacy of Arévalo. He was told that the Latin American Policy
                            Committee had agreed in December on eight courses of action for
                            Guatemala as follows:</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Mr. Martin [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]
                            indicated that [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                            declassified</hi>] not too much progress had been made. Finding and
                            building up an acceptable candidate in Guatemala seemed almost <pb facs="0501" n="326" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_326"/> impossible.
                            Mario Mendez Montenegro had been discredited in the municipal elections
                            and possibly Jose Cruz Salazar was stronger in the interior than had
                            been expected. Three observers are working on the poll of Arévalo’s
                            strength in the interior and find that it is not as strong as it was
                            suspected. By March, the results should be known. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] Arévalo’s prestige in
                            Guatemala without the United States appearing to take [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]. Positions at Padua and
                            West Berlin Universities have been found for Arévalo and, after there is
                            some pressure on him, possibly he might take one of these. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] is also
                            beginning to look into the military attitude. The military leaders at
                            present seem to indicate that they will not tolerate Arévalo’s election.
                                [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] another inter-agency
                            meeting will take place early in March. The President was very
                            interested and wanted to know more about Arévalo himself. He does not
                            feel that we should appear to be in open <pb facs="d133-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d133-2"/> opposition to Arévalo because he
                            is afraid that if we could not do anything about stopping his election
                            we must keep some lines open to him. The President wanted to know what
                            the Mexicans think of Arévalo. (Mr. Martin has sent <persName corresp="#p_MTC_1">Tom Mann</persName> a letter on this subject.)
                                [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] Mr. Martin indicated
                            he had also written President Betancourt and Foreign Minister Muniz of
                            Argentina that Arévalo was not a suitable candidate and the President
                            wanted to know what Betancourt thought of Arévalo. Mr. Martin said that
                            our Ambassador had twice reported that Betancourt was pretty
                            disillusioned about Arévalo and the President suggested that the
                            inter-agency meeting take place in mid-March before the Costa Rican
                            meeting and that he would talk to Betancourt about Arévalo when the
                            former visits Washington soon. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                                declassified</hi>] indicated that one course of action open to
                            Ydígoras is a trial of Arévalo for killing a Colonel Arana. The
                            President made it clear that he did not want any physical action taken
                            against Arévalo. This was clearly understood. He also wanted to know who
                            Arévalo’s friends in the United States are. It was agreed we would try
                            and find this out. He was very interested in Arévalo’s recent book and
                            arrangements were being made to send a copy to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DRA_1">Dungan</persName>. The President especially
                            wanted to know what Arévalo had said or done the last two or three
                            years, does this show he has changed? What does he think about things?
                            Would it be possible to get along with him?</p>
                        <p>In the Haiti talks (reported separately) Mr. Martin indicated that
                            President Duvalier had failed to perform properly and would probably not
                            retire when his normal term of the presidency ended in May. Mr. Martin
                            recalled that he had gone through a phony election last May allegedly
                            extending his term six years. The President again indicated that [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] (Mr. Martin
                            had made it very clear that the opposition was completely fragmented) we
                            should not cut all our bridges to Duvalier.</p>
                        <pb facs="0502" n="327" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_327"/>
                        <p>Another topic of interest introduced was the President’s question as to
                            why Muniz had raised a question of budgetary support in talks earlier
                            that day. Mr. Martin reported that even when Ambassador McClintock had
                            left Buenos Aires budgetary support was not on the schedule and that
                            Muniz was very embarrassed to raise this but had apparently gotten
                            orders from his President at the time of his departure to try and get
                            some money.</p>
                        <p>The President also spoke of his visit to Costa Rica which will be covered
                            in a separate memorandum.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>V. Lansing Collins</signed>
                            <affiliation>Director<lb/>Office of Central American and Panamanian
                                Affairs</affiliation>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>