<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>260. Memorandum from Jacob D. Esterline to the Chief, to the Chief, WH/4/PM,
                    May 2/4/PM, May 2</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10-12mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d260</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">260</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="260"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d260">
                <head>260. Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Jacob D.
                        Esterline</persName> to the Chief, <gloss target="#t_WH_1">WH</gloss>/4/PM,
                    May 2<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d260fn1">Straightening out dates of
                        strike force concept for the <persName corresp="#p_TGMD_1">Taylor</persName>
                        Committee. Secret. 2 pp. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Files: Job
                        85–00664R, Box 2, vol III, Part III.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-05-02">May 2, 1961</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d260-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d260-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Straightening Out Dates of Strike Force Concept for the <persName
                            corresp="#p_TGMD_1">Taylor</persName> Committee</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] has in his notes
                    instructions to write a paper straightening out in the <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD_1">Taylor</persName> Committee’s mind when we actually
                    became involved in strike operations. The need for this paper apparently arises
                    from Lt. Col. Egan’s statement to the effect that we always had a strike force
                    concept. During his testimony he apparently made reference to a trip he took in
                    June to one of the training camps, indicating at the time of trip the strike
                    operation had already been decided upon. My recollection is that Lt. Col. Egan
                    came to us about June 1960 and that he arrived with certain ideas which he
                    carried from the Pentagon on how best to tackle the Cuban problem. This,
                    however, did not constitute [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] policy. I am sure you—or more particularly, members of
                    your staff—will find that we had no approved philosophy of the operation within
                    the Project until well in September. The training program [<hi rend="italic"
                        >less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] was directed solely toward training
                    an instructor cadre in small unit or “guerrilla-type” operations. This cadre
                    when it arrived in Guatemala, in addition to working on building the camp [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] continued to train the
                    first recruits in the same kind of training they had received.</p>
                <p>2. Another example of my positiveness that we were not, at Project level,
                    thinking of a strike operation is the first conversation that we held in my
                    office in Barton Hall wherein I referred to the fact that the PM staff had been
                    talking about the development of a strike operation, but that I, myself, was not
                    convinced of it at the time and that I preferred to put small teams into
                    existing units at the appropriate time. As I recall, you had an open mind at
                    that point although without positive study of Cuba you leaned toward the concept
                    I outlined. It was at a somewhat later date, therefore (probably before the
                    first of October), that we talked again and you stated your conviction that
                    CASTRO could not be overthrown without a major or catalytic effort being made
                        <pb facs="0808" n="633" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_633"/> against him. After
                    deliberation I came to the same conclusion and we then began to think in terms
                    of expanding the force to the strength of a reinforced battalion
                    more-or-less.</p>
                <pb facs="d260-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d260-2"/>
                <p>3. The foregoing is important only because General <persName corresp="#p_TGMD_1"
                        >Taylor</persName> is going into very fine points in his analysis of
                    government policy. It is incumbent upon us, therefore, to get the record
                    straight in this manner, and, although Lt. Col. Egan may have had in his own
                    mind the idea of a strike operation—and I believe he came to us with some ideas
                    on hitting the Isle of Pines—this nevertheless was not approved Project or
                    Agency policy until quite a few months later. In point of fact, as I look back
                    over that period I’m sure during that period I found myself drifting along
                    devoting myself merely to creating basic capabilities in a variety of fields
                    without any clear-cut idea of what national policy would permit us to do.</p>
                <p>4. I hope the foregoing will be of some use to the PM staff in putting together
                    the paper required by General <persName corresp="#p_TGMD_1">Taylor</persName>. I
                    will be available all day today; however, if further clarification is needed
                    over and above that readily available within the PM staff, I suppose [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] or [<hi rend="italic"
                        >less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] would be in the best position to
                    comment on this as they were, in fact, the only instructors on the scene at the
                    time.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_EJD_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Jacob D. Esterline</persName>
                    </signed>
                    <affiliation>C/<gloss target="#t_WH_1">WH</gloss>/4</affiliation>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
