<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                        <head>261. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> memorandum, May 3<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d261fn1">Detailed statement of the
                                circumstances surrounding the cancellation of the D-day air strike.
                                Secret. 3 pp. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, DDO/<gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss>/COG Files: Job 82–00679R, Box 3,
                                Papers Furnished the Green Committee.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1961-05-03">May 3, 1961</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d261-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d261-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Detailed Statement of all the Circumstances Surrounding the
                                Cancellation of the D-Day Air Strike</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REFERENCE</head>
                            <item>Memorandum Entitled, Additional Information Desired of <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, dated 1 May 1961, paragraph
                                1</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0809" n="634" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_634"/>
                        <p>1. On D–1 (Sunday, 16 April 1961) at 2130 hours General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> was telephoned by Special
                            Assistant to the President <persName corresp="#p_BM_1">McGeorge
                                Bundy</persName>. General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> received this call in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName>’s office. On completion of
                            the call, General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName>
                            indicated that Mr. Bundy had stated it had been decided that there be no
                            air activity until such activity could be conducted from the air strip
                            in the beach area. Mr. Bundy had indicated that he had been in
                            communication with the President. Mr. Bundy was leaving for New York to
                            consult with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SAE_1">Stevenson</persName>. The President had directed that the Agency
                            consult the Secretary of State.</p>
                        <p>2. General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> called Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName>. It was indicated
                            that Mr. Bundy had also called Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> undertook to come immediately to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName>’s office.</p>
                        <p>3. At 2150 Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCT_1">Barnes</persName> telephoned
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName>’s office to say
                            that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName> had called to
                            say that the President had suggested that there be no air activity until
                            such activity could be conducted from the air strip in the beach area,
                            but that that should not be the case if there were operational reasons
                            against it.</p>
                        <p>4. Shortly after ten o’clock, General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> went to see the Secretary of State. Shortly
                            after General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> left, Colonel
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCJ_1">Hawkins</persName> returned from dinner
                            and was briefed by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName>
                            as to the above developments. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_HCJ_1">Hawkins</persName> telephoned Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> at Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName>’s conference and advised that the results of a
                            cancellation of the air strike could be disastrous. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_HCJ_1">Hawkins</persName> requested that the matter be
                            taken up again with the President in order to explain the seriousness of
                            the situation and to request consideration.</p>
                        <p>5. When General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> returned at
                            approximately 2315, General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> stated that there had been a change in our orders
                            and that air support would be limited to close support of the beachhead.
                            They reported they had not seen the President, but that Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName> had telephoned the
                            President and recommended there be no air strike, in view of political
                            considerations.</p>
                        <pb facs="d261-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d261-2"/>
                        <p>6. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_HCJ_1">Hawkins</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName> and Mr. Drain all pointed
                            out that this change came too late to divert the strike force; our most
                            recent information indicated that, according to the strike plan, at that
                            very moment the force was transferring to the smaller craft and
                            proceeding towards the beach and therefore could not be recalled. The
                            task force officers estimated that the failure to strike the aircraft,
                            which Zip reports and actual photography had shown in place after the
                            D–2 air strike, would be that our shipping would be attacked at dawn, or
                            shortly thereafter, with a result that supplies would not be landed and
                            some of the ships certainly sunk. It was put that the cancellation of
                            the D-Day strike would probably mean failure of the mission. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> replied that we had
                            our “marching orders” and would comply.</p>
                        <p>7. General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> requested that
                            Colonel <persName>Beerli</persName>, the Acting Chief of the Air
                            Division, be called to send to the Puerto Cabezas Air Base <pb facs="0810" n="635" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_635"/> a revised air
                            order. Such a revision was transmitted at 0158 on 17 April and said, in
                            part:</p>
                        <quote><p>“Complete plan amended to place all B–26 aircraft at disposal of
                                Brigade commander for Task Force protection: targets outlined in OPS
                                Plan 200–1, attachment 1, appendix 2 to Annex B are cancelled. . .
                                target restrictions are as follows: (1) only those armed vessels
                                approaching task force or landing area; (2) no seaports to be
                                attacked; (3) only those land targets that are called for by Brigade
                                Commander for close in support; (4) no large cargo
                            ships.”</p></quote>
                        <p>8. A message received from the Puerto Cabezas Air Base at 0645 on the
                            17th indicated that the above message was received at that base 17
                            minutes after transmission. The Base’s reply read, in part:</p>
                        <quote><p>“Refs received and reluctantly complied with. Complete plan
                                amendment per refs received 170715Z with all pilots in cockpit ready
                                for start engines. Needless to say this less than desirable
                                operating procedure when 12 aircraft timed for take-off between
                                0730Z and 0800Z. Realize it desired give maximum protection to
                                Brigade however believe change will not afford as much protection as
                                original strike plan. The only real offensive danger to the Brigade
                                is enemy fighters and bombers which are better hit on their home
                                field—not repeat not over the beachhead. . . Pilots were in
                                continual briefings today without sleep prior strike as a result
                                late guidance and last minute changes.”</p></quote>
                        <pb facs="d261-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d261-3"/>
                        <p>9. At approximately 0015 of the 17th, General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> telephoned Major General
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> at the latter’s home
                            and requested that General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> join General <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> and Project officers in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EJD_1">Esterline</persName>’s office. General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> arrived at 0100. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> informed General
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> as to the
                            cancellation of the strategic strikes on the airfields and on the
                            Managua Military Reservation and explored with General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> what the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> might do to compensate for this
                            limitation. General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> left
                            at approximately 0145 to consult with <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> personnel. TS cable <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> 99422 was subsequently transmitted by General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName> to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_CRAJE_1">Clark</persName> and Admiral Denison. That
                            cable, a warning order, indicated that the <gloss target="#t_CEF_1">CEF</gloss> aircraft would be limited on 17 April to defense of the
                            beachhead from air and ground attack and that limited Cuban aircraft
                            patrol activity was expected in the area. It also stated that the
                            recipients should be prepared to execute on order the following missions
                            “as soon after first light as practicable throughout daylight hours 17
                            April:</p>
                        <quote><p>“a. Provide Air Cap for <gloss target="#t_CEF_1">CEF</gloss>
                                shipping outside territorial waters. Rules of engagement as stated
                                in your Op Plan apply as applicable.</p>
                            <p>“b. Provide EW for <gloss target="#t_CEF_1">CEF</gloss> ships to
                                include <gloss target="#t_LCI_1">LCI</gloss>’s for purpose of
                                warning ships of approaching aircraft. EW ships should remain
                                maximum distance off shore consistent with capability to communicate
                                with <gloss target="#t_CEF_1">CEF</gloss> ships.”</p></quote>
                        <p>10. At 0525 Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName> called
                            Colonel Shuler of the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> Staff to
                            advise him to implement General <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW_1">Gray</persName>’s warning order immediately, <pb facs="0811" n="636" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_636"/> with the following
                            amendments: paragraph a, negative; paragraph b, affirmative, with two
                            provisos: (1) no support to be closer than 30 miles to the coast of
                            Cuba, and (2) ships not to be too close to one another. Mr. Bissell had
                            earlier received this advice in a telephone conversation with General
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGCP_1">Cabell</persName> and the Secretary of
                            State.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>