<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="278g" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278g">
                        <head>278G. Memorandum from <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Inspector
                            General Kirkpatrick to Assistant Deputy Director for Plans <persName corresp="#p_BCT_1">Barnes</persName>, January 22<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d278gfn1">Response to <persName corresp="#p_BCT_1">Barnes</persName>’ January 19 memorandum
                                commenting on Kirkpatrick’s survey of the Cuban operation. 2 pp.
                                Secret. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> Files, History Staff Files: Job
                                85–00664R.</note></head>
                        <pb facs="d278g-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d278g-1"/>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1962-01-22">January 22, 1962</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Tracy:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Thank you for your courtesy in sending me a copy of your memorandum of 19
                            January concerning the Inspector General’s Survey of the Cuban
                            Operation. I do hope that Dick forwards it to the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>, and I am enclosing a copy of this
                            note to you in case you wish to send a copy to Dick.</p>
                        <p>I have not had time to study your memorandum, or even in fact do more
                            than glance at the <gloss target="#t_DDP_1">DD/P</gloss> analysis in
                            view of the meeting with the President’s Board all day Friday and the
                            fact that I am going to be away all this week. However, I will make the
                            following comments. Needless to say, I completely disagree with your
                            statement that it is an incompetent job. I feel that it is competent and
                            I believe that the more than one file cabinet drawer full of background
                            documents will prove its competence. I do not believe that it is biased.
                            We made it very clear at the start of the report that it would only deal
                            with inadequacies and failures and would not purport to be a thorough
                            analysis of the operation.</p>
                        <p>Most of all I object most strongly to your third observation, namely that
                            it is malicious and intentionally biased. I have asked the men who did
                            this survey to review your memorandum and comment on the reasons you
                            believe that it is biased. I should perhaps acknowledge that more time
                            should have been spent with you or <persName corresp="#p_BRM_1">Bissell</persName>, but inasmuch as this devolved on me, if there
                            is a fault, it is mine personally. But to imply that for some reason,
                            unknown to me, that we would slant this report is an unfair comment. You
                            apparently feel there was something unusual in the distribution of the
                            final report. The only thing unusual in it was that we had two Directors
                            at the time, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName>
                            having asked for it received it as he was leaving for the West Coast on
                            the day before Thanksgiving and everybody else got their copies on the
                            day after Thanksgiving. Your concern as to how the President’s Board and
                            the Attorney General knew of the survey’s existence can be answered very
                            simply. In 1956 the President’s Board in writing advised all agencies
                            that all <pb facs="d278g-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d278g-2"/>
                            inspector general reports should be forwarded to them automatically. I
                            don’t believe it was a week after the Cuban operation that the direct
                            question came from that Board as to whether <pb facs="1069" n="894" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_894"/> an inspection was going to be done
                            to which an affirmative reply was given. The Attorney General’s source I
                            do not know.</p>
                        <p>Finally, as far as to what should be done next, you and Dick should know
                            that at the conclusion of my discussion with the President’s Board I
                            urged that a group, or individual, who had not in any way been
                            associated with the operation be charged with taking the <persName corresp="#p_TGMD_1">Taylor</persName> Report, our report and your
                            comments and all background material and writing a truly national and
                            detailed report. I believe that would be a far better solution than
                            trying to develop a <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> position, which
                            really is not very practical inasmuch as there were so many outside
                            factors affecting this operation.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>Lyman B. Kirkpatrick</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>