<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-10-22T18:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-10-22T18:08:00-05:00" n="365" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                        <head>365. Telegram 222308Z from the White House to <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName>, October 22<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d365fn1">Transmits text of <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName> letter to <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName>
                                <gloss target="#t_re_1">re</gloss> Soviet build up in Cuba to the
                                Department. Top Secret. 2 pp. <gloss target="#t_DOS_1">DOS</gloss>,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CF_1">CF</gloss>,
                            737.56361/10–2262.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-10-22T23:08:00+00:00">October
                                    22, 1962, 2308Z</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>For <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> Duty Officer Secretariat.
                            Attention: Mr. Little from Situation Room. Cite <gloss target="#t_CAP_1">CAP</gloss> 5497–62.</p>
                        <p>My Dear Friend</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Bruce called to see me this morning and gave me evidence of
                            the Soviet build up in Cuba. I quite understand how fiercely American
                            public opinion will react when it knows these facts. I have this moment
                            received through our teleprinter the text of your proposed declaration
                            tonight. Let me say at once that we shall of course give you all the
                            support we can in the Security Council. I hope that you will provide us
                            immediately with the best legal case that can be made in support of the
                            broad moral position so that our representative can weigh in
                            effectively. Of course the international lawyers will take the point
                            that a blockade which involves the searching of ships of all countries
                            is difficult to defend in peace time. Indeed quite a lot of controversy
                            has gone on in the past about its use in wartime. However, we must rest
                            not so much on precedent as on the unprecedented condition of the modern
                            world in a nuclear age.</p>
                        <p>If, as I assume, the Security Council resolution is vetoed the only
                            appeal is to the Assembly. What the result will be there no one can <pb facs="1319" n="1144" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1144"/> tell but I
                            doubt whether they will be in favor of any conclusive action or even if
                            they are I do not see how they will enforce it. What I think we must now
                            consider is <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>’s likely
                            reaction. He may reply either in <pb facs="d365-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d365-2"/> words or in kind or both. If he
                            contents himself with the first he may demand the removal of all
                            American bases in Europe. If he decided to act he may do so either in
                            the Caribbean or elsewhere. If he reacts in the Caribbean his obvious
                            method would be to escort his ships and force you into the position of
                            attacking them. This fire-first dilemma has always worried us and we
                            have always hoped to impale the Russians on this horn. No doubt you have
                            thought of this but I would be glad to know how you feel it can be
                            handled. Alternatively, he may bring some pressure on the weaker parts
                            of the free world defense system. This may be in South-East Asia, in
                            Iran, possibly in Turkey, but more likely in Berlin. If he reacts
                            outside the Caribbean—as I fear he may—it will be tempting for him to
                            answer one blockade by declaring another. We must therefore be ready.
                            Any retaliatory action on Berlin as envisaged in the various contingency
                            plans will lead us either to an escalation to world war or to the
                            holding of a conference. What seems to be essential is that you and I
                            should think over and decide in what direction we want to steer things
                            within the alliance and elsewhere. We should take counsel as soon as we
                            have the Russian reaction.</p>
                        <p>While you know how deeply I sympathize with your difficulty and how much
                            we will do to help in every way, it would only be right to tell you that
                            there are two aspects which give me concern. Many of us in Europe have
                            lived so long in close proximity to the enemy’s nuclear weapons of the
                            most devastating kind that we have got accustomed to it. So European
                            opinion will need attention. The second, which is more worrying, is that
                            if <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> comes to a
                            conference he will of course try to trade his Cuba position against his
                            ambitions in Berlin and elsewhere. This we must avoid at all costs, as
                            it will endanger the unity of the alliance.</p>
                        <p>With warm regard, Harold MacMillan.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>