<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>367. Circular telegram 726, October 23</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10-12mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-10-23T01:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-10-23T01:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recwKa2RCO7F6zrUd" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Overflight</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rectswnul2C5uzE9Y" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Munitions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-10-23T01:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-10-23T01:55:00-05:00" n="367"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <head>367. Circular telegram 726, October 23<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d367fn1">Instructions to meet with highest available official to
                        persuade government to which accredited to take actions to prevent Soviet
                        Bloc military equipment from reaching Cuba. Secret. 4 pp. <gloss
                            target="#t_DOS_1">DOS</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CF_1">CF</gloss>,
                        737.00/10–2362.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-10-23T01:55:00">October 23, 1962, 1:55
                            a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d367-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d367-1"/>
                <p>In view situation described President’s radio-TV statement this evening
                    (communicated separately) you instructed seek appointment immediately at highest
                    feasible level and by such means as may seem most likely achieve purpose, to
                    endeavor persuade government to which accredited take such actions as indicated
                    in following paragraphs to prevent Soviet Bloc military equipment reaching
                    Cuba.</p>
                <p>US considers its own safety and world peace jeopardized by confirmation of
                    offensive nuclear build up on Cuba. You should emphasize in your discussions
                    that Government has before it critical opportunity take decisive action for
                    preservation of peace as well as positive demonstration its friendship for
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>All African Ambassadors accredited Washington, along with others will be fully
                    briefed by Secretary at State Department this evening and will presumably
                    urgently communicate gist.</p>
                <p>Briefing will include critical proofs reasons our concern. Needless to say
                    Government should be made aware deadly serious nature this démarche.</p>
                <p>If you believe your démarche should be followed up by Presidential communication
                    to Chief of State, advise immediately.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Review:</p>
                <p>The following African countries have civil aviation agreements with Soviet Bloc:
                        <gloss target="#t_UAR_1">UAR</gloss>, Ghana, Guinea, Mali, Morocco, Senegal
                    and Sudan. In <pb facs="d367-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d367-2"/>
                    addition, overflight rights have been requested from Chad, Libya, Niger, Somalia
                    and Tunisia, with the following results: Niger, request approved; Chad, Somalia
                    and Tunisia, have not replied to the Soviet request; Libya has stated that
                    overflights will be considered individually.</p>
                <p>At present time, flights from Khartoum to the West Coast of Africa have been
                    blocked by Chad’s refusal to grant overflights.</p>
                <pb facs="1322" n="1147" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1147"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">General Tactics:</p>
                <p>A. <gloss target="#t_CA_1">CA</gloss>–674, sent to Rabat, Dakar, Lagos, Paris,
                    should be implemented as quickly as possible and cabled responses sent
                    soonest.</p>
                <p>B. In countries where agreements now in force, high level approach should be made
                    seeking prohibition of through flights direct to Cuba or to Cuba via South
                    America. Should it prove impractical to secure these blanket assurances our
                    retreat position should be to urge denial of onward flights carrying military
                    equipment of any type. This particularly true where Czechs and Polish airlines
                    unlike Soviet have legal rights overfly and make technical landings such as in
                    Senegal.</p>
                <p>C. All governments involved should be urged to deny special rpt special Soviet
                    Bloc flights which appear to be destined for South America and Cuba.</p>
                <p>D. Urge governments who have not yet granted overflights to refuse such as
                    request if made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Fort Lamy:</hi> Government should be immediately urged
                    continue its policy and not rpt not reply to Soviet requests for
                    overflights.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Rabat:</hi> Morocco a key control point between Belgrade
                    or Cairo and Dakar, Conakry or Bamako. Refusal by Morocco authorities to permit
                    landings or onward <pb facs="d367-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d367-3"/>
                    flights of Bloc aircraft carrying military equipment would contribute
                    immeasurably to successful blocking of shipments by air.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Khartoum:</hi> While onward Western flights under Soviet
                    agreement not yet implemented because of Chad refusal permit overflight GOS
                    could make maximum contribution this effort by refusing Soviet rights military
                    laden aircraft land Khartoum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Accra-Bamako-Conakry:</hi> In view of the avowed policy of
                    non-alignment of the Government of Guinea (Mali and Ghana) and consequent
                    intention to avoid scrupulous involvement in the Cold War, the U.S. Government
                    is confident that the Governments of Guinea (Mali and Ghana) will not (rpt not)
                    permit the use of its territory, including overflights for the transport by
                    aircraft of the Soviet Union and its allies of arms, munitions and other
                    implements of war destined for Cuba. To assist the Government of Guinea (Mali
                    and Ghana) in identifying material of this type the U.S. Government would be
                    willing to make competent technical personnel available.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Lagos &amp; Monrovia:</hi> While it doubtful Soviets will
                    plan use routes through Liberia &amp; Nigeria nevertheless U.S. request to
                    refuse overflights should be made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For UAM States:</hi> Niger &amp; Senegal only UAM countries in
                    which Soviets have air agreement or overflight permission. However, same
                    approach as indicated above for Lagos and Monrovia should be made by Niamey.
                    Dakar Embassy should make strongest possible representa<pb facs="1323" n="1148"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1148"/>tions as to key airport from which
                    principal air shipment may jump off for Cuba.</p>
                <pb facs="d367-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d367-4"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Paris:</hi> France should be urged influence UAM countries
                    approve U.S. request and act accordingly. This is of maximum necessity in Niger
                    and Senegal.</p>
                <p>End.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_RD_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
