<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-01-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="594" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d594">
                        <head>594. Memorandum of conversation between <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> and other U.S. and Soviet officials, January
                                10<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d594fn1">U.S.-Soviet relations.
                                Secret. 3 pp. <gloss target="#t_DOS_1">DOS</gloss>, Secretary’s
                                Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 65 D 330.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1963-01-10">January 10, 1963, noon</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d594-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d594-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>U.S.-Soviet Relations</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi></head>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item>John C. Guthrie, Director, SOV</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">U.S.S.R.</hi></head>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Vasiliy Vasilyevich
                                            Kuznetsov</persName>, First Deputy Foreign
                                        Minister</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Anatoliy F.
                                            Dobrynin</persName>, Soviet Ambassador</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_MLI_1">Lev Isaakovich
                                            Mendelevich</persName>, Assistant to <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName></item>
                                    <item>Viktor Pavlovich Karpov, First Secretary of Embassy
                                        (Interpreter)</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> thanked the Secretary
                            for the opportunity of seeing him. He said that the Secretary, of
                            course, knew why he had been sent here by Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>. After two and a half
                            months the talks on the Cuban situation in New York had concluded and it
                            was therefore considered useful for him to meet the Secretary now. At
                            his meeting with the President yesterday, the President had expressed
                            the opinion that while the results of the New York talks had not been
                            everything which might have been desired, the text of the joint letter
                            to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Secretary General did
                            represent progress. The Secretary interjected that both the President
                            and he appreciated the genuine effort <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> had made to achieve agreement in New York.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> replied that the
                            United States representatives had also been very expert and frank,
                            expressing U.S. positions very clearly. The resulting general atmosphere
                            had been business-like and this was encouraging.</p>
                        <p>Looking back to the end of October, <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> continued, we may say that an important
                            conclusion should be drawn in order that we might move ahead and that
                            U.S.-Soviet relations will be even better. He had agreed with the
                            President’s statement that relations between the two countries should be
                            good. The important conclusion which clearly emerges from the crisis is
                            that when our two mighty powers display sincere efforts to reach
                            agreement on important problems affect<pb facs="1733" n="1558" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1558"/>ing the fate of mankind, they can
                            agree. During the crisis constructive steps had been taken by the Soviet
                            Government and <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> in his
                            exchanges with the President. The President had also taken constructive
                            steps and as a result agreement was reached which permitted a solution
                            to the crisis. This very <pb facs="d594-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d594-2"/> important circumstance has been noted in Moscow.
                            But with this, it is worth saying that it took only five days to agree
                            to avert thermonuclear war but two and a half months to agree on a
                            document reflecting the essence and spirit of the basic agreement.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said that he wished to
                            stress that the role of our two countries is outstanding as the whole
                            world recognizes. It is, therefore, important to try over and over to
                            improve our relations and to combine our efforts for the solution of
                            bilateral and international problems in the interests of maintaining and
                            consolidating peace. The Soviet Government agrees with the President
                            that now that the New York negotiations have been concluded, the way has
                            been paved to a certain extent to give more attention to other
                            international problems. With regard to our relations, there is still
                            something to do and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is not
                            satisfied with the present status. <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> has made quite clear the sincere desire of
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> to do everything possible to
                            improve relations in order to remove obstacles in the path to the
                            betterment of relations and then to unite our efforts to solve other
                            problems. The Secretary probably realizes, <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said, that the relations between us play an
                            important role in international affairs and the world situation depends
                            to a great extent on our relations. <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said he had no particular problems in mind but
                            believed the Secretary knew what they were. He did mention that our
                            economic relations, specifically trade, are unsatisfactory and that our
                            cultural relations, although some results have been achieved in this
                            field, could be still further improved. The Soviet Government would like
                            to do its best to clear away obstacles.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that he was very interested in <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName>’s views. We are interested
                            in improving our relations, as the President said. We do not doubt that
                            the President and <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            bear very heavy historical responsibilities in this phase of world
                            history. Both men understand this. This is one reason why the President
                            has sought to maintain effective channels of communications between us.
                            But the historical importance of our relations for good or ill makes us
                            feel we must maintain effective communications channels and not just in
                            the physical sense. The Secretary observed that when he became Secretary
                            he had not dealt with Soviet affairs for some 10 years. He has observed
                            one noticeable difference between the two periods inasmuch as it was now
                            possible to talk with some degree of understanding across the
                            ideological gap which separates us. One of our great problems, the
                            Secretary said, is that we must recognize our very important ideological
                            differences. We both try to understand our differences and we must <pb facs="1734" n="1559" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1559"/> also try to
                            enter into the other side’s thinking. There was still much to be done in
                            this area.</p>
                        <pb facs="d594-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d594-3"/>
                        <p>Twelve to 14 years ago, the Secretary observed, he had talked with Jakob
                            Malik in New York and had agreed with him to talk about what each did
                            not like about the other’s policy. We should try to explore genuine
                            common interests objectively considered and attempt to establish real
                            communications with each other. While he had been speaking about the
                            general subject of communications, the Secretary said he also wished to
                            talk about the problem of physical communications. Recently the United
                            States Government had offered to establish on a reciprocal basis radio
                            transmitters in the Embassies in Moscow and Washington. For the United
                            States this represented simply a desire to improve our technical
                            communications with our Embassy. Rapidity of communications is a matter
                            of joint interest. The Secretary noted that the Soviets have two leased
                            lines to the United States whereas we have none to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said that he did not
                            know the details of this problem but promised to take it up upon his
                            return to Moscow. With regard to the Secretary’s comments on the general
                            spirit of our relations, <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> asserted that people in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> live in a magnificent and happy
                            period. <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> is a very
                            real man who knows the spirit and thoughts of the rank and file. He is a
                            most devoted fighter for good relations between our two countries and
                            for the maintenance and consolidation of peace. Your President,
                            therefore, has a good partner, <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said, and you were lucky that you had
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> as the head of
                            the Soviet Government in October.</p>
                        <p>However, there are some groups in the U.S. who were not interested in
                            having good relations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.
                            This is not the case in the Soviet Union so that the U.S. has more
                            difficulty in this sense than does the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. It is important not to look backward in the search
                            for peace. Unfortunately, such tendencies do exist in the U.S. and it is
                            up to the United States Government to handle this situation. Sometimes
                            even United States officials show signs of this pressure. For example,
                            in December at a press conference the Secretary had said that the system
                            in Cuba was inconsistent with Western Hemispheric ideals. This sentiment
                            reflects backward views and impressions.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary opined that it might be well for the two Foreign Offices to
                            make up a group of four or five people, yours to try to think like
                            Americans and ours to try to think like the Soviets. As for his December
                            10 press conference, the Secretary noted that the President had stated a
                            year and a half ago that there were two points in regard to Cuba which
                            were not negotiable: its political-military alliance with an outside
                            power and interference in the internal affairs of other countries.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> observed that mutual
                            understanding was very important but asked the Secretary whether he did
                            not think that at this <pb facs="1735" n="1560" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1560"/> stage each side understood something about the
                            policies of the other. Ideological differences cannot be solved.
                            However, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> freely admits that
                            even in the light of this basic difficulty we can solve important
                            problems in the interest of peace and humanity. United States official
                            policy is based on the understanding that a country’s social system is
                            not part of its legal system. In the United States there is a theory
                            that the Western Hemisphere is a special place which should only be
                            bound by the ideals now found there. Not everyone will agree with this,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KVV_1">Kuznetsov</persName> said. The
                            situation in Latin America is not so ideal that it does not require
                            change. Indeed, many governments in the Western Hemisphere seek change.
                            The Soviet Union wishes for friendly relations with other countries,
                            especially the United States, and it does not wish ideology to
                            interfere.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>