<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>656. Memorandum from Sherman Kent to to McCone, April 19, April 19</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10-12mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d656</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">656</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="656"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d656">
                <head>656. Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Sherman Kent</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJA_1">McCone</persName>, April 19<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d656fn1">Comments on proposed new covert policy and
                        program toward Cuba. Secret. 5 pp. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                        Files: Job 91–00741R, Mongoose Papers, Box 1.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-04-19">April 19, 1963</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d656-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d656-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Comments on Proposed New Covert Policy and Program towards Cuba</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. The following comment was prepared by Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1"
                        >Kent</persName>, Smith, Huizenga, and Whitman of this office. We are in
                    general agreement with this paper’s estimates of specific Soviet reactions to
                    specific measures against Cuba. In this connection, our only general comment is
                    that reactions would probably be sharper to measures taken from outside Cuba
                    (D1, 2, and 3) than to those mounted internally (d 4), since these latter could
                    not be so successfully represented as US-inspired in Soviet political
                    exploitation. With respect to anti-shipping measures (D1, 2), it is possible
                    that reprisals would be taken against US ships in Latin American ports where
                    local Communists have significant sabotage capabilities, e.g. Venezuela.</p>
                <pb facs="d656-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d656-2"/>
                <pb facs="1856" n="1681" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1681"/>
                <p>2. Turning to more general reactions, we think that the paper and its Annex are
                    deficient in failing to consider how both the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and Cuba would interpret basic US policy toward Cuba in the
                    light of actions such as those proposed here. We believe that, at the present
                    juncture, both the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and Cuba wish to bring
                    about a period of calm in the Caribbean, reduce the constant threat of a crisis,
                    and in this way work for a stabilization of Cuba’s position and its <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> acceptance by its neighbors. We think they
                    probably intend to continue this policy until they are satisfied that Cuba can
                    again be used as a Communist base for forward action without excessive risk.
                    They realize that the US is unreconciled to the present regime, but they
                    probably hope that the US will limit itself to measures of isolation, and will
                    refrain from more active and direct measures. In this, they are probably
                    somewhat encouraged by the absence of low-level overflights and, to a greater
                    extent, by US declarations and measures against independent exile attacks.</p>
                <p>3. The unfurling of a program of more aggressive sabotage, harassment, and
                    resistance activities would at <pb facs="d656-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="d656-3"/> some point cause the Soviets and Cubans to question
                    whether a period of calm could be achieved. As incidents mounted, they would be
                    increasingly inclined to believe that the US could not be induced to let the
                    Castro regime survive, and that tactics of non-provocation would not divert the
                    US from its increasingly manifest intention to bring down the regime by indirect
                    action. Fears of direct US action, including even an invasion, would be revived.
                    We have no basis for predicting at what point the Soviets and Cubans would reach
                    these conclusions, but it is likely that Castro would be more concerned, and
                    earlier, than the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, with consequent
                    strains in Havana-Moscow relations. Castro might at some point use his own
                    military forces in a way designed to force the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss>’s hand.</p>
                <p>4. The Soviets, in these circumstances, would look for ways to arrest a trend
                    which appeared to point toward the ultimate fall of the Cuban regime and, in the
                    meantime, was complicating their relations with Castro. One of their first acts
                    might be to communicate privately with the President in a way which combined
                    [illegible in the original] of direct retaliation with hints that
                    Soviet-American relations as a whole were at stake in the Cuban <pb
                        facs="d656-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d656-4"/> confrontation. In
                    fact, under these circumstances, the Soviets probably would harden their
                    attitude on other international issues; at a minimum, they would find it
                    difficult to conclude major agreements at a time when US pressures on Cuba were
                    high. This might be thought of as a disadvantage if we expected that any gains
                    on other issues would result from US efforts to promote a more relaxed
                    atmosphere. At the present phase, however, it does not seem likely that Soviet
                    attitudes on matters like Berlin and disarmament will be much affected by such
                    considerations.</p>
                <pb facs="1857" n="1682" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1682"/>
                <p>5. If the Soviets found that such measures failed to deter the US, and it
                    appeared to them that covert action posed a real threat to the Cuban regime, the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> would have to decide whether to take
                    greater risks to arrest this trend. If they chose to do so, the issue of aerial
                    surveillance would offer an appropriate confrontation. They might believe that
                    continuing reconnaissance plus a rise in sabotage and harassment from outside
                    Cuba offered a promising case for resort to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> in an effort to force a major reversal of US policy toward Cuba.
                    To dramatize their case, they might shoot down a <gloss target="#t_U2_1"
                        >U–2</gloss>, absorb the likely US retaliation, <pb facs="d656-5" n="5"
                        type="facsimile" xml:id="d656-5"/> and thus seize the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> with a major crisis. From the Soviet viewpoint,
                    however, the latter would be a hazardous move offering an uncertain outcome, and
                    a decision to court such a showdown would depend upon numerous factors which are
                    themselves constantly changing.</p>
                <p>6. If the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> were unwilling to incur high
                    risks, it would probably seek to meet US activities locally and directly by
                    aiding Cuba’s efforts to protect its shipping and installations and to suppress
                    internal elements. If the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> adhered to this
                    policy, and Castro was in fact seriously weakened, it would probably content
                    itself with trying to maximize the political costs to the US of having restored
                    “imperialism” in Cuba.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KS_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Sherman Kent</persName>
                    </signed>
                    <affiliation>Assistant Director<lb/>National Estimates</affiliation>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
