<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>75. Memorandum from Woodward to Moscoso, March 7 to Moscoso, March 7</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10-12mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-03-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="75"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                <head>75. Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_WRF_1">Woodward</persName> to
                    Moscoso, March 7<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d75fn1">Costa Rican financial
                        difficulties. Confidential. 3 pp. <gloss target="#t_DOS_1">DOS</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_CF_1">CF</gloss>, 818.10/3–762.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-03-07">March 7, 1962</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d75-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d75-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Costa Rican Financial Difficulties</item>
                </list>
                <p>On February 15 Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TR_1">Telles</persName> received
                    a memorandum from President-elect <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1"
                        >Orlich</persName> of Costa Rica reviewing the fiscal situation of the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss>, which, in the latter’s words, adds
                    up to “a picture of absolute insolvency”, with the Government requiring a total
                    of 134 million colones, or approximately $20 million, to balance its books in
                    calendar 1962. The memorandum requested assistance from the U.S. to cover the
                    deficit in the form of a long-term, low interest loan to be extended prior to
                    June 30, 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1">Orlich</persName>’s memorandum was delivered to
                    the Ambassador by Raúl Hess, who has been designated as the future Costa Rican
                    Minister of Economy in the new administration which takes office on May 8, and
                    by Jaime Solera, who is slated to be a director of the Central Bank. The latter,
                    acting as spokesman for <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1">Orlich</persName>, made it
                    clear that he had no authority to speak for the outgoing <persName
                        corresp="#p_EJM_1">Echandi</persName> Government but expressed the hope that
                    a loan could be obtained from the U.S. to cover the budgetary deficit. The
                    Embassy does not consider the <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1">Orlich</persName>
                    memorandum as a formal request for a loan, which could only be made by the
                    present <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1">Echandi</persName> Government.</p>
                <p>The Solera-Hess visit followed a previous approach to the Embassy on February 8
                    by Finance Minister Borbon Castro, in which he estimated the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> needs from external sources to meet the
                    budgetary gap at $5 million and promised to give the Embassy a detailed analysis
                    of the situation, which would presumably serve to justify a loan request. This
                    analysis has not yet been received by the Embassy nor does it have a firm
                    indication that the <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1">Echandi</persName> Government
                    plans to request a U.S. loan during the remaining two months of its term of
                    office.</p>
                <pb facs="d75-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d75-2"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Nature of the Deficit</p>
                <p>The <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1">Orlich</persName> memorandum, which is said to
                    be based on Central Bank figures, breaks down the deficit into four categories,
                    as follows:</p>
                <pb facs="0370" n="195" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_195"/>
                <table>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Million Colones</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>Payments on internal bank loans due before April 30</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>Payments on 1961 obligations falling due in 1962 (Floating
                            Debt)</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>Decrease expected in 1962 revenues</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>Expenditures not included in 1962 budget</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row role="data">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>TOTAL</cell>
                        <cell>134</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Item 1 represents payments falling due on loans contracted by the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> with the commercial banks and the Central
                    Bank. Obligations to the Central Bank consist of short term public bond issues
                    and Treasury notes. The floating debt (Item 2) represents payments due to
                    individuals in 1962 on obligations contracted in 1961. Item 3 represents an
                    anticipated shortfall in 1962 revenues to meet expenditures programmed in the
                    1962 budget while item 4 consists of expenditures (unexplained) which were not
                    included in the budget. Only items 1 and 2, totaling 73 million colones, appear
                    to represent obligations for which the <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss>
                    has already contracted.</p>
                <p>The memorandum points out that the budgetary situation has led to the suspension
                    of service on a number of Costa Rica’s external obligations. The country is in
                    arrears to the extent of $600,000 on interest payments due on an Eximbank loan
                    for the Inter-American Highway and has also failed to pay interest of £70,000
                    due on sterling bonds and on bonds held in France. The Foreign Bondholders
                    Protective Council has expressed concern over the possibility of a default on
                    service of dollar bonds due April 15. It is anticipated that all U.S. and
                    international lending institutions will suspend action on current loan
                    applications of the <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> because of the
                    serious question that these defaults have raised respecting its
                    credit-worthiness.</p>
                <p>From the material already submitted by the Embassy, particularly the Central Bank
                    memorandum on Costa Rica’s fiscal situation, it appears that the present
                    budgetary crisis is the culmination of several years’ mismanagement of <gloss
                        target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> finances and that rectification of the
                    situation will require a thorough overhaul of <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1"
                        >GOCR</gloss> budget and fiscal practices as well as a reform of the tax
                    structure to create new sources of public <pb facs="d75-3" n="3"
                        type="facsimile" xml:id="d75-3"/> revenue. In this connection, an official
                    of the IBRD has indicated that it would be prepared to respond to a <gloss
                        target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> request for the assignment of a fiscal
                    expert to provide advice on reform measures.</p>
                <p>The loss of confidence in the national finances is already having adverse effects
                    on the national economy, creating uncertainty for private enterprise and
                    threatening a halt in economic and social development programs undertaken by the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss>. USAID reports that the Government
                    has failed to make contributions to certain projects included in the aid program
                    because of its shortage of funds.</p>
                <pb facs="0371" n="196" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_196"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Proposed Fact-Finding Mission by <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss> Fiscal Expert</p>
                <p>In response to a request from the Director of <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss>/Costa Rica for the temporary detail of an economist versed in
                    fiscal matters to assist the mission in assessing the Costa Rican financial
                    situation, AID/W is considering the sending of Mr. Frederic R. Fisher to San
                    José.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> believes that the timing of sending an
                        <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> official to Costa Rica for the above
                    purpose has political implications which merit serious study. In any event he
                    should not proceed until the new administration takes over on May 8. 1) The
                        <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1">Echandi</persName> Administration has about two
                    months to go before transferring power. <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1"
                        >Echandi</persName> has not requested a loan. It is not clear whether his
                    government intends to do so or intends to leave the deficit for the incoming
                        <persName corresp="#p_OBFJ_1">Orlich</persName> Administration to handle. In
                    either case the sudden appearance of the deficit will most certainly be fraught
                    with politics. When the PLN assumes power they will naturally exploit the
                    deficit problem bequeathed by the <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1"
                        >Echandi</persName> Administration, both for political purposes and in order
                    to justify the necessary corrective measures. If a United States expert carries
                    on extensive consultations with the Minister of Finance and the Central Bank the
                    United States will find itself in the middle of a political fight. This might
                    prejudice our desire to help the Costa Ricans work out a solution to the
                    problem. 2) Even though <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1">Echandi</persName> applies
                    for a loan no meaningful assessment of corrective measures could be considered
                    with the present lame-duck administration. 3) It is not clear whether <gloss
                        target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> is prepared, in principle, to consider
                    favorably a <gloss target="#t_GOCR_1">GOCR</gloss> request of $5 to $20 million
                    for a budgetary support loan.</p>
                <p>Because of the political implications involved in Costa Rica’s financial crisis
                    and the undesirability of any action that could be intergrated by the Costa
                    Ricans as a United States commitment to extend financial assistance at this
                    time, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> recommends that prior to Mr. Fisher’s
                    going to San José the Embassy and <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>/Costa
                    Rica be requested to transmit additional information on the problem available
                    through their channels. From this data we should be able to make an adequate
                    preliminary assessment of the situation and recommendations for United States
                    action.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_WRF_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WRF_1">Robert F. Woodward</persName>
                    </signed>
                    <affiliation>Assistant Secretary</affiliation>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
