<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mr. Mao Tse-tung to the
                        American Ambassador in China (
                        Hurley
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="political-prisoners" subject="political-prisoners" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422" lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/1–1049</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mao Tse-tung</persName> to the
                        American Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Yenan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-11">January 11,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear General Hurley</hi>: Your courteous letter of
                    January 7th, 1945 has been received.</p>
                <p>The five-point proposal set forth by our party in November of 1944 was refused by
                    the National Government. And it was extremely difficult for our party to agree
                    to the three-point proposal of the National Government,<note n="26" xml:id="d132fn26">See Third Counterdraft by Chinese Government
                        Representatives, November 21, 1944, <ref target="frus1944v06#pg_706">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 706</ref>.</note> so we proposed that
                    the National Government first voluntarily carry out four points including the
                    release of political prisoners with which to prove whether or not the National
                    Government is sincere in wanting to solve national problems on a democratic
                    basis. Your letter proposing to hold a conference between the two parties with
                    your personal participation in Yenan has been received with great appreciation,
                    but I still feel that nothing can be achieved from this conference except to
                    inconvenience you by travelling back and forth. All the secret negotiations of
                    the past eight years between the two parties have proved that there is not the
                    least sincerity on the part of the National Government. I would like to ask you
                    to be so kind as <pb facs="0179" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> to transfer the
                    following proposals of our party to the National Government:</p>
                <p>To call, in Chungking, a preparatory conference for convening a National Affairs
                    Conference; the preparatory conference to be made up of delegates from the
                    Kuomintang, the Communist Party and the Democratic Federation; guarantee that
                    proceedings of the conference will be public; that the delegates will have equal
                    standing and freedom of travel.</p>
                <p>If the above proposals are agreed to by the National Government, General Chow
                    En-lai will go to Chungking for discussions. We would appreciate your kind
                    reply.</p>
                <p>With my warm personal regards and wishes for your continued health and success, I
                    remain,</p>
                <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
                <closer>[Signature in Chinese] <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mao Tse-tung</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
