<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5–1945: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-19">May 19,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received May 19—1:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>801. Following is Central News Agency English service version of resolution
                        on Chinese Communist problem passed May 17 session of Sixth Kuomintang
                        Congress: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“After careful consideration of the report on the Chinese Communists’
                                problem submitted by the Central Executive Committee, the Congress
                                endorsed the policy of the Committee to seek a political solution of
                                the problem. With the responsibility of guiding the nation during
                                these arduous years on their shoulders, the Kuomintang has
                                consistently been striving for China’s freedom and equality [by?]
                                means of national unity and through a successful prosecution of the
                                war.</p>
                            <p>In September 1937, the Chinese Communist Party announced its four
                                pledges to support the National Government and to obey Government
                                    orders.<note n="50" xml:id="d261fn50">See telegram of September
                                    24, 1937, 4 p.m., from the Consul General at Hankow, <ref target="frus1937v03#pg_548">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 548</ref>.</note> Despite
                                these pledges, the Chinese Communist Party has persisted in armed
                                insubordination and refusal to carry out the military and
                                administrative orders of the National Government. However, our
                                party, as is generally known at home and abroad, has <pb facs="0397" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> maintained a policy of forbearance and
                                spared no efforts to preserve unity.</p>
                            <p>With the convening of the National Assembly in sight, the long
                                cherished wish of our party to return the reins of power to the
                                people and to establish a constitutional government will be
                                fulfilled in the not distant future. In order to consolidate
                                national unity and insure victory against Japan, our party must
                                carry out the policy of seeking a political solution of the Chinese
                                Communist problem with renewed vigor. We hope the Chinese Communists
                                are equally aware of the fact that the founding of the republic was
                                not an easy task and that the war against Japan has yet to be won.
                                We hope that the Chinese Communists will not fail to appreciate the
                                difficulties still confronting the nation, but will make good their
                                pledges of September 1937. We hold that at [<hi rend="italic">the?</hi>] settlement of all questions can be reached through
                                discussions as long as they do not adversely affect the progress of
                                our war against aggression or endanger the state. An amicable
                                settlement will be to the interest of the nation. We urge all of our
                                comrades to give their support to this policy.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>