<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="471" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d471">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00B/11–1445</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Navy Department</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="30" xml:id="d471fn30">Sent from the Office of the Chief of
                            Naval Operations to the Division of Foreign Activity Correlation.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">Serial 0057P21</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-14">14 November
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Excerpts from recent dispatches received from the Commander, Seventh Fleet,
                        are paraphrased for the information of the Department of State: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“As of 10 November, the Generalissimo was exerting pressure on the
                                Commanding General, China, for assistance by U.S. Forces in moving
                                his troops into Manchuria. Reaction of the Commanding General is
                                that the scope of the U.S. Mission does not include Manchuria, which
                                is strictly a problem to be resolved by the Russians and Chinese. He
                                adds that, on arrival at the Manchurian border of Chinese Forces,
                                U.S. liaison resources and personnel will be withdrawn. Communists
                                report that the Koito Iron Works in Peiping, which formerly supplied
                                arms to the Japanese, still operating. A report from Yenan on 3
                                November claimed that Japanese troops were included in the
                                Generalissimo’s forces in the drive to the south from Shih
                                Kiachwang.”</p>
                            <p>“As of 11 November, Yenan reiterated claims that Japanese troops are
                                presently employed by CNA and puppet troops in North China. Tientsin
                                and Tsingtao reported quiet. The Commander, Seventh Fleet, is of the
                                opinion that Communists are being shifted from Shantung to Manchuria
                                for training and equipping, possibly with Russian assistance.”</p>
                            <p>“Large scale Communist activity was reported on 12 November in the
                                Peiping, Tientsin, Ching Wang Tao area. A railroad bridge was
                                damaged at Hsu-Ko-Chuan and a train was derailed at Tang Fang. The
                                collision of two trains which occurred at Peitaiho was presumably
                                deliberate. The Russians are said by an American observer to be
                                widening the gauge of the North Manchuria Railroad, employing forced
                                Japanese labor. He adds that large numbers of Japanese are serving
                                in the Nationalist Forces in North China. The Commanding General,
                                China, has refused to assist French Forces in Indo China on the
                                basis that the U.S. might otherwise become involved in the internal
                                struggle.”</p>
                            <p>“Also on 12 November, it was reliably reported that Chinese
                                Communists in Wei Hai Wei and Chefoo are being supplied by the
                                Russians with munitions and Chinese Forces from Dairen. Chou En Lai
                                also made the statement but later denied it. Press and radio
                                accusations by Chinese Communists concerning ‘intervention by the
                                U.S. in <pb facs="0637" n="627" xml:id="pg_627"/> the Chinese civil
                                struggle’ are designed to force the recall of our forces by demands
                                of isolationist and Communist groups in the U.S.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> L. <hi rend="smallcaps">McCrea</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rear Admiral, USN.</hi>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>