<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commanding General, United States Forces, China Theater ( (Wedemeyer), ),
                    to the Chief of Staff, United States Army ( (Marshall))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recMHJD4XLL5GtXeu" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Emissary</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recVMjpePTbXrmHOO" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="477"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d477">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Nanking Embassy Files, Lot F–73: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commanding General, United States Forces, China
                        Theater</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wedemeyer</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of Staff, United States Army</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Marshall</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-16">November 16,
                            1945</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[CFBX 14735.] The following message has been received from the Commanding General
                    3d Phib Corps: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Railroad train en route Tangshan to Chinwangtao has been receiving small
                            arms fire from village about 600 yards north of Loanshein [Lwanhsien]
                            (118 45—39 45). Three hundred yards of track and road-bed destroyed by
                            mines causing several casualties among Chinese workmen. Peck under fire
                            yesterday in same general locality. Peck has requested an air bombing
                            mission against this village. Am directing Peck send emissary to village
                            to inform Communist leader that if fire continues against our forces I
                            will order an air strafing mission against village. Reports indicate
                            such villages often abandoned by civilians. Unless otherwise directed,
                            if firing continues from this village directed against our troops, I
                            intend to order air strafing mission.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0646" n="636" xml:id="pg_636"/>
                <p>My reply thereto was as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“If American lives are endangered by the small arms fire received from
                            village about 600 yards north of Loanhsien, as indicated in your radio
                            CAC 0368, it is desired that you inform the military leader or
                            responsible authority in that village in writing, both through a
                            carefully selected emissary and through dropped leaflets, that fire from
                            that particular village is endangering American lives and that such
                            firing must be stopped. After insuring that your warning to said
                            military leader or responsible authority has been received and
                            understood, should firing that jeopardizes American lives continue, you
                            are authorized to take appropriate military action. Your warning and
                            action should include necessary measures to insure safety of innocent
                            persons.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The railroad line Chinwangtao–Tangku on which the above incident occurred, is
                    essential as a supply line for the Marines in Peking-Tientsin-Taku area because
                    the Port of Taku may freeze in December, thus jeopardizing the supply situation
                    of the Marines in that area if they are not withdrawn prior to 1 January.
                    Further, the railroad line Chinwangtao–Tangshan also on which firing occurred is
                    necessary for movement of coal to the sea coast for shipment to Shanghai where
                    there are approximately 19,000 American troops closing out the China Theater and
                    awaiting shipment home.</p>
                <p>Information contained in paragraphs 1 and 2 above was furnished to the senior
                    American in Chungking with instructions to pass to the Generalissimo and
                    Communist leader Chou En-lai who is presently in Chungking.</p>
                <p>In view of the developments in North China which inevitably will involve our
                    forces in incidents of increasingly serious nature, it is recommended that the
                    entire Marine force be evacuated from China, movement to be initiated at once.
                    It is further recommended that the Chinese Government be informed of this
                    decision so that the Generalissimo can make provisions to relieve the Marines by
                    Central Government troops. The American Forces including the Marines in China
                    have completed their assigned mission of assisting in the redisposition of
                    Chinese Central Government Forces to facilitate the disarming and deportation of
                    Japanese. All of the incidents that have occurred thus far have been caused by
                    Chinese Communists or Chinese bandits and therefore are directly related to
                    fratricidal warfare which by existing Theater Directive Americans are cautioned
                    to avoid. In submitting this recommendation it is realized: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The Chinese Communists will interpret removal of U.S. Forces as a
                            complete success in their program of intimidation and propaganda.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Coal supply to Shanghai may be interrupted causing untold suffering
                            and chaos in that area. Stability in Shanghai area is vital to the
                            Generalissimo for political, economic and psychological reasons.</item>
                        <pb facs="0647" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Further, although we have complied with our directives and have placed
                            sufficient Chinese Central Government troops in North China to disarm
                            the Japanese and facilitate their repatriation were it not for Communist
                            opposition, it is realized that open civil war may break out once the
                            Marines are removed. At the same time, however, it is possible that the
                            fratricidal strife now instant in North China might reach the scale of
                            open civil war even though the Marines are not evacuated.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Marine Commander has exercised excellent judgment throughout in avoiding
                    serious incidents under increasingly difficult conditions. However the Chinese
                    Communists in all probability are striving to create an incident which will
                    prove before the bar of public opinion that Americans are participating in
                    fratricidal warfare. It will be extremely difficult if not impossible to avoid
                    involvement with dissident groups particularly when one such group will do
                    utmost to precipitate embarrassing situations.</p>
                <p>Admiral Kinkaid has seen this message and concurs.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
