<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commanding General, United States Forces, China Theater ( (Wedemeyer), ),
                    to the Chief of Staff, United States Army ( (Eisenhower))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recsTmAcLGbo1pCoe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic stability</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="recuvwbOC4H2MyRrN" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Amphibious force</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recVMjpePTbXrmHOO" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="500"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Nanking Embassy Files, Lot F–73: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commanding General, United States Forces, China
                        Theater</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wedemeyer</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of Staff, United States Army</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Eisenhower</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-26">November 26,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[CFBX 15676.] Further comments to War 84094<note n="76" xml:id="d500fn76"
                        >Telegram of November 19 from the Chief of Staff, U. S. Army, to the
                        Commanding General, U.S. Forces, China Theater, <ref target="#pg_644">p.
                            644</ref>.</note> follow. It is my considered opinion that the Chinese
                    Central Government does not now have the capability to eliminate Japanese from
                    North China and <pb facs="0690" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/> Manchuria under
                    existing conditions without further United States and/or Allied assistance and,
                    in the case of Manchuria probably the wholehearted cooperation of the Soviet
                    Russians. The Generalissimo has stated that he has decided to temporarily forego
                    reoccupation of Manchuria. His current operations in Southern Manchuria he
                    personally described as having the objective of seizing the line in Jehol
                    Province including the railroad running from Chihhsien (121 degrees East 41
                    degrees North) to Ishsien–Chaoyang–Yei Pai Shan (119 degrees 30 minutes East 41
                    degrees 15 minutes North)–Chengte (118 degrees East 41 degrees North) to Peking.
                    He wants to deny the port of Hulutao to the Chinese Communists and to contribute
                    to the protection of the north flank in his operations in North China against
                    forays or penetrations south into North China. Concurrently the Generalissimo
                    said that he intends to cope with the Chinese Communists in the area south of
                    the Great Wall and north of the Yangtze Valley with a view to eliminating all
                    Japanese and establishing political and economic stability. This appears to be
                    sound procedure but I doubt his ability to achieve satisfactory results in North
                    China for several months, perhaps years. He simply does not have adequate or
                    appropriate resources to protect the long lines of communications against
                    depredations and interceptions by Chinese Communist guerrillas. He now has five
                    armies in North China and desires urgently to move five more there. He can not
                    support logistically the five armies presently in the area with his available
                    sea and air transports even when his armies are operating close to seaports. As
                    his forces advance inland and become more widely dispersed, logistical support
                    will be confounded and probably rendered impossible by aforementioned Chinese
                    Communist action.</p>
                <p>With regard to repatriation plan in China Theater, it was visualized that all of
                    the Japanese in the area north of the Yangtze Valley and south of the Great Wall
                    would be evacuated in first priority for obvious reasons. A joint conference was
                    held in Shanghai to formulate plans for repatriation of Japanese from China,
                    including representatives of SCAP, China Theater, Chinese National Military
                    Council, Chinese Supreme Field Commander, Chinese War Transport Board, United
                    States Seventh Fleet, Seventh Amphibious Force and Third Amphibious Corps.</p>
                <p>Responsibility for organizing concentration pools at ports of embarkation and for
                    maintaining flow of Japanese to these pools was accepted by the Chinese.</p>
                <p>Commencing 15 November [19]45, the Seventh Fleet agreed to employ 14 LST’s in
                    shuttle service between China and Japan. By 15 December [19]45 the number of
                    LST’s was to be increased to 107.</p>
                <p>Initially Japanese were to be evacuated from Tangku, Tsingtao and Shanghai. After
                    1 January [19]46, when South China ports <pb facs="0691" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"
                    /> would be cleared of mines and when it was estimated that available Japanese
                    would have been evacuated through at least one of the northern ports, it was
                    planned to initiate their evacuation from South China areas.</p>
                <p>There are three limitations to evacuation of Japanese, exclusive of shipping, as
                    follows: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>By SCAP: Ports of Hakata, Kagoshima and Sasebo are prepared to receive
                            a total of 8,000 repatriates a day from China.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>By Chinese: The Chinese have agreed to maintain a flow of Japanese to
                            the ports equal to the average daily evacuation rate of 3,000. However
                            they have already indicated their inability to move the Japanese from
                            the interior due to current disorders, involving intercepted lines of
                            communications. Further, the Chinese Central Government considers
                            essential retention of armed Japanese in the area to protect LOC<note
                                n="77" xml:id="d500fn77">Line of communication.</note> and certain
                            key areas until the Central Government is in position to assume these
                            responsibilities and also to prevent Chinese Communists from moving in
                            and assuming control.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>By CNO<note n="78" xml:id="d500fn78">Chief of Naval Operations.</note>
                            and CinCPac:<note n="79" xml:id="d500fn79">Commander in Chief, U. S.
                                Pacific Fleet.</note> CNO 181755Z dated 18 November [19]45<note
                                n="80" xml:id="d500fn80">Not found in Department files.</note> and
                            based on CinCPac recommendations limited use of naval shipping to areas
                            occupied by United States Forces, that is, to Tangku and Tsingtao. These
                            two ports are limited to shipping a total of 90,000 a month. Subject
                            radio further states that repatriation of Japanese in United States
                            naval vessels will cease upon the inactivation of China Theater. If
                            China Theater is inactivated on 31 December [19]45 as currently
                            contemplated, United States naval vessels would be able to move
                            approximately 130,000 repatriates from two North China ports mentioned
                            above, assuming of course that Chinese continue flow to those ports. As
                            of 30 November [19]45 it is estimated that only 35,000 Japanese will be
                            repatriated through those two ports. According to information from U. S.
                            sources in North China, the Japs will not be made available in adequate
                            numbers.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>There are approximately 723,000 Jap soldiers and 126,000 civilians in the area
                    between the Yellow River and the Yangtze Valley inclusive. Practically all of
                    these have been disarmed. If the Navy could remove the restriction on the use of
                    Shanghai and could make shipping available, the bulk of these Japanese could be
                    evacuated in about 7 months time, contingent of course upon the amount of
                    shipping made available and the ability of the Chinese to insure a steady
                    capacity flow. The port of Shanghai could handle about 4,000 a day. This
                    evacuation of Japanese from the area between the Yellow River and the Yangtze
                    Valley is deemed feasible and would contribute materially to the accomplishment
                    of the over-all repatriation program.</p>
                <p>If United States Forces are required to remain in China until repatriation of all
                    Japanese is completed, it is readily apparent that <pb facs="0692" n="682"
                        xml:id="pg_682"/> the inactivation program will be postponed at least for 1
                    year, possibly longer. Examination of my last directive from the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff (Warx 77563<note n="81" xml:id="d500fn81">Not found in Department files;
                        for extract, see enclosure to memorandum of November 13 from the Acting
                        Chairman of the State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee to the Secretary of
                        State, <ref target="#pg_621">p. 621</ref>.</note> refers) in the light of
                    repatriation, so far accomplished, and military developments transpiring since
                    the date of issue 21 October [19]45 indicates following with reference to
                    specific paragraphs in that directive: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Paragraph <hi rend="italic">a</hi>—The evacuation or disposition of
                            United States Army equipment and supplies is well in hand, in consonance
                            with announced United States policies and regulations. This will not be
                            accomplished until authorized representatives of FLC<note n="82"
                                xml:id="d500fn82">Foreign Liquidation Commission under Maj. Gen.
                                Donald H. Connolly.</note> under State Department dispose of surplus
                            property for Army personnel will be required to protect property until
                            property is disposed of.</p>
                        <p>Paragraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi>—Practically completed, with only few
                            isolated cases requiring attention. Should be consummated by December
                            15th.</p>
                        <p>Paragraph <hi rend="italic">c</hi>—Plans and preparations for United
                            States Military Advisory Group have advanced to stage where further
                            progress can not be made until firm instructions are received from the
                            War Department concerning final agreements reached by the United States
                            and Chinese Governments. It is understood that negotiations continue and
                            it is recognized that the over-all situation may strongly influence
                            future action in this regard.</p>
                        <p>Paragraph <hi rend="italic">d</hi>—By December 31st all United States
                            Army installations, command, and activities of the China Theater will be
                            closed out except in Chungking, Nanking and Shanghai areas. The closing
                            of a few installations may be delayed by negotiations for surplus
                            property disposal and by time involved in turning over weather stations
                            to Chinese. When the Generalissimo and his Government move to Nanking,
                            installations in Chungking area will be closed out promptly. A nucleus
                            will be maintained in Nanking and by the first of the year United States
                            personnel in the Shanghai area should total not more than 6,000,
                            assuming of course that present inactivation plan can be carried out in
                            view of limitations mentioned above. I should like to invite the
                            attention of the War Department that all of my directives (Warx
                                51593,<note n="83" xml:id="d500fn83">Telegram of October 24, 1944,
                                    <ref target="frus1944v06#pg_178">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 178</ref>.</note> supplemented
                            by Warx 47513<note n="84" xml:id="d500fn84">Telegram of August 10 from
                                the Joint Chiefs of Staff to the Commanding General, U.S. Forces,
                                China Theater, <ref target="#pg_527">p. 527</ref>.</note> and
                            further supplemented by Warx 77563<note n="85" xml:id="d500fn85">See
                                footnote 81, above.</note>) do not indicate that United States
                            Forces, China Theater, have the mission of assisting the Chinese to
                            disarm and/or to deport Japanese in the area, although certain War
                            Department messages received in the Theater may be construed that we
                            have responsibilities therewith. I have been admonished in Warx 47513
                            paragraph 5 that the Japanese will surrender to the Chinese Central
                            Government and if circumstances require their surrender to U. S. Forces,
                            they will be immediately turned over to the Chinese Central Government.
                            In paragraph 6 of the same supplementary <pb facs="0693" n="683"
                                xml:id="pg_683"/> directive I have been directed to assist the
                            Chinese Government in the rapid transport of Chinese Central Government
                            Forces to key areas in China. This I have done with U. S. planes and
                            with U. S. shipping to an appropriate degree in order to facilitate
                            reoccupation by Chinese Central Government Forces of key areas formerly
                            held by the Japanese. If I were to assist the Central Government in
                            transporting additional forces and supplies to such areas, it would be
                            definitely to facilitate their operations against Chinese Communists
                            which I have been directed repeatedly to avoid.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">General Comments:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There are so many intangibles involved in the situation, it is difficult to
                    provide the War Department with firm answers. Broadly viewed, developments in
                    the Far East have created a situation, which subject the foreign policy of the
                    United States to supreme test concerning realistic implementation. It must be
                    recognized in the War Department, and I hope in the State Department, that our
                    present situation is untenable principally because: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The Chinese Communists are doing utmost to intimidate and to involve
                            United States Forces in military operations that definitely can be
                            construed as offensive in nature. They hope thereby to influence public
                            opinion in the States and abroad in their contention that the United
                            States is interfering with the internal affairs of China and that our
                            military forces should be removed summarily.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The Generalissimo and all Chinese Central Government officials are
                            constantly pressing for increased United States aid and also are
                            striving to create conditions that render our military assistance
                            against the Chinese Communists, and possibly the Soviet Communists,
                            mandatory or inevitable.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Enemy troops and civilians are not being repatriated. For the present
                            the Chinese Central Government is circumventing repatriation plans
                            because armed Japs are being used to protect LOC and key areas. The
                            Chinese Communists want the Japs disarmed and removed because they are
                            poised to seize their arms and equipment and also to occupy areas
                            vacated by the Japs.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I would appreciate War Department support in presenting the above pertinent
                    information and emphasizing the following basic premises to the President and to
                    the State Department: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is impossible to unify China and Manchuria with United States
                            assistance without becoming involved in fratricidal warfare.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is further impossible to assist the Chinese Central Government in
                            the repatriation of the Japanese in the area without U. S. Forces
                            becoming involved in fratricidal warfare.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is impossible to accomplish the unification of China and Manchuria
                            and the repatriation of the Japanese in the area without additional U.
                            S. or Allied Nations Military Forces and shipping resources far beyond
                            those now available or contemplated in the Theater.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0694" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It appears that the United States Government must decide upon one of the
                    following courses of action: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Evacuate all U.S. Forces from China as soon as practicable and accept
                            resulting consequences. I consider it impossible to carry out the
                            following conflicting orders now contained in the present apparent U. S.
                            policy: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Assist in the rapid deployment of Chinese Central Government
                                    Forces to key areas in China.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Assist in disarming the Japanese and their deportation to
                                    Japan.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Avoid participation in fratricidal warfare.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Approach the solution to the problem presented in the Far East
                            unilaterally, change existing Theater directive and make available to me
                            sufficient United States Forces, including air, ground and sea as well
                            as shipping, to carry out the unification of China and Manchuria under
                            the Central Government including the orderly and prompt repatriation of
                            all Japanese in the China Theater. This abrogates recently enunciated
                            United States foreign policy of self-determination. It would undoubtedly
                            be contrary to United States public opinion.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Invoke the machinery visualized in United Nations Charter, establish
                            immediately a trusteeship for Manchuria and Korea and pool the military
                            resources of the United Nations for temporary employment in China proper
                            to insure the expeditious repatriation of the Japanese. Thereafter
                            withdraw all United Nations Forces and assistance from China and permit
                            the Chinese to determine for themselves through processes of evolution
                            or revolution, by whom and how they will be governed. Adoption of this
                            course of action establishes precedent similarly in Java, Palestine,
                            Iran, Indo-China and other potential explosive areas.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
