<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-28T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-28T01:00:00-05:00" n="502" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d502">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/11–2845: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Robertson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-28T13:00:00+07:00">November 28,
                                1945—1 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received 2:54 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2056. Below is given summary of Military Attaché’s report for week ending
                        November 24:</p>
                    <p>Perhaps darkest aspect of a gloomy week was failure of Political Consultative
                        Council to meet November 20 and doubt expressed in some quarter whether it
                        would be convened in near future. Chou Enlai is about to proceed to Yenan
                        after conversations lasting 2 months <pb facs="0697" n="687" xml:id="pg_687"/> with Central Government authorities; conversations largely futile, at
                        least regarding urgent issues between Communists and Central Government.
                        Immediate return of Chou to Chungking from Yenan seems problematical, in
                        spite of Central Government press statements to contrary. It is implied that
                        negotiations are still in progress, but only more sanguine elements have
                        confidence in these negotiations.</p>
                    <p>On November 22 Chungking announced lifting of siege of Paotou, but there
                        seems little doubt that Communist troops will vigorously continue attacks on
                        both Paotou and Kweisui as well as other strategic place[s] along
                        Peiping–Suiyuan Railway; a long struggle in this region is probable. Place[s
                        likewise?] along 130-mile sector between Yunmeng, Hupeh Province, and
                        Hsiping, Honan Province. The goal of these operations is control of southern
                        portion of Pinghan railway. The Honan–Hupeh region and Suiyuan Province
                        continue to be center of most intense military activities, but evidence
                        increased during week that focus might be shifting to northeast. Communists
                        have been ejected from Shanhaikuan by elements of Central Government 13th
                        and 94th Armies who were reported moving north along Peiping–Mukden railway.
                        Presence of U. S. troops in the region, together with fact that victorious
                        Central Government Forces are American equipped, trained and transported,
                        has caused a new wave of anti-American feeling among Communists. Loss of
                        Shanhaikuan area and arrival of additional crack Central Government Forces
                        in Hopei are additional threats to aspirations of Communists in northeastern
                        provinces. Strict Russian adherence to their pledges of military withdrawal
                        has frustrated effectively hope of Central Government to obtain speedily
                        control of Manchuria. Communists have been moving into vacuum created by
                        evacuation of Russian troops and seem to be well entrenched with estimated
                        strength of 100,000 in many sections of Manchuria. Officials sent by Central
                        Government to Manchuria to set up controls after Japanese surrender have
                        been ordered back.</p>
                    <p>A number of high Chinese general officers are stated to have expressed
                        opinion recently that no settlement between Central Government and
                        Communists by negotiations can be hoped for and that a continuation of
                        hostilities is inevitable. These officers ventured opinion that strategy of
                        Communists is a piecemeal conquest of North China, with liquidation of
                        Central Government Forces in Shansi and Suiyuan as first major objective and
                        reduction of Tientsin–Peiping region as subsequent task. This view of
                        situation seems to be corroborated by current trend.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Robertson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>