<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d582</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">582</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1c8936cc6bb154a" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="yalta-agreement">Yalta Agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="582" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d582">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/12–745</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-07">December 7,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary telephoned the Chinese Ambassador<note n="5" xml:id="d582fn5">Wei
                        Tao-ming.</note> about 6:30 and asked him to come to the Department to see
                    him. When the Ambassador arrived the Secretary apologized for having had the
                    Ambassador come in the morning, at which time he had been unable to discuss the
                    matter he had hoped to discuss. He remarked that the Ambassador by this time had
                    probably heard the news of the plans to meet in Moscow on December 15.</p>
                <p>The Secretary told the Ambassador that, as he would recall, an agreement had been
                    reached at Yalta between the heads of the three Governments that their foreign
                    secretaries would meet every three or four months to consider informally and in
                    an exploratory way matters pending between them.<note n="6" xml:id="d582fn6">See
                            <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_968">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta and
                            Yalta, 1945, pp. 968</ref>, <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_974">974</ref>.</note> They had met at San Francisco, at Potsdam in July, again
                    in London in September, and they felt that answered the Yalta agreement. Now
                    another three months has passed and the Secretary, considering the number of
                    matters pending between them, had felt it would be wise to meet in Moscow and
                    has proposed this meeting.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he felt that there should be a discussion with the Russians
                    about the atomic bomb before the opening of the UNO on January 2, that failure
                    to have such a discussion might seriously affect the UNO.</p>
                <pb facs="0842" n="832" xml:id="pg_832"/>
                <p>The Secretary explained that he had hoped to release the news about the meeting
                    this morning, but Moscow had asked that it be held up and this afternoon they
                    had suggested a slight change and the announcement was being made this
                    evening.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he thought the Ambassador would agree it would be good for all
                    concerned if the views of ourselves and the Soviet Union on matters other than
                    the atomic bomb [apparent omission], and until some progress is made it is
                    difficult to resume the Council of Foreign Ministers.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said he felt it was very important to have such a meeting and
                    bring harmony on certain questions. He inquired if the Secretary expected to
                    bring about a meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers in Moscow later
                    on.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he did have such hopes and added, “I am an optimist there.” He
                    told the Ambassador that he had pressed for his proposal regarding the peace
                    conference at London and that if an agreement could be reached on this issue the
                    Council could immediately get into operation. He said there is a stalemate now
                    and he does not think we should continue to drift when there are so many
                    outstanding matters.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that in London he had stood by the Chinese and French
                    representatives and that a lot of people believed that his insistence on their
                    remaining caused the division—but there were many other problems.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador wished the Secretary all success in the forthcoming meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
