<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Hurley) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="670"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d670">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.93/7–2945: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-29">29 July
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>290927. This is a sidelight for your information. At 1335 hours Chungking time
                    July 291 sent you, both Army and Navy, a reply from Soong to your message of
                    July 28. He states that he has an understanding with Molotov to return to Moscow
                    to reach there soon after Stalin’s return. This was not a message direct to
                    Stalin as you requested. It was the best we could get. We hope it fulfills the
                    purpose. Soong will return to Moscow to resume negotiations. After his return
                    from Moscow Soong told me that he doubted the advisability of returning to
                    Moscow himself. At that time he suggested the advisability of having Dr. Wang
                    Shih-chieh appointed Foreign Minister and sending him to Moscow. I told Soong
                    frankly that I thought his plan not feasible and that he should personally
                    conclude the negotiations. This morning in our conference with Soong and Chiang
                    Kai-shek, Soong suggested in my presence the advisability of making Dr. Wang
                    Minister of Foreign Relations and sending him <pb facs="0963" n="953"
                        xml:id="pg_953"/> to Moscow to conclude negotiations with Stalin. I opposed
                    this on the grounds that Soong as Prime Minister is the only man in China other
                    than the Generalissimo with proper hand to negotiate with Stalin. If Soong
                    declines to go, sending a new Foreign Minister might have a damaging or perhaps
                    a destructive effect on the negotiations. It was finally agreed that Soong would
                    return to Moscow but it was suggested that Dr. Wang be appointed Foreign
                    Minister and accompany him. This would be satisfactory. Soong is distressed
                    about his political future. He fears the proposed agreement with the Soviet will
                    be damaging to him personally. The first time I saw Soong after his return from
                    Moscow he threw up his hands and said, “I am a broken man. I am personally ill
                    from overstrain and overwork.” Later he said, “This proposed agreement with
                    Soviet will be destructive politically to the man responsible for it.” There is
                    every indication that the Generalissmo is anxious for a just, friendly and early
                    agreement with Soviet. The Soviet Ambassador here states Soong agreed in Moscow
                    that China will join Soviet in recognizing independence of People’s Republic of
                    Outer Mongolia. As I heretofore advised you Chiang Kai-shek directed [possible
                    garble] Soong to take this action. At the same time he directed Soong to obtain
                    from Soviet modification of terms on railroads and ports in return for
                    recognition of independence of Outer Mongolia. Perhaps it is this point that is
                    distressing Soong. It appears that Soong has not yet obtained any modification
                    in regard to railroads and ports.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
