<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-16T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-16T04:00:00-05:00" n="726" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d726">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6–1645: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-16T16:00:00+07:00">June 16,
                                    1945—4 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received June 16—11:06 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1000. Following analysis of present situation in Sinkiang is based on
                            recent telegrams from Wash [<hi rend="italic">Ward</hi>]:</p>
                        <p>Chinese defense of Li [<hi rend="italic">defeat in Ili</hi>] valley in
                            January followed by collapse of Tihwa conspiracy in May resulted in an
                            impasse which should have afforded an opportunity to settle revolt as
                            purely internal affair. However, according to special delegate Li
                            Tsu-nung and others in position to know, Chinese authorities have made
                            no effort to <pb facs="1012" n="1002" xml:id="pg_1002"/> effect such a
                            local settlement, nor do they contemplate further action with a view to
                            a military solution. General Chu is reported to believe that settlement
                            can be reached only through diplomatic channels as he is said to be
                            convinced that revolt was inspired by USSR. In considered opinion of
                            British and American consuls, however, revolt resulted not from Soviet
                            instigation but from abundant internal causes, although quite possibly
                            there exists on the Soviet side of the border substantial tacit sympathy
                            with the rebels, especially among members of same race. In support of
                            this belief Ward cites apparent lack of over-all direction of rebel
                            activities as evidenced by failure of rebels who have been northwest of
                            Yenchi for more than a month to attack the city, and to take advantage
                            of the continued unrest in northern Sinkiang and the obvious Chinese
                            weakness in southern Sinkiang.</p>
                        <p>Ward has been confidentially informed that early in June special
                            delegate, acting on orders from the Central Government, requested
                            through Soviet Consul General good offices of USSR in settlement of
                            revolt. Consul General reportedly suggested that matter be referred to
                            Moscow. According to special delegate, problem will be discussed by
                            Molotov and Soong in Moscow.</p>
                        <p>Sent to Department. Repeated to Moscow.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Huklet</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>