<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Hurley
                    ) to President Truman
                    
                    Notation on the original: “Copy to General
                        Marshall and to Admiral King.” Copy obtained from former President Harry S.
                        Truman.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-20T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="democracy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647" lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="radio" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385" lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="armed-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241" lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="civil-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="espionage" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893" lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="public-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378" lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 P. W./5–2145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="45a" xml:id="d73fn45a">Notation on the original: “Copy to General
                        Marshall and to Admiral King.” Copy obtained from former President Harry S.
                        Truman.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-20">20 May,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>201118. Lord Louis Mountbatten and the diplomatic, commercial and military
                    representatives of the other nations with colonial interests in Asia are
                    endeavoring to obtain the appointment of Lord Louis as Commander under the
                    Generalissimo of all the United Nations Forces in China. Should Lord Louis or
                    any other British Admiral or General receive this appointment in preference to
                    an American it would constitute an overwhelming victory for the hegemony of the
                    imperialist nations and the principles of colonial imperialism in Asia. Such an
                    appointment would also be a distinct setback for America and democracy in
                    Asia.</p>
                <p>In dealing with this new development the United States is not in an altogether
                    fortunate position. President Roosevelt definitely refused to appoint an
                    American commander or to assume responsibility when the situation in China
                    appeared to be approaching a collapse. At this point it would be appropriate to
                    read the following messages: President Roosevelt’s messages through me to Chiang
                    Kai-shek dated October <pb facs="0118" n="108" xml:id="pg_108"/> 6 [<hi rend="italic">5</hi>] and October 18, 1944<note n="45b" xml:id="d73fn45b">For telegram dated October 5, 1944, see <ref target="frus1944v06#pg_165">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 165</ref>. Telegram of October 18 not
                        found in Department files.</note> and my message to the President dated
                    October 13, 1944.<note n="45c" xml:id="d73fn45c">See <hi rend="italic">Military
                            Situation in the Far East:</hi> Hearings before the Senate Committees on
                        Armed Services and on Foreign Relations, 82d Cong., 1st sess. (Washington,
                        Government Printing Office, 1951), p. 2879.</note> The Generalissimo finally
                    declined to appoint Stilwell commander under him of all forces in the Chinese
                    Theater.</p>
                <p>I then advised the President that the only issue between him and Chiang Kai-shek
                    was Stilwell, the Generalissimo looked upon Roosevelt as his own personal
                    friend, as China’s greatest supporter and as the world’s greatest leader of the
                    forces of liberty and democracy. The Generalissimo said he would appoint any
                    other American General whom the President would select. The President declined
                    to offer the Generalissimo an American General for this position in his message
                    of October 6, 1944, in the following words: “The current [<hi rend="italic">ground</hi>] situation in China has so deteriorated since my original
                    proposal that I am now inclined to feel that the United States should not assume
                    the responsibility involved in placing an American officer in command of your
                    ground forces throughout China.”</p>
                <p>On October 13, 1944, I said in part to the President: “If you are not going to
                    appoint some other American officer, we should withdraw from China. I do not
                    agree with what you have said in your telegram to Chiang Kai-shek to the effect
                    that America declines to take responsibility in China because we fear a
                    collapse. It is because there is danger of a collapse that America should assume
                    responsibility.” In the same telegram I said to the President, “I recommend that
                    you appoint an American General who will be acceptable to the Generalissimo” and
                    again, “We should accept the responsibility which the Generalissimo wishes to
                    give for an American commander of all ground and air forces in China; for the
                    reorganization of his service of supply, for the training of his army and every
                    other responsibility that he will give American officers with adequate
                    authority.” In that same telegram I advised the President: “If we permit China
                    to collapse, if we fail to keep the Chinese Army in the war all the angels in
                    Heaven swearing we were right in sustaining Stilwell will not change the verdict
                    of history. America will have failed in China. I am convinced that we can keep
                    China in the war and that we can reorganize the Chinese Army through the
                    Generalissimo.”</p>
                <p>The President, however, reiterated his position in his message of October 18 in
                    the following words: “As stated in my October 6 message, I do not feel that an
                    American should in the present situation <pb facs="0119" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/> assume responsibility in a command position for the operation of Chinese
                    forces in China. However, I will furnish a qualified officer to serve as your
                    Chief of Staff.” In the same telegram the President went on to separate the
                    India-Burma Theater from China and to establish a separate China Theater. This
                    latter action I consider sound. It simplified command processes by making China
                    a separate theater. In view of existing conditions it is proper to continue
                    China as a separate theater. You will note that the President made a number of
                    other requirements which the Generalissimo freely accepted and expedited.</p>
                <p>I pause here, Mr. President, to make a personal statement. The correspondence
                    above quoted shows the great tolerance of President Roosevelt and the latitude
                    he gave me to express my opinions when they were in complete conflict with his
                    own, he knew of course that once he announced his decision I would make it my
                    own and implement it effectively. This is the attitude, Sir, that I now assume
                    toward you.</p>
                <p>In the President’s message you can read that while he was against taking
                    responsibility for an American commander in the chaotic condition that then
                    prevailed in China he still placed in the Generalissimo’s hands what I believe
                    to be sufficient American support to prevent the collapse of the Government and
                    to stop the Japanese attack. The action of the President also stimulated the
                    endeavors of Chiang Kai-shek and other Chinese leaders in their efforts to work
                    out their own salvation. The President as you will note also advised the
                    Generalissimo that I would remain with the Generalissimo as the President’s
                    personal representative in military affairs. At that time I advised the
                    Generalissimo that with an American Chief of Staff who would also be commander
                    of all American forces in China and an American commander of the Air Forces and
                    an American commander of the Service of Supply and American officers in charge
                    of training and in various other positions of responsibility and with myself
                    near the Generalissimo as representative of the President we could in
                    cooperation with the Chinese still stop the Japanese attack and prevent the
                    collapse of the Chinese National Government and its military establishment. I
                    convinced him that we could also harmonize the relations between the American
                    military establishment and the Generalissimo and between the American Government
                    and the Government of China. The Generalissimo accepted this advice.</p>
                <p>After Stilwell had been relieved and the resignation of Gauss had been accepted,
                    many American Army and diplomatic officials returned with them or after them to
                    Washington. About that time there began an inspired attack in the American press
                    and radio against the National Government of China. To some extent this attack
                    had the support of American officials who had been removed in China. The <pb facs="0120" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/> attack was also supported by
                    ideological propagandists and crusaders against the American ideology, some few
                    of whom had been serving as war correspondents in China. Because of this
                    onslaught the American public seemed to have been convinced that the Chinese
                    National Government must collapse. The extent to which this opinion was held is
                    indicated by the fact that two distinguished United States Senators, Chandler
                    and Brewster, who had visited China, issued a statement expressing the opinion
                    that nothing short of a miracle could prevent the collapse of the National
                    Government of China.</p>
                <p>While the President refused to appoint an American commander, his policy was
                    still to sustain the National Government of China. Incidentally that has been
                    the policy of the United States since before Pearl Harbor. In Secretary Hull’s
                    statement to the Japanese and in the President’s statement to the Japanese
                    immediately before Pearl Harbor, it was strongly asserted that America was
                    committed to support economically, politically, and militarily the National
                    Government of the Republic of China.<note n="45d" xml:id="d73fn45d">See point 4
                        of Section II of outline of proposed basis for agreement between the United
                        States and Japan, dated November 26, 1941, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_768">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 768</ref>, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_769">769</ref>.</note> This same policy was
                    continued in America’s mutual aid pact–Lend-Lease agreement with China. America
                    has from the beginning until now recognized both as <hi rend="italic">de
                        facto</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> the National Government of the
                    Republic of China.</p>
                <p>Before my first visit to China, President Roosevelt briefed me on all of these
                    matters and directed me to prevent the collapse of the National Government and
                    to harmonize the relations between the Chinese Government and military
                    establishment and the American Government and military establishment, the
                    President was fully advised of all the imperfections and shortcomings of the
                    National Government and of all the difficulties encountered by American
                    officials in their relations with Chiang Kai-shek. In face of all these facts
                    the President said he knew of no other regime or government or of any other
                    leader in China from whom we could expect more support and cooperation than we
                    were receiving from the National Government and from Chiang Kai-shek. During the
                    Stilwell controversy and before the arrival of General Wedemeyer, owing to the
                    disastrous military situation in China I recommended (1) that we remove the B–29
                    strategical bombers from this area and base them where they could be supplied
                    from the sea thereby relieving over the Hump tonnage which could be used to
                    supply tactical air and ground forces; (2) that the United States use so much of
                    the American and Chinese resources then in India and Burma as would be necessary
                    to stop the Japanese drive in China.</p>
                <p>At this time General Wedemeyer who had been selected by President <pb facs="0121" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/> Roosevelt and the Joint Chiefs of Staff reported
                    to the Generalissimo. Wedemeyer was immediately appointed Chief of Staff by the
                    Generalissimo. Wedemeyer was also appointed commander of the American Forces in
                    China. At the time Wedemeyer took command the Chinese Army was in full retreat.
                    Both Chungking the Capital and Kunming the American base were in immediate
                    danger of being captured by the Japanese. Wedemeyer made a number of correct
                    decisions. He implemented his decisions quickly and successfully. He used
                    American and Chinese resources from India and Burma carefully and with due
                    consideration for existing conditions in the India–Burma Theater. He used only
                    so much of the Chinese-American resources as was necessary to stop the Japanese
                    drive on Kunming and Chungking.</p>
                <p>Wedemeyer is working in complete confidence and cooperation with the
                    Generalissimo. Wedemeyer has harmonized and integrated the American and Chinese
                    staffs so that they are now working as one team with the objective—the defeat of
                    Japan. Wedemeyer is training and reorganizing the Chinese Army through the
                    Generalissimo. In at least 36 divisions he is exchanging the Chinese antiquated
                    weapons for American equipment and training Chinese in the use of American
                    equipment. To say the least, Wedemeyer has stopped Japan in this Theater. He has
                    stabilized the military situation in China. In this he has had the unlimited
                    support and cooperation of the American Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                <p>No one realizes more fully than Wedemeyer and myself the tremendous effect that
                    American victories in the Pacific had in bringing about the change in the
                    military situation in China. It should be apparent to the most skeptical that
                    America has succeeded in preventing the collapse of the National Government of
                    China, in harmonizing relations between America and China and in keeping the
                    Chinese Army in the field and in contact with the enemy. The Chinese Army every
                    place is now stabilized and holding. In some places it has resumed the
                    offensive.</p>
                <p>In addition to this we have been instrumental in bringing about closer and more
                    harmonious relations between Russia and China. For this purpose at the direction
                    of President Roosevelt I made two visits to Moscow. We have obtained the
                    approval of Britain and Russia for the unification of the armed forces of China.
                    We have obtained an agreement by Britain and Russia for the support of the
                    American policy in China which is to endorse and support the aspirations of the
                    Chinese people to create for themselves free united democratic government. We
                    have been instrumental if not the prime movers of having Chiang Kai-shek make
                    beneficial personnel changes in the National Government. We have urged the
                    Generalissimo and <pb facs="0122" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> the National
                    Government to inaugurate the action now taking place for the adoption of a
                    democratic constitution, the liberalization of government and the inauguration
                    of democratic processes.</p>
                <p>We have succeeded in having the National Government recognize the Chinese
                    Communist armed party as a political party by appointing a Chinese Communist as
                    a delegate to represent the National Government at San Francisco. The Communists
                    recognized the National Government by accepting the appointment. We have visited
                    with the Communist leaders in their own territory. We have brought about
                    conferences between the Communist and National leaders in which they seem to
                    have eliminated some of their conflicts. In the controversy between the
                    Government and the Communist Party we had two major objectives, (1) to avoid
                    what appeared to be an immediately impending civil war, (2) to unite the
                    Communist and National Government armies under one commander to fight Japan.
                    Russia’s approval for unification of the armed forces of China and the fact that
                    Chiang Kai-shek is now working for unification indicates the possibility of a
                    satisfactory solution. The Communist armed party, however, still contends and in
                    my opinion with some degree of reasonableness that they will not submit their
                    troops to the command of the Chinese National Government unless an American or
                    other Allied officer is placed in command under the National Government of all
                    the armed forces of China.</p>
                <p>All the foregoing has been achieved by vigorously implementing America’s policy
                    to support the National Government changing as far as possible what we conceived
                    to be unworthy objectives of that Government. What we have recited here could
                    never have been accomplished by the individuals who mistakenly opposed and
                    weakened the National Government, who desired to have America recognize the
                    Chinese Communist armed party as a belligerent and unite our forces with the
                    Communist Party, thereby eliminating the National Government. If these well
                    meaning but misguided Americans who seemed not to understand America’s true
                    policy in China had succeeded, the Chinese National Government would have
                    collapsed. Chaos and civil war in my opinion would have ensued and America would
                    have failed in China.</p>
                <p>The foregoing recitation of facts is intended to give you a picture of the events
                    that led to the present stabilized position of the Chinese National Government.
                    Throughout this period Great Britain had no troops in contact with Japan in the
                    China Theater. Great Britain did not contribute to the prevention of the
                    collapse of the Chinese National Government. At a time when the stability of the
                    Chinese Government was questionable and it appeared that the Chinese Army might
                    not continue in the war, Great Britain was not seeking the command <pb facs="0123" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> nor assuming any responsibility in
                    China. Great Britain has avoided any responsibility in the controversy between
                    the Communist armed party and the National Government. In fact we have found
                    evidence that some of Great Britain’s agents were actually endeavoring to keep
                    China divided against herself. Now that the Chinese with the leadership and
                    support of America have recovered and are fighting, the British would not be
                    averse to stepping into a position where they could claim credit for what has
                    been achieved as well as credit for the final defeat of Japan and thereby
                    reestablish the prestige of imperialism.</p>
                <p>The personal representative of Prime Minister Churchill, the British Embassy, the
                    British War Mission and other British commercial, propaganda and espionage
                    missions, the Canadian Embassy, the Australian Embassy, the Netherlands Embassy
                    and the French members maintain staffs in China. No troops of any of these
                    nations participated in any combat contacts against Japan in the Chinese
                    Theater. The French claim that French troops and guerillas have fought Japan
                    during that period in Indochina. The fact remains, however, that there are no
                    British, French, Dutch, Canadians or Australian troops in China. Notwithstanding
                    this, I was advised under date of May 15 that the British Major General Hayes
                    had been appointed by the British Chiefs of Staff as “General Officer Commanding
                    British Forces in China”.</p>
                <p>If Lord Mountbatten or any other British Admiral or General is appointed to the
                    position of commander in China, the resources he will use to complete the defeat
                    of Japan will be more than 95 percent American. It will be another clear case of
                    the use of American resources to defeat American principles and American
                    policies. It is also claimed that Lord Louis has a well organized headquarters
                    which could move immediately into the Chinese theater. It is true that he has a
                    modern military headquarters. It is true that Lord Louis has an American deputy
                    commander and other able American officers on his staff, but Lord Louis and his
                    staff do not have the knowledge of China and the experience with the enemy in
                    China now possessed by Wedemeyer and the American and Chinese staffs at
                    Chungking, So far as the American commanders or deputy commanders are concerned,
                    you, Mr. President, have at your disposal American generals whose combat
                    experience and achievements are far superior even to the record that Lord Louis’
                    public relations officers claim for him.</p>
                <p>The paramount political issue in Asia for many years has been the issue between
                    democracy and imperialism. We supported Chinese democratic aspirations against
                    the imperialism of Japan. The question is will we now permit British, French and
                    Dutch imperialists to <pb facs="0124" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> use the
                    resources of the American democracy to reestablish imperialism in Asia. It is
                    the old conflict between the aspirations of people to be free and the desire of
                    predatory nations to rule. I have omitted any discussion in regard to the
                    position of Russia for reasons that will be well known to you. The appointment
                    of Lord Louis or any other imperialist as Commander in China would constitute
                    nullification of American principles and achievements in China. We are not
                    opposed to giving the British more credit than they deserve in this war against
                    Japan, but we are opposed to the surrender of the principles of democracy that
                    led America into the war for the purpose of destroying Japanese imperialism.</p>
                <p>America has fought Japan practically alone on the sea and on the land. All the
                    imperialistic nations have done has been in an endeavor to recover their
                    colonial possessions, largely by the use of American and Chinese resources, and
                    reestablish the prestige of imperialism. The defeat administered to Japan on the
                    sea and on the land and the present attack on the homeland of Japan should
                    indicate even to the casual observer that all the Southeast Asia colonial or
                    imperial areas must fall like ripe apples as America approaches the heart of
                    Japan. The command of Lord Louis in Southeast Asia has been at most a holding
                    job. Its mission as a holding force was made easy by American victories in the
                    Pacific. Because of American victories in the Pacific, the Japanese are now in
                    full retreat from Lord Louis’ area and his job now is one of easy and leisurely
                    mopping up.</p>
                <p>I recommend (1) that you oppose the appointment of any General other than an
                    American as Commander of all the forces in the Chinese Theater, (2) that you
                    authorize me to approach the Generalissimo with the suggestion that you might
                    now consider the assignment of an American General to be appointed by the
                    Generalissimo to command all forces in the Chinese Theater.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
