<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in China (
                        Robertson
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d768</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">768</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-31T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-31T02:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-31T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-31T02:00:00-05:00" n="768" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d768">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/10–3145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Robertson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-31T14:00:00+07:00">October 31, 1945—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 31—12:28 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1900. Minister of Foreign Affairs Wang Shih-chieh advises us as follows:</p>
                <p>The Russians have persisted in their refusal to allow landing of Chinese Govt
                    troops at Dairen. The Russians state landings will be permitted at Yingkou and
                    Hulutao, both inferior harbors to Dairen. Large concentrations of Communist
                    troops are reported near Hulutao. In order not to delay further movements of
                    troops into Manchuria, Chinese will proceed with landings at these two ports but
                    without waiving their right to land at Dairen. The Chinese staff at Changchun,
                    including Generals Hsiung Hsi-fei, Director General of Headquarters, and Chiang
                    Ching-kuo, Foreign Office Special Commissioner, are being denied freedom of
                    movement by Russians.</p>
                <p>He states that in opinion of Chinese Govt recent truculence of Communists and
                    attitude exhibited by Russians have a direct relationship.</p>
                <p>He says that negotiations with Communists were proceeding satisfactorily until
                    September 24. Between September 24 and October 17 Communist troops cut every
                    railway communication over which troops could be moved into liberated areas. He
                    said further there had been repeated unprovoked attacks on Govt troops,
                    mentioning specifically instance of heavy casualties to Govt forces when
                    Communists suddenly and unexpectedly attacked in Shansi Province.</p>
                <pb facs="1046" n="1036" xml:id="pg_1036"/>
                <p>Yenan broadcasts have made repeated attacks upon Govt and upon US policy.
                    Minister Wang stated he considered it unwise to engage in public debates with
                    Communists during period when efforts were being made to reach an agreement but
                    that he would endeavor to keep us confidentially informed as to course of events
                    and progress of conversations.</p>
                <p>Wang Ping-nan, Communist liaison man, makes frequent visits to Embassy in
                    interest of Communists (see Embtel 1884, October 29 and 1899, October 31<note n="74" xml:id="d768fn74">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_480">pp. 480</ref> and <ref target="#pg_482">482</ref>, respectively.</note>). The Embassy is unable
                    to evaluate claims and counter-claims that are made but shall endeavor to
                    present to you information given by both sides. We assume Dept is keeping
                    Ambassador Hurley fully advised our telegrams this subject.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robertson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
