<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. John D.
                            Sumner of the Office of Financial and Development Policy to
                        Mr. Willard L. Thorp, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary
                        of State (
                        Clayton
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d865</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">865</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-08-30T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="865" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d865">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/8–3045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">John D.
                            Sumner</persName> of the Office of Financial and Development Policy to
                        Mr. <persName>Willard L. Thorp</persName>, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary
                        of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clayton</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-30">August 30,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Aside from statements which have appeared in the press, the economic offices of
                    the Department appear to have little information as to what may have been
                    proposed by Dr. Soong to Mr. Crowley or to the Secretary of State, regarding the
                    financial needs of China, or to what the reaction of Mr. Crowley or the
                    Secretary may have been.</p>
                <p>I have checked two contacts in FEA who told me that they doubt whether anybody in
                    FEA knows except Mr. Crowley. On a purely gossip basis, one of my informants
                    said that he had heard that Mr. Crowley had indicated to Dr. Soong that it might
                    be possible to make 500 million dollars available to China through the
                    Export-Import Bank.</p>
                <p>I then talked with the head of China work in the economic wing of Treasury and
                    was told that they have no information. The belief was also expressed that Dr.
                    Soong did not discuss this matter with Secretary Vinson.</p>
                <p>Financial assistance to China involves a number of highly important questions
                    which would seem to require careful consideration within the economic offices of
                    the Department, as well as elsewhere in the Government. I very much hope,
                    therefore, that it may be possible to discover what transpired between Dr. Soong
                    and Mr. Crowley and perhaps also with the Secretary.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
