<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-12T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-12T20:00:00-05:00" n="9" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">124.93/1–1345: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-13T08:00:00+07:00">January 13,
                                1945—8 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received January 15—9 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>53. Coordination of U. S. civil establishments at Chungking and Embassy staff
                        requirements.</p>
                    <p>1. Donald Nelson recommended to the President by letter October 19<note n="36" xml:id="d9fn36">
                            <ref target="frus1944v06#pg_280">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 280</ref>.</note> that man of
                        outstanding qualifications be appointed to head FEA<note n="37" xml:id="d9fn37">Foreign Economic Administration.</note> establishment at
                        Chungking and be given rate [<hi rend="italic">rank</hi>] of Minister to
                        work under general direction of the Ambassador. President indicated he
                        approved.</p>
                    <p>I do not believe that this recommendation goes far enough. I suggest that
                        what we must consider is the broad basis of (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) our
                        needs for active, day to day supervision and coordination of the related <pb facs="0042" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/> functions and operations of all U.
                        S. Civil Government agencies here; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) our needs for
                        (1) coordinating those activities with the requirements of American
                        political and economic policy as invested in the Embassy and for (2)
                        coordinating all appropriate activities with the needs of the theater
                        commander and directing them into channels concretely helpful to our armed
                        forces in the war against Japan.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly I recommend that a qualified Foreign Service Officer or auxiliary
                        officer (such as a mature, experienced business executive who is politically
                        as well as economically minded) be assigned here to act as over-all
                        coordinator and supervisor of the various civil agencies, or civil branches
                        of other agencies, with which Embassy has affiliation or relations,
                        including the American advisers on Chinese War Production Board, leaving for
                        the time being the present administrative structures of those agencies as
                        they are. I am mindful in this respect of the need of fair recognition of
                        the work of the heads of agencies and their position vis-à-vis Chinese
                        officials with whom they deal. For example, Stanton<note n="40" xml:id="d9fn40">W. T. Stanton.</note> who heads FEA here is doing a very
                        good job and his personal position should not be lowered in the eyes of the
                        Chinese.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with Nelson’s recommendation that the new appointee operate
                        under the direction of the Ambassador, and as the direction and coordination
                        of American Civil Affairs should logically rest in the Embassy, I recommend
                        that the new appointee be assigned as staff officer of the Embassy. I feel
                        that this could be most appropriately accomplished by following precedents
                        we have established in other countries by assigning him here as Counselor
                        for Economic Affairs with personal rank of Minister. As such he could under
                        my direction and in my behalf (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) preside over the
                        weekly meetings we have inaugurated of representatives here of all American
                        civil and military agencies; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) carry on, expand and
                        make more effective the much needed work of coordination which we have
                        started; and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) enter into active supervision of
                        appropriate activities as a full time job. Atcheson<note n="41" xml:id="d9fn41">George Atcheson, Jr., Counselor of Embassy.</note> and
                        senior officers of the Embassy concur fully in these recommendations.</p>
                    <p>2. Embassy has a number of additional urgent staff needs, some of which have
                        been previously brought to Department’s attention. These needs are daily
                        growing more urgent, as follows: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>a thoroughly qualified Commercial Attaché having intellectual and
                                technical capacity to study and report on China’s vital economic
                                [and] financial problems as well as to continue Sumner’s<note n="42" xml:id="d9fn42">John D. Sumner, Adviser on Economic
                                    Affairs.</note> work after latter’s departure. With present
                                needs in this respect being augmented <pb facs="0043" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/> by increasing requests from Commerce Department
                                for wide variety of economic and commercial reporting. Commercial
                                Attaché should have at least two officers to assist him, at least
                                one American confidential typist, and a number of Chinese assistants
                                and typists. Boehringer,<note n="43" xml:id="d9fn43">Carl H.
                                    Boehringer, Second Secretary of Embassy.</note> who has been in
                                charge of Embassy’s Commercial Section, is due to be returned to
                                U.S. in 2 months and should in any case be relieved of this work in
                                order that he might devote himself to wartime economic reporting on
                                occupied areas. (His replacement should be qualified to do such
                                reporting.) Howard,<note n="44" xml:id="d9fn44">Hungerford B.
                                    Howard, Third Secretary of Embassy.</note> who has been handling
                                visas and citizenship, should have his commercial reporting training
                                utilized in the Commercial Attaché’s office. (See (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) below.<note n="45" xml:id="d9fn45">Not
                                printed.</note>)</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>First Secretary with demonstrated capacity for administrative work
                                and with both Embassy and Consular experience to replace Yunj<note n="46" xml:id="d9fn46">William E. Yuni, Second Secretary of
                                    Embassy.</note> as result of latter’s resignation. None of the
                                other second secretaries assigned here have had the all-around
                                administrative experience in large diplomatic and consular offices
                                necessary to take over our administrative desk with its wide variety
                                of duties and problems arising from peculiar situation here and our
                                close relations with the U. S. Army and other Government agencies.
                                It is a task which requires quick thinking, accuracy, decisiveness
                                and great versatility.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Political officers. Our highly important Political Section must be
                                adequately staffed. We are handicapped at the present time because
                                of the detail of so many officers to the army and at the same time
                                the ordering home of two of our best political reporters
                                simultaneously. Under present staff conditions the two officers at
                                present assigned to the Political Section necessarily devote a major
                                portion of their time to such time-consuming problems as withdrawal
                                of American citizens, protection cases and Chinese translation work.
                                We should have at least one additional and competent political
                                reporting officer.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>[Here follows an outline of clerical requirements.]</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>4. I make these recommendations after full consideration and consultation
                        with my staff officers. Ever since my assumption of charge of this Embassy
                        it has been a matter my daily wonder to me how the present inadequate staff
                        manages to carry on under present conditions. I express the hope that the
                        Department will be able to give immediate attention to these matters.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>