<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="977" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d977">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">711.932/5–3045</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Director of the
                            Office of Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Stanton</hi>)<note n="67" xml:id="d977fn67">Copy transmitted to the Ambassador in China in
                            Department’s instruction No. 167, June 13.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">San
                                    Francisco</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-30">May 30, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>During the course of an informal conversation with Dr. Wu<note n="68" xml:id="d977fn68">Dr. John C. H. Wu, Adviser to the Chinese Delegation
                            to the United Nations Conference on International Organization, San
                            Francisco, April 25–June 26, 1945.</note> in regard to the draft
                        commercial treaty which we presented to the Chinese Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs on April 2, 1945, Dr. Wu stated he agreed that it was highly
                        desirable that consideration and negotiation of the treaty proceed without
                        too much delay. He indicated that this was also the feeling of Dr. Sun Fo,
                        President of the Legislative Yuan, with whom Dr. Wu is very closely
                        associated.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wu informed Mr. Stanton that he had been requested by Dr. Sun Fo to look
                        into the question of ownership of real property by aliens in the United
                        States, having in mind the differing requirements prescribed by the
                        legislation of the various states of the United States. Dr. Wu said that he
                        and Dr. Sun Fo desired information on this <pb facs="1328" n="1318" xml:id="pg_1318"/> question in order that they might be in a position to
                        answer questions which would likely be propounded by their colleagues of the
                        Legislative Yuan in regard to the extent to which Chinese may acquire and
                        own real property in the United States. Dr. Wu said further that both he and
                        Dr. Sun Fo feel very strongly that the conclusion of a treaty with the
                        United States is of particular importance in view of China’s dependence upon
                        the United States and the support and assistance which the United States is
                        giving to China.</p>
                    <p>There ensued some discussion of the complicated nature of this problem and of
                        the formula which appears in our draft treaty regarding real property. Dr.
                        Wu expressed the personal opinion that the provisions in our draft treaty on
                        real property would in all probability be acceptable to the Chinese
                        Government. He said that he and Dr. Sun Fo hoped it would be possible for
                        them to appear before the Legislative Yuan, which as the highest legislative
                        organ of the Chinese Government is responsible for the ratification of
                        treaties, and be able to state that in a majority of the states of the
                        United States Chinese may acquire and own real property. He said he thought
                        this would satisfy those members of the Legislative Yuan who are inclined to
                        insist on full reciprocity in matters of this nature.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wu said that he would be glad to continue informal discussions regarding
                        this particular point in Washington after the Conference and would be very
                        grateful for any material the Department could let him have or could refer
                        him to relating to this particular problem.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>