<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Dawes))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-05-20T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-05-20T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-05-20T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-05-20T15:00:00-05:00" n="107"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a3/905a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dawes</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="26" xml:id="d107fn26">Sent also to the Ambassador in Japan,
                            <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis</hi>, on the same date, as the
                        Department’s telegram No. 92.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-05-20T16:00:00-04:00"
                            >May 20, 1930—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>127. In arguments before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee it has been
                    contended by some of the “big Navy” opponents of the treaty, who thereby seek to
                    confuse and discredit the treaty, that construction might be placed on article
                    19, second sentence, so as to permit replacements of tonnage in 6-inch cruisers
                    with the same amount of tonnage in 8-inch cruisers or vice versa by any of the
                    three parties. Since the word “replacement” necessarily implies the substitution
                    of the same amount of tonnage in the same kind of ships, we believe there is no
                    basis for such contention. We consider, moreover, that this contention is
                    directly contrary to the fair implications of the provision for transfer
                    included in article 17, and also directly disregards division of cruisers into
                    two sub-categories made by articles 15 and 16. We are anxious, nevertheless,
                    that the treaty’s enemies in the Senate may be given no possible excuse.
                    Approach should be made therefore to the appropriate British authorities to
                    inquire whether an exchange of notes on the following terms would be consented
                        to:<note n="27" xml:id="d107fn27">Quoted passage not paraphrased.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It is the understanding of the Government of the United States that the
                            word category in Article nineteen of the London Naval Treaty of 1930
                            means category or sub-category. The Government of the United States
                            declares that it interprets the Treaty to mean that vessels becoming
                            overage in either sub-category A or sub-category B of the cruiser
                            categories (Article sixteen) shall be replaceable only in that
                            sub-category.</p>
                        <p>“The American Government will be most happy to have the confirmation of
                            this understanding from His Majesty’s Government.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Use your best efforts to obtain Foreign Office consent to an exchange of notes of
                    this nature as soon as possible. A similar note will be addressed to the
                    Imperial Japanese Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
