<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in France ( (Armour))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-10-23T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-10-23T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-10-23T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-10-23T20:00:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a3/1175: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-10-23T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >October 23, 1930—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>270. Your No. 337, October 22, 3 p.m. The primary interest of the American
                    Government is not whether the French naval building program is what is announced
                    in <hi rend="italic">Figaro</hi>, or elsewhere; it is solely whether or not the
                    building program of the French Government is of such size and character as to
                    threaten the stability in the naval levels set by the London Treaty.</p>
                <p>While an exact formula for figures is not being suggested, the American
                    Government has pointed out, and it has been informed that the Government of
                    Japan will do likewise, the advisability of permitting the issue to be postponed
                    during the lifetime of the present treaty. The interests of both France and
                    Italy might be fully safeguarded, it would seem, by a unilateral statement by
                    France to the effect that while the London Treaty remains in force, that is up
                    to 1936, her building program could be reduced materially, subject, of course,
                    to a similar and satisfactory unilateral declaration by Italy.</p>
                <p>Similar representations accompanied by suggestion of the same formula of a
                    unilateral declaration have been made to Italian Government together with
                    suggestion that whole question of naval parity be postponed until 1936. The
                    entire matter has been discussed with Claudel, and it has been pointed out,
                    furthermore, that France was not in any way adding to her security by insisting
                    on high levels in naval armament and by prolonging unduly the period of
                    uncertainty on this subject through failing either to come to an agreement with
                    Italy or to act simultaneously with that power along independent lines.</p>
                <p>It is my belief that Claudel has not got across the true gist of my conversation
                    with him on the subject; Gibson should be very careful, therefore, to emphasize
                    every point as if the French Government had no previous knowledge of the subject
                    he wishes to take up.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Embassy at London.<note n="58" xml:id="d129fn58">Transmitted as
                        Department’s telegram No. 269, October 23, 9 p.m.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
