<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-01-27T11:32:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-01-27T11:32:00-05:00" n="304" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d304">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/962: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hibbard</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                            Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-01-27T12:00:00-04:32">January 27,
                                        1930—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 5:05
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>4. Department’s telegram No. 9, January 25, 1 p.m. I spoke to the
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs this morning at 10, not having been
                                able to see him yesterday. I repeated to him the contents of the
                                telegram under acknowledgment and left with him an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> in the same sense. I stated that the present
                                seemed a most propitious time to accept one of the suggestions made
                                by the neutral Governments and that such action would place Bolivia
                                in a most favorable light. He replied that the Bolivian Army was
                                under the complete control of the Government and that there was no
                                danger of any hostilities on the part of Bolivia. Orders had been
                                sent to all contingents in the Chaco to be ready to repulse any
                                attack but to provoke or make none. All alarming messages had been
                                sent out by Paraguay to prejudice the situation and for reasons of
                                internal politics. The Bolivian War Office also had intercepted
                                Paraguayan messages which could be made to appear equally damaging
                                but the Bolivian Government refused to publish them. He stated that
                                he attached no importance to a brief encounter of patrols in a
                                disputed territory as it had been common all over the world where
                                such conditions existed. The agitation of Paraguay was due to the
                                fear that Bolivia would make reprisals as she had done in the case
                                of Boquerón. This fear was unfounded as Bolivia would maintain peace
                                but was prepared to repel any aggression.</p>
                            <p>I asked if the Bolivian Government had as yet had time to study the
                                note of the neutral Governments of January 9. He replied that it had
                                not as the results of the representations of the Uruguayan
                                Government relative to the completion of the terms of the
                                conciliation agreement were being awaited. I asked if the present
                                incident would further delay consideration of the note and he
                                agreed.</p>
                            <p>The press is strictly censored but the tone has been very moderate in
                                the last few days. The public is not excited. Business circles are
                                exerting pressure against military action because of the already
                                depressed financial condition. Siles has not yet announced his plans
                                but as elections must be called according to the electoral law on
                                February 2nd some announcement may be made this week.</p>
                            <p>Two Vickers vespa [<hi rend="italic">bombing?</hi>] planes have
                                reached Santa Cruz and will probably go on to Puerto Suarez. Three
                                Breguets are flying south to the Pilcomayo but have not arrived.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hibbard</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>