<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Honduras ( (Lay))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d329</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">329</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-05-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-05-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="329"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">715.1715/366a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Honduras</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lay</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="84" xml:id="d329fn84">The same, <hi rend="italic">mutatis
                            mutandis</hi>, on the same date to the Minister in Nicaragua as
                        instruction No. 16.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-05-21">May 21,
                            1930</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department understands that the Governments
                    of Honduras and Nicaragua are now in substantial agreement with respect to the
                    method to be followed in adjusting the dispute which prevails with respect to a
                    portion of their common boundary. The procedure apparently contemplated by the
                    two Governments embraces the signing <pb facs="0442" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/>
                    of a protocol of agreement, based upon the award of the King of Spain and
                    providing for the appointment of a commission of engineers, to be formed of one
                    Honduran engineer and one Nicaraguan engineer and to be presided over by an
                    American engineer, who shall act as President.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as both Governments have expressed the desire that the Government of the
                    United States shall thus cooperate in the settlement of the difficulty, the
                    Department is prepared, if such action would be agreeable to the two Governments
                    concerned, to lend its further cooperation by authorizing the American
                    representatives at Tegucigalpa and Managua to collaborate in the preparation of
                    the protocol of agreement.</p>
                <p>A similar instruction is being addressed to the American Minister at Managua.
                    Upon its receipt he will determine whether it is opportune and appropriate to
                    undertake the action it contemplates and, if so, he will inform you of that fact
                    and inquire whether the situation at Tegucigalpa likewise is propitious for the
                    initiation of similar negotiations. When your respective Legations are in
                    agreement as to the advisability of opening negotiations and the date upon which
                    they shall be initiated and it has been ascertained by informal inquiry of both
                    Governments that the assistance of this Government in the elaboration of the
                    protocol of agreement would be acceptable, you may then submit the following
                    general outline of the protocol of agreement for consideration, stating that
                    similar action is being taken by the American Legation at Managua: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Whereas, the Governments of the Republics of Honduras and Nicaragua are
                            desirous of strengthening the fraternal ties of friendship which have
                            traditionally bound them, through the removal of the only obstacle to
                            complete harmony which now exists;</p>
                        <p>“And whereas on December 23, 1906, His Majesty the King of Spain rendered
                            an arbitral award designating the boundary line between the two
                            Republics from the Atlantic to the Pass of Teotecacinte (the remainder
                            of the line, from the Pass of Teotecacinte to the Gulf of Fonseca having
                            been definitively accepted by both Governments);</p>
                        <p rend="center">It is hereby agreed: <list>
                                <item>“1. The Governments of Honduras and Nicaragua mutually pledge
                                    their acceptance of the award of the King of Spain as handed
                                    down by him on December 23, 1906;</item>
                                <item>“2. The Governments of Honduras and Nicaragua hereby
                                    unconditionally agree that the delineation of the boundary
                                    determined by the award of the King of Spain, to which the
                                    preceding article refers, shall be entrusted to a Joint
                                    Commission, consisting of an engineer appointed by each
                                    Government and presided over by an American engineer designated
                                    by the Government of the United States of America;</item>
                                <item>“3. The Governments of Honduras and Nicaragua agree that the
                                    Commission of engineers described in the preceding article shall
                                    have <pb facs="0443" n="363" xml:id="pg_363"/> full authority to
                                    establish the boundary line between the two Republics from the
                                    Atlantic Ocean to the Pass of Teotecacinte, in accordance with
                                    the award of the King of Spain, establishing that line at points
                                    where the award of the King of Spain may require clarification
                                    and interpreting the meaning of the award in such instances as
                                    its meaning may not be clear;</item>
                                <item>“4. In the event that the two Commissioners cannot reach an
                                    agreement, the President of the Commission shall render a
                                    decision which shall be final; and</item>
                                <item>“5. The Governments of Honduras and Nicaragua agree that the
                                    decisions, findings, and recommendations of the Joint Boundary
                                    Commission hereinbefore mentioned shall be accepted as final and
                                    without appeal, and that the boundary line as laid down by the
                                    Joint Commission shall be accepted by both Governments as their
                                    true and definitive common frontier.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Should alterations in the protocol be suggested, you should bear in mind that the
                    essential points of agreement are that the Commission shall be established, that
                    it shall function under the award of the King of Spain, and that its decisions
                    and demarcation of the line shall be accepted by both Governments as final.</p>
                <p>This Government would view with gratification the early settlement of this
                    dispute, and it is desired that you report frequently and fully the progress of
                    your representations.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis White</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
