<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Bolivia ( (Hibbard) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-05-29T17:32:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-05-29T17:32:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-05-29T17:32:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-05-29T17:32:00-05:00" n="412"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">824.00/496: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hibbard</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">La Paz</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-05-29T18:00:00-04:32"
                            >May 29, 1930—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 30—2:25 p.m.<note n="2" xml:id="d412fn2">Telegram in two
                            sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>32. My telegram No. 31.<note n="3" xml:id="d412fn3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                    </note> I have received the following note from the Minister of Foreign
                    Affairs.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“La Paz, May 28, 1930.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Chargé d’Affaires: The decree, copy of which I have the honor to enclose
                        herewith, will inform you that today His Excellency, the President of the
                        Republic, Dr. Hernando Siles, has resigned his high constitutional office
                        and that the Cabinet (Council of Ministers) has assumed the functions of the
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>I also have the honor to inform you that while the National Convention is
                        being assembled, the Council of Ministers will continue the functions of the
                        Executive power in all normality, respecting international conventions and
                        all obligations of the state.</p>
                    <p>Requesting you to be so kind as to inform your Government of the contents of
                        this note, I am pleased to offer you the assurance of my high consideration.
                        Signed F. Vega.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0496" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/>
                    <p rend="center">Decree.</p>
                    <p>“The Council of Ministers considering:</p>
                    <p>That the President of the Republic, Dr. Hernando Siles, basing his opinion on
                        the grave condition of the state and desiring to consolidate the
                        institutionary of the country, has resigned today irrevocably his high
                        office, thus preventing himself from intervening in the solution of the
                        political problem raised by parliamentary and popular manifestations
                        soliciting his continuance in the Government;</p>
                    <p>That it is necessary to normalize the institutional progress of the Republic,
                        giving the Nation the possibility of resolving its own problems by itself
                        with high civic spirit;</p>
                    <p>That the majority of the Nation has manifested the urgent necessity of
                        proceeding with the constitutional reform for which it is indispensable to
                        have recourse to the popular will, fountainhead of sovereignty;</p>
                    <p>That the ordinary National Congress is not endowed with sufficient power to
                        resolve the existing problems nor to fix the standard conducive to the
                        normalization of the institutional life of the Republic;</p>
                    <p>That the public administration cannot remain unattended without producing
                        grave disorder and jeopardizing the stability of the Nation;</p>
                    <p>That the merely transitory functions imposed upon the Council of Ministers,
                        by the exceptional circumstances of the present time, should last only for
                        the time strictly necessary to consult the desire of the country, meanwhile
                        [directing] the administration and fulfilling the external obligations which
                        the Republic has incurred,</p>
                    <p>Decrees: <list>
                            <item>Article 1. The Council of Ministers assumes the functions of the
                                Executive power.</item>
                            <item>Article 2. The conventional elections are convoked for Sunday,
                                June 29th, next, for the purpose of electing Senators and Deputies
                                in the entire Republic, who will jointly constitute the National
                                Convention.</item>
                            <item>Article 3. The National Convention will begin its functions on
                                July 28 of this year, in the city of La Paz, and will proceed
                                immediately to resolve the political problem and to consider the
                                constitutional reforms which may be proposed. Their work finished as
                                members of the convention, the Senators and Deputies will exercise
                                the functions of the ordinary Legislative power until they complete
                                their term of office.</item>
                            <item>Article 4. A supplementary decree will regulate the
                                elections.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Done in the Palace of Government in the city of La Paz, this 28th day of May
                        1930. Signed G. Antelo Araúz, Minister [of Government] and Justice; F. Vega,
                        Minister for Foreign Affairs and Worship (ad interim) and War; F. Mercado,
                        Minister of Hacienda; J. Aguirre Achá, Minister of Public Instruction;
                        Lieutenant Colonel Toro, Minister of Fomento and Communications; Colonel
                        Banzer, Minister of Agriculture and Colonization.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>I have acknowledged the receipt of this note, stating that in accordance with the
                    request contained therein I have informed my Government of its contents.</p>
                <pb facs="0497" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/>
                <p>This afternoon there was a meeting of the diplomatic corps to discuss what
                    attitude should be taken toward the new Government. Three points were raised: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Whether, in view of the fact that this Government is in reality a
                            continuation of President Siles’ administration although
                            unconstitutional, relations should not be continued normally with the
                            exception of treaty negotiations.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Whether if relations are continued normally this does not give tacit
                            recognition to an unconstitutional government which might prove
                            embarrassing later, particularly as there is a grave possibility that
                            the power may be seized by an individual before the Constituent Assembly
                            meets.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Whether a formal act of recognition should be made and if so to whom
                            should it be addressed.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The consensus of opinion was that nothing should be done which would embarrass
                    the present administration and that it was therefore desirable to have
                    uniformity of action by all representatives. However no one was prepared to
                    commit his Government and it was decided that each should cable for
                    instructions. I therefore respectfully request instructions as soon as possible
                    as there will be another meeting of the corps on Monday afternoon in view of the
                    arrival of the new Minister for Foreign Affairs.</p>
                <p>As far as American interests are concerned the question of recognition has
                    importance as the bankers must decide whether they will permit this Government
                    to draw on funds now deposited in New York for future payments on the service of
                    the Bolivian external debt.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hibbard</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
