<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-04-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="571" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d571">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.7442/44</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of Informal Canadian–United States
                                Conference on Aviation Radio Held at U. S. Customs House, New York
                                City, April 10–11, 1930</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" from="1930-04-10" to="1930-04-11" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">April 10–11, 1930</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center">First Meeting</p>
                        <p>The meeting opened at 10:45 A.M.</p>
                        <p>The following persons were present:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Representing Canada:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Commander C. P. Edwards, Director of Radio Telegraph Branch,
                                    Department of Marine,</item>
                                <item>Mr. G. C. W. Browne, Chief Inspector, Radio Telegraph Branch,
                                    Department of Marine,</item>
                                <item>Major W. A. Steel, Royal Canadian Signals, Department of
                                    National Defense,</item>
                                <item>Captain W. L. Laurie, Royal Canadian Signals, Department of
                                    National Defense.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Representing the United States:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Commissioner W. D. L. Starbuck, Federal Radio
                                    Commission,</item>
                                <item>Colonel Clarence M. Young, Assistant Secretary of
                                    Commerce,</item>
                                <item>Mr. W. R. Vallance, Assistant Solicitor, State
                                    Department,</item>
                                <item>Captain F. C. Hingsburg, Chief Engineer, Airways Division,
                                    Department of Commerce,</item>
                                <pb facs="0616" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                                <item>Dr. C. B. Jolliffe, Chief Engineer, Federal Radio
                                    Commission,</item>
                                <item>Mr. Gerald C. Gross, Engineer, Federal Radio
                                    Commission.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Commissioner Starbuck presided over the meeting as chairman of the host
                            delegation. He welcomed the representatives present and called attention
                            to the fact that it seemed to be the unanimous desire to make this
                            conference a purely informative one for the mutual exchange of ideas
                            between the representatives of aviation radio from both countries
                            present.</p>
                        <p>He then suggested that Colonel Young, Assistant Secretary of Commerce for
                            Aeronautics, describe the purpose of the conference.</p>
                        <p>Colonel Young pointed out that the interests of the United States and
                            Canada in aviation radio are of the same character, and stated that
                            aviation radio falls naturally into two distinct classifications:—1.
                            Radio navigation aids to aircraft; 2. Radio communication with
                            aircraft.</p>
                        <p>Commander Edwards then stated that all aviation services in Canada, both
                            civil and military, come under the Department of National Defense, while
                            the allocation of frequencies comes under the jurisdiction of the
                            Department of Marine. Representatives of both Departments were included
                            in the Canadian group present. He suggested that the logical procedure
                            for the conference might be to have the system now being followed in the
                            United States outlined, following which the Canadian representatives
                            could describe the procedure now being followed in Canada, and after
                            this mutual exchange of information some satisfactory arrangement might
                            be worked out.</p>
                        <p>At the suggestion of the Chairman, Captain Hingsburg then proceeded to
                            describe the present system of radio aids to air navigation being
                            followed in the United States.</p>
                        <p>Starting with the teletype circuits which are being extended over United
                            States Civil Airways, he described the operation of these circuits and
                            stated that data are being collected and brought up to the minute every
                            fifteen minutes so that a pilot can depend upon regular weather
                            broadcasts at regular periods. In addition to the collection and
                            dissemination of weather information, the same teletype circuits are
                            used for message and other dispatch work.</p>
                        <p>The information collected by the teletype circuits is broadcast on
                            standardized 2 K W transmitting sets operating in the frequency band
                            237–350 kc.</p>
                        <p>Transmitting sets used for radio beacon work operating most of the time
                            are only interrupted for the periodic weather broadcasts. These
                            broadcasts last usually only three minutes so that the interruption to
                            the beacon service will not be long.</p>
                        <p>The present beacon system makes use of the aural signal, but in view of
                            the development of the visual beacon it is planned to install a <pb facs="0617" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> double beacon at one of the
                            stations along the airways, namely Bellefonte, Pennsylvania, so that
                            practical tests on both systems may be carried on. There are at present
                            nine aural beacons in operation and it is planned by next summer to have
                            thirty-five beacons of the aural type operating.</p>
                        <p>Commander Edwards then pointed out that the International Radio
                                Convention<note n="40a" xml:id="d571fn40a">Signed at Washington,
                                November 25, 1927, <ref target="frus1927v01#pg_288"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1927, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 288</ref>.</note> applies only
                            to international service, and that the convention provides that for
                            regional groups special arrangements may be made. For example, on the
                            North American continent if new arrangements appear to be desirable
                            between the United States, Canada, Mexico and other nations, such
                            arrangements may well be made by a Regional Agreement. Commander Edwards
                            then asked concerning the tie-up between marine and aviation
                            beacons.</p>
                        <p>Captain Hingsburg replied that in this country the services were handled
                            in the same department and were so arranged as to avoid interference. In
                            all cases where interference had been found it has been adjusted by the
                            proper distance separation. He further stated that some thought had been
                            given to the question of having one additional frequency in the same
                            general band for communication messages to planes which messages might
                            be too long to interrupt the regular beacon service. At Commander
                            Edwards’ inquiry Captain Hingsburg explained that the band referred to
                            was from 237 to 350 kilocycles.</p>
                        <p>Major Steel then asked as to how planes would be taken care of from
                            stations using both the visual and aural systems, and Captain Hingsburg
                            replied that only one station at present was proposed for such joint
                            testing and that both services would be made available.</p>
                        <p>Commissioner Starbuck then suggested that the only object of the
                            conference is to provide safe and reliable communication for aircraft in
                            flight and said that undoubtedly the conference will find itself in
                            general agreement. He then asked Mr. Gross to describe the radio
                            communication system now being followed in the United States.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Gross then described in detail the aviation plan adopted by the
                            Federal Radio Commission in cooperation with other United States
                            governmental departments and commercial aviation companies. The plan was
                            distributed to the representatives present and appears as Annex A<note n="41" xml:id="d571fn41">Not printed.</note> to these minutes. He
                            pointed out that the plan was intended to be flexible and had been
                            modified from time to time to suit the requirements of the growing art.
                            There are undoubtedly a number of ways in which the aviation plan can be
                            improved and it is proposed to improve and revise it gradually as more
                            and more practical operating data become available. After some general
                            discussion on this aviation plan, the conference adjourned for lunch at
                            1 p.m.</p>
                        <pb facs="0618" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/>
                        <p>The meeting reconvened after lunch. Major Steel then described the
                            Canadian system of aviation radio, pointing out that most of the
                            airplane companies are subsidized by air mail contracts. The air mail
                            route starts from Halifax and runs through to Windsor. At Windsor the
                            mail is at present transferred through St. Paul and Minneapolis by
                            American companies to Winnipeg. From Winnipeg the mail is carried by
                            Canadian companies to Vancouver.</p>
                        <p>It is proposed that planes may leave Montreal and proceed through Ottawa
                            to Sudbury. From Sudbury they would travel along the north shore of Lake
                            Superior to Winnipeg. The other main route is the one flying into
                            northern Canada from Edmonton as shown on the attached map<note n="41a" xml:id="d571fn41a">Not reproduced.</note> from opposite page 40 of
                            the 1928 Canadian Aviation Report. In general the radio service is
                            conducted in Canada on 1200 meters (250 kc). The information is
                            collected by teletype and broadcast by radio.</p>
                        <p>In general the system is similar in nature to that used in the United
                            States with the difference that one transmitter is used jointly for
                            aural beacon service, visual beacon service or voice.</p>
                        <p>Three stations are now operating on the above system, in Montreal,
                            Toronto and Winnipeg. It is planned to put eight more into service by
                            next summer.</p>
                        <p>After some discussion on the merits of the visual vs. the aural beacon,
                            Major Steel stated that the Canadian authorities are strongly in favor
                            of the visual beacon and intend using that system.</p>
                        <p>Commander Edwards suggested that a technical committee be appointed to
                            consider the question of how best to link the systems operated by both
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>During some discussion on receiving sets Major Steel pointed out that a
                            number of receivers today will cover the range from 850 to 1300 meters
                            (353 to 230 kc), and Captain Hingsburg stated that the best ratio on
                            frequency range is 2.5 or 2.0 to 1. Major Steel then stated that the
                            Canadian authorities do not propose to have communication traffic
                            carried on within bands used for beacon and weather service. It is
                            expected, however, to handle emergency messages of an urgent nature for
                            operating companies by broadcasts to the planes.</p>
                        <p>Major Steel further stated that it is proposed to carry on communication
                            services in entirely different bands but that 100 meters (3000 kc) is
                            entirely too long a wave for this work in Canada.</p>
                        <p>Commander Edwards then stated that the communication might perhaps be in
                            the band around 5000 kc. Itinerant plane communication service is
                            especially important in Canada, but due to the more northerly latitudes
                            higher frequencies are necessary.</p>
                        <p>Major Steel then suggested that the harmonic relationship might <pb facs="0619" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/> be followed and that if the
                            United States used around 3000 kc, Canada might use a frequency in the
                            neighborhood of 6000 kc. He also stated that the Canadian government
                            contemplated a series of stations from Halifax to Vancouver to be
                            assigned one frequency throughout the chain. Commander Edwards then
                            stated that with reference to his previous suggestion it might be
                            desirable to appoint a technical committee to study this question and
                            formulate some general statements of policy, such committee to report to
                            the main conference at 2 P.M., Friday, April 11.</p>
                        <p>Without objection the suggestion was carried and the following committee
                            was designated for this work: <list>
                                <item>Major Steel</item>
                                <item>Captain Laurie</item>
                                <item>Mr. Browne</item>
                                <item>Captain Hingsburg</item>
                                <item>Dr. Jolliffe</item>
                                <item>Mr. Gross</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The Committee arranged to meet at 8:30 P.M. Thursday, April 10, and the
                            following morning if necessary.</p>
                        <p>The conference then adjourned at 5:45 P.M.</p>
                        <p rend="center">Second Meeting</p>
                        <p>The second and last meeting of the Conference opened at 2 P.M. April 11,
                            1930.</p>
                        <p>The following persons were present:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Representing Canada:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Commander C. P. Edwards, Director of Radio Telegraph Branch,
                                    Department of Marine,</item>
                                <item>Mr. G. C. W. Browne, Chief Inspector, Radio Telegraph Branch,
                                    Department of Marine,</item>
                                <item>Major W. A. Steel, Royal Canadian Signals, Department of
                                    National Defense,</item>
                                <item>Captain W. L. Laurie, Royal Canadian Signals, Department of
                                    National Defense.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Representing the United States:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Commissioner W. D. L. Starbuck, Federal Radio
                                    Commission,</item>
                                <item>Captain F. C. Hingsburg, Chief Engineer, Airways Division,
                                    Department of Commerce.</item>
                                <item>Dr. C. B. Jolliffe, Chief Engineer, Federal Radio
                                    Commission,</item>
                                <item>Mr. Gerald C. Gross, Engineer, Federal Radio
                                    Commission.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Commissioner Starbuck presided. He suggested that the report of the
                            Technical Committee which met Thursday night and Friday morning be read
                            and discussed. Each item of the report was considered separately and
                            discussed at length, and some improvements in the <pb facs="0620" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/> language of the suggested texts were made.
                            The corrected report was adopted unanimously. This appears as Annex 1 to
                            these minutes.</p>
                        <p>Commander Edwards then brought up the question of priority of marine over
                            aviation beacons in the band 285–350 kc. and considerable discussion
                            took place. After several resolutions touching on the subject had been
                            presented and considered it was decided that no formal resolution should
                            be adopted on this point.</p>
                        <p>The minutes of the first meeting were then read and after some
                            corrections had been made were adopted.</p>
                        <p>At 6 P.M. the conference adjourned sine die.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Annex 1]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Informal Canadian-U. S. Aviation Radio
                                    Conference</hi></head>
                            <p>The coordination of airways communications and radio aids to air
                                navigation in Canada and the United States is desirable, and the
                                following principles are proposed as a guide in the operation of
                                these systems.</p>
                            <p>The conference recommends that the two Governments study these
                                principles and attempt to apply them to their respective systems and
                                that by correspondence and future conferences these principles be
                                further developed and closer coordination obtained.</p>
                            <p>It is further recommended that: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The International Air Calling Frequency 333 kc. be not
                                        required regionally for aircraft or aeronautical stations in
                                        Canada or the United States.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>It be recognized that a frequency separation of 6 kc. is
                                        ordinarily sufficient between stations operating radio range
                                        beacon and radio telephone services.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>A minimum distance of 750 miles between radio beacon
                                        stations operating on the same frequency is desirable. It is
                                        recommended that this separation be maintained between
                                        nations, although in some cases it may be necessary to
                                        reduce the separation within the interior of either
                                        country.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The following frequencies: <list>
                                            <item>237</item>
                                            <item>240</item>
                                            <item>248</item>
                                            <item>278 kc.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>out of the band 194–284 kc. be reserved regionally for air
                                        services.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The following frequencies shall remain free from
                                        assignments in the United States within 750 miles of
                                        Canadian airways radio stations: <list>
                                            <item>248</item>
                                            <item>290</item>
                                            <item>296</item>
                                            <item>326</item>
                                            <item>332 kc.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>In addition, no further assignments in the United States
                                        should be <pb facs="0621" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/> made on
                                        the following frequencies within 750 miles of Canadian
                                        airways radio stations: <list>
                                            <item>240</item>
                                            <item>314 kc.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>The following frequencies shall remain free from
                                        assignments in Canada within 750 miles of United States
                                        airways radio stations: <list>
                                            <item>254</item>
                                            <item>260</item>
                                            <item>266</item>
                                            <item>272</item>
                                            <item>284</item>
                                            <item>302</item>
                                            <item>308</item>
                                            <item>320</item>
                                            <item>338</item>
                                            <item>344</item>
                                            <item>350</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>The frequency 278 kc. should be reserved primarily for low
                                        power airport use.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>One frequency, approximately 237 kc. shall be reserved for
                                        emergency messages from ground stations to aircraft in cases
                                        where such messages might interfere with the regular airways
                                        beacon service.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>The following frequencies should be reserved for Canadian
                                        stations operating along the Canadian Transcontinental
                                        Airways from Halifax to Vancouver: <list>
                                            <item>3492</item>
                                            <item>5630 kc</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>The United States authorities will discuss with aviation
                                        companies operating between Chicago, Minneapolis, and St.
                                        Paul a change of frequencies from those now specified in the
                                        U. S. Aviation Plan for the Green Chain to the Red Chain
                                        frequencies in order that Canadian planes flying from
                                        Winnipeg to Minneapolis and St. Paul will be able to have
                                        closer frequency coordination.</item>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item>The United States will continue to use 3106 kc. as a
                                        national calling frequency and Canada will use the frequency
                                        5630 kc. for the same purpose, since the experience gained
                                        to date in the United States and Canada would indicate that
                                        the common calling frequency selected in the United States
                                        might not be equally suitable in Canada.</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>