<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="158" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                        <head>158. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName type="from">Bundy</persName>) to Secretary
                            of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d158fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Bundy Files, Management. Personal and
                                Confidential.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-12-01">December 1, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>On Sunday you asked me for a memorandum on members of my professional
                            staff, and here it is.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">1. Deputies</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>My principal deputy is <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Robert
                                Komer</persName> (age 43), who has been here for nearly five years.
                            Before that he worked in the Central Intelligence Agency in intelligence
                            evaluation. He is a graduate of Harvard College and the Harvard Business
                            School, and served in the Army in World War II. You know Komer well
                            enough to make your own judgment, I am sure. To me he has been an
                            invaluable colleague. He is able, energetic, quick and highly
                            knowledgeable. While he presses his point of view with energy, he is
                            disciplined in the execution of decisions, whether or not they accord
                            with his recommendations. I believe him to be, in many ways, the most
                            suitable candidate to succeed me here, and I think that if he were the
                            principal officer, he would accept the need for insuring fair and
                            complete presentation of other points of view than his own. It is indeed
                            precisely because of his alertness and reliability in moments of tension
                            and uncertainty that I initially recommended him to the President for
                            appointment as my Deputy. He is a man upon whom we can rely in times
                            when I am out of town or otherwise unavailable.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Francis Bator</persName> (age 40) is my
                            deputy for economics. He came here in early 1964, after a year as
                            consultant to <persName>David Bell</persName> in <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>. Before that, he was an associate professor of
                            Economics at MIT, where he did his graduate work after taking his
                            Bachelor’s degree at Harvard. I think <pb facs="0401" n="367" xml:id="pg_367"/> him to be the most gifted analytical student of
                            international economics now working effectively in the bureaucracy. He
                            has played a quite critical role in all of our balance of payments work.
                            In addition, since the departure of <persName corresp="#p_KD4">David
                                Klein</persName>, he has been the principal staff officer here for
                            European problems, and has established close relations with <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">John Leddy</persName> and John McNaughton. I think
                            you will find that <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George Ball</persName>
                            knows him well, and thinks highly of him. <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Bator</persName> does not have the experience or the breadth of
                            political knowledge to take over the top job here, and in some ways he
                            might be still more valuable to the government in a sub-Cabinet post in
                            the Treasury. As a practical matter, he does extremely good work where
                            he is, and the President has found him quick and helpful in a number of
                            important matters.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">2. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> veterans</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Executive Secretary of the National Security Council, as you know, is
                                <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley Smith</persName> (age 54), and I
                            think he would like to leave his present job, in good time. The <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> as a formal council has had even less
                            to do under President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>
                            than it did under President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>. But <persName>Smith</persName> is not sure just
                            where he would want to go if he does leave. I was wrong in telling you
                            the other day that he would be ready now for a chance at an Embassy. As
                            you suspected, his wife’s architectural undertakings make such a move
                            impractical in the near future. <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley
                                Smith</persName> is one of the most experienced and loyal of
                            professional bureaucrats. He has chosen not to develop a taste for
                            active participation in the making of policy, but he runs a clean,
                            thorough, and highly knowledgeable shop.</p>
                        <p>Two other staff members have great seniority on the National Security
                            Council staff—(1) Charles Johnson, age 53, who is the liaison officer
                            for space and telecommunications, and some parts of atomic energy; and
                            (2) Russell Ash (age 51), who spends most of his time supporting
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJP1">Patrick Coyne</persName> in the staff
                            work for the President’s Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board, but also
                            has responsibility for our internal security. These two men have
                            long-standing civil service status within the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>. They are both loyal public servants of real ability.
                            Neither of them is likely to move to substantially higher
                            responsibilities, as far as I can tell.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">3. Far East</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The next senior member of my staff is <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Chester
                                Cooper</persName> (age 48), who works on Far Eastern affairs. He
                            came to us in 1964 from <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, where he
                            ranked just after <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Ray Cline</persName> on
                            the “open” side of the house. He has done extraordinarily devoted and
                            useful work here, but both he and I agree that, for reasons which are
                            hard to explain, his service has not been quite up to either his hopes
                            or mine. I believe he intends presently to seek an academic leave of
                            absence from the Central Intelligence Agency, <pb facs="0402" n="368" xml:id="pg_368"/> and I believe that this arrangement would be very
                            much in his interest and also in ours. I think the timing of this move
                            can be adjusted so that my successor would have the opportunity which he
                            deserves to pick his own principal Far Eastern staff officer. My
                            instinct would be to concert a choice with my brother Bill.</p>
                        <p>Under <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName>, in Far Eastern
                            affairs, there are three more junior staff officers: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Mr. James Thomson (age 34), <gloss target="#t_FSR1">FSR</gloss>-3, came to us from the Far Eastern bureau two
                                    years ago. He was brought into the Department by Chester Bowles,
                                    and is a gifted young man, but not perfectly suited to the
                                    bureaucracy. My hunch is that in due course he should go back to
                                    academic life (he has received regular feelers from Yale, where
                                    he did his graduate work in Chinese).</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Don W. Ropa (age 38), <gloss target="#t_GS1">GS</gloss>-14,
                                    came to us from <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> only last
                                    July when the expanding struggle in Vietnam placed heavier
                                    requirements of coordination upon <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName>’s office. Ropa has shown great energy and
                                    determination, and I think my successor would probably wish to
                                    keep him here, with a more senior officer, after <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName>’s departure. If not, I
                                    am equally confident that the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> would be glad to get him back.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Miss Ruth Nicalo is a veteran of the National Security Council
                                    staff, and I am ashamed to have to say that I do not know much
                                    about her work, although I know she has been very helpful to a
                                    number of my colleagues in the Executive Office Building.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">4. Middle East and Africa</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Under <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> in Middle Eastern and
                            African affairs are two able young men: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>One is Hal H. Saunders (age 35), a <gloss target="#t_GS1">GS</gloss>-13, who came to us three years ago from <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. He is unusually thoughtful and
                                    hard-working, and I think he has the confidence and trust of the
                                    working levels in all departments. Where Komer goes Saunders is
                                    likely to go, and he is an admirable staff assistant to his able
                                    boss.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Ulric Haynes (age 34), <gloss target="#t_FSR1">FSR</gloss>-4,
                                    handles African affairs. He is the ablest young Negro I have met
                                    in ten years of fairly constant looking. He has both judgment
                                    and energy. He is also unusually clear-headed about African
                                    affairs. He came to the Department from the Ford Foundation, and
                                    an intelligent Foundation executive might well try to get him
                                    back.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">5. Economic and European Affairs</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Under <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Francis Bator</persName> in economic
                            and European affairs is Edward K. Hamilton (age 26), <gloss target="#t_GS1">GS</gloss>-13. <persName corresp="#p_HEK1">Hamilton</persName> came to us from the Budget Bureau, where he
                            established an extraordinary reputation as the most effective young man
                            to join that bureau in recent years. He has done <pb facs="0403" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/> outstanding work here, and while his life has been
                            clouded in recent months by family troubles, I feel confident that he
                            will go on to make a record as one of the best public servants of his
                            generation. If for any reason he should decide to leave the government,
                            I am equally confident that he would succeed in private life.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">6. Latin American Affairs</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Our Latin American affairs are handled by William Bowdler (age 41), an
                                <gloss target="#t_FSO1">FSO</gloss> 2. Bowdler was picked out by
                            Jack Vaughn, and has done genuinely outstanding work over here. He
                            handles the entire Latin American account, and he does it in the closest
                            cooperation with <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>. I see no reason
                            why he should not continue sympathetically and effectively in the same
                            work in the future.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">7. Disarmament and Technology</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I get great support here from the half-time service of Spurgeon Keeny,
                            who divides his time between Don Hornig’s office and mine. Keeny is a
                            really extraordinary public servant, and almost nothing happens in this
                            complex field that he does not hear about from his wide circle of
                            trusted colleagues in every department. He tends to know about sensitive
                            new developments in weaponry before Cy Vance and Bob McNamara, and he
                            knows about tricky issues in technical intelligence before Helms and
                            Raborn. But he is much more than a source of information-he also has
                            good judgment and broad experience in his subject. If he did not look
                            like an undergraduate, I think he would already be emerging into the
                            level of Presidential appointments.</p>
                        <p>8. Finally, I should mention two special liaison officers: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JP6">Peter Jessup</persName> (age
                                    45), who handles the staff work for our supervision of covert
                                    intelligence. He came from the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and he, or an officer like him, should be here
                                    as long as the 303 Committee continues. <persName corresp="#p_JP6">Jessup</persName> does this work with great
                                    skill and sense.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Colonel Richard Bowman (age 39) is our liaison officer with
                                    the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>. He is an able and
                                    hard-working officer, even if he sometimes has trouble in
                                    separating his Air Force allegiance from his staff obligations
                                    here.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>9. And last of all, I should mention my personal assistant, Gordon Chase
                            (age 33), <gloss target="#t_GS1">GS</gloss>-15, although he is leaving
                            any day now to accept a double promotion in <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_CG4">Chase</persName> came to us
                            from the Foreign Service and has proved himself to be fully first-rate
                            as a staff assistant. He now wants a chance to spread his wings in a job
                            with more direct responsibility, and he has fully earned it.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">
                                    <hi rend="strong">McGeorge Bundy</hi>
                                </persName><note n="2" xml:id="d158fn2">Printed from a copy that
                                    bears this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>