<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>164. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d164</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">164</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec5kKeA0KbYzTwuY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="covert-actions">Covert actions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="164" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d164">
                <head>164. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On the morning of March 31, 1966, Deputy Special Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Francis Bator</persName> drafted a
                    memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Bill Moyers</persName>, the
                    President’s Press Secretary, in which he outlined the points <persName
                        corresp="#p_MBD1">Moyers</persName> might want to make at a National
                    Security Council staff meeting scheduled for noon that day, including the fact
                    that “as long as [there was] no final appointment of new Special Assistant for
                    National Security, <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Moyers</persName> will act in
                    that capacity.” (Johnson Library, Bator Papers, Chron File) The meeting,
                    however, was not held.</p>
                <p>At a news conference that began at 12:30 p.m. March 31, the President announced
                    that he was naming <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt W. Rostow</persName>, who
                    had served since late 1961 as Counselor for the Department of State and Chairman
                    of its Policy Planning Council, as Special Assistant to the President. The
                    appointment became effective the next day. The President indicated that
                        <persName>Rostow</persName> would “come to the White House to work
                    principally, but not necessarily exclusively, in the field of foreign policy. I
                    will especially look to him for the development of long-range plans in that
                    field, as well as special coordination of Latin American development.” When
                    asked by a reporter whether it could be said that <persName>Rostow</persName>
                    would “take over all or many of the duties and assignments handled by <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>,” the President responded: “it
                    could be, but that would be inaccurate. It would not be true. Most of the men
                    play any position here. We hope—I hope Mr. <persName>Rostow</persName> can. Part
                    of the work Mr. Bundy did we will say will now be done by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName>. Some of the work Mr. Bundy did is now
                    being done by <persName corresp="#p_VJJ1">Jack Valenti</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_MBD1">Bill Moyers</persName>.” For text, see <hi rend="italic"
                        >Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName
                            corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>, 1965</hi>, Book I, pages
                    384–392. Within 4 days of appointing Rostow, the President designated both him
                    and <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Moyers</persName> as Bundy’s replacement on the
                    National Security Council’s 303 Committee, which reviewed and approved covert
                    actions (see <ref target="#d249">Document 249</ref> and <ref target="#d249fn4"
                        >footnote 4</ref> thereto). However, <persName corresp="#p_MBD1"
                        >Moyers</persName> attended only one 303 Committee meeting as a regular
                    member, while <persName>Rostow</persName> attended regularly. (National Security
                    Council, Special Group/303 Committee Files, Minutes)</p>
                <p>In reporting <persName>Rostow</persName>’s appointment in its April 1 issue, <hi
                        rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> stated that the President seemed
                    “reluctant to put in the hands of one man the kind of power within Government
                    that Mr. Bundy had. In effect, Mr. Bundy created within the White House a little
                    State Department that rode herd on many aspects of foreign policy. The President
                    apparently intends to shift many of the policy-making aspects of the post back
                    to the State Department, using a number of men inside the White House as
                    personal advisers to him on foreign affairs.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
