<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-05-07T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-05-07T14:00:00-05:00" n="296" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d296">
                    <head>296. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Mission to the United Nations</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d296fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                            Security File, Country File, United Nations, Article 19, Vol 1.
                            Confidential; Limdis. Drafted by Pelcovits and Jackson on May 6; cleared
                            in <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>,
                                <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SOV1">SOV</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_CH4">Cleveland</persName>. Repeated to London, Moscow,
                            and Geneva for Gardner.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-05-07T15:00:00-04:00">May 7, 1964, 3 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>2875. Ref: <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 3956.<note n="2" xml:id="d296fn2">Dated May 1; it set out proposals for future
                            discussions with the Soviets on Article 19 issues. (Ibid.)</note> Subj:
                        Soviet Position on Payment Arrears.</p>
                    <p>Re methods for handling arrears problem following is for your guidance in
                        talks with Sovs and Secretariat.</p>
                    <p>Dept concurs in general with line you propose take on arrears problem in
                        event Fedorenko makes another approach. Our understanding is that you do not
                        propose to take initiative for any meeting on this subject but are preparing
                        contingency position. In next talk, if Sovs renew request for proposals on
                        settling arrears you would adopt position <pb facs="0671" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/> described this telegram. Also, our understanding that
                        in any discussions with Sovs (or informal exchanges with Working Group) on
                        financing arrangements, you would adhere to line in comment B of <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> and guard against any weakening of
                        essential and inherent link between problem of future and satisfactory
                        settlement of arrears.</p>
                    <p>Following are points we suggest you emphasize in event next discussion with
                        Sovs turns to arrears problem: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We are flexible on accounting devices for settling arrears, and
                                will not make issue of modalities. We believe several possibilities
                                can be designed which would allow Sovs to settle their debts without
                                appearing to abandon their position. (<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. We suggest that you do not get into question of
                                how particular solution relates to Sov “principles”. We will try to
                                be accommodating but feel that question of whether settlement is
                                detrimental to their principles is matter basically for them and not
                                for us. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.)</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Particular devices are matter Sovs will want to work out with
                                Secretariat. We are willing to go along with any reasonable scheme
                                that does not violate Financial Regulations and is consistent with
                                Charter. We would not want to leave impression (para 3 of <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>) that we would be satisfied
                                with minimal payment just to avoid Article 19 hassle at this time.
                                This may well be outcome but we are concerned with satisfactory
                                settlement arrears and not simply resolution Article 19 issue. We
                                recognize that Sovs may be concerned about possibility that after
                                they have worked out apparently viable scheme with Secretariat we
                                might pull out rug from under them by rejecting it as
                                unsatisfactory. If this becomes apparent in conversations with
                                Fedorenko you are authorized to outline in very general terms
                                methods we might regard as satisfying requirements, using as
                                illustrations the consolidated account and ex gratia devices
                                described below. You should avoid, of course, being drawn into any
                                negotiations with Soviets on modalities to pay off arrearages. We
                                would like this aspect kept between <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. We want to avoid any suggestion
                                of US–<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> deal in which we appear
                                to abandon principle of financial integrity <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and wink at violation of financial rules to avoid
                                showdown. For this reason Dept believes you should not at this time
                                seek informal exchanges with Sovs, even at working level, on methods
                                of arrears payment. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Sovs may be concerned by prospect that after they pay they will
                                suffer prestige loss and that US public and press will picture
                                result as backdown from showdown. We cannot of course control what
                                others and press will say but believe that world will applaud
                                satisfactory outcome and that Sovs will not suffer from policy of
                                support for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. If satisfactory
                                arrangement can be worked out we would in public statements indicate
                                our gratification at settlement and would not seek to exploit it to
                                their detriment.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0672" n="638" xml:id="pg_638"/>
                    <p>In meantime, as suggested <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 3847,<note n="3" xml:id="d296fn3">Dated April 23. (National Archives and Records
                            Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 10–4)</note> you are authorized carry on consultations
                        with <persName corresp="#p_NCV1">Narasimhan</persName> and Turner,<note n="4" xml:id="d296fn4">Bruce R. Turner, Under Secretary, Office of the
                            Controller, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Secretariat.</note> on
                        assumption Sovs may be open some means paying debts and will seek
                        Secretariat advice. (We would want to avoid putting this in context that
                        would lend credibility to Sov complaint we are compromising confidential
                        nature of US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> discussions on future financing.) You can say we are
                        flexible on modalities Secretariat might work out with those in arrears,
                        including Sovs, in such fashion as not to compromise Financial
                        Regulations.</p>
                    <p>You should emphasize to Secretariat we believe they in position to discuss
                        proposals for alleviation immediate financial crisis in light <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Res 1877 (S–IV)<note n="5" xml:id="d296fn5">For text, see <hi rend="italic">United Nations Yearbook, 1963</hi>, pp.
                            575–576.</note> which “Appeals to Member States … to pay their arrears,
                        disregarding other factors …” and request <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> to work out with Members “arrangements as to the most
                        appropriate modalities within the letter and spirit of the Charter.” Key
                        elements of Res are payment “without prejudice to their respective
                        positions” and “possibility of payment by installments.”</p>
                    <p>Following are three illustrative devices that have been suggested and that
                        might meet problem. You can tell Secretariat we believe any of these offer
                        possibilities satisfactory financial settlement and might be politically
                        acceptable. All of them assume that Sovs pay Working Capital Fund
                        assessments and will not object to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        crediting their regular budget payments to cover arrears for items for which
                        payment withheld in 1963.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consolidated account</hi>. All arrears as of June 30,
                            1964 would be consolidated in a single account. Payments would then be
                            made by those in arrears not to separate accounts but to consolidated
                            one. Barton (Canada) has already surfaced this idea in his paper<note n="6" xml:id="d296fn6">Not found.</note> and Secretariat already
                            familiar with it. Idea would be that <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            would start International Cooperation Year with clean slate, with
                            arrears paid and new agreements in hand on authorizing and financing
                            future peacekeeping operations. We believe this might have atmospheric
                            possibilities in view of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>-<gloss target="#t_ICY1">ICY</gloss> letter July
                            15, 1963<note n="7" xml:id="d296fn7">Printed in Izvestia July 18,
                                1963.</note> pointing out <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            successes and calling for solution of important international questions
                            during the year. Consolidated account formula might also have particular
                            appeal to French. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. While
                            consolidation might raise some legal and perhaps accounting problems, we
                            believe such solution would readily obtain <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> endorsement. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                        <pb facs="0673" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ex gratia payment, covering total arrears, in single
                                contribution or in installments</hi>. Sovs would not pay on
                            peacekeeping accounts but make ex gratia contribution to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to mitigate <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>’s financial crisis and avoid situation which could
                            prejudice prospects for international understanding. Sovs might couple
                            this payment with reservation of their legal position. Sovs would not
                            attach such conditions to ex gratia contribution that comptroller unable
                            credit contributions to peacekeeping arrears. In subsequent years Sovs
                            would make further voluntary contributions in requisite sums and with
                            similar reservations.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Voluntary Payments for Peacekeeping (<gloss target="#t_UNOC1">UNOC</gloss> &amp; <gloss target="#t_UNEF1">UNEF</gloss>) Arrears</hi>. Sovs would make “voluntary” payment
                            to settle all or part of their peacekeeping arrears, probably after
                                <gloss target="#t_UNOC1">UNOC</gloss> withdraws, at the same time
                            reserving their legal position. Soviets might arrange pay in
                            installments if they wish.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Apart from tie to International Cooperation Year, Dept does not believe that,
                        at this stage of discussion with Sovs, linkage of arrears problem with other
                        issues, either in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> context or outside, is
                        likely be fruitful approach. We have already made logical tie with future of
                        peacekeeping and in that connection emphasized our common interest in
                        strengthening <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> peacekeeping capacity.</p>
                    <p>Department aware that in broader context in which this was in President’s
                        January 8 reply to Khrushchev, strengthening of peacekeeping encompasses
                        wide range of common objectives in putting limitations on nuclear weapons,
                        reducing risks of war, and moving toward effective disarmament. We will
                        continue to study possibilities of linkage to some of these broader
                        questions but believe that to bring any of them in now would be
                        premature.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>