<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>469. Memorandum From Samuel Belk of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the
                    National Security Council Staff to the President’s Special Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Bundy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recinJH9WjQoeQgtf" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002546"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Peacekeeping operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recfBXf5mApMtKJKj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peacekeeping-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002546" lcsh-match="exact">Peacekeeping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="469"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                <head>469. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_BSE1" type="from">Samuel
                        Belk</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName type="to"
                        >Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d469fn1">Source: Johnson
                        Library, National Security File, Komer Files, Cyprus. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-02-27">February 27, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Rundown of how we now stand on the matter of Cyprus in the Security
                        Council</item>
                </list>
                <p>At yesterday’s meeting, the Ivory Coast Delegate spoke in favor of our position;
                    Czechoslovakia took the Soviet line; Morocco wavered, although took the position
                    that the Security Council was not the proper forum to change a treaty; and the
                    Cyprus Delegate put the question straight to the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss>, Turkey and Greece as to their interpretation of Article 4 of
                    the Treaty of Guarantee. With regard to the latter, the Greek Delegate said
                    categorically that his country did not regard this Article as granting the right
                    of military intervention. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and Turkish
                    delegates did not respond to the question. (Please see the text of the Treaty of
                    Guarantee attached.)<note n="2" xml:id="d469fn2">Not attached; for text, see <hi
                            rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1959</hi>, pp.
                        765–775.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department, i.e., Abe Chayes and Co., have come up with nothing to indicate
                    that the US ever has taken a stand in the interpretation of the Treaty. The best
                    that has been offered is the difference between the language of the Treaty in
                    which “each of the three guaranteeing Powers <hi rend="italic">reserves</hi>
                    [italics mine]<note n="3" xml:id="d469fn3">Brackets in the source text.</note>
                    the right to “take action”, and the argument that this does not grant the right
                    to take action. Presumably this would depend on the particular interpretation
                    each Power would choose to give it. The Turks have made it clear that their
                    interpretation is that the Treaty grants the right to intervene.</p>
                <p>The Department is now in the process of drafting an instruction to <gloss
                        target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d469fn4">Telegram 2290 to New York, February 26. (National
                        Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–8
                            <gloss target="#t_Cyp1">CYP</gloss>)</note> to urge the Turks to steer
                    as clear of the language of the Treaty as possible in the Council; to insist
                    that it is not the proper forum to discuss the validity of existing treaties;
                    and that the purpose of the Council should be to restore peace and order in
                    Cyprus.</p>
                <p>As a backdrop of the Security Council’s consideration of the problem is the
                    possibility that the matter might get into the General Assembly. This would
                    happen in case there was a veto and as many as seven Council members (permanent
                    or non-permanent) voted to send it to the Assembly or, alternatively, if a
                    simple majority of the Assembly <pb facs="1036" n="1002" xml:id="pg_1002"/> (57)
                    voted to accept the problem in the Assembly. Should this happen, we would be in
                    a most awkward situation, with the whole issue of Article 19, financing and
                    Chirep suddenly placed before us. There is good reason to doubt that this will
                    happen. Although opinion is divided, there is reason to believe that the
                    Russians are not yet ready to face up to these problems in view of their
                    repeated statements that they would like to enter into bilateral negotiations
                    with the US on the matter of financing. Also, if the Russians cast a veto on
                    behalf of Makarios and allowed the matter to get into the <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss>, they would be acting counter to their often stated position
                    that the right place for peacekeeping operations is in the Security Council, not
                    in the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>There may be some hope in a draft resolution sponsored by the six non-members of
                    the Council which is now under discussion in New York. However, if Makarios
                    holds to his past position, he will reject it because of references to the
                    Treaty of Guarantee. On the other hand, there is reason to believe, from a
                    statement by the Cypriot Delegate to <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1"
                        >Stevenson</persName> yesterday, that the Cypriots may be concerned lest
                    they move too far in aligning themselves with the Soviet Union and, as a result,
                    might be moving toward some sort of compromise.</p>
                <p>The next Council meeting is tomorrow, when the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    and Turkey will be hard pressed to answer the Cypriot inquiry as to their
                    interpretation of the Treaty.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BSE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Samuel E. Belk</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d469fn5">Printed from a copy that bears this typewritten
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
