<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                        <head>76. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>During a telephone conversation between President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> that began at 5:11 p.m.
                            on May 27, 1966, the following discussion took place regarding a
                            replacement for Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Thomas Mann</persName>, who had indicated that he
                            planned to step down:</p>
                        <pb facs="0200" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/>
                        <p>President: “I really want a good new person in Mann’s place, but I
                            haven’t found one. What has been your thinking on it? Has it jelled any
                            more?”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>: “Well, I think the key
                            qualification for a man on that spot is someone who is utterly loyal to
                            you and to me. Now, in terms of running this Department and people
                            familiar with it and government and that kind of thing and on the inside
                            part of the job, I don’t think of anybody better than or even comparable
                            to Luke Battle. In terms of somebody who might help more on the public
                            side and with some of these liberal Senators, we might be able to better
                            that. This is one of the reasons I thought about our friend in the
                            Philippines, Bill Blair. I would be interested in the name Gene Rostow,
                            whose name has come up in different places.”</p>
                        <p>President: “I only saw that in a column. Who originated it?”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>: “I don’t know. I don’t know.
                            Since I saw it in a column, I suppose that somebody’s been talking about
                            it around town. Nobody’s spoken to me about it.”</p>
                        <p>President: “Nobody has to me.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>: “But George and I have
                            talked about recruiting this fellow for some time. He is an able fellow.
                            It wouldn’t have been too easy while <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt</persName> was over in this Department to have two brothers at
                            the top spots here, but he’s an extraordinary able fellow, <persName corresp="#p_DSP1">Dean</persName> of the Law School, you know, at
                            Yale. So that’s a new name and a fresh person here that would be, I
                            think, well received by a lot of people. And he’s helped us I think
                            generally on our foreign policy problems. But I think that’s something
                            that-now the other possibility is to just leave it open for a bit until
                            we feel out what you want to do about the number two spot and how that
                            shapes up.”</p>
                        <p>The President and <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> then
                            discussed candidates to replace <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George
                                Ball</persName> as Under Secretary of State. (Johnson Library,
                            Recordings and Transcripts, Recording of a Telephone Conversation
                            between Johnson and <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, Tape
                            66.15, Side B, <gloss target="#t_PNO1">PNO</gloss> 1) The portion of the
                            conversation printed here was prepared in the Office of the Historian
                            specifically for this volume.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>