<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Laukhuff––Reinstein Minutes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d103</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">103</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-04-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-04-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="103"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59 D 95, CF 103</note>
                <head>
                    <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Laukhuff</hi>
                    </persName>–<persName corresp="#p_REINSTEINJJ1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Reinstein</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d103fn1">The source text indicates that
                            <persName>Laukhuff</persName> was the drafter of these minutes on Mar.
                        17 and <persName corresp="#p_REINSTEINJJ1">Reinstein</persName> on Apr. 1.
                        Copies of these minutes were circulated in the Department of State as
                        document Ger–London MIN 9, Apr. 16, 1952.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-04-01">April 1,
                            1952</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Germany</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Financial Contribution to Defense</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> reported that a message
                    had been received from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCCLOYJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                    that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> accepted the
                    documents which had been <pb facs="0216" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/> agreed on by
                    the Foreign Ministers the previous evening with two minor amendments.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d103fn2">Telegram 20, Feb. 26, from Bonn to Lisbon, <ref
                            target="#pg_262">p. 262</ref>.</note> First, in the letter from the
                    Chancellor to the three Foreign Ministers to delete the sentence reading: “These
                    payments will cover its contribution to the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                    and the support of Allied forces in the Federal Republic”, and substitute the
                    following: “These payments will include the support of Allied forces in the
                    Federal Republic.” Second, in the letter of reply to the Chancellor by the Three
                    Foreign Ministers, delete the phrase “and will be used exclusively for the
                    Federal Republic’s contribution to the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and
                    the support of Allied Forces in the Federal Republic” and substitute the
                    following: “and will include the support of Allied Forces in the Federal
                    Republic.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> explained that these
                    changes were proposed to safeguard the position of the Federal Government which
                    it had formulated as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Federal Republic proceeds on the assumption that in the sense of the
                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty the payments for the
                            support of the Allied forces in the Federal Republic are reckoned as
                            part of the Federal Republic’s contribution to <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                                >EDC</gloss>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In the event that the Foreign Ministers were unable to accept the two amendments
                    proposed by the Chancellor, he would be willing to agree to the documents as
                    they were drafted with a footnote safeguarding the position of the Federal
                    Republic in the exact words quoted above.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> said that unless the
                    High Commission received contrary advices from the Foreign Ministers, it was
                    proposed to publish the communiqué at Bonn at 6:00 p.m., <gloss target="#t_GMT1"
                        >G.M.T.</gloss> (Lisbon time).<note n="3" xml:id="d103fn3">The agreed press
                        statement referred to here is quoted in telegram 23, Feb. 26, from Lisbon,
                            <ref target="#pg_261">p. 261</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> indicated he was
                    unwilling to modify the texts which had been submitted by the Chancellor, and it
                    was agreed to maintain them. It was understood that this meant that the footnote
                    would be included. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                    remarked that he accepted the existence of the footnote, but not its content.
                    The Federal Government would make the assumption and the Allies would take note
                    of it.</p>
                <p>It was agreed to issue the communiqué at Lisbon at 6:00 p.m. It was also agreed
                    to send a message to the three High Commissioners congratulating them on their
                    handling of the negotiations with the Germans on this subject.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d103fn4">
                        <p>The message of congratulation under reference here, as transmitted in
                            telegram 28, Feb. 27, from Lisbon to Bonn, repeated to Washington as
                                <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 98, reads as follows: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Three Foreign Mins, before leaving Lisbon, wish to congratulate
                                    Allied <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> most warmly on
                                    securing Fed Govt’s agreement so promptly to the total figure
                                    for Ger’s financial contribution to defense for the first year,
                                    and on their handling of these whole contractual negots.”
                                    (740.5/2–2752)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0217" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">security safeguards</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> proposed that the civil
                    aircraft problem be dealt with by omitting civil aircraft from the list in the
                        <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty of articles not to be produced in
                    strategic areas and that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1"
                        >Adenauer</persName> be asked to include in a communication to the three
                    Governments an assurance in the following terms: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In respect of civil aircraft, none are being produced in the Federal
                            Republic at the present time, nor are there any facilities available for
                            such production. The Government of the Federal Republic intends to
                            purchase from other countries such civil aircraft as may be required in
                            Germany. If in the future, the condition should change, the Federal
                            Republic will seek agreement on this matter with the Governments of the
                            US, UK and France in the light of the situation then prevailing.”<note
                                n="5" xml:id="d103fn5">The paragraph quoted here was quoted again in
                                the telegraphic report on this meeting, <gloss target="#t_Secto1"
                                    >Secto</gloss> 100, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> and in telegram
                                262400Z from <persName corresp="#p_NASHFC1">Nash</persName> to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LOVETTRA1">Lovett</persName>, <ref
                                    target="#pg_167">p. 167</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>After reading the US draft Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1"
                        >Schuman</persName> said he could recommend this to his Government. If they
                    got a real community in Europe a sense of community would arise and there would
                    be comprehension on both sides.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> recalled that the
                    Chancellor was going to make a general statement to the three Governments on
                    security controls. Either in that communication or in one appended to it and
                    having the same effect he would say what was in the US draft on civil aviation.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> thought this would be
                    more acceptable to <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> than
                    some arrangement prohibiting production for 50 years. Summarizing the position
                    reached, he said the Ministers proposed to remove cannon from the list, to put a
                    proposal on gun powder along the lines suggested in the morning session (that is
                    to let the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> work it out) and then they would
                    ask <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> to say this on civil
                    aviation.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">conclusion of contractual arrangements</hi>
                </p>
                <p>During the course of the general exchange of remarks on the conclusion of the
                    contractual arrangements and the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> said he hoped to be
                    able to come to Europe for the signature of the General Agreement.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Trieste</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> said he wished to raise
                    another issue briefly, that of Trieste.<note n="6" xml:id="d103fn6">For
                        documentation on U.S. efforts to assist in the conclusion of the dispute
                        over Trieste, see <ref target="frus1952-54v08">volume <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >viii</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> He said he was worried about this. The Yugoslavs were raising
                    difficulties. They want to go back to the older arrangement. We ought to look at
                    this problem to try to find a common approach to it.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> agreed that we should
                    study it together. He said he had been told by <persName
                        corresp="#p_DEGASPERIA1">De Gasperi</persName> that the <gloss
                        target="#t_UP1">UP</gloss> was having an interview with <persName
                        corresp="#p_TITOJB1">Tito</persName> today. According to <persName
                        corresp="#p_DEGASPERIA1">De Gasperi</persName> the Italians and the
                    Yugoslavs <pb facs="0218" n="174" xml:id="pg_174"/> were further apart now than
                    a year ago. The Secretary said the United States had felt that the Yugoslavs
                    were not negotiating in good faith. They were now encouraging the idea of a free
                    state.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> observed that we were
                    giving aid to Yugoslavia and we should impose conditions. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PERKINSGW1">Perkins</persName> informed the Ministers that the
                    United States was having talks with the French and British now in Washington on
                    the question of aid to Yugoslavia.<note n="7" xml:id="d103fn7">Documentation on
                        U.S. economic and military assistance to Yugoslavia is included in <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v08">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> thought
                    that we ought to toughen up a bit.</p>
                <p>It was agreed to include this subject in the Washington discussions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
