<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States High Commissioner for Germany ( (McCloy) ) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-02-28T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-02-28T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-28T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-28T13:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/2–2852: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MCCLOYJJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d139fn1">This telegram was repeated for information to Paris
                        and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-02-28T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 28, 1952—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1747. Inform Defense. <gloss target="#t_AGSec1">AgSec</gloss> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_SLATERJE1">Slater</persName>. Fol is brief summary report
                    informal mtg of three <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOMers</gloss> held 28
                    February.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> fin contrib to Western
                    def</hi>.</p>
                <p>I opened mtg with statement my disappointment at report that Fr were now taking
                    position they wld not agree to accept ltr from three <gloss target="#t_FonMin1"
                        >FonMin</gloss>s to Chancellor<note n="2" xml:id="d139fn2">For the proposed
                        text of the letter under reference here, see telegram 22, Feb. 26, from
                        Lisbon to Bonn, <ref target="#pg_260">p. 260</ref>.</note> with inclusion of
                    footnote contained in para 3 of Bonn sent Lisbon 20 of 26 February.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d139fn3">Not printed.</note> I informed mtg that I had informed
                        <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> at 1900 hours 26
                    February (in accordance with <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>) that his
                    proposals had been accepted and, therefore, it wld be very embarrassing to
                    reopen this matter with him. <persName corresp="#p_KIRKPATRICKSIA1"
                        >Kirkpatrick</persName> then said cable report of <gloss target="#t_FM1"
                        >FM</gloss> mtg<note n="4" xml:id="d139fn4">For reports of the <persName
                            corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>–<persName
                            corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1"
                            >Schuman</persName> meeting of Feb. 26, 5 p.m. under reference here, see
                            <ref target="#pg_167">p. 167</ref>–<ref target="#pg_174"
                        >174</ref>.</note> stated that altho <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1"
                        >Schuman</persName> cld not accept <hi rend="underline">amendments</hi> to
                    texts as contained in <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>, Fr cld accept
                    both footnotes. (Word <hi rend="underline">footnotes</hi>—in plural—appeared
                    twice in his cable from Lisbon as it had in ours to Lisbon.) I pointed out
                    Chancellor had made it abundantly clear that acceptance of either amendments to
                    text or insertion footnotes which clearly stated <gloss target="#t_FedRep1"
                        >FedRep</gloss>’s reservation were a condition to his agrmt to global
                    contrib. Voting implications were also mentioned by him in explaining his
                    proposals. Further, I did not believe he was attempting to obtain an overriding
                    position for <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> vis-à-vis Fr.</p>
                <p>After considerable discussion and telephone calls between <persName
                        corresp="#p_BERARDA1">Berard</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1"
                        >Schuman</persName>, Fr agreed to accept both footnotes provided that the
                    one contained in Chancellor’s reply wld clearly indicate that the vote [<hi
                        rend="italic">note?</hi>] merely stated a Ger position without being binding
                    on the <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BERARDA1">Berard</persName> said <persName
                        corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>’s main concern was that discussion
                    on voting issue shld not be prejudiced by current exchange of ltrs. After
                    clearance with Paris after the mtg, <persName corresp="#p_BERARDA1"
                        >Berard</persName> gave me fol wording which I will personally give to
                    Chancellor, as chairman, later this afternoon to determine if agreeable with
                    him.</p>
                <p>The footnote shld now commence with the phrase: “The three Fon Mins have taken
                    cognizance of the position of the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>
                    according to which the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> proceeds on the
                    assumption that in the sense of the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty
                    etc.” Same as footnote in <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d139fn5">Telegram 1824, Mar. 4, from Bonn, briefly reporting on an
                        informal session of the Allied High Commissioners that day, indicated that
                        the High Commission had agreed that the text of the letter from the
                        American, British, and French Foreign Ministers to Chancellor <persName
                            corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName>, as amended here, should be
                        sent immediately to the three capitals for signature by the Foreign
                        Ministers. (740.5/3–452)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0309" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KIRKPATRICKSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName> insisted real
                    problem to be solved now was not exchange of ltrs or presence of footnote, but
                    rather question of voting formula within <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>.
                    Question of ltrs wld be academic if Ger conditions for a rep vote in accordance
                    with their contrib were not accepted. <persName corresp="#p_KIRKPATRICKSIA1"
                        >Kirkpatrick</persName> said that Fr wld, in his opinion, be most
                    ill-advised not to include in their over-all contrib for voting purposes the amt
                    which they expend on the Indochina campaign. (Fr had previously indicated Paris
                    had not yet decided whether to include Indochina expenses.) If France did not
                    include this figure, Ger might have a preponderance of voting strength within
                        <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, a fact which was of vital concern to
                    UK. (In this connection, Fr replied their govt did not wish <gloss
                        target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> to be in position to review or pass on
                    Fr expenses in Indochina as Fr Govt wanted free hand this matter. <gloss
                        target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> wld probably claim expenditures were
                    too high.) While I agreed with <persName corresp="#p_KIRKPATRICKSIA1"
                        >Kirkpatrick</persName> that voting issue was of primary importance and must
                    be resolved as soon as possible if further progress was to be made on subj of
                    fin contrib, I stated it was still to Allied advantage (if only psychological)
                    to have signature now on fin contrib commitment.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Publication war criminals records.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In accordance with para 2 of London sent Dept <gloss target="#t_Secto1"
                        >Secto</gloss> 16 rptd info Paris 1780, Bonn 310, Lisbon 143 of 18
                        February,<note n="6" xml:id="d139fn6">Not printed. It reported upon the
                            <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>–<persName
                            corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1"
                            >Schuman</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1"
                            >Adenauer</persName> meeting of Feb. 18, 10 a.m. For a record of that
                        meeting, see the <persName>Laukhuff</persName> minutes, <ref target="#pg_60"
                            >p. 60</ref>.</note> we agreed to instruct experts to compile facts on
                    records of war criminals with particular ref to those who fall in fol
                    categories: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) those who have had previous criminal
                    convictions; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) those who had personally committed
                    murder (as opposed to those who had given orders to others to do so); and (<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) those who had been convicted of concentration camp
                    atrocities. I added and they agreed that guilty mil leaders shld also be
                    included. It was further agreed task shld be completed by end of March in order
                    that info cld be made public in advance of Bundestag consideration of proposed
                    contractual provision establishing mixed boards on clemency and criminals of
                    war.</p>
                <p>I took occasion to announce that except in special cases involving compassionate
                    grounds, I did not intend to take any action on outstanding petitions which have
                    been or wld be submitted to me, but rather that I intended to leave such cases
                    for consideration by mixed board when established. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KIRKPATRICKSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName> indicated he hoped to
                    finish review which he was currently undertaking in about two months time.</p>
                <p>3. Security safeguards being reported separately in next two fol cables.<note
                        n="7" xml:id="d139fn7">Telegram 1748, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>; telegram
                        1749 is not printed, but see footnote 5, <hi rend="italic"
                        >infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCCLOYJJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mccloy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
