<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Deputy Special Representative in Europe ( (Anderson) ) to
                    the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-06-18T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-06-18T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfDPXugH8GvkDjP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085264"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Defense policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-18T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-18T07:00:00-05:00" n="216"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/6–1853: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Special Representative in Europe</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_ANDERSONFL1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Anderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-18T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 18, 1953—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 2413. <gloss target="#t_noforn1"
                        >Noforn</gloss>. Limit distribution. For <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MARTINEM1">Martin</persName>.
                    Reference: Final paragraph <gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 2389, June
                        15.<note n="1" xml:id="d216fn1">Not printed; it reported the Italian views
                        on the scope of the Annual Review general report and noted that they
                        believed the Annual Review was becoming a strictly military process which no
                        longer balanced military and nonmilitary considerations. Finally, the
                        telegram reported that the Italians understood that <persName
                            corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1">Ismay</persName> would soon urge the Council to
                        consider the gap between <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> requirements
                        and availabilities. (740.5/6–1553)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0453" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We checked with friend in <gloss target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss> and learned
                        that there has been under discussion in <gloss target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss> a
                        paper entitled “Need For review of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        Defense Policy.”<note n="2" xml:id="d216fn2">No copy of this paper has been
                            found in the Department of State files.</note> Paper was prepared by
                        Sergent addressed to <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1"
                        >Ismay</persName>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Concern is expressed in paper that <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>
                        “continues build its policy on a strategic plan for which it is unwilling
                        provide resources <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> military authorities
                        say are necessary.” <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Action recommended in military field is that <gloss
                                    target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> request Military Committee consider
                                shortfall, below stated requirements, in military resources which
                                are being made available. Committee’s review should be particularly
                                addressed to question whether a redistribution of defense effort
                                might result in more effective combination of forces and material,
                                or a more effective concentration of them in certain areas. In
                                addition, committee might be asked whether undue emphasis on
                                “quality” may not lead to development of larger “tail” than <gloss
                                    target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces as whole can afford.
                                Finally, committee might be asked whether allocation of effort
                                between three services is such as to yield most effective overall
                                strength.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>In political field action recommended is that, if it has to be
                                accepted that military requirements can not be met, it desirable
                                that responsible statesmen of member countries express themselves
                                firmly in support <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> effort and
                                that there be no implication any diminution of interest on part any
                                members. Further, if <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is found
                                have inadequate resources, will be increasingly necessary that
                                utilization these resources be guided by common and consistent
                                policy. Finally, foregoing would imply greater willingness on part
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members to confer on
                                important policy decisions before these are taken in national
                                capitals.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Paper was discussed with <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1"
                            >Ismay</persName> by a few members <gloss target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss>
                        June 12. Upshot of discussion then was that paper should be redrafted before
                        further consideration.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Some top level members <gloss target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss> oppose matters
                        being raised by <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1">Ismay</persName> with
                        Council at this time. <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1">Ismay</persName>
                        himself apparently has not yet made up his mind whether to raise it.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In our view, it clearly desirable that <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1"
                            >Ismay</persName> not raise matter with Council either in present or
                        revised form. On other hand, any direct effort on US part to dissuade him
                        would involve admission we aware internal discussion this matter in <gloss
                            target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss>. It entirely possible issue may die natural
                        death within <gloss target="#t_IS1">IS</gloss>. Thus, consider it best we
                        avoid any overt action to kill it at this stage. In any case, should
                            <persName corresp="#p_ISMAYLHLI1">Ismay</persName> decide in near future
                        place matter before Council in present or revised form, we would be advised
                        of this in advance.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>For obvious reasons request above information be held very closely.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ANDERSONFL1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Anderson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
