<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/3–3054</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the <gloss type="from">Special Assistant</gloss> to the Counselor of the Department of
                                State</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GALLOWAYWJ1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Galloway</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-03-30">March 30, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list rend="flushleft" type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Consultations on Atomic Weapons</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Jean Daridan</persName>,
                                French Minister</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MACARTHURDII1">Douglas MacArthur
                                    II</persName>, Counselor, Department of State</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GALLOWAYWJ1">W. J. Galloway</persName>,
                                Special Assistant to the Counselor</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At his request, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName>
                            came in to see Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MACARTHURDII1">MacArthur</persName> this morning. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> said he understood there
                            was a possibility that the question of atomic weapons might be one of
                            the topics to be discussed at the forthcoming <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting. Presumably this would be further discussion
                            of those aspects of the matter raised at the last <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting.<note n="1" xml:id="d251fn1">See statement by the Secretary of State to the North Atlantic
                                Council, Dec. 14, 1953, <ref target="#pg_461">p. 461</ref>, and
                                telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 7 from Paris, Dec.
                                16, 1953, <ref target="#pg_471">p. 471</ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> said that the French
                            Government had no objection to such a discussion taking place at the
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting and assumed that since
                            the primary responsibility in these matters rested with the United
                            States, the discussion would be on the initiative of this
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> then came to what
                            was obviously the purpose of his visit. He said that a telegram had been
                            received from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                            suggesting that it would be desirable for the Secretary, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> and himself to have private
                            discussions on the conditions for the utilization of atomic weapons in
                            the general European area and specifically from bases in French North
                            Africa and Metropolitan France. He mentioned that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName>’s recent statement on
                            the use of atomic weapons from bases in the UK<note n="2" xml:id="d251fn2">On Mar. 23, in response to a query in Parliament;
                                Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName> had made a brief statement reconfirming
                                U.S. airbase rights in the United Kingdom for retaliatory purposes,
                                subject to prior consultation between officials of the two
                                governments. The rights had first been formally extended by the
                                United Kingdom during the time of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName>’s visit to
                                Washington in January 1952 (<hi rend="italic">H C. Debs</hi>., 5th
                                series, vol. 525, cols. 1050–1052). Documentation on the <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName> visit to
                                Washington in January 1952 is printed in <ref target="frus1952-54v06p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> seemed to make such talks desirable. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> proposed that these talks
                            take place when the three ministers are together in Paris for the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> then said that
                            the Embassy understood from the U.S. Armed Services that the proposals
                            for amending the McMahon Act<note n="3" xml:id="d251fn3">Reference is to
                                the Atomic Energy Act of 1946 (Public Law 585, 79th Cong., 60 Stat.
                                755, Aug. 1, 1946).</note> would probably not be considered by
                            Congress before June.</p>
                        <p>He said that the French Government now proposed that the Standing Group
                            should begin working on these questions of employment of atomic weapons
                            under <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> without waiting for formal
                            Congressional <pb facs="0531" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/> action. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> gave the
                            impression that the French Government was not proposing any formal
                            action on the part of the Standing Group, but rather that it should just
                            begin thinking about the problem. He said the French Government believed
                            that the Standing Group was the proper body to deal with the matter.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> indicated that a
                            member of the Embassy staff would be in touch with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1">Arneson</persName> in regard to the French
                            Government’s suggestion.<note n="4" xml:id="d251fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MARTINJ1">Jacques Martin</persName>, First
                                Secretary of the French Embassy, called on <persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1">R. Gordon Arneson</persName> of <gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss> later on Mar. 30 to stress once
                                again the desirability of private tripartite discussions at the
                                forthcoming <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> meeting concerning
                                prior consultation on the use of atomic weapons. “He stressed that
                                while <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> felt such
                                a discussion was highly desirable he would, of course, leave it to
                                the Secretary to decide when the time was ripe.” <persName corresp="#p_MARTINEM1">Martin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1">Arneson</persName> also reviewed the
                                importance of the <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName> statement and <persName corresp="#p_MARTINEM1">Martin</persName> asked for a prognosis
                                on the passage of the amendment to the Atomic Energy Act of 1946. He
                                was given the same answers as was <persName corresp="#p_DARIDANJ1">Daridan</persName> earlier (Memorandum of conversation, by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1">Arneson</persName>, Mar. 30,
                                1954, 740.5/3–3054).</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>