<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Dunn) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-01-15T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-01-15T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="receiqhGHZGpcOok4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">SACEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-01-15T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-01-15T14:00:00-05:00" n="369"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/1–1553: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DUNNJC1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d369fn1">Repeated to London and Bonn.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-01-15T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 15, 1953—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3975. Reference <gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 1152, January 14<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d369fn2">Not printed; it reported that since the investiture
                        of <persName corresp="#p_MAYERR1">René Mayer</persName> as French Prime
                        Minister at the turn of the year <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1"
                            >Alphand</persName> and other supporters were greatly encouraged about
                        the prospects for French ratification of the <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                            >EDC</gloss> Treaty. (740.5/1–1353)</note> and <gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3964, January 15.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d369fn3">Not printed; it reported that French officials on the
                            <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Interim Committee had advised the
                            <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> observer that the modifications
                        to <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> proposed by the <persName
                            corresp="#p_MAYERR1">Mayer</persName> government were limited to
                        negotiating protocols which would insure French freedom to withdraw forces
                        for use within the French Union, insure French freedom to produce and export
                        war matériel within the French Union without the possibility of a veto by
                        the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Commissariat, insure the integrity
                        of French forces and Franco-German equality in a weighted voting procedure,
                        and, finally, insure that French forces remaining in the Federal Republic
                        after June 30, 1953 would have the same status as U.K. and U.S. forces.
                        (740.5/1–553)</note> Subject is European Defense Community.</p>
                <p>In conversation with Embassy <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> observer this
                    morning, <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> outlined tentative
                    plans of French Government on additional protocols to <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> treaty. He stressed that protocols should be considered as
                    implementation or completion of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty and
                    that French proposals do not require any revision of any paragraph in <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty. He regretted that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MAYERR1">Mayer</persName> had used term “rectification” in
                        <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty in speech before Anglo-American
                    press club but acknowledged that perhaps this word might give certain groups in
                    France satisfaction even though it was inaccurate. <persName
                        corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> was troubled that certain
                    newspapers already took line that protocols being sought did not amount to
                    anything. It would help ratification greatly if assembly could believe protocols
                    were very important. Following is substance present French intentions: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>With reference to protocol directing <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1"
                                >SACEUR</gloss> to approve withdrawal of French units for use in
                            French Union, <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> added
                                <pb facs="0747" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/> very little to information
                            in earlier messages. He did say that protocol should also include
                            binding recommendation to French Government to replace withdrawn units
                            as quickly as possible. Exact language proposed should be available to
                            us this week end.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> suggested that
                            theoretical problem of weighted-voting procedure under Article 43–BIS
                            might be corrected by provision prolonging indefinitely transitional
                            voting procedure, thus maintaining Franco-German equality.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>On maintenance of “integrity” of French forces, <persName
                                corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> stressed that <gloss
                                target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> administration would have a voice in
                            naming officers in French overseas forces in same way that France would
                            have a voice in nomination of officers in <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                                >EDC</gloss> forces. He hoped this important concession of joint
                            administration would enable other <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                            countries to agree quickly to French proposal.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> again mentioned two
                            years as length of interim period for French troops to have special
                            status in Germany taking into account status of United States and
                            British troops. He added that French would also propose establishment of
                            a system whereby <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> forces, stationed
                            in a country other than their own, would receive certain station and
                            expatriation allowances.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> said French would
                            propose that support costs for French troops in Germany continue for six
                            months after date <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty and
                            contractual agreements enter into force.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> proposed three lines
                            of action for British: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Certain agreements covering manner in which land and air
                                    forces of United Kingdom and <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                    would be integrated and work together, including provision for
                                    mixed commands, are already being discussed and drafts from
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MILLARSFRH1">Hoyer-Millar</persName>
                                    are expected soon.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>New ways should be found for British to go further in
                                    committing themselves to maintain troops on European
                                    continent.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Institutional association between United Kingdom and <gloss
                                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, such as that being discussed
                                    in Luxembourg and Strasbourg, should be developed.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>(7)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> also said that a
                            general understanding would have to be reached with United States on
                            administration, organization and procedures in connection with end-item
                                assistance.<note n="4" xml:id="d369fn4">Documentation on U.S.
                                economic assistance to France is presented in <ref
                                    target="frus1952-54v06p1">volume VI</ref>.</note> He apologized
                            for pressing United States now in view of delay of interim committee in
                            not accepting our proposal to exchange views sooner. He hoped we could
                            submit in next few days a preliminary paper on our intentions which
                            would provide a basis for talks to proceed with interim
                            committee.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> concluded by stating that
                    these points had not been definitively approved by Cabinet action but he
                    believed requests for protocols would be limited to these points. He then
                    touched on Saar and United States aid as related matters which would have to be
                    discussed. He expected French Cabinet to make final decisions next week on these
                    subjects and to begin conversations with other <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> countries <pb facs="0748" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/> the week
                    following. He said he would give German <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                    delegation some indication of French intentions and is making an appointment
                    with deputy head of German delegation this afternoon.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> confirmed that groups in
                    French Government were still thinking about possibility of interim period in
                    which certain provisions of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty would not
                    go into effect.</p>
                <p>He said suggestions involved permitting each government, including German
                    Government, to exercise defense powers for brief period which would be directly
                    in conflict with <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty. He did not expect
                    any of suggestions to be adopted. His staff was now preparing a paper to
                    demonstrate that <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty already had made
                    provision for transitional period adequate to permit practical operation.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d369fn5">Telegrams <gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss>
                        1171 (Jan. 15), 3998 (Jan. 16), 4031 (Jan. 19), and 4045 (Jan. 20) from
                            <persName corresp="#p_DRAPERWHJ1">Draper</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_DUNNJC1">Dunn</persName> at Paris reported the confused and
                        concerned reaction of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> signatory
                        governments, especially Italy and the United Kingdom, to the planned
                        introduction by France of new protocols to the <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                            >EDC</gloss> Treaty. Telegram 4045 also reported that <persName
                            corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> had responded to this
                        unfavorable reaction with the promise to make the drafts of the suggested
                        protocols available to the heads of the delegations to the <gloss
                            target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Interim Committee as quickly as possible,
                        perhaps as early as <gloss target="#t_FEB1">Feb</gloss>. 15. All telegrams
                        cited above are in file 740.5.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DUNNJC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dunn</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
