<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-14T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-14T11:00:00-05:00" n="461" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d461">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/12–1453: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_ACHILLESTC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Achilles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d461fn1">Repeated to London, Bonn, and
                                Moscow.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-14T17:00:00+01:00">December
                                    14, 1953—5 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2282. Following summary conversation afternoon December 13 <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d461fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> was in Paris for
                                the Twelfth Session of the North Atlantic Council; for documentation
                                on the Council meeting, see <ref target="#pg_454">pp. 454</ref>
                                ff.</note> accompanied by <persName corresp="#p_CONANTJB1">Conant</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MACARTHURDII1">MacArthur</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Secretary congratulated <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> results German elections. Later [<hi rend="italic">Latter?</hi>] stated outcome elections gave German
                            Government presently much needed stability and consistency. Secretary
                            commented on importance of government on continent of Europe which could
                            take strong and constructive positions with respect any common problems
                            confronting us. Constructive leadership especially important now.
                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> replied
                            objectives Germany and United States alike in European as well as world
                            problems.</p>
                        <p>Secretary stated implementation <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                            immediate task and hoped <gloss target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> would
                            follow shortly since without European unity Europe had little
                            future.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> said he more
                            optimistic after arrival Paris. Thought would be helpful if Italy
                            ratified <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> near future and before vote
                            in French Assembly. Secretary said he had impression Italian action
                            improbable prior settlement Trieste. Added such settlement would require
                            time although United States trying hard bring it about. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> agreed adding his talks
                            with Italian officials and Yugoslav Ambassador <persName>Bonn</persName>
                            indicated firm desire both sides for settlement.</p>
                        <pb facs="0910" n="866" xml:id="pg_866"/>
                        <p>On French Parliamentary situation re <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> said according
                            his calculation there about 310 voted in favor <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and 300 against. Much therefore depends on mood of
                            Parliament when vote taken. He likened situation to that prevailing at
                            time of vote on <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                            Plan. To help situation in France and create proper mood in Parliament
                            Chancellor said he considering announcing a German decision purchase
                            more wine and meat in France at appropriate moment. Believes this would
                            have good effect among French farmers and in turn upon peasant and
                            conservative vote in Parliament. Secretary expressed belief it possible
                            obtain ratification through combined influences which might be exercised
                            when <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> came to vote and that important
                            thing was to bring <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> to vote in French
                            Parliament.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> saw less
                            difficulty bringing <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> to vote and felt
                            after presidential elections new government would initiate parliamentary
                            process leading to definite vote.</p>
                        <p>Secretary pointed to Saar and projected four-power meeting with
                                Soviets<note n="3" xml:id="d461fn3">Documentation on the Four-Power
                                Conference at Berlin, Jan. 25–Feb. 18, 1954 is presented in <ref target="frus1952-54v07p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> as delaying factors. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> agreed vote would be
                            delayed till after four-power meeting but confident Saar would be
                            solved. Referred to communiqué following his talk with <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> December 12 as best yet
                            issued on subject.</p>
                        <p>Secretary said Saar settlement would require sacrifices on Chancellor’s
                            part but these would lead to tremendous benefits Germany and Europe.</p>
                        <p>Secretary referred to possible impression elements in Germany might have
                            received from United States visitors and military figures to effect
                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> not really important and failing
                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, United States would develop
                            some alternative solution with Germany. Said he wished make clear this
                            was not the case. Chancellor expressed full understanding of United
                            States position in this respect.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> referred to
                            four-power meeting and expressed concern over opportunity for delay
                            which it presented. His principal worry is French would fall for Soviet
                            delaying tactics. Said if conference came to dead end, it very important
                            that public opinion, especially in France see failure as result Soviet
                            obstructionism. Secretary agreed and replied that general agreement had
                            been reached at Bermuda<note n="4" xml:id="d461fn4">For documentation on
                                the Bermuda Conference of the Heads of Government of the United
                                States, the United Kingdom, and France, see <ref target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1710">pp. 1710</ref> ff.</note> that
                            meeting should last no more than two or three weeks. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> indicated that if
                            conference could be terminated in four to five weeks West would be well
                            out of it. Secretary assured Chancellor that if four-power meeting held
                            we would work in close contact with him but in manner best calculated
                            take account French sensibilities. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName>
                            <pb facs="0911" n="867" xml:id="pg_867"/> said he fully recognized
                            French sensibilities had to be taken account particularly by
                            Germany.</p>
                        <p>Secretary said from standpoint Europe’s security presence United States
                            forces in Europe is deemed very important. United States hoped to
                            continue this kind of contribution so long as it serves really useful
                            purpose. Chancellor replied everyone in Germany convinced usefulness
                            United States forces in Europe and Germany, adding that relations
                            between United States forces and German population excellent. Secretary
                            referred to rumors that in event <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and
                            development German forces this would be signal for retreat United States
                            forces from continent but stated in his opinion reverse is true.</p>
                        <p>In answer to Secretary’s query regarding paper (United Kingdom-French
                                draft)<note n="5" xml:id="d461fn5">Not found in Department of State
                                files.</note> which French had given him regarding declaration on
                            European security, Chancellor said he had examined it and had some
                            suggestions. He felt text of paper did not adequately reflect <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            relationship. He said paper in present form referred to “strictly
                            defensive character of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, of which the
                            forces cannot be employed except for the protection of the territory of
                            member states against an armed attack in Europe”. This phrase he said
                            did not take account of (1) where <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            forces not in <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> are attacked; (2) if
                            an attack is launched against UK or UK forces in <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> countries; and (3) if other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries are attacked. He made reference to <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            protocols and to treaty between UK and <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. He said Germans would give their comments to French
                            but felt in general there should be deletions of existing text to bring
                            it in line with envisaged relationship between <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and
                            particularly to emphasize its defensive aspects. Secretary agreed paper
                            in present form needed change.</p>
                        <p>In reply question we would receive German comments on German elections
                            and formation and status of all-German government, <persName corresp="#p_HALLSTEINW1">Hallstein</persName> replied a short paper
                            would be given to US, UK and French.<note n="6" xml:id="d461fn6">The
                                paper under reference has not been identified further.</note> He
                            added it essential this paper be amplified by oral explanation since
                            conflicting views within different German ministries made it impossible
                            to sum up entire situation in paper. He envisaged Dr. <persName corresp="#p_GREWEW1">Grewe</persName> would be present in Paris
                            during tripartite working group meetings so he could give oral
                            explanations as required.</p>
                        <p>Secretary expressed personal agreement on desirability Dr. <persName corresp="#p_GREWEW1">Grewe</persName>’s presence Paris, but United
                            States would have to consult with UK and French before giving definitive
                            reply. He again emphasized United States desire have closest possible
                            contact and cooperation with Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName>. Chancellor expressed
                            great appreciation and <pb facs="0912" n="868" xml:id="pg_868"/> said
                            one of his guiding principles for long time had been belief in absolute
                            necessity to cooperate with United States.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_ACHILLESTC1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Achilles</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>