<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="469"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 203</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d469fn1">The conversation took place at the Secretary’s
                        residence, 66 Miquelstrasse, Berlin, where <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName> was staying during the Berlin Conference;
                        documentation on the conference is presented in <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v07p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1954-02-17">February 17, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The four French prerequisites to <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Accord with the UK.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>US undertaking re troops.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Saar settlement.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Question of “democratic control” of <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                                >EDC</gloss> Army.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0920" n="876" xml:id="pg_876"/>
                <p>Regarding <hi rend="italic">1</hi>, <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> felt that the arrangements now practically agreed upon
                    would suffice provided there was a satisfactory understanding under <hi
                        rend="italic">2</hi>. The British would not give adequate undertakings if
                    they thought the US was going to pull out. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> expressed the personal view that if they started out
                    with close association with <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, the UK would
                    end up with membership.</p>
                <p>Regarding <hi rend="italic">2</hi>, there should be some undertaking to maintain
                    Anglo-American forces on the Continent; also, some declaration that we did not
                    regard the North Atlantic Treaty as expiring in twenty years, but as an
                    agreement which normally would continue.</p>
                <p>There should be agreement on maintenance of the forward strategy rather than
                    peripheral strategy and acceptance of the concept of some contribution by the US
                    to maintaining an appropriate balance of strength on the Continent. Also, it
                    would be desirable that the US would indicate its willingness to sit in on talks
                    which would otherwise confront the French with the Germans so that the French
                    would not be left alone. There was some discussion as to the possible form the
                    US action might take. <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName>
                    suggested a Congressional resolution. I said that this matter of troop
                    disposition was under our Constitution primarily a matter for the President.
                    Even the proposed constitutional amendment would probably expressly reaffirm the
                    authority of the President to make agreements as Commander-in-Chief without the
                    necessity for any Congressional participation. I thought that an appropriate
                    communication from the President, perhaps sent with the knowledge and informal
                    approval of some of the Congressional committees, would give the maximum that
                    could be expected under our constitutional provisions.</p>
                <p>With regard to <hi rend="italic">3</hi>, there would have to be a general
                    settlement of the Saar matter, although not every detail would have to be
                    settled. It could be contingent upon the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, as
                    obviously you could not Europeanize the Saar unless there was going to be a
                    Europe. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> should realize the
                    importance of this Saar matter and be willing to talk about it seriously and
                    above all soon and quietly. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    complained that there had always been too much publicity, even by <persName
                        corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> to prior talks with him and with
                        <persName corresp="#p_FRANGOISPONCETA1">Francois-Poncet</persName>.</p>
                <p>As to <hi rend="italic">4</hi>, there was long discussion between <persName
                        corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> as to where the most votes could
                    be gotten,—whether by playing to the socialists in favor of establishing
                    democratic control or from the right which feared an all-European political
                    organ. Since this was not a matter on which the US could be helpful, we did not
                    take any part in this discussion. However, <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> indicated he thought this was the most difficult point
                    of all to solve.</p>
                <p>Regarding procedure, <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    indicated his belief that the present government would probably hold on until
                    the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> vote. He thought that whatever was done
                    under points <hi rend="italic">1, 2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">3</hi> should, as
                    far as possible, <pb facs="0921" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/> be done
                    simultaneously at the moment when they would have the greatest impact. I asked
                    as to whether we could work this out in Washington with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BONNETH1">Bonnet</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_BONNETH1">Bonnet</persName>
                    had his full confidence, but that he lacked technical qualifications. <persName
                        corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> suggested working these things out
                    with <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> in Paris, but I said I
                    doubted whether this was the best place. It should preferably be done where the
                    President and I could be in personal touch with the matter. Also, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName>, as former Under Secretary, could
                    not, from a Congressional standpoint, usefully be given too great a role in this
                    matter. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> agreed and said that
                    he would send <persName corresp="#p_ALPHANDH1">Alphand</persName> to Washington,
                    but wanted him to come under some cover which would avoid wide-spread
                    speculation in France.</p>
                <p>I said that I wanted <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> to know
                    that we wanted to do everything possible to help put the <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> through. I saw no acceptable alternative. Some want to proceed
                    at once to arm the Germans to a large extent and to proceed to put the
                    contractuals in force without French concurrence. Others would want to adopt a
                    peripheral strategy based on Britain and Spain primarily. Others would want to
                    return to isolationism. I could not see what the outcome would be, but surely it
                    would not be anything good, and it would almost surely mark the end to the role
                    of France as a great power. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    said he fully accepted all of this, and he was dedicated to accomplishment of
                    the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. It was not precisely what he would have
                    liked, but it was better than any alternative. I said <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> was not precisely in the form I would have negotiated it, but
                    the President and I either had to elect to go ahead on what was or had to try to
                    make a fresh start, and the first course seemed preferable. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> said it was the same with
                        him.<note n="2" xml:id="d469fn2">At its 186th meeting on Feb. 26, the
                        National Security Council “Noted the President’s directive that the
                        Secretaries of State and Defense each designate a representative to prepare,
                        for Council consideration at its next meeting, recommendations as to
                        assurances which might be given the French, in connection with the European
                        Defense Community, as to the retention of U.S. forces in Europe and
                        continued participation of the United States in the North Atlantic Treaty
                        Organization” (<gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> files, lot 66 D 95, “Record of Actions by the National
                        Security Council”).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Foster Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
