<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-21T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-21T12:00:00-05:00" n="48" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/2–2152:
                                            Telegram</note>
                                        <head>
                                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States
                                                  Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d48fn1">This telegram was
                                                repeated for information to London, Paris, and
                                                Bonn.</note>
                                        </head>
                                        <opener>
                                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                                <placeName>
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>,
                                                  <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-02-21T17:00:00+00:00">February 21,
                                                  1952—5 p.m.</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p>
                                            <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 30. 1. Final mtg
                                            of three mins with <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> in London was held Tues, Feb
                                            19.</p>
                                        <p>2. Security controls.<note n="2" xml:id="d48fn2">The four
                                                Ministers presumably began their discussion at this
                                                point of the report of the tripartite working group
                                                on security controls referred to in <persName corresp="#p_BARNESRG1">Barnes</persName> minutes
                                                of the tripartite meeting of the morning of Feb. 19,
                                                  <ref target="#pg_72">p. 72</ref>.</note> Official
                                            subcommittee presented draft language which cld be
                                            inserted in Art A–4 of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty as subpara (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>). After some discussion of majority needed
                                            for decisions by <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                            Council on this matter, it was agreed exact language
                                            shld be left to Paris <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> conference but language recommended
                                            shld run along fol lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“Not to place orders, as concerns the materials
                                                  enumerated in list II, in strategically exposed,
                                                  areas except in accordance with gen directives of
                                                  the Council of Mins unanimously agreed”</p>
                                            </quote>
                                        </p>
                                        <p>There followed brief discussion of draft text of letter
                                            to be sent by Chancellor to other <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> govts.<note n="3" xml:id="d48fn3">For the agreed text of the letter to
                                                be sent by Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> to the
                                                governments of the European Defense Community, see
                                                  <ref target="#pg_104">p. 104</ref>.</note> Gers
                                            had proposed that sentence assuring equal supply of arms
                                            to Ger contingents shld apply to arms “of all kinds” but
                                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> quickly accepted US–UK redraft
                                            limiting assurance to arms of types “necessary to
                                            fulfill (Ger) assigned task to def of Europe”. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> also
                                            gave way without discussion on handling of research
                                            problem and abandoned proposal to enable Ger scientists
                                            participate “in all kinds of research work”, in favor of
                                            UK–US proposal preventing Ger research in listed
                                            armaments except as requested by <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. Four mins then agreed texts of two
                                            ltrs to be sent by <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName>, as telegraphed textually from
                                                <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss> Bonn Feb 20
                                            (telegram numbers not yet known here<note n="4" xml:id="d48fn4">The texts were sent in telegram
                                                1632, Feb. 20, from Bonn, not printed.
                                                (740.5/2–2052)</note>).</p>
                                        <p>Discussion shifted to items to be listed in list II of
                                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> suggested list be discussed in
                                            Paris by mil experts, and <pb facs="0120" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/> kept returning to this theme. Other
                                            three mins however insisted every attempt be made there
                                            and then to agree list. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> said
                                            many items were ill-defined. Wld “chemical weapons” and
                                            “propellant” prohibit production of explosives used in
                                            mines and ammunition for sporting weapons and police?
                                            How big are “small coastal vessels”? Shouldn’t guided
                                            missiles mean V-weapons? He said <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> has no wish or
                                            ability to make civil aircraft but how cld he face Ger
                                            people and say he had obligated them for 50 years not to
                                            make them. Secy said list shld be discussed as decisions
                                            on categories were political. It was important to US to
                                            know whether propellants and gunbarrels were to be
                                            included. We might wish to ask <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> to make these and
                                            such requests shld not be made more difficult by
                                            anything in <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> treaty.
                                            If list agreed, experts cld then refine it. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> felt best
                                            solution was to list all proposed items but allow <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> to make exceptions.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> made point he wanted to be sure
                                            these prohibitions wld not interfere with peace economy
                                            or lead to arguments over meaning.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> suggested
                                            accepting list in principle, omitting civil aircraft and
                                            noting French reservation on propellants and gunbarrels.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            said however he cld not consider anything accepted
                                            unless agreed “in toto”. After further discussion,
                                            consensus was that everyone agreed list shld include
                                            atomic, biological and chemical weapons, long-range and
                                            guided missiles, mil aircraft, and naval vessels other
                                            than minor defensive craft. <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> indicated he
                                            wld drop civil aircraft. That left French position “in
                                            suspense” on civil aircraft, propellants and gunbarrels.
                                            It was agreed that the High Commissioners shld immed
                                            begin discussions with <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> in Bonn to define agreed items
                                            and mins wld seek agreement in further info discussions
                                            in Lisbon on disagreed items.</p>
                                        <p>In reply to final inquiry from <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> said he
                                            was prepared to write letter to UK or any govt stating
                                                <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> has no
                                            intention of producing aircraft but intends to purchase
                                                them.<note n="5" xml:id="d48fn5">In his telegram 8
                                                from Bonn to Lisbon for <persName corresp="#p_BYROADEHA1">Byroade</persName>,
                                                repeated to the Department of State as 1663,
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_MCCLOYJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                                                reported that <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> had been asked to furnish
                                                American authorities a written formula embodying the
                                                undertaking given orally here to <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_HALLSTEINW1">Hallstein</persName> had
                                                offered the following text of such a formula: “The
                                                  <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> does not
                                                intend to manufacture civil aircraft but only to
                                                purchase them.” (740.5/2–2152)</note>
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> accepted
                                            this. When <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> stated such declaration cld be
                                            “repealed” at any time, <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> said:
                                            “Have confidence” ! He added production wld be so
                                            costly, especially if mil aircraft not produced, that
                                            his successor cld not build them “even if wholly mad”.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            took note and said he wld refer to his govt. Re police,
                                            he added he might propose to <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> conference to define police in terms
                                            used in document given to Chancellor day before. (“…
                                            numbers, cadres and equipment of all police forces in
                                                <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> will be
                                            limited to scale required <pb facs="0121" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/> for function of maintaining
                                            internal law and order, on basis comparable with other
                                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> countries”).</p>
                                        <p>3. <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>
                                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> membership.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> referred to French Assembly
                                            resolution mention of countries having territorial
                                            claims and stated he reiterated general convention
                                            statement that realization of such claims (by <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>) cld take place
                                            only by peaceful means. Further, in agreeing to proposed
                                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> para re <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> relationship, <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> does not
                                            relinquish desire to be <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> member. Furthermore, he interprets
                                            this provision (para 9<hi rend="italic">b</hi> of <gloss target="#t_Deps1">Deps</gloss> report<note n="6" xml:id="d48fn6">The reference here is to paragraph 9
                                                  (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of document D–D (52) 35
                                                Final, the Deputies Report on relationships between
                                                  <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, p. 249.</note>) to
                                            mean if <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> decision
                                            affects rights and duties of <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> members, Ger will be consulted.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            limited himself to observing that French Parliamentary
                                            discussions reflect a state of mind. French law must be
                                            passed in order to admit new member to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. In any event he felt
                                            everyone has same aim and cooperation will develop.</p>
                                        <p>4. Statement by <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>. Announcing vote of confidence
                                            in French Assembly.<note n="7" xml:id="d48fn7">The
                                                reference here is presumably to the adoption on Feb.
                                                19 by the French National Assembly of a resolution
                                                on a European Defense Force and German participation
                                                in the European Defense Community. Regarding the
                                                resolution, see telegrams 5048 and 5049, both Feb.
                                                17, from Paris, <ref target="#pg_615">pp. 615</ref>
                                                and <ref target="#pg_616">616</ref>.</note>
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> said
                                            it leaves much difficulty still ahead on <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> question. He appealed
                                            to colleagues to take into account difficulties which
                                            will face any French Govt. His govt firmly desires to
                                            achieve <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, as only
                                            policy for France and peace. If socialists abstain or
                                            vote against, there will be no majority for <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. French Govt not
                                            discouraged, however, though there is no guarantee its
                                            aim will be achieved. <persName corresp="#p_EDENSA1">Eden</persName> and Secretary assured him they wld
                                            do all they cld to help him and each other.</p>
                                        <p>5. Communiqué. Draft communiqué was presented by
                                            subcommittee, discussed, revised and agreed.<note n="8" xml:id="d48fn8">The reference here is presumably to
                                                the draft communiqué quoted in telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 17, Feb. 18, from
                                                London, <ref target="#pg_103">p. 103</ref>. For the
                                                tripartite communiqué as agreed and issued on Feb.
                                                19, see <ref target="#pg_105">p. 105</ref>.</note>
                                        </p>
                                    </div>
                                </body></text></TEI>