<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-09T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-09T05:00:00-05:00" n="526" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d526">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">762.022/6–954: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DILLONCD1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dillon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d526fn1">Repeated to London and Bonn.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-09T11:00:00+01:00">June 9,
                                    1954—11 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>4764. I informed <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANNM1">Schumann</persName>
                            yesterday afternoon following lines of paragraph 2 of US–UK brief<note n="2" xml:id="d526fn2">Reference is to the Text of Brief agreed by
                                United Kingdom/United States Working Group (May 1954), not
                                printed.</note> that if French and Germans reached Saar agreement in
                            their present negotiations based on the Nater’s plan, US in conjunction
                            with the UK was prepared to support that agreement in the peace treaty,
                            provided that the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> had come into
                            being. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANNM1">Schumann</persName> raised his
                            eyebrows a little bit at this proviso and referred, as he and <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> often have, to the US
                            guarantees, as he described them, which were freely given in 1947 and
                                1951.<note n="3" xml:id="d526fn3">For text of the 1947 U.S.
                                guarantee under reference, see <ref target="frus1947v02#pg_1082">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 1082</ref>–<ref target="frus1947v02#pg_1083">1083</ref>. For information
                                concerning the 1951 guarantee reaffirming U.S. policy that there
                                should be no change in the status of the Saar pending a final peace
                                treaty, see the editorial note, <ref target="frus1951v03p2#pg_1979">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, Part 2, p. 1979</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>He then said that the matter was of no real importance since there would
                            be no Saar settlement unless <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> was
                            ratified because of the informal link between the two imposed by the
                            German situation. I took this occasion to tell <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANNM1">Schumann</persName> that while I had no
                            specific instruction on the subject from my government, I felt
                            personally certain that if the worst came to the worst and the US had to
                            reappraise their European policies, that the declarations of 1947 and
                            1951 on the Saar would very definitely be included in such a
                            reappraisal. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANNM1">Schumann</persName> made
                            no particular comment.</p>
                        <p>He then said that he was very pleased at the news I had brought him about
                            the US willingness to support the Saar settlement in the peace treaty as
                            this was an absolutely essential part of the Saar “prealable” as far as
                            the French Parliament was concerned.</p>
                        <p>He then observed that our Ambassadors meeting in London was taking place
                            about a week too soon. He said that if the French Government <pb facs="1013" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/> survived the Indochina debate,
                            as he hoped it would, they would move immediately to set a date for the
                                <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> meeting to finalize
                            agreement on the Saar. He said he hoped this meeting could take place at
                            the end of this week but observed that this might not give enough time
                            to arrange the meeting. It might have to wait until next week. This
                            would certainly be the case, he said, if the Indochina debate turned
                            into a question of confidence which would put off the final vote until
                            Friday.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DILLONCD1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dillon</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>