<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="579" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/8–2154</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SPAAKPH1" type="to">Spaak</persName>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d579fn1">The source text was transmitted to
                                Brussels in telegram 194 at 3:45 p.m. on Aug. 21 with instructions
                                to <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> to deliver it
                                if he thought it would be helpful. Telegram 194 was repeated to
                                London at the same time with the instruction that a copy of the
                                source text be delivered to <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName> together with <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>’ personal message to
                                the Prime Minister (<ref target="#pg_1060">p. 1060</ref>). In
                                telegram 170 from Brussels, Aug. 22, sent also to London, <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> reported that he had
                                delivered a copy of the source text to <persName corresp="#p_SPAAKPH1">Spaak</persName> and that he had also
                                delivered a copy of <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>’ message to <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> (<hi rend="italic">infra</hi>) to the French Prime Minister
                                (740.5/8–2254).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-08-21">August 21,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I have been following with the closest interest the developments at the
                            Brussels Conference, which is so crucial to all our efforts to build
                            strength and unity in Europe. I have noted with particular appreciation
                            your skillful and patient efforts to bring about agreement under the
                            most difficult conditions.</p>
                        <p>It is my most earnest hope that the Conference will reach agreement <pb facs="1103" n="1059" xml:id="pg_1059"/> on a formula which all
                            participants can freely accept. However, I also feel that we must be
                            prepared to deal urgently with the serious situation which would arise
                            if, in spite of every effort, the Conference failed to reach agreement.
                            I am sure you will recall our luncheon conversation at Geneva at which
                            we discussed the possibility of a meeting under Article 132 of the
                                <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty,<note n="2" xml:id="d579fn2">For a report on this luncheon, see telegram <gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 28, Apr. 29, <ref target="#pg_951">p. 951</ref>.</note> with the US and UK in
                            attendance, along with the ratifying countries. I feel that the failure
                            of the Brussels meeting would be a matter of such grave consequence as
                            to make such a meeting necessary.</p>
                        <p>If you agree and if in your judgment circumstances at Brussels make it
                            desirable, I for my part would not object to your informing the
                            Ministers at Brussels that you propose calling a meeting immediately to
                            be attended by the <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                            countries, Germany, the US, and the UK. I believe it should be made
                            clear that the purpose of this meeting will be to consider with urgency
                            how best to associate Germany in sovereign equality with the West and to
                            bring about German rearmament. US would be willing to accept an
                            invitation on assumption UK would do likewise.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>