<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="580" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d580">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/8–2154</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFRANCEP1" type="to">Mendès-France</persName>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d580fn1">The source text was transmitted to
                                Brussels in <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> telegram 195 at
                                4:09 p.m. on Aug. 21 with instructions to <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> to deliver it if he
                                thought it would be helpful. Telegram 195 was repeated to London
                                with the instruction that a copy of the source text be delivered to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1">Churchill</persName>,
                                together with the message to <persName corresp="#p_SPAAKPH1">Spaak</persName> (<hi rend="italic">supra</hi>) and <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>’ message to the British
                                Prime Minister (<hi rend="italic">infra</hi>), only after <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> had delivered it to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName>.
                                In telegram 170 from Brussels, Aug. 22, sent also to London,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BRUCEDKE1">Bruce</persName> reported that
                                he had delivered copies of both messages (740.5/8–2254).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-08-21">August 21,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I am deeply disturbed at the report I have received of the
                                difficulties being encountered at the Brussels meeting and I
                                conceive it my solemn duty to address this appeal to you and your
                                fellow conferees.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I need not recount the vicissitudes which we have faced in common
                                during the post war [era] in our efforts to assure an enduring peace
                                in Western Europe in the face of an external threat of formidable
                                proportions; nor in our efforts to achieve stability with the
                                memories still unfortunately vivid of the internecine strife which
                                has threatened the survival of the cradle of our civilization twice
                                in this century. Now all that we have worked for stands in a very
                                real and immediate sense at the crossroads. The decision is between
                                resolutely choosing the path of statesmanship or that leading toward
                                disunity and chaos.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>There is, I know, no question in our minds as to which road we
                                must choose. Our problem is how we can all get on this road
                                together.</item>
                            <pb facs="1104" n="1060" xml:id="pg_1060"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The grave problems which are presently facing France and her
                                partners at Brussels are primarily and in the first instance their
                                own concern. We must therefore accept the judgment of the Brussels
                                Conference on any points unanimously and willingly agreed. In
                                achieving such a meeting of the minds, however, there are certain
                                considerations which must be borne in mind: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Any changes in the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                        Treaty which would result in further unacceptable delay,
                                        such as would result from resubmission to parliaments,
                                        should be avoided.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Any changes in the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                        Treaty which seriously impair or indefinitely postpone its
                                        surpranational and integrative features strike at the basic
                                        concept of European unity, which in my judgment is the best
                                        and last hope of Europe, and should therefore be
                                        avoided.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Any changes in the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                        Treaty which discriminate against any of its participants
                                        sow the seeds of resentment and breed future peril and
                                        should likewise be avoided.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>In addition, I must recall the various engagements which my
                                Government stands ready to assume at such time as the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> comes into effect. We must, of
                                course, review, in the light of changes, whether these undertakings
                                remain justified.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>If the Brussels Conference breaks up with no agreement, we shall
                                be faced with a great crisis. Our disposition would be, first, to
                                consult immediately with the UK and those <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> countries which have ratified the Treaty to
                                determine urgently what steps should be taken to associate Germany
                                in sovereign equality with the West and to bring about German
                                rearmament.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>I have felt this message necessary in order that there be no doubt
                                as to the vital importance we place on the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> in its essential features and on the need, in all
                                our interests, for its coming into force with the very minimum of
                                further delay.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Since I believe that the other <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>
                                powers and the British should know clearly where the U.S. stands on
                                these problems, I am making the preceding paragraphs of this message
                                available to them.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>