<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="64" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59 D
                                            95, CF 102</note>
                                        <head>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_BATTLELC1">Lucius D.
                                                  Battle</persName>
                                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d64fn1">The information set
                                                forth above is derived from the memorandum printed
                                                here.</note>
                                        </head>
                                        <opener>
                                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1952-02-20">February 20,
                                                1952</date>.</dateline>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p>Following the opening meeting of the North Atlantic
                                                Council,<note n="2" xml:id="d64fn2">See <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 25, above on this
                                                page, for a summary report.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> spoke to
                                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            and invited him to the residence for <pb facs="0157" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> tea. He offered Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            a chance for him to bring any of his people he wanted
                                            to, but indicated that it would be a very informal
                                            session. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> arrived alone.</p>
                                        <p>The conversation was very pleasant, friendly, and
                                            amusing. There was no evidence of any feeling on Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>’s part that he had been subjected to
                                            “rough treatment” in the last meeting in London. Most of
                                            the conversation is of no great interest, but a few
                                            points should be noted.</p>
                                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            expressed his pleasure at the outcome of the London
                                            meetings. He said that he thought progress had been
                                            made. He repeated again several points which he has made
                                            in the meetings, such as the fact that France is the
                                            only country which would give up a national army under
                                            the European defense force arrangement. He spoke of the
                                            fact that time was required to solve all the problems
                                            involved.</p>
                                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>
                                            asked him whether he had consulted his government on the
                                            outstanding issues which are unsettled, and mentioned
                                            particularly the question of security controls. Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>’s reply was not a definite one. He
                                            implied that his government in Paris was working on the
                                            matter, but indicated he would talk to his Prime
                                            Minister, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FAUREE1">Faure</persName>, when he arrived in Lisbon
                                            tonight. The Secretary said that he would await word
                                            from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> as to when it was desirable to
                                            get together again, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> replied
                                            that he would try to tell Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> tomorrow,
                                            at the 11 o’clock meeting of the Council,<note n="3" xml:id="d64fn3">There was no North Atlantic Council
                                                meeting scheduled for 11 a.m. on Feb. 21. The
                                                Foreign Ministers were scheduled to meet at that
                                                time; see <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss>
                                                34, <ref target="#pg_120">p. 120</ref>.</note> when
                                            there should be subsequent meetings on these problems.
                                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>
                                            said he was available at any time. Both the Secretary
                                            and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> agreed that it would be useful
                                            for meetings to continue here on the unresolved
                                            questions left over from London.</p>
                                        <p>There was some interesting talk about the comparison of
                                            the European defense community to the Charlemagne
                                            Empire. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName> replied that there was a body of
                                            opinion in France which considered the European defense
                                            force more nearly like the army of the Holy Roman
                                            Empire, and said that there was some fear that the force
                                            was being created under some sort of “Vatican” policy.
                                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>
                                            said he had not known of this, and expressed great
                                            interest in it.</p>
                                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            brought up the question of the guarantee against
                                            non-secession from the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName> said that he had consulted the
                                            President by telegram, and the President was willing to
                                            do what he could.<note n="4" xml:id="d64fn4">Presumably
                                                the reference here is to <persName corresp="#p_ACHESONDG1">Acheson</persName>’s
                                                message of Feb. 16 to President Truman, <ref target="#pg_78">p. 78</ref>; regarding the
                                                President’s reply thereto, see footnote 4, <ref target="#pg_80">p. 80</ref>.</note> He said he
                                            thought that the President would send up a message to
                                            the Congress when the German arrangements went up, and
                                            that the message would refer to the actions of Congress
                                            on stationing of troops in Europe, on European
                                            integration, etc., and possibly ask for a reaffirmation
                                                <pb facs="0158" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> of the
                                            wish of the Congress with regard to these matters. The
                                            message would also say that the arrangements with
                                            Germany were conditioned on Germany becoming a member of
                                            the European defense force, and would indicate that
                                            membership was expected to be a conditioned one, so that
                                            no interpolation could be given that Germany could join
                                            the force, then resign, and thus meet the condition in
                                            the setting up of the contractual arrangement. Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SCHUMANR1">Schuman</persName>
                                            said that he thought that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ADENAUERK1">Adenauer</persName> had made
                                            a clear decision to stay with the West. He said that he
                                            had no fear that he personally would make any move to
                                            withdraw, because he thought his decision was a
                                            considered one and a firm one.</p>
                                    </div>
                                </body></text></TEI>