<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">122.51T/7–2754</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Dakar</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FCV1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ferguson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                    <lb/> No. 17</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Dakar</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-27">July 27, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <list type="references">
                                <head>Ref:</head>
                                <item>CG’s Despatch No. 8 dated July 15, 1954<note n="1" xml:id="d100fn1">Not printed; it reported the Consul’s
                                        preliminary impressions resulting from his travel in French
                                        West Africa. (751T.00/7–1554)</note>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            <pb facs="0299" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>Subject:</head>
                                <item>Desirability of an American Consulate at Abidjan, Ivory Coast,
                                    French West Africa.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>A recent trip by the undersigned to the Ivory Coast served to a
                                previously held opinion that it would be highly desirable to open a
                                Consulate at Abidjan. I realize that the Department has given
                                consideration to this proposal off and on for a number of years and
                                I realize further that it is probably out of the question from a
                                budgetary point of view at the present time. Nevertheless, it seems
                                desirable to go on the record at this time while the impressions
                                obtained during my visit there are still fresh in my mind and to
                                express my sincere conviction that the interests of the United
                                States Government in this part of the world would be better served
                                if such an office were in existence.</p>
                            <p>The following appear to me to be the more impelling reasons for
                                opening a Consulate at Abidjan: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Economic</hi> As the Department is
                                            aware, the Ivory Coast is, for the foreseeable future at
                                            least, by far the most important of the eight
                                            territories of French West Africa from an economic point
                                            of view. Furthermore, it is the only one with
                                            substantial trade connections with the United States,
                                            principally in the form of exports of cocoa and coffee
                                            but with a definite potential for more diverse economic
                                            reactions in the future. The Consulate General is able
                                            to follow the economic situation in the Ivory Coast by
                                            virtue of published material available in Dakar and,
                                            infrequently, by brief visits to the area in question.
                                            This is not a really satisfactory system and much of the
                                            material we process for reporting purposes is incomplete
                                            and almost all of it is out of date.</p>
                                        <p>With the certain increase in the economic importance of
                                            the territory in the future, the Consulate General
                                            doubts that under its present system it can even hope to
                                            cover it adequately. The Consulate General will be
                                            prepared to support its opinion on the growing economic
                                            importance of the Ivory Coast with facts and figures
                                            should the Department so desire.</p></item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Consular Affairs</hi> While I have not
                                        given any extensive thought to the matter, a reasonable
                                        consular district for Abidjan would include the territories
                                        of the Ivory Coast, Upper Volta and Dahomey in French West
                                        Africa and the Trust Territory of French Togoland. The
                                        Consulate General’s records at the moment show 53 American
                                        citizens resident in the Ivory Coast, 68 in Upper Volta, 20
                                        in Dahomey and 6 in Togoland, mostly missionaries. With the
                                        economic development of the Ivory Coast and, to a lesser
                                        extent, Dahomey, this figure may be expected to increase.
                                        Similarly the number of visa applicants will in all
                                        probability become greater for the same reason. With the
                                        opening of the excellent deep water port of Abidjan and the
                                        increase in trade with the United States, shipping and
                                        invoice services should also be kept in mind.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Informational Activities</hi> The Ivory
                                        Coast with its higher proportion of educated Africans offers
                                        a good field for <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>
                                        activity and during my visit there, I received several
                                        requests for films magazines etcetera. Misconceptions about
                                        the United States are prevalent and I believe useful work
                                        could be carried on. In a smaller scale the same is true of
                                        Dahomey although Upper Volta is probably too primitive for
                                            <pb facs="0300" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/> effective work
                                        and the French authorities certainly would not permit it in
                                        Togoland.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Political</hi> The Ivory Coast is, of
                                        course, the most politically articulate and mature of the
                                        eight territories of the Federation and political activity
                                        is intense and of growing importance. (Senegal is, of course
                                        politically fairly mature but with a French rather than a
                                        truly African coloration.) The Territorial Assembly of the
                                        Ivory Coast, as previously reported, has already gone beyond
                                        the limited powers entrusted to it in the Constitution of
                                        1946 and is acting as <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                                        legislature with the full approval of the French
                                        authorities. It was in the Ivory Coast also that the only
                                        serious Communist inspired disturbances broke out and,
                                        although there seems little possibility of a recurrence of
                                        this type of activity, the fact remains that there exists in
                                        the Ivory Coast a potent native political force under the
                                        popular leader <persName>Felix Houphouët-Boigny</persName>
                                        which could turn against the French the moment the
                                        impression arose that the latter were working against,
                                        rather than for, the development of the area towards
                                        eventual autonomy. It is most difficult to follow this
                                        situation from Dakar and the Consulate General has to rely
                                        too often on official sources and material appearing in the
                                        press. An officer stationed permanently in Abidjan could
                                        undoubtedly establish contacts with important African
                                        political figures, impossible from the remoteness of Dakar,
                                        which could be of very great value to the Department.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Of equal importance is the question of French Togoland which is now
                                in the Dakar consular district but which might as well be in the
                                upper reaches of the Amazon as far as political reporting is
                                concerned. We have no information here about Togoland and no
                                possibility of obtaining any except by an actual visit to the area.
                                I hope to be able to do this during the present fiscal year but
                                infrequent short visits of this type where the officer concerned
                                would be chaperoned at all times by the French authorities do not,
                                in the final analysis, contribute very much to an understanding of
                                the area. With the Togoland problem a constant thorn in the side of
                                the United Nations and with considerable publicity being given to
                                    it,<note n="2" xml:id="d100fn2">For further documentation on
                                    this subject, see <ref target="frus1952-54v03#pg_1168">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1168</ref> ff.</note> it
                                seems most unfortunate that the United States Government has no
                                facilities for obtaining accurate and timely information. Our
                                trouble in Dakar arises out of the fact that there is no official
                                connection of any sort between French West Africa and the Trust
                                Territory and officials here, even though perfectly willing to
                                provide any information they may possess, know little more about
                                French Togoland than I do and have no facilities for increasing
                                their knowledge. While the Consulate General at Accra is, of course,
                                geographically nearer Togoland than a Consulate at Abidjan would be,
                                there seems little likelihood that the French will reconsider their
                                refusal to grant an exequatur for Togoland to any American official
                                not permanently stationed in French territory.Abidjan therefore
                                which is reasonably near Lomé, the capital of French Togoland, would
                                appear to be the answer and would permit frequent visits, some for
                                protracted periods of time by qualified American officials.</p>
                            <p>Reverting to the budgetary situation, I do not think that the
                                establishment of a Consulate at Abidjan need be particularly
                                elaborate and, <pb facs="0301" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/> to meet the
                                needs I have in mind, it could be staffed with one Consul (<gloss target="#t_FSO1">FSO</gloss> 4 or 5), one vice Consul (<gloss target="#t_FSO1">FSO</gloss> 6 or <gloss target="#t_FSS1">FSS</gloss> 10), one American clerk and two or three local
                                employees. Furthermore the expenses of running Dakar could be
                                reduced somewhat with a Consulate at Abidjan particularly as our
                                present authorized complement of two economic officers could be cut
                                to one and much of the money we are now spending for publications
                                etc could be transferred to the new office. Dakar’s budget for local
                                travel could also be substantially reduced.</p>
                            <p>All in all, I am firmly convinced that when financially possible a
                                Consulate at Abidjan would be of great benefit to the United States
                                from the point of view of political, economic and other
                                intelligence, for the promotion of American trade and for the
                                general projection of the United States into an area of Africa which
                                is increasing in importance with every month that passes.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_FCV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">C.
                                            Vaughan Ferguson, Jr</hi>.</persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>