<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="178" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">033.1100 HI/9–2453</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Leopoldville</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mallon</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                    <lb/> No. 51</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Leopoldville</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-24">September 24,
                                        1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>Subject:</head>
                                <item>Alleged Visit of Hickenlooper Delegation to Uranium Mine at
                                    Shinkolobwe</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>There is enclosed a copy and translation of an article that appeared
                                in the <hi rend="italic">Echo du Katanga</hi>, daily Elisabethville
                                newspaper, of September 18, 1953,<note n="1" xml:id="d178fn1">Not
                                    printed.</note> regarding the press conference held by Senator
                                Hickenlooper at Elisabethville on September 5, 1953, at which the
                                Senator stated that no member of the delegation visited the uranium
                                mine at Shinkolobwe during the visit to the Jadotville area.</p>
                            <p>As previously reported, Mr. <persName>Pierre Ryckmans</persName>,
                                former Governor General of the Belgian Congo and presently Belgian
                                Atomic Energy Commissioner, arrived in Leopoldville on September 1,
                                a few hours before the Hickenlooper party. He sent word that he
                                wanted to see me before he met the Senator, and an appointment was
                                arranged for September 2 at 8:00 a.m.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName>Ryckmans</persName> asked me whether any member of the
                                party wished to visit the uranium mine at Shinkolobwe. I replied
                                that I knew nothing about their desires in the matter. Mr.
                                    <persName>Ryckmans</persName> then said that some time ago a
                                Belgian parliamentary delegation had visited the Congo and had been
                                refused permission to visit the mine. He went on to say that it
                                might be embarrassing in Brussels if the American delegation <pb facs="0460" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/> were permitted to make the
                                    visit,<note n="2" xml:id="d178fn2">The visit of the delegation,
                                    which was led by Senator Bourke B. Hickenlooper of Iowa and
                                    Congressman <persName>W. Sterling Cole</persName> of New York,
                                    had created a certain degree of controversy though it was
                                    intended as a good will gesture on the part of the delegates
                                    whose primary destination was South Africa. Shinkolobwe was a
                                    very sensitive spot and every effort had been made by both the
                                    Belgian and the U.S. Governments to downplay the mention of
                                    uranium and the arrangements which had been reached pertaining
                                    to it. For documentation concerning this trip, see file
                                    855A.2546.</note> but that the Belgian authorities had invited
                                the Joint Congressional Committee and certain members of the Atomic
                                Energy Commission to visit the Congo, and that if certain of them
                                wished to see Shinkolobwe, he could arrange it with the appropriate
                                authorities on the spot. I said that I would be glad to put the
                                question up to Senator Hickenlooper, who was staying with
                                Congressman <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Cole</persName> in my house,
                                but Mr. <persName>Ryckmans</persName> said he preferred to speak to
                                the Senator himself.</p>
                            <p>The first thing on the official program was a boat trip on the Congo
                                River, and during this trip I saw Mr. <persName>Ryckmans</persName>
                                talking to Senator Hickenlooper off in a corner where they could not
                                be heard. I heard no more about the matter during their stay in
                                Leopoldville.</p>
                            <p>The party left Leopoldville for Kamina and Elisabethville on
                                September 3. On September 4 they visited the Union Minière
                                installations at Jadotville, which is about eleven miles from
                                Shinkolobwe. They were in Jadotville from about 10:00 a.m. to 4:00
                                p.m., and it is quite possible that during that time two or three of
                                the party could have been driven over to Shinkolobwe and back. I
                                have, however, no official information on this.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="smallcaps">Patrick
                                        Mallon</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>