<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Under Secretary of State ( (Smith) ) to the Secretary of Defense (
                    (Wilson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">196</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recEmfen6T5wplQqD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Title II</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rece9c3648fe9d1e98" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-security-act">Mutual Security Act</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Mutual Defense Assistance Act of</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="196"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">775.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1"
                    >MSP</gloss>/4–653</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SGWB1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_WCE1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d196fn1">This letter was drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WAE1">Wellons</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RJF1"
                            >Root</persName> (<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>) and cleared in the
                        offices of <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SMSA1"
                            >S/MSA</gloss>, L, and E.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-06">April 6,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I refer to the letter to the
                    Secretary of Defense dated March 6, 1952, and the reply to the Secretary of
                    State dated April 22, 1952,<note n="2" xml:id="d196fn2">Neither letter is
                        printed, but see telegram 282 to Ethiopia, Mar. 20, 1952, <ref
                            target="#pg_419">p. 419</ref>. Regarding the Department of Defense
                        reply, see <ref target="#d181fn2">footnote 2, <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>
                        </ref>. For the determination by the Director of Mutual Security of
                        Ethiopia’s eligibility for reimbursable aid, see telegram 377 to Ethiopia,
                        May 15, 1952, <ref target="#pg_423">p. 423</ref>.</note> concerning military
                    assistance for Ethiopia. In <pb facs="0489" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> the letter
                    of March 6, 1952, the Department of State recommended that Ethiopia be found
                    eligible for grant military assistance under Section 202 of the Mutual Security
                    Act of 1951. The reply of April 22, 1952, reported the conclusions of the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff that Ethiopia should be made eligible for reimbursable military
                    aid under Section 408 (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Mutual Defense
                    Assistance Act of 1949, as amended, but that Ethiopia did not meet the
                    requirements for eligibility for grant aid.</p>
                <p>During the year which has elapsed there have been several significant
                    developments which I believe justify reconsideration of the recommendation that
                    Ethiopia be found eligible for grant military aid. Under the agreement to
                    provide military equipment on a reimbursable basis signed in June, 1952, the
                    Ethiopians submitted a request for equipment to arm a division equivalent to a
                    United States infantry division, the cost of which is nearly $4,700,000. Our
                    legislation requires that this be paid for in advance—a condition which the
                    Ethiopian Government is not able to meet.</p>
                <p>Since last summer the Department of State, in closest collaboration with the
                    Department of Defense, has been negotiating with the Ethiopian Government for a
                    military base rights agreement to cover United States military facilities and
                    requirements in Eritrea. In December these negotiations reached a stalemate.</p>
                <p>Last month the Ethiopian Foreign Minister, accompanied by the Commander of the
                    Imperial Ethiopian Body Guard (General <persName>Mulughetta Bulli</persName>),
                    which provided the Ethiopian troops in Korea, returned to Washington with
                    instructions from the Emperor to settle with the highest United States
                    authorities the three questions of: (1) the United States base agreement, (2) a
                    United States military training mission, and (3) the cost of arms to be
                    purchased from the United States. In conferences which officials of the
                    Department of State and Department of Defense have had with the Ethiopian
                    representatives during the last two weeks it has become evident that the
                    Ethiopians are not prepared to conclude the kind of base agreement we have been
                    seeking without assurances of adequate military assistance from us. Adequate
                    military assistance to them means in reality a grant of essential arms and a
                    military training mission. Decisions which have already been taken by the
                    Defense and State Departments with respect to the mission are, we believe,
                    adequate to satisfy the Ethiopians on this score. Now, however, the Ethiopians
                    have made the furnishing of arms virtually as a gift the essential issue. The
                    Emperor’s assignment of General <persName>Mulughetta</persName> to assist in the
                    negotiations has made this fact clear.</p>
                <p>The legislation pertaining to sales of military equipment does not allow this
                    Government to arrange generous long-term installment payments at reduced prices,
                    which is the only basis on which the Ethiopians <pb facs="0490" n="444"
                        xml:id="pg_444"/> could pay for the arms they need. If the needs of the
                    Ethiopians are to be met, and their approval obtained for our base agreement, it
                    will be necessary to make them eligible for grant military aid. It is our
                    understanding that the unobligated and uncommitted funds available for military
                    assistance under Section 201 of the Mutual Security Act of 1951 now amount to
                    $26,000,000. As you know, ten percent of the total appropriation for Title II
                    military assistance can be transferred to countries in the Near East area, and
                    Ethiopia is in that area. It would appear, therefore, that funds are available
                    from which limited grant aid could be provided to Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>A year ago the Department of State believed that the provision of grant aid to
                    Ethiopia was fully justified. The reasons given them have been reinforced by our
                    experience during the last year and can be summarized as follows: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Ethiopia has maintained in Korea for nearly two years a contingent of
                            about 1200 troops who have proved in combat that they are very effective
                            soldiers. The third battalion of Ethiopian troops left for Korea in
                            March, 1953. By act as well as by word the Ethiopians have proved that
                            they are on “our side” and are strong supporters of collective security.
                            The presence in Korea of colored troops from an independent African
                            country is of great value to us in the propaganda war as well as in the
                            Korean war. On this basis alone, Ethiopia’s request for arms assistance
                            deserves sympathetic consideration.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Ethiopia’s armed forces seriously need new equipment. In recent
                            conferences the Commander of the Imperial Ethiopian Body Guard has
                            emphasized that nearly 90 per cent of their equipment, most of it
                            captured from the Italians, has become useless. Grant aid from the
                            United States would put weapons in the hands of troops in existing units
                            and thus increase the effectiveness of Ethiopia’s internal security
                            forces. This is particularly important since last September when
                            Ethiopia assumed responsibility for the defense and security of Eritrea,
                            where the American military installations are located. Thus adequately
                            armed Ethiopian forces would immediately increase the ability of the
                            country to defend itself and would be an important contribution to the
                            defensive strength of the region and the United States.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>In the last two weeks the Ethiopian Foreign Minister has repeatedly
                            emphasized that dissatisfaction and criticism of the Emperor’s
                            pro-American policy which the Foreign Minister has energetically pursued
                            over the last ten years has increased and that now the policy must show
                            obvious benefits, particularly in the field of military assistance. The
                            alternative is for Ethiopia to turn to other countries, for American
                            influence and prestige to decrease drastically, and we may lose a good
                            opportunity to contribute to the sound military, economic and political
                            development of a key country in that region.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Arms assistance to Ethiopia could be cited to the states in the Near
                            East area as evidence that genuine cooperation with the United States
                            and the United Nations, as in Korea, leads to mutual benefits.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The Emperor has let it be known several times in recent months that he
                            would gladly join any alliance or grouping of nations opposed to
                            communism, especially any Middle East Defense Organization. The <pb
                                facs="0491" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> Department of State believes
                            that Ethiopia could become an effective member of <gloss
                                target="#t_MEDO1">MEDO</gloss> when, or after, that organization is
                            formed.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In view of all of these considerations, this Department believes that the
                    President should be asked to determine that the strategic location of Ethiopia
                    makes it of direct importance to the defense of the Near East area, that grant
                    military assistance to Ethiopia is of critical importance to the defense of the
                    free nations, and that the immediately increased ability of Ethiopia to defend
                    itself is important to the preservation of the peace and security of the Near
                    East area and to the security of the United States. The Department of Defense is
                    asked to join in a recommendation to this effect, with the understanding that
                    the total arms assistance to be provided would be related to a program for
                    strengthening the Ethiopian armed forces, thus contributing to the security of
                    American military installations and the ability of the area to defend itself, in
                    an amount not to exceed $5,000,000, and with the understanding that Ethiopia
                    would be required to purchase as much of the equipment needed as it can
                    reasonably afford.</p>
                <p>If the Department of Defense concurs, I will transmit this recommendation
                    immediately to the Director for Mutual Security with a request for a
                    Presidential finding that Ethiopia is eligible for grant military aid. For
                    maximum benefit it is important to complete these negotiations while the
                    Ethiopian Foreign Minister is still in Washington; therefore rapid action on our
                    part is essential.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter B. Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
