<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Accra ( (Cole) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-11-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-11-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="23"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">745G.00/11–2753</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Accra</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CWE1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cole</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 99</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Accra</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-11-27">November 27,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>Reference:</head>
                    <item>Accra’s despatch 151 of May 22, 1953<note n="1" xml:id="d23fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_41">p. 41</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Conference of West African Nationalists</item>
                </list>
                <p>There follows a summary of information which I obtained about the above subject
                    from the Ministry of Defense and External Affairs on November 26 with regard to
                    the Conference of West African Nationalists convened by <persName
                        corresp="#p_NK2">Kwame Nkrumah</persName>, Prime Minister of the Gold Coast,
                    to take place at Kumasi on December 4 through 6.<note n="2" xml:id="d23fn2">For
                        accounts of the conference at Kumasi, see telegram 48, Dec. 8, 1953, from
                        Accra, <ref target="#d24">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref> and despatch 107, Dec. 9, from Accra, <ref target="#pg_69">p.
                            69</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Fenner Brockway</persName>, the Leftist Member of Parliament, and the
                    Congress of Peoples Against Imperialist Oppression had some ideas about calling
                    for a “Pan-African Conference”. COPAIO itself is not, however, involved in the
                    Kumasi meeting, which may to some extent represent a move on <persName
                        corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s part to seize the initiative from
                    COPAIO.</p>
                <p>So far as the Ministry is aware, <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>
                    has invited some 11 “delegates” from Nigeria; six from Sierra Leone; two from
                    the Gambia; two from Liberia; and about eight persons from the Gold Coast. The
                    invitees are believed to include the following: <persName>Obafemi
                        Awolowo</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ADBN1">Nnamdi
                        Azikiwe</persName> from Nigeria plus two leaders of the Nigeria branch of
                    the Convention Peoples Party; <persName>Bankole Bright</persName> and Dr.
                        <persName>Margai</persName> from Sierra Leone; <persName corresp="#p_OS1"
                        >Sylvanus Olympio</persName> from Togoland; and <persName>J. B.
                        Danquah</persName>, <persName>Nii Ama Ollenu</persName>, and <persName>Kojo
                        Busia</persName> from the Gold Coast. In addition to <persName
                        corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>, it is understood that <persName>Kojo
                        Botsio</persName> (Gold Coast <pb facs="0112" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/>
                    Minister of Education) and <persName>K. A. Gbedemah</persName> (Minister of
                    Commerce and Industry) will address the gathering.</p>
                <p>No especial significance is imputed to the “conference” by British officials
                    here, although possibly the Colonial Office attaches more importance to it as
                    being indicative of as trend or as raising possible apprehensions on the part of
                    certain other colonial powers. The Kumasi conference is a “whittled down”
                    version of the proposed meeting discussed in my despatch No. 151 of May 22
                    entitled “Conference of West African Nationalists,” which was to have taken
                    place about last August. It is thought that <persName corresp="#p_NK2"
                        >Nkrumah</persName> is not enthusiastic about the affair, but has to go
                    through with it since there had been so much talk about such a gathering and
                    since his prestige as a nationalist leader depends to some extent upon his
                    posing as the guiding spirit in the concept of a West African federation.
                    According to the Ministry of Defense and External Affairs no delegates have been
                    invited from French territories (other than possibly <persName corresp="#p_OS1"
                        >Olympio</persName>) and the French Consul General here has confirmed that
                    such is the case so far as can be ascertained. <persName corresp="#p_NK2"
                        >Nkrumah</persName> has not, however, been very specific about whom he has
                    invited, since the nonappearance of prominent individuals would if known detract
                    from his standing as an influential figure. It seems doubtful that such
                    prominent personalities as <persName corresp="#p_ADBN1">Azikiwe</persName> and
                        <persName>Awolowo</persName> will appear.</p>
                <p>The agenda for the forthcoming conference is likewise understood to be couched in
                    very general terms and to call for discussion of social, educational, and
                    political themes.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">William E. Cole</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
