<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-02-28T18:36:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-02-28T18:36:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-28T18:36:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-28T18:36:00-05:00" n="372"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">772.00/2–2852: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_AWR1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d372fn1">This telegram was repeated to Paris, Karachi, and
                        Tunis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-02-28T18:36:00-05:00"
                            >February 28, 1952—6:36 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>554. Re: Tunisia. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> (<gloss
                        target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>) called on <persName corresp="#p_GEA1"
                        >Gross</persName> and Hyde. He had come to put before us frankly the plans
                    of the Asian-Arab group to bring Tunisian situation before <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> in March. A majority of the group has already
                    received its <gloss target="#t_instrs1">instrs</gloss> to do so and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> regards it as definitely decided that
                    he will request <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting, probably next
                    week.</p>
                <p>In general, feeling of <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s and group is that
                    Tunisian situation is likely to endanger international peace and it should be
                    ventilated in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> without delay. The firmness or
                    conciliatory character of presentation by <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s
                    and others will depend on attitude of France in <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> emphasized
                    important political fact of 15, or perhaps 16, UN members sponsoring a simple
                    request that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> consider Tunisian situation.</p>
                <p>He reported that this group had considered meeting with US <gloss
                        target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss> and requesting that we take lead in presenting
                    this case. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> feels it is in
                    character with US role of favoring the development of self-government for
                    colonial peoples to do so. He hopes we will not adopt the alternative of support
                    for what he considers a series of French colonial blunders. He invited our
                    leadership in presenting Tunisian situation and if not our leadership at least
                    our cooperation. However, he pointed out that if we cannot cooperate with
                    Asian-Arab group they will still proceed and present their case to <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> commented that he would report
                    fully this conversation and that we had not <gloss target="#t_instrs1"
                        >instrs</gloss> on general question and that on the substance the <gloss
                        target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> must necessarily study all the facts.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> promised to confer further with
                        <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> as soon as we have further
                    info from the <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1"
                        >Bokhari</persName> felt it premature until the general reaction of US to
                    this proposed agenda item is known to commit himself on tactical and <pb
                        facs="0729" n="683" xml:id="pg_683"/> procedural matters. He felt these
                    questions would in many instances be decided by the US attitude toward case as a
                    whole.</p>
                <p>His general theory of case is for 15 states jointly to request <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting characterizing subject as Tunisian
                    situation involving a threat to the peace. Sponsors see in this case pattern of
                    infringement of <persName corresp="#p_BPC1">Bey</persName>’s sovereignty over a
                    period of 70 years with resulting regime governing against will of people. It
                    follows that any former colonial people, such as <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                        >Pak</gloss>s, react against this. Also, situation is deteriorating with
                    numbers of Tunisians being killed and vicious circle results with French
                    refusing to negotiate until atmosphere is calm and their refusal results in
                    disorders. With leaders in prison or refugees, case need general debate in
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Very bad impression is created by refusal of passports to Tunisian Ministers<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d372fn2">On Feb. 12, an officer of the French Embassy called
                        at the Department of State and asked the United States to refuse visas to
                        two Tunisian Ministers visiting Paris who wanted to go to New York in
                        connection with possible Security Council action on Tunisia. The Department
                        replied that it would be impossible to refuse to issue the visas because the
                        Tunisians had valid diplomatic passports. (Memorandum of conversation of
                        Feb. 12; 772.13/2–1252) Telegram 4968 from Paris, Feb. 13, sent the
                        translation of a note received from the Foreign Ministry that day. The note
                        informed the Ambassador that the French Government had terminated the
                        diplomatic passports of the Tunisians. The French intended to exchange the
                        diplomatic passports for ordinary ones, valid for travel only in France and
                        return to Tunisia. (872.181/2–1352) Paris telegram 4995, Feb. 14, reported
                        the Embassy had informed the Tunisians that it could not issue U.S. visas
                        since their diplomatic passports had been invalidated by the French
                        Government. (872.181/2–1452)</note> who possess first-hand info of use of
                        <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>s in preparing and presenting <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> case. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1"
                        >Bokhari</persName> felt <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> is “police
                    station” which, if UN has meaning, should be open day or night to receive
                    complaints from all. He intends to seek a <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> res
                    requesting presence of these Ministers.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> will urge that all co-sponsors of
                    complaint to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> who are not members be invited to
                    sit at table on theory that this privilege has always been granted and number
                    involved should not affect the privilege. In answer to question by <persName
                        corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName>, he added that if US is favorably
                    disposed to case in general, an accommodation could be reached on whether it is
                    desirable to have fewer than 15 come to table.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> felt it would be great political
                    mistake for France, and particularly for US to attempt in any way to hinder
                    placing of case on agenda. He added complaint was so drafted in describing case
                    as a situation to make it simple for all <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    members to favor a general discussion. This general <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> discussion is first primary objective of presenting case to
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BAS1"
                        >Bokhari</persName> understood that final relief to be attained from <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> would have to be worked out in the light of the
                    discussion. Once case is on agenda, however, he argued that all loyal <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> members, and particularly US should come forward
                    with suggestions on what a proper solution should be, and he again invited our
                    collaboration.</p>
                <pb facs="0730" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/>
                <p>We left it that <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> would make no
                    formal move to call <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting until after
                    reasonable time has elapsed to get <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>’s
                    reaction and <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gross</persName> agreed to be in touch
                    with <persName corresp="#p_BAS1">Bokhari</persName> early next week.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AWR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
