<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Dunn) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-06-21T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-06-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-21T08:00:00-05:00" n="436"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d436">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">772.00/6–2152: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DJC1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d436fn1">This telegram was repeated to London and
                        Tunis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-21T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 21, 1952—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>8009. Although govt finds itself in unpleasant position as result of Assembly’s
                    failure to endorse its Tunisian program, and although <pb facs="0826" n="780"
                        xml:id="pg_780"/> narrow margin by which censure of <persName
                        corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> was avoided has weakened his position,
                    we believe yesterday’s debate was not as disastrous for govt and for its
                    Tunisian policies as some press comment here wld have it.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d436fn2">
                        <p>Telegram 8020 from Paris, June 22, gave a breakdown of the June 20 vote
                            on the Tunisian question in the French Assembly. By a vote of 328 to 258
                            the Assembly had rejected a motion to endorse the government program for
                            Tunisia. It also rejected, by a vote of 276 to 224, a motion to censure
                                <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> for his part in
                            bringing about a Tunisian settlement. (772.00/6–2252)</p>
                        <p>A memorandum by <persName corresp="#p_MRH1">McBride</persName> (<gloss
                                target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>) to <persName corresp="#p_BHM1"
                                >Byington</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KRB1"
                                >Knight</persName> (<gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>) and
                            Bon-bright (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>), dated June 22, had an
                            interpretation of the French vote. While the government program was not
                            approved, it was not disapproved either. Since the government had
                            disposed of all opposition motions, Prime Minister <persName
                                corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> was expected to impose the reform
                            program. But, according to the memorandum, any effort by <persName
                                corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> to promulgate a more liberal
                            program would probably lead to his downfall. The suggestion was made
                            that the United States refrain from pressuring the French on the North
                            African problem in the near future. (772.00/6–2252)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Since prog has not been disapproved, govt will definitely proceed with its
                        submission to <persName corresp="#p_BPC1">Bey</persName>. We are informed to
                        this effect by <persName>Binoche</persName>, Dir <gloss target="#t_FonOff1"
                            >FonOff</gloss> African and Levant Affairs. Date tentatively envisaged
                        is June 30, in view holidays fol Ramadan.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Debate and the votes fol it also indicated in our view that more liberal
                        program cld not have got past the Assembly under present conditions. Leftist
                        support for more liberal prog wld not have made up for losses on the
                        right.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>This consideration cld be talking-point for <persName corresp="#p_HJC1"
                            >Hauteclocque</persName> in his dealings with Tunisians. It is true that
                        he has no clear mandate from Assembly to proceed, but he can point to govt’s
                        and <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s difficulties as evidence
                        govt has gone as far as it can.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s position has been impaired,
                        not only due to his Tunisian policy but due to accumulation of opposition on
                        other issues as well. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> has
                        publicly defended him, however, and said it wld be “cowardice” to jettison
                        him; and therefore we feel <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s
                        position in Cabinet, while weakened, has not become untenable.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>It is significant govt did not in fact, seek clear endorsement of its
                        Tunisian policy from Assembly. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName>
                        considered for a while putting confidence question on affirmative motion but
                        decided against it. That decision meant govt wld content itself with
                        rejection of opposition motions. That is what has taken place.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Fact nevertheless remains that <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> has
                    somewhat lost stature in Assembly. Assembly itself, however, by demonstrating
                    its inability to obtain majority for any alternative to govt’s Tunisian policy.
                    Has not acquitted itself brilliantly in the debate either. What has damaged
                        <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s position most was not the
                    total of 227 votes against his person (largely accounted for by Gaullists and
                    Commies) but large number of abstentions. Breakdown of vote not yet
                    available.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dunn</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
