<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="583" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d583">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>
                                files, lot 60 D 268, “Indians in South Africa”</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Department of State Position Paper</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d583fn1">This paper was prepared for the use of
                                    the U.S. Delegation to the Seventh Session of the UN General
                                    Assembly. A memorandum by the Assistant Secretary for United
                                    Nations Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Robert D.
                                        Murphy</persName>, to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> referred to this paper, among others, as
                                    a draft and indicated that it had been cleared with all
                                    interested bureaus. (Sept. 4, 1953; <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hickerson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Key</persName> files, lot 58 D 33, “Notes/South
                                    Africa”)</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                    <lb/> SD/A/C.1/426</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-04">September 4,
                                        1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Race Conflict in South Africa
                                    Resulting From Policies of <hi rend="italic">Apartheid</hi></hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Problem</hi></p>
                            <p>Thirteen Arab-Asian states submitted for inclusion in the agenda of
                                the last General Assembly the question of race conflict in South
                                Africa resulting from the <hi rend="italic">apartheid</hi> policy of
                                the Government of the Union of South Africa. The Assembly
                                established a Commission to study the question; the Commission will
                                report its conclusions to the General Assembly at the forthcoming
                                Session. It also decided to retain this item on the provisional
                                agenda of the 1953 Session.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">United States Position</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The United States should vote for inclusion of this item on
                                    the agenda. (For explanation, see comment below.)</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>While stressing its opposition to race discrimination, the
                                    United States should take the position that the Assembly has
                                    already fully discussed the <hi rend="italic">apartheid</hi>
                                    problem and that further substantive action would be ineffective
                                    and undesirable. Subject to the Department’s comment on specific
                                    proposals, this should be the criterion by which the Delegation
                                    should be guided in the voting. In particular, the United States
                                    should oppose any formal approval of the Commission’s
                                    anticipated conclusions critical of South Africa, or the
                                    continuation of the Commission.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>As a means of disposing of the mater, the United States could
                                    support a general resolution similar to one passed in 1952,
                                    calling upon all states to bring their human rights policies
                                    into accord with Charter principles.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The United States should vote against any proposal
                                    automatically including this item on the provisional agenda of
                                    the Ninth Session.</item>
                            </list>
                            <pb facs="1056" n="1010" xml:id="pg_1010"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Comment</hi></p>
                            <p>This item is already included in the provisional agenda as the result
                                of action by the Seventh General Assembly. It was placed on the
                                agenda of that Session by an overwhelming vote of 45–6–8;
                                consequently it would be unrealistic to assume that our opposition
                                to inclusion would result in deletion of the item from the agenda.
                                Moreover, the Assembly has never asked a commission for a report and
                                then refused to consider this report by reversing a prior decision
                                to retain the item on its agenda. The United States last year
                                favored discussion of this problem. The United States representative
                                stated that the Assembly has the right to discuss this matter and
                                that Article 2(7) cannot be taken as a bar to this right. This
                                statement reflects the fact that the Charter is replete with
                                references to human rights; and in particular United Nations Members
                                have pledged themselves to cooperate in promoting respect for human
                                rights (Articles 55 and 56). However, the United States opposed any
                                Assembly action censuring South Africa and abstained on the proposal
                                to establish the Commission. If the United States should now oppose
                                even the inclusion of this question in the agenda it would open
                                itself to propaganda charges of not only seeking to block free
                                discussion but also of sympathizing with the <persName corresp="#p_MDDF1">Malan</persName> policy. Finally, our
                                opposition to inclusion might seriously affect the Assembly support
                                for our own charges against Soviet Communism based on its
                                suppression of basic human rights (e.g., forced labor).</p>
                            <p>The Report of the Commission will undoubtedly indicate failure to
                                make any progress in dealing with the problem. Discussion of the
                                report should be utilized to demonstrate that there are no practical
                                advantages in further Assembly action.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>