<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Department of State Position Paper</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d584</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">584</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="584"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d584">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> files, lot 71 D 440</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Department of State Position Paper</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d584fn1">This paper was prepared for use of the U.S.
                        Delegation to the Eighth Session of the UN General Assembly.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> SD/A/C.4/123</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-05">September 5,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Question of South West Africa: Report of the</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Committee on South West Africa</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>To deal with the situation brought about by the inability of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on South West Africa and the Union of
                    South Africa to agree on measures for implementing the advisory opinion of the
                    International Court of Justice to the effect that the mandated territory <pb
                        facs="1057" n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/> of South West Africa be placed under
                    a form of United Nations supervision. Although this question was postponed by
                    the Seventh General Assembly, and the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee
                    (of which the United States is a member) was asked to continue its efforts to
                    negotiate an agreement with the Union, meetings between the Committee and
                    representatives of the Union have proved fruitless.<note n="2" xml:id="d584fn2"
                        >On June 25, 1953, the Representative of the Union of South Africa repeated
                        to the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on South West Africa his
                        government’s position that South Africa had no binding responsibility to the
                        United Nations for the administration of South West Africa; and he
                        reiterated the South African proposal that a new instrument, concerning the
                        administration of the territory, be concluded between the Union of South
                        Africa and the three remaining Principal Allied and Associated Powers of
                        World War I (France, the United Kingdom, and the United States). The South
                        African Representative then asked whether the Committee as a whole had
                        decided formally to reject this proposal. The formal response of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee was delivered to the Representative
                        of the Union Government on July 10, 1953. It stated that the South African
                        proposal “did not provide for means for implementing the advisory opinion of
                        the International Court of Justice and did not recognize the principle of
                        supervision of the administration of South West Africa by the United
                        Nations.” The Committee, which had been commissioned under resolution 570
                        (VI) to seek means of implementing the advisory opinion of the International
                        Court of Justice, therefore, stated that it was unable to accept the
                        proposal as a basis for detailed discussion. The Committee also noted that
                        “negotiations for a new international instrument could be undertaken only by
                        the United Nations, acting through an agency appointed by any responsible to
                        it.” (Report of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on South West
                        Africa to the General Assembly, Sept. 21, 1953, UN document A/2475) A draft
                        of the Committee’s response and an explanatory memorandum were forwarded to
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SDV1">Sandifer</persName> (<gloss target="#t_UNA1"
                            >UNA</gloss>) on July 6, 1953. A handwritten note attached to the draft
                        indicates that it was approved by Deputy Under Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>, but that the Secretary did not
                        see it. (<gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss> files, lot 60 D 512, “South
                        West Africa, 1953”)</note> Under the circumstances it is unlikely that the
                    Assembly will continue this Committee, but efforts may be expected to put
                    pressure on the Union to proceed with implementing the Court’s opinion or to
                    condemn the Union for not having done so.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Position</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The United States should continue to support implementation of the Court’s
                        opinion.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The United States should take the position that it would be inappropriate
                        to urge the Union to place South West Africa under trusteeship as such a
                        proposal would go beyond the Court’s opinion. In the event that a proposal
                        to this effect is nonetheless put to a vote, the United States should
                        abstain.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The United States should seek to keep the door open to a possible future
                        agreement between the Union and the United Nations regarding South West
                        Africa. Consequently, while it might concur in a resolution regretting the
                        failure thus far to implement the Court’s opinion, it should oppose an
                        overtly condemnatory resolution.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The disposition of the mandated territory of South West Africa has been a subject
                    of discussion in the United Nations since 1946. The <pb facs="1058" n="1012"
                        xml:id="pg_1012"/> Union considers the League of Nations mandate
                    non-existent and wishes, in effect, to assimilate the territory to the
                    Union.</p>
                <p>The United Nations objects to such assimilation, especially under present
                    segregation policies of the Union; urges trusteeship or some other form of
                    United Nations supervision; and has appointed a Committee of five (Thailand,
                    Norway, Syria, Uruguay, and the United States) to negotiate a satisfactory
                    agreement with the Union.</p>
                <p>The International Court of Justice gave an advisory opinion on the matter in
                    1950, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, as follows: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The mandate continues in force;</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It cannot be altered unilaterally</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The supervisory function of the League should be exercised by the
                            United Nations, but in a manner which would not “exceed” the supervision
                            applied under the Mandates System.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Union Government rejects the Court’s opinion and has made a proposal that an
                    Agreement might be made with the three remaining Principal Allied and Associated
                    Powers (United Kingdom, France, United States) as principals, but not as <hi
                        rend="italic">agents</hi> of the United Nations. The United States and the
                    United Kingdom have indicated they would consider this only if approved by the
                    United Nations. The United Nations, however, finds this unacceptable.</p>
                <p>The United States and the United Nations have approved the advisory opinion of
                    the Court and this has been the basis of the negotiations.</p>
                <p>As the Union of South Africa rejects the opinion, especially the provision for
                    United Nations supervision, no arrangement satisfactory to the General Assembly
                    and the Union has been found.</p>
                <p>In its most recent communications to the representative of the Union (July,
                    1953), the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on South West Africa sets
                    forth in detail the reasons for which the Union’s proposal is unsatisfactory and
                    urges the Union to accept the principle of international supervision “so that
                    the negotiations concerning South West Africa may be brought to a satisfactory
                    conclusion”. To date there has been no reply to this communication from the
                    Union.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
