<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="599" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d599">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>
                                files, lot 60 D 268, “Indians in South Africa”</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of
                                    United Nations Political and Security Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WDW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wainhouse</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Deputy
                                    Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d599fn1">This
                                    memorandum was drafted by Brown (<gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>) and cleared in draft by <persName corresp="#p_MLC1">Meeker</persName> (<gloss target="#t_LUNA1">L/UNA</gloss>) and <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>).</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-31">December 31,
                                        1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="smallcaps">Questions Raised by Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> Regarding U.S.
                                    Position on <hi rend="italic">Apartheid</hi> Case at</hi> 8<hi rend="smallcaps">th United Nations General Assembly</hi></p>
                            <p>The memorandum of conversation between Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RGH1">Hayden Raynor</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d599fn2">Reference is to the conversation of Dec. 17,
                                    1953, a summary of which is printed, <ref target="#d598"><ref target="#d598"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref></ref>.</note> which is returned herewith,
                                raises two questions. First, the Ambassador seeks an explanation as
                                to why the United States Delegation “switched from a negative vote
                                in the committee to an abstention in plenary on the provision
                                continuing the commission.” Second, he states that he had been
                                assured earlier in New York that the United States would oppose the
                                continuation of the <hi rend="italic">Apartheid</hi> Commission and
                                had so reported to his Government which now wished to find out the
                                reasons for the change in the United States position.</p>
                            <p>It is possible that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> will request an appointment with you for the
                                purpose of further discussion of these two matters. A copy of the
                                resolution involved is attached for your use in any such
                                    conversation.<note n="3" xml:id="d599fn3">Not printed.</note> It
                                might also be desirable for you to invite Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLC1">Leonard Meeker</persName>, <gloss target="#t_LUNA1">L/UNA</gloss>, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Ward Allen</persName>, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, who were directly concerned with this case in New
                                York, to attend any discussion you may have with Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>.</p>
                            <p>With respect to the first point raised by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>, the following facts are
                                relevant: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>As the result of a Delegation meeting which considered the
                                        position paper on this item, a telegram was sent to the
                                        Department recommending an abstention on the draft
                                        resolution before the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                                        Political Committee.<note n="4" xml:id="d599fn4">Not
                                            printed; telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 322 from New York, Nov. 25, 1953.
                                            (845A.411/11–2553)</note> In its reply the Department,
                                        on the direct decision <pb facs="1077" n="1031" xml:id="pg_1031"/> of the Secretary, authorized the
                                        Delegation to abstain but suggested, in the event of a
                                        paragraph-by-paragraph vote, that the Delegation vote
                                        against paragraph 3(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (i).<note n="5" xml:id="d599fn5">Telegram <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">Gadel</gloss> 107 to New York,
                                            Dec. 1, 1953, <ref target="#pg_1025">p.
                                            1025</ref>.</note> (This provision, which followed the
                                        request that the Commission continue its study of the racial
                                        situation in South Africa, asked that it do so “with
                                        reference to the various implications of the situation on
                                        the populations affected;” the suggestion that the United
                                        States vote against this one provision came directly from
                                        the Secretary.) Otherwise the Delegation was authorized to
                                        abstain on all provisions of the resolution, including that
                                        one in effect continuing the commission for another
                                        year.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Following Delegation consideration of these instructions
                                        and before any voting took place in the Committee, the
                                        contents of the Department’s telegram were fully explained
                                        by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Ward Allen</persName> to
                                        Mr. <persName>Jordaan</persName> (permanent South African
                                        representative to the UN), and the proposed US voting
                                        position made clear. <persName>Jordaan</persName> stated he
                                        would, of course, advise Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> immediately.<note n="6" xml:id="d599fn6">No record of this conversation
                                            has been found in Department of State
                                        files.</note></item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item><p>The alleged inconsistency in the United States vote
                                            arose from the different way in which the resolution was
                                            divided, for purposes of paragraph-by-paragraph voting,
                                            in the committee and in the plenary. <list>
                                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                                <item><hi rend="italic">In the committee</hi> the
                                                  resolution was divided so that the committee vote
                                                  was taken at one time on <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of the following parts of paragraph 3:
                                                  “requests the Commission (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to contine its study of the development
                                                  of the racial situation in the Union of South
                                                  Africa (i) with reference to the various
                                                  implications of the situation on the populations
                                                  affected.” Since the Department had suggested that
                                                  the Delegation vote against paragraph 3(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (i), the only way in which
                                                  such a negative vote could be cast in these
                                                  circumstances was to vote in the negative on the
                                                  entire clause, even though this seemed also to
                                                  imply a negative position on the other part of the
                                                  clause, on which we would have abstained, had it
                                                  been voted upon separately.</item>
                                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                                <item><hi rend="italic">In the plenary</hi>,
                                                  however, the resolution was divided for purposes
                                                  of paragraph-by-paragraph voting in a different
                                                  way. Paragraph 3(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                                  (“Requests the Commission (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to continue its study of the racial
                                                  situation in the Union of South Africa”) was voted
                                                  upon first, so that the United States abstained on
                                                  this provision. Then paragraph 3(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (i) (“with reference to the various
                                                  implications of the situation on the populations
                                                  affected”) was put to the vote, and our
                                                  Delegation, in accordance with the Department’s
                                                  suggestion, voted in the negative.</item>
                                            </list></p>
                                        <p>(In both Committee and plenary we abstained in the vote
                                            on the resolution as a whole.)</p></item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Following the vote in the plenary the South African
                                        Delegation asked our Delegation why the United States had
                                        changed its position respecting continuation of the
                                        Commission. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName>
                                        pointed out to Mr. <persName>Jordaan</persName><note n="6" xml:id="d599fn6a">No record of this conversation has
                                            been found in Department of State files.</note> the
                                        difference in the way in which the resolution had been put
                                        to the vote in the committee and in the plenary together
                                        with the fact that, as previously explained to the South
                                        African Delegation, the United States desired to abstain on
                                        all parts of the 17-power resolution except for paragraph
                                            3(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (i) on which it voted
                                        negatively.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <pb facs="1078" n="1032" xml:id="pg_1032"/>
                            <p>As for the second point raised by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>, that is, that he was given
                                assurances that the United States would oppose the continuation of
                                the Commission, he was, of course, given no “asssurances”. In a
                                preliminary conversation<note n="7" xml:id="d599fn7">Presumably,
                                    reference is to conversation between <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> on Sept. 17, 1953. The memorandum of
                                    conversation by <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName>,
                                    however, stated only that <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName> outlined to <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> the U.S. position on each of the three
                                    South African items on the General Assembly’s agenda. It
                                    contained no specific comments on the Commission in question.
                                    (745X.00/9–1753)</note> on various South African issues early in
                                the session with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName>
                                before the Delegation’s consideration of the <hi rend="italic">apartheid</hi> item and before it was reached in the Committee,
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> was advised
                                that the United States did not believe the Commission was useful or
                                helpful (a position publicly stated in Committee by Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_BFP2">Bolton</persName>) and that in the
                                Department’s view we should oppose its continuance. (This was in
                                accordance with the Department’s position paper.)<note n="8" xml:id="d599fn8">Dated Sept. 4, <ref target="#pg_1009">p.
                                        1009</ref>.</note> It was agreed that further consultations
                                between the two Delegations would be held when the item was reached
                                in the Committee and specific proposals were made. Contact was
                                maintained with the South African Delegation and when the two draft
                                resolutions were introduced, it was advised that voting instructions
                                had been requested from the Department. As stated above, the South
                                African Delegation was subsequently advised prior to any voting of
                                the United States voting position.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>