<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-18T15:32:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-18T15:32:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">771.00/6–2752: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Legation at
                                        Tangier</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d70fn1">This
                                    telegram, which was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_REJ1">Earle
                                        Junior Richey</persName> of the Office of African Affairs,
                                    was repeated to London, Paris, Madrid, Lisbon, and
                                Rome.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-18T16:32:00-04:00">July 18, 1952—4:32
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>23. Fol summarizes <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>’s position
                                on proposals for reorganization Tangier admin (<gloss target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss>s 433 June 27<note n="2" xml:id="d70fn2">Not printed; after prolonged discussion with his
                                    British colleague, <persName>Thomas Godric Aylett
                                        Muntz</persName>, the U.S. Representative at Tangier,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VJC1">John Carter Vincent</persName>,
                                    suggested the positions he thought the United States should take
                                    on the controversial issues. (771.00/6–2752)</note> and 11 July
                                    10<note n="3" xml:id="d70fn3">Not printed; <persName corresp="#p_VJC1">Vincent</persName> replied to <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName>’s telegram cited in
                                    footnote 4 below and noted the positions taken by the Spanish
                                    and Italian Representatives at the July 5 meeting of the Control
                                    Committee and as well a 10-point proposal, made on July 7, by
                                    the French member of a negotiating working group which included
                                    the Spanish, British, and Italian Ministers and himself.
                                    (771.00/7–1052)</note> and <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 9 July 5).<note n="4" xml:id="d70fn4">Not
                                    printed; Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">David Bruce</persName> responded to the points raised by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VJC1">Vincent</persName> in telegram
                                    433, cited in footnote 2 above, and stressed the importance to
                                    the United States of a vice presidency of the Legislative
                                    Assembly. He also wondered whether the United States should
                                    support a full reinstatement of Italy’s prewar rights in Tangier
                                    given the apparent reservations of the French.
                                    (771.00/7–552)</note></p>
                            <pb facs="0244" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Admin to be neutral. Administrator and Asst Administrators to
                                    be apptd for three year terms.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>No objection to Span Asst Administrator in charge Public
                                    Health and Welfare but with no responsibility for public order.
                                        <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> questions advisability
                                    giving Span Asst Administrator responsibility over labor matters
                                    which we feel shld be responsibility neutral Administrator
                                    assisted by neutral labor adviser if such is necessary. Span
                                    record on labor hardly lends itself to responsibility for such
                                    matters in Internatl Zone.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We support English Asst Administrator for Fin.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> favors selection of Asst
                                    Administrators by Comite Control rather than by nomination of
                                    interested govt but considers pt relatively unimportant and is
                                    willing go along with majority opinion.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>We support Ital request for Vice President Legislative
                                    Assembly: for increasing Ital membership therein to three and
                                    for amending Art 11(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of 1945
                                        Accord.<note n="5" xml:id="d70fn5">Article 11 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>): “The provisions of the Agreement
                                        and dahirs of 1928, in so far as they altered conditions in
                                        which the Italian Government is entitled to participate in
                                        the administration of the Zone, shall cease to operate.” The
                                        text is from <hi rend="italic">The International City of
                                            Tangier</hi> by <persName>Graham H. Stuart</persName>
                                        (Stanford, 1955), p. 252.</note> We do not support Ital
                                    desire to make Ital legal adviser Asst Administrator and have so
                                    informed Ital and Fr <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>s
                                    here.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Believe we shld follow majority lead on matter increased Port
                                    Reps Legislative Assembly.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>We agree that you shld abstain on reestab Mixed Bureau of
                                    Info.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> desires that specific
                                    amendment to 1945 Accord be made to provide for Amer Vice
                                    Presidency Legislative Assembly.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>We see no objection limiting period of duration of amendments
                                    to five years as suggested by Fr.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> supports <gloss target="#t_Brit1">Brit</gloss> Commissioner for
                                    security.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> concurs <gloss target="#t_Brit1">Brit</gloss> suggestion that Art II of
                                    1945 Accord be amended to provide that accord will continue in
                                    force until new convention is drafted.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> supports reorganization
                                    Mixed Tribunal.</item>
                                <label>13.</label>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> not satisfied with Span
                                    and Fr proposals for organization of police. We believe proposal
                                    for two chiefs police with equal authority under admin
                                    impractical and that we shld insist on one neutral chief of
                                    police with Span Deputy in Charge <hi rend="italic">gendarmérie</hi> (or mobile guard) and Fr Deputy in charge
                                    regular police; Span to have Fr Assist Deputy and Frenchman to
                                    have Span Assist Deputy. Police Commissioners to be one-third
                                    Fr, one-third Span and one-third other nationalities. Deputies
                                    wld have equal rank but wld be responsible to neutral chief who
                                    in turn responsible to Administrator who has final <pb facs="0245" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> responsibility for
                                    public order. <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> sees no
                                    reason acquiesce Fr and Span proposals re police and therefore
                                    wishes you discuss proposals further with your Span, Fr and
                                    English colleagues explaining <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> feels strongly this pt and is considering
                                    instructing you vote against this proposal unless satis
                                    compromise can be reached. <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>
                                    will take same line with interested <gloss target="#t_Emb1">emb</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss>s in Washington. Since we are
                                    mtg Fr and Span on other proposals we fail see why Fr and Span
                                    shld not give on this pt. Keep <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> informed your efforts this matter.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_ADG1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>