<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="105" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d105">
                    <head>No. 100.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cramer</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-05-10"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 10, 1878</date>.
                            (Received May 29.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 472.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that yesterday
                        at 12 o’clock m. a newly-built iron-clad war-vessel was launched at the
                        royal dock-yard near this city, in the presence of the King, the royal
                        family, the diplomatic corps, and many naval, military, and civil officers,
                        all of whom had been specially invited to attend, “<hi rend="italic">en
                            gala</hi>”, the imposing ceremony. The occasion furnished a holiday to
                        the people of the city. Said ironclad, Helgoland by name, given it in honor
                        of the sea-fight near the isle of Helgoland on the 9th of May, 1864, is a
                        casemated ship of 5,350 tons displacement, and will be armed with four
                        26-centimeter and one 30½-centimeter breech-loading Krupp guns, besides a
                        number of guns of smaller caliber. It is built entirely of iron, is 250 feet
                        long and 57½ feet wide amidships, and draws 18 feet water. Its armor-plates
                        vary in thickness from 12 inches to 4 feet, and has an apparatus for
                        projecting Whitehead torpedoes. It is altogether the largest and strongest
                        war-vessel of the Danish navy, and large hopes are built upon its efficiency
                        in case Denmark should become involved in a war.</p>
                    <p>In this connection it may be of interest to you to be informed that, in the
                        event of a war between Great Britain and Russia, the Danish Government
                        would—so it is reported in several leading Danish newspapers—issue a
                        proclamation of neutrality, based upon the principles contained in the
                        Danish and Swedish-Norwegian proclamation of neutrality, issued at the
                        breaking out of the Crimean war in 1853. This latter proclamation, among
                        other things, reserved to Denmark the right of closing its harbors against
                        the war-vessels of the several belligerents.</p>
                    <pb facs="0222" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                    <p>Another important measure adopted by the Danish Government is the following:
                        During the past twelve years a part of the Danish army were annually, during
                        the summer months, in camp at Hald, in Jutland. for drilling and maneuvering
                        purposes. But, on account of the present critical state of affairs in
                        Europe, the government has decided not to scatter the army over the whole
                        kingdom, but to concentrate it near its capital. Hence, the army maneuvers
                        for the approaching summer will take place in a camp prepared for that
                        purpose near this city. The government wants to be prepared for any
                        emergency, as regards either the maintenance of a strict neutrality in the
                        event of a war between the two powers named above, or the free
                        self-determination, in case either one of these powers should either
                        encroach upon the country’s right or attempt to coerce it out of its
                        neutrality. For this reason it has also decided to put its war-navy into a
                        state of readiness, for which purpose the Rigsdag at its late session voted
                        a special sum of money. Altogether, there is great uneasiness felt here
                        among the people on account of the critical state of affairs between Great
                        Britain and Russia, and the possible if not probable outbreak of a war
                        between them. As for the sympathy of the public in this case, it is almost
                        universally on the side of Russia.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>M. J. CRAMER.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>