<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 114.Mr. Noyes to Mr. Evarts..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1878-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1878-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="119"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d119">
                <head>No. 114.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Noyes</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-03-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 28, 1878</date>. (Received April
                        11.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 80.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You are aware that for about two years the French
                    Government has been considering the subject of a thorough revision and recast of
                    its tariffs.</p>
                <p>After calling the attention of all the chambers of commerce in France to the
                    matter, and soliciting an expression of opinion as to the reforms and new
                    methods advisable, the administration submitted the whole question to a
                    committee, styled “the superior council of commerce and industry.” My
                    predecessor, Mr. Washburne, informed the Department of these facts in his
                    dispatch No. 1319, of May 16, 1876.</p>
                <p>After many months of labor the proceedings and report of this committee were
                    published, and upon the conclusions it had reached the government framed a new
                    tariff bill, which was introduced in the chambers in March, 1877. The change of
                    ministry and of policy which took place on the 16th of May last postponed the
                    whole matter for the time being. It is now revived by the present minister of
                    commere, Mr. Teisserenc de Bort, and pressed upon the chambers, which will very
                    likely come to a decision at an early day.</p>
                <p>But the question presents itself this year in a somewhat different form, with
                    tendencies not as liberal, and therefore not as favorable to American interests
                    as were exhibited by the bill of March, 1877.</p>
                <p>For a clear understanding of this matter a few words of explanation are
                    necessary:</p>
                <p>Before 1860 the imports levied on foreign goods admitted into France were
                    determined by a tariff of a decidedly protective character. In 1860 the Emperor,
                    acting under the influence of Mr. Cobden, made a special treaty of commerce with
                    England, which inaugurated in France a new and more liberal commercial policy.
                    Its results having been entirely satisfactory, France tendered to other
                    countries the advantages given to England, and made a series of treaties, based
                    upon the same principle, and which are now about to expire or have already
                    terminated. The consequence of this policy was the establishment of a system of
                    double tariffs, one <hi rend="italic">general</hi> and rather high, applicable
                    to all countries having no commercial treaty with France the other special or
                        <hi rend="italic">conventional</hi>, based on treaty stipulations. This
                    double system is now in force, with this additional feature, that in 1873 a
                    supplemental tax of 24 per cent. was added to the general tariff. The question
                    submitted to the chamber of commerce <pb facs="0233" n="171" xml:id="pg_171"/>
                    was whether this system should be continued or modified in some respects.</p>
                <p>The conclusions reached by the majority of these bodies can be summed up as
                    follows: They recommend— <list>
                        <label>1st.</label>
                        <item>Extension of the treaty system.</item>
                        <label>2d.</label>
                        <item>Reduction of the general tariff.</item>
                        <label>3d.</label>
                        <item>Substitution of specific for ad valorem duties.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The superior council of agriculture, commerce, and industry, to which the matter
                    was afterward referred, went a little further: it decided to recommend the
                    suppression of the supplemental tax of 24 per cent. added to the general tariff,
                    with the exception, however, as to cotton fabrics, which were to be still
                    submitted to a certain supplemental tax.</p>
                <p>Acting upon these suggestions, the French Government framed the tariff bill
                    presented last year, which stipulated— <list>
                        <label>1st.</label>
                        <item>That the rates of the new general tariff should not be above those of
                            the previous conventional tariffs.</item>
                        <label>2d.</label>
                        <item>That the duties on cotton fabrics should be increased only 10 per
                            cent, instead of 24 per cent.</item>
                        <label>3d.</label>
                        <item>That an additional tax of 20 per cent. should be levied on all
                            products from countries where duties on French goods are above the
                            average of 15 per cent.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>But the new bill contains nothing of the kind, though it professes to be very
                    liberal.</p>
                <p>In the first place, the duties on a considerable class of articles are raised.
                    For instance, lobsters, which were admitted free, pay now as other fish; pickled
                    oysters and cheese pay nearly twice as much as before; rice and petroleum pay
                    more.</p>
                <p>Secondly. The duties on cotton thread and cotton fabrics and a number of other
                    articles, instead of bearing the supplemental tax of 10 per cent, as before
                    proposed, are to pay 24 per cent.</p>
                <p>Thirdly. An additional tax of 50 per cent., instead of 20 per cent., is to be
                    levied on all products from countries where French goods are subjected to
                    imposts of more than 20 per cent.</p>
                <p>In short, therefore, the new tariff bill imposes a tax of 24 per cent. on a very
                    large number of foreign articles, and threatens the countries which will not
                    submit to these heavy duties, and which attempt to retaliate by imposing
                    equivalent duties on French products, with increase of this 24 per cent. duty to
                    50 per cent.</p>
                <p>The motives which have induced the French Government to so depart from the policy
                    of last year’s project must be stated. In the “Exposé des Motifs,” or argument
                    which heads the bill, the government contends that its object is not to seek <hi
                        rend="italic">protection</hi> for French products, but <hi rend="italic"
                        >compensation</hi>, and to make this more clear, it says: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>These duties will certainly he gradually lowered as new treaties of
                            commerce shall he made. Thus, in the recent conventions with Italy and
                            Spain, the government has abandoned part of the imports levied on game,
                            poultry, eggs, rice, fruits in cans, &amp;c</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Speaking of the additional duty of 24 per cent, which was rejected in the former
                    bill, it says: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>We had done so because we supposed that the economical doctrines which
                            had prevailed since 1860 (doctrines hostile to protection) in most of
                            the large states would continue to be favorably received. We hoped that
                            future commercial treaties would mark a new progress in the direction of
                            free trade, and would so facilitate the extension of our trade and
                            increase the consumption of our products in foreign markets. * * * But
                            the desire to derive from the customs larger revenues seems to have
                            given a new turn to ideas in this matter. * * *</p>
                        <p>In the presence of this state of things arising precisely when our
                            treaties of commerce are all about to expire, France cannot remain
                            unprotected by granting spontaneously <pb facs="0234" n="172"
                                xml:id="pg_172"/> the benefit of the conventional tariff to nations
                            which will not reciprocate and which make their markets comparatively
                            inaccessible to the products of French agriculture and manufacture, and
                            which thus render by their exactions commercial treaties with us
                            impossible. * * * By the general treaty clause applicable to the most
                            favored nation, which is incorporated in our modern convention of
                            commerce, we have given to all nations willing to enter into treaty
                            stipulations with us the certainty that they can secure at least the
                            rates of the conventional tariff. We show thereby that, as we wish to be
                            well armed tor future negotiations, we do not intend to walk backward in
                            the direction of protection.<note n="*" xml:id="d119fn1">As to the
                                50-per cent. clause, the French “Exposé” says: “It is specially
                                directed against the products of countries which levy on our
                                products exorbitant imposts.”</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It can be seen by these quotations that the plain aim of the French Government is
                    to compel, or, to say the least, to induce, other countries to enter into treaty
                    stipulations with France favorable to her, and on this point it seems it can
                    depend upon the support of the Chamber of Deputies; for out of 33 members
                    composing the committee to which the tariff has been referred, 20 at least are
                        <hi rend="italic">compensators</hi>, as they style themselves, that is to
                    say, aiming to get compensation for liberal concessions.</p>
                <p>I inclose herewith an official printed copy of the new tariff bill, with all the
                    documents attached to it.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EDWARD F. NOYES.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
