<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-04-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="164" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d164">
                    <head>No. 159.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">von
                                Schlözer</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Imperial
                                    German Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-04-08"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8,
                            1878</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the appendix to the papers relating to the
                        foreign relations of the United States of last year, in addition to the two
                        circulars issued by you in July and August, to your consular officers, the
                        commercial reports furnished by those officers in obedience thereto are
                        printed.</p>
                    <p>These documents have probably nowhere attracted more attention than in
                        Germany. Their value has been generally recognized there, and in consequence
                        of those reports, more earnest efforts have been made than before to
                        ascertain what can be done by the United States and Germany to increase the
                        trade between the two countries.</p>
                    <p>In the course of these investigations a circumstance has been found to exist
                        which is very prejudicial to the development of German-American commerce,
                        and which, consequently, gives rise to much complaint in German commercial
                        and manufacturing circles. This is the system adopted by some American
                        consulates in Germany on requiring samples of merchandise to be deposited
                        with them prior to certifying the invoices.</p>
                    <p>The regulations prescribed for the use of the consular service of the United
                        States for the year 1874 contain (§ 473) the following directions:</p>
                    <p>“They will, <hi rend="italic">in all proper cases</hi>, require samples of
                        the merchandise to be deposited with them, especially when the invoice
                        descriptions of merchandise are not <hi rend="italic">specific and full</hi>
                        enough to enable them or the customs officers to judge intelligently of the
                        market value without inspection of the merchandise itself. It is
                        particularly enjoined upon consular officers at Aix-la-Chapelle, Berlin,
                        Leipsic, Dresden, and Frankfort, <hi rend="italic">generally</hi> to require
                        samples of all merchandise imported from there of a nature to be
                        sampled.”</p>
                    <p>These regulations afford various facilities, as regards the requirement of
                        samples, which would be very advantageous to commerce if they were always
                        complied with.</p>
                    <p>Certain American consulates in Germany, however—for instance, in the Rhine
                        countries—constantly insist, under all circumstances, that the most accurate
                        samples shall be delivered to them of every single variety of goods that are
                        to be sent to the United States, even if the invoice description is
                        “specific and full enough.” These articles are often of precisely the same
                        quality as regards value, and differ only in color, style, width, length,
                        and similar matters which do not affect their value in the slightest degree;
                        nevertheless, the shippers are obliged to furnish samples of every such
                        variety.</p>
                    <p>This requirement causes them great trouble and inconvenience, to which must
                        be added another circumstance, possessing no less objectionable
                        features.</p>
                    <p>In section 475 of the regulations, the direction is given that “all samples
                        must be carefully preserved, with the cards or statements accompanying them,
                        and must not be suffered to be inspected or seen by others than officers or
                        agents of the government.”</p>
                    <p>Notwithstanding this regulation, repeated complaints have been made to the
                        Imperial Government that the samples deposited by manufacturers with their
                        invoices are frequently left open at several American <pb facs="0297" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> consulates, where they can be seen and
                        examined by visitors without molestation.</p>
                    <p>Persons engaged in the same business thus have an opportunity, by calling at
                        the consulate, to become thoroughly acquainted, in a very short time, with
                        the most important secrets of their competitors, and at once to imitate
                        every novelty invented by the latter.</p>
                    <p>With a. view to remedying these evils, I have been instructed by my
                        government very respectfully to submit the question to you, esteemed Mr.
                        Secretary of State, in the interest of our commercial relations, whether it
                        would not be possible to instruct your consuls in Germany, 1st, <hi rend="italic">to require no deposit of samples</hi> in all cases in
                        which they have no reason to doubt the correctness of the invoices, or the
                        credibility of the declarers; 2d, in case the requirement of samples seems
                        necessary, to content themselves with <hi rend="italic">one</hi> sample for
                        each kind of goods whose value is the same; and, 3d, not to allow such
                        samples to remain exposed to the view of the public, and especially of the
                        competitors of the manufacturers and merchants interested.</p>
                    <p>I should feel exceedingly obliged to you if you would be pleased to take
                        these three points into consideration, and, in due time, to honor me with a
                        reply.</p>
                    <p>Accept, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>SCHLÖZER.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>