<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 204.Sir Edward
                                Thornton to Mr. Evarts..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1878-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1878-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-02-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="209" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d209">
                <head>No. 204.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Edward
                                Thornton</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-02-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19, 1878</date>.
                            (Received February 20.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith, for the
                        information of your government, copy of a dispatch, and of its inclosures,
                        which I have received from the governor-general of Canada relative to the
                        supposed intention of “Sitting Bull” to enter the United States for hostile
                        purposes, and informing me of the precautions taken by the Canadian
                        Government in this matter.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EDW’D THORNTON.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lord <persName type="from">Dufferin</persName> to
                                Sir <persName type="to">Edward Thornton</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Government House</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Ottawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-02-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 14,
                                    1878</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 10.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your dispatch No. 6, of
                            the 4th instant, on the subject of the supposed intention of “Sitting
                            Bull” to enter the United States for hostile purposes, I have the honor
                            to inclose herewith a memorandum from the secretary of state for Canada
                            which will inform you of the nature of the precautions taken by my
                            government in this matter, as well as of the opinions entertained by the
                            commissioner of the north-west police force in regard to the
                            apprehensions of trouble from Sioux Indians.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>DUFFERIN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum upon the dispatch of</hi> 4 <hi rend="italic">th February</hi>, 1878, <hi rend="italic">from Her
                                Majesty’s minister at Washington to his excellency the
                                governor-general relative to the supposed intentions of “Sitting
                                Bull” and his followers to invade United States
                            territory</hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Secretary of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Ottawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-02-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11, 1878</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, fully realizing the consequences which might result from
                            “Sitting Bull” and other Indians making Canadian territory a basis for
                            hostile operations against the United States, has taken every precaution
                            to prevent such a possibility.</p>
                    <p>The United States Indians who have crossed the boundary and taken refuge
                            in British <pb facs="0407" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> territory can
                            purchase ammunition only by permit granted by officers of the mounted
                            police, and those permits are limited to the actual requirements of the
                            Indians for killing buffalo for food. Outposts are stationed at
                            convenient distances between the mounted-police post at the Cypress
                            Hills (Fort Walsh) and the Indian camps, and the Indians have been
                            informed, beyond the possibility of misunderstanding, that they can
                            expect nothing whatever from the Queen’s Government exeept to be
                            protected so long as they remain peaceable and observe the laws of the
                            country; that their claim to be British Indians is denied, and that the
                            Queen’s Government look upon them all as United States Indians, who have
                            taken refuge in British territory, and that if they cross the line and
                            engage in hostilities against the United States they will forfeit all
                            claim to protection.</p>
                    <p>Copy of a letter dated the 17th October, 1877, from Lieutenant-Colonel
                            McLeod, commissioner of the northwest mounted police, to the United
                            States commissioners, conveying to them the result of an interview which
                            he held with the Indians after the failure of negotiations, is annexed
                            hereto.</p>
                    <p>Upon receipt of the dispatch of the 19th January last, from Sir E.
                            Thornton to his excellency the governor general, the undersigned
                            communicated by telegraph with the commissioner of the mounted police,
                            and has already transmitted to his excellency a telegram and a letter
                            from that officer in reply to his inquiries. He has now the honor to
                            transmit copy of a telegram from the assistant commissioner, dated Fort
                            Walsh, February 2, in which that officer reports that he was with
                            Sitting Bull on the 1st instant, gives the number of lodges of United
                            States Indians in Canadian territory states that there is no foundation
                            for the rumors that the Assiniboines and Yanktons are joining in bands,
                            nor yet in the rumor that Sitting Bull intends to move south.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned has given instructions for periodical reports to be
                            furnished to him of the movements of these United States Indians, and
                            will cause everything of importance contained therein to be communicated
                            to his excellency for transmission to Washington.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. W. SCOTT,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of
                                State</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName type="from">James F. McLeod</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">United States
                            commissioners</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Northwest Mounted Police</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fort
                                        Walsh</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-10-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">Octobor</hi> 17,
                                1877</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: In answer to your note I beg to
                            inform you that after the interview of the commissioners with the
                            Indians, I had a “talk” with the latter.</p>
                    <p>I endeavored to press upon them the importance of the answer they had
                            just made; that although some of the speakers to the commissioners had
                            claimed to be British Indians, we denied the claim, and that the Queen’s
                            Government looked upon them all as American Indians who had taken refuge
                            in our country from their enemies.</p>
                    <p>I pointed out to them that their only hope was the buffalo; that it would
                            not be many years before that source of supply would cease, and that
                            they could expect nothing whatever from the Queen’s Government except
                            protection as long as they behaved themselves.</p>
                    <p>I warned them that their decision affected not only themselves but their
                            children, and that they shouid think well before it was too late.</p>
                    <p>I told them they must not cross the line with hostile intent; that if
                            they did they would not only have the Americans for their enemies, but
                            also the police and the. British Government, and urged upon them to
                            carry my words to their camps and tell all their young men what I had
                            said, and warn them of the consequence of disobedience, pointing out to
                            them that a few indiscreet young warriors might involve all in the most
                            serious trouble.</p>
                    <p>They unanimously adhered to the answer they had given to the commission,
                            and promised to obey what I had told them. I do not think there need be
                            the least anxiety about any of these Indians crossing the line, at any
                            rate not for some time to come.</p>
                    <p>In haste, most respectfully, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>JAMES F. McLEOD,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Commissioner</hi>.</item>
                                <item>General <hi rend="smallcaps">A. F. Terry</hi>,</item>
                                <item>General <hi rend="smallcaps">A. G. Lawrence</hi>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sitting Bull Commission, Fort
                                        Walsh</hi>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0408" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in
                            inclosure.—Telegram.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Irvine</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Scott</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort
                                        Walsh, Cypress Hills, N. W. T.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-02-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 2, 1878</date>. (By mail to Helena,
                                Mont.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I was with Sitting Bull yesterday. He is quietly camped with about thirty
                            lodges three miles from our post.</p>
                    <p>At end of Cypress Hills, about sixty miles from here, Spotted Eagle, with
                            about one hundred and fifty lodges, was moving up from east to join
                            Sitting Bull. There are about two hundred other lodges of American Sioux
                            in the neighborhood of Wood Mountain, and there are besides about
                            seventy-five lodges of Nez Percés with Spotted Eagle.</p>
                    <p>No foundation whatever for rumors that Assiniboines and Yanktons are
                            joining in bands, and that Sitting Bull intends to move south.</p>
                    <p>I leave on Monday (4th February) for Wood Mountain; will stop in all
                            Sioux camps on my way.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. G. IRVINE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Commissioner,
                                    Northwest Mounted Police</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
