<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-01-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="340" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d340">
                    <head>No. 335.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Foster</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-01-02"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 2,
                            1878</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 439.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith a copy of a dispatch
                        transmitted by General Ord to the Secretary of War, relative to the recent
                        expedition of Lieutenant Ward into Mexican territory, and the co-operation
                        of Mexican troops with his command. You may express casually to Mr. Vallarta
                        the gratification afforded by the friendly spirit manifested by Mexican
                        officers towards the officers of the United States upon the occasion
                        referred to, as well as the hope and belief that such a spirit, if
                        continued, will tend not only to repress the depredations on the Rio Grande,
                        but will be an important step towards renewing official intercourse between
                        the two countries.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure to No. 439.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Ord</persName> to
                                General <persName type="to">Sheridan</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chicago, Ill</hi>.</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-12-24"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 24,
                                    1877</date>.<lb/>(Received 10.55 a.m.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">General <hi rend="smallcaps">E. D.
                                Townsend</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington, D. C.:</hi></p>
                        <p>The following telegram from General Ord is forwarded for the information
                            of the General of the Army.</p>
                        <p rend="right">P. H. SHERIDAN, <hi rend="italic">Lieut. General.</hi></p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Lieutenant Ward was sent to Rio Grande to find trail of horses
                                stolen and driven into Mexico on 15th instant. Has just come in. The
                                Mexican troops got to the river <pb facs="0599" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> on morning of 20th. Ward showed the Mexican
                                lieutenant the trail, and at his invitation crossed the river and
                                joined the Mexican troops. They followed the trail together all day,
                                going about 25 miles. As it had rained heavily the trail was hard to
                                follow, and another hard rain setting in they found it impossible to
                                follow it farther. The trail was left about three miles from
                                Newtown, and only six or eight miles below where it crossed the
                                river. Ward says there was perfect good feeling among Mexican
                                soldiers and our own, and that the lieutenant offered to go with him
                                anywhere he thought the horses could be found.</p>
                            <p rend="right">“ORD, <hi rend="italic">Brigadier-General.</hi>”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>