<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 468.Mr. Lowell to Mr. Evarts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d473</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">473</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1878-08-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1878-08-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-08-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-08-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="473"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d473">
                <head>No. 468.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lowell</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-08-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 6, 1878</date>. (Received August
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 105.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The appearance of the dreaded <hi rend="italic"
                        >Phylloxera</hi> in Spain seems to me of sufficient importance to warrant my
                    calling your attention to it. It has certainly shown itself in the neighborhood
                    of Malaga, and is reported in some parts of Cataluña. You know how destructive
                    it has been in France, where it has already reduced the area of land in
                    vineyards by something over one-third, and where, in spite of the offer of large
                    rewards, no effectual way of checking its progress has been discovered, and it
                    is to be feared that in Spain, with laxer habits of administration, it may prove
                    even more disastrous.</p>
                <p>The universal depression of business is felt perhaps more severely in Spain than
                    in any other country, and the destruction or diminution of a branch of industry
                    so important as that of wine-making would be a national calamity.</p>
                <p>Besides the great exportation of the wines of Xerez, there is another, perhaps
                    even greater, of the rough Catalonian wines to France, whence, after
                    manipulation at Bordeaux, they are distributed to the rest of the world as
                    genuine products of the Bordelais. The ravages of the phylloxera in France and
                    favorable changes in the tariff seemed likely very much to increase this trade,
                    and accordingly, should the evil spread, it threatens to have a very serious
                    effect on the prosperity of a country already overburdened.</p>
                <p>The remedy thus far proposed and in part adopted, as most effectual, is the
                    uprooting of a belt of vines in order to isolate the infected district. But the
                    weakness of this method lies in the natural temptation to conceal the existence
                    of the evil on the part of small proprietors, dependent on their patches of
                    vineyard for subsistence.</p>
                <p>On every account it is to be hoped that Spain, whose resources would be greatly
                    strengthened by a few years of regular government, may not be the victim of a
                    misfortune which, by increasing the already great misery and discontent, might
                    even lead to grave political consequences.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. R. LOWELL.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
