<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="516" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d516">
                        <head>No. 511.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Maynard</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-04-29"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 29, 1878</date>.
                                (Received June 3.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 246.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Since the signing of the treaty of San
                            Stefano, the 3d of March last (dispatch No. 229, of March 6, 1878), we
                            have had no war, nor yet can we, in any proper sense of the term, be
                            said to have had peace. The attitude of some of the other powers, of
                            Great Britain and Austria especially, has been so equivocal, that an
                            atmosphere of uncertainty has surrounded us and prevented a return of
                            tranquillity. The Russian army to the number of some 90,000 remains in
                            the neighborhood; and the Turks have been busy in collecting their
                            scattered forces and in enlisting new recruits, until they claim to have
                            nearly 150,000 men of all arms just around the city under constant
                            drill, and commanded by Ghazi Osman Pasha, the chief pride of the
                            Ottoman service. This alone would keep up a state of disquiet. For the
                            last two months the city has been full of Russians, chiefly officers and
                            men from the army, usually in full military costume. The Grand Duke
                            Nicholas, in chief command, has come often to the city in the imperial
                            yacht, the Livadia, and interchanged civilities with the Sultan and
                            other Turkish officials. To-day he leaves for Russia, turning over the
                            command to General Todleben. The dashing young Skobeleff has been a good
                            deal in the city, keeping up social intercourse with Americans and
                            Englishmen and other nationalities. “With the German embassy relations
                            have been maintained which ordinarily would have a political
                            significance. Rut it must be remembered that at the outbreak of the war
                            Russian subjects in Turkey were placed under the protection of that
                            embassy (dispatch No. 148, of April 28, 1877); that the ambassador,
                            Prince Reuss, was for several years accredited to the court of St.
                            Petersburg in the same exalted character, and that the Princess Reuss,
                            his wife, is a near relative of the imperial family of Russia.</p>
                        <p>At one moment it seemed probable the relations between Turkey and Russia
                            would amount to an alliance offensive and defensive. But I have reason
                            to believe the Grand Duke ceases to have any such expectation, even if
                            he ever entertained it. As the controversy between Great Britain and
                            Russia takes shape, it becomes evident that Turkey, from political
                            necessity, even if not from choice, will side with the former.</p>
                        <p>The change in Her Britannic Majesty’s ministry of foreign affairs was
                            hailed at first as an indication of peace, recollecting the attitude of
                            the Marquis of Salisbury during the conference (dispatch No. 126, of
                            January 30, 1877). His lordship’s circular of the 1st instant, published
                            here on the 9th, removed that impression effectually. It is hardly
                            saying too much for that able state paper to declare that it for the
                            first time presented the attitude of his government intelligently and
                            respectably as the champion of public law and of the faith of treaties,
                            and entitled to <pb facs="0935" n="873" xml:id="pg_873"/> a voice in
                            settling the affairs of Turkey whether she wished it or not. The effect
                            of this declaration has been unquestionably very great upon the relative
                            influence of Great Britain and Russia in the East; that of the former
                            has rapidly and constantly increased, while that of the latter seems
                            even more rapidly to have waned. To the treaty of San Stefano it was a
                            deadly thrust. Even the reply of Prince Gortschakoff, which came ten
                            days later, equally able, with the added power proverbial to a soft
                            answer, has not countervailed. The two instalments have the common merit
                            of setting forth in a clear light the issue between the great rival
                            powers touching the affairs of the Ottoman Empire. Their bearing upon
                            current events here is so important that they form a part of Turkish
                            history. As such I transmit them, although they have probably been
                            communicated already by my colleagues at London, and St. Petersburg.</p>
                        <p>The Turks are evidently preparing to take advantage of the turn of
                            events. I understand they have not yet evacuated the strong posts of
                            Batoum, Varna, and Shumla, included in the cessions by article 19 of the
                            treaty of San Stefano, and are negotiating for the immediate release of
                            their prisoners held by Russia, in numbers sufficient of themselves to
                            form a considerable army.</p>
                        <p>Russia has not re-established her embassy near the Sublime Porte, giving
                            an apparent advantage to Great Britain, whose diplomatic representative
                            has remained here, and has been vigilant and energetic.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile great uneasiness and anxiety prevail in the public mind.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp; c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>HORACE MAYNARD.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                246.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Marquis of Salisbury’s circular.</hi></head>
                            <p rend="center">[From the Daily Levant Herald of April 9, 1878.]</p>
                            <p>The following circular dispatch, addressed by the Marquis of
                                Salisbury to Her Majesty’s embassies, was issued from the foreign
                                office on the 1st instant:</p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                            Office</hi>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1,
                                            1878</date>.</dateline></opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>): I have received the Queen’s commands to request your
                                    excellency to explain to the government to which you are
                                    accredited the course which Her Majesty’s Government have
                                    thought it their duty to pursue in reference to the
                                    preliminaries of peace concluded between the Ottoman and Russian
                                    Governments, and to the European Congress which it has been
                                    proposed to hold for the examination of that treaty.</p>
                                <p>On the 14th of January, in view of the reports which had reached
                                    Her Majesty’s Government as to the negotiations for peace which
                                    were about to be opened between the Russian Government and the
                                    Porte, and in order to avoid any possible misconception, Her
                                    Majesty’s Government instructed Lord A. Loftus to state to
                                    Prince Gortschakoff that, in the opinion of Her Majesty’s
                                    Government, any treaty concluded between the Government of
                                    Russia and the Porte affecting the treaties of 1856 and 1871,
                                    must be an European treaty, and would not be valid without the
                                    assent of the powers who were parties to those treaties.</p>
                                <p>On the 25th of January, the Russian Government replied by the
                                    assurance that they did not intend to settle by themselves
                                    (“isolément”) European questions having reference to the peace
                                    which is to be made (“se rattachant à la paix”).</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government, having learned that the bases of peace
                                    had been arranged between the Turkish and Russian delegates at
                                    Kezanlik, instructed Lord A. Loftus, on the 29th of January, to
                                    state to the Russian Government that Her Majesty’s Government
                                    while recognizing any arrangements made by the Russian and
                                    Turkish delegates at Kezanlik for the conclusion of an armistice
                                    and for the settlement of bases of peace as binding between the
                                    two belligerents, declared that in so far as these arrangements
                                    were calculated to modify European treaties and to affect
                                    general and British interests, Her Majesty’s Government were
                                    unable to recognize in them any validity unless they were made
                                    the subject of a formal agreement among the parties to the
                                    treaty of Paris.</p>
                                <pb facs="0936" n="874" xml:id="pg_874"/>
                                <p>On the 30th of January, Lord A. Loftus communicated this
                                    declaration to Prince Gortschakoff, and His Highness replied,
                                    that to effect an armistice certain bases of peace were
                                    necessary, but they were only to be considered as preliminaries
                                    and not definitive as regarded Europe; and stated categorically
                                    that questions bearing on European interests could be concerted
                                    with European powers, and that he had given Her Majesty’s
                                    Government clear and positive assurances to this effect.</p>
                                <p>On the 4th of February, the Austrian ambassador communicated a
                                    telegram inviting Her Majesty’s Government to a conference at
                                    Vienna, and Her Majesty’s Government at once accepted the
                                    proposals.</p>
                                <p>On the 5th of February, his excellency addressed a formal
                                    invitation to Lord Derby, stating that:</p>
                                <p>“L’Autriche-Hongrie, en sa qualité de puissance signataire des
                                    actes internationaux qui ont eu pour objet de régler le système
                                    politique en Orient, a toujours réservé en présence de la guerre
                                    actuelle, sa part d’influence sur le règlement définitif des
                                    conditions de le paix future.</p>
                                <p>“Le gouvernement impérial de la Russie, auquel nous avons fait
                                    part de ce point de vue, l’a pleinement apprécié.</p>
                                <p>“Aujourd’hui que des préliminaires de paix vienuent d’être signés
                                    entre la Russie et la Turquie le moment nous semble venu
                                    d’établir l’accord de l’Europe sur les modifications qu’il
                                    deviendrait nécessaire d’apporter aux traités susmentionnés.</p>
                                <p>“Le mode le plus apte à amener cette entente nous parait être la
                                    réunion d’une conférence des puissances signataires du traité de
                                    Paris de 1856, et du protocole de Londres de 1871.”</p>
                                <p>On the 9th instant, the Austrian Government proposed that instead
                                    of the conference at Baden-Baden, as previously contemplated, a
                                    congress should be assembled at Berlin. Her Majesty’s Government
                                    replied that they had no objection to this change, but that they
                                    considered “that it would be desirable to have it understood, in
                                    the first place, that all questions dealt with in the treaty of
                                    peace between Russia and Turkey should be considered as subject
                                    to be discussed in the congress, and that no alteration in the
                                    condition of things previously established by treaty should be
                                    acknowledged as valid until it has received the assent of the
                                    powers.”</p>
                                <p>On the 12th of March, Count Beust was told that Her Majesty’s
                                    Government must be perfectly clear on the points mentioned in
                                    the letter to him of the 9th instant, before they could
                                    definitively agree to go into congress.</p>
                                <p>On the 13th, Her Majesty’s Government explained further the first
                                    condition:</p>
                                <p>“That they must distinctly understand, before they can enter into
                                    congress, that every article in the treaty between Russia and
                                    Turkey will be placed before the congress, not necessarily for
                                    acceptance, but in order that it may be considered what articles
                                    require acceptance or concurrence by the several powers, and
                                    what do not.”</p>
                                <p>On the 14th, the Russian ambassador communicated the following
                                    telegram from Prince Gortschakoff:</p>
                                <p>“Toutes les grandes puissances savent déjà que le texte complet
                                    du traité préliminaire de paix avec la Porte leur será
                                    communiqué dès que les ratifications auront été échangées, ce
                                    qui ne saurait tarder. Il sera simultanément public ici. Nous
                                    n’avons rien à cacher.”</p>
                                <p>On the 17th, Lord A. Loftus reported that he had received the
                                    following memorandum from Prince Gortschakoff:</p>
                                <p>“In reply to communication made by Lord A. Loftus of the dispatch
                                    by which Lord Derby has replied to the proposal of Count Beust
                                    relating to the meeting of the congress at Berlin, I have the
                                    honor to repeat the assurance which Count Schouvaloff has been
                                    already charged to give to Her Majesty’s Government, viz, that
                                    the preliminary treaty of peace, concluded between Russia and
                                    Turkey, shall be textually communicated to the great powers
                                    before the meeting of the congress, and that in the congress
                                    itself each power will have the full liberty of its
                                    appreciations and of its action.”</p>
                                <p>In a dispatch received on the 18th, Lord A. Loftus stated that
                                    Prince Gortschakoff had said to him that of course he could not
                                    impose silence on any member of the congress, but he could only
                                    accept a discussion on those portions of the treaty which
                                    affected European interests.</p>
                                <p>Lord Derby having asked Count Schouvaloff for a reply from Prince
                                    Gortschakoff his excellency informed him on the 19th that he was
                                    “charged to represent to Her Majesty’s Government that the
                                    treaty of peace concluded between Russia and Turkey, the only
                                    one which existed, for there was no secret engagement, would be
                                    communicated to the Government of the Queen in its entirety, and
                                    long before (“bien avant”) the assembling of the congress. The
                                    Government of the Queen, in like manner as the other great
                                    powers, reserved to themselves at the congress their full
                                    liberty of appreciation and action. This same liberty, which she
                                    did not dispute to others, Russia claimed for herself. Now, it
                                    would be to restrict her, if, alone among all the powers, Russia
                                    contracted a preliminary engagement.</p>
                                <p>On the 21st, Lord Derby replied that Her Majesty’s Government
                                    could not recede <pb facs="0937" n="875" xml:id="pg_875"/> from
                                    the position already clearly defined by them; that they must
                                    distinctly understand, before they could enter into congress,
                                    that every article in the treaty between Russia and Turkey would
                                    be placed before the congress, not necessarily for acceptance,
                                    but in order that it might be considered what articles required
                                    acceptance or concurrence by the other powers and what did
                                    not.</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government were unable to accept the view now put
                                    forward by Prince Gortschakoff that the freedom of opinion and
                                    action in congress of Russia, more than of any other power,
                                    would be restricted by this preliminary understanding.</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government therefore desired to ask whether the
                                    Government of Russia were willing that the communication of the
                                    treaty <hi rend="italic">en entier</hi> to the various powers
                                    should be treated as a placing of the treaty before the
                                    congress, in order that the whole treaty, in its relation to
                                    existing treaties, might be examined and considered by the
                                    congress.</p>
                                <p>On the 26th, Count Schouvaloff wrote to Lord Derby that the
                                    imperial cabinet deemed it its duty to adhere to the declaration
                                    which he was ordered to make to the Government of the Queen, and
                                    which was stated in the letter which he had the honor to address
                                    to him dated the 19th of March.</p>
                                <p>As different interpretations had been given to the “liberty of
                                    appreciation and action” which Russia thought it right to
                                    reserve to herself at the congress, the imperial cabinet defined
                                    the meaning of the term in the following manner:</p>
                                <p>“It leaves to the other powers the liberty of raising such
                                    questions at the congress as they might think it fit to discuss,
                                    and reserves to itself the liberty of accepting or not accepting
                                    the discussion of these questions.”</p>
                                <p>Her Majesty’s Government deeply regret the decision which the
                                    Russian Government have thus announced.</p>
                                <p>How far the stipulations of the treaty of San Stefano would
                                    commend themselves as expedient to the judgment of the European
                                    powers, it is not at present possible to decide. But even if a
                                    considerable portion of them were such as were likely to be
                                    approved, the reservation of a right, at discretion, to refuse
                                    to accept a discussion of them in a congress of the powers would
                                    not on that account be the less open to the most serious
                                    objection. An inspection of the treaty will sufficiently show
                                    that Her Majesty’s Government could not, in a European congress,
                                    accept any partial or fragmentary examination of its provisions.
                                    Every material stipulation which it contains involves a
                                    departure from the treaty of 1856.</p>
                                <p>By the declaration annexed to the first protocol of the
                                    conference held in London in 1871, the plenipotentiaries of the
                                    great powers, including Russia, recognized “that it is an
                                    essential principle of the law of nations that no power can
                                    liberate itself from the engagements of a treaty, nor modify the
                                    stipulations thereof, unless with the consent of the contracting
                                    powers by means of an amicable arrangement.”</p>
                                <p>It is impossible for Her Majesty’s Government, without violating
                                    the spirit of this declaration, to acquiesce in the withdrawal
                                    from the cognizance of the powers of articles in the new treaty
                                    which are modifications of existing treaty engagements, and
                                    inconsistent with them.</p>
                                <p>The general nature of the treaty and the combined effect of its
                                    several stipulations upon the interests of the signatory powers
                                    furnish another and a conclusive reason against the separate
                                    discussion of any one portion of those stipulations apart from
                                    the rest.</p>
                                <p>The most important consequences to which the treaty practically
                                    leads are those which result from its action, as a whole, upon
                                    the nations of Southeastern Europe. By the articles erecting the
                                    new Bulgaria, a strong Slav state will be created under the
                                    auspices and control of Russia, possessing important harbors
                                    upon the shores of the Black Sea and the Archipelago, and
                                    conferring upon that power a preponderating influence over both
                                    political and commercial relations in those seas. It will be so
                                    constituted as to merge in the dominant Slav majority a
                                    considerable mass of population which is Greek in race and
                                    sympathy, and which views with alarm the prospect of absorption
                                    in a community alien to it not only in nationality, but in
                                    political tendency and in religious allegiance. The provisions
                                    by which this new state is to be subjected to a ruler whom
                                    Russia will practically choose, its administration framed by a
                                    Russian commissary, and the first working of its institutions
                                    commenced under the control of a Russian army, sufficiently
                                    indicate the political system of which in future it is to form
                                    apart.</p>
                                <p>Stipulations are added which will extend this influence even
                                    beyond the boundaries of the new Bulgaria. The provision, in
                                    itself highly commendable, of improved institutions for the
                                    populations of Thessaly and Epirus, is accompanied by a
                                    condition that the law by which they are to be secured shall be
                                    framed under the supervision of the Russian Government. It is
                                    followed by engagements for the protection of members of the
                                    Russian Church, which are certainly not more limited in their
                                    scope than those articles of the treaty of Kainardji upon which
                                    the claims were founded which were abrogated in 1856. Such
                                    stipulations cannot be viewed with satisfaction either by the
                                    Government of Greece or by the powers to whom all parts of the
                                    Ottoman Empire are <pb facs="0938" n="876" xml:id="pg_876"/> a
                                    matter of common interest. The general effect of this portion of
                                    the treaty will he to increase the power of the Russian Empire
                                    in the countries and on the shores where a Greek population
                                    dominates, not only to the prejudice of that nation, hut also of
                                    every country having interests on the coasts of the
                                    Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                                <p>The territorial severance from Constantinople of the Greek,
                                    Albanian, and Slavonic provinces which are still left under the
                                    Government of the Porte, will cause their administration to be
                                    attended with constant difficulty, and even embarrassment; and
                                    will not only deprive the Porte of the political strength which
                                    might have arisen from their possession, but will expose the
                                    inhabitants to a serious risk of anarchy.</p>
                                <p>By the other portions of the treaty analogous results are arrived
                                    at upon other frontiers of the Ottoman Empire. The compulsory
                                    alienation of Bessarabia from Roumania, the extension of
                                    Bulgaria to the shores of the Black Sea, which are principally
                                    inhabited by Mussulmans and Greeks, and the acquisition of the
                                    important harbor of Batoum, will make the will of the Russian
                                    Government dominant over all the vicinity of the Black Sea. The
                                    acquisition of the strongholds of Armenia will place the
                                    population of that province under the immediate influence of the
                                    power which holds them; while the extensive European trade which
                                    now passes from Trebizond to Persia will, in consequence of the
                                    cessions in Kurdistan, be liable to be arrested at the pleasure
                                    of the Russian Government by the prohibitory barriers of their
                                    commercial system.</p>
                                <p>Provision is made for an indemnity, of which the amount is
                                    obviously beyond the means of Turkey to discharge, even if the
                                    fact be left out of account that any surplus of its revenues is
                                    already hypothecated to other creditors. The mode of payment of
                                    this indemnity is left, in vague language, to ulterior
                                    negotiations between Russia and the Porte. Payment may be
                                    demanded immediately, or it may be left as an unredeemed and
                                    unredeemable obligation to weigh down the independence of the
                                    Porte for many years. Its discharge may be commuted into a yet
                                    larger cession of territory, or it may take the form of special
                                    engagements subordinating in all things the policy of Turkey to
                                    that of Russia. It is impossible not to recognize in this
                                    provision an instrument of formidable efficiency for the
                                    coercion of the Ottoman Government, if the necessity for
                                    employing it should arise.</p>
                                <p>Objections may be urged individually against these various
                                    stipulations; and arguments, on the other hand, may possibly be
                                    advanced to show that they are not individually inconsistent
                                    with the attainment of the lasting peace and stability which it
                                    is the highest object of all present negotiations to establish
                                    in the provinces of European and Asiatic Turkey. But their
                                    separate and individual operation, whether defensive or not, is
                                    not that which should engage the most earnest attention of the
                                    signatory powers. Their combined effect, in addition to the
                                    results upon the Greek population and upon the balance of
                                    maritime power which have been already pointed out, is to
                                    depress, almost to the point of entire subjection, the political
                                    independence of the Government of Constantinople. The formal
                                    jurisdiction of that government extends over geographical
                                    positions which must, under all circumstances, be of the deepest
                                    interest to Great Britain. It is in the power of the Ottoman
                                    Government to close or to open the straits which form the
                                    natural highway of nations between the Ægean Sea and the Euxine.
                                    Its dominion is recognized at the head of the Persian Gulf, on
                                    the shores of the Levant, and in the immediate neighborhood of
                                    the Suez Canal. It cannot be otherwise than a matter of extreme
                                    solicitude to this country that the government to which this
                                    jurisdiction belongs should be so closely pressed by the
                                    political outposts of a greatly superior power that its
                                    independent action, and even existence, is almost impossible.
                                    These results arise not so much from the language of any single
                                    article in the treaty as from the operation of the instrument as
                                    a whole. A discussion limited to articles selected by one power
                                    in the Congress would be an illusory remedy for the dangers to
                                    English interests and to the permanent peace of Europe, which
                                    would result from the state of things which the treaty proposes
                                    to establish.</p>
                                <p>The object of Her Majesty’s Government at the Constantinople
                                    conference was to give effect to the policy of reforming Turkey
                                    under the Ottoman Government, removing well-grounded grievances,
                                    and thus preserving the empire until the time when it might be
                                    able to dispense with protective guarantees. It was obvious that
                                    this could only be brought about by rendering the different
                                    populations so far contented with their position as to inspire
                                    them with a spirit of patriotism, and make them ready to defend
                                    the Ottoman Empire as loyal subjects of the Sultan.</p>
                                <p>The policy was frustrated by the unfortunate resistance of the
                                    Ottoman Government itself, and, under the altered circumstances
                                    of the present time, the same result cannot be attained to the
                                    same extent by the same means. Large changes may, and no doubt
                                    will, be requisite in the treaties by which Southeastern Europe
                                    has hitherto been ruled. But good government, assured peace, and
                                    freedom, for populations to whom those blessings have been
                                    strange, are still the objects which this country earnestly
                                    desires to secure.</p>
                                <p>In requiring a fall consideration of the general interests which
                                    the new arrangements threaten to affect, Her Majesty’s
                                    Government believe that they are taking the surest means of
                                    securing those objects. They would willingly have entered a
                                    Congress in <pb facs="0939" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/> which the
                                    stipulations in question could have been examined as a whole, in
                                    their relation to existing treaties, to the acknowledged rights
                                    of Great Britain and of other powers, and to the beneficent ends
                                    which the united action of Europe has always been directed to
                                    secure. But neither the interests which Her Majesty’s Government
                                    are specially bound to guard nor the well-being of the regions
                                    with which the treaty deals would be consulted by the assembling
                                    of a Congress whose deliberations were to be restricted by such
                                    reservations as those which have been laid down by Prince
                                    Gortschakoff in his most recent communication.</p>
                                <p>Your excellency will read this dispatch to the minister of
                                    foreign affairs, and give him a copy of it.</p>
                                <p>I am, &amp; c.,</p>
                                <closer><signed>SALISBURY.</signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                    246.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <p rend="center">[From the Daily Levant Herald of April 20, 1878.]</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">The Russian reply to
                                England.</hi></p>
                            <p>The St. Petersburg official journals of the 11th instant publish
                                Prince Gortschakoff’s circular in answer to that of Lord Salisbury
                                and a long annexed <hi rend="italic">pro memoriâ</hi>. The circular
                                is as follows:</p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Circular of the Chancellor of the Empire
                                        to the Ambassadors of Russia at Berlin, Paris, London,
                                        Vienna, and Rome.</hi></head>
                                <dateline><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">St.
                                        Petersburg</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1878-03-28" to="1878-04-09"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 28 (<hi rend="italic">April</hi> 9),
                                        1878</date>.</dateline>
                                <p>Lord A. Loftus has communicated to me the circular addressed by
                                    the Marquis of Salisbury to the great powers, under date April
                                    1. It has been subjected to a careful examination, and we duly
                                    recognize the frankness with which it sets forth the views of
                                    the Government of Her Britannic Majesty on the preliminary
                                    treaty of peace of San Stefano. We therein find presented in
                                    long detail the objections of the English cabinet, bat we look
                                    in vain for any proposals it might be disposed to suggest toward
                                    a practical solution of the present crisis in the East. The
                                    Marquis of Salisbury tells us what the English Government does
                                    not wish, but tells us nothing as to what it does wish. We think
                                    it would be serviceable if his lordship would be good enough to
                                    make this latter point known in order to promote an
                                    understanding of the situation. As regards the declaration of
                                    the views of the Government of Her Britannic Majesty on the
                                    subject of the congress, I can only recall the course which on
                                    their side the imperial cabinet have followed in this question.
                                    It has officially communicated to the great powers the text of
                                    the preliminary treaty of San Stefano with an explanatory map.
                                    We added that at the congress, if it were to meet, each of the
                                    powers there represented would have full liberty of appreciation
                                    and action. In claiming the same right for Russia we can only
                                    reiterate the same declaration. Be pleased to communicate the
                                    present dispatch, with its annex, to the government to which you
                                    are accredited.</p>
                                <p>The annex to the circular is entitled “Pro Memoriâ,” and is as
                                    follows: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>It is not accurate to say that the treaty of San
                                            Stefano has created a new Bulgaria or a very strong Slav
                                            State under the control of Russia. Bulgaria existed,
                                            though in a state of oppression. Europe perceived this,
                                            and was desirous of providing a remedy. The
                                            Constantinople conference indicated the measures deemed
                                            necessary to attain this end. In suggesting these
                                            measures the plenipotentiaries assembled in the
                                            Constantinople conference certainly did not think of
                                            rendering them inefficacious. It should be admitted that
                                            they contemplated the endowment of Bulgaria with a
                                            national existence and a real administrative autonomy.
                                            In such case the Bulgarian State, though divided in two
                                            provinces, would have been constituted in germ, and this
                                            germ, developing itself under the <hi rend="italic">œgis</hi> of Europe, would have achieved the result
                                            which the treaty of San Stefano is designed to bring to
                                            maturity. The refusal made by the Porte, and the war by
                                            which it was followed, did not permit, in the avowal of
                                            the Marquis of Salisbury himself, of a return pure and
                                            simple to the programme of the conference of
                                            Constantinople. The treaty of San Stefano only makes it
                                            obligatory on the Porte to consent to a programme of
                                            reforms more complete, more <hi rend="italic">précis</hi>, and more practical; but even the fact
                                            that the treaty of San Stefano is a preliminary one
                                            indicates that in the mind of the imperial cabinet it is
                                            only a matter of principle, without prejudging
                                            definitely the application, which requires technical
                                            studies, an exact appreciation of geographical
                                            necessities, and the conciliation of numerous interests.
                                            It is <pb facs="0940" n="878" xml:id="pg_878"/> because
                                            of this that many articles are expressed in vague terms,
                                            so as to leave room for ulterior under standings as to
                                            the modifications deemed indispensable.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>The treaty of San Stefano has not placed the new state
                                            under the control of Russia. The imperial cabinet has
                                            done only what it accomplished in 1830 for
                                            Moldo-Wallachia. Experience has demonstrated that the
                                            work of that period in these principalities was useful
                                            by contributing to the prosperity of these provinces. It
                                            was not perceived that the result would be such a
                                            preponderance of the influence of Russia as to disturb
                                            the European equilibrium. It may be added that if
                                            Moldo-Wallachia, which owes its existence to and borders
                                            upon Russia, has been able to make itself independent of
                                            her, with yet stronger reason should one count on the
                                            same result for Bulgaria, the territory of which would
                                            be separated from Russia in the foreseen event of a
                                            cession of the Dobrudja to Roumania.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>The <hi rend="italic">maximum</hi> term of two years
                                            has been assigned to the provisional occupation of
                                            Bulgaria because this lapse of time has been thought
                                            necessary to maintain order and peace, to protect the
                                            Christian and Mussulman populations against reciprocal
                                            reprisals, to reorganize the country, and to introduce
                                            national institutions, the native militia, &amp; c.; and
                                            also because, if the occupation had been indefinite, the
                                            fact might-have been regarded as a step towards a <hi rend="italic">prise de possession</hi>, which the
                                            imperial cabinet has never contemplated. But it is
                                            unnecessary to say that, this term being approximate,
                                            the imperial cabinet is quite ready to shorten it as
                                            much as possible without endangering the success of the
                                            difficult work which it is proposed to carry out in the
                                            interests of general peace.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>The delimitation of Bulgaria has been indicated only
                                            in general terms. The sole principle which has been laid
                                            down is that of the majority of the population, and
                                            certainly anything more equitable and rational can
                                            hardly be imagined. It meets the objections suggested by
                                            the difference of the races of the minority, whose
                                            interests, moreover, have been guarded by express
                                            stipulations. But the application of this principle has
                                            been reserved for a mixed commission, whose local
                                            investigations can alone dissipate the doubt and
                                            uncertainty which still exist in respect of these vexed
                                            questions. The preliminary delimitation is opposed on
                                            the ground that it assigns to Bulgaria some ports on the
                                            Black Sea, but the Constantinople conference itself
                                            decided that unless these countries debouched on the sea
                                            they could not prosper. With regard to the ports of the
                                            Ægean Sea, the commercial development of Bulgaria has
                                            alone been in view. Certainly, Russia will not profit by
                                            this development so much as England and the powers whose
                                            Mediterranean commerce—much more active than that of
                                            Russia—has always been a powerful lever for the
                                            maintenance of their political influence.</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>The preliminary treaty in no way places Bulgaria under
                                            the domination of a chief chosen by Russia. It is
                                            formally stipulated that the governor shall be elected
                                            by native administrative councils, with the confirmation
                                            of the Porte and the assent of Europe, and that members
                                            of the reigning dynasties shall not be eligible for the
                                            office. It is not seen what better guarantees could be
                                            given of the liberty of elections. As to the
                                            organization of the principality, that is left to an
                                            assembly of native notables. The Russian imperial
                                            commissary has only a right of <hi rend="italic">surveillance</hi> to exercise in. concert with an
                                            Ottoman commissary. Moreover, an understanding between
                                            the great powers and the Porte is expressly reserved, in
                                            order that the Russian imperial commissary may be
                                            associated with special delegates. Meanwhile, the
                                            provisional measures taken by the Russian authorities
                                            for the administration of the country are far from being
                                            framed with the view, as has been affirmed, of making
                                            Bulgaria a part of the Russian political system. Almost
                                            no change has been made in institutions to which the
                                            country was accustomed. Care has only been taken with
                                            the execution, which was defective. The slight
                                            alterations which have been effected are the abolition
                                            of the <hi rend="italic">redevance</hi> for redemption
                                            from the military service, the abolition of the tithes
                                            and their replacement by a more normal impost, the
                                            abolition of the rent of the imposts, which was the
                                            source of the principal abuses, and the right attributed
                                            to the Christian inhabitants in mixed localities to
                                            refuse at election time those Mussulmans who had
                                            distinguished themselves by acts of persecution towards
                                            the Christian population. The state of siege to which
                                            the country was reduced during the war rendering the
                                            nomination of Russian governors indispensable,
                                            Bulgarians have in all quarters been appointed
                                            vice-governors, in order that after the peace, according
                                            to the rapidity with which tranquillity is restored in
                                            the country, these vice-governors might be able to
                                            replace the Russian governors without causing any
                                            interruption to the administration of the country. The
                                            exclusive object of all these provisional measures has
                                            been to protect the national development and to render
                                            possible the reunion of the first Bulgarian assembly
                                            called to regulate the institutions of the
                                            principality.</item>
                                        <label>6.</label>
                                        <item>The assertion that the treaty of San Stefano has
                                            extended the influence of Russia beyond the limits of
                                            Bulgaria, while stipulating for ameliorated institutions
                                            for Epirus and Thessaly, affords room for surprise. If
                                            Russia had stipulated for nothing in favor of those
                                            provinces, she would have been accused of sacrificing
                                            the Greeks to the Slavs; if she had sought to obtain for
                                            them the vassal autonomy which is condemned in Bulgaria,
                                            she would have been accused of entirely destroying the
                                            Ottoman <pb facs="0941" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/> Empire
                                            and implanting Russian influence in its place. The
                                            imperial cabinet has always understood the mission
                                            which, in a Christian sense, history assigns to her in
                                            the East, without distinction of race or of creed. If
                                            she has stipulated for conditions’ more complete and
                                            more precise in favor of Bulgaria, it is because that
                                            country had been the principal cause and theater of the
                                            war, and that Russia had acquired positive belligerent
                                            rights. But in limiting itself to stipulating for
                                            ameliorated institutions for the Greek provinces it
                                            reserved to the great powers an extensive right of
                                            protest. It is equally inaccurate that the treaty of San
                                            Stefano stipulated that these institutions should be
                                            placed under the direction of Russia. The general type
                                            to which they have been assimilated by the treaty is
                                            that of the Cretan regulation, which has been <hi rend="italic">octroyé</hi> by the Porte under the
                                            influence of the great powers. The treaty stipulates
                                            that the application should be made by a special
                                            commission, or that the native element should be largely
                                            represented. It obliges the Porte, it is true, to
                                            consult Russia before putting it in execution, but does
                                            not interdict the Porte from equally consulting the
                                            representatives of the friendly powers.</item>
                                        <label>7.</label>
                                        <item>The subsequent clause, concerning the protection of
                                            the members of the Russian Church, must have been ill
                                            understood to be compared to that of the treaty of,
                                            Kainardji, abolished in 1856. The clause of Kainardji
                                            concerned the Greek Orthodox body, and could embrace all
                                            the Christian subjects of the Sultan who professed the
                                            rite. The treaty of San Stefano mentions exclusively
                                            monks, ecclesiastics, and pilgrims who are Russian or of
                                            Russian origin, and stipulates for them only the rights,
                                            advantages, and privileges belonging to the
                                            ecclesiastics of other nationalities. From all this it
                                            is impossible to regard as just the assertion that the
                                                <hi rend="italic">ensemble</hi> of these
                                            stipulations of San Stefano is of such a nature as to
                                            extend the power of the Russian Empire in countries
                                            where the Greek population predominates, to the
                                            prejudice of this nation and to all countries having
                                            interests in the East and in the Mediterranean.</item>
                                        <label>8.</label>
                                        <item>One may equally find exaggerations in the affirmation
                                            that the <hi rend="italic">ensemble</hi> of the
                                            stipulations of San Stefano as to the retrocession of
                                            Roumanian Bessarabia, the extension of Bulgaria up to
                                            the Black Sea, and the acquisition of the port of Batoum
                                            render the will of Russia, predominant in the whole
                                            neighborhood of the Black Sea. Russia has powerfully
                                            contributed in the past to emancipate Greece and
                                            Roumania, but has not reaped so much benefit from it as
                                            have the other powers. The retrocession of Roumanian
                                            Bessarabia would be only a return of an order of things
                                            modified twenty-two years ago for reasons which have no
                                            longer a <hi rend="italic">raison d’être</hi>, nor legal
                                            title, nor even pretext, since that the liberty of the
                                            navigation of the Danube has been placed under the
                                            control and guarantee of a <hi rend="italic">commission
                                                internationale</hi>, and especially at the moment
                                            when Roumania proclaimed her independence and when
                                            Europe seemed disposed to recognize it. It must be added
                                            that this retrocession does not include all the part of
                                            Bessarabia ceded in 1856. The delta of the Danube is
                                            excluded from it, and the project of the Russian
                                            Government is to give it to Roumania, from which it had
                                            been taken in 1857. This circumstance reduces
                                            considerably the importance of the desired retrocession
                                            from the point of view of influence over the navigation
                                            of the mouths of the Danube.</item>
                                        <label>9.</label>
                                        <item>Batoum is the only good port in this district
                                            available for the commerce and the security of Russia
                                            drawn from a war which she has waged single-handed and
                                            which has cost her so much. It is not then by any means
                                            a gratuitous cession, it is far from being the
                                            equivalent of the pecuniary indemnity which it would
                                            represent.</item>
                                        <label>10.</label>
                                        <item>As to the acquisitions in Armenia, they only possess a
                                            defensive value. It is possible that England would
                                            rather see these strong positions in the hands of the
                                            Turks, but from the same motives Russia sets a value
                                            upon the possession of them for her own security, so as
                                            not to have to lay siege to them in each war, as in the
                                            case of the fortress of Kars, which she has been obliged
                                            to take three times within half a century. Territorial
                                            cessions are a natural consequence of war. If England
                                            had wished to spare them to Turkey, she had only to ally
                                            herself with Russia, as was proposed to her on two
                                            occasions, first, by the Berlin Memorandum and then by
                                            the mission of Count Elston Soumarokoff to Vienna, in
                                            order to put a united maritime pressure on the Porte,
                                            which would probably have sufficed to obtain the ends
                                            acquired to-day at the price of so much bloodshed. The
                                            English Government, having refused this, has now no
                                            ground for denying to Russia, who has shed her blood,
                                            the right of promoting the creation of a state of things
                                            which relieves her henceforward from such sacrifices or
                                            renders them less onerous, But what is impossible to
                                            understand are the consequences to the freedom of the
                                            European commerce of Trebizond, via Persia, which are
                                            drawn from these rectifications of frontier. These
                                            assertions are in contradiction to those uttered on more
                                            than one occasion by several members of the British
                                            Cabinet, according to whom the taking possession of
                                            Erzeroum and of Trebizond by Russia would not constitute
                                            a danger to British interests. The rectifications of
                                            frontier in Asia, stipulated by the treaty of San
                                            Stefano, are very far from touching this extension. It
                                            is carrying distrust to an extreme to affirm that they
                                            place Russia in the position of impeding by prohibitive
                                            obstacles the European commercial system.</item>
                                        <label>11.</label>
                                        <item>The objections taken to the treaty of San Stefano in
                                            regard to the indemnity claimed from Turkey are surely
                                            not better established. The amount of this indemnity <pb facs="0942" n="880" xml:id="pg_880"/> is out of all
                                            proportion with the overwhelming charges which the war
                                            has entailed upon Russia. It may be that they exceed the
                                            actual resources of Turkey and increase her difficulty
                                            in satisfying the claims of her creditors. But it is to
                                            be noted that Turkey failed in her obligations towards
                                            her creditors long before the war, by reason of the
                                            disorder caused by her maladministration. There is
                                            reason to believe that if peace is established upon the
                                            rational bases which the treaty of San Stefano has in
                                            view, and to which the European sanction would give a
                                            solid and lasting character, it would result, as far as
                                            Turkey herself is concerned, in a diminution of her
                                            expenses, and an augmentation of her resources, which
                                            would enable her to respond to the exigencies of her
                                            foreign credit. It is in view of these possible results
                                            that the stipulations of San Stefano which relate to the
                                            indemnity have been maintained in the undefined state
                                            which has been made the subject of reproach. If the
                                            amount of the indemnity is criticised as being too high,
                                            the unreasonableness of an immediate payment has been
                                            criticised for a much stronger reason. If the precise
                                            manner of payment had been stipulated, it would have
                                            been necessary to encroach upon a region already
                                            mortgaged to the foreign creditors of the Porte. It is
                                            that which the treaty of San Stefano has sought to
                                            avoid, reserving the question for a future hearing. It
                                            is true that by this precaution Russia exposes herself
                                            to the suspicion of seeking to paralyze or to dominate
                                            over Turkey for several years, or of meditating new
                                            territorial acquisitions as a substitute for the
                                            indemnity. It would have been easier to have seen in
                                            this a design to care for Turkey as well as for the
                                            interests of Europe, and to maintain the Turkish
                                            Government in the fulfillment of its engagements and of
                                            pacific relationships which would be profitable to all.
                                            But against mistrust there is no remedy.</item>
                                        <label>12.</label>
                                        <item>From the conclusion of the Marquis of Salisbury’s
                                            dispatch it is gathered that the end and ardent desire
                                            of Her Majesty’s Government are always to insure good
                                            government, peace, and liberty to the populations to
                                            whom these benefits have been strange. With equal
                                            satisfaction has the frank avowal been noted that this
                                            policy has been frustrated by the unhappy resistance of
                                            the Ottoman Government; that in face of the modified
                                            circumstances of the present time the same result cannot
                                            be obtained in the same direction by the same means—that
                                            is to say, the programme of the conference of
                                            Constantinople—and that great changes may and without
                                            doubt will be necessary in the treaties by which the
                                            southeast of Europe has up to the present time been
                                            governed. If to these considerations be added the fact
                                            that the reiterated refusal of the English Government to
                                            join in exercising collective material pressure on the
                                            Porte has prevented Europe from obtaining pacifically
                                            the results desired by the Cabinet of London itself, it
                                            will be recognized that the war and the peace of San
                                            Stefano have answered to the exigencies of the situation
                                            which the Marquis of Salisbury has set forth with such
                                            great frankness and in such a high spirit. This
                                            situation resolves itself into this: The existing
                                            treaties have been successively infringed for 22
                                            years—first by the Turkish Government, which has not
                                            fulfilled its obligations toward the Christians; then by
                                            the united principalities, by the French occupation of
                                            Syria, and by the conference of Constantinople itself,
                                            constituting an interference in the interior affairs of
                                            the Ottoman Empire.</item>
                                        <label>13.</label>
                                        <item>The Marquis of Salisbury himself recognizes that great
                                            changes must and ought to be made. In the present
                                            circumstances, it remains for us to learn how his
                                            lordship means to reconcile practically these treaties
                                            and the recognized rights of Great Britain and other
                                            powers with the benevolent wishes towards a realization
                                            of which the united action of Europe has always been
                                            directed for a good government, peace, and assured
                                            liberty to the populations to whom these benefits have
                                            been strange. It remains also to be learned how beyond
                                            the preliminary bases laid down by the treaty of San
                                            Stefano, his lordship means to reach the desired goal
                                            while bearing in mind the rights acquired by Russia, for
                                            the sacrifices which she has borne, and borne alone, in
                                            order to render the realization possible. The dispatch
                                            of the Marquis of Salisbury contains no response to
                                            these questions. For these reasons it appears that the
                                            considerations which it contains would have been more
                                            effective if accompanied by practical proposals of a
                                            nature to assure an understanding in the solution of
                                            present difficulties in the general interest of a solid
                                            and lasting pacification in the East.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>