<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 518.Mr. Maynard to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d523</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">523</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1878-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1878-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recvFVZiL6ijeo9Lc" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104428"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political rights</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recUxK0PiRCnqTXts" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000044"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Farming</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="523"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d523">
                <head>No. 518.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Maynard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-09-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 28, 1878</date>. (Received Nov.
                        11.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 276.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have procured authorized copies of the treaty
                    of Berlin, with an English version, which may be taken as authentic; and
                    transmit them in connection with dispatch No. 269, of July 24, 1878.</p>
                <p>This now famous instrument can hardly be deemed successful as a measure
                    re-establishing peace in the East. True, a conflict between Great Britain and
                    Russia has been postponed, if not prevented, and the relations between Turkey
                    and Russia agreed upon at San Stefano confirmed; while in the capital, things
                    have settled into a state little short of apathy or even torpor quite painful to
                    witness.</p>
                <p>But in all the provinces there are great disturbances, amounting in some
                    instances to actual war. This is especially the condition in Bosnia and the
                    Herzegovina, where the Austro-Hungarian occupation provided for by the treaty is
                    resisted at every step by a hostile population fully aroused and thoroughly
                    armed.</p>
                <p>The occupation has become an invasion, with no alternative, apparently, but
                    conquest or retreat.</p>
                <p>In the Rhodope Mountains, has gathered a force, variously reported from 10,000 to
                    20,000 and even 30,000 men, armed apparently against all comers, of whom two
                    Englishmen are said to be the significant leaders. They are represented to be,
                    many of them, very rough characters, bashi bazouks, brigands, freebooters, and
                    outlaws. They succeed in keeping that region disturbed and preventing all
                    peaceful pursuits. Some weeks ago a commission of delegates from the different
                    powers was sent out to treat with them and ascertain any grievances requiring
                    redress; but I understand it failed to agree, and returned without accomplishing
                    anything.</p>
                <p>In Albania affairs appear to be even worse, if possible. With a view to restore
                    tranquillity, Mehemet AM Pasha was sent by the Sublime Porte into the
                    disaffected district.</p>
                <p>The first intelligence after his arrival was that he and’ his retinue had been
                    set upon by the Grhys at Diakovo (on Humphrey’s map, Jakova; Arrowsmith’s,
                    Jacova; Kiepertf’s, Diakowitza), a small town not far from Prisrend, and all put
                    to death. Various accounts of this distressing affair have been published, of
                    which I inclose one of the most rational.</p>
                <p>The fate of this distinguished officer has made a profound impression and caused
                    much speculation, with reflections, which it might be doing injustice to repeat.
                    He had been one of the Turkish plenipotentiaries <pb facs="0957" n="895"
                        xml:id="pg_895"/> at the congress of Berlin, and had but recently returned.
                    Some notice of him will be found in dispatch No. 181, of August 31, 1877.</p>
                <p>On the Greek frontier there is little improvement the last month.</p>
                <p>Turkey is disinclined to concede the demands of Greece, and Greece has appealed
                    to the treaty powers to enforce their recommendation made in her behalf at
                    Berlin, with what effect is not yet apparent. At the time, Mehemet Ali Pasha was
                    sent into Albania, Ghazi Ahmed Moukhtar Pasha was sent on a similar mission to
                    the island of Crete, and apparently with much better success. If we may trust
                    reports, the ferment of that “excited people has been in a good degree
                    allayed.</p>
                <p>The situation in Asia is not much better; Batoum has been abandoned by the Turks
                    to the Russians, who have retired from Erzeroum within the lines fixed by the
                    treaty. Between them, everything was done mutually. Not so with the people. From
                    Batoum the Lazes fled by thousands at the approach of the Russians, and from
                    Erzeroum the Armenian Christians followed the retiring Russians in
                    panic-stricken crowds. Strong appeals in their behalf have been made to the
                    British Government, through the ambassador at the Porte.</p>
                <p>A countryman of ours has sent me a copy of one, extracts from which are
                    inclosed.</p>
                <p>Insurrectionary movements are reported further south, in the province of the
                    Kozan, but I do not learn their character or extent.</p>
                <p>The mutual undertakings between Turkey and Russia by the treaty of San Stefano,
                    with the slight modification by the treaty of Berlin, have been substantially
                    carried into effect.</p>
                <p>The Russian armies have retired from around Constantinople as far as Adrianople.
                    The British fleet has also withdrawn about the same distance to Artaki Bay in
                    the southern part of the Marmora, near the site of the ancient Cyzicus; with
                    this difference, however, the fleet can steam back to the former anchorage in a
                    few hours, whereas the places evacuated by the Russians have been occupied by
                    Turkish troops.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp; c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HORACE MAYNARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 276.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Treaty of Berlin</hi>.</head>
                    <p>In the name of Almighty God.</p>
                    <p>Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland,
                        Empress of India, His Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia, His
                        Majesty the Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia, &amp; c., and King
                        Apostolic of Hungary, the President of the French Republic, His Majesty the
                        King of Italy, His Majesty the Emperor of all the Pussias, and His Majesty
                        the Emperor of the Ottomans, being desirous to regulate, with a view to
                        European -order, conformably to the stipulations of the Treaty of Paris of
                        30th March, 1856, the question raised in the East by the events of late
                        years, and by the war terminated by the preliminary Treaty of San Stefano,
                        have been unanimously of opinion that the meeting of a Congress would offer
                        the best means of facilitating an understanding.</p>
                    <p>Their said Majesties and the President of the French Republic have, in
                        consequence, appointed as their Plenipotentiaries, that is to say: <list>
                            <item>Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and
                                Ireland, Empress of India, the Right Honourable Benjamin Disraeli,
                                Earl of Beaconsfield, Viscount Hughenden, a Peer of Parliament,
                                Member of Her Majesty’s Most Honourable Privy Council, First Lord of
                                Her Majesty’s Treasury, and Prime Minister of England; the Most
                                Honourable Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne Cecil, Marquis of
                                Salisbury, Earl of Salisbury, Viscount Cranborne, Baron Cecil, a
                                Peer of Parliament, Member of Her Majesty’s Most Honourable Privy
                                Council, Her Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign
                                Affairs; and the Right Honourable Lord Odo William Leopold Russell,
                                Member of Her Majesty’s Privy Council, Her Ambassador Extraordinary
                                and Plenipotentiary at the Court of His Majesty the Emperor of
                                Germany, King of Prussia;</item>
                            <pb facs="0958" n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/>
                            <item>His Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia, Otho, Prince
                                Bismarck, His President of the Council of Ministers of Prussia,
                                Chancellor of the Empire; Bernard Ernest de Bülow, His Minister of
                                State and Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; and Chlodwig
                                Charles Victor, Prince of Hohenlohe-Schillingsfürst, Prince of
                                Ratibor and Corvey, His Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary
                                to the French Republic, Great Chamberlain of the Crown of
                                Bavaria;</item>
                            <item>His Majesty the Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia, &amp; c., and
                                King Apostolic of Hungary, Jules, Count Andrassy of Csik
                                Szent-Király and Krasna-Horka, Grandee of Spain of the First Class,
                                Privy Councillor, His Minister of the Imperial Household and for
                                Foreign Affairs, Lieutenant Field-Marshal in his armies; Louis Count
                                Károlyi of Nagy-Károlyi, Chamberlain and Privy Councillor, His
                                Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at the Court of His
                                Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia; and Henri, Baron de
                                Hay merle, Privy Councillor, His Ambassador Extraordinary and
                                Plenipotentiary at the Court of His Majesty the King of
                                Italy;</item>
                            <item>The President of the French Republic, William Henri Waddington,
                                Senator, Member of the Institute, Minister Secretary of State for
                                Foreign Affairs; Charles Raymond de la Criox de Chevrière, Count de
                                Saint-Vallier, Senator, Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary
                                from France at the Court of His Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King
                                of Prussia; and Felix Hippolyte Desprez, Councillor of State,
                                Minister Plenipotentiary of the First Class, charged with the
                                direction of Political Affairs at the Department of Foreign
                                Affairs;</item>
                            <item>His Majesty the King of Italy, Louis, Count Corti, Senator, His
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs; and Edward, Count de Launay, His
                                Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at the Court of His
                                Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia;</item>
                            <item>His Majesty the Emperor of all the Russias, Alexander, Prince
                                Gortchakow, His Chancellor of the Empire; Peter, Count de
                                Schouvaloff, General of Cavalry, his Aide-de-camp General, Member of
                                the Council of the Empire, and His Embassador Extraordinary and
                                Plenipotentiary at the Court of Her Britannic Majesty; and Paul
                                d’Oubril, Privy Councillor, his Ambassador Extraordinary and
                                Plenipotentiary at the Court of His Majesty the Emperor of Germany,
                                King of Prussia;</item>
                            <item>And His Majesty the Emperor of the Ottomans, Alexander
                                Carathéodory Pasha, His Minister of Public Works; Mehemed Ali Pasha,
                                Mushir of his Armies; and Sadoullah Bey, his Ambassador
                                Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at the Court of His Majesty the
                                Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia;</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Who, in accordance with the proposal of the Court of Austria-Hungary, and on
                        the invitation of the Court of Germany, have met at Berlin furnished with
                        full powers, which have been found in good and due form.</p>
                    <p>An. understanding having been happily established between them, they have
                        agreed to the following stipulations:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Bulgaria is constituted an autonomous and tributary Principality under the
                        suzerainty of His Imperial Majesty the Sultan; it will have a Christian
                        Government and a national militia.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Principality of Bulgaria will include the following territories:</p>
                    <p>The frontier follows on the north the right bank of the Danube from the
                        former frontier of Servia up to a point to be determined by a European
                        Commission to the east of Silistria, and thence runs to the Black Sea to the
                        south of Mangalia, which is included in Roumanian territory. The Black Sea
                        forms the eastern boundary of Bulgaria. On the south the frontier follows
                        upward from its mouth the mid-channel of the brook near which are situated
                        the villages of Hodžakiöj, Selam-Kïöj, Aivadšik, Kulibe, Sudžuluk; crosses
                        obliquely the valley of the Deli-Kamcik, passes south of Belibe and Kemhalik
                        and north of Hadzimahale after having crossed the Deli Kamžik at 2½ kilom.
                        above Cengei; reaches the crest at a point situated between Tekenlik and
                        Aidos-Bredza, and follows it by Karnabad Balkan, Prisevica Balkan, Kazan
                        Balkan to the north of Kotel as far as Demir Kapu. It proceeds by the
                        principal chain of the Great Balkan, the whole length of which it follows up
                        to the summit of Kosica.</p>
                    <p>There it leaves the crest of the Balkan, descends southwards between the
                        villages of Pirtop and Dužanci, the one being left to Bulgaria and the other
                        to Eastern Roumelia, as far as the brook of Tuzlu Dere, follows that stream
                        to its junction with the Topolnica, then the latter river until it meets the
                        Smovskio Dere near the village of Petricevo, leaving to Eastern Roumelia a
                        zone with a radius of 2 kilom. above that junction, ascends between the
                        brooks of Smovskio Dere and the Kamenica, following the line of the
                        watershed so as to turn to the southwest at the level of Voinjak and reach
                        directly the point 875 of the Austrian Staff map.</p>
                    <p>The frontier line cuts at right angles the upper basin of the brook of
                        Ichtiman Dere, passes between Bogdina and Karaúla, so as to rejoin the line
                        of the watershed separating the basins of the Isker and the Marica, between
                        Camurli and Hadžilar, follows <pb facs="0959" n="897" xml:id="pg_897"/> that
                        line by the summits of Velina Mogila, the “col” 531, Zmailica Vrh,
                        Sumnatica, and rejoins the administrative boundary of the Sandjak of Sofia
                        between Sivri Tas and Cadir Tepe.</p>
                    <p>From Cadir Tepe, the frontier, taking a southwesterly direction, follows the
                        watershed between the basins of the Mesta Karasu on the one side and the
                        Struma Karasu on the other, runs along the crests of the mountains of
                        Rhodope called Demir Kapu, Iskoftepe, Kadimesar Balkan, and Aiji Gedük up to
                        Kapetnik Balkan, and thus joins the former administrative frontier of the
                        Sandjak of Sofia.</p>
                    <p>From Kapetnik Balkan and the frontier is indicated by the watershed between
                        the valleys of the Rilska reka and of the Bistrica reka, and follows the
                        ridge called Vode hica Planina, descending into the valley of the Struma at
                        the junction of this river with the Rilska reka, leaving the village of
                        Barakli to Turkey. It ascends then south of the village of Jelešnica, and
                        reaches by the shortest line the chain of Golem a Planina at the summit of
                        Gitka, and rejoins there the former administrative frontier of the Sandjak
                        of Sofia, leaving, however, to Turkey the whole of the basin of the Suha
                        reka.</p>
                    <p>From Mount Gitka the western frontier goes towards Mount Crni Vrh by the
                        mountains of Karvena Jabuka, following the former administrative limit of
                        the Sandjak of Sofia in the upper part of the basins of Egrisu and of the
                        Lepnica, ascends with it the crests of Babina Polana, and reaches Mount Crni
                        Vrh.</p>
                    <p>From Mount Crni Vrh the frontier follows the watershed between the Struma and
                        the Morava by the summits of the Strešer, Vilogolo, and Mešid Planina,
                        rejoins by the Gračina, Crana Trava, Darkovska, and Drainica Plan, then the
                        Deščani Kladanec, the watershed of the High Sukowa and of the Morava, goes
                        straight to the Stol, and descends from it so as to cut the road from Sofia
                        to Pirot, 1,000 metres northwest of the village of Seguša. It ascends in a
                        straight line the Vidlic Planina, and thence Mount Radočina in the chain of
                        the Kodža Balkan, leaving to Servia the village of Doikinci, and to Bulgaria
                        that of Senakos.</p>
                    <p>From the summit of Mount Radocina the frontier follows towards the west the
                        crest of the Balkans by Ciprovec Balkan and Star a Planina up to the former
                        eastern frontier of the Principality of Servia, near to the Kula Smiljova
                        Čuka, and thence that former frontier as far as the Danube, which it rejoins
                        at Rakovitza.</p>
                    <p>This delimitation shall be fixed on the Spot by the European Commission, on
                        which the signatory powers shall be represented. It is understood— <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That this Commission will take into consideration the necessity
                                for His Imperial Majesty the Sultan to be able to defend the Balkan
                                frontiers of Eastern Roumelia.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>That no fortifications may be erected within a radius of 10 kilom.
                                from Samakow.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Prince of Bulgaria shall be freely elected by the population and
                        confirmed by the Sublime Porte, with the assent of the Powers. No member of
                        the Reigning Dynasties of the Great European Powers may be elected Prince of
                        Bulgaria.</p>
                    <p>In case of a vacancy in the princely dignity, the election of the new Prince
                        shall take place under the same conditions and with the same forms.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>An Assembly of Notables of Bulgaria, convoked at Tirnovo, shall, before the
                        election of the Prince, draw up the Organic Law of the Principality.</p>
                    <p>In the districts where Bulgarians are intermixed with Turkish, Roumanian,
                        Greek, or other populations, the rights and interests of these populations
                        shall be taken into consideration as regards the elections and the drawing
                        up of the Organic Law.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The following points shall form the basis of the public law of Bulgaria:</p>
                    <p>The difference of religious creeds and confessions shall not be alleged
                        against any person as a ground for exclusion or incapacity in matters
                        relating to the enjoyment of civil and political rights, admission to public
                        employments, functions, and honours, or the exercise of the various
                        professions and industries in any locality whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>The freedom and outward exercise of all forms of worship are assured to all
                        persons belonging to Bulgaria, as well as to foreigners, and no hindrance
                        shall be offered either to the hierarchical organization of the different
                        communions, or to their relations with their spiritual chiefs.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The provisional administration of Bulgaria shall be under the direction of an
                        Imperial Russian Commissary until the completion of the Organic Law. An
                        Imperial <pb facs="0960" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/> Turkish Commissary, as
                        well as the Consuls delegated <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> by the other
                        Powers, signatory of the present Treaty, shall he called to assist him so as
                        to control the working of this provisional <hi rend="italic">régime</hi>. In
                        case of disagreement amongst the Consular Delegates, the vote of the
                        majority shall he accepted, and in case of divergence between the majority
                        and the Imperial Russian Commissary or the Imperial Turkish Commissary, the
                        Representatives of the Signatory Powers at Constantinople, assembled in
                        Conference, shall give their decision.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The provisional régime shall not be prolonged beyond a period of nine months
                        from the exchange of the ratifications of the present Treaty.</p>
                    <p>When the Organic Law is completed the election of the Prince of Bulgaria
                        shall be proceeded with immediately. As soon as the Prince shall have been
                        installed, the new organization shall be put into force, and the
                        Principality shall enter into the full enjoyment of its autonomy.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Treaties of Commerce and of Navigation as well as all the Conventions and
                        arrangements concluded between Foreign Powers and the Porte, and now in
                        force, are maintained in the Principality of Bulgaria, and no change shall
                        be made in them with regard to any Power without its previous consent.</p>
                    <p>No transit duties shall be levied in Bulgaria on goods passing through that
                        Principality.</p>
                    <p>The subjects and citizens and commerce of all the Powers shall be treated in
                        the Principality on a footing of strict equality.</p>
                    <p>The immunities and privileges of foreigners, as well as the rights of
                        Consular jurisdiction and protection as established by the Capitulations and
                        usages, shall remain in full force so long as they shall not have been
                        modified with the consent of the parties concerned.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The amount of the annual tribute which the Principality of Bulgaria shall pay
                        to the Suzerain Court—such amount being paid into whatever bank the Porte
                        may hereafter designate—shall be fixed by an agreement between the Powers
                        Signatory of the present Treaty at the close of the first year of the
                        working of the new organization. This tribute shall be calculated on the
                        mean revenue of the territory of the Principality.</p>
                    <p>As Bulgaria is to bear a portion of the public debt of the Empire, when the
                        Powers fix the tribute they shall take into consideration what portion of
                        that debt can, on the basis of a fair proportion, be assigned to the
                        Principality.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article X</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Bulgaria takes the place of the Imperial Ottoman Government in its
                        undertakings and obligations towards the Rustchuk-Varna Railway Company,
                        dating from the exchange of the ratifications of the present Treaty. The
                        settlement of the previous accounts is reserved for an understanding between
                        the Sublime Porte, the Government of the Principality, and the
                        administration of this Company.</p>
                    <p>The Principality of Bulgaria, likewise, so far as it is concerned, takes the
                        place of the Sublime Porte in the engagements which the latter has
                        contracted, as well towards Austria-Hungary as towards the Company, for
                        working the railways of European Turkey in respect to the completion and
                        connection, as well as the working of the railways situated in its
                        territory.</p>
                    <p>The Conventions necessary for the settlement of these questions shall be
                        concluded between Austria-Hungary, the Porte, Servia, and the Principality
                        of Bulgaria immediately after the conclusion of peace.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Ottoman army shall no longer remain in Bulgaria; all the old fortresses
                        shall be razed at the expense of the Principality within one year or, sooner
                        if possible; the local government shall immediately take steps for their
                        demolition, and shall not construct fresh ones.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte shall have the right of disposing as it likes of the war
                        material and other effects belonging to the Ottoman Government which may
                        have remained in the fortresses of the Danube already evacuated in virtue of
                        the Armistice of the 31st January, as well as of those in the strongholds of
                        Shumla and Varna.</p>
                    <pb facs="0961" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Mussulman proprietors or others who may take up their abode outside the
                        Principality may continue to hold there their real property, by farming it
                        out, or having it administered by third parties.</p>
                    <p>A Turco-Bulgarian Commission shall be appointed to settle, within a period of
                        two years, all questions relative to the mode of alienation, working, or use
                        on the account of the Sublime Porte, of property belonging to the State and
                        religious foundations (vakoufs), as well as of the questions regarding the
                        interests of private persons engaged therein.</p>
                    <p>Persons belonging to the Principality of Bulgaria, who shall travel or dwell
                        in the other parts of the Ottoman Empire, shall be subject to the Ottoman
                        authorities and laws.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>A province is formed south of the Balkans which will take the name of
                        “Eastern Roumelia,” and will remain under the direct political and military
                        authority of His Imperial Majesty the Sultan, under conditions of
                        administrative autonomy. It shall have a Christian Governor-General.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Eastern Roumelia is bounded on the north and north-west by Bulgaria, and
                        comprises the territories included by the following line:—</p>
                    <p>Starting from the Black Sea the frontier follows upwards from its mouth the
                        mid-channel of the brook near which are situated the villages of Hodžakiöj,
                        Selam-Kiöj, Aivadšik, Kulibe, Sudzuluk, crosses obliquely the valley of the
                        Deli Kamčik, passes south of Belibe and Kemhalik, and north of Hadžimahale,
                        after having crossed the Deli-Kamčik at 2½ kilom. above Cengei; reaches the
                        crest at a point situated between Tekenlik and Aidos-Bredza, and follows it
                        by Karnabad Balkan, Prisevica Balkan, Kazan Balkan to the North of Kotel as
                        far as Demir Kapu. It proceeds by the principal chain of the Great Balkan,
                        the whole length of which it follows up to the summit of Kosica.</p>
                    <p>At this point the western frontier of Roumelia leaves the crest of the
                        Balkan, descends southwards between the villages of Pirtop and Duzanci—the
                        one being left to Bulgaria and the other to Eastern Roumelia, as far as the
                        brook of Tuzlu Dere, follows that stream to its junction with the Topolnica,
                        then the latter river until it meets the Smovskio Dere near the village of
                        Petričevo, leaving to Eastern Roumelia a zone with a radius of 2 kilom.
                        above that junction, ascends between the brooks of Smovskio Dere and the
                        Kamenica, folio wing, the line of the watershed so as to turn to the
                        south-west at the level of Voinjak and reach directly the point 875 of the
                        Austrian Staff map.</p>
                    <p>The frontier line cuts at right angles the upper basin of the brook of
                        Ichtiman Dere, passes between Bogdina and Karaúla, so as to rejoin the line
                        of the watershed separating the basins of the Isker and the Marica, between
                        Camurli and Hadzilar, follows that line by the summits of Velina Mogila, the
                        “col” 531, Zmailica Vrh, Sumnatica, and rejoins the administrative boundary
                        of the Sandjak of Sofia between Sivri Taš and Cadir Tepe.</p>
                    <p>The frontier of Roumelia leaves that of Bulgaria at Mount Čadir Tepe,
                        following the line of the watershed between the basins of the Marica and of
                        its affluents on one side, and of the Mesta Karasu and of its affluents on
                        the other, and takes the direction southeast and then south along the crest
                        of the Despoto Dagh Mountains, towards Mount Kruschowa (whence starts the
                        frontier line of the Treaty of San Stefano).</p>
                    <p>From Mount Kruschowa the frontier is the same as the line laid down by the
                        Treaty of San Stefano, that is to say, the chain of the Black Balkans (Kara
                        Balkan), the mountains Kulaghy-Dagh, Eschek-Tschepellii, Karakolas, and
                        Ischiklar, from whence it descends due south-east till it reaches the River
                        Arda, and follows the mid-channel of this river up to a point close to the
                        village of Adacali, which remains to Turkey.</p>
                    <p>From this point the frontier line ascends the crest of the Beštepe-Dagh,
                        which it follows, then descends and crosses the Maritza, at a point situated
                        5 kilom. above the bridge of Mustafa Pasha; thence it takes a northerly
                        direction by the line of the watershed between Demirhanli Dere and the small
                        affluents of the Maritza to Küdeler Baïr, whence it runs east to Sakar Baïr;
                        from this point it crosses the valley of the Tundža in the direction of
                        Büjük Derbend, which is left to the north, as also is Soudzak. From Büjük
                        Derbend it regains the line of the watershed between the affluents of the
                        Tunzda on the north and those of the Maritza on the south, up to the level
                        of Kaibilar, which is included in Eastern Roumelia, and passes to the south
                        of V. Almali between the basin of Maritza to the south and the various
                        streams which flow straight into the <pb facs="0962" n="900" xml:id="pg_900"
                        /> Black Sea, between the villages of Belevrin and Alatli; it follows to the
                        north of Karanlik the crests of Vosna and Zuvak, the line which separates
                        the waters of the Duka and those of the Karagač-Su, and rejoins the Black
                        Sea between those two rivers.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty the Sultan shall have the right of providing for the defence of
                        the land and sea frontiers of the province by erecting fortifications on
                        those frontiers, and maintaining troops there.</p>
                    <p>Internal order is maintained in Eastern Roumelia by a native gendarmerie
                        assisted by a local militia.</p>
                    <p>In forming these corps, the officers of which are nominated by the Sultan,
                        regard shall be paid in the different localities to the religion of the
                        inhabitants.</p>
                    <p>His Imperial Majesty the Sultan undertakes not to employ irregular troops,
                        such as Bashi-Bazouks and Circassians, in the garrisons of the frontiers.
                        The rugular troops detailed for this service must not in any case be
                        billeted on the inhabitants. When they passs through the province they shall
                        not make a stay there.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XVI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Governor-General shall have the right of summoning the Ottoman troops in
                        the event of the internal or external security of the province being
                        threatened. In such an eventuality the Sublime Porte shall inform the
                        Representatives of the Powers at Constantinople of such a decision, as well
                        as of the exigencies which justify it.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Governor-General of Eastern Roumelia shall be nominated by the Sublime
                        Porte, with the assent of the Powers, for a term of five years.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XVIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Immediately after the exchange of the ratifications of the present Treaty, a
                        European Commission shall be formed to arrange, in concert with the Ottoman
                        Porte, the organization of Eastern Roumelia. This Commission will have to
                        determine, within three months, the powers and functions of the
                        Governor-General, as well as the administrative, judicial, and financial
                        system of the province, taking as its basis the various laws for vilayets
                        and the proposals made in the eighth sitting of the Conference of
                        Constantinople.</p>
                    <p>The whole of the arrangements determined on for Eastern Roumelia shall form
                        the subject of an Imperial Firman, which will be issued by the Sublime
                        Porte, and which it will communicate to the Powers.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The European Commission shall be charged to administer, in concert with the
                        Sublime Porte, the finances of the province until the completion of the new
                        organization.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Treaties, Conventions, and international arrangements of any kind
                        whatsoever, concluded or to be concluded between the Porte and foreign
                        Powers, shall apply in Eastern Roumelia as in the whole Ottoman Empire. The
                        immunities and privileges acquired by foreigners, whatever their status,
                        shall be respected in this province. The Sublime Porte undertakes to enforce
                        there the general laws of the Empire on religious liberty in favour of all
                        forms of worship.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The rights and obligations of the Sublime Porte with regard to the railways
                        of Eastern Roumelia are maintained in their integrity.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The strength of the Russian corps of occupation in Bulgaria and Eastern
                        Roumelia, which shall be composed of six divisions of infantry and two
                        divisions of cavalry, shall not exceed 50,000 men. It shall be maintained at
                        the expense of the country <pb facs="0963" n="901" xml:id="pg_901"/>
                        occupied. The army of occupation will preserve its communications with
                        Russia not only through Roumania, in accordance with arrangements to he
                        concluded between the two States, but also through the ports of the Black
                        Sea, Varna and Bourgas, where it may, during the period of occupation,
                        organize the necessary depôts.</p>
                    <p>The period of the occupation of Eastern Roumelia and Bulgaria by the Imperial
                        Russian troops is fixed at nine months from the date of the exchange of the
                        ratifications of the present Treaty.</p>
                    <p>The Imperial Russian Government undertakes that within a further period of
                        three months the passage of its troops across Roumania shall cease, and that
                        Principality shall be completely evacuated.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte undertakes scrupulously to apply in the Island of Crete the
                        Organic Law of 1868, with such modifications as may be considered
                        equitable.</p>
                    <p>Similar laws adapted to local requirements, excepting as regards the
                        exemption from taxation granted to Crete, shall also be introduced into the
                        other parts of Turkey in Europe for which no special organization has been
                        provided by the present Treaty.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte shall depute special Commissions, in which the native
                        element shall be largely represented, to settle the details of the new laws
                        in each province.</p>
                    <p>The schemes of organization resulting from these labours shall be submitted
                        for examination to the Sublime Porte, which, before promulgating the Acts
                        for putting them into force, shall consult the European Commission
                        instituted for Eastern Roumelia.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXIV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In the event of the Sublime Porte and Greece being unable to agree upon the
                        rectification of frontier suggested in the 13th Protocol of the Congress of
                        Berlin, Germany, Austria-Hungary, France, Great Britain, Italy, and Russia
                        reserve to themselves to offer their mediation to the two parties to
                        facilitate negotiations.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Provinces of Bosnia and Herzegovina shall be occupied and administered by
                        Austria-Hungary. The Government of Austria-Hungary, not desiring to
                        undertake the administration of the Sandjak of Novi-Bazar, which extends
                        between Servia and Montenegro in a south-easterly direction to the other
                        side of Mitrovitza, the Ottoman Administration will continue to exercise its
                        functions there. Nevertheless, in order to assure the maintenance of the new
                        political state of affairs, as well as freedom and security of
                        communications, Austria-Hungary reserves the right of keeping garrisons and
                        having military and commercial roads in the whole of this part of the
                        ancient Vilayet of Bosnia. To this end the Governments of Austria-Hungary
                        and Turkey reserve to themselves to come to an understanding on the
                        details.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXVI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The independence of Montenegro is recognized by the Sublime Porte and by all
                        those of the High Contracting Parties who had not hitherto admitted it.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The High Contracting parties are agreed on the following conditions:</p>
                    <p>In Montenegro the difference of religious creeds and confessions shall not be
                        alleged against any person as a ground for exclusion or incapacity in
                        matters relating to the enjoyment of civil and political rights, admission
                        to public employments, functions, and honours, or the exercise of the
                        various professions and industries in any locality whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>The freedom and outward exercise of all forms of worship shall be assured to
                        all persons belonging to Montenegro, as well as to foreigners, and no
                        hindrance shall be offered either to the hierarchical organization of the
                        different communions, or to their relations with their spiritual chiefs.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXVIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The new frontiers of Montenegro are fixed as follows:</p>
                    <p>Starting at Ilino-brdo to the north of Klobuk, the line descends to the
                        Trebinjčica towards Grančarevo, which remains to Herzegovina, then ascends
                        the course of that river up to a point 1 kilom, below its confluence with
                        the Čepelica, and from thence passes by the most direct line on to the
                        heights which border the River Trebinjčica. <pb facs="0964" n="902"
                            xml:id="pg_902"/> It then proceeds in the direction of Pilatova, leaving
                        that village to Montenegro, and continues along the heights in a northerly
                        direction, maintaining as far as possible a distance of 6 kilom. from the
                        Bilek-Korito-Gacko road, up to the “col” between the Somina Planina and
                        Mount Čurilo, whence it proceeds in an easterly direction by Vratkoviči,
                        leaving this village to Herzegovina, up to Mount Orline. Starting from this
                        point the frontier, leaving Ravno to Montenegro, goes straight to the
                        north-northeast, crossing the summits of the Leberšnik and of the Volujak,
                        then descends by the shortest line on to the River Piva, which it crosses,
                        and rejoins the River Tara, passing between Crkvica and Nedvina. From this
                        point it ascends the Tara to Mojkovac, from which place it passes along the
                        crest of the ridge as far as Siškojezero. Leaving this point it coincides
                        with the former frontier as far as the village of Sekulare. From there the
                        new frontier passes along the crests of the Mokra Planina, the village of
                        Mokra remaining to Montenegro; it then reaches the point 2,166 on the
                        Austrian Staff Map, following the principal chain and the line of the
                        watershed between the Lim on the one side, and the Drin as well as the
                        Cievna (Zem) on the other.</p>
                    <p>It then coincides with the existing boundaries between the tribe of the
                        Kuči-Drekaloviči on one side, and the Kučka-Krajna, as well as the tribes of
                        the Klementi and Grudi, on the other, to the plain of Podgorica, from whence
                        it proceeds towards Plavnica, leaving the Klementi, Grudi, and Hoti tribes
                        to Albania.</p>
                    <p>Thence the new frontier crosses the lake near the Islet of Gorica-Topal, and,
                        from Gorica-Topal, takes a straight line to the top of the crest, whence it
                        follows the watershed between Megured and Kalimed, leaving Mrkovič to
                        Montenegro, and reaching the Adriatic at V. Kruči.</p>
                    <p>On the northwest the frontier will be formed by a line passing from the coast
                        between the villages of Susana and Zubči, and terminating at the extreme
                        southeast point of the existing frontier of Montenegro on the Vrsuta
                        Planina.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXIX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Antivari and its sea-board are annexed to Montenegro under the following
                        conditions:</p>
                    <p>The districts situated to the south of that territory, in accordance with the
                        delimitation above laid down, as far as the Boyana, including Dulcinjo,
                        shall be restored to Turkey.</p>
                    <p>The Commune of Spiča, as far as the southernmost point of the territory
                        indicated in the detailed description of the frontiers, shall be
                        incorporated with Dalmatia.</p>
                    <p>Montenegro shall have full and complete freedom of navigation on the Boyana.
                        No fortifications shall be constructed on the course of that river except
                        such as may be necessary for the local defence of the stronghold of Scutari,
                        and they shall not extend beyond a distance of 6 kilom. from that town.</p>
                    <p>Montenegro shall have neither ships of war nor flag of war.</p>
                    <p>The port of Antivari and all the waters of Montenegro shall remain closed to
                        the ships of war of all nations.</p>
                    <p>The fortifications situated on Montenegrin territory between the lake and the
                        coast shall be razed, and none shall be rebuilt within this zone.</p>
                    <p>The administration of the maritime and sanitary police, both at Antivari and
                        along the coast of Montenegro, shall be carried out by Austria-Hungary by
                        means of light coast-guard boats.</p>
                    <p>Montenegro shall adopt the maritime code in force in Dalmatia. On her side
                        Austria-Hungary undertakes to grant consular protection to the Montenegrin
                        merchant flag.</p>
                    <p>Montenegro shall come to an understanding with Austria-Hungary on the right
                        to construct and keep up across the new Montenegrin territory a road and a
                        railway.</p>
                    <p>Absolute freedom of communication shall be guaranteed on these roads.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Mussulmans or others possessing property in the territories annexed to
                        Montenegro, who may wish to take up their residence outside the
                        Principality, can retain their real property either by farming it out, or by
                        having it administered by third parties.</p>
                    <p>No one shall be liable to be expropriated otherwise than by legal process for
                        the public welfare, and with a previous indemnity.</p>
                    <p>A Turco-Montenegrin Commission shall be appointed to settle, within a period
                        of three years, all questions relative to the mode of alienation, working,
                        or use, on the account of the Sublime Porte, of property belonging to the
                        state and religious foundations (Vakoufs), as well as of the questions
                        regarding the interests of private parties engaged therein.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Principality of Montenegro shall come to a direct understanding with the
                        Ottoman Porte with regard to the establishment of Montenegrin agents at
                        Constantinople, <pb facs="0965" n="903" xml:id="pg_903"/> and at certain
                        places in the Ottoman Empire where the necessity for them shall be
                        admitted.</p>
                    <p>Montenegrins travelling or residing in the Ottoman Empire shall be subject to
                        the Ottoman laws and authorities, according to the general principles of
                        international law, and the customs established with regard to
                        Montenegrins.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Montenegrin troops shall be bound to evacuate within twenty days from the
                        date of the ratification of the present treaty, or sooner, if possible, the
                        territory that they occupy at present beyond the new limits of the
                        Principality.</p>
                    <p>The Ottoman troops shall evacuate the territories ceded to Montenegro within
                        the same period of twenty days. A supplementary period of fifteen days
                        shall, however, be granted to them, as well for evacuating the fortresses
                        and withdrawing the stores and material of war from them, as for drawing up
                        inventories of the implements and articles which cannot be immediately
                        removed.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>As Montenegro is to bear a portion of the Ottoman public debt for the new
                        territories assigned to her by the Treaty of Peace, the Representatives of
                        the Powers at Constantinople shall determine the amount of the same in
                        concert with the Sublime Porte on an equitable basis.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXIV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties recognize the independence of the Principality
                        of Servia, subject to the conditions set forth in the following Article.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In Servia the difference of religious creeds and confessions shall not be
                        alleged against any person as a ground for exclusion or incapacity in
                        matters relating to the enjoyment of civil and political rights, admission
                        to public employments, functions, and honours, or the exercise of the
                        various professions and industries, in any locality whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>The freedom and outward exercise of all forms of worship shall be assured to
                        all persons belonging to Servia, as well as to foreigners, and no hindrance
                        shall be offered either to the hierarchical organization of the different
                        communions, or to their relations with their spiritual chiefs.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXVI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Servia receives the territories included in the following delimitation:</p>
                    <p>The new frontier follows the existing line ascending the mid-channel of the
                        Drina from its confluence with the Save, leaving Mali Zwornik and Sakhar to
                        the Principality, and continues to follow the former boundary of Servia as
                        far as the Kopaonik, leaving it at the summit of the Kanilug. Prom that
                        point it follows at first the western boundary of the Sandjak of Nisch by
                        the southern spur of the Kopaonik, by the crests of the Marica and Mrdar
                        Planina, which form the watershed between the basins of the Ibar and Sitnica
                        on one side, and that of the Toplica on the other, leaving Prepolac to
                        Turkey.</p>
                    <p>It then turns to the south by the watershed between the Brvenica and the
                        Medvedja, leaving the whole of the basin of the Medvedja to Servia; follows
                        the crests of the Goljak Planina (which forms the watershed between the
                        Kriva-Rjeka on one side and the Poljanica, Veternica, and Morawa on the
                        other), as far as the summit of the Poljanica. It then follows the spur of
                        the Karpina Planina as far as the confluence of the Koinska and the Morawa,
                        crosses this river, and ascends by the watershed between the Koinska brook
                        and the stream which falls into the Morawa near Neradovce, to reach the Sv.
                        Ilija Planina above Trgovište. Thence it follows the crest of the Sv. Ilija
                        as far as Mount Kljuc, and passing by the points marked 1516 and 1547 on the
                        map, and by the Babina Gora, it reaches Mount Crni-Vrh.</p>
                    <p>From Mount Crni Vrh, the new delimitation coincides with that of Bulgaria,
                        that is to say:</p>
                    <p>The line of frontier follows the watershed between the Struma and the Morava
                        by the summits of Strešer, Vilogolo, and Mešid Planina, rejoins by the
                        Gačina, Crna Trava, Darkovska, and Drainica Plan, then the Deščani Kladanec,
                        the watershed of the High Sukowa and of the Morava, goes straight to the
                        Stol, and descends from it be as to cut the road from Sofia to Pirot 1,000
                        metres northwest of the village of <pb facs="0966" n="904" xml:id="pg_904"/>
                        Seguša. It ascends in a straight line the Vidlič Planina, and thence Mount
                        Radočina in the chain of the Kodža Balkan, leaving to Servia the village of
                        Doikinci, and to Bulgaria that of Senakos.</p>
                    <p>From the summit of Mount Radočina the frontier follows towards the northwest
                        the crest of the Balkans by Ciprovec Balkan and Stara Planina up to the
                        former eastern frontier of the Principality of Servia, near to the Kula
                        Smiljova čuka, and thence that former frontier as far as the Danube, which
                        it joins at Rakovitza.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Until the conclusion of fresh arrangements no change shall be made in Servia
                        in the actual conditions of the commercial intercourse of the Principality
                        with foreign countries.</p>
                    <p>No transit duties shall be levied on goods passing through Servia.</p>
                    <p>The immunities and privileges of foreign subjects, as well as the rights of
                        Consular jurisdiction and protection, as at present existing, shall remain
                        in full force so long as they shall not have been modified by mutual consent
                        between the Principality and the Powers concerned.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXVIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Principality of Servia takes the place, so far as it is concerned, of the
                        Sublime Porte in the engagements which the latter has contracted as well
                        towards Austria-Hungary as towards the Company for the working of the
                        railways of Turkey in Europe, in respect to the completion and connection,
                        as well as the working of the railways to be constructed on the territory
                        newly acquired by the Principality.</p>
                    <p>The Conventions necessary for settling these question shall be concluded,
                        immediately after the signature of the present Treaty, between
                        Austria-Hungary, the Porte, Servia, and, within the limits of its
                        competency, the Principality of Bulgaria.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXXIX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Mussulmans possessing property in the territories annexed to Servia, who may
                        wish to reside outside the Principality, may retain their real property,
                        either by farming it out or by having it administered by third parties.</p>
                    <p>A Turco-Servian Commission shall be appointed to settle, within a period of
                        three years, all questions relative to the mode of alienation, working, or
                        use, on the account of the Sublime Porte, of the property belonging to the
                        State and religious foundations (Vakoufs), as well as of the questions
                        regarding the interests of private persons engaged therein.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XL</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Until the conclusion of a treaty between Turkey and Servia, Servian subjects
                        travelling or residing in the Ottoman Empire shall be treated according to
                        the general principles of international law.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Servian troops shall be bound to evacuate within fifteen days from the
                        exchange of the ratifications of the present treaty the territory not
                        comprised within the new limits of the Principality.</p>
                    <p>The Ottoman troops shall evacuate the territories ceded to Servia within the
                        same term of fifteen days. A supplementary term of an equal number of days
                        shall, however, be granted to them as well for evacuating the fortresses and
                        withdrawing the provisions and material of war as for drawing up the
                        inventory of the implements and objects which cannot be removed at once.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>As Servia is to bear a portion of the Ottoman Public Debt for the new
                        territories assigned to her by the present Treaty, the Representatives at
                        Constantinople shall fix the amount of it in concert with the Sublime Porte
                        on an equitable basis.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The High Contracting Parties recognize the independence of Roumania, subject
                        to the conditions set forth in the two following Articles.</p>
                    <pb facs="0967" n="905" xml:id="pg_905"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLIV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In Roumania the difference of religious creeds and confessions shall not he
                        alleged against any person as a ground for exclusion or incapacity in
                        matters relating to the enjoyment of civil and political rights, admission
                        to public employments, functions, and honors, or the exercise of the various
                        professions and industries in any locality whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>The freedom and outward exercise of all forms of worship shall be assured to
                        all persons belonging to the Roumanian State, as well as to foreigners, and
                        no hindrance shall be offered either to the hierarchical organization of the
                        different communions, or to their relations with their spiritual chiefs.</p>
                    <p>The subjects and citizens of all the Powers, traders or others, shall be
                        treated in Roumania, without distinction of creed, on a footing of perfect
                        equality.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Principality of Roumania restores to His Majesty the Emperor of Russia
                        that portion of the Bessarabian territory detached from Russia by the Treaty
                        of Paris of 1858, bounded on the west by the mid-channel of the Pruth, and
                        on the south by the mid-channel of the Kilia Branch and the Stary-Stamboul
                        mouth.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLVI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The islands forming the Delta of the Danube, as well as the Isle of Serpents,
                        the Sandjak of Toultcha, comprising the districts (cazas) of Kilia, Soulina
                        Mahmoudié, Isaktcha, Toultcha, Matchin, Babadagh, Hirsovo, Kustendje,
                        Medjidié, are added to Roumania. The Principality receives in addition the
                        territory situated to the south of the Dobroutcha as far as a line starting
                        from the east of Silistria and terminating on the Black Sea, south of
                        Mangalia.</p>
                    <p>The frontier line shall be determined on the spot by the European Commission
                        appointed for the delimitation of Bulgaria.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The question of the division of the waters and the fisheries shall be
                        submitted to the arbitration of the European Commission of the Danube.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLVIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>No transit duties shall be levied in Roumania on goods passing through the
                        Principality.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article XLIX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Roumania shall have power to make Conventions to determine the privileges and
                        attributes of Consuls in regard to protection within the Principality.
                        Existing rights shall remain in force so long as they shall not have been
                        modified by the mutual consent of the Principality and the parties
                        concerned.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article L</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Until the conclusion of a Treaty between Turkey and Roumania, fixing the
                        privileges and attributes of Consuls, Roumanian subjects travelling or
                        residing in the Ottoman Empire, and Ottoman subjects travelling or residing
                        in Roumania, shall enjoy the rights guaranteed to the subjects of other
                        European Powers.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>With regard to public works and other enterprises of a like nature, Roumania
                        shall be substituted for the Sublime Porte as regards its rights and
                        obligations throughout the ceded territory.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In order to increase the guarantees which assure the freedom of navigation on
                        the Danube which is recognized as of European interest, the High Contracting
                        Parties determine that all the fortresses and fortifications existing on the
                        course of the river from the Iron Gates to its mouths shall be razed, and no
                        new ones erected. No vessel of war shall navigate the Danube below the Iron
                        Gates with the exception of vessels of light tonnage in the service of the
                        river police and customs. The “stationnaires” of the powers at the mouths of
                        the Danube may, however, ascend the river as far as Galatz.</p>
                    <pb facs="0968" n="906" xml:id="pg_906"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LIII.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The European Commission of the Danube, on which Roumania shall be
                        represented, is maintained in its functions, and shall exercise them
                        henceforth as far as Galatz in complete independence of the territorial
                        authorities. All the treaties, arrangements, acts, and decisions relating to
                        its rights, privileges, prerogatives, and obligations are confirmed.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LIV.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>One year before the expiration of the term assigned for the duration of the
                        European Commission the Powers shall come to an understanding as to the
                        prolongation of its powers, or the modifications which they may consider
                        necessary to introduce.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LV.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The regulations respecting navigation, river police, and supervision from the
                        Iron Gates to Galatz shall be drawn up by the European Commission, assisted
                        by Delegates of the Riverain States, and placed in harmony with those which
                        have been or may be issued for the portion of the river below Galatz.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LVI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The European Commission of the Danube shall come to an arrangement with the
                        proper authorities to ensure the maintenance of the lighthouse on the Isle
                        of Serpents.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LVII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The execution of the works which have for their object the removal of the
                        obstacles which the Iron Gates and the Cataracts place in the way of
                        navigation is entrusted to Austria-Hungary. The Riverain States on this part
                        of the river shall afford every facility which may be required in the
                        interest of the works.</p>
                    <p>The provisions of the VIth Article of the Treaty of London of the 13th March,
                        1871, relating to the right of levying a provisional tax in order to cover
                        the cost of these works, are maintained in favour of Austria-Hungary.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LVIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte cedes to the Russian Empire in Asia the territories of
                        Ardahan, Kars, and Batoum, together with the latter port, as well as all the
                        territories comprised between the former Russo-Turkish frontier and the
                        following line:—</p>
                    <p>The new frontier starting from the Black Sea, and coinciding with the line
                        laid down by the Treaty of San Stefano as far as a point to the northwest of
                        Khorda, and to the south of Artwin, continues in a straight line as far as
                        the River Tchoroukh, crosses this river and passes to the east of
                        Aschmichen, going in a straight line to the south so as to rejoin the
                        Russian frontier indicated in the Treaty of San Stefano, at a point to the
                        south of Nariman, leaving the town of Olti to Russia. From the point
                        indicated near Nariman the frontier turns to the east, passes by Tebrenec,
                        which remains to Russia, and continues as far as the Pennek Tschaï.</p>
                    <p>It follows this river as far as Bardouz, then turns towards the south,
                        leaving Bardouz and Jönikioy to Russia. From a point to the west of the
                        village of Karaougan, the frontier takes the direction of Medjingert,
                        continues in a straight line towards the summit of the Mountain Kassadagh,
                        and follows the line of the watershed between the affluents of the Araxes on
                        the north and those of the Mourad Sou on the south, as far as the former
                        frontier of Russia.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LIX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty the Emperor of Russia declares that it is his intention to
                        constitute Batoum a free port, essentially commercial.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LX</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The valley of Alaschkerd<note n="*" xml:id="d523fn1">See Agreement, <ref
                                target="#pg_908">page 908</ref>.</note> and the town of Bayazid,
                        ceded to Russia by Article XIX of the Treaty of San Stefano, are restored to
                        Turkey.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte cedes to Persia the town and territory of Khotour, as fixed
                        by the mixed Anglo-Russian Commission for the delimitation of the frontiers
                        of Turkey and of Persia.</p>
                    <pb facs="0969" n="907" xml:id="pg_907"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LXI</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte undertakes to carry out, without further delay, the
                        improvements and reforms demanded by local requirements in the provinces
                        inhabited by the Armenians, and to guarantee their security against the
                        Circassians and Kurds.</p>
                    <p>It will periodically make known the steps-taken to this effect to the Powers,
                        who will superintend their application.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LXII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Sublime Porte having expressed the intention to maintain the principle of
                        religious liberty, and give it the widest scope, the Contracting Parties
                        take note of this spontaneous declaration.</p>
                    <p>In no part of the Ottoman Empire shall difference of religion be alleged
                        against any person as a ground for exclusion or incapacity as regards the
                        discharge of civil and political rights, admission to the public
                        employments, functions, and honours, or the exercise of the various
                        professions and industries.</p>
                    <p>All persons shall be admitted, without distinction of religion, to give
                        evidence before the tribunals.</p>
                    <p>The freedom and outward exercise of all forms of worship are assured to all,
                        and no hindrance shall be offered either to the hierarchical organization of
                        the various communions or to their relations with their spiritual
                        chiefs.</p>
                    <p>Ecclesiastics, pilgrims, and monks of all nationalities travelling in Turkey
                        in Europe, or in Turkey in Asia, shall enjoy the same rights, advantages,
                        and privileges.</p>
                    <p>The right of official protection by the Diplomatic and Consular Agents of the
                        Powers in Turkey is recognized both as regards the above-mentioned persons
                        and their religious, charitable, and other establishments in the Holy Places
                        and elsewhere.</p>
                    <p>The rights possessed by France are expressly reserved, audit is well
                        understood that no alterations can be made in the <hi rend="italic">status
                            quo</hi> in the Holy Places.</p>
                    <p>The monks of Mount Athos, of whatever country they may be natives, shall be
                        maintained in their former possessions and advantages, and shall enjoy,
                        without any exception, complete equality of rights and prerogatives.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LXIII</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Treaty of Paris of March 30, 1856, as well as the Treaty of London of
                        March 13, 1871, are maintained in all such of their provisions as are not
                        abrogated or modified by the preceding stipulations.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article LXIV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The present Treaty shall be ratified, and the ratifications exchanged at
                        Berlin within three weeks, or sooner if possible.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed it, and affixed
                        to it the seal of their arms.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1878-07-13">the thirteenth day of the
                                month of July, one thousand eight hundred and
                            seventy-eight</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] (Signed)
                            <signed>BEACONSFIELD.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>SALISBURY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>ODO RUSSELL.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>v. BISMARCK.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>BÜLOW.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>HOHENLOHE.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>ANDRÁSSY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>KÁROLYI.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>HAYMERLE.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>WADDINGTON.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>SAINT-VALLIER.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>H. DESPREZ.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>L. CORTI.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>LAUNAY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>GORTCHAKOW.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>SCHOUVALOFF.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>P. D’OUBRIL.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>AL. CARATHÉODORY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>MEHEMED ALI.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>SADOULLAH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0970" n="908" xml:id="pg_908"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Procès-Verbal</hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Undersigned having met together for the purpose of exchanging the
                        ratifications of the Treaty concluded at Berlin on the 13th July, 1878, the
                        instruments of these ratifications confirming the said Treaty were produced
                        by the Representatives of Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of
                        Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, His Majesty the German Emperor,
                        King of Prussia, His Majesty the Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia, &amp;
                        c, and Apostolic King of Hungary, His Excellency the President of the French
                        Republic, His Majesty the King of Italy, and His Majesty the Emperor of all
                        the Russias, and having, after examination, been found in good and due form,
                        the exchange thereof took place.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador of Turkey, while expressing the regret of the Sublime Porte
                        that the Turkish instruments of ratification could not be despatched in
                        time, announces that he is authorized to declare that His Majesty the
                        Emperor of the Ottomans has likewise ratified the Treaty of the 13th July,
                        1878, and that he considers the same valid from this day’s date.</p>
                    <p>Sadoullah Bey announces, moreover, that the exchange of the Turkish
                        instruments of ratification will take place within fifteen days.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof the Undersigned have drawn up the present <hi
                            rend="italic">procès-verbal</hi>, to which they have affixed the seals
                        of their arms.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1878-08-03">the third day of the month of
                                August, one thousand eight hundred and
                            seventy-eight</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>ODO RUSSELL.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>RADOWITZ.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>MOÜY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>LAUNAY.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>ARAPOFF.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>SADOULLAH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Agreement signed by the Marquis of Salisbury and Count
                            Schouvaloff, July</hi> 12, 1878.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The more detailed tracing of the line of the Alashkerd shall be carried out
                        on the spot, in conformity with the Treaty of Berlin, by a military
                        commission composed of a Russian officer, an Ottoman officer, and an English
                        officer.</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>SALISBURY.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>SCHOUVALOFF.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-07-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 12, 1878</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 276.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Account of Mehemet Ali Pasha’s death.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>A Salonica letter of the 13th ultimo, published in the Pall Mall Gazette of
                        September 25, gives details of the sad death of Mehemet Ali Pasha, some of
                        which I do not recollect to have yet seen in print.</p>
                    <p>The news of the untoward fate of the gallant Mehemet Ali and his suite has
                        reached you long ago by telegraph. No coherent statement of the occurrences
                        at Diakovo reached Salonica until to-night (September 13). By this evening’s
                        train a brother-in-law of Mehemet Ali, Edhem Bey, and a wounded servant of
                        the same general, arrived from the interior, having narrowly escaped in
                        disguise. I hasten to give you the substance of their verbal report to the
                        governor here, as repeated to me by that official almost immediately after
                        the interview.</p>
                    <p>When the decision of the congress relative to the cessions to the
                        principalities and the Austrian occupation was made known in Southern
                        Bosnia, the inhabitants—in especial the Ghega Albanians—assembled in large
                        numbers and publicly declared the Porte incapable of guarding their rights.
                        They then took a solemn oath of fraternity for the defense of their country
                        against all aggression or change. This declaration was drawn up in due form,
                        and signed by all who had taken the oath. Foremost among the signers were
                        three leading Albanian chieftains—Abdullah Pasha, Bairam Bey, and Shakyr
                        Bey—men of great influence in the country; indeed, Bairam alone, it is said,
                        could command the services of 5,000 armed adherents. A few weeks ago Mehemet
                        Ali was dispatched on a pacificatory mission to Southern Bosnia and Albania.
                        On reaching Diakovo he had interviews with the Albanians; and, perceiving
                            <pb facs="0971" n="909" xml:id="pg_909"/> their disaffection, he
                        demanded to have his guard re-enforced. Accordingly he received (whence not
                        stated), a battalion—a battalion, however, under nominal strength. The sight
                        of these troops cooled the Albanians; and so Mehemet Ali, retaining two
                        companies as his body-guard, sent the rest into quarters. He succeeded in
                        convincing the three chieftains above named of the uselessness of
                        resistance, and they went over to his side. Reconciliation was sealed by
                        Mehemet Ali taking up his quarters, with his staff and escort, in the konak
                        of Abdullah Pasha, a large house in the middle of the town. But when the
                        Albanians learned the defection of the three chiefs they declared them
                        traitors and prepared to take vengeance on them, a course in which they were
                        abetted by the town population, which includes 16,000 Mussulmans. Although
                        their anger was mainly directed against their own leaders, they had a
                        distinct grudge against Mehemet Ali. During a disturbance at Diakovo, some
                        years back, a Hungarian commander, Mahmoud Pasha, treated the townspeople
                        with great harshness. They believed Mehemet Ali to be also a Hungarian and
                        in league with the Austrians. Moreover, as a foreigner, they threw on him
                        all the odium of the concessions of the Congress.</p>
                    <p>On Wednesday, September 4, a detachment of Albanians, incited by the
                        townspeople, surrounded the barracks, and, having cut off the water-supply,
                        summoned the troops to surrender. The insurgents promised liberty to the
                        rank and file on condition of their delivering up their officers. The men
                        agreed, and some officers—number not known—were killed; the rest escaped
                        disguised as privates. Meanwhile, 10,000, or, according to Edhem Bey,
                        12,000, Albanians surrounded the house of Abdullah Pasha, and opened a heavy
                        fire, to which the inmates (including two companies of infantry) replied.
                        This went on for two days. By Friday, however, the little garrison had
                        expended its ammunition, and was reduced in numbers by upwards of sixty
                        persons— namely, several officers, forty soldiers, and twenty servants. In
                        these straits, the remainder of the rank and file laid down their arms and
                        surrendered to the Albanians; some of the officers escaping in the uniform
                        of their men. This was on Friday afternoon. Meanwhile, some of the Albanians
                        had mounted a neighboring minaret, from which they were able to take clear
                        aim into the <hi rend="italic">selamlik</hi> where Mehemet Ali and his staff
                        were; at the same time they set fire to the opposite (the <hi rend="italic"
                            >haremlik</hi>) end of the house, whence the women had, fortunately,
                        been removed. The well-directed fire from the mosque and the increasing heat
                        and smoke finally drove Mehemet Ali and his companions, about 3 p.m., to
                        take refuge in an adjoining tower. Now, this tower had a separate entrance,
                        unguarded, and the door was decayed. The fire, or the smoke, now spread to
                        the tower and made it untenable, when Mehemet Ali exclaimed, “At least let
                        me have a soldier’s death I” and rushing down met the Albanians swarming in.
                        He immediately fell, riddled with bullets. The Albanians did not at once
                        discover all the refugees; but Abdullah Pasha, having been wounded in the
                        leg, was easily secured. They took him to the top of the tower and dashed
                        him down into the street below. As the body fell it was the mark of scores
                        of muskets, and reached the ground frightfully, unrecognizably disfigured.
                        The malcontents now sought out Bairam and Shakyr, and put them also to
                        death. Foremost among the assailants were the most trusted adherents of the
                        three chieftains. The Albanians continued to discharge their fire on the
                        dead bodies. That of Mehemet Ali is stated (probably at random) to have
                        received 200 bullets before burial. He was interred the same day. During the
                        whole affair the governor of Diakovo made no attempt to assist the besieged,
                        or even (apparently) to give an alarm to the neighboring districts; although
                        Diakovo is only six hours from Prizrend and nine from Prishtina, the latter
                        a railway as well as telegraph station.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 276.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cole</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Maynard</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Erzeroum</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-09-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 1, 1878</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose a copy of statements made in a
                        letter to Mr. Layard as to political matters this way. Thinking you might
                        have an interest in hearing of these things, I take the liberty to send this
                        along to you as it is, trusting you will pardon me in this instance for not
                        writing you a separate sheet, especially as there is not time, and I wish to
                        send by this courier.</p>
                    <p>Though the first page has some reference to our work for the poor, the rest
                        of the letter treats of what, to my mind, is of vital importance for these
                        parts.</p>
                    <p>We doubt not all foreign representatives are doing all they can to introduce
                        reforms into the Turkish Government; but I assure you it must be by some
                        other visible power as the responsible agent, or I for one can hope for
                        little. It is for this visible, <hi rend="italic">tangible</hi> exponent
                        that I have appealed, as you will see.</p>
                    <p>We are happy to report that as Americans we have been, since I wrote you
                        last, treated with the greatest consideration both by Turks and Russians,
                        and have not the <pb facs="0972" n="910" xml:id="pg_910"/> least ground for
                        complaint in these respects; though for the poor downtrodden Christians of
                        Armenia our hearts are in much sadness.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. M. GOLE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure to inclosure 3 in No. 276.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cole</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Layard</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You will be interested in knowing that the
                        great amount of poverty which has been crowding up to our doors for more
                        than six months past has so far decreased that for the present we are
                        relieved for the most part of this compassionate work.* * * Not to dwell
                        longer on this work for the poor, I beg to call your excellency’s attention
                        to another most vital question with reference to this rilajet especially,
                        which has passed for a time under Russian rule. If something is not done at
                        once there will be a perfect stampede of Christians from all these parts to
                        Russian territory. Yon may wonder why this should be, since your
                        excellency’s government has given such strong pledges for future
                        reforms.</p>
                    <p>But you are probably aware that these interior provinces are steeped in
                        ignorance, there being probably not one in twenty that can read at all, and
                        what can read have not the facilities for getting reliable news, as
                        newspapers, telegrams, &amp; c. But, supposing they had all these facilities
                        even, I should hope for little then, as the past is such a doleful reminder.
                        They know of no way of judging of the future but by the past, and until they
                        can see something besides a Mohammedan head rising up before them for a
                        government, they will not believe nor be persuaded.</p>
                    <p>The past twenty-five years have been replete with promises of reform, and
                        they regard them as of no more value than the paper on which they are
                        written.</p>
                    <p>Hitherto we have been able to hold our people in these places, though not a
                        few from other sects have already emigrated; and to me, on the ground,
                        seeing and knowing, as I have opportunity to do, it is no surprise that
                        there should be an uprising on the part of Christians. Can they stand and be
                        smitten down like dogs, see their families subjected to fiendish treatment
                        worse than death?</p>
                    <p>If I mistake not, my friend Rev. a.m. Barnum, D. D., of Harpoot, has informed
                        Your Excellency as to the direful oppression and misrule in the Geglia
                        region. In view of this I will not take your time in rehearsal, though my
                        heart has been greatly saddened by repeated and full reports of oppression
                        at the hands of such as should constitute a government in that province, but
                        to call your attention to very grave irregularities in the Khanoos region to
                        the south, to illustrate what I have said above, respecting the great
                        importance of some <hi rend="italic">visible</hi> exponent of actual
                        reform.</p>
                    <p>This province was, in the early spring, in such a state of anarchy at the
                        hands of the Koords, that most diabolical work was inaugurated, as Your
                        Excellency may be aware.</p>
                    <p>It is at the present time bordering upon if not already in such a state. My
                        latest advices are that in place of the local government, which seems
                        powerless to restrain them, two Koordish Beys, at the head of some 200
                        horsemen, are lording it in most heart-rending ways. They take forcible
                        possession of houses, exact impossible things, demand bribes, thrust into
                        prison, devastate homes, violating its sacred honor. And please bear in mind
                        that these, too, are none other than relations of the commander-in-chief of
                        the Turkish forces in Armenia, Ismail Pasha himself.</p>
                    <p>Can you wonder, then, with such a state’ of things that people are
                        disheartened and meditate a leap though it be in the dark, as from their
                        poverty must be the case if they rush in crowds to Russia? But, as I have
                        said before, give us the visible sign, a sure voucher for the future, and we
                        might hold them still.</p>
                    <p>This itis which leads me to take up my pen at the present time. Can you not
                        direct us to some such ground-work on which these timid Christians may rest?
                        What shall be the data? Could you not dispatch some officer of Your
                        Excellency’s government at once to give assurance, to these scattering ones?
                        I am aware that it is much to expect and may be next to impossible. Still,
                        if nothing more than some irregular agent, under your approval, could come
                        it would help <hi rend="italic">so</hi> much. The people must have something
                        tangible, must see with their eyes or they <hi rend="italic">will not</hi>
                        believe.</p>
                    <p>You must agree with me that this uprising population is too valuable to be
                        lost to the country that is to be so intimately connected with Your
                        Excellency’s government, and especially if in the transfer untold misery is
                        to be brought upon them.</p>
                    <p>If we might learn at once by telegraph that a commissioner was dispatched for
                        these parts, it would be one of the most joyful messages that could speed
                        over the wires, and the man would doubtless be received here with all the
                        pomp of an incoming king.</p>
                    <p>One of our people is just in from the Alashgerd region Christians there have
                        become oblivious of the harvest, that demands their time and energies, and
                        were turning their whole attention to preparations for leaving for
                        Russia.</p>
                    <pb facs="0973" n="911" xml:id="pg_911"/>
                    <p>There have been provoking causes on the part of Christians that will be
                        likely to lead the Koords to wreak vengeance on them, as they have vowed
                        again and again they shall do. Two of their number were justly killed in
                        self-defense some time since in an attack they instituted themselves on a
                        Christian village in the plain.</p>
                    <p>In other places poor Christians, so oppressed and down-trodden in the past,
                        have been over-elated at this seeming promotion and have been insolent to
                        Mohammedans, as I can testify from personal observation; and, moreover, the
                        Russians have not hesitated to solicit volunteers to their army and police
                        force from Christians; and from the poverty of the people during these times
                        a goodly number have responded.</p>
                    <p>Your Excellency must see what is to be feared from such a state of things, if
                        stern law is not administered at once from some <hi rend="italic">trusty
                            visible</hi> power. The Russians are already beginning to move, and
                        will, from present appearance, evacuate the place altogether in a few weeks
                        at most. While we do not apprehend serious danger in this city, believe me,
                        some of the provinces are bordering on a state of anarchy, and if anything
                        is done it must be done at once.</p>
                    <p>For the sake of downtrodden Armenia; for the sake of poor humanity that now
                        trembles in the balance; for the sake of that which makes life so desirable
                        to us all—home and the home relations—I beg you to listen to this
                        appeal.</p>
                    <p>I am, in behalf of Christians in Armenia,</p>
                    <p>Yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. M. COLE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">American missionary</hi>,</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 276.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cole</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Maynard</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Erzeroum</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-09-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 14, 1878</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am waiting with anxiety for a reply to my
                        letter to your excellency and the English ambassador of fourteen days since.
                        All that I anticipated in that letter, and a hundred fold more, is already
                        inaugurated; not only the provinces I referred to but others, and even this
                        plain and city, are up in arms. Yesterday was such a day as we shall not
                        soon forget. The Turks have been most barefaced in their threats toward
                        Christians for some time. For some days they have begun here and there,
                        inside the city and out, to put into execution their threats. Several men
                        were deliberately knocked down in the open market. These were attacked
                        outside of the city, one of them, one of my own employés, and he might soon
                        have been killed but for the interference of others. This is what we were
                        seeing take place right here in the city with the Russian guard in full
                        force. And added to this, and in keeping with these terrible threats, night
                        before last several Turks entered the house of a poor inoffensive man, bound
                        him and his family and outraged the latter in a most shameful manner, so
                        that she now lies at the point of death. The house was also plundered of
                        what they had. This last has been enough to touch the match to such
                        combustible substances as we have in the mass of the people this way, be
                        they Christian or Mohammedan. Hence we had such a scene enacted yesterday in
                        this place as we shall not soon forget.</p>
                    <p>Christians went in a tumultuous crowd of thousands to the governor-general,
                        first of all, after which they went to the mayor and French consul. Not
                        getting very good satisfaction in any of these places, they become
                        boisterous, crying out, “Protect us or kill us,” &amp; c.</p>
                    <p>Finally the mayor issued an order for the police to scatter the crowd, which
                        they did with some difficulty, arresting a few of the most boisterous. But
                        they were not to be thus silenced. They now gathered in still greater crowds
                        in the large Armenian cemetery and became all the more vociferous.</p>
                    <p>The Armenian Church ecclesiastics gathered them into their large church (and
                        the most of them were Armenians), and attempted to make an address, persuade
                        them to be patient, turn to their various employments as loyal subjects of
                        the government. At this the crowd called out, “We can’t receive any such
                        talk,” and the meeting broke up in great confusion. Their bishop also became
                        so intimidated, as it is thought from his own people, since they dealt out
                        threats at him from his seeming inactivity in the matter, that he had a
                        strong Russian guard stationed at his door immediately. Upon this, not a few
                        called out, “Let us turn to the Americans, who secured us from starvation
                        last winter.” They came to us, though not in such a crowd and in a much more
                        honorable way. Yesterday and to-day have been largely to encourage and
                        pacify the poor bewildered, terrified ones that have been crowding upon us
                        in larger or smaller groups. I learned they had the plan of coming by the
                        thousands in front of our door, but I begged their chief men to put a stop
                        to such a course if they had respect to my honor. That what I <hi
                            rend="italic">could</hi> do I would do all the more cheerfully if they
                        would refrain from such demonstrations.</p>
                    <p>Thanks to them that they have heeded our request (and not a few of them have
                        been <pb facs="0974" n="912" xml:id="pg_912"/> to our doors for their daily
                        bread the past winter, and we have a good influence over them), and our
                        house has not been put in the least danger as yet, nor we annoyed further
                        than interrupted, so that I find it difficult, with so many coming and
                        going, to lay the whole matter before you in a connected careful manner.</p>
                    <p>I have this day sent to your excellency a very long telegram, some 150 words,
                        through Russia, and in the Russian language, stating at the beginning that
                        “what I feared in the letter which I sent (that is the copy of letter to Mr.
                        Layard which I sent you, suggesting emigration, great mixtures, anarchy,
                        &amp; c.) to your excellency had already begun.” From this I went on to
                        describe briefly the state of things with us in this city as I have done now
                        with pen.</p>
                    <p>Though I suggested danger to us as well as to the city in the telegram, still
                        I would not have your excellency think that as yet we have reason to fear
                        for our personal safety unless the condition of the town should become most
                        desperate, which we cannot anticipate, though matters yesterday looked most
                        formidable, indeed.</p>
                    <p>We and our flag are held in high repute, and all nationalities are on
                        friendly terms with us as far as we can see. Though other ecclesiastics have
                        placed guards at their doors, we feel no need of any at ours, and trust our
                        residence will be kept in safety unless a perfect frenzy should possess the
                        whole town, in which case ours might have to succumb, last of all.</p>
                    <p>The people have confidence and respect for us, though they seem to look upon
                        their own highest dignitaries with great distrust.</p>
                    <p>I shall wait with great anxiety a speedy reply to the telegram, as the people
                        crowd upon us for some encouraging news.</p>
                    <p>As I wrote in the letter to Mr. Layard, the province of Alashgerd has already
                        been given over to the Koords, and the poor Christians have fled toward
                        Russia.</p>
                    <p>The plain east of us is bordering on such a state, as also the villages of
                        this plain.</p>
                    <p>I might fill pages more in black rehearsals of what is going on in other
                        regions, which have also had great weight in urging me on to present the
                        matter before you, but it would only weary you, and I forbear.</p>
                    <p>Am happy to repeat, however, that Ismail Pasha has paid good heed to
                        telegrams I sent him as to Geghi and Khanous regions, and some efforts at
                        reforms are being made.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp; c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. M. COLE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—The telegram was finally sent in French instead of Russian.</p>
                    </postscript>
                    <postscript>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">P. S.—</hi>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-09-15">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">September</hi> 15</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The letter which I inclose I wrote very
                            hastily, hoping it would go by courier, but in the rush of people upon
                            us and upon the agent who attends to dispatching the courier it failed
                            to be sent. Just at this moment an opportunity to send it presents
                            itself, and I hastily send it away.</p>
                        <p>I am happy to report more quiet. Yesterday, by beatings in some cases and
                            threats of fines, the shops were opened. The people are waiting
                            anxiously to see what replies will come to the telegrams sent by
                            different ones. We do hope something will be accomplished so that this
                            Armenian race may not be wholly lost to these parts. They are emigrating
                            every day in great numbers.</p>
                        <p>I can but feel that the English Government is gravely at fault in not
                            dispatching some representatives of their own to these parts to assure
                            these Christians in personal presence.</p>
                        <p>With great respect, &amp; c.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>R. M. COLE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation of telegram referred to in Mr. Cole to
                            Mr. Maynard.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Erzeroum</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-09-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 10, 1878</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Minister</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Constantinople:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>We have the panic that I had anticipated and given you notice of. The Turks
                        openly menace the Christians. They are so excited by their vindictive spirit
                        that they have not patience even to wait three days for the retreat of the
                        Russian army, and they are beginning now to post themselves along the roads
                        to pillage the villages; and to-night they have sacked some houses in the
                        city, and in entering them they violated a woman, and in the last
                        twenty-four hours they have wounded several Christians. Now the panic is
                        carrying away everything. All the (Christian bazaars are closed, and if
                        prompt and efficacious measures shall not be taken, we fear for personal
                        safety of the inhabitants and ourselves. If possible, stay the retreat of
                        the Russian army.</p>
                    <p>If you like, do, in the name of humanity and for the safety of the
                        Christians, that for which we, with all the Christians, shall thank you.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>COLE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">American missionary.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
