<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-01-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="536" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d536">
                    <head>No. 531.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Heap</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Hunter</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate
                                    of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tunis</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25, 1878</date>.
                            (Received February 25.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 259.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that I have availed
                        myself of the kind invitation of Lieut. Commander H. H. Gorringe, commanding
                        the United States steamer Gettysburg, to visit the western ports of this
                        regency, <pb facs="0992" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/> and after returning to
                        Tunis to assist at the official court reception on the 16th of December (the
                        Great Bairam), to proceed to the eastern coast to visit the ports on that
                        side of Tunisia.</p>
                    <p>The Bey having been informed of my intention to make this tour in the
                        Gettysburg, gave particular instructions to the governors and other
                        authorities of the coast towns to receive and treat us with every honor and
                        attention, and to see that we were supplied with whatever we might
                        require.</p>
                    <p>We sailed accordingly on the 6th December last to the westward, visiting
                        Porto Farina, Bizerta, the island of Galita, and Tabarca. The captain was
                        able to render a service to the Tunisian Government in conveying from
                        Bizerta to the island of Galita some officers and a party of men the Bey
                        wished to send there, and who had been windbound at Bizerta for forty-five
                        days.</p>
                    <p>Captain Gorringe has submitted to the Navy Department the necessity that
                        exists for a light-house on the island of Galita, which will be the subject
                        of a communication I shall have the honor to make to the department after
                        ascertaining the views of the Bey in the matter.</p>
                    <p>Having returned from the western coast, I presented Captain Gorringe and some
                        of his officers to the Bey, on the 16th of December, at the grand court
                        reception which is held annually on the recurrence of the festival of
                        Bairam. The court is arrayed with great magnificence, and I was glad the
                        officers were afforded an opportunity of witnessing this splendid
                        spectacle.</p>
                    <p>On the 21st December I sailed again on the Gettysburg to the eastern coast.
                        When we reached Monastir, on the 24th, the captain was compelled to sail for
                        Malta, as he was getting short of coal. On arriving there on Christmas night
                        and drawing the tires it was found that the boilers and machinery required
                        some repairs, which were not completed until the 7th January, when we sailed
                        for Cape Mesurata, 100 miles east of the city of Tripoli. Thence we sailed
                        westward, touching at every point of the coast which required examination;
                        were detained several days at the port of Tripoli by stormy weather, and
                        finally reached Zerzis, the southernmost town on the Tunisian coast, on the
                        17th.</p>
                    <p>When we arrived at Gabes, on the gulf of that name, a party was made up to
                        visit the site of the proposed canal to connect the Mediterranean with the
                        Schotts and Sebkhas of the Great Desert of Sahara, which have been found to
                        be beneath the level of the sea. The party returned after an absence of two
                        days. The weather was excessively cold on the desert, the thermometer
                        falling to 29 degrees. I have already transmitted a report on the project of
                        introducing the waters of this sea into the desert by a cutting at some
                        point on the Gulf of Gabes. Captain Gorringe is preparing a report on the
                        same subject, which will, I think, be found not only exceedingly
                        interesting, but exhaustive. We returned here this morning.</p>
                    <p>This excursion will, I hope, have a beneficial effect on our interests. The
                        United States flag has been shown at points where it had never before been
                        seen and was unknown, and valuable information and statistics have been
                        collected, which will be useful to our commerce.</p>
                    <p>The politeness and attention of the authorities of the numerous places we
                        visited on this coast could not be exceeded. Everywhere provisions were sent
                        on board in quantities sufficient to supply the entire crew of the
                        Gettysburg, and nothing we could say could prevent their sending them.
                        Bullocks, sheep, fish, poultry, vegetables, fruit, eggs, butter, milk, &amp;
                        c., were sent in profusion. At Gabes the governor gave his carriage and
                        furnished a number of excellent horses, together with an escort <pb facs="0993" n="931" xml:id="pg_931"/> for the visit to the desert, which
                        I regret I was unable to join. Captain Gorringe will submit to the Navy
                        Department the expediency of making some return for these attentions.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>While we were in Malta, General Grant and family arrived in the United States
                        ship Vandalia, and Captain Gorringe and I immediately called on the
                        ex-President. When he returned our visit he desired me to inform the Bey
                        that he should visit Tunis in April next. The Bey intends, I believe, to
                        receive General Grant with the same honors with which he has received royal
                        personages who have visited this regency, and to offer him his palace in
                        town as a residence during his stay here.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp; c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>G. H. HEAP.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>