<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-02-17T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-02-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.61/594: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-17T19:00:00+03:00"
                            >February 17, 1936—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 17—5:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>49. On my return to Moscow yesterday, Litvinov,<note n="36" xml:id="d174fn36"
                        >Maxim Maximovich Litvinov, Soviet Commissar for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                    Marshal Budenny, and an unusually large number of Soviet officers and officials
                    came to my house and showed every evidence of having been directed to cultivate
                    more friendly personal relations with this mission. A member of the Soviet
                    hierarchy, close to the Kremlin, informed me later that Litvinov had made every
                    effort to have Troyanovsky<note n="37" xml:id="d174fn37">Alexander Antonovich
                        Troyanovsky, Soviet Ambassador in the United States.</note> removed from
                    Washington, but that Troyanovsky in the course of three conversations with
                    Stalin had persuaded the dictator that it was Litvinov and not himself
                    (Troyanovsky) who had wrecked Soviet relations with the United States. He
                    asserted that Litvinov had received instructions to adopt a more reasonable
                    attitude toward the United States.</p>
                <p>In the course of a conversation Litvinov made the following statements to me:</p>
                <p>1. He asserted that he was convinced that there was no possibility whatsoever of
                    an early Japanese attack on the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>He said, “The Japanese know that if they attack us and Germany does not attack us
                    the war may be long but in the end they will be defeated utterly.”</p>
                <p>2. He said that he was equally convinced that there was no possibility of an
                    early German attack on Czechoslovakia or any part of Central Europe or the
                    Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>3. He said he believed the French Chamber of Deputies certainly would vote for
                    the Franco-Soviet Pact of Mutual Assistance but was much less certain with
                    regard to the French Senate.</p>
                <p>4. He asserted that he had positive information that a council of the superior
                    officers of the German Reichswehr recently had recommended to Hitler that even
                    in case of ratification of the Franco-Soviet Pact of Mutual Assistance the
                    German Government should not immediately begin to fortify the Rhineland. He
                    added that technical considerations had played a large part in this decision,
                    that German industry was so fully occupied by war preparations of other sorts
                    that it would be impossible at the moment to begin serious military
                    constructions in the Rhineland.</p>
                <p>5. He stated that the German Government had offered again to extend credits of
                    one billion marks to the Soviet Government for purchases <pb facs="0281" n="201"
                        xml:id="pg_201"/> in Germany. He added that the Soviet Government had
                    replied that the maximum it would consider utilizing was five hundred million
                    marks.</p>
                <p>6. He stated that while his visit to London had improved greatly relations
                    between Great Britain and the Soviet Union he had obtained no definite promises
                    of support. He said that he had proposed an Anglo-Soviet pact of mutual
                    assistance similar to the Franco-Soviet pact but that he had really no hope that
                    this proposal would be accepted. He said that Eden personally might be favorable
                    but that the weight of British tradition would be too much for him to overcome.
                    Litvinov added “I believe the British will adhere to the policy they pursued
                    before 1914. They may even make fewer commitments than they then made to the
                    French. But at the last minute faced by the fact of German aggression they will
                    make war”.</p>
                <p>7. In connection with the question of German aggression against the Soviet Union,
                    Litvinov reiterated the opinions which the Soviet Ambassador to Poland had
                    expressed to me at great length during the trip from Warsaw to Moscow. Litvinov
                    said that the Soviet Government was certain now that Germany could not attack
                    the Soviet Union except by way of Poland. He asserted that the way to the north
                    by way of Lithuania and Latvia offered insufficient area for the maneuvering of
                    great forces and had been completely closed by Soviet preparations. He asserted
                    that the way to the south via Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Rumania could not be
                    opened except by a German attack on Czechoslovakia and Rumania and even if
                    opened would give a line of communications so long and inadequate that the
                    Russian armies on the Rumanian border would be able to defeat the German armies.
                    He then asserted that he still believed Poland might cooperate with Germany in
                    an attack on the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>(I had a rather intimate conversation with Beck, Polish Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs, on my way through Warsaw which reenforced my opinion that there is no
                    possibility whatever of Poland participating with Germany in such an attack on
                    the Soviet Union. Among other strong statements on this subject Beck remarked
                    “our basic policy is never to allow a German or a Bolshevik soldier to set foot
                    on Polish soil. In case of war anywhere in Europe, we shall remain neutral so
                    long as possible.”).</p>
                <p>The informant, close to the Kremlin, quoted above, also stated to me that outward
                    appearances to the contrary, notwithstanding, Litvinov’s conversation with
                    Flandin had been thoroughly unsatisfactory from the point of view of the Soviet
                    Government and that the Kremlin believed the Franco-Soviet pact would not be
                    ratified by the French Senate.</p>
                <pb facs="0282" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                <p>With regard to relations between the Soviet Government and the People’s Republic
                    of Mongolia, the same informant asserted positively that while the Soviet
                    Government had made no written promises to Gendun, Chairman of the Council of
                    Ministers of the People’s Republic of Mongolia, during his recent visit to
                    Moscow, verbal promises had been given that the Soviet Government would accord
                    military assistance appropriate to any situation which might arise,<note n="38"
                        xml:id="d174fn38">For report of military assistance agreement, signed March
                        13, 1936, see telegram No. 95, April 1, 2 p.m., from the Ambassador In the
                        Soviet Union, <ref target="frus1936v04#pg_94">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >iv</hi>, p. 94</ref>.</note> “ending with one hundred per cent
                    military assistance in case the Japanese should approach Urga.[”]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
