<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="175" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d175">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751.62/344</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Straus</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2563</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-21">February 21,
                                1936</date>.<lb/>[Received March 3.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I paid a courtesy call, by appointment,
                            on M. Sarraut, the new Prime Minister, on Thursday, February 20. The
                            President of the Council, who is also Minister of the Interior, received
                            me in his office at the Ministry of the Interior at the Place
                            Beauvau.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to report that my conversation with M. Sarraut lasted
                            three-quarters of an hour and concerned itself chiefly with the broader
                            aspects of world problems. He was greatly preoccupied concerning the
                            peace of Europe and in fact world peace, as a world war would, he felt,
                            certainly follow a European war. The Japanese peril, he thought, was one
                            of particular concern due to the domination of the militarists in that
                            country. Western civilization may have brought blessings to Japan from
                            their point of view, but from the European and American points of view
                            the modern development of Japan raised serious problems.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister spoke briefly of his own war experiences and of the
                            feeling in France for Germany over a period of years. At the present
                            time there was no great hatred of the Germans among the French
                            population. There was, moreover, an intense desire in France to avoid
                            the recurrence of another such struggle as took place in 1914. He said
                            that he would devote his energy to finding some means of preventing war.
                            The French on the one hand, he personally believed, did not desire to
                            form a military ring around Germany and that, on the other hand, it was
                            unlikely that the Germans had at the moment any warlike intentions,
                            provided something could be done to satisfy her needs for raw materials
                            and some territorial expansion for her <pb facs="0283" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/> excess population. He thought the taking away from
                            Germany by the Versailles Treaty<note n="39" xml:id="d175fn39">Signed
                                June 28, 1919, <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_57">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris Peace
                                    Conference, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p.
                                    57</ref>.</note> of the German colonies had been a mistake. He
                            believed that England, although loath to give up any of her African
                            possessions, might be persuaded to return to Germany the latter’s
                            pre-war possessions, provided that Germany gave certain guarantees that
                            she would not use these colonies as bases for propaganda directed at the
                            colonial possessions in Africa of other powers.</p>
                        <p>M. Sarraut believed that the first step in securing world-wide security
                            would be the calling of an international conference at which all
                            questions of international relations should be considered. The agenda
                            for this meeting should be carefully prepared beforehand so as not to
                            run the risks of a failure similar to that of the London Economic
                                Conference.<note n="40" xml:id="d175fn40">Held June 12–July 27,
                                1933; see <ref target="frus1933v01#pg_452">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1933, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 452</ref> ff.</note> On the
                            agenda of this conference should be the question of securing for each
                            nation</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>required raw materials,</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>markets for its products,</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>outlets for surplus population.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>He reiterated that he doubted that Hitler wanted war. However, there were
                            militaristic elements in the German Government and the doctrine of
                            pan-Germanism was one which might give rise to war in the future if some
                            peaceful solution was not forthcoming. The military group in Germany, he
                            thought, would sooner or later seek the restoration of the Hohenzollerns
                            in the person of the second son of the Crown Prince, whether Hitler
                            liked it or not.</p>
                        <p>I asked the Prime Minister whether he thought that there was any precise
                            arrangement between Germany and Japan. He replied that he had no
                            definite knowledge of any such agreement. He had, however, noted that
                            Germany was according visiting Japanese delegations a warm welcome and
                            he suspected that some sort of an understanding existed.</p>
                        <p>When I asked him whether he believed that there was any Polish-German
                            agreement, he replied that, in his opinion, Pilsudski<note n="41" xml:id="d175fn41">Marshal Josef Pilsudski, late Chief of Polish Army
                                Staff and former Premier, who died May 12, 1935.</note> had mediated
                            between Japan and Germany, motivated by his hatred of the Soviets, and
                            had probably been the intermediary by which some sort of assistance
                            would be given Germany by Japan. His remarks at this point were not
                            entirely clear, but I gained the impression that in the case of trouble
                            between Germany and Russia, Poland would probably take the side of
                            Germany.</p>
                        <p>Turning to internal affairs, M. Sarraut told me that general elections
                            would probably take place at the end of April or beginning of <pb facs="0284" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/> May and that Parliament would
                            adjourn about the middle of March. The elections he ventured to predict,
                            would probably show a decided swing to the Left.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Jesse Isidor Straus</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>