<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Germany ( (Dodd) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-03-18T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-03-18T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-03-18T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-03-18T14:00:00-05:00" n="217"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Mutual Guarantee (Locarno)/475:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dodd</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-03-18T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 18, 1936—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 18—6:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>85. I submit the following as certain important objectives and considerations at
                    the London discussions as viewed from Berlin:</p>
                <pb facs="0335" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/>
                <p>First. French efforts to persuade England, in default of immediate economic or
                    military action against Germany, to make an agreement on the lines of the
                    abortive 1919 Anglo-American-French treaty<note n="9" xml:id="d217fn9">Signed
                        June 28, 1919; for text, see <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_757">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris Peace Conference,
                            1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 757</ref>.</note> or of
                    the so-called Geneva protocol of 1924.<note n="10" xml:id="d217fn10">Protocol
                        for the Pacific Settlement of International Disputes, October 2, 1924; for
                        text, see League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Journal</hi>,
                        Special Supplement No. 24, Annex 13, p. 107.</note> This is in accord with
                    the constant French pressure on England throughout the post-war period to have
                    such a British guarantee which has, as a matter of fact, come ever closer to
                    realization as England has found it necessary to occupy herself more and more
                    with the continent and in her new position of champion of the League. As opposed
                    to this French thesis, the German view is that France can accomplish the same
                    end by the “new Locarno” and other proposals in Hitler’s memorandum; that this
                    would avoid a return to the policy of pre-war alliances achieving the desired
                    result in the modern cooperative manner.</p>
                <p>Second. The military reoccupation of the Rhineland zone and especially its
                    fortification which Germany intends is a serious threat to the preponderance of
                    French influence in central and eastern Europe if indeed it does not definitely
                    end it. With the Rhineland zone as provided in the Versailles treaty, the French
                    army constituted a conserved threat against Germany if and when she might
                    undertake a military adventure either against Russia or in the Danubian region.
                    It was this which has given France such dominating influence in central and
                    eastern Europe as much as the weakness of the Germany army under the Versailles
                    treaty. With the demilitarized zone reoccupied and fortified, France and if
                    necessary Belgium also may be contained by a relatively moderate force and thus
                    prevented from creating an effective immediate military diversion in support of
                    the Little Entente or Russia. In brief, a fortified Rhineland zone and the
                    powerful army which Germany proposes to have would seem to spell the end of
                    France’s present position on the continent.</p>
                <p>Repeated to London, Paris, Rome, Brussels, Geneva.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dodd</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
