<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-11-25T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-11-25T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-11-25T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-11-25T02:00:00-05:00" n="311"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762.94/94: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-11-25T10:00:00+03:00"
                            >November 25, 1936—10 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 25—9 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>294. My 279, November 17, 6 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese Ambassador has told me: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That Litvinov informed him categorically on November 18 that the
                                Soviet Government had reliable information to the effect that <pb
                                    facs="0479" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/> Japan and Germany had
                                entered into a secret agreement providing for mutual military
                                assistance in case either country should become involved in a war
                                with the Soviet Union.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That Litvinov also advised him that the Soviet Government had been
                                reliably informed that the Nanking Government had decided to accede
                                to the demand of the Japanese Government that both Governments enter
                                into an agreement jointly to combat Communism in the Far
                                East.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That he had replied that if the Soviet Government considered as
                                reliable sources furnishing it with information of the kind
                                contained in Litvinov’s second statement he would be inclined to
                                doubt all information obtained from Soviet so-called reliable
                                sources.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That his Embassy was not convinced that Japan and Germany had
                                entered into a military pact of the kind suggested by Litvinov;
                                and,</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That Japan had been demanding for some time that China enter into
                                an agreement with it providing for a joint campaign against
                                Communism in the Far East, one of the means for the carrying out of
                                the campaign being the establishment of a line of Chinese-Japanese
                                military outposts following roughly the Great Wall from the sea to
                                Turkestan but that China was determined not to comply with such a
                                demand.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The French Ambassador has told me, <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That Litvinov informed him on November 22 that it now seemed
                                possible that the secret agreement between Japan and Germany merely
                                provided that if one of the two powers should become engaged in a
                                war with a third power the other power would not assist the third
                                power by supplying it with military equipment or raw or other
                                materials. Litvinov himself had apparently begun to doubt the truth
                                of his previous statements regarding the scope of the so-called
                                military agreement; and,</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the French Embassy was not convinced that Japan and Germany
                                had entered into a pact obligating one of the parties to render
                                military assistance to the other in case either should become
                                involved in a war with the Soviet Union.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The Japanese Chargé d’Affaires has advised me, <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That Litvinov told him last week that in view of the apparent
                                inclination of Japan to enter into an agreement with Germany aimed
                                at the Soviet Union, the Central Executive Committee had failed to
                                authorize the signing of the fisheries agreement and that
                                authorization would not be forthcoming until the attitude of Japan
                                towards the Soviet Union had been clarified.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the two drafts of the treaty had been prepared for signature
                                and were to have been signed some time between November 18 and
                                November 23; and,</item>
                            <pb facs="0480" n="400" xml:id="pg_400"/>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That he had told Litvinov that he had no information which would
                                cause him to believe that Japan and Germany had entered into any
                                kind of an agreement aimed at the Soviet Union.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated by mail to Tokyo, Riga, Berlin and Paris.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
