<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="318" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d318">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 Belgium/210</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d318fn2">Copy transmitted to the Ambassador in
                                    Belgium in Department’s instruction No. 320, February 4, 1936,
                                    not printed.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-25">January 25,
                                        1936</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>During the call of the Ambassador,<note n="3" xml:id="d318fn3">Count
                                    Robert van der Straten-Ponthoz, Belgian Ambassador in the United
                                    States.</note> I took up with him the question of alcohol
                                smuggling into this country and spoke substantially along the
                                following lines:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Mr. Ambassador, I should like to discuss with you informally
                                        a situation which is of very real interest to the United
                                        States Government. Since last May, five steamers have sailed
                                        from Antwerp with a total of approximately 360,000 gallons
                                        of alcohol, destined for smuggling into the United States.
                                        Four of these vessels discharged their cargoes on the high
                                        seas into small, well-known smuggling vessels, and the fifth
                                        vessel landed its alcohol cargo at St. Pierre about the
                                        middle of last month. The illicit importation of this
                                        alcohol into the United States represents a loss to the
                                        United States Government of about five million dollars in
                                        revenue.</p>
                                    <p>“This smuggled alcohol is used as a base for the manufacture
                                        of cheap synthetic liquor; the 360,000 gallons which I have
                                        just mentioned would normally be manufactured into
                                        approximately 3,240,000 quarts of whiskey, gin, or brandy,
                                        which can, of course, be sold at a very low price since no
                                        duty or taxes have been paid on it. This illicit product, of
                                        course, competes with the products of legitimate producers,
                                        both foreign and domestic, and not only reduces their sales
                                        but has repercussions in allied trade and industries.</p>
                                    <p>“The United States Government has discussed with a number of
                                        other governments the elimination of this traffic. With the
                                        cooperation of other governments we have succeeded in
                                        eliminating all smuggling bases heretofore existing. Canada,
                                        Cuba, Guatemala, Mexico, Great Britain and France have each
                                        taken appropriate measures to put an end to the use of their
                                        territory as a smuggling base. It is precisely because of
                                        the cooperation which we have had from these governments
                                        that smugglers have in recent months been compelled to
                                        trans-ship their cargoes on the high seas. In most cases,
                                        the governments mentioned have eliminated the smuggling of
                                        alcohol by requiring a bond in an adequate amount of the
                                        production of a landing certificate to insure a delivery of
                                        the cargo at its declared destination.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0488" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/>
                                    <p>“Belgium now remains the only country from which large-scale
                                        alcohol smuggling operations are directed against the United
                                        States. I am told that Belgium already has a law, (enacted
                                        July 30, 1930), requiring the giving of a bond for the
                                        production of a landing certificate covering shipments of
                                        alcohol and spirits to neighboring countries. It would thus
                                        seem to be a relatively easy matter for Belgium to extend
                                        this law to include all shipments of these commodities,
                                        regardless of their destination. Such a step would be of
                                        great assistance to us, and would be in line with similar
                                        action already taken by other countries.</p>
                                    <p>“Last October and November, Ambassador Morris discussed this
                                        question in considerable detail with officials of the
                                        Belgian Government. At that time your Prime Minister told
                                        Mr. Morris that he would be disposed to recommend
                                        cooperative action along the abovementioned line, provided
                                        that Belgium’s neighbors took similar steps. May I emphasize
                                        in this regard that the British and French Governments have
                                        already taken action to prevent the use of their territory
                                        which has heretofore been used as smuggling bases, and that
                                        Belgium is the only country with which we now have a
                                        smuggling problem. In these circumstances it seems to me
                                        that your Government might well feel that it could cooperate
                                        with us in this matter without stipulating that we discuss
                                        hypothetical questions with other countries where no problem
                                        exists. In fact, I cannot conceal my disappointment at the
                                        attitude which your Government has thus far taken.</p>
                                    <p>“May I express the hope that you will ask your Government to
                                        reconsider its decision in this matter and give earnest
                                        consideration to cooperative action to put an end to this
                                        illicit traffic.”<note n="*" xml:id="d318fn4">The above
                                            quoted paragraphs are excerpts taken from a memorandum
                                            prepared in WE [Division of Western European Affairs]
                                            for the Secretary’s guidance, [Footnote in the
                                            original.]</note>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Ambassador expressed special interest in this matter and inquired
                                if he had not already written me a letter indicating that steps
                                would be taken. I replied that no letter had come to my attention,
                                but that I was aware of the fact that the Belgian Government had not
                                thus far taken any steps or shown any sign of taking steps to
                                cooperate with this Government under laws it already has for the
                                purpose of preventing this smuggling, which is so damaging to the
                                United States and worth so little to Belgium as a nation.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador said he would give the matter every attention right
                                away and felt sure his Government would be glad to cooperate.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ull</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>