<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-07-02T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-07-02T12:00:00-05:00" n="333" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 Belgium/260: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Chargé in Belgium</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sussdorff</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-07-02T13:00:00-04:00">July
                                        2, 1936—1 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>22. Your telegram No. 31, June 3, 5 p.m. and despatch No. 838, May
                                26, 1936.<note n="22" xml:id="d333fn22">Neither printed.</note>
                                Following excerpt from letter from Secretary of the Treasury may be
                                communicated in writing to the Belgian authorities: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“It is suggested that the Belgian Government should be
                                        advised that the laws of the United States authorize the
                                        Secretary of the Treasury to impose landing-certificate bond
                                        requirements upon any vessel of whatever nationality when
                                        necessary to protect the national revenue. This means that
                                        should a suspected vessel such as the <hi rend="italic">Hillfern</hi> attempt to clear from an American port
                                        for a foreign destination, a landing-certificate bond could
                                        be imposed, and in this connection it might be added that
                                        such a bond would certainly be imposed should this be
                                        requested by the authorities of the country against which
                                        her activities were supposed to be directed. This action
                                        would be possible under American law, notwithstanding the
                                        fact that the legislation by its terms relates to instances
                                        where such action is necessary to protect the national
                                        revenue, on the very proper theory that where any vessel is
                                        engaged in the smuggling traffic, her unlawful <pb facs="0503" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> activities might
                                        just as well be directed against the United States as
                                        against the foreign country supposed to be her actual
                                        destination.</p>
                                    <p>“Should a foreign-flag vessel come into an American port to
                                        take cargo under circumstances indicating an intent to
                                        smuggle such cargo into a foreign country or to permit this
                                        to be done by connivance with others, notice would be given
                                        to the ship’s master or agent that clearance would be
                                        permitted only after posting a substantial bond, this to be
                                        forfeited unless a landing certificate, properly
                                        authenticated by the customs authorities of the country of
                                        declared destination and evidencing lawful entry of such
                                        cargo into that country, should be produced in due course.
                                        If the operation of the suspected vessel were not
                                        legitimate, this would of course have the effect of
                                        preventing the loading of the vessel, for the reason that
                                        forfeiture of the bond would take all profit out of the
                                        proposed venture. The fact that the Government of the United
                                        States is known to be in a position to impose, and if
                                        necessary will unhesitatingly impose, landing certificate
                                        bond requirements, effectually prevents foreign-flag vessels
                                        from coming into American ports to take out cargoes destined
                                        for smuggling into other countries.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Above quotation embodied in note to Belgian Ambassador here.<note n="23" xml:id="d333fn23">Dated July 2, 1936; not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>For your own information see United States Code Title 19, Sections
                                1622, 1623 and 1624.</p>
                            <p>Instruction follows.<note n="24" xml:id="d333fn24">No. 379, July 1,
                                    1936; not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>