<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-22T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-22T22:00:00-05:00" n="34" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/632: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-23T03:00:00+00:00">January
                                    23, 1936—3 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received January 22—11 p.m.<note n="30" xml:id="d34fn30">Telegram in two sections.</note>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>64. The French Ambassador came to see me last night to discuss the future
                            procedure of the Conference, particularly with regard to inviting
                            Germany and Russia in at an early date as the British wished to do. He
                            said that while France, until the Anglo-German naval accord,<note n="31" xml:id="d34fn31">For correspondence concerning accord, see <ref target="frus1935v01#pg_162">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 162</ref> ff.</note> favored
                            bringing Germany into the naval negotiations, conditions had now changed
                            radically. In the first place the political situation in France is now
                            very precarious, and in the second place the British naval agreement
                            with Germany raises serious questions for France. He said that they were
                            now doubtful of the wisdom of making a naval agreement with Germany
                            unless they could get a secondary agreement as to land and air armaments
                            which he admitted was now impossible. Furthermore, he said that sitting
                            in conference with Germany to negotiate a new naval agreement would be
                            construed as a condonement of Germany’s violation of the Treaty of
                            Versailles.</p>
                        <p>The French consider it desirable to try to reach some agreement
                            temporarily to which we should endeavor to get Japan, Germany and Russia
                            to adhere at a later date, but that unless Japan, at least, were to
                            become a party to the agreement they could not see that it would be of
                            much value.</p>
                        <p>I told him that if such an agreement were only to be made effective on
                            condition that Japan adhere he could be sure that Japan would refuse,
                            but that if provision were made in such treaty for freedom of action on
                            the part of the contracting powers in case of departure from its limits
                            by a noncontracting power the latter would have more incentive to abide
                            by the limits fixed.</p>
                        <p>I added that the question of German participation was primarily one for
                            France and England to determine since we are not a party to the Treaty
                            of Versailles and since we do not wish to mix in European political
                            problems.</p>
                        <p>Monsieur Corbin then asked if there was a possibility of substantial
                            reductions in types which would justify us in going ahead. I told him we
                            could at least agree not to increase any of the types provided for under
                            existing treaties, either as to tonnage or calibre of guns and that I
                            thought we might perhaps agree upon certain reductions which I proceeded
                            to outline.</p>
                        <pb facs="0121" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/>
                        <p>He said that if that was all the reduction we could get it would be a
                            very great disappointment to the French.</p>
                        <p>I replied that although the minor reductions that could now be agreed
                            upon might be disappointing to certain powers it would be infinitely
                            better to agree not to increase existing types than to have no
                            qualitative agreement and an ensuing naval race which in the course of
                            years would make the present types seem small indeed. He remarked that
                            this was an important aspect to consider.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion Monsieur Corbin said that he was waiting for a further
                            reply from his Government in answer to his report of the talks he had
                            had with the British regarding Germany and that as soon as he received a
                            reply be would like to have another talk with me as they were anxious to
                            work out something if now possible.</p>
                        <p>In a conversation with Reber<note n="32" xml:id="d34fn32">Samuel Reber,
                                technical assistant for the Department of State.</note> tonight
                            Boncour and Deleuze<note n="33" xml:id="d34fn33">Jean Paul-Boncour and
                                Capt. E. E. Deleuze, technical advisers to the French
                                delegation.</note> reiterated what Corbin had said about the
                            impossibility from the political angle for France to agree at this time
                            to include Germany in the conference. No government in France could
                            survive if it agreed to making such advance to Germany. They said that
                            the British who had told them last summer that Germany would agree to
                            whatever qualitative limits were accepted by the five naval powers were
                            now insisting that she must be given an opportunity to express her own
                            views and must therefore be brought into the conference at some future
                            date. The French are convinced that the Anglo-German naval accord is
                            only valid pending the conclusion of a more comprehensive naval
                            agreement and that the British fear that if the wider agreement were to
                            prove unacceptable to Germany the bilateral accord would fall and
                            Germany regain her complete freedom of action.</p>
                        <p>The only solution which Boncour considers might be acceptable to his
                            Government is to have the four powers prepare the best qualitative
                            agreement possible and leave it open until the end of this year for the
                            adherence of Germany and of Japan. If these two powers have not accepted
                            by that time the others are going to again reconvene to discuss the
                            situation. The French add that even in this case England must accept the
                            responsibility of presenting this agreement to Germany.</p>
                        <p>The political situation in France is such, Boncour explained, that if
                            some such solution cannot be found the French feel that it might be
                            better to end the conference now and wait at least until after the
                            elections have taken place in France before resuming negotiations. They
                            add that this delay may also make Japan’s return easier. In order,
                            however, to avoid making the German issue the cause for <pb facs="0122" n="42" xml:id="pg_42"/> adjournment they may insist upon lower
                            qualitative limits—which they in any case would prefer—than are
                            acceptable either to England or to ourselves thus precluding any further
                            progress at this time.</p>
                        <p>Boncour leaves for Paris tomorrow to seek final instructions as to the
                            position France will adopt at the next meeting of the First Committee
                            now scheduled for January 29.</p>
                        <p>In a talk with Lord Monsell this evening he told me that while the French
                            were taking a very irreconcilable position just now he was convinced
                            that they would ultimately recede from it and accept a qualitative
                            agreement such as contemplated because it is of vital importance to
                            France that the Anglo-German naval agreement which is a protection to
                            France as well as to England should continue. Moreover, it is most
                            important for the French to have an agreement limiting the number of
                            8–inch gun cruisers which Germany can build and providing for exchange
                            of information.</p>
                        <p>The British have intimated to us that it is essential that any
                            qualitative agreement shall include Germany.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>