<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-04-16T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-04-16T17:00:00-05:00" n="340" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d340">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 St. Pierre-Miquelon/358a:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Straus</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-04-16T17:00:00-05:00">April
                                        16, 1936—5 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>123. Following is text of proposed decree forwarded to Minister of
                                Colonies April 5 by authorities at St. Pierre-Miquelon to replace
                                decree of April 9, 1935, now in effect: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <list>
                                        <item>“Article 1. Decree of April 18, 1922, derogating
                                            decree of July 8, 1919, concerning whiskies and gins,
                                            and decree of July 29, 1926, derogating decree of July
                                            8, 1919, concerning trois-six alcohol, are
                                            abrogated.</item>
                                        <item>Article 2. Decree of April 9, 1935, remains in force
                                            only for exportations of foreign alcohols in storage at
                                            St. Pierre-Miquelon.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0510" n="430" xml:id="pg_430"/>
                                        <item>Article 3. A decree countersigned by the Minister of
                                            Colonies will regulate, should such a case arise, the
                                            installation of distilleries of alcohol in St.
                                            Pierre-Miquelon.</item>
                                        <item>Article 4. All provisions to the contrary are
                                            abrogated.”</item>
                                    </list>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Above decree would prohibit importation foreign alcohols and whiskies
                                and permit importation and exportation of all French alcoholic
                                products.</p>
                            <p>Unless you perceive objection, please discuss matter informally with
                                French authorities and state that we greatly appreciate the helpful
                                cooperation which the French Government has given in the matter of
                                preventing the use of St. Pierre-Miquelon as a smuggling base, that
                                we hope it will be continued and that we do not believe they would
                                wish to see the unscrupulous persons engaged in the smuggling
                                traffic once more obtain a foothold at St. Pierre. In order to avoid
                                such a contingency it would seem to be desirable to retain certain
                                provisions of the present decree for all exports, namely, article 1,
                                prohibiting clearance for the high seas, article 2, prohibiting
                                clearance in vessels under 200 tons, and article 6, regarding
                                liquors for ships’ stores. It would seem to be especially necessary,
                                in order to prevent smuggling, that the landing certificate bond
                                continue to be required for all shipments of alcohol from St.
                                Pierre, regardless of its origin.</p>
                            <p>While the establishment of industries at St. Pierre-Miquelon is a
                                domestic matter, the establishment of a distillery to manufacture
                                alcohol would obviously be for the purpose of exporting it, as there
                                is practically no demand at St. Pierre for this product. Any alcohol
                                manufactured would therefore appear to be very likely intended for
                                smuggling into the United States, where the illicit product made
                                therefrom would compete with legitimate domestic and foreign
                                liquors, including those of France.</p>
                            <p>The continued cooperation of the French Government in preventing the
                                use of its territory so close to the shores of this country from
                                again being used as a base for smuggling into the United States,
                                would be greatly appreciated.</p>
                            <p>Telegraph reply for Treasury.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>