<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 St. Pierre-Miquelon/434:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-04T17:00:00+00:00">December 4, 1936—5 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 6:32 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1194. Department’s telegram No. 475, November 23, 7 p.m. We have been
                                informed by the Foreign Office that it intends to suggest <pb facs="0515" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/> to the Ministry of
                                Colonies that it add to the decree proposed by the Administration of
                                St. Pierre the following points: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>(1) The importation of French alcohols with the exception of
                                        “aperitifs, eaux-de-vie et spiritueux beneficiant d’une
                                        appellation d’origine ou constituant des pupiluits [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] de ‘marque’” shall be controlled
                                        by a quota strictly based upon the amount of local
                                        consumption with a view to eliminating fraud; (2) the
                                        “régime de la caution” with regard to the exportation of
                                        alcohol from St. Pierre will be maintained in force until
                                        the present stock in St. Pierre-Miquelon is exhausted; (3)
                                        the manufacture of “alcool de traite” will be
                                        prohibited.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>We suggested to the Foreign Office that in view of the fact that in
                                principle it wished to prohibit the exportation of alcohol from St.
                                Pierre there should be in the proposed decree a specific provision
                                to that effect. The Foreign Office informed us that it would suggest
                                this matter to the Ministry of Colonies but that it doubted that the
                                latter would agree thereto.</p>
                            <p>The Foreign Office likewise informed us that its suggestion with
                                regard to placing a quota on the importation into St. Pierre of
                                French alcohol would probably be refused by the Ministry of Colonies
                                which would likely propose that instead there be placed an import
                                tax of 15 francs per litre amounting to the same as the export tax
                                at present in force in order that the colonies might thereby benefit
                                by the increased revenue.</p>
                            <p>We have informed the Foreign Minister that we are reporting the
                                foregoing to the State Department in order to ascertain the
                                Department’s views thereon.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>