<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-09-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="547" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d547">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.4131/190</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. John R. Minter of the Division
                                    of Western European Affairs</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-09-21">September 21,
                                        1936</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Mr. Chalkley had come to the Department at our request to talk about
                                several dominion and colonial matters. Shortly after the <pb facs="0766" n="686" xml:id="pg_686"/> conversation began, Mr.
                                Dunn was called away by the Secretary and I continued alone to
                                convey to Chalkley the sense of our planned conversation. After
                                covering the subjects which we had planned to talk about Mr.
                                Chalkley inquired of me in a roundabout way regarding the outlook
                                for continuing conversations regarding a trade agreement with the
                                United Kingdom. He said that he hoped we were not overlooking the
                                time element; that his last conversations with the Department had
                                been in June; that he was told at that time that we would continue
                                our studies seeking a “basis”; that he wondered whether the “basis”
                                had been found and whether if found we were intentionally waiting
                                until after elections to reveal the same.</p>
                            <p>He went on to say that he had no instructions but that he was simply
                                taking this occasion to express his personal feeling that it would
                                be a physical impossibility to conclude an agreement before June 12,
                                    1937,<note n="49" xml:id="d547fn49">Date of expiration of the
                                    Trade Agreements Act.</note> if matters were still in a very
                                preliminary stage at the middle of November. He said that the
                                British had made no studies whatever and that he was sure they had
                                not the machinery for completing studies after announcement, say in
                                January, in time to begin negotiations which could be completed
                                before June 12.</p>
                            <p>I was convinced that Chalkley was actually obeying instructions to
                                “casually mention the subject on some suitable occasion.” I also
                                felt certain that the British must have done some intensive work in
                                preparation for more conversations. However I told Chalkley that
                                without having been present at the previous conversations or at any
                                time informed of exact reasons for delay I could only give a
                                personal opinion, not to mention that I also had no instructions. I
                                said that my personal opinion was that the best “basis” would be
                                conciliation of views and a common purpose in our commercial
                                policies. I had not detected the imminence of the desired <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>. Chalkley insisted that he
                                thought we came nearer to seeing eye to eye than we did earlier in
                                the year. I felt sure that Chalkley was aware of the recent
                                memoranda which the Secretary had had presented to Mr. Eden both
                                regarding commercial policy generally and such specific matters as
                                Anglo-Argentine and Anglo-Peruvian negotiations.</p>
                            <p>We did not however dwell long on this broad subject and the
                                conversation ended with Chalkley repeating his reminder of the
                                shortness of time in such a way as to lead me to believe that he
                                would like me in the same “uninstructed” way “on some suitable
                                occasion” to convey to him the true sense of the Department’s
                                present feelings on the general subject.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>