<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Bingham))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d569</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">569</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-07-09T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-07-09T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-07-09T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-07-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="569"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d569">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.79640/278: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-07-09T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 9, 1936—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>245. Your No. 328, June 29, 4 p.m. Please communicate the following immediately
                    to the British Foreign Office: <pb facs="0805" n="725" xml:id="pg_725"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have the honor to refer to the note of the Foreign Office of June 29,
                            1936, in regard to the establishment of the proposed transatlantic air
                            services and to state that my Government has given careful consideration
                            to the contents of that note and has instructed me to communicate the
                            following reply to His Majesty’s Government.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Separate Services.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>My Government has given most careful consideration to your comments with
                            reference to the United States–Bermuda service, and have noted that His
                            Majesty’s Government agree that aircraft employed on the United
                            States–Bermuda local service should be separate and independent from
                            those employed on the transatlantic service. My Government has likewise
                            noted your assurance that His Majesty’s Government have never intended,
                            nor do they intend, to use the local service between Bermuda and the
                            United States as a means of creating a separate transatlantic service,
                            additional to that provided in the draft permit now under
                            consideration.</p>
                        <p>Subject to the above conditions, my Government agrees to regard the
                            operations confined to the United States-Bermuda route as a separate
                            local service, with the understanding, however, that the permits for
                            this service shall run concurrently with the permit for the
                            transatlantic service, but shall lapse if such local service connects
                            with or becomes a part of any through service.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Information as to Airports and Airways or Routes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>My Government respectfully invites His Majesty’s Government’s attention
                            to the fact that it indicated in the note of the American Embassy of May
                            1, 1936, a series of airports on the Atlantic coast for use by the
                            proposed services, and is prepared, within its own territory and
                            territorial waters, to designate routes leading thereto. Maps indicating
                            such routes will be forwarded to London within a few days for delivery
                            to His Majesty’s Government. My Government now desires to be informed as
                            to the airports which will be made available to the American company
                            operating the services in the United Kingdom, Newfoundland and Bermuda
                            and as to the airways or routes leading thereto.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Communication with the Governments of Canada and the
                                Irish Free State.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Although it was stated in the note of the American Embassy of May 1,
                            1936, that my Government had indicated its intention of communicating
                            with the Governments of Canada and the Irish Free State, my Government
                            now believes that it might be more expeditious, if no objection is
                            perceived, for His Majesty’s Government to approach the Canadian and the
                            Irish Free State Governments with a view to having them furnish the
                            desired information as to airports and airways or routes within the
                            territorial jurisdiction of those Governments. As Canadian territory is
                            adjacent to the United States and as the air routes must necessarily
                            connect, my Government, in order to avoid delay, is also furnishing the
                            Canadian Government directly with information in regard to the proposed
                            routes in United States territory.</p>
                        <pb facs="0806" n="726" xml:id="pg_726"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Right of Revocation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>With reference to the right of revocation, my Government desires that His
                            Majesty’s Government be informed in response to specific inquiry that it
                            proposes to include in the permits to Imperial Airways, Limited, or a
                            company in which Imperial Airways hold a controlling interest, the
                            following provision: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>‘This permit may be withdrawn upon notice for important reasons
                                    of public policy when the conditions thereof or the actual
                                    practice thereunder is no longer regarded by the Government of
                                    the United States as being in its interest. Such notice shall be
                                    sent to your company only after consultation between the two
                                    Governments concerned for a period of at least 60 days.
                                    Withdrawal will take effect 2 years after such notice has been
                                    sent.’</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Texts of Permits.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>My Government will within a few days telegraph for transmission to His
                            Majesty’s Government the complete texts of the proposed permits.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Conclusion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>My Government earnestly hopes that the considerations set forth above
                            will be acceptable to His Majesty’s Government and that it will be
                            possible for both Governments to issue the permits, valid as of June 1,
                            1936, at an early date. My Government desires to add that it is prepared
                            to extend the most complete cooperation possible in any arrangements for
                            the conduct of preliminary experimental flights.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Please communicate to the British Foreign Office simultaneously with the above, a
                    further note in the following language: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have the honor to refer to previous correspondence concerning the
                            establishment of transatlantic and United States–Bermuda air
                            services.</p>
                        <p>With reference to the acceptability of Pan American Airways Company for
                            the proposed services my Government is pleased to inform His Majesty’s
                            Government that the fundamental data referred to in the letter of the
                            Acting Secretary of Commerce of December 15 [<hi rend="italic">13</hi>],
                                1935,<note n="89" xml:id="d569fn89">Not printed.</note> addressed to
                            the Director General of Civil Aviation in Great Britain, have been
                            submitted by Pan American Airways Company, and that the company is
                            acceptable to the United States Government and is hereby approved for
                            the proposed services, which approval shall remain in force and effect
                            so long as there is no violation of present or future laws of the United
                            States and the company continues to provide a reasonably efficient air
                            transport service.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
