<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the American Delegation ( (Davis) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-02-21T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-02-21T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-21T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-21T09:00:00-05:00" n="57"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d57">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/672: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-21T14:00:00+00:00"
                            >February 21, 1936—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 21—11:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>102. In a talk with Eden last evening he told me in substance the following:
                    Their Ambassador in Paris had under instructions made representations to Flandin
                    to the effect that a naval agreement is vitally important to both Great Britain
                    and to France. That if such an agreement is to be satisfactory and effective it
                    is essential that Germany be a party. Hence the British Government must ask the
                    French Government as an act of friendship to aid in bringing about such
                    agreement. Furthermore the Ambassador informed Flandin that it is essential for
                    Anglo-French cooperation that France give this concrete evidence of her desire
                    to cooperate in the proper spirit and that if the French should block a naval
                    agreement it would have a very serious reaction on public opinion in
                    England.</p>
                <p>Eden said he was somewhat hopeful as French were now showing more of an
                    inclination to fall into line.</p>
                <p>I told Eden that Corbin had indicated to me (see my 99, February 19, 8 p.m.) the
                    idea of making a naval agreement dependent upon general political development
                    and what my reply had been. Eden said he thought I was quite correct in refusing
                    to have a naval agreement dependent upon political developments or settlements;
                    that while the British would be glad to have an air agreement they were opposed
                    to making such an agreement dependent upon a naval agreement or vice versa. He
                    will make it clear to the French that the best preparation for a subsequent air
                    agreement would be an unconditional naval agreement with Germany as a party to
                    it. He will furthermore point out that if an attempt were made to get an air and
                    a naval agreement at the same time the result would be not to get either
                    one.</p>
                <p>I suggest for your consideration that if de Laboulaye approaches you again, or if
                    there is an opportunity to do so, it would be helpful if you take a similar line
                    while explaining, of course, that what the French and British do as between
                    themselves is of no concern of ours except as it affects a general naval
                    agreement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
