<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-03-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="647" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d647">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 Canada/5065</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division
                                    of Western European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conference at the
                                    Treasury Department on March 30, 1936</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-03-31">March 31,
                                    1936</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The following persons were present: <list>
                                    <item>Treasury Department: <list>
                                            <item>Acting Secretary Wayne Taylor (in whose office the
                                                conference was held)</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Harold Graves, Special Assistant to the
                                                Secretary of the Treasury</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Eli Frank, Assistant to the General Counsel,
                                                Treasury Department.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Department of State: <list>
                                            <item>Assistant Secretary R. W. Moore</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Green H. Hackworth<note n="28" xml:id="d647fn28">Legal Adviser.</note>
                                            </item>
                                            <item>Mr. John Hickerson</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <pb facs="0891" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/>
                                    <item>Canadian Representatives: <list>
                                            <item>The Canadian Chargé d’Affaires, Mr. Hume
                                                Wrong</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Lazarus Phillips and</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Sam Jacobs, representing Joseph E. Seagram and
                                                Sons, Ltd., and the Distillers Corporation, Ltd.
                                                (these companies comprising the so-called Bronfman
                                                interests).</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Jack Lash, of Toronto, representing Hiram
                                                Walker and Sons, Ltd., Gooderham and Wortz,
                                                Ltd.</item>
                                            <item>Colonel J. L. Ralston and</item>
                                            <item>Mr. Forsythe, representing Canadian Industrial
                                                Alcohol, Ltd. (of which the Consolidated Distillers,
                                                Ltd., is a subsidiary).</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>After a few introductory remarks by Acting Secretary Taylor and Mr.
                                Wrong, Mr. Frank, of the Treasury Department, stated that he thought
                                that the representatives of the Canadian companies understood the
                                nature of the claims which the Treasury Department was asserting
                                against them; that is, a claim for $5.00 import duty and $2.00
                                excise tax per proof gallon of spirits introduced into the United
                                States during 1933 and earlier years of the prohibition era, to say
                                nothing of possible income tax claims.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Forsythe, representing Canadian Industrial Alcohol, stated that
                                the company which he represented had a new president, who assumed
                                office in 1934, the Board of Directors had changed completely since
                                1933, and there had been great changes in lists of stockholders. He
                                went on to say that he found it difficult to understand how the
                                management of the company as now constituted could be said to be
                                responsible in any way for any alleged actions on the part of their
                                predecessors, actions of which Mr. Forsythe stated he was totally
                                ignorant and about which he could express no opinion. He and Colonel
                                Ralston expressed the thought that the pending legislation is unfair
                                and unprecedented. They stated that they had never heard of
                                legislation which in effect gave an executive official power to
                                force a private company in a friendly country to withdraw from
                                business on the assertion of a claim against it; they stated that
                                this was prejudging the merits of the claim and giving the company
                                virtually no recourse.</p>
                            <p>The representatives of the Treasury Department insisted that the
                                Canadian companies misunderstood the nature of the proposed
                                legislation. There then followed a brief discussion of the
                                legislation, inconclusive in nature, until someone suggested that
                                the purpose of the meeting being to devise a means to make the
                                legislation unnecessary, the discussion of the legislation was
                                perhaps out of place. Acting Secretary Taylor thereupon stated that
                                this was true and that the discussion might well be confined to
                                practical assurances on the part of the Canadian concerns that they
                                would appear in court to contest any suits which the Government
                                brought against them and <pb facs="0892" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/>
                                give guarantees that the United States Government would be enabled
                                to collect any judgment which it might obtain. At this point Mr.
                                Forsythe stated that, notwithstanding his earlier comments about the
                                complete ignorance of his company in respect of any alleged
                                infractions of American law on the part of their predecessors, at
                                the request of the Canadian Government his firm had sent him to
                                Washington to discuss the whole question with the Treasury
                                Department. He said that he was completely in the dark and would
                                find it difficult to discuss “practical assurances” until he knew
                                the amount of the American Government’s claim against his company
                                and the nature of the charges. The representatives of the Treasury
                                Department indicated that they were not in a position at this time
                                to reveal the amount of the claim. There was much discussion over
                                the point of whether practical assurances could be given by the
                                companies until they knew the amounts of the Treasury’s claims. Mr.
                                Lash, representing the Hiram Walker interests, and Mr. Phillips
                                stated that they were of the same mind as Mr. Forsythe about the
                                necessity for information respecting the amounts of the claims.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Lazarus Phillips, representing the Seagram interests, stated that
                                he and other legal representatives of his company had seen various
                                references in the American press to possible claims by the Treasury
                                Department against their company and had at various times last year
                                discussed the question informally with legal representatives of the
                                Treasury Department. He indicated that then, as now, his company was
                                prepared to discuss a settlement out of court; if this could not be
                                achieved he was, he said, even though his company considered the
                                Treasury claim without merit, prepared to discuss practical
                                assurances that his company would contest the suits in our court and
                                pay any judgments obtained against them. He stated, however, that he
                                regretted to see the haste with which the Treasury Department
                                desired to proceed in the matter of the pending legislation. He
                                urged that the Treasury Department drop Section 403 in the pending
                                bill in order that the enactment of the general liquor tax bill at
                                the earliest possible date be facilitated. He stated that he was
                                sure that the other Canadian companies would be prepared to discuss
                                their cases fully and frankly with the Treasury Department and that,
                                should it not be possible in the next month or six weeks to obtain
                                settlements or satisfactory assurances that the companies will
                                submit to our jurisdiction and pay judgment obtained against them,
                                the Treasury could then very easily obtain either this legislation
                                which is now pending or a modified version of it. He made it clear
                                that he considered the legislation unfair but indicated that he
                                believed that the Treasury Department might find that it was
                                unnecessary.</p>
                            <p>Acting Secretary Taylor, after about an hour and a half of
                                conversation along the above-mentioned lines, suggested that the
                                meeting <pb facs="0893" n="813" xml:id="pg_813"/> be adjourned and
                                that the representatives of the Canadian companies discuss their
                                cases either individually or collectively with representatives of
                                the Bureau (presumably the Bureau of Customs). This was agreed to,
                                and Judge Moore, Mr. Hackworth, and Mr. Hickerson left the
                                meeting.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hickerson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>