<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-02-22T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-02-22T09:00:00-05:00" n="1" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102S/1739: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-02-22T22:00:00+08:00">February 22, 1939—10
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received February 22—2 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>139. The Japanese Consul General<note n="2" xml:id="d1fn2">Y.
                                    Miura.</note> accompanied by the commanders of the Japanese
                                naval landing party and the Japanese Army garrison called on the
                                Chairman of the Shanghai Municipal Council<note n="3" xml:id="d1fn3">Cornell S. Franklin, American lawyer.</note> this afternoon and
                                handed him a communication which is summarized below. At the same
                                time the Japanese Consul General stated orally that the requests
                                made in the communication were presented in a genuine spirit of
                                cooperation and good will with a view to the suppression of
                                terrorist activities, adding that there is reason to believe that
                                these activities are being carried on for the purpose of causing a
                                direct clash between Japan and the Municipal Council and also with
                                some third powers especially Great Britain and “we must be very
                                careful not to be trapped by such a sinister strategy.”</p>
                            <p>The written communication refers to various representations made to
                                the Council regarding terrorist activities and comments that while
                                the Council must have been in possession of reports that such
                                activities were contemplated during Chinese New Year holidays and
                                the Council should have taken strict precautionary measures during
                                these days, according to reliable information the Council sent a
                                large number of police off duty on New Year’s Day, thus weakening
                                the actual strength of the force at a time when it ought to have
                                been augmented. The letter says that such an attitude on the part of
                                the Council is difficult to understand and “I cannot help expressing
                                my doubt about its sincere sympathy.”</p>
                            <p>The letter proceeds to comment on recent occurrences and the
                                ineffectiveness of the police in dealing with them and states that
                                breach <pb facs="0008" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> of peace and order in
                                Shanghai has serious effects upon peace and order and the
                                pacification of the people in the whole Japanese occupied area and
                                therefore “cannot be viewed with indifference by the Japanese
                                authorities who are endeavoring for the establishment of a new order
                                in East Asia.”</p>
                            <p>The letter finally submits the following requests: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>That the emergency proclamation of the Municipal Council
                                        dated July 19, 1938,<note n="4" xml:id="d1fn4">See telegram
                                            No. 992, July 14, 1938, 6 p.m., from the Consul General
                                            at Shanghai, <ref target="frus1938v03#pg_225"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1938, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p.
                                            225</ref>.</note> concerning the arrest and expulsion of
                                        criminals shall be strictly enforced.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>That the Japanese police organs, including the <hi rend="italic">gendarmerie</hi> and the consular police,
                                        should at whatever place and time necessary in the
                                        International Settlement take necessary measures for the
                                        protection of the Japanese subjects and the suppression of
                                        terrorism and thus cooperate with the municipal police
                                        force.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>That the Japanese authorities when they deem it necessary
                                        should in cooperation with the municipal authorities search
                                        the Chinese people entering the Settlement from or leaving
                                        it to the Whangpoo River or the Soochow Creek and the goods
                                        carried by them and detain them if not allowed.</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>That the Japanese branch of the municipal police should
                                        immediately be strengthened.</item>
                                    <label>(5)</label>
                                    <item>That the search of Chinese people at key points in the
                                        Settlement should be enforced immediately.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The letter then adds that the Japanese authorities reserve the right
                                to make other demands in connection with the matter and asks for a
                                reply at the earliest convenience.</p>
                            <p>The contents of the communication have not been published here but at
                                a press conference this evening the spokesman stated that the
                                Japanese authorities had presented the Council with “a plan” to deal
                                with the situation.</p>
                            <p>Developments will be reported.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Chungking, Peiping and Tokyo.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>