<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="17"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102S/1780</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2062</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-03-16">March 16,
                            1939</date>.<lb/>[Received April 26.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my despatch No. 2045
                    of March 10, 1939, reporting further developments connected with the demands
                    made by the Japanese authorities upon the Shanghai Municipal Council.</p>
                <p>Attention is invited to the final paragraph of the above mentioned despatch in
                    which it was pointed out that although the situation facing the Municipal Police
                    is admittedly a difficult one, the tendency shown by the Municipal Police to
                    allow the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> to encroach on their
                    authority is one that may lead to independent action by the Japanese military
                    police in the International Settlement. There is now enclosed a copy of a
                    letter, dated March 13,<note n="28" xml:id="d17fn28">Not printed.</note>
                    addressed by the Commanding Officer of the U. S. Fourth Marines to the Liaison
                    Officer at Japanese Military Headquarters concerning an incident which occurred
                    within the American Defense Sector on the morning of March 11 in which the
                    Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> were discovered to be engaged in the
                    arrest of a Chinese and to be taking action independent of the Shanghai
                    Municipal Police. It will be noted that Colonel Fegan stressed the point that
                    the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> have no right to take
                    independent action in the American Sector. There is also enclosed a copy of a
                    letter, dated March 13,<note n="28" xml:id="d17fn30">Not printed.</note>
                    addressed by Colonel Fegan to the Commissioner of the Shanghai Municipal Police
                        <pb facs="0025" n="19" xml:id="pg_19"/> regarding this same incident, in
                    which the former sets forth his position in regard to the conduct of raids
                    carried out in the American Sector in cooperation with Japanese police organs,
                    and in which he reiterates that independent Japanese action in the conduct of
                    such raids cannot be permitted.</p>
                <p>As an instance of further Japanese attempts to encroach upon the authority of the
                    Shanghai Municipal Police, there is enclosed a copy of a police report, dated
                    March 12,<note n="29" xml:id="d17fn29">Not printed.</note> concerning the
                    attempted establishment by the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> of an
                    office in a Chinese hotel located in the heart of the Settlement and within the
                    British Defense Sector. As will be noted, the Commissioner of Police brought
                    this matter to the attention of the Commandant of the Japanese <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gendarmerie</hi> and pointed out that the presence of police other than the
                    Municipal Police could not be approved without the consent of the Municipal
                    Council and the military commander in charge of the defense sector concerned,
                    and requested that instructions be issued to this Japanese <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gendarmerie</hi> office to cease functioning pending discussions between
                    those concerned. At the same time the Commissioner addressed a letter to the
                    British Commandant concerning this matter.</p>
                <p>Latest reports received from the Shanghai Municipal Police indicate that some
                    twenty Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> officers and men are still in
                    the hotel mentioned above, and it appears that the position taken by the British
                    military authorities is that inasmuch as these Gendarmes are in plain clothes,
                    the establishment of such an office is purely a police matter and not the
                    concern of the foreign military commanders. The British position was revealed at
                    an informal conference held on March 13 between the commanding officers of the
                    various foreign defense forces, including the Italian Commandant, and the
                    Secretary of the Council and the Commissioner of Police. A copy of a letter,
                    dated March 15, addressed to me by Colonel Fegan, outlining the discussions
                    which took place at the conference mentioned, is enclosed.<note n="29"
                        xml:id="d17fn31">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It will be noted from Colonel Fegan’s letter that after some discussion the
                    British military commandant apparently agreed to associate himself with the
                    American commandant in supporting the Commissioner of Police in his protest to
                    the Commandant of the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> against the
                    establishment by the Japanese of any offices or police detachments within the
                    International Settlement south of Soochow Creek without the prior approval and
                    sanction of the Municipal Council and the Municipal Police. However, I have
                    ascertained from Police Headquarters that the British military authorities have
                    not replied to the Commissioner’s letter regarding the establishment of the
                    Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> office referred to above and <pb
                        facs="0026" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> that no reply has been received from the
                    Commandant of the Japanese <hi rend="italic">Gendarmerie</hi> concerning this
                    matter.</p>
                <p>In regard to the question of the conduct of raids at the instigation of the
                    Japanese, the consensus of opinion of the military commandants present at the
                    informal conference held on March 13, was that it was neither necessary nor
                    desirable for military observers to be present at all raids but that they should
                    be informed prior to the inception of any raid within their respective sectors
                    and should reserve the right to have observers present if they so desire.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C. E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
