<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Amoy ( (MacVitty) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-30T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-30T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-30T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-30T23:00:00-05:00" n="182"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102 Kulangsu/247: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Amoy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVitty</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Amoy</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-31T12:00:00+08:00"
                            >August 31, 1939—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received August 31—8:35
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>My August 23, 8 p.m. and August 24, 7 p.m.<note n="28" xml:id="d182fn28">Latter
                        not printed.</note> Uchida said day before yesterday that his Foreign Office
                    rejected his suggestion as outlined in the above mentioned telegrams, and
                    insists on the appointment of a new Japanese inspector of police, in addition to
                    the present Japanese sub-inspector, the new appointee to rank with but after the
                    Russian; he added that the other questions mentioned in the telegram under
                    reference could be satisfactorily arranged; that the new arrangements would not
                    be a financial burden to the Municipal Council; that reduction in the number of
                    new Japanese constables would be considered; but that the coercive measures
                    could not be lifted until an agreement was reached.</p>
                <p>If my colleagues and the Municipal Council had favored acceptance of this plan I
                    would have interposed no objection; however, last night it was decided not to
                    consider Uchida’s informal proposal through Benninghoff for the following
                    reasons: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>It is backed by threats and coercive measures.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The appointment of a Japanese inspector, nominated by his Government
                            to an important administrative position in the international Settlement
                            and over whom the Municipal Council could exercise only a nominal
                            control, would jeopardize the independence and international character
                            of the Settlement.</item>
                        <pb facs="0160" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The Council cannot consider having Japan pay the salary of any of its
                            employees. Benninghoff informally conveyed this decision to Uchida. It
                            might also be added that despite any guarantees which may be made, the
                            Settlement authorities fear that further demands would be made within a
                            short time.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I feel almost certain that if the Japanese Foreign Office would accept the
                    promotion of the present Japanese sub-inspector, it would be possible to settle
                    quickly the Kulangsu problem.</p>
                <p>Sent to Peiping. Repeated to Chungking, Shanghai. Peiping please repeat to
                    Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVitty</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
