<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-03-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.5034 (China)/472</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Peck</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 658</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-03-18">March 18, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to the Embassy’s
                                despatch no. 1874, January 12, 1939,<note n="26" xml:id="d350fn26">Not printed.</note> in regard to the application of the
                                Tientsin Investment Corporation, Incorporated, for registration as
                                an American firm.</p>
                            <p>An examination of the material submitted with your despatch indicates
                                that the place of business of the applicant is at Tientsin, China,
                                and that it maintains an office in the United States merely for the
                                purpose of complying with the laws of Nevada under which the
                                Corporation was created. The applicant is engaged in the business of
                                banking at Tientsin without any governmental supervision of or check
                                upon its activities. There is no American governmental machinery in
                                existence for such supervision.</p>
                            <p>Events have shown the need for governmental supervision of the
                                activities of banks. No enterprise would be permitted to engage in
                                the business of banking in the United States without such
                                supervision and the Department believes that the development of
                                American banking abroad, without governmental supervision, under the
                                framework of American extraterritoriality should note that paragraph
                                7 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) of Section 4 of the China Trade Act,
                                1922, provides <hi rend="italic">inter alia:</hi>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“A China Trade Act corporation shall not engage in the
                                        business of discounting bills, notes, or other evidences of
                                        debt, of receiving deposits, of buying and selling bills of
                                        exchange, or of issuing bills, notes, or other evidences of
                                        debt, for circulation as money; nor engage in any other form
                                        of banking business; …”<note n="27" xml:id="d350fn27">Omission indicated in the original
                                        instruction.</note></p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>The examples afforded by the Oriental Banking Corporation and the
                                Thrift Investment Finance and Trust Corporation also point to <pb facs="0309" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> the soundness of the view
                                that unregulated banking enterprise in the Far East should not be
                                encouraged.</p>
                            <p>American banks operating in the United States with branches abroad
                                are subject to supervision at home and their branches in China are
                                thus in a category different from that of banks which operate solely
                                abroad.</p>
                            <p>Under the circumstances outlined above, and without going into the
                                question of the amount of American interest in the Tientsin
                                Investment Corporation or into the question of the soundness or
                                nationality of its management, the Department is of the opinion that
                                the application of the Tientsin Investment Corporation for consular
                                registration should be disapproved.</p>
                            <p>Please send copies of this instruction to the various consular
                                offices in China for their information and guidance in similar
                                cases.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">R.
                                        Walton Moore</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>