<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-03-21T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-03-21T20:00:00-05:00" n="352" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">393.115 Standard-Vacuum Oil Co./99:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-03-22T09:00:00+08:00">March 22, 1939—9
                                        a.m.</date><lb/>[Received March 22—7:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Embassy’s 171, March 13, 2 p.m. The Chairman of the Chekiang
                                Provincial Government has not yet replied to my telegram of March 10
                                and the Standard-Vacuum Oil Company now informs me orally that they
                                have received information from their Ningpo agent to the effect that
                                the garrison commander at Ningpo has received no instructions from
                                the Provincial Chairman in regard to the matter of the illegal tax
                                imposed on the company’s steamer <hi rend="italic">Meinan</hi>. The
                                agent further reports that the garrison commander now insists on
                                collecting retroactively public welfare tax on the last six trips of
                                the vessel and that he will commence on April 1 the collection of
                                ships survey fee.</p>
                            <p>I am again telegraphing the Chairman of the Chekiang Provincial
                                Government requesting that action be taken to prevent the garrison
                                commander at Ningpo from imposing illegal taxes on American shipping
                                and respectfully suggest that the Embassy again approach the Chinese
                                Government with a view to having appropriate instructions issued
                                promptly not only to the Chairman of the Chekiang Provincial
                                Government but also to the garrison commander at Ningpo.</p>
                            <p>Sent to Chungking.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>