<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Japan ( (Dooman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d552</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">552</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-01T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-01T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-01T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-01T05:00:00-05:00" n="552"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d552">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894.5151/145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dooman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-01T19:00:00+09:00"
                            >August 1, 1939—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received August 1—9:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>380. Department’s 229, July 29, 3 p.m., blocked funds American President
                    Lines.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Upon the receipt of the Department’s 177, June 29, 6 p.m., the matter of
                        the blocked funds was taken up with the Foreign Office and continually
                        pressed. On July 20 Mr. Yoshizawa<note n="31" xml:id="d552fn31">Seijiro
                            Yoshizawa, Director of American Affairs Bureau, Japanese Foreign
                            Office.</note> was handed a copy in paraphrase of the Department’s 177
                        with the request that he lay the matter before the Foreign Minister.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Upon the receipt of the Department’s 209, July 21, 9 [<hi rend="italic"
                            >4</hi>] p.m., Mr. Yoshizawa was again approached, the telegram read to
                        him and he was informed that I proposed to see the Vice Minister<note n="32"
                            xml:id="d552fn32">Renzo Sawada.</note> that day regarding the matter.
                        Mr. Yoshizawa asked that I refrain from seeing the Foreign Minister as he
                        would give us a favorable reply that afternoon. Mr. Yoshizawa replied the
                        same afternoon as reported in our 359, July 24, 6 p.m. The following day a
                        member of the Foreign Office telephoned the Embassy that the Ministry of
                        Finance was seeking some method by which the funds of the American Line
                        could be promptly transferred. We are still awaiting information on this
                        phase.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I called this afternoon on the Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs and went
                        into this matter at great length. I emphasized the importance of the
                        President Line being permitted to remit funds promptly to the United States;
                        I described the freedom with which Japanese steamship companies could remit
                        to Japan their earnings in the United States; and I followed with a
                        statement following closely along the lines of the Department’s 229. I
                        called Sawada’s attention to the fact that the Japanese Government is
                        expected to set up a system for the prompt remittance of earnings in Japan
                        of American steamship companies; and I asked in conclusion that he indicate
                        to me as soon as possible the date on which I might expect to receive a
                        favorable reply.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I also took up this matter again with Yoshizawa today making
                        representations similar to those which I made to the Vice Minister.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dooman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
