<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Vernon L. Phelps of the Division of Trade
                    Agreements</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="564"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d564">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.8331/122</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Vernon L. Phelps of the
                        Division of Trade Agreements</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-07-31">July 31,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Egyptian Minister</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Hawkins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Phelps</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Egyptian Minister called by appointment on July 31, 1939 to discuss further
                    the possibility of undertaking trade-agreement negotiations between the United
                    States and Egypt, with particular reference to the observations of the Committee
                    on Foreign Trade in Egypt (outlined in the attached memorandum handed to Mr.
                    Alling by the Minister on July 17<note n="24" xml:id="d564fn24">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>) relative to the Department’s
                    suggestions regarding the possibility of undertaking negotiations which were
                    contained in the informal memorandum handed to the Minister on April 24,
                        1939.<note n="25" xml:id="d564fn25">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_495">p. 495</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Minister was told that an informal memorandum would be prepared for him
                    containing this Government’s views regarding the <pb facs="0506" n="500"
                        xml:id="pg_500"/> observations of the Committee on Foreign Trade in Egypt,
                    but that it seemed desirable to discuss certain points in connection therewith.
                    (This memorandum, intended to be handed to the Minister, is attached
                        hereto).<note n="26" xml:id="d564fn26">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Referring to the products which might constitute the basis for possible
                    concessions by Egypt, contained in Lists A and B of the Department’s memorandum
                    of April 24, Mr. Hawkins stated that this Government feels that it could not
                    agree to the withdrawal of all the items in List B (tariff items with respect to
                    which it was proposed that the existing moderate Egyptian customs duties be
                    bound) but it would be disposed to give consideration to possible modification
                    of both Lists A and B in the event decision should be reached to proceed with
                    active negotiations.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that the Egyptian authorities desire to exclude List B from
                    consideration for the reasons that (1) the United States is not the principal
                    supplier of these products and (2) it is against the policy of the Egyptian
                    Government to bind existing statutory customs duties in its commercial
                        agreements.<note n="*" xml:id="d564fn29">Subsequent investigation has
                        revealed that in the one existing Egyptian commercial agreement containing
                        reciprocal tariff concessions, that between Egypt and Palestine of August
                        18, 1936, the rates of duty on certain products which had been promulgated
                        by decree in July 1935 were consolidated in the agreement without change.
                        However, it appears that the promulgation of these reduced rates in July
                        1935 was the direct result of the visit of a Palestine Trade Mission to
                        Egypt in June 1935 so that their consolidation in the agreement of August
                        18, 1936 seems to have been simply the publication of the terms of an
                        agreement reached a year earlier and made effective at that time by decree.
                        (See despatch, Treaty Series No. 7 (1937), from London, February 3, 1937,
                        enclosure 1, containing the text of this agreement (667N.8331/6), and the
                        Acting Commercial Attaché economic and trade notes no. 15, July 8, 1935,
                        “Egyptian Customs Tariff Changes.”) [Footnote in the original.]</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Hawkins stated that, since it is the general policy of this Government in its
                    trade-agreement negotiations to request concessions on products in respect of
                    which the United States is the principal or an important supplier of the other
                    country’s imports, we would not maintain a request for a concession on a product
                    with respect to which further investigation shows clearly that the United States
                    is a minor supplier of the Egyptian market. In this connection, the Minister
                    promised to supply the Department with 1938 statistics of Egyptian imports of
                    the items in the aforementioned Lists A and B.</p>
                <p>With respect to the Egyptian request for a tariff reduction of 50 percent on
                    cottonseed oil, the Minister was informed that it is also the general policy of
                    the United States to grant concessions only on products in respect of which the
                    other country is the principal or an important supplier, and that therefore no
                    concession to Egypt on this product could be considered for the reason that
                    Egypt is a minor supplier of the American market.</p>
                <pb facs="0507" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/>
                <p>As to a concession on long-staple cotton, the problems involved and the
                    difficulties arising in connection with the formulation of a decision at this
                    time were explained to the Minister, and he was informed that pending the
                    outcome of the meeting on cotton to be held in Washington in September<note
                        n="27" xml:id="d564fn27">See <ref target="frus1939v02">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>
                        </ref>, section entitled “Meeting of Representatives of Chief Cotton
                        Exporting Countries …”</note> and a definitive formulation of its domestic
                    cotton program, this Government finds itself unable to decide whether a
                    concession could be granted on long-staple cotton. In this connection, the
                    Minister suggested that no reference be made to long-staple cotton in the
                    informal memorandum (attached hereto) containing the views of this Government
                    regarding the observations of the Egyptian Committee on Foreign Trade, for the
                    reason that the Department’s position regarding this matter had been fully
                    covered in its memorandum of April 24, 1939. Nevertheless, it seems desirable,
                    in view of the fact that the invitations to the meeting on cotton to be held in
                    Washington in September 1939 and the announcement of this Government’s export
                    subsidy on cotton<note n="28" xml:id="d564fn28">Announced by the Secretary of
                        Agriculture on July 22, 1939, to be effective July 27, 1939.</note> were
                    both issued subsequently to April 24, 1939, to state clearly our position on the
                    matter at this time.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
