<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Italy ( (Phillips) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="585"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d585">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">365D.1163/161</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1716</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-01-23">January 23,
                            1940</date>.<lb/>[Received February 9.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Confirming my telegram No. 52 of January 22, 7
                        p.m.,<note n="15" xml:id="d585fn15">Not printed.</note> I have the honor to
                    transmit herewith a copy and translation of a Note dated January 13, 1940
                    (received by the Embassy January 20) from the Italian Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs in reply to my communication to him of November 21, 1939, which I
                    delivered pursuant to your instruction No. 547 of November 10, 1939, File No.
                    365D.1163.</p>
                <p>As reported in my telegram No. 52, Count Ciano takes the position that the
                    procedure of the Italian East African authorities in expropriating the hospital
                    owned by the United Presbyterian Mission at Addis Ababa and in expelling the
                    Mission’s representatives from Ethiopia was entirely in accordance with the
                    legislation applicable in such matters.</p>
                <p>The letter mentioned in the penultimate paragraph of Count Ciano’s Note was dated
                    June 18, not January 18, 1937.<note n="16" xml:id="d585fn16">See telegram No.
                        291, June 21, 1937, 1 p.m. from the Ambassador in Italy, <ref
                            target="frus1937v02#pg_710">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 710</ref>.</note> In that letter the
                    Minister, speaking of the future activities of foreign missions in the conquered
                    territory, said “If the said missions, outside the educational field, intend to
                    carry on work of a humanitarian and <pb facs="0529" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/>
                    philanthropic character, any requests will in due course be examined, <hi
                        rend="underline">when the juridical question of recognition of the Empire
                        has become an accomplished fact.</hi>” (Underlining supplied).</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ciano</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Ambassador</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">13/01477/3</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-01-13">January 13,
                                1940</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my
                        letter No. 242139/120 of December 3, 1939<note n="17" xml:id="d585fn17">See
                            last paragraph of despatch No. 1676, December 18, 1939, from the
                            Ambassador in Italy, <ref target="#pg_522">p. 522</ref>.</note> and to
                        submit to Your Excellency the information given me by the Royal Ministry of
                        Italian Africa regarding the expropriation of the hospital of the American
                        United Presbyterian Church Mission in Addis Ababa and the expulsion of Dr.
                        John A. Cremer and the Rev. Duncan C. Henry from Italian East Africa.</p>
                    <p>As regards the hospital at Addis Ababa, the competent Royal Authorities have
                        advised that, for reasons of public utility, expropriation was ordered under
                        Viceregal Decree No. 124 of July 8, 1939, and indemnification therefor
                        established as 980,000 lire.</p>
                    <p>Following the protest presented by the aforesaid mission and in partial
                        satisfaction thereof, the indemnification was raised to 1,370,000 lire—an
                        amount set by a special and regularly constituted commission, which
                        appraised the various real property of which the hospital is composed on an
                        absolutely fair basis.</p>
                    <p>In the event that the aforesaid mission deems it cannot accept the
                        above-mentioned indemnification for expropriation, it can resort to the
                        usual legal procedure provided for in expropriation cases by the legislation
                        of Italian East Africa, which is the same as Italian legislation.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the payment of the sum of 1,370,000 lire, the Governor General
                        of Italian East Africa has advised that such payment could be made without
                        further formality during the current month, but that it does not appear
                        possible to make payment in American currency, in view of the regulations
                        governing foreign exchange.</p>
                    <p>As regards the expulsion of the two above-mentioned American citizens from
                        the territory of Italian East Africa, the competent Royal Authorities have
                        pointed out that, independently of other motives, such expulsion is the
                        result of a provision of general character, strictly <pb facs="0530" n="524"
                            xml:id="pg_524"/> applied to Italian nationals as well, prohibiting
                        sojourn in Italian East Africa by anyone not engaged in some specific
                        activity.</p>
                    <p>In this connection the competent Royal Authorities have stated that the
                        liquidation of the Gore and Saio missions has also been completed.</p>
                    <p>The presence in Italian East Africa of the two individuals in question could
                        not, moreover, be justified by humanitarian and philanthropic activities on
                        their part: in this connection I refer to the letter I had the honor to send
                        Your Excellency on January (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) 18, 1937.</p>
                    <p>In any case I remain at your disposal for any further explanations and
                        information you may desire.</p>
                    <p>I am, Mr. Ambassador,</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ciano</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
