<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="621" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d621">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">882.20/431</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Walton</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 251</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-03">January 3, 1939</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    January 27.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to make the following
                                observations:</p>
                            <p>At so momentous a period in international relationships, Liberia’s
                                strategic geographical position on the West Coast of Africa invests
                                it with added importance politically and economically. The
                                contributory factors to this metamorphosis have been: (1) A
                                narrowing world due, in the main, to the remarkable development of
                                aerial transportation and aerial communication; (2) revolutionary
                                social changes in Europe and Asia; (3) the aggressive challenging of
                                the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in the Mediterranean; (4) the
                                promotion of more mutual inter-American relations; (5) envisagement
                                of Liberia as a fertile field for the exploitation in the areas of
                                trade, agriculture and mineralogy.</p>
                            <p>In regard to its geography Liberia is the halfway point on the west
                                African Coast. Liberia is situated midway between Europe and South
                                America. Liberia is situated approximately midway between Europe and
                                South Africa.</p>
                            <p>Taking into account the Machiavellian international policy so
                                vigorously pursued nowadays by autocratic powers, it is obvious that
                                distance, even when measured in terms of thousands of miles, does
                                not preclude the United States from finding it imperative to give
                                immediate attention to political and economic considerations which
                                may inevitably have a direct bearing on its future welfare.</p>
                            <p>It is no cry of the alarmist to assert that for any totalitarian
                                state to gain a strong foothold on the West Coast of Africa would
                                undoubtedly menace the good neighbor policy of the United States in
                                South America; and that the establishment of an airplane base, a
                                naval base, a radio or a cable station by either Germany or Italy,
                                particularly Germany, would prove detrimental to Pan-America and its
                                ideologies.</p>
                            <pb facs="0563" n="557" xml:id="pg_557"/>
                            <p>The esteem in which Germany holds Liberia as a strategic point of
                                communication between Europe and South America was clearly indicated
                                shortly before the World War. In 1911, toward the close of President
                                Arthur Barclay’s administration, the Liberian Government granted a
                                Dutch company a cable concession which was subsequently sold to a
                                German concern, commonly known as the German-South American Cable
                                Company. In 1912, at the beginning of President Howard’s
                                administration, the company opened a cable station at Monrovia. As
                                many as forty German employees were quartered in the company’s local
                                community house. Liberians were regularly employed. Seven men worked
                                on each shift. The station was operated throughout the day and
                                night.</p>
                            <p>Monrovia was in constant touch with Pernambuco, the South American
                                station; also Emden, Germany, Teneriffe, Canary Islands; Lome,
                                Togoland, and Duala, Cameroons. During the World War when Liberia
                                joined the Allies, the German cable station was forced to close. In
                                retaliation, a German submarine bombarded the French cable station
                                at the Liberian capital.</p>
                            <p>Italy’s rise to a dominant and aggressively articulate role in the
                                Mediterranean has evoked misgivings as to the future availability of
                                the Suez Canal at all times for shipping. The United States enjoys a
                                large, profitable export trade with South Africa. If the Suez Canal
                                were blockaded there would remain the sea route to South Africa via
                                the West African Coast. That is, if the democracies do not permit a
                                    <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> by totalitarian states in
                                the political penetration of the Canary Islands, or some point of
                                vantage on the West Coast of Africa.</p>
                            <p>So interrelated are the economic and political issues involved which
                                have cast Liberia in a principal role in this drama of “Preparedness
                                in Africa,” (which should mean so much to the economic progress and
                                political security of both the United States and the African
                                republic) that one issue cannot be seriously considered without the
                                other.</p>
                            <p>With the development of American overseas trade with Africa, our
                                merchant ships, in the event of war, would need protection. Liberia
                                is the logical port in this region for a naval base to safeguard our
                                sea lanes.</p>
                            <p>Apart from the utilization of Monrovia as a naval base, an airplane
                                base or a base for aerial communication, it should be an ideal
                                location for the storage of cargo consigned for transshipment either
                                northward or southward. To American shipping, Monrovia might
                                gradually assume a maritime status similar to that of Dakar to
                                French shipping, or that of Freetown, Accra and Lagos to British
                                shipping.</p>
                            <p>Because it was founded under the aegis of the American Colonization
                                Society, with the active cooperation of the Federal Government,
                                Liberia has been regarded more or less by Americans as a sentimental
                                    <pb facs="0564" n="558" xml:id="pg_558"/> attachment. In the
                                light of the incredible occurrences transpiring today in the field
                                of internationalism, it would appear that the future political and
                                economic interests of both Liberia and the United States can more
                                effectively be served by Americans combining traditional sentiment
                                with a more realistic appreciation for Liberia’s wealth of
                                    potentialities.<note n="1a" xml:id="d621fn1a"><p>A memorandum
                                        attached to this despatch in the files reads as follows:
                                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                            <p>“Comment made by Division of Near Eastern Affairs on
                                                March 2, 1939, on despatch no. 251, January 3, 1939,
                                                received from the American Legation at Monrovia:</p>
                                            <p>“Your observations have been noted by the Secretary
                                                and the Under Secretary, as well as by other
                                                officers of the Department, and are being brought to
                                                the attention of the Navy, as of possible interest
                                                to it. We assume, of course, that you would not have
                                                offered these suggestions, however tentatively,
                                                without considering Liberia’s sensibilities; and
                                                that the Liberian Government has made its anxiety so
                                                plain in regard to the menace of aggression by
                                                certain European powers that it would be willing to
                                                risk the alternative of virtual American domination
                                                along the lines you mention.”</p>
                                        </quote></p></note></p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lester A.
                                Walton</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>