<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="632" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d632">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">882.20/439</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                    Division of Near Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-18">April 18,
                                    1939</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The French Ambassador came to see me this morning to inquire about
                                recent conversations that had taken place in Monrovia between the
                                Liberian Secretary of State and the French Chargé d’Affaires at that
                                capital. It appears that the French Government has been advised that
                                inquiry has been made of its Chargé d’Affaires in Monrovia with a
                                view to ascertaining to what extent France would be able to assist
                                Liberia in the event of war.</p>
                            <p>I informed the Ambassador of the earlier phases of this matter as
                                they had been brought to the attention of the Department shortly
                                after the Munich Conference. The Liberian Government had at that
                                time instructed its Secretary of the Treasury to proceed to Europe
                                with a view to initiating negotiations for a tripartite agreement
                                designed to give Liberia assurance that in time of war Great Britain
                                    <pb facs="0572" n="566" xml:id="pg_566"/> and France would
                                furnish Liberia aerial, naval and other protection. The Liberian
                                Government had at the time expressed the hope that this Government
                                would look with favor upon the proposed plan.</p>
                            <p>Upon being advised of the above development and in view of the
                                uncertainty of the situation prevailing in Europe at that moment,
                                the Department expressed its doubts that any useful purpose would be
                                served by approaching the British and French Governments in the
                                matter at that time.</p>
                            <p>Subsequently the Department was informed that on February 22, last,
                                the French Chargé d’Affaires called upon the Liberian Secretary of
                                State and, after referring to the alliance between France and Great
                                Britain, stated that in the event either of their possessions in
                                West Africa were attacked they would jointly defend each other. The
                                French Chargé d’Affaires then inquired informally of the Liberian
                                Secretary of State as to what actual military resistance, if any,
                                the Liberian Government would be able to make in the event of war
                                and if Liberia were attacked by Germany.</p>
                            <p>In communicating the above information to our Legation in Monrovia
                                the view was expressed by the Liberian Government that in its own
                                interests as an independent state Liberia should either make
                                adequate arrangement to defend itself against a possible attack or
                                correlate its defenses with those of the two governments whose
                                frontiers join those of Liberia.</p>
                            <p>In view of the Liberian Government’s request for any suggestion which
                                this Government might consider it proper to give in the light of the
                                above developments, the Department had instructed the American
                                Minister in Monrovia to state that it had no objection to any
                                arrangement that might be entered into by the three governments
                                concerned for the defensive assistance of Liberia.</p>
                            <p>I asked the Ambassador whether he had any idea as to what sort of
                                steps his Government might be prepared to take to assist Liberia in
                                case of any serious threat from one of the totalitarian powers. The
                                Ambassador stated that he had no detailed information on the subject
                                and believed, furthermore, that it would be difficult if not
                                impossible for France to detach any portion of its fleet to guard
                                the Liberian coast against invasion. He believed, on the other hand,
                                that in case of war both the British and French Governments would be
                                obliged to take all necessary steps to prevent the establishment of
                                hostile submarine or air bases in Liberia, and in that connection he
                                considered it very important that the Liberians should be on the
                                alert and should keep the British and French Governments promptly
                                advised of any suspicious developments. He added in conclusion that
                                he presumed it would be generally understood that neither France nor
                                Great Britain has any designs whatsoever on Liberian territory.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>