<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-09T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-09T20:00:00-05:00" n="880" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d880">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">890D.927/89: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-09T20:00:00-05:00">January 9, 1939—8
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>22. Committee for the Excavation of Antioch, of which Morey of
                                Princeton is chairman and in which the Musées Nationaux of Paris
                                participates, have a contract for excavation work in the Hatay,
                                signed with the High Commissioner in Beirut in 1937 and valid until
                                1942. The contract is said to provide for a division of
                                archaeological finds. The local authorities in the Hatay are now
                                reported to contemplate abrogation of the contract and enforcement
                                of the Turkish antiquities law, which forbids any exportation of
                                archaeological finds.</p>
                            <p>The Committee’s difficulties have been discussed by our Consul
                                General in Beirut with the Acting High Commissioner, who appears to
                                feel that notwithstanding his responsibility, his intervention with
                                the Hatay authorities is unlikely to be effective at this time. He
                                has agreed to instruct his delegate at Antioch, who will join the
                                French Ambassador at Ankara within the next 10 days to discuss with
                                the Turkish authorities all outstanding Hatay questions, to keep the
                                Princeton expedition in mind during these discussions. He appears to
                                feel, however, that this question may be considered of secondary
                                importance at Ankara.</p>
                            <pb facs="0840" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/>
                            <p>Please discuss the matter with the appropriate French authorities,
                                pointing out that the American Government assumes that the Hatay
                                authorities will scrupulously honor their obligations under the
                                terms of Article 14 of the Mandate and under the contract, and that
                                the American Government of course looks to the French Government for
                                the preservation of American rights and interests in the Hatay.</p>
                            <p>If the French Government is not in a position to give you the
                                assurances desired, please submit your confidential recommendations
                                regarding the advisability of our approaching the Turkish
                                authorities at Ankara.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>