<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> Files</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Central Intelligence Agency</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>–36/1</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-26">November 26,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">National Intelligence Estimate</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Prospects for the Survival of a Non-Communist
                                    Regime in Burma</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>To review the conclusions of <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>–36,
                                “Prospects for Survival of a Non-Communist Regime in Burma,” dated 1
                                August 1951, with reference to the timing of possible control over
                                part or all of Burma by the Burmese Communists.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">estimate</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>In <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>–36 it was estimated
                                    that the Communists “will probably be able within the next year
                                    or two to achieve <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control over a
                                    considerable area of northern Burma” and that if covert Chinese
                                        <pb facs="0331" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/> Communists aid to
                                    the Burmese Communists continues “the Burmese Government is not
                                    likely to survive in the long run unless it greatly increases
                                    its political and military strength.”</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Recent reports indicate that the situation may be
                                    deteriorating more rapidly than had been estimated in <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>–36. As anticipated, the Chinese
                                    Communists have continued their support of the Burmese
                                    Communists. In addition there is evidence that the Burmese
                                    Communists are making progress toward collaboration with the
                                    Karens, thus increasing the over-all capabilities of the
                                    insurgents. The pro-Communist Burma Workers and Peasants Party
                                    has become increasingly effective in unifying overt left-wing
                                    opposition to the Burmese Government and in hampering the
                                    government’s operations against the insurgents. Within the
                                    government itself, friction between certain Army leaders
                                    (particularly Ne Win) and the Socialist leaders has not abated,
                                    and there are indications of rising tension between the moderate
                                    Socialists and leftists led by Ba Swe.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We conclude, therefore, that internal tensions are likely to
                                    weaken the regime more rapidly than anticipated in <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>–36 and that there is a greater
                                    possibility that the present government may be replaced by a
                                    leftist regime or even, though less likely, by a pro-Communist
                                    regime. We conclude also that the Burmese Communists will
                                    probably extend their military control in northern Burma during
                                    the current fair weather season (six to eight months) and that,
                                    even without direct participation by Chinese Communist Forces,
                                    they will be able to achieve effective control over considerable
                                    areas of northern Burma in a year to eighteen months.</item>
                            </list>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>