<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-07-18T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-07-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-18T10:00:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.551/7–1851: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister at Saigon</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d242fn1">This telegram was transmitted in two parts.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-18T23:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 18, 1951—11 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>157. De Lattre asked see me yesterday evening. I found him incensed by certain
                    passages in <hi rend="italic">Time–Life</hi> correspondent Dowling’s story of
                    celebration July 14 particularly assertion that “truth of matter was that never
                    in Indochina were below the surf ace Franco-Amer relations at lower ebb”. (For
                    other statements in Dowling’s despatch objected to by De Lattre see <gloss
                        target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 160 rptd Paris 57, July 18).<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d242fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. De Lattre launched into long complaint against type of Amer correspondent’s
                    writing, he asserted, tendentious and sensational stories seeking to “envenom”
                    Franco-Amer and Franco-Viets relations here without appreciation Fr sacrifices
                    and contribution towards holding pass against Communism; difficulties which wld
                    be perilously increased here as result of cease-fire in Korea. I agreed that
                    there had been several incidents of sensational and incorrect reporting, but
                    reminded De Lattre he had generally had magnificent press in US. I cld not, as
                    he suggested, exert any authority over free Amer press beyond giving facts when
                    correspondents consulted me. Postponement signature <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss> agreement unfortunately provided material for press despatch of
                    type he disliked. Agreement shld, I felt, be signed earliest possible moment. De
                    Lattre replied he agreed emphatically and for that reason had sent his financial
                    counselor to Paris to speed up final approval. He referred to my ltr (<gloss
                        target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 3, rptd Paris 1, July 1)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d242fn3">Not printed.</note> in which I took exception to statement
                    in his press release that Amer negotiators “must have known” that agreement cld
                    not have been signed on June 30. I repeated my objection to the statement saying
                    that we had no reason to doubt the assurance of Viet Govt that they were
                    authorized sign agreement on that date. De Lattre argued our negotiators must
                    have known that consultative procedure <pb facs="0473" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                    between Vietnam and Fr made that date impossible and that in any case “courtesy
                    shld have suggested” that we consult High Commissariat to assure ourselves
                    everything was in order. I replied that we had no reasons go behind Viet Govt
                    assurance and since it was a bilateral agreement with Viets there was no reason
                    again consult Fr, particularly in view fact we had formal assurances in writing
                    from the Fr negotiator that Fr approval draft had been obtained. Further
                    argument was terminated by De Lattre saying, “you can not convince me and I can
                    not convince you. Let’s drop the discussion.”</p>
                <p>2. Returning to the question Amer press reports on Indochina, De Lattre again
                    expressed his concern over their effect on Franco-Amer relations and asserted
                    that reporters must have gotten some of their incorrect material from members
                        <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> mission and possibly also from junior
                    members Leg and Amer consulate in Hanoi.</p>
                <p>I said I welcomed chance discuss state our relations here and our policy and that
                    I was in some position to speak with authority. Dept had confirmed that Amer
                    cooperation and actions here were to supplement and not to supplant or undermine
                    position of Fr in Indochina. As regards <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                    operations, they wld be carried on with proper consultation and due regard and
                    sympathetic understanding of Fr position. (Note: I did not go beyond this gen
                    assurance in this conversation at this time in view objections raised by Blum
                        <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> chief (see <gloss target="#t_Toeca1"
                        >Toeca</gloss> 841, July 12<note n="3" xml:id="d242fn4">For extracts, see
                            <ref target="#pg_450">p. 450</ref>.</note>)) to the specific assurances
                    proposed in para numbered 2 my 2355, June 29, rptd Paris 944. I am firmly
                    convinced however, for reasons advanced in my 2355 that these precise assurances
                    must be given, preferably before De Lattre departs for Fr next week.</p>
                <p>As regards assertions members <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission and
                    Legation were taking line at variance with our policy in <gloss target="#t_IC1"
                        >IC</gloss>, I intended shortly brief all members Legation and US missions
                    here to the end that they fully understood value to cause of freedom French
                    efforts <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> and validity French aims that the
                    Associated States of <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> remain in French Union. I
                    wld warn them that they must not give encouragement by listening without comment
                    to improper—I repeated improper—criticisms of French sacrifices and intentions
                    and that I wld consider any violation of this rule as insubordination.</p>
                <p>On other hand, I had two things to request of him of which the first was very
                    important and was that he take steps to stop false and anti-American reports of
                    his entourage and secret police regarding American aims and operations in <gloss
                        target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss>. I remarked that I knew that every intelligence
                    service and secret police which relied in part on paid informers recd false and
                    tendentious reports and I was certain that was case here. De Lattre demurred
                    saying he did not think he <pb facs="0474" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> had recd
                    any anti-American reports. I replied I felt certain he had. One such report he
                    had given much credence to was that American Consulate Hanoi was subsidizing Dai
                    Viet paper <hi rend="italic">Thoi Bao</hi> now closed. As another example I felt
                    fairly sure Chinese language specialist my Legation, who of excellent character
                    and standing, had been represented to High Commissariat as being a secret
                    service agent. De Lattre wld not agree that he was recipient false stories about
                    American activities but took note my statement. I continued that minor request
                    of mine was that there be fuller exchange info. We were receiving good
                    cooperation as regards economic and military intelligence but French studies and
                    info on <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss> and Commie activities <gloss
                        target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> were only partly made available to us. I asked
                    that officials be instructed give us full info on such points and he agreed that
                    he wld do so but without much enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>3. De Lattre then took up question of newspaper stories that France was
                    considering some sort truce with Ho Chi Minh and <gloss target="#t_VM1"
                        >VM</gloss>. Without definitely asserting that French Govt wld never
                    undertake such action, he said he wld not and cld not make such a compromise. It
                    wld mean rapid loss <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss>’s independence to Chinese
                    and Commie imperialism. With loss his only son in battle he had, he said, a
                    greater moral authority and duty fight on here until Associated States were
                    fully secured. He was confident victory although danger of greater Chinese aid
                    and even participation in <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss> military operations
                    had greatly increased with prospect of Korean truce. De Lattre said he was going
                    see job through here. Stories that he wld accept governorship French Morocco
                    were completely without foundation; he had no ambition accept any other position
                    France cld offer him. His trip France wld be very brief (see <gloss
                        target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 158, rptd Paris 55, July 18).<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d242fn5">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>4. De Lattre informed me that he wld be glad attend opening of American library
                    either July 23 or 24 and wld make few remarks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Dept will notice that in my conversation with De
                    Lattre I said most of things which I advocated in mytel 2355, June 29. It will
                    be necessary, I feel, however, have another frank talk with De Lattre and in
                    that case I hope be authorized make without change all statements advocated
                    mytel 2355.</p>
                <p>The resentment caused by the postponements signature <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss> agreement and <hi rend="italic">Time–Life</hi> correspondent’s
                    despatch referred to in this telegram have given De Lattre, I believe, some
                    salutary worry with regard Franco-American relations <gloss target="#t_IC1"
                        >IC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Sent Dept 157, rptd info Paris 54.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
