<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="340" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d340">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AA/3–1251</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director, Office of Philippine
                                    and Southeast Asian Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lacy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-12">March 12,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Dissolution of <gloss target="#t_UNCI1">UNCI</gloss>
                            </p>
                            <p>The dissolution of <gloss target="#t_UNCI1">UNCI</gloss> has been
                                discussed by United States representatives with other members of the
                                Commission, and with the Netherlands. To date, the Belgians and the
                                Australians have indicated they will not agree to the early
                                dissolution of the Commission unless the Dutch concur.</p>
                            <p>The Netherlands approached us on November 20 in regard to the
                                dissolution of the Commission. They opposed its liquidation or
                                curtailment of its activity at that time because the demobilization
                                of the ex-<gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss> had not been
                                completed; there was no agreement on New Guinea; and because of the
                                possibility that dissolution might be interpreted as acquiescence in
                                the negation by Indonesia of the right of self determination.<note n="1" xml:id="d340fn1">For documentation, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_964">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 964</ref> ff.</note>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0628" n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/>
                            <p>Our present information from Djakarta indicates that the <gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss> problem will probably be cleared
                                up sometime in May. In regard to New Guinea, in view of the attitude
                                expressed by Australia we do not believe that the Commission is
                                competent to decide the substance of this issue. The Indonesians for
                                their part have indicated that because of Australia’s participation
                                they would not accept a solution by the Commission. The Commission
                                could possibly be called upon, however, for procedural suggestions
                                to solve the problem.</p>
                            <p>The question of the right of self determination has not been raised
                                for sometime and the unitary state was established last August. We
                                do not see how dissolution of the Commission could at this time be
                                interpreted as acquiescence in the negation by the Government of
                                Indonesia of the right of self determination.</p>
                            <p>At the beginning of February we requested our Embassies in Canberra,
                                Brussels and The Hague to attempt to secure agreement on a target
                                date of March 31 for the dissolution of the Commission. The
                                Netherlands informed us that they believed a target date of March 31
                                was premature but that they could see no objection to the
                                dissolution of the Commission following the solution of the <gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss> problem. At this time we
                                attempted to secure agreement with the Netherlands in Djakarta that
                                barring any new developments and immediately following the solution
                                of the <gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss> problem that the
                                Commission (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) report to the Security Council
                                the conclusion of its work and recommend its dissolution and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) disband leaving caretaker functions to
                                members of the respective Embassies in Djakarta until such time as
                                the Council notes and approves its report.</p>
                            <p>On February 27 the Dutch informed us that they will agree to the
                                withdrawal of the Commission’s Secretariat and Military Observers
                                following the solution of the ex-<gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss> problem but that they do not want to see the
                                Commission formally dissolved for the following reasons: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>They consider the Commission should remain in being so
                                        long as the Indonesian question is on the agenda of the
                                        Security Council.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Other similar United Nations Commissions have not
                                        heretofore been formally dissolved.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Domestic political considerations in the Netherlands
                                        render agreement on the complete dissolution of the
                                        Commission at this time impossible.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Should the need for United Nations machinery in Indonesia
                                        again arise, they believe it would be impossible to
                                        establish another commission in the Security Council whose
                                        composition would be as acceptable as the present
                                        one.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0629" n="611" xml:id="pg_611"/>
                            <p>These reasons are not compelling from our point of view. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>There is no necessary connection between the Indonesian
                                        case’s being on the agenda of the Security Council and the
                                        dissolution of the Commission. As the Netherlands must be
                                        aware there are a number of cases on the Council’s agenda in
                                        which there are no commissions in the field. We would
                                        consider, and believe other Council members would concur, in
                                        the propriety of the case’s remaining on the agenda of the
                                        Council after the Commission is formally dissolved.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Although it is true that other similar commissions have
                                        not been dissolved it is also true that the successful
                                        settlement of the Netherlands-Indonesian dispute was hailed
                                        by an overwhelming majority of the Members of the United
                                        Nations in December 1949. Presumably, therefore, there will
                                        be no reason for the Commission’s continued existence after
                                        its one remaining job is completed. From the standpoint of
                                        good United Nations practice it appears to us that a
                                        commission which is not in fact active is detrimental to the
                                        United Nations and detracts from dignity of its members. We
                                        do not believe that United Nations field commissions should
                                        be maintained indefinitely on the chance that there may
                                        possibly be a need for them at an unforeseen later
                                        time.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>We are sympathetic, of course, to Netherlands domestic
                                        political considerations vis-à-vis the dissolution of the
                                        Commission. The question of the dissolution of the
                                        Commission, however, has been under discussion between our
                                        two Governments since November of last year and we hope that
                                        Dutch domestic problems in this regard will be resolved in
                                        the near future.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Although it is perhaps true that it would be impossible to
                                        establish another commission of the Security Council with a
                                        similar composition, it should be pointed out that other
                                        machinery of pacific settlement exists, such as the the
                                        Conciliation Panel and the Peace Observation Commission and
                                        would be available if a legitimate need arose for its use.
                                        Furthermore, we believe that the present composition of the
                                        Commission would militate against its participation in the
                                        substance of the only problem with which we can foresee at
                                        this time that it might have to deal, i.e., the New Guinea
                                        problem.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Although it has no objection to another approach to the Dutch on this
                                issue, <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss> does not believe the Dutch
                                are likely to alter their present position substantially, at least
                                until a new government is formed in the Hague. <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss> favors dissolution of the
                                Commission but feels that representations to this end should be
                                subject to political considerations of our relations with the Dutch,
                                the Indonesians and the Australians. Nevertheless, in view of the
                                other considerations outlined above, I suggest that you call in
                                Ambassador van Roijen<note n="2" xml:id="d340fn2">J. Herman van
                                    Roijen, Netherlands Ambassador to the United States.</note> and
                                    <pb facs="0630" n="612" xml:id="pg_612"/> express to him our
                                considered view that the Commission should be dissolved following
                                the liquidation of the ex-<gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss>
                                issue.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>