<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-31T03:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-31T03:30:00-05:00" n="386" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d386">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.00/5–3151: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cochran</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-31T16:00:00+07:30">May
                                        31, 1951—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1681. Amb Ali visited with me 2 hours my home forenoon thirtieth his
                                request. He gratified statement Masjumi party will support Sukiman
                                Govt; believes this is strongest <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt to date; thinks it has good chance success,
                                if principal parties continue cooperate. He has observed
                                shortcomings of govt ministries and floundering that has resulted
                                from too many parties, too much polit maneuvering and too few
                                capable leaders occupying positions sufficiently long to exercise
                                auth efficiently.</p>
                            <pb facs="0686" n="668" xml:id="pg_668"/>
                            <p>Amb Ali bad only kindest things to say about US Govt and was
                                particularly appreciative of farewell talks had with Sec State and
                                Asst Secy Rusk. Was glad to bring their messages to his govt and
                                hopes take back reciprocal good will greetings when he leaves <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> first week June.</p>
                            <p>We discussed Emb also and mentioned possible repercussions Kem
                                amendment. Amb Ali said <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt
                                thru various ministries particularly that of economics working on
                                list of strategic materials as required by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolution prior June 18. He admitted most guardedly
                                there is strong controversy within <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt as to whether rubber shld be included. I
                                reminded him it was Brit shipments rubber to Commies that perhaps
                                contributed more than any other cause to congressional unhappiness
                                and trend in direction Kem legislation. I said <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> wld certainly get bad reaction in
                                US if rubber not included. He made point other countries now also
                                deciding what materials they should consider strategic, and implied
                                    <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> might not be alone in
                                classifying rubber as non-strategic. He said <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> had been quite stirred up over
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolution. He understood Amer
                                viewpoint but saw difficulty reconciling this with <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>. He was under impression US Govt
                                wld be satisfied, however, if <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                                simply adhered to “historic pattern” in fon trade. (Care must be
                                taken to see that <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s do not
                                interpret this expression to permit them export directly or through
                                new intermediaries goods to ultimate destinations) such as Chi or
                                Russia (that heretofore reached such destinations thru Malaya).</p>
                            <p>Recd Amb Ali and dictated foregoing parts in present form before
                                arrival <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>s 1310 and
                                    1311.<note n="1" xml:id="d386fn1">Neither printed; for a summary
                                    of telegram 1311 to Djakarta, May 29, see footnote 3, <ref target="#pg_667">p. 667</ref>. Telegram 1310 to Djakarta,
                                    May 29, which is not here printed, dealt with the British
                                    interpretation of the United Nations embargo resolution.
                                    Documentation on the British position is scheduled for
                                    publication in volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>.</note> My
                                conversation with Amb Ali adds evidence that as revealed in my talk
                                with Brit Amb (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1657)<note n="2" xml:id="d386fn2">Not here printed.</note> and Djuanda
                                    (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1671) that Brit have
                                been in touch with <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s in effort
                                have strategic character rubber exports analyzed and determined
                                quantitatively. Telegraphic press reports from Colombo indicate
                                Ceylon intends boldly flaunt <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                recommendation insofar as rubber concerned.</p>
                            <p>I will continue keep <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt
                                informed at every opportunity as to US expectation <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> embargo rubber as duty <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> member. <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> not likely however, to make public statement
                                committing <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> to full embargo on
                                rubber so long as reason to doubt Brit will go that far.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cochran</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>