<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="4" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> Files: Lot 53D255</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Report by the <gloss type="from">Defense
                                        Department Representative</gloss> to the Southeast Asia Aid
                                    Policy Committee</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Malony</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> D–41</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-22">January 22,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Report of General Malony on Far Eastern
                                    Trip</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d4fn1">Major General Malony visited
                                    the Philippines, Malaya, Viet-Nam, Thailand, and Burma in
                                    December 1950 to familiarize himself with conditions affecting
                                    policy in Southeast Asia. He discussed the existing situation
                                    arid the effectiveness of U.S. programs, particularly military
                                    assistance programs, with ranking U.S. officials and indigenous
                                    leaders in each country. General Malony’s final written report
                                    on his trip was circulated as document <gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> D–38, January 10, not printed. The above
                                    report (<gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> D–41) represented
                                    a supplement to <gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> D–38,
                                    based on statements made at an interdepartmental meeting held
                                    under the auspices of the Bureau of Far Eastern Affairs,
                                    Department of State, on January 4. (<gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> Files: Lot 53D255)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">philippines</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Since his visit, General Malony had found that the adverse opinion
                                concerning possible dispatch of U.S. personnel to the combat-team
                                level, as in Greece, had been undergoing a change. The experience in
                                Greece had shown how useful this effort could be; and the important
                                thing was to revive quickly a feeling of strength in the
                                military.</p>
                            <p>The problem of intelligence remained acute, and it was probably true
                                that (again, as had been the case in Greece) the guerrilla
                                intelligence was quicker than the Government’s.</p>
                            <p>The Erskine–Melby report on the <gloss target="#t_Huk1">Huk</gloss>
                                situation had been excellent.<note n="2" xml:id="d4fn2">A joint
                                    Mutual Defense Assistance Program survey mission headed by John
                                    F. Melby, Special Assistant to Dean Busk, Assistant Secretary of
                                    State for Far Eastern Affairs, and Maj. Gen. Graves B. Erskine,
                                    Commanding General of the First Marine Division, visited
                                    Southeast Asia in July and August 1950. For documentation on the
                                    mission, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_1">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff. For
                                    information on the mission’s stop in the Philippines, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_1493">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 1493</ref> ff.</note>
                                Unfortunately, there had been little or no improvement since that
                                report was made. Experienced U.S. soldiers for Philippines service
                                were almost entirely limited to over-age ex-scouts or former troops.
                                The demands for experienced personnel and materials for suppression
                                simply could not be met immediately.</p>
                            <p>Responsible U.S. officials in Manila received the Bell Report<note n="3" xml:id="d4fn3">For extracts from the Bell report October
                                    9, 1950, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_1497">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 1497</ref>.</note> with the
                                feeling that it was a “last hope operation” and had to be
                                followed-up on successfully.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">malaya</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It was his opinion that the operation for suppressing dissidents in
                                Malaya was 90% political rather than military. This situation was
                                quiet when he was there, although the incident over the Dutch-Malay
                                child took place shortly after he left. Mr. MacDonald,<note n="4" xml:id="d4fn4">British Commissioner General for Southeast
                                    Asia.</note> for whom he <pb facs="0029" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/>
                                had the greatest respect, had outlined for him the long-term job
                                which the British saw in cutting down the inter-racial barriers and
                                in creating a Malayan nationality. It was probable that the British
                                authorities would ask the U.S. for limited help, as for example
                                Chinese-speaking teachers.</p>
                            <p>He had formed the opinion that the British, in view of the strategic
                                location and highly important dollar-earning raw materials of
                                Malaya, would make great efforts to hold onto the Peninsula.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">indo-china</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>He had asked General De LaTour<note n="5" xml:id="d4fn5">Gen. Boyer
                                    de Latour, Commander of French Union forces in northern
                                    Indochina in December 1950.</note> why the northeastern strip on
                                the coast on <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-China was being
                                held, despite its military vulnerability. He had been advised that
                                French mining installations, and the possible necessity for use as
                                an embarkation point for a possible amphibious operation were the
                                reasons.</p>
                            <p>His limited observations of the National Armies had led him to
                                believe that they were physically fit, and if given adequate
                                training and equipment might well make a good show.</p>
                            <p>While the U.S. Government talked of 12 battalions of Vietnamese, Bao
                                Dai had spoken of 4 divisions. Bao Dai also inferred that since no
                                French money would probably be forthcoming for the increase of his
                                forces to that size, the U.S. would probably be asked to provide the
                                money for equipping them. The lists prepared by Bao Dai and General
                                    Carpentier<note n="6" xml:id="d4fn6">Gen. Marcel Carpentier,
                                    Commander of French Union forces in Indochina, 1949–1950.</note>
                                of military needs for Vietnam had not differed greatly and have been
                                reconciled by Brink.<note n="7" xml:id="d4fn7">Brig. Gen. Francis G.
                                    Brink, Chief of the Military Assistance Advisory Group at
                                    Saigon.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">thailand</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Thai economic situation was relatively good and likely to
                                continue so if <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-China did not
                                fall.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Questions and Answers</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">philippines</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. Was there any evidence that trouble was
                                expected from the Moros?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. He had attempted several times to get an
                                answer to this question, but it had been avoided by the officials
                                approached.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. How did he evaluate, in general, the
                                    anti-<gloss target="#t_Huk1">Huk</gloss> program?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. Much, of course, remained to be done. But
                                he had been particularly impressed with Defense Minister Magsaysay’s
                                determination and pro-American attitude. If able to act without
                                interference, <pb facs="0030" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> he might make
                                a very good effort. It went without saying that the Defense Minister
                                was a prime target for assassination by the <gloss target="#t_Huk1">Huk</gloss>s.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">malaya</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. What was his impression of the recent
                                riots in Malaya?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. They did not appear to be manifestations
                                of a general anti-British feeling, but rather an instigated
                                flare-up, which had not seemed to bear any considerable effect on
                                the general situation.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. If <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-China and Thailand fell, would it, in his opinion, be
                                wise to attempt to hold Malaya, whatever the determination of the
                                British to hold on?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. In his opinion, it would be wise to
                                attempt to hold Malaya; and he felt it could be done, since the
                                peninsula provided a site for favorable air and sea activities.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. Had anything been said during his stay in
                                Malaya concerning additional <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss>
                                supplies?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. Nothing had been said concerning this
                                matter. In his opinion, the needs of Malaya lay in other fields; but
                                because of their will to fight he had recommended that such military
                                assistance as they required be provided to Malaya.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. Had he observed any significant
                                independence movement in Malaya?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. His opportunity of obtaining an answer to
                                this question had been limited. But his feeling was that any
                                “nationalist” sentiment was oriented toward greater national unity
                                within the Commonwealth, rather than complete independence.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">indo-china</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. In his opinion, was a further subsidy from
                                the U.S. for France necessary for the continuation of the National
                                Armies. More specifically, what was his opinion on the ability and
                                willingness of the Associated States to raise the money necessary
                                for their contribution to the Armies?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. The question applied to more than the
                                National Armies plans, and a real problem existed with regard to the
                                ability of the Associated States to raise necessary monies. The tax
                                collection power, had, of course, been turned over to Vietnam, but
                                the French-Vietnamese problems of transition related to this
                                function, as well as to all other functions assumed by the
                                governments of the Associated States, made the situation very
                                nebulous.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">thailand</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. What was the state of the Laotian
                                infiltration into Thailand, which so disturbed the Thai Government
                                and people?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. The recent French announcement that it
                                would send about four thousand men to the border regions to oppose
                                guerrilla activity had <pb facs="0031" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/> cut
                                Thai concern with the problem somewhat, but the problem of
                                infiltration still existed.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. What was his opinion of the <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> program in Burma?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. The existence of an approved program for
                                river craft appeared to have been quite helpful for U.S.
                                interests.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">smuggling</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In answer to questions on smuggling, General Malony reported
                                that:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>There was a feeling in <hi rend="italic">Malaya</hi>,
                                    particularly among the British, that the Indonesian policy of
                                    U.S. had opened a “back door” through Malaya for smuggling,
                                    particularly from, the Philippines. The British were certain
                                    there was relatively little smuggling going on in Malaya since
                                    many Chinese had been resettled from the edges of plantations,
                                    and a constant surveillance barred them from producing support
                                    in food and money to the guerrillas. Pushing the dissident
                                    forces back further into the hills had also cut down smuggling.
                                    Considerable smuggling continued in <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-China;</hi> but the
                                    Thai and British officials were cooperating in making pursuit
                                    across borders possible. Some smuggling continued from Hainan by
                                    air drops, but sending <gloss target="#t_PBY1">PBY</gloss>’s
                                    should cut down this traffic somewhat. If a <hi rend="italic">regional</hi> pact were developed for the area, smuggling
                                    certainly should be one of the questions of common concern to be
                                    dealt with as soon as possible.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">regional problems</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">General:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. Had there been any noticeable feeling of
                                indigenous belief that regional cooperation was necessary?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. The only concrete evidence of such feeling
                                which he had encountered was in Thailand, where the Navy
                                Commander-in-Chief had indicated they would favor a regional
                                grouping if Australia or the U.S. headed it. He considered this as a
                                poor source.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">U.S. Organizational Arrangements in the Area</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In answer to a question as to the wisdom of setting up a U.S.
                                Government regional office to deal with <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> problems, General Malony felt that a more
                                centralized regional organization would be generally useful, but
                                that it should not be limited to <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> matters. Rather, <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> problems were less in need of such a center of
                                decisions short of Washington than were the economic and other
                                programs in the area. But all of the programs could use such a
                                device.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Continuance of Aid in Region</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. Did he feel that the situation warranted
                                continued and increased aid in the region?</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. Yes. U.S. officials were now able to sort
                                out the facts and analyze the regional situation better than ever
                                before. The U.S. should not <pb facs="0032" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/>
                                act on its apprehensions but on what lines of action would profit it
                                most; and continuance of aid was definitely indicated.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>