<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="476" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d476">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">894.00/1–1851</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy to the
                                    Consultant</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Allison</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d476fn1">On January 16 Mr. Allison had been designated
                                    by President Truman as Deputy to Mr. Dulles, with a simultaneous
                                    appointment as Minister in the Office of the U.S. Political
                                    Adviser to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-18">January 18,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Japan</p>
                            <p>
                                <table>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Charles E. Wilson, Office of
                                            Defense Mobilization<note n="2" xml:id="d476fn2">Mr.
                                                Wilson was Director of the <gloss target="#t_ODM1">ODM</gloss>.</note>
                                        </cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell/>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Sidney Weinberg, Office of
                                            Defense Mobilization</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell/>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">General Lucius Clay, Office of
                                            Defense Mobilization<note n="3" xml:id="d476fn3">Mr.
                                                Weinberg and General Clay were both Special
                                                Assistants to Mr. Wilson.</note>
                                        </cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell/>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">John Foster Dulles, Department of
                                            State</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell/>
                                        <cell rendition="#hanging">John M. Allison, Department of
                                            State</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </p>
                            <p>Mr. Dulles called on Mr. Wilson to explain the purpose of his Mission
                                to Japan insofar as it affected the operations of Mr. Wilson’s
                                agency. Mr. Dulles pointed out that, in accordance with the letter
                                to him from the President, his Mission was to discover whether or
                                not it would be possible to get a reliable commitment of the
                                Japanese nation to the cause of the free world. In order to
                                accomplish this, the United States would have to make certain
                                military and economic commitments to the Japanese of a general
                                nature. As far as the military side of the problem is concerned,
                                there was complete agreement between the State and Defense
                                Department over the necessity of contributing substantial forces to
                                the defense of the island chain of which Japan forms a part. In
                                regard to economic problems, if Japan is to be on the side of the
                                free world, it will be necessary to assure that its industry can
                                keep running and that it will receive sufficient quantities of the
                                necessary raw materials, particularly coking coal and iron ore. It
                                was from this point of view that Mr. Dulles wished to talk to Mr.
                                Wilson and his associates, for if the United States were to use all
                                of these materials for its own industry and not be willing to make
                                reasonable quantities available to the Japanese, it would be futile
                                to expect the Japanese to keep away from Communism. Mr. Wilson
                                expressed complete agreement with the objectives outlined by Mr.
                                Dulles, but pointed out that false hopes should not be held out to
                                the Japanese and that they should be induced to be realistic in
                                their expectations of what might become available. As the discussion
                                progressed and it became evident that, insofar as iron ore and
                                coking coal were concerned, Japan’s needs were comparatively
                                modest—5 million tons of the former and 2 million of the latter—both
                                Mr. Wilson <pb facs="0823" n="805" xml:id="pg_805"/> and General
                                Clay expressed the opinion that it would probably be possible to
                                assure a continuance of these quantities if necessary. Mr. Dulles
                                pointed out that Japan formerly had obtained large quantities of
                                iron ore from Malaya and the Philippines and that these sources
                                could possibly be re-activated so that the burden on the United
                                States would be lessened. General Clay expressed considerable
                                concern over any assurances of continuing large exports of cotton to
                                Japan, as this commodity was apparently going to be in short
                                supply.</p>
                            <p>General Clay pointed out further that it was not possible at this
                                time to make any commitments regarding specific quantities or types
                                of material which might be available and that presumably at some
                                time it would be necessary for some agency of the Government,
                                possibly the State Department, to make a decision as to what the
                                priorities would be among all the various applicants for raw
                                materials. Mr. Dulles stated that he understood this thoroughly and
                                is not expecting any such commitments at this time, but merely
                                wanted to apprise Mr. Wilson and his colleagues of the problem and
                                of the necessity of being able to give some general assurance to the
                                Japanese. Mr. Dulles emphasized that, should the Soviets obtain the
                                industrial power of Germany and Japan, it would place them in such a
                                position of strength that it would be necessary for the United
                                States to spend more and produce more to offset this difference, so
                                that it really was to the interest of the United States to make it
                                possible for Japan to stay on our side. The meeting closed with Mr.
                                Wilson’s expressing complete understanding of the situation and
                                agreement that it was important to keep the Japanese on our
                                side.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>