<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="546" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d546">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/4–951: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the United States Political Adviser to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>
                                </hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-09T18:00:00-05:00">April
                                        9, 1951—6 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Topad1">Topad</gloss> 1441. For Sebald from
                                Dulles. As you know, UK is preparing its own Treaty draft<note n="1" xml:id="d546fn1">See footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_979">p.
                                        979</ref>.</note> and arrangements are now under
                                consideration for some UK Foreign Office people to come to
                                Washington with it shortly in hope that divergencies between UK and
                                US positions can be brought to minimum. In this connection we feel
                                it wld be most helpful if there cld be present in Washington some
                                rep of Jap Govt who cld be consulted from time to time and who wld
                                be in position to indicate points on which Jap wld be willing to
                                make concessions in interest of UK participation. It wld be
                                desirable that there be minimum of publicity concerning such person
                                being in Washington and it wld therefore probably be impossible to
                                have someone such as Iguchi, whose departure from Tokyo cld not be
                                kept quiet. On other hand, it is important that whoever comes shld
                                be fully aware of Jap Govt viewpoint and be in a position to express
                                it dependably. It is possible that if it shld be decided to send
                                someone to Washington, he cld be attached to proposed Overseas Trade
                                Office shortly to be set up here.</p>
                            <pb facs="0986" n="968" xml:id="pg_968"/>
                            <p>We think it important that Japs should take some of responsibility of
                                determining to what extent demands of other govts shld be acceded to
                                in an effort to have a Treaty agreed to by as many powers as
                                possible and that whole burden of making these decisions shld not
                                rest solely upon US.</p>
                            <p>Let us have your comments and suggestions soon as possible.
                                [Dulles.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>