<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Robert A. Fearey of the Office of Northeast Asian
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d553</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">553</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec7iuGEudoprgvdN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048668"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fishery</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="553"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Tokyo Post Files: 320.1 Peace Treaty</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Robert A. Fearey of the Office of Northeast
                        Asian Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>—<date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-18"
                        >1951.</date>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Minutes—Dulles Mission Staff Meeting April</hi> 18, 9:30
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">a. m.</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador Dulles’ Speech</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Dulles suggested that Mr. Johnson sound out General Ridgway on whether
                    he would consider it appropriate to be present during his April 23 speech.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d553fn1">For text of Mr. Dulles’ speech, “Peace without Fear,”
                        delivered in Tokyo April 23, see Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bulletin</hi>, May 7, 1951, p. 726.</note> Ambassador Sebald said that
                    he believed <pb facs="1001" n="983" xml:id="pg_983"/> that General Ridgway’s
                    attendance might be undesirable, the General being left to sit on the stage as
                    Exhibit A without any clearly defined function. Ambassador Dulles recalled that
                    General Marshall when Secretary of State had sat on the platform when Mr. Dulles
                    had made an address in Paris some years ago in order to give weight to what Mr.
                    Dulles said, and he did not see why General Ridgway should not be present for
                    the same purpose. Ambassador Dulles further stated that he believed Mr. Yoshida
                    and a number of other distinguished Japanese should also be present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Johnson said that he also was lukewarm on the question of General Ridgway’s
                    attendance, believing it might be preferable for General Hickey<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d553fn2">Maj. Gen. Doyle O. Hickey, Chief of Staff to <gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>.</note> or General Fox to be present.
                    Colonel Babcock said that he believed General Ridgway should be allowed to feel
                    his way in establishing contact with the Japanese, determining how far and how
                    fast he wished to go. Ambassador Dulles said that he agreed but believed that if
                    General Ridgway wished to break with tradition and mix around more this might be
                    a good occasion to begin, and that it therefore seemed appropriate for Mr.
                    Johnson to sound out the General on the question. He said that he probably would
                    not have a draft of his speech before Saturday and that it therefore might not
                    be possible to clear the final draft with Washington.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Addendum to U.S.–Japan Bilateral Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Dulles said that Mr. Yoshida should be informed that we will want to
                    suggest some slight changes in the addendum regarding the Korea operation.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d553fn3">Reference is to draft Addendum to Agreement Between
                        the United States and Japan for Collective Self-Defense. See Annex III to
                        the letter of February 10 from Ambassador Dulles to Mr. Acheson, <ref
                            target="#pg_876">p. 876</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Shipping Conventions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Dulles said that he had had lunch the previous day with Senator
                    Magnuson, who had said that he believed that Japan should undertake in the
                    treaty to sit down after the treaty had come into effect and negotiate regarding
                    its participation in international shipping conventions. Ambassador Dulles said
                    that this seemed a reasonable proposal and that consideration should be given to
                    including such a provision in the treaty draft.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Seals</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Sebald mentioned that the Japanese Government had agreed to consider
                    that the exchange of letters between Ambassador Dulles and Prime Minister
                    Yoshida regarding post-treaty fishery relationships also covered sealing.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Treaty Signing Ceremony</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Dulles raised the question of where the treaty signing ceremony should
                    be held. Ambassador Sebald said that he believed it <pb facs="1002" n="984"
                        xml:id="pg_984"/> should be in Tokyo. Ambassador Dulles said that he
                    understood that Mr. Clutton had advised his Government that if the ceremony were
                    held in Tokyo it would poison relations between the Allies and Japan for the
                    future. Ambassador Sebald said that he had talked the matter over with Mr.
                    Iguchi, who had indicated that the Government had no objection to Tokyo as the
                    site. Ambassador Sebald said that Mr. Clutton had stated that he had learned
                    second or third hand that Mr. Yoshida opposed Tokyo as the site but that he
                    (Ambassador Sebald) had run the matter down and learned that the Japanese
                    Government thought the idea of Tokyo an excellent one. Mr. Clutton had also said
                    he had reason to believe that Yoshida would refuse to sign the treaty, running
                    in a caretaker cabinet at the last minute to do so. Mr. Iguchi, however, had
                    informed him that this was not true. The impression in some quarters to the
                    contrary had arisen from possible difficulties on the question of who should
                    head the delegation, since the Speaker of the Lower House and the President of
                    the Upper House outranked Mr. Yoshida as Foreign Minister. Ambassador Sebald had
                    suggested that Mr. Yoshida head the delegation as Prime Minister. Mr. Iguchi had
                    stated that Mr. Yoshida had vociferously denied ever stating that he would
                    refuse to sign the treaty, pointing out that he had negotiated the treaty and it
                    would be absurd for him later to refuse to sign it.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">British Delaying Tactics</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Dulles cited several examples of what appeared to be deliberate
                    delaying tactics by the British on the Japanese treaty and related issues.
                    Representatives of the Foreign Office and Board of Trade and a British legal
                    expert would be in Washington to go over the U.S. and British drafts next week,
                    following which Ambassador Dulles might go to London. It would be necessary
                    before his departure to find out from the President whether he should inform the
                    British that we intend to proceed without them if necessary.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conversation with General Ridgway and Mr. Yoshida</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In response to Mr. Johnson’s question as to what Ambassador Dulles planned to say
                    at his meeting at 11:00 o’clock with General Ridgway and Mr. Yoshida,<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d553fn4">No memorandum of this conversation has been found in
                        Department of State files.</note> Ambassador Dulles said that he planned to
                    emphasize that there had been no change in fundamental U.S. policy and that that
                    policy, like the house which had withstood the earthquake, could now be
                    considered firmer than ever. The only question was whether the Japanese remain
                    equally firm following the dramatic events of the past week. The fact that the
                    Mission is here and that the U.S. is pushing firmly ahead is convincing proof
                    that the U.S. <pb facs="1003" n="985" xml:id="pg_985"/> has not altered its
                    views. It is up to the Japanese to show that they are as solid as we. Ambassador
                    Dulles said that he hoped to find out from Mr. Yoshida what the Japanese fears
                    were and to get Mr. Yoshida’s suggestions on the points he should hammer in his
                    speech. Ambassador Dulles said he further expected to emphasize the esteem in
                    which General Ridgway is held in the U.S. and the great confidence which the
                    American people have developed in him as a result of his work in Korea. He also
                    planned to inform Mr. Yoshida of the details of the bi-partisan backing of his
                    Mission.</p>
                <p>Finally, Ambassador Dulles said, he intended to point out the absurdity of an
                    overall peace in the light of Mr. Malik’s termination of the treaty discussions
                    and other Russian actions. Talk of an overall peace is really a smoke screen
                    sent up by Japanese who wish to attack the Government or who do not wish peace
                    at all. Mr. Johnson suggested that it might not be advisable completely to burn
                    our bridges behind us on the question of an overall peace. Although it appeared
                    at present an unlikely possibility, it was conceivable that we might change our
                    views on the desirability of an immediate peace settlement. In such
                    circumstances it would be better if we had left ourselves in a position to blame
                    Soviet recalcitrance for the further delay rather than British objections or
                    other difficulties with our Allies. In other words, it might be advisable for us
                    to leave ourselves at least a little room in which to turn around.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
