<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Political Adviser to SCAP ( (Sebald) ) to the Director of
                    the office of Northeast Asian Affairs ( (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="568"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d568">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">794.00/4–3051</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser to <gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>
                    </hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the office of Northeast Asian
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">personal</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-30">April 30,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Alex</hi>: We hope through the course of today to be
                    able to telegraph the verbatim text of General Ridgway’s Constitution Day
                    statement to the Japanese people,<note n="1" xml:id="d568fn1">Not printed
                        here.</note> which, I understand, is being given to the press shortly for
                    release on May 3.</p>
                <pb facs="1041" n="1023" xml:id="pg_1023"/>
                <p>The key paragraph in the statement is the one which states in effect that the
                    Japanese Government has been authorized to re-examine all ordinances based upon
                        <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> directives, with a view to making
                    necessary changes in accordance with experience to date.</p>
                <p>I attended a staff conference yesterday over which General Ridgway presided, and
                    at which the proposed statement was discussed. The purpose of the paragraph
                    mentioned above is to give the Japanese Government authority to re-examine the
                    entire purge question, with a view to ameliorating the purge to the point where
                    it will not be more severe than provided for by <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                        >FEC</gloss> Policy Decisions. This is in accordance with the Department’s
                    policy, I believe, as exemplified in Article 13 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 13/2.<note n="2" xml:id="d568fn2">For <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> 13/2, see <ref target="frus1948v06#pg_858">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 858</ref>.</note> Government Section is
                    being charged with inviting the Japanese Government’s attention to the purpose
                    of the paragraph in question, which has purposely been broadly phrased in order
                    not to focus attention specifically upon the purge. It is my understanding that
                    all army and navy officers who became commissioned subsequent to the outbreak of
                    the China Incident in 1937—with perhaps a few minor exceptions—will be included
                    in the depurge. Additionally, large numbers of local officials, teachers,
                    industrialists, government officials, publicists, etc., will probably also
                    eventually be depurged.</p>
                <p>When asked for my opinion at the staff conference, I said that this action is
                    long overdue, it is in conformity with U.S. policy, as I understand it, and that
                    the depurge of the many people who would be included in this action will do much
                    to lessen an irritant which has been growing year after year. I said also that
                    this action would go far in cementing future good relations with a select and
                    influential class of Japanese.</p>
                <p>It will, of course, take some time before the Japanese Government will be in a
                    position to implement the authority granted in the Constitution Day statement,
                    but I will do everything possible to expedite action, as I believe this is what
                    the Department wants. I might say that the consensus of the conference was that
                    if the cut-off date for military and naval officers should be made early, e.g.,
                    as a maximum, 1931, Washington should be queried and support of the United
                    States Government requested. Frank Rizzo, Chief of the Government Section, on
                    the other hand feels that we are on entirely safe ground if 1937 is adopted as
                    the cut-off date.</p>
                <p>As the information contained herein reflects the discussion in a highly
                    classified conference, I would appreciate your limiting the information to those
                    who need to know.<note n="3" xml:id="d568fn3">For further documentation on this
                        topic, see Mr. Johnson’s reply of May 16, <ref target="#pg_1045">p.
                            1045</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sebald</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
