<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-16T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-16T15:00:00-05:00" n="578" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d578">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/5–1651: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the United States Political Adviser to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>
                                </hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-16T16:00:00-04:00">May
                                        16, 1951—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Topad1">Topad</gloss> 1626. For Sebald from
                                Dulles.</p>
                            <p>London discussion with Morrison will involve handling of China in
                                peace settlement. We shld like before then to clarify our own
                                position on basis of merits not of compromise. As you know, we have
                                been exchanging views fully with National Govt and draft treaty
                                seems generally satis to them. However, question of Treaty signature
                                on behalf China raises difficult problems. Theoretically choices
                                are: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Signature by Commie regime.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Signature by Natl Govt, either <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>concurrently and at same ceremony with other
                                                Allied Powers;</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>concurrent signature of counterpart at separate
                                                ceremony not attended by other signers; or</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>subsequent signing or adhesion as arranged between
                                                Jap and Natl Govt.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Deferment of any signing on behalf of China until
                                        governmental situation clarified.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="1063" n="1045" xml:id="pg_1045"/>
                            <p>No. 1 is absolutely out so far as the US is concerned for we do not
                                consider Mao Tse-tung as real voice of China.</p>
                            <p>No. 2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                involve apparent treatment of the Natl Govt as authorized to speak
                                for and bind the hundreds of millions of Chi over which it has lost,
                                at least temporarily, <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> auth. No.
                                    2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) wld be seriously objected to by
                                probably all Commonwealth and Western Eur countries, and India,
                                Burma and Indonesia. Even Canada, Aus, NZ which continue recognize
                                Natl regime consider its present lack of governmental relationship
                                to great bulk of Chi people on mainland renders it unqualified to
                                bind them for all time in matter as important as China-Jap peace
                                treaty. Some of these wld probably absolutely refuse give color of
                                approbation by sharing signing ceremony with Natl China</p>
                            <p>In this connection you will recall that in 1919 while US and other
                                Allies recognized Kerensky Govt and heard its views on the
                                Versailles Treaty, this recognized Govt was not accepted as
                                qualified to sign the Versailles Treaty on behalf of Russia.</p>
                            <p>The question of signing wld not, in our opinion, prejudice in any way
                                the questions of recognition Natl Govt and maintenance of dipl and
                                consular relations.</p>
                            <p>Today opinion in US Congress and public wld probably favor concurrent
                                signing with Natl Govt. However, if there were to be subsequent Natl
                                Govt signing before Treaty came to Senate for ratification the
                                situation might, from polit standpoint, be acceptable.</p>
                            <p>Before fixing our position we consider Jap itself is entitled express
                                views on this matter which is vitally important to it, because in
                                long run Jap’s relations with China are of paramount importance to
                                Jap. If Gen Ridgway agrees, pls confer immed with Yoshida and get
                                prompt expression views Jap Govt as to what their own preference wld
                                be as to handling this matter as between choices 2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), 2(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) and 3, or any other course they may want to suggest.
                                [Dulles.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>