<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="61" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/4–551</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Marshall</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-05">April 5,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I enclose herewith
                                a draft of a suggested memorandum to the President which the
                                Secretaries of State and Defense might sign jointly if it meets with
                                your approval. The Memorandum is, I think, largely self-explanatory
                                and a copy was provided informally to your Department on April 3.
                                Mr. Dulles or I shall be glad to supply supplementary background, if
                                you desire.</p>
                            <p>I hope that this can be considered by the Department of Defense as a
                                matter of urgency. The political situation, particularly in
                                Australia where the Japanese peace settlement has been made an issue
                                in pending general elections (the vote to take place on April 28)
                                makes it important that we should be able promptly to indicate a
                                willingness, at least in principle, to make a security arrangement
                                with Australia and New Zealand along the lines approved by the
                                President’s letter of January 10, 1951.<note n="1" xml:id="d61fn1">For text, see enclosure 2 (as annotated) to Mr. Acheson’s
                                    letter of January 9 to Secretary Marshall, <ref target="#pg_788">p. 788</ref>.</note> Also this willingness has a close
                                bearing on currently active negotiations with the United Kingdom
                                regarding a Japanese Peace Treaty which will not exclude rearmament
                                by Japan.</p>
                            <p>I understand that the documents brought back by Mr. Dulles<note n="2" xml:id="d61fn2">See Mr. Dulles’ letter (with enclosure and
                                    annexes) of February 10 to Secretary Acheson, <ref target="#pg_874">p. 874</ref>.</note> from his Presidential
                                Mission to the Western Pacific and the State Department’s tentative
                                and suggestive draft of a Japanese Peace Treaty<note n="3" xml:id="d61fn3">See the draft of March 23, <ref target="#pg_944">p. 944</ref>.</note> are under consideration by your
                                Department. I hope, however, that it may be practical to get the
                                enclosed memorandum to the President without awaiting the complete
                                views of the Department of Defense with reference to the detailed
                                language of the other documents referred to.<note n="4" xml:id="d61fn4">In a covering memorandum of April 5 to the
                                    Secretary, Mr. Dulles stated in part: “It is my intention, as
                                    soon as the letter is signed, to take it personally to Secretary
                                    Marshall and deliver it to him, together with a general
                                    explanation of its background.” Record of such a conversation
                                    with Secretary Marshall has not been found in Department of
                                    State files.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Draft Memorandum for the President</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                </opener>
                                <p>In your letter of January 10, 1951 designating Mr. John Foster
                                    Dulles as your special representative for the purpose of
                                    conducting <pb facs="0202" n="184" xml:id="pg_184"/>
                                    negotiations incident upon bringing about a Japanese Peace
                                    Treaty you stated <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> that the
                                    United States:</p>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Desires that Japan should increasingly acquire the ability
                                        to defend itself, and that, in order further to implement
                                        this policy, the United States Government is willing to make
                                        a mutual assistance arrangement among the Pacific Island
                                        nations (Australia, New Zealand, the Philippines, Japan, the
                                        United States and perhaps Indonesia) which would have the
                                        dual purpose of assuring combined action as between the
                                        members to resist aggression from without and also to resist
                                        attack by one of the members, e.g. Japan, if Japan should
                                        again become aggressive.”</p>
                                </quote>
                                <p>Consideration of this matter, particularly during the course of
                                    Ambassador Dulles’ visit to Japan, the Philippines, Australia
                                    and New Zealand, made apparent that the desired results can be
                                    better achieved by a <hi rend="italic">series</hi> of
                                    arrangements rather than by a <hi rend="italic">single</hi>
                                    arrangement. <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>Japan is not legally, economically or politically in a
                                            position now to undertake what the Vandenberg Resolution
                                            speaks of as “continuous and effective self-help and
                                            mutual aid”. Therefore, it would not be practical at
                                            this time to make more than a <hi rend="italic">provisional</hi> arrangement with Japan which, as
                                            contemplated by the memorandum which you approved on
                                            September 7, 1950, would give the United States the
                                            right to garrison forces in Japan while avoiding any
                                            prohibition of Japan’s inalienable right to self-defense
                                            and to possess the means to exercise that right.
                                            Accordingly, the Dulles Mission drafted in Japan the
                                            tentative text of a bi-lateral treaty along these lines
                                            which would in essence give the United States the right
                                            to maintain armed forces in and about Japan until the
                                            United States was of the opinion some other arrangement
                                            would satisfactorily provide for security in the Japan
                                            area. In this connection the Japanese Prime Minister
                                            stated in his communiqué issued concurrently with Mr.
                                            Dulles’ final communiqué in Japan that “when we recover
                                            our independence and join the council of free nations as
                                            an equal member, the substance and scope of the Japanese
                                            contribution will be determined according to the extent
                                            of our economic and industrial recovery.”<note n="5" xml:id="d61fn5">Full texts of the two communiqués
                                                issued February 11 are included in telegram 1548
                                                from Tokyo, February 12, not printed.
                                                (694.001/2–1251)</note>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>In the case of the Philippines, Ambassador Dulles
                                            found interest in a mutual assistance arrangement with
                                            the United States which would not, however, put the
                                            Philippines in the position of being in effect an “ally”
                                            of Japan. This latter is a step for which their public
                                            opinion was not yet prepared.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>In the case of Australia and New Zealand it was found
                                            that their public opinion also would not accept an
                                            “alliance” with Japan but that there was much interest
                                            in a mutual assistance arrangement, initially limited to
                                            Australia, New Zealand and the United States. This would
                                            provide for consultation and coordination of planning
                                            with other states in a position to contribute to the
                                            security of the Pacific area. The <pb facs="0203" n="185" xml:id="pg_185"/> tentative text<note n="6" xml:id="d61fn6">Reference is to the draft of
                                                February 17, <ref target="#pg_172">p.
                                                172</ref>.</note> of such an arrangement was
                                            drafted, in Canberra, by Ambassador Dulles and the
                                            Foreign Ministers of Australia and New Zealand.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>The United Kingdom has strongly objected to a single
                                            arrangement between the United States, Japan, the
                                            Philippines, Australia, New Zealand and possibly
                                            Indonesia, on the theory that to identify in this way
                                            the <hi rend="italic">island chain</hi> would increase
                                            the <hi rend="italic">mainland</hi> danger, particularly
                                            to the U.K. positions in Hongkong and Malaya. However,
                                            the United Kingdom does not object to a series of
                                            arrangements between the United States and Japan, the
                                            United States and the Philippines, and the United
                                            States, Australia and New Zealand, which would provide
                                            for consultation and coordinated planning with as common
                                            denominator the influence and participation of the
                                            United States.</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>With respect to Indonesia there is evidence that it
                                            wishes to be invited to participate in some form of
                                            mutual security arrangement, but that it would not
                                            accept such an invitation. Politically it may be
                                            important to have it publicly known that Indonesia would
                                            be welcome in a mutual security arrangement and this
                                            matter is now being given further study.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>With your approval, a tentative and suggestive draft of a
                                    Japanese peace treaty has now been circulated which, in
                                    accordance with the memorandum you approved on September 7,
                                    1950, will not restrict Japan’s right to rearm. It is thus
                                    important that the United States promptly be in a position to
                                    announce publicly its intention to supplement this treaty
                                    proposal by arrangements for “assuring combined action … if
                                    Japan should again become aggressive.” (Your letter of January
                                    10, 1951.)</p>
                                <p>It is accordingly recommended that Mr. Dulles’ terms of reference
                                    as contained in your letter of January 10, 1951, be amended to
                                    authorize “mutual security arrangements” (plural) instead of “a
                                    mutual security arrangement” (singular).</p>
                                <p>It is believed that the three arrangements contemplated, one with
                                    Japan, one with the Philippines, one with Australia and New
                                    Zealand, and possibly one with Indonesia, will in fact achieve
                                    what your letter of January 10, 1951 described as “the dual
                                    purpose of assuring combined action as between the members to
                                    resist aggression from without and also to resist attack by one
                                    of the members, e.g., Japan, if Japan should again become
                                        aggressive.”<note n="7" xml:id="d61fn7">In a memorandum to
                                        Mr. Dulles of April 3, George W. Perkins, Assistant
                                        Secretary of State for European Affairs, had stated: “My
                                        only comment on the draft memorandum to the President on the
                                        Pacific security arrangement is that it is excellent. From
                                        our point of view the proposed change from one pact to three
                                        is an improvement.” (Lot 54D423)</note>
                                </p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>