<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversations, by the Consultant to the Secretary (
                    (Dulles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d760</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">760</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="760"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d760">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Dulles Papers</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversations, by <gloss type="from">the
                            Consultant</gloss> to the Secretary</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-22">October 22,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Ratification of Treaties</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Secretary Acheson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">John Foster Dulles</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>I first saw Secretary Acheson about 12 noon. I told him that since I had seen him
                    last week I had had the opportunity to talk with Senators Milliken, Wiley, H.
                    Alexander Smith, and Hickenlooper, With reference to the ratification of the
                    Japanese Peace Treaty and related Security Treaties. Without in any way asking
                    their consent, and without getting any commitment from them, I had indicated
                    that I was considering, at the request of the President and the Secretary of
                    State, the suggestion that I should assume responsibility for handling the case
                    for ratification before the Senate, and that they had not indicated that they
                    felt there was any objection to my doing so. I accordingly told the Secretary
                    that I was prepared to assume this responsibility if the President and he wished
                    to delegate this task and corresponding authority to me, but only on two
                    conditions; namely, first, that it was the intention of the President to seek
                    prompt action by the Senate immediately upon its reconvening in January, and
                    second, that the President was aware of the fact that any major action in 1952
                    would have political significance and there would be efforts on the part of both
                    parties to gain credit or distribute discredit, and no doubt there would be some
                    people around the President who would try to represent me as lacking in loyalty
                    because of the way I would probably handle the case for ratification on behalf
                    of the Executive. I would want the President to anticipate this and be prepared
                    to assume my loyalty in this matter, despite what might be said to him to the
                    contrary.</p>
                <p>With reference to the first point, I pointed out that it was quite likely that
                    the Department of Defense would want to postpone ratification in order to
                    preserve the command relationship and to bargain for position under the Security
                    Treaty and Administrative Agreement, but that I considered that there was ample
                    time for Defense to make whatever arrangements were necessary between now and
                    the probable date of the Treaty coming into force after the Senate took it up in
                    January. I would not, I said, be responsible for getting ratification of the
                    Treaties if their consideration by the Senate were deferred, as every day of
                    approach to the Presidential campaign would increase the difficulty of getting
                    the requisite Senate vote.</p>
                <pb facs="1397" n="1379" xml:id="pg_1379"/>
                <p>The Secretary said he would at once discuss this matter with the President and
                    would let me know the President’s conclusion. He said he entirely concurred in
                    the position I had expressed.</p>
                <p>I then met with the Secretary at 1:30 p. m., he having had an appointment with
                    the President in the meantime. The Secretary told me that the President was in
                    full agreement with my position and accepted it. He said that he knew quite well
                    that the Pentagon would probably seek delays but that he was determined to push
                    the Treaties through to ratification at the earliest possible moment. He also
                    foresaw the political hazards I had mentioned but was determined not to allow
                    rumors or political representations to dislodge his faith that I would loyally
                    and in a non-partisan spirit seek the ratification of the Treaties.</p>
                <p>I told the Secretary that in view of the President’s and his desire that I should
                    proceed under these conditions, I was prepared to do so.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
