<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Consultant to the Secretary ( (Dulles) ) to the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs ( (Rusk))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d762</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">762</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="762"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d762">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 54D423</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Consultant to the Secretary</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                        Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-22">October 22,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In connection with the Administrative Agreement to be made pursuant to the United
                    States-Japanese Security Treaty, I have the following observations to make:</p>
                <p>(1) The first declaration of the Japanese Peace Treaty reads:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The Allied Powers and Japan are resolved that henceforth their relations
                        shall be those of nations which, as sovereign equals, cooperate in friendly
                        association to promote their common welfare and maintain international peace
                        and security.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>The task is to implement the Security Treaty in a manner consistent with, and not
                    violative of, that solemn resolve. The Administrative Agreement must in all
                    respects treat Japan as a sovereign equal and put our working relations with the
                    Japanese on such a basis that we shall, thereunder, “cooperate in friendly
                    association”.</p>
                <p>(2) To achieve security involves, of necessity, some burdensome and irksome
                    conditions. These necessities must be accepted in good spirit by the Japanese,
                    and I am confident that they will be. But “necessities” must be distinguished
                    from mere convenience or prestige or desire to avoid adjustment to the fact
                    that, when the Treaty comes into force, the Japanese (will properly expect to be
                    treated as sovereign in their own homeland.</p>
                <p>(3) Those who think primarily in legalistic terms, or who feel that their
                    particular duty is to spell out, on paper, United States rights adequate to meet
                    all conceivable contingencies may seek an agreement which will concede us
                    elaborate extraterritorial privileges, command relationships and prestige
                    positions. Such an approach could be self-defeating. As between sovereign
                    nations, legal rights are dependable so long as they are a definition of
                    mutuality of interest and desire. Once they cease to be that, they are
                    undependable. And United States position in Japan becomes, in fact, untenable,
                    and a liability rather than an asset, if the Japanese people preponderantly
                    resent it and want it to end, and if it can only be preserved by a show of force
                        <pb facs="1399" n="1381" xml:id="pg_1381"/> as against the Japanese, The
                    Administrative Agreement should seek to define the rights and obligations of the
                    parties, so as to avoid future misunderstandings and frictions. But it could do
                    more harm than good if it were drawn so as to create a feeling on the part of
                    United States security forces in Japan that they need not feel dependent on
                    constantly cultivating, and always enjoying, Japanese good will.</p>
                <p>(4) It will be peculiarly difficult to carry out our treaty resolve “as sovereign
                    equals, [to]<note n="1" xml:id="d762fn1">Brackets in the source text.</note>
                    cooperate in friendly association to … maintain international peace and
                    security” because that is a new relationship, very different from that of the
                    “Supreme Command” to which Japan was subject under the Surrender Terms. Also,
                    that new relationship has to be achieved primarily by soldiers, many of whom, as
                    an incident to war and victory, have gotten into the habit of treating the
                    Japanese as inferiors. To alter that attitude will be immensely difficult. It
                    will require a constant effort of will on the part of Americans in command in
                    Japan and those in the ranks. It will require the kind of concern which can be
                    expected only if there is ever-present consciousness of the fact that unless the
                    land, air and sea forces which the United States maintains in and about Japan
                    actually adapt themseleves to the new relationship foreseen by the Treaty of
                    Peace, they will have squandered the immensely valuable opportunity which has
                    been gained by victory and peace in the Pacific War.</p>
                <p>(5) The matter involves not merely our position in Japan but has broad
                    implications as regards all of Asia. The Chinese Communists, using the old
                    Japanese war slogan of “Asia for the Asiatics”, are attempting to rally all of
                    Asia to rise up to eject violently all Western influence. India shows a tendency
                    to move in that direction and in substance India’s refusal to sign the Treaty of
                    Peace was based on its Government’s belief that it will prove impracticable for
                    the United States to develop under the Security Treaty, the kind of “friendly
                    association” with a defeated nation of alien race, which is pledged by the Peace
                    Treaty. If this Indian belief is verified, and if it is demonstrated to all
                    Asia, which is intently watching, that Westerners as represented by the United
                    States find it congenially impossible to deal with Orientals on a basis of
                    respect and equality, that will have grave repercussions throughout all of Asia.
                    It will make it likely that all of the Asiatics will unite, under communist
                    leadership, against the West. Then the situation would be more dangerous to us
                    than when Japan attempted this same result under the same slogan.</p>
                <p>(6) I have presented the foregoing views in substance to the President, Secretary
                    of State and the Secretary of Defense.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
