<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Consultant to the Secretary (
                    (Dulles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-07-18T11:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-07-18T11:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-18T11:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-18T11:15:00-05:00" n="86"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 54D423</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Consultant to the
                        Secretary</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-18T12:15:00-04:00"
                            >July 18, 1951—12:15 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">General Omar N. Bradley</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. John Foster Dulles</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>I had told Deputy Secretary Lovett that it might be useful for General Bradley
                    and me to speak together in view of the impression gained by the foreign Affairs
                    Committee that we had give somewhat Pacific security. General Bradley
                    subsequently telephoned me and I met with him at his office at 12:15 p. m., July
                    18.</p>
                <p>General Bradley said he had told the Committee that if there were political
                    reason why the present unilateral arrangement with the <pb facs="0242" n="224"
                        xml:id="pg_224"/> Philippines should be changed by bringing the Philippines
                    into the trilateral arrangement with Australia–New Zealand, the Joint Chiefs
                    would have no serious objection, although they preferred the present
                    arrangement. I recalled to General Bradley the statement contained in paragraph
                        2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of the memorandum from the Joint Chiefs to the
                    Secretary of Defense of April 11, 1951,<note n="1" xml:id="d86fn1">See Secretary
                        Marshall’s letter of April 13 to Secretary Acheson, <ref target="#pg_201">p.
                            201</ref>.</note> that there would be “serious disadvantages” in a new
                    arrangement with the Philippine Republic and any “enlargement” of the
                    arrangements presently in effect “would be contrary to U.S. security interests”.
                    General Bradley said that he perhaps had not had this fully in mind when he
                    testified before the Committee, but that the considerations in the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff statement referred to were not sufficiently strong so that they would
                    object to an alteration of the present arrangements if there were political
                    reasons therefor.</p>
                <p>I stated that at the time in question (April) there had not seemed to be
                    political reasons of sufficient importance to outweigh the military viewpoint
                    expressed. However, I said that situation might be changing as a result of the
                    strong public emotion in the Philippines against the U.S. because of what they
                    considered to be the leniency of the proposed Japanese Peace Treaty. This
                    emotion had led them to look for every pretext for criticizing the U.S. and one
                    point that had recently emerged was the apparent discrimination in treating with
                    Japan’s security and Australia–New Zealand security on a treaty basis of
                    mutuality, whereas the Philippines was dealt with on a unilateral basis. We did
                    not think that either the Philippines or Australia–New Zealand wanted to be
                    linked together by the same security treaty, but it might be desirable to have a
                    bilateral treaty between the Philippines and the U.S. which would contain mutual
                    declarations of the Monroe Doctrine type. I said that it might be unnecessary to
                    have a “council”. However, General Bradley said there would be no military
                    objection to a “council” if it was essentially of a political character and
                    avoided the interchange of military planning information.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohn</hi>] F[<hi rend="smallcaps">oster</hi>]
                            D[<hi rend="smallcaps">ulles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
