<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>110. Telegram From the Embassy in the Soviet Union to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-09-19T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-09-19T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="rec626bb089a1004d2" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Atomic
                        weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-19T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-19T12:00:00-05:00" n="110"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                <head>110. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d110fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 793.00/9–1958. Official Use Only; <gloss target="#t_Niact1"
                            >Niact</gloss>. Transmitted in five sections. Received at 9:29 p.m. Also
                        sent priority to CINCPAC for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss> and
                        repeated priority to USUN, London, Taipei, Warsaw, and Hong Kong.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-09-19T20:00:00+03:00">September 19, 1958, 8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>634. Following is text of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                    reply to President’s letter of September 12, which Kuznetsov handed me this
                        afternoon.<note n="1" xml:id="d110fn1">Reported in telegram 631 from Moscow,
                        September 19. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.) The Embassy commented on the
                        letter in telegram 644, September 20. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                        793.00/9–2058; see Supplement) A translation of the letter differing from
                        this one was published in Soviet News on September 22.</note>
                </p>
                <p>“Mr. President, Having received your letter of September 12 and studied it, I was
                    grieved that you, as it seems to me, did not understand the essence of my
                    message to you. The essence of that message was to show the danger which
                    threatens humanity if the USA does not renounce its aggressive policy, which is
                    constantly creating hotbeds of serious conflicts first in one and then in
                    another region of the world and has led to the creation at the present time of
                    an especially tense situation in the Far East.</p>
                <p>Recognizing in your answer that in the region of the Island of Taiwan a dangerous
                    situation has been created, you at the same time try to remove from the
                    Government of the USA responsibility for the tension in that area threatening
                    the cause of peace. In this connection the justifications for the aggressive
                    activities of the USA in your message completely distort the actual position of
                    things, drawing a picture which has nothing in common with actuality.</p>
                <p>Anyone who soberly evaluates the situation which has arisen, having regard for
                    the real facts, cannot but realize that the single and genuine source of tension
                    in this part of the world is that the USA has seized age-old Chinese
                    territory—Taiwan and a series of other islands, is supporting on it under the
                    protection of its cannon the <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> clique which has been thrown out by the Chinese people,
                    is encouraging its attacks and provocations against peoples China. The recent
                    events are one of the manifestations of this general aggressive course of the
                    USA in relation to China. Your remark evokes surprise that I, addressing a
                    message to you can not send a letter, as you say, to the Communist leaders of
                    China, in relation to whom and to the Chinese Peoples Republic you repeatedly
                    adopt a scornful and hostile tone in your message. First of all, Mr. President I
                    would like to say to you the following in this connection.</p>
                <p>In the whole history of China there has not been a party and its leaders nor a
                    government that has enjoyed such trust and limitless support of <pb facs="0264"
                        n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/> the entire Chinese people as does the great
                    Communist party of China and its leaders, and also the Government of the Chinese
                    People’s Republic. Yes, really, the leaders of the Communist party are the
                    recognized leaders of the Chinese people, and now they lead not only the Chinese
                    Communist party, but the entire Chinese people, a new, peoples-democratic
                    state—the Chinese People’s Republic.</p>
                <p>I sent the message on the subject of the events in the area of Taiwan to the
                    President of the USA and not to the government of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1"
                        >CPR</gloss> for the simple reason that it is not China which is interfering
                    in the internal affairs of the USA, but the USA, defying all the norms of
                    behavior of civilized states, which has grossly interfered in the affairs of
                    China and is trying by force of arms to install in another’s home its order,
                    creating thereby a serious threat to the cause of peace in the Far East. How is
                    it, Mr. President, that you summon us, as you do, to exert some kind of
                    influence on the government of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> in
                    connection with the events in the area of Taiwan—that means to try to push the
                    Soviet Union into interference in the internal affairs of China. The Soviet
                    Union will never be a party to such a shameful affair, for that would
                    fundamentally contradict its peace-loving foreign policy, would be incompatible
                    with the relations of unbreakable friendship and brotherly cooperation which
                    unite the Soviet and Chinese peoples.</p>
                <p>As you found it necessary to note in your letter, I recently was in Peking and
                    had the opportunity to exchange with the leaders of the government of the <gloss
                        target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> opinions about all questions in which the
                    Soviet Union and the People’s Republic of China are interested. I can say
                    straightaway and frankly that during our talks in Peking that complete unanimity
                    of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CPR1"
                        >CPR</gloss> was confirmed again in the most important thing—that it is
                    necessary also henceforth with all resoluteness to carry out the struggle
                    against aggressive forces and to support the forces defending peace in the whole
                    world. The Chinese people are filled with the urge to develop their economy, to
                    raise their living standards, which is possible only in conditions of peace and
                    security. Therefore, it is natural that the people of China manifest serious
                    alarm in connection with the situation which has developed in the area of the
                    island of Taiwan.</p>
                <p>If on the island of Taiwan over a period of years continues to sit a General
                    discarded by the Chinese people, not subordinate to the lawful government of
                    China and holding certain Offshore Islands which are several kilometers from the
                    major centers of the maritime provinces of China, this intolerable position
                    became possible only because the government of the USA, having interfered in the
                    internal affairs of China, took under military protection the corrupt <persName
                        corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> clique.</p>
                <p>Who can deny that without the support from the side of the USA there would long
                    since not have existed either the <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> clique nor the so-called Taiwan problem, that if it were
                    not for the interference <pb facs="0265" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> of the USA,
                    the peoples of this region would long since have lived in peace and quiet. It is
                    clear to anyone that the US has unlawfully seized these islands because the
                    preservation of the <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>
                    clique on Taiwan gives it the possibility of retaining in this area its armed
                    forces and to threaten the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> with war. Only a
                    traitor and a betrayer of his people such as <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> could permit a foreign power—the US—to concentrate armed
                    forces against China, against the Chinese people. You try to prove that which
                    cannot be proved, that the Government of the USA has some sort of moral and
                    legal right to keep its armed forces in the area of Taiwan. Each tries to
                    interpret facts according to the way his own morality allows him, but it is
                    impossible to avoid facts. They speak for themselves. The facts are that the
                    Government of the USA, by force, seized islands belonging to the Chinese people,
                    which are separated from the American continent by 10,000 kilometers, and is
                    trying to hold them. Moreover, you want China to disclaim this territory and to
                    reconcile herself to the fact that it is in foreign hands and serves as a base
                    for the spreading of aggression against the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>
                    and other peace-loving [countries] of Asia.</p>
                <p>But isn’t it evident, and doesn’t the entire experience of the struggle of
                    peoples for national liberation and independence show, that a great world power
                    such as the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>, never will agree to the cutting
                    off of a part of its territory, and moreover, will not reconcile itself to the
                    fact that on this territory foreign armed forces have been accumulated with the
                    aim of aggression against it?</p>
                <p>As is apparent from your letter, it is precisely the preservation of this
                    situation which the Government of the USA is trying to achieve. Otherwise, what
                    sense can there be in your words about the fact that I have not addressed myself
                    to the leaders of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> with a letter
                    appealing to them for moderation. If we agreed with your point of view, then in
                    effect we would begin to cooperate in the preparation of war against China—our
                    great friend and ally. It is sufficient to consider this suggestion only for a
                    minute in order for its absurdity to become evident. How is it possible, Mr.
                    President, to expect that we will lull the vigilance of our Chinese friends and
                    cooperate with aggressive forces in the preparation for an attack on the <gloss
                        target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and thereby in the preparation for an attack on
                    the Soviet Union? It is futile to expect this from us.</p>
                <p>In your letter you announce that the island of Taiwan and the Offshore Islands
                    never were under the control of Communist China. This declaration is made,
                    apparently, in order to justify the attempt to sever these territories from the
                        <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. Incidentally, the USA solemnly
                    recognized that these territories belonged to China in the Cairo Declaration of
                        <pb facs="0266" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/> 1943.<note n="2" xml:id="d110fn2"
                        >For text of the communiqué issued at Cairo on December 1, 1943, by
                        President Franklin D. Roosevelt, President <persName corresp="#p_CKG1"
                            >Chiang Kai-shek</persName>, and Prime Minister Churchill, see <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Cairo and
                        Tehran, 1943, p. 448.</note> This was also confirmed in the Potsdam
                    Declaration of 1945,<note n="3" xml:id="d110fn3">For text of the proclamation by
                        President Harry S. Truman, President <persName>Chiang</persName>, and Prime
                        Minister Churchill issued at Potsdam on July 26, 1945, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid.,</hi> The Conference of Berlin (The Potsdam Conference), 1945,
                        vol. II, p. 1474.</note> which the USA and certain other great powers
                    signed. Under these declarations are the signature of your predecessors in the
                    post of President—Franklin Roosevelt and Harry Truman. But can it be that the
                    aforementioned territories ceased to be Chinese after, in China, as a result of
                    the victories of the peoples revolution, there was created a government which
                    reflects the will of the whole Chinese people and which is governed by the ideas
                    of Communism? Certainly not. To deny this means to interfere in the internal
                    affairs of other peoples, means to take upon oneself the function of a gendarme.
                    Your declaration bears witness to the fact that the Government of the USA,
                    unfortunately, does not intend to renounce interference in the internal affairs
                    of China and an aggressive course in relation to the Chinese People’s Republic.
                    And just this is a very dangerous policy which creates a threat of an outbreak
                    of military conflict in the Far East and in other regions. Certainly if you
                    construct your policy proceeding from such conceptions, then England, were she
                    in a position to do so, could, for example, begin war against the USA only on
                    the basis that the US at one time did not exist and that its present territory
                    was a colony of the British Empire.</p>
                <p>It is impossible also not to note that, in your letter, the opposing of Taiwan
                    and of the Offshore Islands to all of China is an undisguised attempt to create
                    a situation of “two Chinas”. Similar attempts having the aim of dismembering the
                    territory of China are decisively repudiated by the people and the Government of
                    the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> as well as by all who treat with respect
                    the sovereign rights of peoples and the territorial integrity of states. Until
                    now, Mr. President, you apparently proceed from the premise that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> represents something in China.
                    In fact, for 600 million Chinese he is merely a hated shadow of the past, and
                    they wish that this shadow would disappear as soon as possible and forever. In
                    China, there is only one government—the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. Not
                    to see this is to base your actions on illusions which, it goes without saying,
                    cannot serve as the basis for the foreign policy of any state.</p>
                <p>The allegation in your letter that the armed forces of the USA are acting in the
                    area of Taiwan in pursuance of treaty obligations of the USA to a handful of
                    betrayers of the Chinese people headed by <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> is groundless. I am not even speaking about that handful
                    of people whom, even in 1949, Acheson, then Secretary of State of the USA,
                    characterized as people who were corrupt and who had lost the trust of their <pb
                        facs="0267" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> people, who have long represented no
                    one but themselves. At the present time <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> can assume the capacity of representative of China with
                    no more basis than, for instance, Kerensky the capacity of representative of the
                    Soviet people. And if the logic of your letter is followed, it derives that
                    while Kerensky, who is maintained somewhere within the USA, is alive, and you
                    could also conclude a treaty with him as head of the provisional government of
                    Russia which existed at one time, the US, relying on that treaty as it now
                    relies on its treaty with <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                    Kai-shek</persName>, could begin a war against the Soviet Union. Now doesn’t
                    this example demonstrate how absurd are references to treaty obligations such as
                    those which the USA has with <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName>? This kind of a treaty is invented and fabricated
                    exclusively for concealment of aggressive aims.</p>
                <p>You assert in your letter that <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName>, who is supported by the Government of the USA, is
                    recognized by the majority of states. I would not begin to employ such
                    arithmetic, Mr. President, because it can lead to a serious error. However, I
                    should point out that at the present time the <gloss target="#t_CPR1"
                        >CPR</gloss> is recognized by more than thirty states, whose population
                    comes to more than a billion persons. With regard to the recognition of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> clique by a number of
                    governments you yourself know well what efforts it has cost and costs the US to
                    achieve retention of such recognition. This your State Secretary
                        <persName>Dulles</persName> also knows well. I do not reveal a secret if I
                    say that the countries retaining relations with the Chiang Kai-shekists are
                    burdened by such recognition, and this recognition is approaching its end. It
                    cannot be doubted that the majority of states which retain diplomatic relations
                    with <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> under pressure of
                    the USA will be happy when there finally comes to an end the situation which is
                    in open contradiction to common sense and goes contrary to the interests of the
                    peoples of these countries, and when China occupies its just place in
                    international organizations.</p>
                <p>It is undoubtedly very well known to you that even those countries which do not
                    dare to recognize the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> because of the danger
                    of incurring the displeasure of the USA are experiencing serious qualms about
                    the possible results of the present policy of the US in relation to the <gloss
                        target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. This is understandable because the threats of
                    the statesmen of the USA addressed to the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>
                    and also the concentration of American armed forces and other military
                    preparations of the USA in the area of Taiwan actually create a threat of the
                    eruption of an armed conflict with all of the dangerous consequences deriving
                    therefrom. With regard to the blackmail and threats relating to People’s China,
                    it is necessary to say that they have not achieved and cannot achieve their
                    goal.</p>
                <p>As I already pointed out in my previous message, some American military figures
                    are even trying to threaten China with atomic weapons. In the press it is
                    revealed that units of the American Air Force equipped <pb facs="0268" n="236"
                        xml:id="pg_236"/> with atomic arms are being transferred to Taiwan, that
                    there are being delivered various missiles and guided missiles, in particular
                    the type “Nike Hercules”, that sites for their launching are being constructed,
                    and so on. Such activity of the Government of the USA cannot, of course, lead to
                    a reduction of tension in this area, to a relaxation of the situation and to the
                    creation of conditions for the strengthening of trust. On the contrary, these
                    activities are directed toward the exacerbation of the situation and increase
                    danger of the outbreak of war involving use of the most destructive kinds of
                    modern weapons.</p>
                <p>I should say to you in all candor, Mr. President, that atomic blackmail with
                    regard to the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> does not frighten either us or
                    the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. Those who nurture plans for an atomic
                    attack on the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> should not forget that not
                    only the USA but the other side as well possesses atomic and hydrogen weapons
                    and also the appropriate means for their delivery, and if such an attack is made
                    on the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>, the aggressor will immediately
                    receive a proper repulse with these very means.</p>
                <p>War against China on the pretext of defense of the so-called interests of
                    security of the USA or on any other such artificial pretext whatever will get
                    the US nowhere. To unleash war against People’s China means to send to certain
                    death the sons of the American people and to ignite the conflagration of world
                    war. This means to take on one’s self a heavy responsibility before humanity and
                    before history. Responsibility for this, Mr. President, also will lie personally
                    on you.</p>
                <p>It is especially necessary to emphasize that such a step of the Government of the
                    USA would be unanimously condemned by the peoples of the entire world, among
                    them I am convinced, also the American people.</p>
                <p>I have already stated to you and I consider it necessary to emphasize it once
                    more that an attack on the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> is an attack on
                    the Soviet Union. With the great friend, ally and neighbor of our country—with
                    People’s China—we have concluded a treaty of friendship, alliance, and mutual
                    assistance, corresponding to the basic interests of the Soviet and Chinese
                    peoples, to the interests of peace and let no one doubt this: We will fulfill
                    completely the obligations we have assumed.</p>
                <p>Therefore, I would like once more to turn to you with an appeal not to overheat
                    the atmosphere, not to create conditions which would disturb mankind which is
                    thirsting for peace, to think over and weigh all the circumstances before
                    undertaking any steps which might lead to catastrophic consequences.</p>
                <p>The duty of governments and above all of the governments of our countries is to
                    do everything necessary so that the development of international events should
                    go in the direction of strengthening peaceful co-operation, so that trade should
                    be developed among peoples, economic <pb facs="0269" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/>
                    ties, cultural relations, so that all results of labor are directed toward the
                    raising of the welfare of peoples and for the security of further progress.</p>
                <p>After your election as President of the USA, Soviet leaders placed great hopes on
                    you. Remembering the good experience of cooperation between the Soviet Union and
                    the US in that period when you were in command of the armed forces of the USA,
                    England and France in the war against fascism, against Hitlerite Germany, we
                    calculated that this cooperation could be realized also after the war, in the
                    present period, in the interest of the preservation and consolidation of peace.
                    However, now the policy which you as President are conducting to a significant
                    degree has undermined these good feelings and is ever more strengthening among
                    us the opinion that Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName>’ “brink of war” policy in
                    essence is not separated from your name, is linked with it. This is very
                    regrettable.</p>
                <p>In our time a “position of strength” policy, a policy of balancing “on the brink
                    of war” cannot be successful. In contrast to that period when Hitler unleashed a
                    world war, now the forces of peace are immeasurably strengthened and what is
                    especially important the relation of forces on the international arena has
                    radically changed in their favor. History will grimly judge those state leaders
                    who, not reckoning with common sense and with the interests of the peoples of
                    the whole world, seek to follow the path of military adventures.</p>
                <p>It is generally known that the Government of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1"
                        >CPR</gloss> has repeatedly taken the initiative and come out with proposals
                    directed toward the weakening of tension in the Far East, toward the peaceful
                    settlement of international questions at issue in this region. Despite the
                    assertion contained in your message, in the course of the negotiations between
                    the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and USA on the level of Ambassadors in
                    Geneva, the representatives of China repeatedly proposed that both sides on the
                    basis of the principles of mutual respect of sovereignty and territorial
                    integrity and noninterference in internal affairs should come out with
                    declarations of their readiness to settle disputes between the <gloss
                        target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and the USA in the area of Taiwan by means of
                    peaceful negotiations and not to resort to the application of force or to the
                    threat of force. The Chinese-American negotiations in Geneva did not give
                    positive results only because the USA refused to take such a position and as
                    result of which unilaterally broke off the talks.</p>
                <p>In your message you, Mr. President, declare that you welcome the renewal of talks
                    between the USA and the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>. We also welcome the
                    initiative of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and are glad that the
                    efforts of the Government of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> in this
                    direction have met a response on the part of the Government of the US.</p>
                <p>We would like to hope that in these negotiations the USA will finally adopt a
                    reasonable, realistic position. Reasonableness and realism of position can be
                    expressed only if the Government of the USA will come to <pb facs="0270" n="238"
                        xml:id="pg_238"/> an evaluation of the situation which has arisen by taking
                    into account the historical changes which have taken place in China, by ceasing
                    to support the clique of <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>
                    and by forming the necessary conclusions from the fact that China is the Chinese
                    People’s Republic whose government represents the Chinese state, the whole
                    Chinese people.</p>
                <p>If one does not conduct a line toward the preparation of war and indeed is guided
                    by ideas of peaceful cooperation, then it is most important to recognize the
                    Government of the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Such a step by the Government of the USA would at once improve the international
                    situation and would everywhere be welcomed as an extremely valuable contribution
                    to the cause of preserving peace. An approach toward the solution of
                    international problems from the positions of peaceful cooperation dictates also
                    the necessity to cease an obstructionist policy in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> organization and not to put obstacles in the way of settlement
                    of the pressing question about the restoration of the rights of the <gloss
                        target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. This
                    undoubtedly would be met by satisfaction by all member states of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> inasmuch as without the <gloss target="#t_CPR1"
                        >CPR</gloss> the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> organization cannot be a
                    full-blooded international organ for the support of international peace and
                    security as the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter demands.</p>
                <p>It is necessary once and for all to finish with interference in the internal
                    affairs of China. The American Naval fleet must be withdrawn from the Taiwan
                    Straits and American soldiers must leave Taiwan and go home. Without this there
                    cannot be lasting peace in the Far East. If the USA does not do this now, then
                    no other way will be left to People’s China except the expulsion of the armed
                    forces hostile to it from its own territory on which a base is being created for
                    an attack on the Chinese People’s Republic. We are completely on the side of the
                    Chinese Government, the Chinese people. We have supported and will support their
                    policy.</p>
                <p>If the Government of the USA will follow the path of respecting the sovereign
                    rights of the great Chinese people and will base its policy in relation to China
                    on the principles of peaceful coexistence, then one cannot doubt that this not
                    only will permit the elimination of the current tension in the area of Taiwan
                    but also will create the necessary conditions for the reliable strengthening of
                    peace in the Far East and in the whole world. With respect (signed) <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">N. Khrushchev</persName>.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
