<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-23T21:02:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-23T21:02:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <head>123. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Poland</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d123fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 611.93/9–2358. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution. Drafted
                                by <persName corresp="#p_LLR1">Lutkins</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MEW1">Martin</persName>, cleared in substance by
                                    <persName>Dulles</persName> and with <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>, and approved
                                by <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>. Repeated to
                                USUN for Lodge and priority to Taipei.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-09-23T22:02:00-04:00">September 23, 1958, 10:02 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>329. <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>–<persName>Wang</persName> Talks. Following are
                            instructions for line you should take at meeting with
                                <persName>Wang</persName> 25th:</p>
                        <pb facs="0300" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/>
                        <p>Begin by pointing out unacceptable nature of new Chinese Communist draft
                            agreed announcement and proceed to rebut <persName>Wang</persName>’s
                            charges. Statement in first paragraph <persName>Wang</persName>’s
                            suggested draft announcement that Chinese Communists prepared to resolve
                            present crisis in Taiwan area through peaceful negotiation without
                            resort to force nullified by Communist use of force against Quemoy and
                            moreover does not affect use of force against GRC and its territory
                            which is crux of matter.</p>
                        <p>US rejects categorically implication in second paragraph of draft
                            announcement that presence of its armed forces in Taiwan area in present
                            circumstances constitutes provocation against Communist China. Reiterate
                            that their presence and operations in area defensive in nature, made
                            necessary under terms of Mutual Defense Treaty with our ally Republic of
                            China to counter unprovoked, unjustified, and wanton armed aggression
                            against its territory and threats to its existence by Chinese
                            Communists. Point out <persName>Wang</persName>’s regime itself has
                            mutual security treaty with Soviet Union, and relied upon that treaty in
                            its aggression in Korea and now relies upon it in its resort to force in
                            Taiwan Straits. <persName>Wang</persName>’s charge that US attempting to
                            invade and occupy offshores as stepping stone to invasion of mainland is
                            patently absurd, belied by well-known US defensive posture throughout
                            world and by defensive character of military measures and preparations
                            taken by it in Taiwan area. Statements by US leaders cited by
                                <persName>Wang</persName> have all made clear that our aims are
                            defensive, in marked contrast to expressions of aggressive warlike
                            intent which have proceeded from Peiping officials in recent weeks.
                            Emphasize that US forces will remain disposed as necessary to fulfill
                            its treaty obligations.</p>
                        <p>State that no amount of repetition by <persName>Wang</persName> to
                            contrary can undo fact that Republic of China is sovereign government
                            recognized by respectable part of world community. As such it has full
                            right in protection its security and interests to conclude alliances and
                            defense treaties with other countries including US. You should
                            forcefully refute <persName>Wang</persName>’s argument that language of
                            our draft agreed announcement demonstrated master-slave relationship.
                            Emphasize that draft said US would seek that offshores not be used for
                            attack against mainland. This demonstrates precisely opposite of what
                                <persName>Wang</persName> arguing, namely that GRC is sovereign ally
                            which US must and will at all times consult before making any commitment
                            affecting its rights and interests.</p>
                        <p>Conversations in first three meetings have revealed basic differences
                            between US and Chinese Communists as to cause of present hostilities in
                            Taiwan Straits and means of resolving crisis. Prolonged reiteration of
                            established positions on these basic points can only result in sterile
                            discussion and disappoint ardent world hope that hostilities in area be
                            terminated and peaceful solution sought. This situation clearly demands
                            immediate cessation of hostilities as prerequisite to further
                            exploration <pb facs="0301" n="269" xml:id="pg_269"/> of means to bridge
                            gap between divergent positions. If Chinese Communists continue to
                            reject call for ceasefire and expansion of conflict should occur, they
                            will bear full responsibility in eyes of world. Accomplishment of
                            ceasefire and elimination of provocative actions on other hand would
                            create atmosphere in which phased reduction of forces and armament in
                            coastal islands and adjacent areas could be discussed with some hope of
                            reaching mutually acceptable arrangements.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Suggestion for revision our draft
                            announcement contained urtel 458<note n="1" xml:id="d123fn1"><persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>’s proposed draft was
                                transmitted in telegram 458 from Warsaw, September 23. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.;</hi> see Supplement)</note> being
                            considered and expect have revised draft ready for presentation at
                            meeting subsequent to next one. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2">Telegram 333 to Warsaw,
                                September 24, authorized <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>
                                to inform <persName>Wang</persName> that revisions to the U.S. draft
                                announcement were under consideration and he expected to present
                                them at the next meeting. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                611.93/9–1458)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName>Dulles</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>