<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-10T11:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-10T10:36:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                        <head>172. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d172fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                793.00/10–1058. Top Secret; Limited Distribution. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEW1">Martin</persName>. The time of the
                                meeting is taken from <persName>Dulles</persName>’ appointment book.
                                (Princeton University, Dulles Papers)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" from="1958-10-10T11:36:00-04:00" to="1958-10-10T12:08:00-04:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">October 10, 1958, 11:36
                                    a.m.–12:08 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Future Moves Regarding Offshore Island Situation</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">George K.C. Yeh</persName>,
                                Chinese Ambassador</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEW1">Martin</persName>, Director,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> that he had invited him in for a chat so that they
                            might look into the future. He said that of course if the fighting were
                            to resume in the offshore island area, the situation would revert to
                            that which had existed before the Communists stopped firing, i.e., to
                            United States escort of GRC convoys, etc. The Secretary noted that the
                            present resupply situation seemed to be in good shape. In this
                            connection he mentioned an encouraging report which had just been
                            received from Taipei.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said the Communists now faced the situation which he
                            foresaw as occurring if we were able to prevent them from gaining the
                            full results of their interdiction of GRC resupply by artillery fire.
                            They were faced with the alternatives of letting their military effort
                            gradually die or of raising the level of this effort, which would have
                            increased the danger of the conflict’s spreading. Maybe the Communists
                            had suspended the hostilities for a week to consider the problem which
                            confronted them. There seemed to be a fair chance that they would decide
                            that it was too hard a nut to crack and they would therefore attempt to
                            gain their ends by political means both in the area and outside of
                            it.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary noted that the situation which the GRC faced with regard to
                            the outside world was not satisfactory. The Communists wished to spread
                            the idea that there was dissension between the GRC and the United States
                            Governments and were attempting to create sentiment against President
                                <persName>Chiang</persName> and his Government in the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> asked, when the
                            Secretary said the situation did not look good for the GRC, did he refer
                            to the fact that the initiative had been taken by the Communists?</p>
                        <p>The Secretary replied no—he had not meant this. He had meant that only
                            with the greatest difficulty was the United States holding back some <pb facs="0392" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/> of its friends from
                            recognizing Communist China and from agreeing to its admission to the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. In this connection he mentioned
                            specifically Canada, Belgium, France and New Zealand. It was only by our
                            exerting the strongest efforts that we could prevent these countries
                            from adopting such policies. We almost had to say to them that we would
                            regard such actions as unfriendly to us.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that these feelings were present even before the
                            flare-up on the offshore islands. Governments like to have relations
                            with the source of power, whether this power is good or evil. Some of
                            these governments felt that it would be better for Communist China to be
                            in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> than to be out of it. They feel
                            that power demands recognition, although this does not mean that they
                            like the power. Therefore the Secretary saw difficult times ahead. He
                            said that the “two of us in the room” are almost alone in wanting to
                            carry on our policy. A great many of our friends feel that we can’t
                            expect the Chinese Communists indefinitely to put up with having on
                            their doorstep a revolutionary government. Moreover, they are worried
                            about United States involvement and the Soviet Union’s involvement with
                            the consequent danger of another war. All this presents problems that we
                            need to think about. The Secretary said that he did not have the answers
                            but we cannot be blind to the problems. It won’t do us any good to bury
                            our heads in the sand and go ahead on the assumption that the positions
                            which we occupy will be valid for the next year or two. We should try to
                            meet the situation together.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary stressed that there was no disposition on the part of the
                            United States Government to change its basic policy, which could be
                            summed up as recognition of the Republic of China and the extension to
                            it of military and economic assistance; non-recognition of the Chinese
                            Communist regime and its continued exclusion from the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. The problem was how can we make this
                            policy succeed. The Secretary said he had no formulas.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that he wished to discuss this possibility: that after
                            we see what happens on Sunday (October 12) and after reflection, he
                            would be willing to come out to Taipei to talk to President
                                <persName>Chiang</persName> about the problem of making our policy
                            more palatable to the people of the United States and our allies. The
                            Secretary pointed out that there was a rising tide of opinion against
                            our policy. There was even a change in the United States. Two or three
                            years ago this was a bipartisan matter. Now it is no longer the case. We
                            must face up to bitter opposition and to the feeling that people don’t
                            want another world war. Before World War II a similar feeling in England
                            was summed up in the phrase “Don’t die for Danzig.” Now people are
                            saying “Why die for Quemoy.” There is a trend in Europe toward pacifism.
                            There is a tendency there to sacrifice Asia reminiscent of the feeling
                            there when the Lytton Commission went to Manchuria in the early
                            ‘30’s.</p>
                        <pb facs="0393" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/>
                        <p>However, the Secretary felt that actually the situation was better than
                            it appeared to be publicly. The British Government had stood by us very
                            well. Recently the Netherlands had taken a very strong line of protest
                            against the Chinese Communists’ use of force. The German Ambassador had
                            recently made a good statement. The Secretary had spoken to the German
                            Ambassador, who said the Germans did not like the analogy that the
                            Secretary had made between Berlin and Quemoy.<note n="1" xml:id="d172fn1">Reference is to the conversation cited in <ref target="#d169fn2">footnote 2, Document 169</ref>.</note> The
                            Secretary said the Germans did not like the analogy because it was true.
                            It was a question of the spirit in which we approached these crises. A
                            spirit which would lead the United States to quit in Quemoy would also
                            lead us to quit in Berlin. One can always rationalize retreat. If the
                            United States is in the mood to rationalize retreat we might as well
                            write off Berlin.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary emphasized that it is now time to think about and to do
                            something with regard to the offshore island situation in order to get
                            the support we need for our policy. It is important that the initiative
                            come from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName>’s
                            government. It is important for their prestige and their position in the
                            world. The Secretary asked that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> convey to President
                                <persName>Chiang</persName> this thinking and the fact that the
                            Secretary was willing to go out to Taipei to talk with him directly.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary realized that President <persName>Chiang</persName> had his
                            problems. We of course have ours. Our problem is the terrific pressure
                            by our allies and our own public opinion. We must have the support of
                            our own country and our allies. Sometimes it has been necessary (as in
                            his last press conference) to say some things which would gain the
                            support we need. What would help President <persName>Chiang</persName>
                            in his problem would not necessarily help us with our problems. The
                            important thing was to try to get a convergence of GRC and United States
                            lines on some course that would give our policy the best chance of
                            success. We must take some course which will stem the mounting tide of
                            opposition from such countries as Canada, France, and New Zealand and
                            which will keep them with us.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary had recently talked with Canadian Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> and asked him to bear in mind
                            that the United States had the main responsibility for the security of
                            the free world in the western Pacific.<note n="2" xml:id="d172fn2">Reference is apparently to a conversation on October 8; a
                                memorandum of the portion of the conversation on the subject of the
                                “Chinese Situation” is in Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda
                                of Conversation: Lot 64 D 199.</note> Canadians should not allow
                            local pressures for a little business with Red China to undermine our
                            ability to discharge these responsibilities. The Secretary said that
                            only by such pressures as these were we able to hold allies such as
                            Canada in line.</p>
                        <pb facs="0394" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/>
                        <p>In response to a question by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> regarding the position of Prime Minister
                            Diefenbaker, the Secretary said that Mr.
                                <persName>Diefenbaker</persName> was strongly influenced by his
                            close friend, the editor of the “Toronto Globe and Mail”, who had taken
                            a trip to Communist China.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that
                            only as a result of the talks with the Secretary and the President<note n="3" xml:id="d172fn3">On July 8; see <ref target="#d17">Document
                                    17</ref>.</note> had Mr. <persName>Diefenbaker</persName> held
                            back. He mentioned also the powerful influence of the Secretary’s talks
                            with Prime Minister Nash of New Zealand.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that his talks with Nash<note n="4" xml:id="d172fn4">See <ref target="#d144">Document 144</ref>.</note> had prevented
                            the latter from plunging right into the recognition of Communist China,
                            which had actually been a plank in the platform of his political party.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that
                            only these personal discussions with the Secretary had been able to make
                            Nash see things more clearly.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary also referred to a recent speech by Spaak<note n="5" xml:id="d172fn5">NATO Secretary General Paul-Henri Spaak.</note> in
                            which he talked about seeing things more clearly regarding the
                            relationship between the security of Europe and security in the whole
                            world. The Secretary said you can’t draw a line around Europe.</p>
                        <p>As he was about to leave, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> reverted to the Secretary’s mention of Sunday. He
                            had not been quite clear as to the significance of that date.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that Sunday was presumably the last day of the
                            cease-fire and we would know after that whether hostilities are resumed
                            or whether there would perhaps be a fairly prolonged breathing spell. If
                            it were to be such a breathing spell then he thought it might be useful
                            to discuss these problems with President <persName>Chiang</persName>,
                            but he would want a little more time to get his own ideas
                            formulated.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>