<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                        <head>246. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d246fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                793.00/12–958. Secret. No drafting information appears on the source
                                text.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1958-12-09">December 9, 1958</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>’s
                                Letter to Secretary Regarding Reaction to Joint Communiqué</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">George K.C. Yeh</persName>,
                                Chinese Ambassador</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Hsu</persName>, Chinese Minister</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEW1">Martin</persName>, Director,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> called at Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>’s request. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said that because
                            the Secretary was in the hospital he had not yet been able to reply to
                            the letter which he had received from Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName> just before he made his San
                            Francisco speech.<note n="1" xml:id="d246fn1">The letter, dated December
                                3, is filed with a covering note of December 4 from Patrick Pichi
                                Sun, Republic of China Consul General in San Francisco, to
                                    <persName>Dulles</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                793.00/12–458; see Supplement) <persName>Dulles</persName> addressed
                                the California Chamber of Commerce in San Francisco on December 4 on
                                the subject of U.S. policy in the Far East. For text of his address,
                                see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December
                                22, 1958, pp. 989–994.</note> However, he wanted to read to
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> the reply to
                            Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>’s letter
                            which was being recommended to the Secretary.<note n="2" xml:id="d246fn2"><persName>Dulles</persName>’ reply to <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>, December 12, was drafted on
                                December 8. (Department of State, Central Files, 793.00/12–1258; see
                                Supplement)</note> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> indicated that <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>’s letter had been intended to keep the Secretary
                            informed about overseas Chinese opinion.</p>
                        <pb facs="0531" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that if
                            the GRC were to get involved in a war, it would be dependent upon United
                            States forces for support. The United States wanted to strengthen and
                            support the GRC to meet developments on the mainland, but the United
                            States was against the use of force to reunite China and the other
                            divided countries. The GRC should adopt tactics to meet this situation.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> stressed that the
                            Joint Communiqué of October 23 had been a tremendous help in giving our
                            allies a true picture of the GRC’s role and of destroying the false
                            picture which many of them had of a government planning to drag the
                            world into war in its attempt to recover China. Any denigration of the
                            Joint Communiqué by Taipei might destroy support for the GRC in the
                            United States, let alone in the rest of the world. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> then read the text of the
                            proposed letter to Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said he thought
                            the proposed letter was a good one, and again expressed the opinion that
                            the purpose of <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName>’s letter was
                            to keep the Secretary informed. He said that during his visits to the
                            overseas Chinese communities in New York and San Francisco, which he had
                            thought were reasonably successful, he had encountered two lines of
                            criticism. First, since the Chinese Communist regime was now getting an
                            even tighter grip on the people through the communes, it was necessary
                            to offset this with increased pressure from the outside. Such external
                            pressure was necessary to bring about conditions for an uprising.
                            Secondly, since the bases for the return to the mainland were in the
                            hearts and minds of the people, it was essential to keep their hopes for
                            freedom alive. According to the critics, the Joint Communiqué failed on
                            both these points.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> replied that all the
                            opposition which could be generated on the mainland among the people
                            would not be capable of bringing about a successful revolution until the
                            Red Army, or a significant part of it, went over to the side of the
                            people. The peoples’ support could be obtained now but, considering that
                            the Red Army comprised 2–1/2 million men and that the GRC forces were
                            comparatively small in size, the peoples’ support alone was not enough.
                            Moreover, the GRC alone could not succeed without United States support.
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> agreed.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> pointed out that
                            attacks on the GRC were coming from <hi rend="italic">Shih Chieh Jih Pao
                                (Chinese World)</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lien Ho Jih Pao (United
                                Journal)</hi>, both published in New York City. He said these papers
                            had been supported by United States agencies in the past. While they
                            were anti-Communist they were also critical of the GRC. In addition,
                            there was a Communist paper in New York called the <hi rend="italic">Hua
                                Chiao Jih Pao</hi>. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Lien Ho Jih
                                Pao</hi>, Mr. <persName>Wu Ching-fu</persName>, had editorially
                            called for the resignation of <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                                Kai-shek</persName> and his chief advisors. His paper had also
                            criticized Secretary <persName>Dulles</persName> for having “a two
                            Chinas” policy.</p>
                        <pb facs="0532" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that
                            Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName> was very
                            reasonable and would be the last person to retract any statement such as
                            the Joint Communiqué, to which the GRC had agreed. Minister <persName corresp="#p_HS1">Huang</persName> would be very surprised and sorry
                            to hear that Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> was upset by his
                            letter.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said that the GRC
                            should not regard the Joint Communiqué as a negative thing to which it
                            was tied by agreement, but should make it the basis for a positive
                            policy. Unfortunately, Vice President Chen Cheng’s statement about
                            counterattacking the mainland<note n="3" xml:id="d246fn3">Reference is
                                apparently to a speech by <persName>Ch’en</persName> on November 12,
                                reported in telegram 743 to Taipei, November 14. (Department of
                                State, Central Files, 793.00/11–1458)</note> was contrary to the
                            concept of the Joint Communiqué. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> stressed that he had telegraphed
                            his government some time ago to avoid using the word “counterattack.”
                            However, he had had no reply to this message.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>