<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="377" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                        <head>377. Draft Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                            Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="from">Robertson</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HCA1" type="to">Herter</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d377fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>/EA Files: Lot 66 D 225, Tibetan.
                                Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LLR1">Lutkins</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEW1">Martin</persName>, and Bacon on May
                                5. The memorandum was never sent to the Secretary. It was sent to
                                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> and NEA for concurrence, but
                                neither bureau concurred. Their responses were set forth in
                                memoranda from Walmsley and Rountree to <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>, dated May 18 and 21, respectively, which
                                indicate that they felt <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>’s policy recommendations did not reflect
                                the staff study which had been prepared by an interbureau working
                                group. Rountree attached suggestions for revisions in the
                                recommendations concerning the recognition question, and Walmsley
                                suggested revisions in the recommendations concerning possible U.N.
                                action. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.;</hi> see Supplement) A handwritten
                                note by <persName corresp="#p_LLR1">Lutkins</persName> on the source
                                text states that at a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> in late May, it was decided that “we should
                                act to have matter raised at U.N.” The staff study, attached to the
                                source text, is not printed.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-05-05">May 5,
                                1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>United States Position on Recognition of an Independent Tibetan
                                Government and United Nations Consideration of Tibet Issue</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Judging by intelligence reports and in the light of developments in Tibet
                            during the past few months, it is a real possibility that the Dalai Lama
                                <pb facs="0798" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/> will shortly 1) proclaim
                            the existence of an independent Tibetan state and government in exile;
                            2) request United States and free world recognition of this state and
                            government; and 3) appeal to the United Nations to consider Tibet’s case
                            against Communist China. If the Tibetans do take such steps, or if some
                            other government should seek to submit the issue to the United Nations
                            in Tibet’s behalf, the United States will have to decide quickly whether
                            it is in our interest to support the Tibetan cause by affirmative
                            action.</p>
                        <p>There is attached a staff study (Tab A) prepared by <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> in coordination with NEA, <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>,
                            which states United States objectives with respect to the Tibet issue;
                            examines the attitudes, intentions, and interests of the parties chiefly
                            concerned with the issue; and discusses the two problems of recognition
                            of an independent Tibetan state and government and United Nations action
                            in terms of historical background, factors relevant to a decision in the
                            present case, and the potential benefits and disadvantages to the United
                            States of positive action. On the basis of this analysis of the
                            situation and the policy problems posed by it, it is believed that our
                            policy with respect to the questions of recognition and United Nations
                            action should be as follows:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">1) Recognition</hi></p>
                        <p>We should at once discreetly sound out friendly states including the
                            United Kingdom on the attitude they would take if the Dalai Lama
                            requests recognition of Tibet as an independent state, adding our view
                            that such a request if made publicly should be given sympathetic
                            consideration.</p>
                        <p>We should not encourage the Dalai Lama to make such a request until and
                            unless we can be certain that it will be well received.</p>
                        <p>If the Tibetans publicly appeal for international recognition of an
                            independent state of Tibet headed by the Dalai Lama, <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>We should give the Tibetans prompt assurances that we are
                                    giving their appeal sympathetic consideration and encourage them
                                    to seek the support of other free world nations.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>We should extend our consultations with other free world
                                    nations on an urgent basis, seeking to persuade them to respond
                                    favorably.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item>Provided we are able to obtain the cooperation of a number of
                                    free world nations including Asian nations, we should extend
                                    recognition. If such cooperation is not forthcoming, we should
                                    reassess the situation to determine what course we should take.
                                    The attitude of India and other uncommitted Asian states should
                                    be considered, but would not be decisive.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>If as a result of seeking international recognition for
                                    Tibetan independence the Dalai Lama should have to leave India,
                                    we should try to assist him to gain asylum in some other free
                                    world country and, if appropriate, offer him asylum in the
                                    United States.</item>
                                <label>e)</label>
                                <item>If we extend recognition, we should seek to induce the GRC to
                                    join us. If the GRC feels unable to do so, we should seek to
                                    induce it at <pb facs="0799" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/> least not
                                    to challenge the validity of United States and other free world
                                    recognition.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2) United Nations Action</hi></p>
                        <p>We should at once discreetly sound out friendly states including the
                            United Kingdom on their attitude toward possible United Nations
                            consideration of the Tibetan problem and on the best procedure if it
                            appears desirable to seek such consideration.</p>
                        <p>If the Tibetans publicly appeal to the United Nations, <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>We should extend our consultations with other free world
                                    nations on an urgent basis, informing them that we support
                                    inscription of the appeal and urging support.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>We should seek to determine the most promising form of United
                                    Nations action and the most appropriate sponsorship, keeping in
                                    mind the desirability of as broad sponsorship as
                                    possible.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item>Depending on developments, we should favor an invitation to
                                    the Dalai Lama to appear before the Security Council or the
                                    General Assembly.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>In the event India and other uncommitted Asian nations should
                                    oppose any prospective United Nations action, we should give
                                    consideration to their objections and the implications for the
                                    success of such action, but their attitude should not be
                                    decisive.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In the absence of action by the Tibetans themselves to appeal to the
                            United Nations, <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>We should not, in the present circumstances, ourselves take an
                                    initiative in submitting the matter to the United Nations, but
                                    should keep the question under constant review.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>We should, insofar as feasible, seek to determine the desires
                                    and intentions of the Dalai Lama with respect to United Nations
                                    action.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item>We should consult fully and on a continuing basis with other
                                    free world countries to ascertain their views regarding possible
                                    courses of United Nations action.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>Depending on the circumstances, if another free world country,
                                    especially an Asian one, should indicate to us an interest in
                                    taking an initiative in the United Nations, we should discreetly
                                    encourage it to do so.</item>
                                <label>e)</label>
                                <item>If it appears that the Dalai Lama would welcome consideration
                                    of the Tibetan issue by the United Nations and that there would
                                    be adequate support, we might wish to stimulate another
                                    government, especially an Asian one, to take the matter to the
                                    United Nations.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>