<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="380" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d380">
                        <head>380. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>At the 409th meeting of the National Security Council on June 4, 1959,
                            Director of Central Intelligence <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen
                                Dulles</persName> discussed developments in Tibet during his
                            briefing on significant world developments, and a brief exchange
                            followed. The relevant portion of the memorandum of discussion of that
                            date by S. Everett Gleason reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> said that the Dalai Lama was
                                    planning to make a public statement on June 6 denouncing
                                    Communist China’s action in Tibet and calling for a campaign to
                                    free Tibet. While <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>
                                    was trying to stop this public statement, it was thought that
                                    the Dalai Lama might make it nevertheless.</p>
                                <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> observed that
                                    there existed very strong feeling in some parts of the
                                    Department of Defense that our current U.S. ‘hands off policy
                                    with respect to Tibet needed re-examination. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> suggested that this matter
                                    not be discussed at the Council meeting at the present time but
                                    that it might be brought up later. The President commented
                                    sharply that he thought the State Department should take the
                                    lead in such matters.” (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Three unsigned and undated memoranda concerning Tibet, which had been
                            sent to <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> with a covering note
                            of June 3 from Deputy Secretary of Defense Thomas S. Gates are filed
                            with a covering memorandum of June 15 from <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> to Gates. One of them, an unsigned memorandum to
                            the Secretary of Defense, reads in part as follows: <list>
                                <item>“1. In its regular meeting of this date, the Collateral
                                    Activities Coordinating Group of which I am Chairman, expressed
                                    its deep concern over the situation in Asia as a result of the
                                    Chinese Communist aggression in Tibet. We believe that the
                                    United States Government should take positive action to denounce
                                    the Communist action as additional evidence of the inevitable
                                    course of international communism. Concurrently, we believe that
                                    the United States should openly proffer assistance to the
                                    Tibetans in every way possible in order to capitalize on the
                                    present climate in Asia.</item>
                                <item>“2. We do not accept the view of some who may feel that it is
                                    wise for the West to refrain from action while the Indians and
                                    other Asians work out their own immediate destiny. Inaction, at
                                    this time, by the West can be interpreted by the Asians as an
                                    indication of weakness, indifference, and a lack of dynamic
                                    leadership. We are convinced that the question of the security
                                    of India and the remaining free nations of Asia is at stake.”
                                    (Washington National Records Center, RG 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 63 A 1574, Tibet
                                    1959)</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>