<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-12-06T20:06:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-12-06T20:06:00-05:00" n="114" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d114">
                        <head>114. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="to">U. Alexis
                                Johnson</persName>, at Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d114fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                611.93/12–655. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution. Cleared in
                                draft by the Secretary and in substance by <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName>, and approved for
                                transmission by <persName corresp="#p_RRBJ1">Robertson</persName>.
                                The source text lists as drafters <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CRN1">Clough</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-12-06T20:06:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">December 6,
                                        1955—8:06 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1353. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1352,<note n="2" xml:id="d114fn2"><ref target="#d113"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> paragraph 4. Following are
                            Department’s views on renunciation of force for presentation as
                            appropriate at meeting subsequent to December 8.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Renunciation of Force. While <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName>’s new draft represents retreat from original
                                language calling for conference on Foreign Minister level, it still
                                evades clearcut renunciation of force both generally and
                                specifically with respect to Taiwan area, leaving Communists free to
                                use force against <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> and Taiwan.
                                Any subsequent defensive reaction by US forces in compliance with
                                treaty obligation could be claimed as violation by US of commitment
                                not to use force against Communists and as rendering null and void
                                Communists’ commitment not to use force against US or Taiwan.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In order prevent Communists from claiming later that their
                                announcement does not cover use of force against <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> and Taiwan, we must insist on
                                inclusion geographical concept contained US draft. Department has
                                therefore inserted appropriate language into Communist draft to
                                cover this point (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                                    [1354]).<note n="3" xml:id="d114fn3"><p>Telegram 1354 to Geneva,
                                        December 6, transmitted to <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> a proposed revision of <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName>’s December 1 draft; the
                                        only portion which differed from <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName>’s draft was paragraph B which reads as
                                        follows:</p>
                                    <p>“The People’s Republic of China and the United States of
                                        America are determined that they should settle disputes
                                        between them through peaceful negotiations without resort to
                                        the threat or use of force; and they renounce the use of
                                        force in general, and with particular reference to the
                                        Taiwan area, except in individual and collective self
                                        defense.”</p>
                                    <p>The telegram further states that the Department had decided
                                        not to object to the form of a joint announcement “so that
                                        if Communists should break off talks they could not utilize
                                        dispute over form of announcement to obscure real issue.”
                                        (Department of State, Central Files,
                                    611.93/12–655)</p></note></item>
                            <pb facs="0235" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>You will note that our amendment separates renunciation of force
                                in Taiwan area from declaration that US and Communists will settle
                                disputes between them peacefully. We have sought to avoid
                                implication that US will negotiate with Communists on such subjects
                                as status of Taiwan or our relations with <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. We cannot of course agree to any wording which
                                would bind us to negotiate on subjects involving rights and
                                interests of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. At an appropriate
                                time you should state that US will not negotiate such subjects in
                                absence of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. You should also at
                                all appropriate times make clear US not recognizing Communist
                                regime.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>While it is true, as stated paragraph 8 your 1241,<note n="4" xml:id="d114fn4"><ref target="#d111">Document 111</ref>.</note>
                                that agreement on Communists December 1 draft and publication
                                thereof would tend to increase difficulty of Communists’ future
                                resort to force, it probably would not constitute much if any
                                greater deterrent than their continued participation in negotiations
                                along present lines. Furthermore, declaration would be widely
                                considered concession by Communists, although it would have cost
                                them nothing, and pressure would be placed on US to make return
                                concession.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>There is danger, as pointed out paragraph 3 your 1241, that
                                Communists may go to public with December 1 draft. If they do, we
                                will counter by pointing out as clearly and simply as possible
                                fundamental defect in Communist draft and their refusal to accept
                                our amendment which proves Communists’ intention to be free to use
                                force against Taiwan. In effect, it would leave Communists free to
                                attack Taiwan and the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>, while
                                preventing US from fulfilling its treaty commitment to go to aid of
                                that government and to use force in individual and collective self
                                defense. We believe this would be strong position, as failure accept
                                our amendment is tantamount to Communists declaring they will use
                                force if they decide to do so.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>