<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-31T10:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-31T10:30:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <head>206. Memorandum on the Substance of Discussions at a Department of
                            State–Joint Chiefs of Staff Meeting, Washington, August 31, 1956, 11:30
                                a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d206fn1">Source: Department of
                                State, State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Meetings: Lot 61 D
                                417. Top Secret. A note on the title page reads: “State Draft. Not
                                cleared with any of participants”. Drafted by the Deputy Under
                                Secretary’s Special Assistant, <persName>W. Tapley
                                    Bennett</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1956-08-31T11:30:00-04:00">August 31,
                                    1956, 11:30 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>[Here follows a list of 25 persons present, including Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">General Taylor</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Arleigh A. Burke</persName>. Assistant
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> and General
                                <persName>Fox</persName> represented the Department of Defense. The
                            Department of State delegation included Deputy Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> and Assistant Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_CLGCP1">Cabell</persName> and Wisner attended the
                            meeting for the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">S. Everett Gleason</persName> for the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>. The first items discussed were 1,
                            “French Military Effort in Viet Nam” and 2, “The Suez Situation”.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3. <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Advisers on the Chinese Off-Shore Islands</hi></p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that
                            President <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang</persName> and other Chinese
                            Government leaders have been greatly perturbed over reports that the
                            United States may be planning to withdraw its <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> advisers from the off-shore islands. <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> explained that the
                            Chinese troops on the islands are now fully trained and no longer need
                                <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> advisers for instruction
                            purposes. The Pentagon is anxious <pb facs="0454" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/> to cut <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>
                            expenses, and the idea had been to have a gradual attrition of the
                            advisers stationed on the off-shore islands. The main problem from the
                            U.S. point of view is that we would lose our independent communications
                            facilities. He agreed that it would perhaps be best to plan for a
                            reduced number of advisers rather than to withdraw the entire group. A
                            small group could be left on the islands, possibly for communications
                            purposes entirely. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>
                            suggested that consideration be given to the issuance of a press release
                            which would make it clear that the United States is not withdrawing its
                            forces from the islands.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion on items 4, “Japanese Labor Relationships of
                            U.S. Armed Forces” and 5, “Austrian Force Levels”.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">6. Plane Incident off the China
                                Coast</hi></p>
                        <p>There was discussion regarding salvage operations with respect to the
                            Navy plane shot down last week by the Chinese Communists. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> mentioned that he had
                            discussed the situation with the Secretary and that the Secretary was
                            not clear in his own mind regarding our legal position with respect to
                            salvage operations on the floor of the sea, as distinct from surface
                            operations to which the traditional three mile limit would apply. The
                            Secretary thought the President should know of the problem and that his
                            views should be ascertained. <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral
                                Radford</persName> pointed out that underwater devices to locate the
                            plane wreckage were on the way to the scene in international waters but
                            that the wreckage itself has not yet been located. Therefore, the
                            question of salvage has not yet arisen. The Navy has the problem of
                            protecting the security of certain equipment which was on board the
                            plane and a major reason for our forces remaining in the area is for the
                            purpose of preventing the Chinese Communists from finding the wreckage
                            and removing it. He stressed that all that was needed now was State
                            Department clearance for the surface search. Once the wreckage was
                            located the problem of salvage operations could be faced.</p>
                        <p>There was some further discussion regarding a press release to be issued
                            the afternoon of August 31 regarding the plane incident.<note n="2" xml:id="d206fn2">See <ref target="#d204">Document
                            204</ref>.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>