<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>222. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-01-13T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Passports</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-13T06:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <head>222. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>Indian Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Jawaharlal Nehru</persName>
                    visited Washington with an official party December 16–20, 1956. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> discussed relations between the United
                    States and the People’s Republic of China in conversations with Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> at Blair House on December 16,
                    with President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> at his
                    Gettysburg farm on December 17, and again with <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName> on December 19 in the President’s office in the White
                    House. A memorandum prepared by <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> of
                    his conversation on December 16 with <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1"
                        >Nehru</persName> contains a brief section dealing with China: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“We discussed briefly the Chinese Communist situation. I said that before
                            there could be any change in our attitude there would have to be a
                            number of changes on the part of the Chinese Communist regime. At the
                            moment the sticking point was the ten Americans imprisoned. So long as
                            they were imprisoned we could not allow other Americans to visit despite
                            very strong pressures from our news-gathering agencies which have been
                            invited by Communist China.</p>
                        <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> said that <persName
                                corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName> had indicated that there
                            were failures on our part. I denied this in some detail and suggested
                            that he check with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGL1"
                                >Mehta</persName>.” (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                                >Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                                >Dulles</persName> Papers, General Memoranda of Conversation)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0481" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                <p>On December 18, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> discussed his
                    exchange with <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> at Gettysburg on the
                    question of China in a telephone conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                        >Dulles</persName>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Sec asked if they talked re Communist China and the Pres. said yes
                            and at considerable detail. The Pres. said we don’t use the word never
                            but until these things that are going on have been relieved there is no
                            sense talking about it. He said <persName corresp="#p_CE1"
                                >Chou</persName> said to him that so many have been released and
                            nothing has been done by us. The Pres. said the hell it hasn’t and
                            explained what had been done. The Sec said he talked to him Sunday and
                            said if they let the 10 go we would take a different position on
                            passports and that might break the logjam. The Pres. also spoke re
                            breaking the Armistice terms in Korea.” (Memorandum of a telephone
                            conversation by Bernau, December 18; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., White
                            House Telephone Conversations)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A memorandum of <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s conversation
                    with <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> on December 19 was prepared in
                    the White House, but a note on the source text reads: “Practically impossible to
                    hear the Prime Minister”. The identity of the person who prepared the memorandum
                    is not indicated on the source text. The section of the memorandum dealing with
                    China reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Prime Minister talked at length, mentioning the name of <persName
                                corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>. The President said that is
                            number one priority. He spoke of the incident of the invitation for
                            newspapermen to go over there, and our thought that, step by step, we
                            might have been able to reach some kind of modus vivendi.</p>
                        <p>“The President spoke of his conversations with <persName corresp="#p_CK1"
                                >Chiang Kai-shek</persName>. When he visited there right after the
                            War, he was impressed to hear everybody talking perfectly freely, and
                            that they seemed to like ‘having us around.’ They put the President in
                            the most beautiful quarters he has ever been in. There seemed no danger,
                            or no thought of any molestation or interference. The President said
                            that he, for one, was particularly shocked when we saw developing in the
                            country those terrible pictures of United States victims.</p>
                        <p>“The President said he would like to get our people over their currently
                            very adverse attitude toward Red China. They put Red China at the bottom
                            of the list, even below Russia, which he does not understand—but that it
                            is true. He thinks most of it is about the ten prisoners and the fact,
                            as he had told <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> the other
                            day, of the casualties suffered in Korea. Our people are sensitive—in
                            World War II, they thought that it was something that had to be fought.
                            He said he never heard discussed so much the theories of World War II as
                            of the casualties of Korea. So the President thinks the main thing from
                            our side is (a) the ten prisoners, and (b) Korea.</p>
                        <p>“With those things straightened out, we would of course naturally do
                            something with our public opinion here; secondly, we could do something,
                            as the President had said before, about sending newspapermen over there
                            who would begin to find out what they are thinking. There would then be
                            a flow of news coming back that would tend to ameliorate this uneasy
                            state of pandimonium. And <pb facs="0482" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                            there could, out of such a small achievement as this, spring something
                            very fine.</p>
                        <p>“But the President’s feeling, as of this moment, is that it is impossible
                            for us to take the first step. He said <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                                >Foster Dulles</persName> may have a different view, but that this
                            is his own feeling.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                <persName>Whitman</persName> File, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                                >Eisenhower</persName> Diaries)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
