<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-08-16T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-08-16T11:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <head>24. Telegram From Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="from">U. Alexis Johnson</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d24fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/8–1655. Confidential;
                                Priority.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-08-16T17:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">August 16,
                                        1955—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>490. As stated my 485<note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2"><persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> gave a brief, preliminary
                                report in telegram 485 from Geneva, August 16, on his meeting that
                                morning with <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 611.93/8–1155)</note> no visible
                            progress made today on fundamental issue of return of Americans.
                                <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> stuck firmly to his
                            previous position on cases being reviewed and we would promptly be
                            informed results those completed. He raised no objections to form <pb facs="0068" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> our draft agreed announcement
                            (mytel 463<note n="3" xml:id="d24fn3"><p>In telegram 463 from Geneva,
                                    August 15, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>
                                    transmitted the text of the draft agreed announcement which he
                                    planned to give <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> the
                                    next day. It was identical to the draft which he had proposed to
                                    the Department on August 13 (see <ref target="#d22fn2">footnote
                                        2, Document 22</ref>) except for revisions made in
                                    accordance with telegram 495, <ref target="#d23"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>. In the proposed U.S.
                                    statement, numbered paragraph 1 reads as follows:</p>
                                <p>“USA recognizes that Chinese nationals in US who desire return to
                                    China mainland are now entitled do so and declares that no
                                    Chinese national who desires depart US for China mainland is now
                                    being prevented from doing so. This includes all those Chinese
                                    nationals who were at one time prevented from departing US.”</p>
                                <p>Paragraph 2(a) reads as follows:</p>
                                <p>“If a Chinese national believes that contrary to declared policy
                                    of US he is encountering official obstruction in departure he
                                    may so inform Indian Embassy and Indian Embassy may, if desired
                                    by <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>, investigate facts and
                                    intervene on such national’s behalf with Government of US.”</p>
                                <p>“China mainland” had been substituted for “<gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>” in every case in which it
                                    signified location. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                    611.93/8–1555)</p></note>) and confined objections to para one,
                            pressing for substitution para one his draft<note n="4" xml:id="d24fn4">Proposed by <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> on August
                                11; see <ref target="#d16">Document 16</ref>.</note> and for
                            broadening scope para 2 (a) to include inquiries initiated by respective
                            governments. Only other point was substitution “China” for “China
                            mainland” to which I countered with substitution by People’s Republic of
                            China to which he made no definite reply. However he reserved right
                            further comment.</p>
                        <p>I again argued against broadening scope para 2 (a) as unnecessary and
                            pointed out direct mention of and discretion given <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> our draft that para. Discussion this
                            point inconclusive.</p>
                        <p>However discussion centered around two versions para one with much talk
                            from <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> about international law,
                            sovereignty, extraterritoriality, jurisdiction over foreigners, attempt
                            by US establish principle Americans not subject <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> law, reciprocal and bilateral nature their para one
                            which recognizes US jurisdiction over Chinese in US, they not asking us
                            exempt from US jurisdiction Chinese in US involved in crimes or having
                            unsettled debts, why should we ask them do so for Americans in China
                            etc.</p>
                        <p>In reply I disclaimed intention raise theoretical questions jurisdiction.
                            Our para one dealt with practical situation and we asked them say no
                            more than we said ourselves. Said I recognized their desire handle
                            matter within framework their law, para one our draft specifically
                            designed enable them to do so, was not something imposed but simply
                            statement what each government decided do within framework its
                            sovereignty and laws. <persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou</persName>’s
                            statement before talks led me believe would promptly and easily be done
                            with respect Americans. Puzzlement at time thus far consumed with no
                            results whatever on Americans. All I had were vague statements cases
                            being “reviewed”. Simultaneous release of flyers who had received
                            varying sentences pointed up what could be done when they wanted to (he
                                <pb facs="0069" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/> had previously alluded to
                            flyers) etc. In reply my specific questions as to what he objected in
                            para one our draft he indicated might be acceptable if second sentence
                            first para his draft added. I immediately rejected pointing out that as
                            far as Americans in China concerned this took away [garble]<note n="5" xml:id="d24fn5"><p><persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>’s
                                    detailed report of the meeting, which he sent in telegram 499
                                    from Geneva, August 16, reads at this point as follows:</p>
                                <p>“I pointed out second sentence his paragraph took away from
                                    American nationals everything granted them in rest of paragraph
                                    since American nationals prevented from departing China were
                                    described by him as involved in crimes or civil cases.”
                                    (Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/8–1655)</p></note>
                            two sentences our draft and still left Americans where they were when
                            these talks started. Said I held no brief for exact wording our para
                            one, what I was interested in was substance which I considered vital.
                            Willing consider any wording he might suggest with same substance. At
                            end long discussion these lines both tacitly agreed neither had anything
                            more to say and agreed meet Thursday with usual fencing as to who was
                            going to do most thinking over subject during interim.</p>
                        <p>At close this phase he said wished “raise another point” and brought up
                            “propaganda campaign” which had been “launched in order slander Chinese
                            people” etc. Since beginning talks <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>
                            “has repeatedly made clear its conciliatory attitude”. Questions
                            “mistreatment” raised. <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> could
                            “endlessly recount miserable treatment” captured Chinese in Korea,
                            campaign was having “adverse effects” talks here etc. I had clear
                            feeling he had received specific instructions make statement and that he
                            was somewhat reluctant do so. I deliberately showed anger and curtly
                            replied I did not understand his motive in raising [this point?].
                            Accounts I had seen were factual interviews with men released.<note n="6" xml:id="d24fn6"><p><persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> commented in telegram 526 to Geneva,
                                    August 16, marked “Personal for <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> from Secretary”, that he had the
                                    impression that the Chinese had intended to announce the release
                                    of the U.S. civilians promptly, expecting that this would create
                                    a wave of good feeling toward them, but that they had altered
                                    this policy because reports of their treatment of the fliers had
                                    created a wave of indignation. The message continues:</p>
                                <p>“<gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s should realize that
                                    whenever prisoners are returned there is inevitably initial wave
                                    of resentment as they tell their stories. This is a phase which
                                        <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s must live through
                                    and they do not get anywhere by postponing it. However, once the
                                    American civilians are out of China, then we may be compelled to
                                    alter our policy toward visitors to the China mainland because
                                    principal reason for deterring those visitors will have ceased,
                                    namely that we do not want more Americans to get in until it has
                                    been demonstrated that those now there can get out. Subject to
                                    possible restraint of Foreign Assets Control Regulations visits
                                    will then occur which would bring back reports which if facts
                                    justify may lead to a different judgment. I do not know whether
                                        <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s realize this
                                    possible sequence of events or whether you will want to intimate
                                    it to them in a very cautious way without of course any
                                    promises. In any event, it may be useful for you to know my
                                    thinking on this matter.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                    611.93/8–1655)</p></note> Our free press accounts not unique,
                            almost all released have told similar accounts. Fault was not with
                            accounts but with treatment that gave rise to accounts. These reports
                                <pb facs="0070" n="42" xml:id="pg_42"/> had raised anxiety in US
                            over Americans in China and made it all more important find early
                            resolution to problem. He was somewhat taken aback and endeavored smooth
                            atmosphere before we left.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">[<persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>]</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>