<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>248. Special National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d248</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">248</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="248"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d248">
                <head>248. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d248fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1"
                            >INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> Files. Secret.
                        According to a note on the cover sheet, “The following intelligence
                        organizations participated in the preparation of this estimate: The Central
                        Intelligence Agency and the intelligence organizations of the Departments of
                        State, the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and the Joint Staff”. All members
                        of the Intelligence Advisory Committee concurred in this estimate on April
                        9, 1957, except for the Atomic Energy Commission representative and the
                        Assistant Director, Federal Bureau of Investigation, who abstained because
                        the subject was outside of their jurisdiction. A map showing the military
                        balance in the Taiwan Strait area is not reproduced.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">SNIE 43–57</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 9, 1957</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">LIKELIHOOD OF MILITARY ACTION BY THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF
                        CHINA<note n="2" xml:id="d248fn2">The basic situation of the Government of
                        the Republic of China is considered in <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                        43–56, “The Prospects of the Government of the Republic of China” (9 October
                        1956). This estimate remains generally valid and covers Chinese Nationalist
                        military capabilities. [Footnote in the source text. For conclusions of
                            <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 43–56, see <ref target="#d213"
                            >Document 213</ref>.]</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To estimate the likelihood of military action by the Chinese Nationalists against
                    the mainland in the next year or so.</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusion</p>
                <p>1. We believe that the Chinese Nationalists are very unlikely to launch an
                    invasion or, in the absence of Chinese Communist provocation, to initiate other
                    major military action against the mainland in the next year or so. There may be
                    some increase in small scale raiding operations, to prevent stabilization of the
                    situation in the Taiwan Strait and to improve intelligence. Moreover, although
                    we believe it to be unlikely, the possibility cannot be excluded that the
                    Nationalists might attempt within the period of this estimate to embroil the US
                    in major hostilities against the Chinese Communists by a “one-shot” military
                    operation, short of invasion, but of a scale or nature calculated to cause
                    substantial Chinese Communist retaliation. (<hi rend="italic">Paras.
                    8–10</hi>)</p>
                <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                <p>2. The Government of the Republic of China (<gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>)
                    has consistently maintained, since its withdrawal to Taiwan in 1949, that its
                    primary objective is to regain control on the mainland and to eliminate the
                    Chinese Communist regime. Military and political action <pb facs="0544" n="516"
                        xml:id="pg_516"/> and planning on Taiwan continue to reflect the primary
                    concern of top Nationalist leaders with preparations for eventual return.
                    Although there probably are a number of Nationalist officials who have little
                    hope of a return to the mainland in the foreseeable future, the top leadership
                    not only maintain this hope, but appear to believe that both their claim to be
                    the government of China and their prospects for recovering the mainland will
                    diminish with prolonged confinement to Taiwan.</p>
                <p>3. There has been in recent months a new flurry of statements by top Nationalist
                    leaders on the subject of return to the mainland, emphasizing the combat
                    readiness of their armed forces. Although these statements have been more
                    numerous and somewhat more definite in tone than in recent years, they probably
                    have been inspired in part by a desire to refute Chinese Communist propaganda
                    alleging “negotiations” with Nationalist leaders on the future of Taiwan. In
                    addition, Nationalist leaders have indicated renewed interest in determining US
                    views on joint military action and have also shown greater awareness of the need
                    for determining the degree and extent of dissatisfaction on the mainland. The
                    Chinese Nationalist armed forces have made plans for large scale operations, but
                    such planning does not appear to go beyond normal staff activity, and there are
                    no indications at this time of any actual preparations for large scale
                    attack.</p>
                <p>4. The following factors exist which might tempt the Nationalists to take action
                    against the mainland over the next year ox so: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>The Nationalist leaders probably estimate that the rate of improvement
                            in their armed forces will level off as the <gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                                >MAP</gloss> program nears completion. Combat units presently have
                            most of their weapons, and major shortages exist only in logistical
                            support equipment. Furthermore, in the Nationalist view, the gradual
                            influx of Taiwanese into the armed forces could over a period of time
                            substantially reduce Nationalist capabilities against the mainland.
                            Finally, the Nationalists probably estimate that the effectiveness of
                            the Chinese Communist forces is increasing at a rapid rate as they
                            acquire better weapons, improve their logistic capabilities, and
                            increase their air and naval strength, and that the relative strength of
                            the Nationalist forces is progressively declining.<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d248fn3">The military capabilities of the Chinese Communists
                                are considered in <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 13–57,
                                “Communist China Through 1961” (19 March 1957). [Footnote in the
                                source text. For text of <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 13–57,
                                see <ref target="#d244">Document 244</ref>.]</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>The Nationalists probably also estimate that there is widespread
                            dissatisfaction with Communist rule among the Chinese people on the
                            mainland, which has been intensified by the recent socialization drive
                            and to some extent by developments in Eastern Europe.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Finally, the Nationalist leaders are concerned that increased pressure
                            throughout the world for greater acceptance of Peiping may <pb
                                facs="0545" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/> make the US unable or
                            unwilling to prevent the seating of the Peiping regime in the United
                            Nations, and may cause the US to support a stabilization of the
                            situation on a “two Chinas” basis.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>5. We estimate that by exercising their maximum capability and with an element of
                    surprise the Chinese Nationalists could establish a beachhead on the China
                    mainland, but without US assistance they could hold it for only a short time
                    against determined Communist counteraction. We believe that the top Nationalist
                    leaders probably make the same military estimate. We believe that under these
                    circumstances they will not attempt an invasion unless they are sure that it
                    will either (a) be accompanied by a large scale uprising of the Chinese people,
                    including substantial defections from the Chinese Communist armed forces, or (b)
                    have the active assistance and support of the US.</p>
                <p>6. The Chinese Nationalists are not likely, within the next year or so, to
                    consider either of these conditions satisfied. They are aware that
                    dissatisfaction on the mainland is not organized and directed, and they probably
                    estimate that an invasion attempt, during the period of this estimate, would not
                    trigger mass uprisings and defections on a scale sufficient to be of significant
                    assistance to them. Moreover, the Chinese Nationalists have almost certainly
                    concluded that the US will not agree to a joint military operation against the
                    mainland, at least under present conditions. We believe, therefore, that they
                    are unlikely to make a formal request of the US for such a joint operation, or
                    to take unilateral action in the hope or expectation of receiving direct US
                    military support. Under the terms of the exchange of notes pursuant to the
                    Mutual Defense Treaty of December 1954 the Government of the Republic of China
                    is committed to “joint agreement” with the US with regard to the “use of force”
                    from territory under its control except for “action of an emergency character
                    which is clearly an exercise of the inherent right of self-defense.” Nationalist
                    leaders almost certainly believe that their best chance of eliciting US support
                    would lie in making the hostilities appear to be Chinese Communist-initiated,
                    and they are fully aware that preparations for a major assault could not be
                    concealed from American eyes. Recently President <persName corresp="#p_CK1"
                        >Chiang</persName> again assured the US Ambassador in Taipei that his
                    government would not attempt a return to the mainland without prior consultation
                    with the US. The top Nationalist leaders, however, probably believe that any
                    Chinese Communist threatening move, such as a movement of combat aircraft to the
                    nearby coastal air fields, would justify counteraction within their emergency
                    right of self-defense.</p>
                <p>7. The possibility cannot be excluded that the Chinese Nationalists might attempt
                    to invade the mainland as a matter of desperation, <pb facs="0546" n="518"
                        xml:id="pg_518"/> if they felt that their position was deteriorating so
                    greatly as to threaten their existence. However, we foresee no events likely to
                    have this result within the period of this estimate; for example, even Japanese
                    recognition of Communist China or the seating of Communist China in the UNGA,
                    should either occur, would probably not drive the Chinese Nationalists to the
                    point of desperation, provided the US continued to give firm support to the
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>8. Accordingly, we conclude that the Chinese Nationalists are very unlikely to
                    launch an invasion, or, in the absence of Chinese Communist provocation, to
                    initiate other major military action against the mainland in the next year or
                    so. The chances of major Nationalist action would be increased if the Chinese
                    Communists were to become involved in hostilities in Korea (with or without
                    collusion between the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> and the <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>) or in Vietnam. However, we believe that,
                    unless such hostilities were accompanied by widespread uprisings on mainland
                    China or the Chinese Nationalists were convinced that the US would support and
                    assist them, the Nationalists probably would not even then undertake major
                    action.</p>
                <p>9. The Chinese Nationalists nevertheless possess the capability, and have
                    indicated an intention, to increase the number of small raids and probing
                    actions against the mainland. Such actions could be planned and launched without
                    prior knowledge of American observers. Motivation for increasing such operations
                    would be to prevent stabilization of the situation in the Taiwan Strait and to
                    improve intelligence relating to the coastal areas of the mainland. We believe
                    that over the next year, assuming the present degree of US controls, there may
                    be some increase in small scale raiding operations for these purposes.</p>
                <p>10. The Chinese Nationalists still believe that their best chance for a
                    successful return to the mainland (short of an internal collapse of the Chinese
                    Communist regime) lies in a war between the US and Communist China. We do not
                    believe the Nationalists would consider that small scale operations would cause
                    the Chinese Communists to hit back in such force as to invoke the <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>–US Defense Treaty, nor do we believe that the
                    Nationalists would conduct any series of larger operations in the face of US
                    disapproval. Although we believe it an unlikely course of action, the
                    possibility cannot be excluded that the Nationalists might attempt within the
                    period of this estimate to embroil the US in major hostilities against the
                    Chinese Communists by a “one-shot” military operation, short of invasion, but of
                    a scale or nature calculated to cause substantial Chinese Communist
                    retaliation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
