<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>298. Telegram From the Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (Johnson) to the ) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-11-22T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-11-22T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfZWpZzigwQIfjx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002653"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airline</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-11-22T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-11-22T07:00:00-05:00" n="298"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                <head>298. Telegram From the Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (<persName
                        corresp="#p_JUA1" type="from">Johnson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d298fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.93/11–2257. Confidential; Priority; Limit Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Prague</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-11-22T13:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 22, 1957—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>316. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 182.<note n="2" xml:id="d298fn2"
                        >Telegram 182 to Prague, November 21, invited <persName corresp="#p_JUA1"
                            >Johnson</persName>’s comments on three alternative methods of
                        continuing the talks with the Chinese: “1) Beam meet with <persName
                            corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> in Warsaw, 2) <persName
                            corresp="#p_RKL1">Rankin</persName> commute Geneva from Belgrade
                        following assignment there, 3) talks be continued at lower level and
                        conducted by <persName>Martin</persName> commuting to Geneva”. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</note> From substantive standpoint favor
                    alternative which would designate another officer of ambassador rank for
                    continuation talks at Geneva. However, suggest <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1"
                        >ChiCom</gloss>s may identify <persName corresp="#p_RKL1">Rankin</persName>
                    with <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> to degree that would tend to prejudice
                    his negotiations if and when <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s may
                    shift from present attitude. Therefore, suggest possibility
                        <persName>Bonbright</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d298fn3">
                        <persName>James C. H. Bonbright</persName>, Ambassador in Portugal.</note>
                    commuting Geneva from Lisbon. If this not feasible favor Beam meeting <persName
                        corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> in Warsaw. This would, of course, require
                        <persName>Martin</persName> commute London–Warsaw (this appears practicable
                    from airline schedules available here) and preferably assignment Dexter to
                    Warsaw. If this done, believe we should also suggest to <gloss
                        target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s alternative of
                        <persName>Martin</persName> meeting at Geneva with <gloss
                        target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss> representative on understanding
                    consideration would be given again designating an ambassador if and when it
                    appeared desirable.</p>
                <p>Must anticipate <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> will require
                    instructions before replying to me on any alternative that lowers level talks or
                    moves them from Geneva. In this event <persName>Martin</persName> could remain
                    at or return to Geneva to receive their reply and make agreement, including
                    public announcement, for next meeting. In such case we could simply state
                    following December 12 meeting that date next meeting will subsequently be
                    announced. In event I just inform <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Wang</persName> of
                    designation new ambassador for subsequent meetings, this could be included in
                    announcement following meeting without making reference to my transfer from
                    Prague unless that is otherwise publicly known at time. (I <pb facs="0670"
                        n="642" xml:id="pg_642"/> would prefer to postpone announcement my transfer
                    from Prague until very shortly before my departure.)</p>
                <p>In any event would appreciate December 12 meeting instructions also covering
                    publicity aspects.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
