<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-07-24T08:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-07-24T08:35:00-05:00" n="281" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d281">
                        <head>281. Telegram 6877 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in
                                Zaire</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d281fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, RG 59, Records of Joseph Sisco, 1951–1976, Entry
                                5405, Box 22, Angola. Secret; Niact Immediate; Nodis;
                                Cherokee.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d281fn2">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VSB1">Vance</persName> summarized his discussion
                                with President <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName>
                                regarding military assistance. <persName corresp="#p_VSB1">Vance</persName> added that <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> did not regard offered U.S. assistance as
                                adequate to the situation.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Kinshasa</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-07-24T13:35:00+00:00">July 24, 1975, 1335Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_VSB1">Vance</persName> Mission: Fourth Meeting
                                With <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> July 23</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>Ref:</head>
                            <item>State 172996</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. Following receipt reftel, I telephoned <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> and arranged to see him again evening July 23. He
                            invited me to stay for dinner with the family, following which we had
                            most useful talk on status of our joint planning for assistance to
                            Angola.</p>
                        <p>2. I told <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> that we had
                            reviewed and forwarded to Washington the list of equipment replacement
                            requirements given US by his generals as well as the categories of
                            equipment they had designated as being most urgently needed. I said I
                            had this morning received instruction reiterating the need to put
                            together a program not to exceed $6 million, although we did not exclude
                            the possibility of some additional assistance now. In explaining this
                            limitation I observed that our ability to help was subject to certain
                            obvious considerations, notably the limitation on funds available, the
                            cost and time required for shipment, and the risk of leaks that arises
                            if large quantities of materiel are sent all at once. I stressed the
                            importance of the last point, noting the need to move in such a way <pb facs="d281-02" n="2" xml:id="d281-02"/> as to avoid exposure, which
                            could seriously harm our efforts to help. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> said he understood these considerations, but that
                            he considered that much less than the equipment from five of his
                            para-battalions (four for Roberto and one for Savimbi) would not rpt not
                            redress the balance. He also reiterated his hope that the items already
                            sent Angola from his mobilization reserve as well as the key items from
                            his paratroops which we cannot supply in the present emergency program
                            would be replaced subsequently.</p>
                        <p>3. I said it was important that I provide Washington with as precise a
                            view as possible of his order of priorities within the broad priority
                            categories of equipment his generals had given us. On his instruction,
                            it is clear. This so we could determine the most useful types of
                            assistance both for a $6 million program and for any aid we might be
                            able to provide above that. I then reviewed with <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> the list provided by the
                            generals and he indicated how he would refine his relative priorities.
                            his most urgent need remains 5,000 M–16 rifles with one–two months
                            ammunition, all of which he hopes can be air shipped to Zaire as soon as
                            possible. His second priority is anti-tank guns to replace more than has
                            already been shipped south to counter the Soviet-supplied armored
                            vehicles he said were having devastating effect on the FNLA. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> went on to designate a number
                            of other priority requirements from the list and indicated which should
                            be shipped by air and which by sea. We have incorporated his views both
                            in a $5 million package and in a larger package which we have developed
                            as requested reftel and are sending by separate telegrams [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>].</p>
                        <p>4. In discussing Zairian military aid to Angola, I took the occasion to
                            remind <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> about US
                            restrictions on the transfer from one country to another of equipment (I
                            had in mind his paratroopers have some old MAP equipment.) supplied
                            under MAP. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> said he
                            understood this and reiterated his assurance that no US materiel, no
                            matter how old it might be, would be sent to Angola.</p>
                        <p>5. [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] In this <pb facs="d281-03" n="3" xml:id="d281-03"/> regard, <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> said he had Amin’s assurance
                            that, as Chairman of the forthcoming OAU summit, he would see to it that
                            the Soviets are appropriately taken to task at the meeting for their
                            intervention in Angola. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName>
                            intends also to work behind the scenes there to encourage other such
                            criticism.</p>
                        <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> did not have much news
                            from Angola. However, he was concerned by reports that two more Soviet
                            vessels have delivered military equipment to the MPLA. I noted reports I
                            had seen recently reflecting adversely on the conduct of certain FNLA
                            officials and troops in Luanda. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> acknowledged this has been a problem, and said he
                            would admonish Roberto again on this matter.</p>
                        <p>7. I told <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> that I intended
                            to return Washington July 25 and would press for earliest possible
                            decision. <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> reiterated
                            need for urgent action. “The Soviets are continuing to send arms into
                            Angola,” he said, “while we are sitting here talking.”</p>
                        <p>8. Recommendation: As noted para 3, we are sending separately the
                            composition of two possible packages: one which meets the current $6
                            million ceiling, and the other which incorporates <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName>’s most urgent minimum
                            requirements and, according our rough estimates, amounts to $10 to $12
                            million. I wish to make clear <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> would not rpt not regard what we could send under
                            the $6 million program as enough to redress the balance in Angola. As it
                            is important that we start to move just as soon as possible, I urge that
                            Washington agencies give top priority to final reviewing and costing out
                            of both packages to permit a decision in the next few days on what can
                            be our highest level. I urge that the decision be in favor of a larger
                            than six million dollar program so that we will have a real impact on
                            Angolan situation.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>Andrew</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>