<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>170. Memorandum From Michael Guhin of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the Assistant to the President for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recm0kKdhKGPVOMsn" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022963"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemicals</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="chemical-and-bacteriological-warfare"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007509"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemical weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <head>170. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_GMA1" type="from">Michael
                        Guhin</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the Assistant to
                    the President for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d170fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 310, Subject Files, Chemical,
                        Biological Warfare (Toxins, etc.) Vol. I. Top Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. Sent for information. A stamped
                        notation on the memorandum indicates <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> saw it December 20. The memorandum was sent
                        through Behr.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d170fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_GMA1">Guhin</persName> briefed <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on the toxins issue. <persName
                            corresp="#p_GMA1">Guhin</persName> included the definition of “toxin”,
                        an outline of the current toxins program, and those arguments in favor and
                        opposed to maintaining a complete toxin program. He concluded with a
                        commentary on the ways in which the information given fit into the larger
                        international discussion of the Geneva Conference and the <gloss
                            target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Draft Convention.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-12-18"
                        >December 18, 1969</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>The Toxins Issue</item>
                </list>
                <p>A. <hi rend="underline">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The issue here arises because toxins <hi rend="underline">are chemicals</hi>
                    (non-living matter which does not multiply itself) which <hi rend="underline"
                        >are produced</hi> by <hi rend="underline">biological processes</hi> from
                    living organisms (i.e., fermentation). DOD has publicly defined toxins as
                    chemicals. The definition is technically correct and accords with the 14-Nation
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Experts’ Report (1 July 1969), the more
                    recent World Health Organization (WHO) Report on chemical and biological weapons
                    (21 November 1969), and <gloss target="#t_OST1">OST</gloss>’s understanding. The
                    only technical dividing line is that biologicals are living and replicate and
                    chemicals do not.</p>
                <p>The WHO Report qualifies its definition somewhat: “In some discussion… such
                    toxins are classified as biological agents because the technology of their
                    production resembles that of biological agents rather than that of chemical
                    agents.” Until last year, toxins were placed in the U.S. biological program
                    category only because of the origin of toxins and the technology of
                    production.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="underline">issue is not</hi> whether toxins should come under the
                    chemical warfare program or the biological research program, as this would only
                    confuse the established technical definition.</p>
                <p>Keeping the definition of toxins as chemicals, <hi rend="underline">the real
                        issue is</hi> what should the toxin program be when considered on its own
                    merits as a separate weapons system, and how would this relate to the
                    President’s decisions and our association with the principles and objectives of
                    the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Draft Convention.</p>
                <pb facs="d170-02" n="2" xml:id="d170-02"/>
                <p>B. <hi rend="underline">Current Toxin Program</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The current toxin program is not large and there is now no production other than
                    for <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss>. Stockpiles consist of one lethal
                    botulinum toxin (23,000 cartridges and other special devices), a few hundred
                    pounds of an incapacitant (staphylococcal enterotoxin, PG) which is not yet
                    standardized, and very small research quantities of shellfish poison and snake
                    venom.</p>
                <p>From the Joint Staff point of view, the main interest seems to be the promising
                    incapacitant (PG) now in research and development. In light of recent tests,
                    Joint Staff hopes to be able to standardize and produce this incapacitant.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="underline">Pros and Cons</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">The main arguments for keeping a complete toxin program
                        are:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Toxins are considered chemicals and are defined as such by the <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Report and the WHO Report.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Our options for the production of toxins and associated weapons system
                        development should not be restricted because toxins are chemicals.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The most promising incapacitant (12–36 days) in <gloss target="#t_RD1"
                            >R&amp;D</gloss> is a toxin (PG), and without PG the U.S. may not be
                        able to field an incapacitating capability in the near future.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Some toxins can now be synthesized and, therefore, it may be possible to
                        develop an effective toxin capability without any biological production
                        process.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">The main arguments for confining our toxin program to
                            <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> for defensive purposes are:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Toxins are technically chemicals, but because of the origin of toxins and
                        their production technology, a complete toxin program would appear to be
                        circumvention of the decision that our biological programs will be confined
                        to <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> for defensive purposes only and to
                        protect against technological surprise.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Toxins have no relation whatsoever with the development of binary weapons.
                        [This position usually appears in conjunction with <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                            >OSD</gloss>’s recommendation, on 8 October 1969, that the chemical
                        warfare program (offensive aspects) should concentrate entirely on <gloss
                            target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> of binary weapons.]</item>
                    <pb facs="d170-03" n="3" xml:id="d170-03"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>While the lethal toxin we now have is more toxic than nerve agents before
                        dissemination as a weapon, it is not more effective after dissemination
                        because it decays rapidly and is unstable.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Nerve agents are more militarily effective because lethal and
                        incapacitating toxins act through the respiratory system and require only a
                        mask for defense and not full protective clothing. Moreover, the military
                        value of incapacitants in retaliation is questionable.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The British have publicly stated (North Atlantic Council Meeting, 2 July
                        1969) that their Draft Convention would prohibit <hi rend="underline">the
                            manufacture</hi> of toxins. (The production of toxins in more than
                        research quantities would require a Pine Bluff-type facility, unless we were
                        able to develop an effective synthesized toxin.)</item>
                </list>
                <p>D. <hi rend="underline">Comment</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In light of the discussions which will be coming in Geneva (Conference of the
                    Committee on Disarmament), and our association with the principles and
                    objectives of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Draft Convention, we cannot
                    avoid confronting the question. We should avoid the semantic problem and affirm
                    the definition of toxins as chemicals. (No agency disagrees with the
                    definition.) The question of the extent of the U.S. toxin program should then be
                    decided on the basis of their relative utility as chemical weapons and whether
                    or not their stockpiling contributes to national security. Since <gloss
                        target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 35 calls for an annual review of our programs
                    by the Under Secretaries Committee, this problem might be considered by that
                    body.</p>
                <p>Whatever the decisions on this matter, I believe that the primary objective
                    should be to avoid any unnecessary erosion of the President’s announced
                    decisions on chemical warfare and biological research.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
