<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                        <head>182. Memorandum From the Director of the U.S. Information Agency
                                (<persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1" type="from">Shakespeare</persName>) to
                            the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d182fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files
                                (H-Files), Box H–26, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meeting
                                2/11/70, Policy on Toxins. Secret. The attachment is not
                                published.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d182fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1">Shakespeare</persName> commented on the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 85 report on toxin policy.
                                He emphasized the importance of maintaining the credibility of the
                                President’s November 25 renunciation of biological weapons, for fear
                                it could potentially damage his reputation domestically and
                                internationally. Then outlined those points in the study he believed
                                would be helpful in maintaining that credibility.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1970-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" notBefore="1970-02-04T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>U.S. Policy on Toxins (<gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>
                                85)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The statement of the arguments for and against the three options in
                                <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 85 represents an improvement
                            in clarity. The new public affairs rationale for each option fills a
                            need that was overlooked in the earlier version of the paper and gives a
                            more realistic picture of the problems and advantages of each of the
                            three alternative positions. I feel that the public affairs rationales
                            contain valid points and helpful arguments but do not give enough
                            attention to the drawbacks or probable negative public reaction that
                            would follow the adoption of either Option I or II and that certain
                            additional factors might usefully be considered.</p>
                        <p>In considering the public treatment of this subject, the first aim should
                            be to maintain the credibility of the President’s November 25
                            renunciation of biological weapons and if possible to extend the wide
                            and highly favorable momentum his statement produced at home and
                            overseas (see attached summary of foreign media reaction).</p>
                        <p>First, an assessment of the general problem: The toxins issue while
                            presently a “sleeper” could grow, once attention is focused on it, into
                            a major public controversy which could damage the President’s reputation
                            at home and abroad. The repugnance with which the public regard such
                            agents—whether they are classified as chemical or biological—is so great
                            that technical explanations and attempts to justify rationally their
                            possible military use would fall mainly upon deaf ears.</p>
                        <pb facs="d182-02" n="2" xml:id="d182-02"/>
                        <p>Public awareness of toxins as possible military weapons is very limited
                            at the moment, but it could rapidly increase if critics at home and
                            abroad were to find a means of attacking the Government through this
                            issue. The groundwork has been laid by several press stories
                            highlighting toxins as a fearful and unsolved problem. A major public
                            controversy over toxins might well occur during the Senate hearings on
                            the Geneva Protocol.</p>
                        <p>Our position reserving the right to use riot control agents and
                            herbicides has already drawn fire from some members of the Senate, and
                            if the decision is made to reserve the option to develop and use toxins
                            we should be prepared for sharp and emotional criticism from both
                            Congress and the press. Thus, our opponents abroad would be handed not
                            only an issue but arguments voiced by American legislators and
                            publications.</p>
                        <p>The revised paper points out that the principal drawback of Option I from
                            the public affairs standpoint would (not could) be the accusation that
                            in spite of the President’s renunciation of all biological weapons the
                            U.S. in effect was retaining them under a different label. We should
                            expect charges that we were opening a major loophole in the November 25
                            statement after second thoughts about the value of toxins as weapons.
                            The impression would be either that the government regretted the
                            original renunciation of biological weapons or intended all along to
                            water it down after the fact.</p>
                        <p>The argument over whether toxins are chemical or biological is not
                            meaningful to the public nor would it be effective in overcoming public
                            resistance to them. To the extent there is public awareness, the public
                            only knows and cares that toxins, however produced, can cause swift and
                            fatal diseases. In fact, to insist that toxins are chemical (and
                            therefore admissible) in the face of conflicting public usage would
                            create an impression of trickery. (This does not dispute the fact that
                            toxins are technically chemical and that most experts agree on this. We
                            are <pb facs="d182-03" n="3" xml:id="d182-03"/> faced with the fact that
                            public usage does not coincide: the two dictionaries in most common use
                            in the U.S., Webster’s <hi rend="underline">Collegiate</hi> and
                            Webster’s <hi rend="underline">New World</hi>, define them in biological
                            terms, as does the famous <hi rend="underline">Petit Larousse</hi> in
                            France.) To justify the development and military use of toxins on the
                            ground that they were chemicals would most likely only reinforce the
                            impression that we were playing a version of the shell game.</p>
                        <p>For these reasons, <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> believes that
                            Option I would be costly and damaging to the reputation of the
                            government and highly undesirable from the public affairs
                            standpoint.</p>
                        <p>In dealing with public attitudes the best would be Option III, since
                            this, by clearly including toxins with the renounced biological weapons,
                            would raise no issue of duplicity and would carry here and abroad a
                            forthright ring of honest follow-through on the President’s
                            announcement.</p>
                        <p>The seven points mentioned on pp. 23–24 of the revised paper would be
                            essential in any public defense of Option II. (We assume that point four
                            should read “… defensive <hi rend="underline">research</hi> purposes” as
                            in point seven, p. 27.) I suggest our public position under Option II
                            concerning chemically synthesized toxins might be better defended by
                            explaining initially that: 1) At the present state of scientific
                            knowledge toxins are produced through biological not chemical processes;
                            therefore our renunciation of biologically produced toxins includes all
                            forms that have been produced. 2) If it should become possible to
                            synthesize toxins chemically this would constitute a new situation which
                            the U.S. would naturally review at that time. This explanation would be
                            understood by the public, and although it might not answer all concerns
                            it would be accepted, I believe.</p>
                        <p>The three points suggested on p. 24 of the paper could be used to reply
                            to any journalists who wished to pursue technical <pb facs="d182-04" n="4" xml:id="d182-04"/> aspects of the subject further, although
                            they do not provide an answer to the probable question whether the U.S.
                            has a research and development program to achieve the chemical
                            production of toxins. Depending upon the facts of the matter, our good
                            faith might still be called into question.</p>
                        <closer><signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SFJJ1">Frank Shakespeare</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>