<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>292. Journal Entry by the Chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission
                    (Seaborg))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="compound-subject" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002599"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Environmental</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="292"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                <head>292. Journal Entry by the Chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SGT1">Seaborg</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d292fn1">Source: Journal of <persName corresp="#p_SGT1">Glenn T.
                            Seaborg</persName>, vol. 20, pp. 304, 307, 309. No classification
                        marking.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d292fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGT1">Seaborg</persName> kept his own record of the
                        discussion concerning the <gloss target="#t_PNE1">PNE</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_LTBT1">LTBT</gloss> at the October 14 <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Under Secretaries meeting. This entry also includes a
                        record of his discussion with Under Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> following the meeting.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-10-14"
                        >October 14, 1969</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to the October 14 Under Secretaries
                    Meeting]</p>
                <p>At 4:10 p.m. I attended a meeting at the State Department of the Under
                    Secretaries Committee. Present were: Chairman <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Elliot
                        L. Richardson</persName>, Jack Stevenson, <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Herman
                        Pollack</persName>, Nelson Sievering, <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">Arthur A.
                        Hartman</persName>, Biltchik, and Wolfgang Lehmann of the State Department;
                    General Robert E. Cushman and Peter Jessup of the CIA; <persName
                        corresp="#p_BCRM1">Colonel Robert M. Behr</persName> of the <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff; <persName corresp="#p_WEG1">General
                        Earle Wheeler</persName> and Major General Demler of the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>; Henry Loomis of the <gloss target="#t_USIA1"
                        >USIA</gloss>: <persName corresp="#p_PDM1">David Packard</persName> of the
                        <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>; Commissioner Theos Thompson, John
                    Kelly, and Allan Labowitz of the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>; <persName
                        corresp="#p_SGC1">Gerard C. Smith</persName> of the <gloss target="#t_ACDA1"
                        >ACDA</gloss>; <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">James Schlesinger</persName> of
                    the <gloss target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss>; and Hubert Heffner and David Freeman of
                    the Office of Science and Technology. The meeting opened with <persName
                        corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> asking me to summarize the
                    excavation shots that are required before the decision can be made as to whether
                    nuclear methods can be applied to the digging of a second canal across the
                    Isthmus. I said that only two shots, the STURTEVANT and the YAWL would be
                    required. The STURTEVANT shot is ready for execution next month, whereas the
                    YAWL shot could be executed next spring. In addition, the excavation program <pb
                        facs="d292-02" n="2" xml:id="d292-02"/> contemplates two other experiments,
                    the GALLEY experiment, which would be some seven shots about a year from now,
                    and the GONDOLA experiment to be conducted in a different medium—a wet clay
                    shale medium—scheduled for the spring of 1971. I emphasized, however, that only
                    the first two shots are required in order to give information for a decision on
                    the canal across the Isthmus.</p>
                <p>The discussion then turned to the question of the interpretation of the Limited
                    Test Ban Treaty in the matter of detectable amounts as opposed to a de minimis
                    interpretation. In order to compare the impending STURTEVANT shot with the
                    SCHOONER experiment I handed out and explained the attached sheet. I emphasized
                    the low level of the radioactivity involved and pointed out that even the
                    background in our meeting room amounted to some 100 picocuries per cubic meter,
                    much greater than the levels we expect at the Canadian border from the
                    STURTEVANT shot. I also pointed out how much larger the maximum permissible
                    concentration of tungsten-187 (the main isotope that will be released in the
                    STURTEVANT experiment) is than the expected level to be released is. There was a
                    great deal of discussion as to the interpretation of the Limited Test Ban Treaty
                    that equates a violation with the ability to detect any radioactivity at all at
                    the border. I emphasized that I didn’t think this is a reasonable interpretation
                    of the Limited Test Ban Treaty and suggested that the phrase, “radioactive
                    debris,” or the Russian translation of this phrase, “radioactive fallout,”
                    implied more than an insignificant detectable amount at the border.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> asked one of the State
                    Department lawyers present, Jack Stevenson, if my interpretation is viable, and
                    he indicated that this is probably the best connotation that could be put on any
                    concept that allows higher levels at the extremely small detectable levels. I
                    said that I believe that the Limited Test Ban Treaty would never have been
                    passed by the Senate (due to opposition by people like Senators Anderson and
                    Jackson) if I hadn’t testified that I thought excavation shots (larger than
                    STURTEVANT) could be carried out under a reasonable interpretation of its
                    provisions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PDM1">Packard</persName> argued for an immediate approval
                    of the STURTEVANT event on the basis that we shouldn’t give in to the
                    unreasonable attitudes and the public clamor against testing and <persName
                        corresp="#p_WEG1">Wheeler</persName> supported him in this. Heffner and
                    others raised the issue of increasing public pressures against activities that
                    are thought to create environmental hazards. He expressed the view that this
                    pressure would become extremely great in the case of STURTEVANT. I agreed with
                    him that this is a serious problem and said that I consider it more serious in
                    the case of STURTEVANT than the question of the interpretation of the Limited
                    Test Ban Treaty. Smith expressed doubt that we should go ahead with the
                    STURTEVANT shot and recalled that the study group had suggested that it be
                    handled separately and that we limit the present recommendation in the suggested
                    draft report to the President, which is concerned primarily with the derivation
                    of an interpretation to the Limited Test Ban Treaty. I expressed agreement with
                    that position and suggested that there are some recommendations in the draft
                    memorandum, such as the recommendation that we resume our bilateral technical
                    talks with the U.S.S.R. at an early date, which the <gloss target="#t_AEC1"
                        >AEC</gloss> would like to see implemented as soon as possible. <persName
                        corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> indicated that he thought it would
                    be possible to go ahead <pb facs="d292-03" n="3" xml:id="d292-03"/> with the
                    bilateral technical talks with the U.S.S.R. without further approval from the
                    President and there seemed to be general agreement on this. <persName
                        corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> also expressed the view that since
                    the draft memorandum to the President (copy attached) doesn’t recommend any
                    particular position, it is doubtful that it should be sent to the President. He
                    suggested instead that staff might restructure the memo so that the main courses
                    of action recommended could be authorized without involvement of the President.
                    These courses of action are: (1) that the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                    will promptly complete the development of the data necessary to establish
                    objective criteria for acceptable levels of radioactivity, (2) on the basis of
                    this, an attempt will be made to find an agreed upon interagency position that
                    will allow a determination of what levels of radioactivity are consistent with
                    the Limited Test Ban Treaty, and (3) resumption of the bilateral technical talks
                    with the U.S.S.R. will be undertaken at an early date.</p>
                <p>At 5:45 p.m. I had a conversation with Under Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_REL1">Elliot L. Richardson</persName> in his office. I told him
                    that I thought the matter of domestic public acceptance of the STURTEVANT shot
                    is more important than the interpretation of the Limited Test Ban Treaty. I
                    thought that a smaller group should discuss this and then perhaps discuss it
                    with the President. I pointed out that in the case of the MILROW and RULISON
                    shots it had been touch and go up to the very end and that the President had
                    been involved in the final decision to go ahead at the very last moment in the
                    case of the MILROW shot. I said that I thought this would also be the case with
                    the STURTEVANT shot and that if the pressure became so great that it became
                    necessary for the President to cancel the shot at the last moment, this would do
                    great harm to both the President and the Plowshare program. I said I thought,
                    therefore, that these hazards should be frankly discussed with the President so
                    that, if he decides to go forward despite the tremendous public pressures that
                    will build up, we would be in a position of not being subject to a last minute
                    cancellation, which would do so much harm to all concerned.</p>
                <p>I said that I had particularly in mind protecting the President on this matter,
                    and that I certainly wouldn’t push for carrying out the STURTEVANT experiment if
                    an examination of these questions of public pressures should make it seem
                    unwise. I pointed out that it could still be conducted as a completely contained
                    device development test as was originally planned if we wanted to go ahead on
                    this basis. <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> seemed quite
                    impressed by these arguments and suggested that a paper might be drawn up
                    summarizing this situation by a small group, including a representative of his
                    office, the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_ACDA1"
                        >ACDA</gloss>, and the <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>. He will take
                    steps to have this done.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to the October 14 Under Secretaries
                    Meeting]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
