<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>339. Telegram 226160 From the Department of State to the to the Mission to
                    the United Nations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d339</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">339</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament Conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="339"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d339">
                <head>339. Telegram 226160 From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Mission to the United Nations</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d339fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–1973, DEF 18–3.
                        Confidential; Immediate. It was repeated to Bonn, Moscow, USMission Geneva,
                        U.S. Delegation to <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>, and USNATO.
                        Drafted by Neidle (<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>/UNP); cleared by Day
                            (<gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss>), McNutt (LM/DMS), Armitage and
                        McIntyre (UNP), <persName corresp="#p_MJJ2">Martin</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>), and Skoug (<gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                            >EUR</gloss>/GER); and approved by Herz (<gloss target="#t_IO1"
                            >IO</gloss>).</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d339fn2">The telegram provided instructions
                        to the U.S. delegation to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to vote
                        affirmatively to the Soviet draft resolution for a world disarmament
                        conference.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-12-16"
                        >December 16, 1971</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>World Disarmament Conference Resolution: Voting Instructions</item>
                </list>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF:</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 5087</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Appreciate USDel’s success in obtaining change in title of 27th GA agenda
                        item in of para 4 to “World Disarmament Conference.” In our view this
                        satisfactorily concludes our effort to avoid commitment in res to hold
                            <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Despite our continued misgivings about “all States” references in res, we
                        feel balance of considerations involved indicates affirmative <gloss
                            target="#t_US1">US</gloss> vote. USDel is so instructed.</item>
                    <pb facs="d339-02" n="2" xml:id="d339-02"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>If Soviet or other key del asserts that res represents commitment to hold
                                <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss>, you may, at your discretion,
                            draw on following in explaining <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            vote:</p>
                        <p>QTE Mr. President, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Delegation is
                            able to support the present draft resolution because in our view it is
                            consistent with the criteria set out by Ambassador PHILLIPS last month.
                            The resolution leaves the question of a possible world disarmament
                            conference open for consideration and does not prejudge the outcome of
                            that consideration. It does not attempt to prescribe when or in what
                            circumstances such a conference might be held.</p>
                        <p>As the Assembly is aware, we have expressed doubt regarding the
                            prospective usefulness of a <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss>. Our
                            doubts remain. However, we are of course prepared to take part in the
                            further consideration called for in the resolution before us, on which
                            the United States is casting (has cast) an affirmative vote. UNQTE</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="d339-03" n="3" xml:id="d339-03"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>We share <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> concern to avoid floor
                        argument over participation question and therefore we would not wish to
                        stimulate possible Soviet rejoinder to any <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                        statement on subject. However, if Soviets or others take initiative in
                        asserting specifically that res has disposed of question of participation in
                            <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss> or that “open to all states” means
                        that the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> or other unrecognized
                        authorities would attend a <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss>, you should
                        make brief statement in reply along following lines: BEGIN QTE I would like
                        to state that in our view operative paragraph 2 of the resolution does not
                        set forth an exhaustive list of the topics which might be addressed in
                        further consideration of a <gloss target="#t_WDC1">WDC</gloss>; we, for
                        example, may wish to comment on additional aspects of the matter.
                        Specifically, the question of the scope of such a conference and of
                        participation are complex having many aspects on which different states
                        might wish to express various views about a variety of situations. They will
                        be able to do so under the present resolution. UNQTE</item>
                    <pb facs="d339-04" n="4" xml:id="d339-04"/>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In unlikely event Soviets or others asset assert specifically that “all
                        states” formula means Vienna Formula states plus <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                            >GDR</gloss>, North Korea and NVN, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Del
                        should say that in his view resolution makes no such determination.</item>
                </list>
                <p>END</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
