<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="BL–20"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="bl_d20">
                <head>BL–20. Memorandum from the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                    Affairs (Rubottom) to the Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                        (Dillon)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="bl_d20fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Central Files, 398.13/3–1359. Confidential. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1959-03-13">March 13, 1959</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Bolivia/<gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> Standby Agreement</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you know, the former <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss>/<gloss
                        target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> standby agreement expired on February 28. The
                    recently negotiated new agreement has not been recommended to the Fund Board
                    because of failure of the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> thus far to live
                    up to the terms offered in its Letter of Intent on the crucial miners
                    wage/commissary price issue.<note n="2" xml:id="bl_d20fn2">After problems arose
                        between the Bolivian Government and the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>
                        relating to the provision of the Government’s Letter of Intent of October 4,
                        1958, Bolivia submitted a new Letter of Intent, dated January 26, but
                        actually signed on January 27, 1959. A photostatic copy of the new Letter
                        was transmitted to the Department of State under cover of despatch 644 from
                        La Paz, January 23, 1959, not printed; 398.13/1–2859.</note> In the absence
                    of an agreement <pb facs="0268" n="180" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_180"/> with
                    the Fund, we have been withholding payments to the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1"
                        >GOB</gloss>. The last payment was made on February 4.</p>
                <p>It has long been our policy to stand behind the Fund on matters of these kinds so
                    as to avoid placing ourselves in the position of dictating economic terms which
                    have major domestic political implications in foreign countries. We have
                    supported the Fund on this issue because we have felt it crucial to the success
                    of the stabilization program this year. Nevertheless, the situation has changed
                    drastically because of recent developments in Bolivia and as of today, the
                    possibility that the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> would be able to
                    obtain agreement with the miners on terms satisfactory to the Fund appears
                    remote indeed. The Government is not only facing a miners’ strike but the
                    possibility of a general strike in sympathy with the miners. This whole
                    situation is fraught with danger and could very well jeopardize the lives of
                    Americans in Bolivia.</p>
                <p>It is my firm belief that the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> has made a
                    maximum reasonable effort to obtain terms acceptable to the Fund and that we
                    cannot expect it to do more than this. I think, therefore, we should endeavour
                    to induce the Fund to agree to accept the last offer made by the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> (20% wage increase plus phasing out of
                    commissary subsidies over 120 days), if this is attainable, or the best possible
                    terms on which the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> can achieve a settlement
                    with the miners. This should reduce the tension in the country and allow us
                    opportunity for a calm evaluation of the effects of such a settlement on the
                    stabilization effort and on <pb facs="bl_d20-2" n="2" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="bl_d20-2"/> the future conduct of our program. Needless to say, it
                    might also allow a breathing space in which we could make personnel adjustments
                    so as to reduce U.S. exposure in the country. I believe, therefore, that it
                    would be highly advisable for you to counsel the Fund to take action along these
                    lines and not to throw in the sponge and withdraw their association with the
                    Bolivian Government.</p>
                <p>The withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> participation in the
                    over-all Bolivian program would have repercussions far beyond the boundaries of
                    that country and might, especially if the United States decides that it must
                    continue the aid program, encourage other countries to take a harder line with
                    the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> (and the United States) every time a
                    financial crisis occurs, hoping to by-pass the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1"
                        >IMF</gloss> and deal with the United States directly.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="bl_d20fn3">On March 13, the Bolivian Government promulgated a
                        Supreme Resolution incorporating <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> terms,
                        which called for unfreezing of mineral commissary prices. Renewal of the
                        Stand-by Agreement and U.S. cash grant aid was dependent upon the
                        Government’s ability to force the striking miners to accept the Supreme
                        Resolution. By mid-May, the Government was successful; it put the miners
                        back to work and announced the renewal of the Stand-by Agreement. Additional
                        documentation is in files 724.00 and 824.10.</note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
