<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DR–19. Memorandum of Discussion at the 441st Meeting of the National Security
                    Council</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v05mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">dr_d19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">DR–19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-04-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-04-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="DR–19"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="dr_d19">
                <head>DR–19. Memorandum of Discussion at the 441st Meeting of the National Security
                        Council<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="dr_d19fn1">Source: <persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman File, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret. Extract. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMW_1">Marion W. Boggs</persName>. The extract
                        printed here is the portion pertaining to the Dominican Republic from
                        combined agenda items 1, 2, and 3: “Significant World Developments Affecting
                        U.S. Security”, “U.S. Policy Toward Cuba”, and “U.S. Policy Toward the
                        Dominican Republic.” Also omitted was agenda item 4, “Future <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Agenda Items.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">[Extract]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Thursday</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1960-04-14">April 14, 1960</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Dulles reported that in the Dominican Republic, Trujillo’s position continued
                    to weaken and was now quite precarious.<note n="2" xml:id="dr_d19fn2">At the
                        440th <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting, April 7, 1960, General
                            <persName corresp="#p_CLGGJCP_1">Charles P. Cabell</persName>, Acting
                        Director of Central Intelligence, and Under Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_DCD_1">Dillon</persName> made brief statements about the
                        Dominican Republic. <persName corresp="#p_CLGGJCP_1">Cabell</persName>
                        stated, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, that Trujillo’s position
                        continued to grow weaker, and <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1">Dillon</persName>
                        commented that “Trujillo may fall before our policy of building up moderate
                        successor elements has had time to succeed.” According to the memorandum of
                        discussion at that meeting, drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BMW_1"
                            >Boggs</persName>, the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>:<lb/>“Noted
                        and discussed the statement by the Under Secretary of State that the
                        position of the Trujillo regime is deteriorating more rapidly than was
                        anticipated at the time of the Department of State presentation on January
                        14, 1960 (NSC Action No. 2178). Therefore, alternative policies in the event
                        of an early collapse of that regime were being actively considered by the
                        Department of State, and would be the subject of consultation with the
                        Department of Defense and the Joint Chiefs of Staff.” (Eisenhower Library,
                        Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Records)<lb/>This action,
                        approved by the President as <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Action
                        2212, was subsequently transmitted to the Secretaries of State and
                        Defense.</note> The wholesale arrests ordered by Trujillo last winter had
                    affected almost every prominent family in the Dominican Republic. Although these
                    arrests had broken up the plotting against Trujillo, they had at the same time
                    weakened the dictator’s position. Mr. Dulles thought that further attempts would
                        <pb facs="0590" n="502" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_502"/> be made to kill or
                    oust Trujillo. Relations between the government and the church were rapidly
                    deteriorating. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Dulles</persName> pointed out
                    incidentally that the attitude of the church in the Dominican Republic was quite
                    different from the attitude of the church in Cuba. The economic situation in the
                    Dominican Republic was worsening. Business is stagnant and international
                    financial sources are drying up. The government has resorted to various
                    subterfuges in an attempt to improve its precarious financial position.
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ_1">Gates</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="dr_d19fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ_1">Thomas S. Gates</persName>, Jr., Secretary of
                        Defense.</note> asked whether it was true that Trujillo was one of the
                    richest men in the world, with more money than the Dominican government. Mr.
                    Dulles said this statement was true; Trujillo was reported to have milked the
                    Dominican Republic of $400 million, an estimate which was probably exaggerated
                    and should be scaled down by one-half or two-thirds. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_ARB_1">Anderson</persName> said he understood that $44 million
                    in gold had been recently removed from Now York banks by the Dominican Republic
                    and had been placed in the Bank of Nova Scotia. Mr. Dulles said he had a
                    detailed report on the financial situation of the Dominican Republic, all the
                    details of which he would not read. However, it appeared that the Dominican
                    Republic now held $15 million in gold and that it had incurred a variety of
                    obligations; for example, a $16.5 million loan from the Bank of Nova Scotia
                    secured by the sugar crop. The Dominican Republic had also drawn $7 million out
                    of a $11.5 million credit with the International Monetary Fund. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_ARB_1">Anderson</persName> said the International
                    Monetary Fund’s dealings with the Dominican Republic might present a problem to
                    the U.S. The Dominican Republic now had drawn so much from the Fund that it
                    could only draw in the future $2 million every 90 days without consulting the
                    Directors of the Fund. If the Dominicans should want to draw more than $2
                    million every 90 days, the question would arise as to how the U.S. Director
                    should vote when the Dominican Republic undertakes the necessary consultation
                    with the Fund.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dulles continuing his briefing, reported that Trujillo, apparently not
                    realizing his position, is not anticipating an early fall from power and is
                    apparently not planning flight. The Dominican military forces have apparently
                    been repelled by the excesses in Cuba and may believe they will be compelled to
                    act against Trujillo before the radical pro-Castro elements, which <pb
                        facs="dr_d19-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="dr_d19-2"/> are daily
                    increasing in strength, take over the government. If there is a gap between the
                    departure of Trujillo and the establishment of the new regime, the radical
                    pro-Castro elements might have an opportunity to seize power. If the army does
                    not hold off these radical elements, a period of chaos might ensue. Mr. Dulles
                    believed that Trujillo’s downfall might not occur for weeks or even months but,
                    on the other hand, the situation might become critical at any moment.</p>
                <pb facs="0591" n="503" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_503"/>
                <p>The Vice President wondered whether the worst outcome of the situation in the
                    Dominican Republic would not be a take-over by the pro-Castro elements. He also
                    wondered whether we were doing everything possible to support other elements.
                    Mr. Dulles said the difficult question was that of leadership of moderate
                    elements in the Dominican Republic. The vice president of the Republic might be
                    able to assume power or the principal military officers might govern through a
                    military junta. Many prominent anti-Trujillo Dominicans were in exile. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1">Dillon</persName> said this government was
                    following the situation in the Dominican Republic closely and intended to try to
                    prevent seizure of power by any pro-Castro group. This would involve working
                    closely with the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>. The Vice President
                    believed that we could not let <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> or
                    a pro-Castro group take over the Dominican Republic even if we had to intervene
                    in order to prevent such a takeover. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1"
                        >Dillon</persName> felt that in order to intervene we would need an
                    invitation. The Vice President feared that the old story was being repeated in
                    the Dominican Republic; that is, the pro-Castro element was the only minority
                    group with strong leadership and definite objectives. Mr. Dulles said there was
                    a group in Venezuela which would like to move into the Dominican Republic and
                    take over the government. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1">Dillon</persName>
                    believed the <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> element in the
                    Dominican Republic was not strong enough to assume control of the government
                    without support from Cuba. It was, accordingly, very important that the U.S. be
                    prepared for rapid action. The Vice President agreed that it was very important
                    that the U.S., if necessary, take rapid action to prevent any move by <persName
                        corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> to seize power in the Dominican
                    Republic.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dulles said the situations in Haiti and Venezuela were being affected by the
                    situations in Cuba and the Dominican Republic. <persName corresp="#p_BR_1"
                        >Betancourt</persName>, it is reported, has made a deal with the army
                    whereby he will abandon government by coalition, will rule Venezuela with his
                    own party supported by the army, and will take action against the communist
                    movement. However, it is possible that the communists know of his plans and may
                    take action to thwart them.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1">Dillon</persName> said there was one favorable
                    aspect to the situation in the Caribbean. If Trujillo could be removed from
                    power in the <pb facs="dr_d19-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="dr_d19-3"/>
                    Dominican Republic while pro-Castro elements were prevented from seizing power
                    in that country, our anti-Castro campaign throughout Latin America would receive
                    a great boost. The Vice President agreed that getting rid of Trujillo would be a
                    favorable development for us.<note n="4" xml:id="dr_d19fn4">In <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Action 2218, taken at this meeting, the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>:<lb/>“Noted and discussed recent
                        developments with regard to the situation in the Dominican Republic, with
                        particular reference to the importance of seeking to prevent anti-Castro and
                        anti-American elements from seizing power in the event of the collapse of
                        the Trujillo regime.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
