<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DR–21. Special National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v05mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">dr_d21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">DR–21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recGMfbg89qOb8ghX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism">Terrorist activities</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="DR–21"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="dr_d21">
                <head>DR–21. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="dr_d21fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR_1"
                            >INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE_1">NIE</gloss> files. Secret.
                        According to a note on the cover sheet the following organizations
                        participated in the preparation of this estimate: the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and the intelligence organizations of the
                        Departments of State, the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and the Joint
                        Staff. The U.S. Intelligence Board concurred in this estimate on April 26,
                        1960.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">SNIE 86.2-60</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1960-04-26">April 26, 1960</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">THE OUTLOOK FOR THE DOMINICAN REPUBLIC</p>
                <p rend="center">THE PROBLEM</p>
                <p>To estimate political prospects in the Dominican Republic in the light of recent
                    developments.</p>
                <p rend="center">THE ESTIMATE</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">The Trujillo Regime</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In our last estimate dealing with the Dominican Republic (SNIE 80/1–59, 29
                        December 1959, paragraphs 7, 53–60) we stated that the 30-year Trujillo
                        dictatorship was in trouble, but concluded that it probably would remain in
                        power through 1960. Since then anti-Trujillo sentiment has gathered momentum
                        and the regime’s prospects have materially declined. We cannot predict the
                        time or the circumstances in which the regime would be likely to come to an
                        end, but this could happen before the end of the year.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>A notable change in the country’s political atmosphere has developed since
                        the wholesale arrests in January, in which members of almost every prominent
                        Dominican family were seized, in many cases with great brutality, and
                        subjected to heavy fines and jail sentences. Drastic action may in fact have
                        been necessary to break what appears to have been an extensive revolutionary
                        conspiracy; precise information as to how far plotting to overthrow Trujillo
                        had proceeded is still lacking. However, the magnitude and severity of the
                        government’s crackdown revealed the regime’s nervousness, made it more
                        intolerable to leading elements in Dominican society, and alienated the
                        Catholic Church. The latter is now Trujillo’s most outspoken opponent inside
                        the country.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Continuing arrests and new trials of alleged plotters suggest that public
                        unrest is spreading. Within the armed services, which remain the mainstay of
                        the regime, a few new signs of rivalry and dissension have appeared; six
                        army officers have been imprisoned and an air force officer is the latest in
                        a series of defectors. The arrest of close relatives <pb facs="0594" n="506"
                            type="typeset" xml:id="pg_506"/> of high-ranking officers and some
                        terrorist activities directed against individuals in these forces are
                        probably also having an adverse effect on their loyalty to Trujillo.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Since our previous estimate, the economic situation has deteriorated
                        further. Business is stagnant, and an increasing number of people are
                        suffering economic hardship. In addition to some flight of private capital,
                        members of the Trujillo family are reported to have made <pb facs="dr_d21-2"
                            n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="dr_d21-2"/> substantial withdrawals from
                        the national reserve bank—a development which might seriously weaken the
                        government’s financial position. Even if these reports prove unfounded or
                        exaggerated, the spread of rumors that such withdrawals were taking place
                        would obviously contribute to a decline in public confidence in the
                        regime.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>On the other hand, Trujillo himself shows no signs of relinquishing
                        control, and there is no information to indicate that discontent in the
                        military is wide-spread. The plans of the internal opposition probably have
                        been set back by the regime’s repressive measures. The numerous exile groups
                        lack cohesion and effectiveness, despite the encouragement and support given
                        them, not only by <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName>, but also
                        by moderate leaders such as Venezuelan President <persName corresp="#p_BR_1"
                            >Betancourt</persName>. There are deep divisions between pro-Communist
                        and anti-Communist elements within these groups.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="strong">The Succession</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The character of the regime which will eventually succeed Trujillo will
                        depend upon the time and circumstances of Trujillo’s departure. In present
                        circumstances, we think it unlikely that Trujillo will be overthrown by a
                        Castro-type invasion or revolution. It is more likely that Trujillo will
                        eventually be forced to leave by the military acting with the encouragement
                        and support of the upper and middle classes and the Church. The longer his
                        departure is delayed, the more explosive the situation is likely to
                        become.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> has already failed in an
                        attempt to overthrow the Trujillo regime through an invasion by Dominican
                        exiles with Cuban support. His agrarian reform program has had no
                        appreciable impact on the Dominican peasantry, who remain generally unaware
                        of it. They generally still regard Trujillo as the Benefactor. The upper and
                        middle classes, though increasingly disaffected toward Trujillo, are
                        repelled by the excesses of the <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1"
                            >Castro</persName> regime in Cuba. The military also are repelled by
                        what they have seen happening in Cuba. Thus there is now in the Dominican
                        Republic no important element likely to support a Castro-type invasion or
                        revolution.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Nevertheless, tension is rising in the Dominican Republic and the eventual
                        fall of the Trujillo regime will be increasingly anticipated. In such
                        circumstances, persons of property and military officers, apart from
                        Trujillo’s personal associates, will become increasingly anxious to <pb
                            facs="0595" n="507" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_507"/> effect a change of
                        regime before uncontrollable disorder develops. At the psychological moment
                        in this progression, it would be in accord with Latin American custom for
                        the military to call upon the dictator to depart before the situation got
                        out of hand. In such matters, however, timing is of the essence. A premature
                        move could be fatal. On the other hand, to hesitate too long would permit an
                        uncontrollable situation to develop.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>If its timing were right, a junta with military, upper and middle class,
                        and Church participation could probably take over the Dominican Republic
                        without serious resistance. Such a junta would probably also take over in
                        the event of Trujillo’s flight, natural death, or assassination. Once in
                        power, however, such a regime would face serious difficulties. The fall of
                        the dictatorship would entail <pb facs="dr_d21-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="dr_d21-3"/> a considerable amount of disorder and confusion.
                        Although its fall would mean liberation to the upper and middle classes, the
                        new regime would not automatically command the support of the urban
                        proletariat and the peasants. Returning exiles, who are generally radical in
                        their political views, would probably seek to incite these elements against
                        a moderate government. Within the government itself, there might be a
                        struggle for power between military and civilian elements. Finally, the
                        Trujillo family has so dominated the Dominican economy that the confusion
                        attendant upon their sudden departure would probably worsen an already bad
                        economic situation.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Although <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> is probably
                        incapable of overthrowing the Trujillo dictatorship, the political turmoil
                        which would follow the fall of that dictatorship would afford him
                        opportunities for political intervention in the Dominican Republic.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> would certainly do all in
                        his power to incite the masses against a moderate regime and to call for a
                        radical revolution on the Cuban model. Unless a moderate Dominican
                        government received prompt support from sympathetic governments of an
                        undoubtedly liberal character (Venezuela, for instance), <persName
                            corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> might emerge as the ultimate
                        victor.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S.-Dominican Relations</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>The fall of the Trujillo regime would present new problems in
                        U.S.-Dominican relations. Even among moderate opposition elements, there is
                        considerable resentment of past U.S. support for and failure to intervene
                        against the Trujillo dictatorship. Furthermore, almost any new regime would
                        feel a need to demonstrate to the Dominican people and to other Caribbean
                        peoples that it was not under U.S. domination. However, a moderate
                        government would also be in desperate need of U.S. assistance. If the U.S.
                        were to render essential aid discreetly, while tolerating occasional
                        demonstrations of Dominican sovereignty, such a government would probably
                        cooperate in fundamental matters. If, on the other hand, a Castro-type
                        government were eventually to come to <pb facs="0596" n="508" type="typeset"
                            xml:id="pg_508"/> power, the U.S. would inevitably be presented with
                        problems similar to those it has with Cuba.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>The Trujillo government has declared that it will not renew its missile
                        tracking station agreement with the U.S. at its expiration in 1961. This may
                        be an attempt to extort U.S. support for the regime in its present
                        difficulties. If Trujillo should fall before the expiration of the
                        agreement, the attitude of a successor regime would depend on the
                        contingencies set forth in paragraphs 10 and 11 above. A moderate government
                        would probably feel obliged to demonstrate Dominican sovereignty, but would
                        also be influenced by its need for U.S. aid. A Castro-type government would
                        probably denounce the tracking station agreement.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
