<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-10T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-10T13:00:00-05:00" n="ES–19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="es_d19">
                        <head>ES–19. Telegram from the Ambassador in El Salvador (Kalijarvi) to the
                            Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="es_d19fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 716.00/9–1060. Confidential.
                                This telegram was sent in two sections.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-09-10T12:00:00-06:00">September
                                    10, 1960, noon</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>137. Reference: <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL_1">Deptel</gloss> 86.<note n="2" xml:id="es_d19fn2">In telegram 86, September 9, 1960, the Department
                                of State urgently requested an evaluation and recommendations on the
                                crisis in El Salvador and an analysis of the changed attitude of the
                                Salvadoran press. (716.00/9–760)</note></p>
                        <p>With collapse yesterday’s strike efforts<note n="3" xml:id="es_d19fn3">Despatch 66 from San Salvador, September 14, 1960, reported that
                                efforts to set a general strike in motion on September 9 failed
                                after <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> agreed to the
                                conciliatory measures mentioned in footnote 4.
                                (716.00/9–1460)</note> and progress in move toward conciliation,
                            situation here decidedly calmer. May have passed crisis. Discussion with
                            Esquivel, President Assembly, and twelve Assembly members last night
                            convinces me military, business, church, wealthy and community leaders
                            on second thought now recognize necessity support <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> through current crisis. While
                            many were ready assist in seeking solution, major move came from
                            Archbishop when he reluctantly issued message of conciliation under
                            specific instructions of Nunciatura. Once committed, Archbishop
                            immediately received support banking business and social community
                            resulting in a meeting yesterday and atmosphere evidently conducive to
                            conciliation (Embtel 135 September 9).<note n="4" xml:id="es_d19fn4">It
                                reported a radio announcement that in a meeting with cabinet
                                officers including Ortíz Mancía and <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Parker</persName>, and a public committee of businessmen and
                                the Archbishop, <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName>
                                agreed to release students arrested but not charged with crimes; to
                                determine by investigation those responsible for the September 2
                                violence, and to suspend the state of siege upon restoration of
                                order. (716.00/9–960)</note> Group last night convinced President
                            still firm. Contemplated investigation will cover not only police
                            violence but also actions on other side.</p>
                        <p>Evident, however, that <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName>
                            hold on government definitely shaken and chances finishing presidential
                            term appreciably reduced. Open question whether <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> hatred of and efforts to smear
                                <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName> by permitting airing
                            of criminal charges against military and other officers for actions
                            taken under <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName> (Torres
                            Valencia and Palomo cases) have so offended military to whom <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName> is darling that a coup will be
                            forthcoming. Conversations with some responsible leaders suggest that
                            perhaps day of reckoning may have been put off until a coup will not be
                            confused with communism. Army as regularly reported holds key to any
                            change now and in the foreseeable future. To date have heard nothing to
                            indicate other than that officers currently control army <pb facs="0691" n="603" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_603"/> still supporting <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName>. Indeed evidence to support
                                <pb facs="es_d19-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="es_d19-2"/>
                            belief that <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> spurred to
                            forceful action in crisis by army.</p>
                        <p>For full appreciation factors involved current situation see Embdes 363
                            March 14<note n="5" xml:id="es_d19fn5">It reported that Lemus’ egotism
                                limited his ability to govern, but he would complete his term in
                                office if he stopped favoring Rubio Melhado as his successor.
                                (716.11/2–1460)</note> and Embtel 304.<note n="6" xml:id="es_d19fn6">See <ref target="#es_d13">Document ES–13</ref>.</note> Situation of
                            President <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> due in part to
                            extension of factors in play at that time. Foremost is increasingly
                            isolated position into which President has maneuvered himself and his
                            hesitancy to act when positive resolute action clearly indicated.</p>
                        <p>When current situation erupted August 16<note n="7" xml:id="es_d19fn7">Telegrams 82 and 83 from San Salvador, August 16 and 17,
                                respectively, reported on anti-U.S., pro-Castro demonstrations
                                outside the U.S. Chancery and the <hi rend="italic">Prensa
                                    Grafica</hi> building on August 16, 1960. (716.00/8–1660 and
                                8–1760)</note> it primarily communist-Castro-led. Public in general
                            appeared favor strong action against better known organizers and
                            agitators. Instead of acting, President hesitated and then temporized
                            giving subversive elements opportunity extend agitation in university
                            and whip students into defiant mood. When President finally decided take
                            action on September 2, rather than being selective against agitation
                            leaders, applied force indiscriminately across board with heavy hand.
                            Result, clearly promoted by purposely planted false rumors re violations
                            women, police excesses against youth, et cetera, was antagonized public
                            which with irresponsible press encouragement, lost sight of real issue
                            and perpetrators of disorders—communism and vanguard professional
                            subverters.</p>
                        <pb facs="es_d19-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="es_d19-3"/>
                        <p>Through entire period <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> did
                            not once seek advice or counsel from Cabinet. Several who wished to give
                            him support were unable reach him. We reliably informed that when group
                            Prud Party members and business leaders attempted on September 1 offer
                            support and assistance in meeting with President, they were rebuffed and
                            told that decisions were his and he would make them. Not until September
                            6 were members Cabinet brought into picture and then were requested sign
                            already prepared executive message to people (Embtel 126 and 127).<note n="8" xml:id="es_d19fn8">Telegram 126, September 6, 1960, informed
                                the Department of State that the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Tribuna
                                    Libre</hi> on September 6, printed an executive message
                                appealing to the people for support of efforts to maintain
                                constitutional government. (716.00/9–660) Telegram 127, September 7,
                                1960, reported on a meeting between Foreign Minister Ortíz Mancía
                                and foreign diplomatic mission chiefs in which he explained the
                                Government’s resort to force against provocative anti-Government
                                demonstrations, <persName corresp="#p_KTV_1">Kalijarvi</persName>
                                concluded that the Government might not use necessary firmness again
                                for lack of public support. (716.00/9–760)</note></p>
                        <p>This egotism, aloofness and apparent obstinate determination to go it
                            alone further isolated <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName>
                            and alienated many who were prepared rally around him during crisis.
                            This also prompted disgruntled <pb facs="0692" n="604" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_604"/> to start searching for an alternative and majority
                            appear to be fastening on ex-President <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName>. While reports of <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName> activities differ greatly, some suggest his
                            forces active throughout crisis attempting utilize it for own partisan
                            political ends. These same reports say <persName corresp="#p_OLCO_1">Osorio</persName> is dressed and waiting in the wings. General
                            consensus is that if Lemus-Osorio rift could be patched up tranquility
                            could be rapidly restored. This voiced from both sides and also from
                            friends of both men. However, I believe breach so great that
                            conciliation between two is wishful thinking.</p>
                        <p>While original disturbances party directed against us “Yanqi imperialism”
                            this aspect disappeared after force and violence turned public ire
                            against President. Leaflets currently being distributed return to this
                            theme strongly suggesting communist leadership, which disappeared during
                            more vociferous disorders, has returned to guide both students and
                                <gloss target="#t_CGTS_1">CGTS</gloss>.</p>
                        <pb facs="es_d19-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="es_d19-4"/>
                        <p>Against this background, current period seems be interlude in what will
                            be continuing test of strength. Regardless <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> faults, Embassy strongly
                            believes present government deserving of our moral and material support
                            and U.S. should render such as long as <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> remains in power and his government continues
                            pursue policies the aims of which coincide with our own. At present
                            time, main forces seem be directed toward maintaining <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> government and avoiding making
                            of El Salvador another Cuba. Thus, while agree that we should make our
                            views known to subtle and direct way which we have already done, do not
                            believe we should publicly deport ourselves in way which would add
                            substance to charges, already being levelled by communists, of
                            intervention in internal affairs. Rather, we should speed up action on
                            pending aid requests, economic integration, social welfare program, et
                            cetera, which will give notice our support and confidence in <persName corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> government.</p>
                        <p>Re press attitudes see Weeka 36.<note n="9" xml:id="es_d19fn9">Reference
                                is to despatch 64 from San Salvador, September 8, 1960.
                                (716.00(W)/9–860)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KTV_1"><hi rend="strong">Kalijarvi</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>