<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-16T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-16T21:00:00-05:00" n="ES–20"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="es_d20">
                <head>ES–20. Telegram from the Ambassador in El Salvador (Kalijarvi) to the
                    Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="es_d20fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, 716.00/9–1660. Confidential;
                        Niact.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1960-09-16T20:00:00-06:00">September 16,
                            1960, 8 p.m.</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>148. Saw Foreign Minister at 10:30. He trying muster 14 family support, [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>].<note n="2" xml:id="es_d20fn2"
                        >Reference presumably is to a beating the Rector received at the hands of
                        the police who also arrested him during a raid on the University, September
                        2, 1960. Documentation on this incident is in decimal file 716.00 and in
                            <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> Special Assistant’s Files, Lot 62 D
                        24, “El Salvador, 1960.”</note> Liked idea of requesting <gloss
                        target="#t_IAPC_1">IAPC</gloss> investigation. Agreed <persName
                        corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> should take firm action, <hi
                        rend="italic">but felt that he should at same time indicate readiness
                        reconsider electoral and other recent laws, and change his cabinet to get
                        rid of Sub-secretary Justice (Julio Fausto Fernandez, former secretary
                        Communist party). Needed to get government side to people</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">President received me alone 12 noon. <persName
                            corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> tired but relaxed. Said he had
                        been waiting for me. Agreed government confronted by grave</hi> problem.
                    While support indicated from many quarters he had received few telegrams of
                    congratulation but not a single friend had come to say he supporting <persName
                        corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName>. This discouraging. Reminded him
                    presidents stand alone, must take decisions regardless of professions of
                    friendship and support. Placing hand on statue Lincoln I had presented him he
                    commented, “Yes, I think of him often at this time. I realize fully what is
                    involved.” Suggested he might wish consider submitting memo to <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> requesting investigation by <gloss target="#t_IAPC_1"
                    >IAPC</gloss>. Liked idea and said would discuss with Foreign Minister.</p>
                <p>Recognized pattern street fighting yesterday importation from abroad. Discussing
                    yesterday’s ceremony said provocation [illegible in the original]. At the end of
                    procession of school children came disorderly procession led by University
                    ex-Chancellors, Perla and [illegible in the original] followed by 500 students
                    and ten groups roughnecks. Subsequently <pb facs="es_d20-2" n="2"
                        type="facsimile" xml:id="es_d20-2"/> determined many of these from
                    neighboring countries. National Guard with fixed bayonets prevented roughnecks
                    breaking into gathered group and confined demonstrations to marching down street
                    singing International and crying support for <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1"
                        >Castro</persName>. Similar group on opposite side park similarly contained.
                    We both agreed a miracle no incident occurred.</p>
                <p>Suggested exiling agitators no punishment. Jail sentences would have more
                    deterring effect. President said unfortunately present laws of country do not
                    permit, but military tribunals under state of siege can and will imprison
                    disturbers. He recognized non-democratic nature tribunals but felt no other
                    alternative for controlling situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0694" n="606" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_606"/>
                <p>Expressed appreciation for U.S. support and requested further assistance [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] also concerning use tear gas and
                    other means controlling mobs. Said he had requested arms, but did not seek U.S.
                    military intervention. Agreed he needed strengthen press section in Casa
                    Presidencial to reach the people.</p>
                <p>I said his government stands at crossroads, needs take firm action control
                    situation or face loss power. He still unable appreciate need take action
                    clearly indicated.</p>
                <p>Visit seemed to give him lift and at no time did he give impression he would
                    resign.</p>
                <p>Reports indicate he not sleeping. May explain apparent weariness. I left today
                    with distinct impression both Foreign Minister and <persName
                        corresp="#p_LLCJM_1">Lemus</persName> unable divorce emotions from their
                    thinking. Neither seems have clear sense of diversion in which he would like to
                    go, let alone ability choose word which would make him there.</p>
                <p>Have cancelled follow-up visit scheduled for tomorrow per Department’s telephone
                        call<note n="3" xml:id="es_d20fn3">The telephone call under reference was
                        not further identified.</note> but believe it essential maintain <pb
                        facs="es_d20-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="es_d20-3"/> as close contact
                    with both President and Foreign Minister as situation will allow. Large measure
                    psychology involved in situation and know President would appreciate receiving
                    any assistance Department may be in position provide.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KTV_1"><hi rend="strong"
                            >Kalijarvi</hi></persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
