<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="ETA–29"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="eta_d29">
                <head>ETA–29. Memorandum from the Director of the Office of Inter-American Regional
                    Economic Affairs (Turkel) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                    Affairs (Rubottom)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="eta_d29fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> Files, Lot 62 D
                        302, “Chron File of Memoranda &amp; Miscellaneous.” Official Use Only.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName>.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1960-02-05">February 5,
                        1960</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Discussion at Secretary’s Staff Conference—February 5, 1960</item>
                </list>
                <p>I feel that you should be aware of the following points that came up at the
                    Secretary’s staff conference on February 5.<note n="2" xml:id="eta_d29fn2">The
                        record of the Secretary’s staff meeting, held at 9:15 a.m. on February 5,
                        drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CJA_1">John A. Calhoun</persName>, Director
                        of the Executive Secretariat, contains a brief mention of the subject dealt
                        with in this memorandum. (Secretary’s Staff Meetings, Lot 63 D
                    75)</note></p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of two matters unrelated to U.S. loan activities in
                    Latin America.]</p>
                <p>3. I stated that my colleagues on <gloss target="#t_IAECOSOC_1">IA–ECOSOC</gloss>
                    yesterday had referred to the February 4 front page article in the New York
                    Times by Kenworthy<note n="3" xml:id="eta_d29fn3">E.W. Kenworthy.</note> stating
                    that U.S. aid to India would increase from $150–170 million per year to $250–300
                    million per year but without any increase in the total. They said if this is so,
                    obviously the priorities of other participants must be reduced. Is this our
                    support for Operation Pan America?</p>
                <p>I said that I did not know about the alleged [illegible in the original] or the
                    accuracy of the article. My Brazilian colleague said that the Brazilian
                    Ambassador at the Pan American Society had recently stated that Latin America
                    had participated in <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss> funds to the extent of
                    only 7-1/2%. He added that if you eliminate the Argentine participation, which
                    [illegible in the original] a stabilization loan, the real participation was
                    around 5%.</p>
                <p>I said to the Secretary that I had looked into the matter and found there were
                    two reasons for the low participation. Latin America had not <pb facs="0172"
                        n="84" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_84"/> submitted many worthwhile projects
                    and the second reason was that they got a low priority since there was a general
                    feeling that they were much more creditworthy than other areas and should have
                    applied to the Eximbank. In any case, I stated, it was an unfortunate article to
                    come out on the eve of the President’s departure to Latin America.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that it should not be forgotten that Latin America gets a
                    very high percentage of Eximbank loans. Was that not so?</p>
                <pb facs="eta_d29-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="eta_d29-2"/>
                <p>I responded that normally Latin America does get a high percentage; about 40% of
                    all Eximbank loans. However, the level of loans in 1958 was about $477 million
                    (because it was a year of many stabilization loans) but had dropped in 1950 to
                    some $233 million. I added that I thought the outlook was not good since the
                    President’s Annual Economic Report shows that it is expected this decline will
                    continue and the justification is that the Inter-American Bank will shortly come
                    into operation. The only trouble with this is that it would actually take quite
                    a long time for the Inter-American Bank to begin making a significant
                    contribution to the economic development of the Hemisphere and thus we were
                    faced with the immediate problem of securing a higher priority for Latin America
                    in the operations of <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
