<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-01-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="ETA–1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="eta_d1">
                <head>ETA–1. Memorandum from the Director of the Executive Secretariat (Howe) to the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs (Rubottom) and the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs (Mann)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="eta_d1fn1">Source: Department of State, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> Files, Lot 60 D 553, “Task Force
                        (Latin American Economic Policy Review) 1958.” Secret.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1958-01-24">January 24,
                        1958</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Economic Policies—Latin America</hi></p>
                <p>Before he left for the Baghdad Pact Conference,<note n="2" xml:id="eta_d1fn2">The
                        Baghdad Pact Council held its fourth ministerial session in Ankara, Turkey,
                        January 26–30, 1958. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1"
                            >Dulles</persName> headed the U.S. observer delegation. For
                        documentation on this subject, see <ref target="frus1958-60v10p2#d303"><hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1958–1960, Eastern Europe;
                            Finland; Greece; Turkey, vol. X, part 2, Documents 303</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1958-60v10p2#d304">304</ref>.</note> the Secretary, in a
                    memorandum on a number of different subjects,<note n="3" xml:id="eta_d1fn3"
                        >Reference is to a memorandum from Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1"
                            >Dulles</persName> to Under Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_HCA_1">Christian A. Herter</persName> and four other
                        principal officers of the Department, dated January 19, 1958.
                        (110.11-DU/2-358)</note> made the following statement.</p>
                <quote><p>“I feel that our economic policies in station to Latin America are too
                        negative. I think we should re-examine our opposition to all trade between
                        Latin America and the Soviet bloc, putting the emphasis rather on means to
                        make that trade safe. Also I think we should re-examine our policy of
                        opposing any stabilizing, or quota, arrangements. I doubt that we are in a
                        good position to withstand in that part of the world a Soviet economic
                        defensive at a time when the demand for raw materials is down and prices are
                        very low.”</p></quote>
                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HCA_1">Herter</persName> would like to have a
                    careful study of this problem promptly undertaken so that as soon as possible
                    recommendations can be put before the Secretary.</p>
                <p>Action on the aspects of this problem which relate to financial and commodity
                    problems in Latin America are assigned to E; those relating to the trade
                    relations of Latin America are assigned to <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>.
                    Governor <persName corresp="#p_HCA_1">Herter</persName> however wants to have
                    the closest possible <pb facs="0090" n="2" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_2"/>
                    coordination in the review of this matter by <gloss target="#t_ARA_1"
                        >ARA</gloss> and E and also in close cooperation with <gloss
                        target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1"
                        >Dillon</persName> will be overseeing the preparation of work on this
                    matter.</p>
                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_HCA_1">Herter</persName> requests from you by
                    Tuesday, January 28, a brief statement of the manner in which you plan to
                    address this problem and the date on which you believe you would expect to have
                    something for the Secretary after appropriate review by other parts of the
                        Department.<note n="4" xml:id="eta_d1fn4">A memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCS_1">Charles S. Whitehouse</persName>, Special Assistant
                        in the Office of the Deputy Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs,
                        to Assistant Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_MTC_1">Mann</persName>, dated January 27, reads in
                        part as follows: “I have spoken to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF_3"
                            >Howe</persName>, pointing out that it would be impossible to get a
                        statement to the Under Secretary by Tuesday, January 28, on this subject as
                        Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_MTC_1">Mann</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DCD_1"
                            >Dillon</persName> are lunching together on Thursday, the 30th, to
                        discuss this problem. <persName corresp="#p_HF_3">Fisher Howe</persName> has
                        agreed, but would appreciate a very brief statement along the lines he
                        requested in the course of Thursday afternoon.” (Rubottom Files, Lot 60 D
                        553, “Task Force (Latin American Economic Policy Review) 1958”)</note></p>
                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HF_3"><hi rend="strong">Fisher
                            Howe</hi></persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
