<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-02-05T20:33:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-02-05T20:33:00-05:00" n="GT–14"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="gt_d14">
                <head>GT–14. Telegram from the Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in
                        Guatemala<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="gt_d14fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Central Files, 714.5622/2–459. Official Use Only; Priority. Drafted
                        by <persName corresp="#p_KB_1">King</persName>, signed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>, and repeated for information to
                        Panama City for <gloss target="#t_CAIRC_1">CAIRC</gloss> and Mexico
                        City.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1959-02-05T20:33:00-05:00">February 5, 1959,
                            8:33 p.m.</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>285. Embtel 298.<note n="2" xml:id="gt_d14fn2">It proposed the flight of a
                        Guatemalan mission to the United States to inspect and purchase B-26
                        bombers. (714.5622/2–459).</note> In view present tension and severance
                    diplomatic relations Guatemala and Mexico,<note n="3" xml:id="gt_d14fn3">Mexican
                        President Lopéz Mateos severed diplomatic relations with Guatemala on
                        January 23 over an incident involving Guatemalan strafing of Mexican fishing
                        boats off the Guatemalan Pacific coast on December 31. The two countries
                        resumed diplomatic relations on September 15, following a settlement of the
                        dispute. For documentation, see 2 <persName corresp="#p_WMM_1"
                            >Whiteman</persName> 87.</note> and in accordance with U.S. policy of
                    withholding shipments armament particularly aircraft, to <gloss target="#t_LA_1"
                        >LA</gloss> areas where such tension exists, Dept plans to suspend
                    temporarily further action on delivery of six B–26 bombers to Guatemala.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="gt_d14fn4">Ambassador Antillón had requested six B–26 planes
                        in a message to <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Dulles</persName>, September 2,
                        1958. (714.5622/9–258)</note> This does not rpt not constitute cancellation
                    of approval of sale given prior to December 31 attack on Mexican fishing boats
                    by <gloss target="#t_GAF_1">GAF</gloss> planes. Normal processing of request
                    merely suspended until tension subsides when Dept would expect that negotiations
                    with <gloss target="#t_GAF_1">GAF</gloss> be resumed.</p>
                <pb facs="0770" n="682" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_682"/>
                <p>Suggest <gloss target="#t_EMB_1">Emb</gloss> in its discretion could explain
                    foregoing frankly to <gloss target="#t_GAF_1">GAF</gloss> Chief Urrutia. If
                        <gloss target="#t_EMB_1">Emb</gloss> believes such approach to Urrutia
                    inadvisable, <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> should be informed that
                    certain administrative delays in processing Guatemalan request have been
                    encountered, and that <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> will be advised when
                    B–26’s are available for inspection.<note n="5" xml:id="gt_d14fn5">At the
                        Department of State’s request, the Department of Defense suspended action on
                        delivery of B-26 bombers to the Guatemalan Air Force. (Telegram 336 to
                        Guatemala, March 4, 1959; 714.5622/3–259). In accord with Mallory’s
                        preference, the Department of State informed the Guatemalan Embassy of the
                        reason for the delay. (Telegram 350 from Guatemala, March 5, 1959;
                        714.5622/3–559).</note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
