<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="GT–22"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="gt_d22">
                <head>GT–22. Memorandum of Conversation by the Officer in Charge of Guatemalan
                    Affairs (Gorrell)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="gt_d22fn1">Source: Department
                        of State, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OAP_1"
                            >OAP</gloss> Files, Lot 63 D 146, “Interdepartmental Memoranda:
                        Guatemala, 1959.” Official Use Only. The source text is an unsigned carbon
                        copy.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1959-09-28">September 28,
                        1959</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Visit of Guatemalan Foreign Minister</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>His Excellency Lic. <persName corresp="#p_UMJV_1">Jesus Victor Unda
                            Murillo</persName>, Minister for Foreign Affairs of Guatemala;</item>
                    <item>His Excellency Col. Arturo Ramirez Pinto, Ambassador of Guatemala;
                        Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">R. R. Rubottom</persName>,
                        Jr.;</item>
                    <item>Mr. Juan L. Correll, Officer in Charge, Guatemala Affairs.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_UMJV_1">Unda Murillo</persName> said he
                    had been requested by President Ydígoras to transmit through Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>, the President’s warm salutations to
                    President and Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName>. The
                    Minister also asked that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>
                    communicate his own personal salutations to Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA_1">Herter</persName>.</p>
                <p>President Ydígoras, the Minister said, had also asked him to inquire of Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> the proper channels for
                    extending an invitation to Governor Muñoz Marin of Puerto Rico to visit
                    Guatemala, and the most effective way of doing so. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> said he would secure this
                    information and transmit it through Ambassador Ramirez Pinto.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that Guatemala is suffering from the drop in coffee prices,
                    which has created financial problem that prevent its dynamic President from
                    doing all the things he would like to do. He expressed satisfaction at the
                    efforts that have been made to stabilize the coffee situation. He mentioned in
                    passing that Guatemala would like to become a sugar exporting nation but
                    understands the difficulties involved in trying to have a quota assigned to it
                    at the present time.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> expressed interest in
                    hearing the Minister’s views on the political situation in Guatemala. The
                    Minister stressed the tension <pb facs="0789" n="701" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_701"/> attendant on the throwing of bombs, some of which, he
                    said, have been tossed by the extreme Leftist <gloss target="#t_PR_1"
                    >PR</gloss>, others by the extreme Rightist <gloss target="#t_MDN_1"
                    >MDN</gloss>, in efforts to create confusion. Some, he said, have hoped to force
                    Ydígoras to set up a dictatorship but the President has refused to do so because
                    he is determined to upload democracy. However, the <pb facs="gt_d22-2" n="2"
                        type="facsimile" xml:id="gt_d22-2"/> Minister continued, by their tactics
                    the <gloss target="#t_PR_1">PR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_MDN_1">MDN</gloss>
                    have unwittingly become tools of an international plot being stage-managed by
                        <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Betancourt</persName> of Venezuela and <persName
                        corresp="#p_CRF_1">Fidel Castro</persName> of Cuba, in the interest of
                    securing the return of Arévalo to the head of the Guatemala Government. Their
                    purpose, the Minister stated, is to set up a network of Governments similar to
                    their own, and <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Betancourt</persName> is the creature
                    of Arévalo, who is serving as close advisor to him, as well as close friend. If
                    elections were to be held next year in Guatemala, the Minister added, Arévalo
                    would be elected by an overwhelming majority, with dire results for the country
                    and great embarrassment for the United States.</p>
                <p>The Minister expressed indignation at the speech given in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss> by the Cuban Foreign Minister, Roa,
                    especially at his having coupled Guatemala with Hungary and Tibet.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="gt_d22fn2">The referenced speech was delivered on September 24,
                        1959; for text, see United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of
                            the General Assembly, Fourteenth Session, Plenary Meetings</hi>
                        (A/PV.806), p. 145.</note> He said he had felt that the Guatemalan Foreign
                    Office could not reply to these remarks, but that the task had been undertaken
                    by the Guatemalan Consul General in New York, who had made a strong reply,
                    making it clear there had been no foreign intervention in Guatemala’s
                    Liberation.</p>
                <p>Stating that he was doing so at the Secretary’s request, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> told the Minister that in the Camp
                    David conversations the “dead line” for settlement of the Berlin issue had been
                    dropped and the way apparently opened for a Summit meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
