<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-08-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="GT–30"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="gt_d30">
                <head>GT–30. Memorandum of Conversation, by the Officer in Charge of Guatemalan
                    Affairs (Godfrey)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="gt_d30fn1">Source: Department
                        of State, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OAP_1"
                            >OAP</gloss> Files, Lot 63 D 146, “Klein and Saks: Guatemala 1960.”
                        Official Use Only. The source text is an unsigned carbon copy.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1960-08-19">August 19, 1960</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Guatemala: Visit of the Minister of Finance</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Manuel Bendfeldt, Minister of Finance of Guatemala</item>
                    <item>Franciso Fernandes, Manager of the Bank of Guatemala</item>
                    <item><persName corresp="#p_AC_1">Carlos Alejos</persName>, Ambassador of
                        Guatemala</item>
                    <item><gloss target="#t_REA_1">REA</gloss> – Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName></item>
                    <item><gloss target="#t_OAP_1">OAP</gloss> – Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCE_1"
                            >Higdon</persName></item>
                    <item><gloss target="#t_OAP_1">OAP</gloss> – Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GRA_1"
                            >Godfrey</persName></item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0805" n="717" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_717"/>
                <p>The Minister of Finance explained that it had been necessary for him to call
                    today instead of on August 22, as had been scheduled, due to the necessity of
                    his immediate return to Guatemala. He stated that he and Mr. Fernandes had just
                    completed negotiation of a $10 million loan from the Bank of America in
                    association with the Chase Manhattan Bank and other unspecified banks. Terms for
                    repayment were five years at 5 percent annual interest. The loan agreement
                    included a provision for the deposit of certain Bank of Guatemala dollar
                    reserves in the loaning banks on a 6-months call basis. The Minister explained
                    that funds from this loan would be used to liquidate outstanding fiscal
                    obligations, i.e. <hi rend="italic">deuda flotante</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that the Guatemala Government had recently completed its plan
                    of Economic Development for the period 1960–64.<note n="2" xml:id="gt_d30fn2"
                        >Not found in Department of State files.</note> He promised to provide
                    copies of this plan through the United States Embassy in Guatemala. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> observed that if external
                    financing would be sought for any part of this plan, then the loan projects
                    should be divided into three different categories: (1) self-liquidating
                    projects; (2) long term, non-self-liquidating (“social”) type loan projects; and
                    (3) mixed type, which would only be partially self-liquidating. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> said that we placed
                    particular emphasis on private initiative and participation of private
                    investment capital in plans for economic development. The Minister replied that
                    his government agreed with this emphasis and for this reason President Ydígoras
                    has not approved the Petem project since it provided for too much government
                    participation and control.</p>
                <pb facs="gt_d30-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="gt_d30-2"/>
                <p>In reply to an inquiry by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THR_1"
                        >Turkel</persName>, the Minister stated that service on the public debt now
                    averages about 10 percent of the total annual budget. Service on the foreign
                    debt now amounts to only a little more than $1 million annually with the major
                    service costs going towards the internal debt. He again emphasized that the loan
                    just concluded with the Bank of America would be used toward liquidating the
                    floating debt of approximately Q$12 million, which included overdue salaries and
                    other various unpaid accounts.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> inquired if the
                    development plan included plans for housing, and observed that while such
                    projects were commendable, all our available loan resources could easily be
                    employed in just housing projects. Of course, this was not possible but we did
                    look with favor on self-help housing projects. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> stated that we also look favorably on
                    projects providing agricultural credit to small farmers. He cited the examples
                    of Costa Rica and Colombia in promoting successful agricultural credit programs.
                    The <pb facs="0806" n="718" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_718"/> Minister stated
                    that some housing projects were a social and political necessity even though
                    economically they did not deserve the same priority as projects designed to
                    increase the general economic income. With regard to agricultural credit, he
                    said the situation in Guatemala could not be compared to that of Costa Rica or
                    Colombia, since such programs of supervised credit would likely prove too
                    expensive to operate in Guatemala. He quoted as an example the loan program for
                    rubber development, where money had been borrowed at 5 3/4 percent and had to be
                    loaned at a maximum of 8 percent. The banks had shown little interest in
                    promoting rubber development loans, since after deducting costs, the banks
                    received only a small return of approximately ½ percent. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> observed, with reference to the rubber
                    development loan, some consideration might be given by Guatemala to
                    renegotiating this loan on more favorable terms.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AC_1">Alejos</persName> pointed out that
                    President Ydígoras faced special problems, both financial and fiscal, at this
                    time and he hoped for assistance from the United States. The Ambassador stated
                    that a primary objective was a loan for the Rio Hondo highway project but it
                    appeared that there were still certain problems to be resolved before the loan
                    project could receive further consideration. He pointed out that the Rio Hondo
                    project was of much more significance than the Rio Molino highway project since,
                    in comparison, the Rio Hondo project would give local employment on a much
                    larger scale.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName> assured the Guatemalan
                    visitors that we were ready to give all possible help to the government of
                    President Ydígoras. He emphasized that the Guatemalans should present
                    well-developed projects and that the presentation should show the relation of
                    the specific project to the overall balance of payments situation, both present
                    and future. He also stated we are interested in the Central American plans for
                    economic integration and are prepared to give sympathetic consideration to
                    projects related to this plan. He said he wished to make a special point,
                    however, that we cannot help with budget deficit financing.</p>
                <p>The Minister thanked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THR_1">Turkel</persName>
                    for his remarks and stated that he clearly understood our inability to finance
                    budget deficits. With regard to the current fiscal difficulties in Guatemala,
                    the Minister stated he was particularly interested in revising the revenue code
                    and that he hoped we would be able to <pb facs="gt_d30-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="gt_d30-3"/> provide expert technical advice for such revision. While
                    he was not interested in technical assistance with regards to fiscal
                    administration, he indicated that he was interested in advice on administration
                    and organization of the Ministry of Finance and Public Credit.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
