<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-01-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="HA–1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="ha_d1">
                <head>HA–1. Memorandum from the Director of the Office of Middle American Affairs
                    (Wieland) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs
                        (Rubottom)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="ha_d1fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Central Files, 738.00/1–958. Confidential. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_LES_1">Edward Little</persName>, Deputy Director of the
                        Office of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs; and cleared with <persName
                            corresp="#p_PA_1">Albert Post</persName> of the Office of Inter-American
                        Regional Economic Affairs. Paragraphs 1, 4, 5(a), and 5(d) were also cleared
                        by telephone with Kenneth Wright, the Assistant Chief of the
                        Cuba-Haiti-Mexico Branch of the International Cooperation Administration. A
                        marginal notation by <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>
                        indicates the Assistant Secretary’s approval of the list of suggested
                        elements in the memorandum. A separate notation on the source text indicates
                        that a copy of the memorandum was given to Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_DGA_1">Gerald Drew</persName> on January 10.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1958-01-09">January 9, 1958</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Authorization to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DGA_1">Drew</persName>
                        to Discuss with Haitian Officials Factors Involved in Restoration of Normal
                        Relations.</item>
                </list>
                <p>With respect to our proposal relating to steps Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGA_1">Drew</persName> will take on his return to Port-au-Prince
                    to attempt to resolve the Talamas case,<note n="2" xml:id="ha_d1fn2">On December
                        29, 1957, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DGA_1">Drew</persName> had
                        returned to Washington for consultation regarding the case of Shibley Jean
                        Talamas, an American citizen who was beaten to death while in the custody of
                        Haitian police on September 29, 1957. Talamas, who had been accused of
                        political activity against the Haitian government, had surrendered himself
                        voluntarily to Haitian authorities after they had assured Embassy officials
                        that Talamas would not be harmed.<lb/>Following Drew’s return to
                        Port-au-Prince on January 14, 1958, extensive negotiation between the two
                        governments produced a settlement along the following lines. The Haitian
                        government publicly expressed its regret over the circumstances surrounding
                        Talamas’ death, reaffirmed guarantees for the security and well-being of
                        American citizens in Haiti, and agreed to pay an indemnity to the Talamas
                        family. The United States had sought to obtain the dismissal of the officers
                        responsible for Talamas’ death, but the Haitian government would agree only
                        to have them court martialed and disciplined. The agreement was embodied in
                        an exchanged of notes between the governments of the United States and Haiti
                        at Port-au-Prince on February 5, 1958. The Embassy at Port-au-Prince
                        transmitted the texts of the notes, which were made public at the time, to
                        the Department of States in despatch 357, February 5, 1958.
                        (238.113-Talamas, Shibley Jean)</note> the Ambassador hopes to be in a
                    position to explain to <pb facs="0823" n="735" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_735"/>
                    President <persName corresp="#p_DF_1">Duvalier</persName> some of the factors
                    which would be involved in reestablishment of normal, friendly relations between
                    our countries if the Haitians give us satisfaction over this incident. These
                    “factors” are in no sense a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>, and the
                    Ambassador has no intention of describing them as such. Rather, the explanation
                    of them would be presented as some of the elements of our relations which
                    existed before Talamas’ death and which would exist now if it were not for that
                    unfortunate occurrence.</p>
                <p>We believe the elements of such restoration are as listed below and, if you
                    agree, the Ambassador will describe these factors to the President if he
                    considers it appropriate in his discussions in Part-au-Prince: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1957 $1 million grant
                            assistance would be made available in accordance with previous
                            arrangements.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Recreational visits of U.S. fleet units would be resumed as soon as
                            they could be scheduled.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Ambassador would immediately recommend that high-ranking Army
                            and/or Marine Corps officers visit Haiti to discuss training of the
                            Haitian Army and the possible augmentation of U.S. military missions in
                            Haiti.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>It would be explained that the U.S. Development Loan Fund is receiving
                            applications from interested governments for economic development
                            project meeting the criteria of the Fund.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Finance Minister Thebaud would be invited to visit Washington to
                            review the Haitian economic situation and to review cooperative steps
                            which might be taken in this field. This visit would also permit the
                            Finance Minister to discuss problems with the ExImbank, the Development
                            Loan Fund, the <gloss target="#t_IBRD_1">IBRD</gloss>, and the <gloss
                                target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>. The visit of Minister Thebaud would
                            also permit discussion of the following matters of mutual concern: <pb
                                facs="ha_d1-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="ha_d1-2"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>Plans for allocation of $2 million grant aid already earmarked
                                    for Haiti from <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1958 Mutual
                                    Security program funds.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>Cooperative steps to stimulate U.S. tourist travel to
                                    Haiti.</item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>Cooperative steps to stimulate U.S. private investment in
                                    Haiti.</item>
                                <label>(d)</label>
                                <item>Review of U.S. technical assistance programs in Haiti to
                                    explore areas where additional projects might be
                                    desirable.</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>(Availability of the remaining $3 million of the Artibonite loan has not been
                    included since it has been made clear to the Haitians that it is only technical
                    difficulties which have held up the release of these funds.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
