<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="NI–21" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="ni_d21">
                        <head>NI–21. Memorandum of Conversation by the Officer in Charge of
                            Nicaraguan Affairs (Godfrey)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="ni_d21fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 615.17/6–760.
                                Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-06-07">June 7,
                                1960</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>NICARAGUA: Visit of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> to discuss Nicaraguan-Honduran
                                Relations and Request for Asylum by Pro-Batista Exiles.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Guillermo
                                    Sevilla-Sacasa</persName>, Ambassador of Nicaragua</item>
                            <item>ARA—<persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Roy R. Rubottom</persName>, Jr.,
                                Assistant Secretary</item>
                            <item>OAP—<persName corresp="#p_GRA_1">Richard A. Godfrey</persName>,
                                Nicaraguan Desk Officer</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">1. Nicaraguan-Honduran Relations</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> stated
                            that he had been instructed by President Somoza to acquaint the
                            Department of State with certain views of the President on current
                            Nicaraguan-Honduran relations. The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss>
                            continues to view with great concern the continued presence in Honduras
                            near the Nicaraguan border of revolutionary groups, which from time to
                            time have made incursions into Nicaragua, the last cited example being
                            that of April 27, 1960. The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> expects
                            the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> to take immediate, effective
                            measures to eliminate these revolutionary groups. Should the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> continue, what the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> considers an evasive attitude on the
                            elimination of these revolutionary groups, then the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> proposes, (1) to withdraw from the
                            Mixed Military Mission now meeting in Tegucigalpa, and (2) to withdraw
                            its Ambassador from Tegucigalpa, since his continued presence there
                            served no useful purpose. President Somoza had also expressed the
                            opinion that President Villeda was misleading the U.S. Ambassador by
                            stating that the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> lacked sufficient
                            facilities to search out and eliminate these revolution groups.
                            President Somoza had stated that the location of the groups was
                            well-known to the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss>, and that members
                            of these groups had circulated freely in Tegucigalpa and had even
                            visited with certain <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> officials.
                            After presenting the above views of President Somoza, Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> requested
                            that the U.S. Government use its good offices through the U.S.
                            Ambassador in Tegucigalpa to press for prompt and decisive action on
                            this matter by the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> observed that
                            President Somoza has every reason to feel as he did <pb facs="hu_d21-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="ni_d21-2"/> in the face of the
                            continued provocations and harassments by these revolutionary groups and
                            he was justified in expecting the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss>
                            to take effective action against those groups using Honduras <pb facs="0961" n="873" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_873"/> as a base of
                            operations. However, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> emphasized that, even though sorely tried by
                            these provocations, it is hoped that President Somoza will bear in mind
                            that Hemispheric obligations constrain all of us to exercise infinite
                            patience and forbearance rather than jeopardize the notable gains we
                            have thus far achieved. This applies particularly to Central America
                            which has experienced during the past few years a series of minor
                            miracles in evolving toward stable, democratic governments. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> illustrated these
                            gains by pointing out (1) that Honduras now enjoys a stable government
                            after years of near-anarchy, (2) that Panama has just experienced the
                            most exemplary election in its history, (3) that the democratic system
                            in Costa Rica continues to flourish in spite of President Echandi having
                            to face a majority opposition in the Costa Rican Assembly and (4) that
                            Guatemala had rid itself of a Communist government and together with
                            Nicaragua and El Salvador are all progressing toward more democratic
                            forms and practices. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> pointed out that the patience of the United
                            States was also being sorely tried in our current relations with Cuba
                            but that we have chosen the path of patience and forbearance, rather
                            than a course of direct action. He expressed the hope that President
                            Somoza would bear all of these things in mind in his current relations
                            with President Villeda and that he would not resort to withdrawal of his
                            Ambassador or of the Nicaraguan members of the Mixed Military
                            Commission. In the meantime, as we have done in the past, the United
                            States will continue to use its good offices in behalf of resolving
                            frictions between Nicaragua and Honduras.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador thanked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> and promised to inform President Somoza of our
                            views.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">2. Request for Asylum by Pro-Batista Exiles</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> said he
                            would also like to mention another matter not related to
                            Nicaraguan-Honduran relations but a matter which had been brought to the
                            fore by the request for asylum in Nicaragua of a group of pro-Batista
                            Cubans now in the Dominican Republic. He stated he had been told by the
                            Dominican Ambassador in Washington, Dr. Luis F. Thomen, that as a result
                            of an “understanding”, or “truce”, between Trujillo and <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Fidel Castro</persName>, some sixty pro-Batista
                            exiles in the Dominican Republic had been given the choice of either
                            leaving the country or being placed in prison. A group of twenty or more
                            of the Cubans have requested President Somoza to grant them asylum in
                            Nicaragua, which request Somoza is reluctant to grant.</p>
                        <p>Another development of which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> was also informed by the Dominican
                            Ambassador, is that Aureliano Sanchez Arango, a Cuban exile, formerly
                            pro-Castro but now in Venezuela, is making a visit to the Dominican
                            Republic. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SSG_1">Sevilla-Sacasa</persName> stated he was at a loss as to how to
                            interpret such a trip by Sanchez Arango, <pb facs="0962" n="874" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_874"/> except that President <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Betancourt</persName> is somehow interested in the
                            current “understanding” between Trujillo and <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> or might be attempting some
                            sort of understanding himself with Trujillo.</p>
                        <pb facs="hu_d21-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="ni_d21-3"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> stated that in his
                            opinion President Somoza should take great care in the matter of
                            granting asylum to a group of pro-Batista exiles, since such a
                            development would undoubtedly have many repercussions unfavorable to
                            Nicaragua. He said he wished it to be clearly understood that, whatever
                            should happen in Cuba, the United States does not want to see another
                            Batista-type regime in Cuba. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                                declassified</hi>] The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> should
                            consider well before taking any action which would favor in any manner
                            the pro-Batista exiles.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>