<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="PA–4" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="pa_d4">
                <head>PA–4. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On July 10, 1958, the Export-Import Bank of Washington announced a $1 million
                    credit to Paraguay to finance installation of Asunción’s first water supply
                    system. An original $7 million credit to Corporación de Obras Sanitarias de
                    Asunción (CORPOSANA) was authorized in 1954 to provide a 15 million
                    gallon-per-day water supply and distribution system for Asunción. The additional
                    credit would enable CORPOSANA to purchase the necessary construction materials
                    and equipment in the U.S. in order to increase the number of service
                    connections, in the water system. Documentation concerning the subject is
                    contained in <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EST_1"
                        >EST</gloss> Files, Lot 62 D 354, “Eximbank.”</p>
                <pb facs="1084" n="996" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_996"/>
                <p>The United States and Paraguay on October 29, 1958, signed a loan agreement
                    making $2.5 million in development loan funds available for completion of an
                    all-weather, rock-surface road in Paraguay known as the Route to Brazil, the
                    funds to be used primarily for financing crushed-rock surfacing of the section
                    between Coronel Oviedo and Puerto Presidente <persName corresp="#p_SGA_1"
                        >Stroessner</persName>. The agreement was signed by Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_PJ_2">Juan Plate</persName> for the Government of Paraguay and
                    Robert B. Menapace, Acting Managing Director of the Development Loan Fund, for
                    the United States. Pertinent documentation is located in <gloss
                        target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EST_1">EST</gloss> Files:
                    Lot 62 D 354, “<gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
