<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="PA–8"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pa_d8">
                <head>PA–8. Despatch from the Ambassador in Paraguay (Ploeser) to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="pa_d8fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Central Files, 734.00/9–959. Confidential.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 100.</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Asunción</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1959-09-09">September 9,
                        1959</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Ambassador’s Report on the Objectives, Progress and Projections of the
                        American Mission in Paraguay<note n="2" xml:id="pa_d8fn2">A handwritten
                            marginal notation reads: “Document read by Asst. Sec. <persName
                                corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> and Amb designate <persName
                                corresp="#p_SHFJ_1">Harry F. Stimpson</persName>.” <persName
                                corresp="#p_SHFJ_1">Stimpson</persName> presented his credentials to
                            the President of Paraguay on October 23, 1959.</note></item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>CONTENTS</head>
                    <item>1. Objectives in Paraguay</item>
                    <item>2. Economic</item>
                    <item>3. Political</item>
                    <item>4. United States Information Service</item>
                    <item>5. Army Attaché</item>
                    <item>6. United States Air Force Mission</item>
                    <item>7. United States Army Mission</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-2"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">1. Objectives in Paraguay</p>
                <p>The objectives of the United States Embassy, as pursued during the past two years
                    in Paraguay, have been: <list>
                        <item>to stabilize the economy and to lay a sound base for
                            development;</item>
                        <item>to establish a mutuality of understanding and confidence so that
                            economic assistance could be programmed with the common purpose of
                            supporting both U.S. policy and Paraguay’s national
                            self-interest;</item>
                        <item>to educate the political thinking of the Government to cooperate with
                            United States objectives in regional and world organizations;</item>
                        <item>to nurture in the people of Paraguay an attitude of friendship and
                            respect for the people of the United States and for our
                            Government;</item>
                        <item>to avoid all appearances of condoning the dictatorship of <persName
                                corresp="#p_SGA_1">General Alfredo Stroessner</persName> and letting
                            it be clearly known that similar cooperation would be extended to any
                            other non-Communist regime which might come to power in Paraguay;
                            and</item>
                        <item>to initiate and foster steps toward democracy in a way that would give
                            no honest pretext for charges of interference.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Measure of Achievement</p>
                <p>We believe that: <list>
                        <item>the measures taken to bring about monetary and fiscal stability have
                            been uniquely successful;</item>
                        <pb facs="1094" n="1006" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1006"/>
                        <item>technical assistance and loan assistance have been applied in a manner
                            that has supported U.S. policy objectives and has been in accord with a
                            reasoned appraisal of Paraguay’s national self-interest;</item>
                        <item>the political thinking of the Government of Paraguay has been educated
                            to express itself in undeviating accord with that of the United States
                            in all regional <pb facs="pa_d8-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                                xml:id="pa_d8-3"/> and international assemblies;</item>
                        <item>the people of Paraguay do radiate and demonstrate a genuine
                            friendliness and respect for North Americans, and being genuine, it has
                            made our tasks here easier and more rewarding;</item>
                        <item>not only have we avoided the pretensions of condoning dictatorship,
                            but on the contrary, we have openly and avowedly advocated the immediate
                            necessity to initiate democratic processes in Paraguay; but</item>
                        <item>the pressures applied to the present government to move it toward
                            greater political liberalism have not been measurably fruitful.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-4"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">2. Economic</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Program Appraisal</hi>—In an effort to evaluate the Country
                    Program for the past two years, we would say:</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Country Team</p>
                <p>All components have been brought together into a harmonious and “hard-hitting”
                    unit. Early in the period, there were discernible sectional weaknesses in the
                    Air Force Mission and in the United States Operations Mission. These debilities
                    were promptly eliminated. For the past year there has not only been the closest
                    cooperation based upon a mutuality of respect, but complete and effective
                    support has been given to all sections of the Embassy. Today, the Country Team
                    is an operational fact rather than only a semantic concept.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">2.</hi> The Stabilization Program</p>
                <p>In December of 1957, the Economic Section of the U.S. Embassy cast a statement of
                    Paraguay’s external indebtedness and her annual service requirements, and then
                    carefully estimated Paraguay’s ability to meet those requirements together with
                    her further absorptive capacity for modest and feasible development. (See
                    Exhibit I—appended<note n="3" xml:id="pa_d8fn3">Not printed.</note>.)</p>
                <p>It is our belief that this was the first time any of the lending agencies of the
                    United States, or the International Bank, or the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1"
                        >IMF</gloss>, had a factual photograph of Paraguay’s external debt
                    obligations or of her potential ability to service them. It is certain that it
                    came as a surprise to the Government of Paraguay.</p>
                <p>Based on that study, the Team was able to recommend credits for selected public
                    works and for private enterprise. The former were directed toward those that
                    would be essential to provide a basis for private investment. Every
                    recommendation was predicated upon the conviction that monetary and fiscal
                    stability had to be reinforced, that <pb facs="1095" n="1007" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_1007"/> inflationary pressures had to be resisted, and that a
                    sound foundation for development had to be laid down.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-5"/>
                <p>This Embassy has [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] supported the
                    contract for continuing monetary stability between the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1"
                        >GOP</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="pa_d8fn4">On August 13, 1959, the Government of Paraguay and the
                        International Monetary Fund entered into a $2.75 million stand-by agreement
                        to facilitate continuation of its fiscal stabilization program. Pertinent
                        documentation is contained in <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_EST_1">EST</gloss> Files, Lot 62 D 354, “<gloss
                            target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>,” and in Department of State decimal file
                        834.10. See also, International Monetary Fund, <hi rend="italic">Annual
                            Report of the Executive Directors for the Fiscal Year Ended April 30,
                            1961</hi> (Washington, 1961), pp. 28–32.</note> Our dealings with the
                    Government have been a synthesis of respect and firmness, and we believe that it
                    is not egotistical to suggest that this relationship has been one of the
                    fundamental reasons for the unique success of the stabilization program in
                    Paraguay since its inception in late 1957.</p>
                <p>At the risk of interrupting the narrative here, we want to make a point of the
                    fact that the Resident Representative of the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1"
                        >IMF</gloss> in Paraguay, Kemal Kurdas, has cooperated with the Embassy so
                    effectively and continuously [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>What has been said of Kemal Kurdas can also be said of Ing. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SG_2">Gustavo Storm</persName>, until a few days ago, President
                    of the Central Bank. Ing. <persName corresp="#p_SG_2">Storm</persName> has been
                    a strong rampart of support for the stabilization program. His policies were
                    formed in constant consultation with the Embassy, with the USOM/P and with the
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>.</p>
                <p>It can be added that there has been an atmosphere of complete integrity
                    maintained between the Ambassador and President Alfredo <persName
                        corresp="#p_SGA_1">Stroessner</persName>. It has been this pattern of honest
                    and open dealing with the President that has made it possible for the Ambassador
                    to obtain his cooperation with the stabilization program in the face of violent
                    attacks—and there have been many violent attacks—by certain members of the
                    Paraguayan cabinet.</p>
                <p>The credits extended in the public sector, e. g., the $2,500,000 for the Brasil
                    Road in 1958 and the $1,000,000 for telecommunications in 1959,<note n="5"
                        xml:id="pa_d8fn5">On August 3, 1959, the Development Loan Fund announced
                        approval of a $1 million loan to the Government of Paraguay to help provide
                        improved telephone, telegraph, and teletypewriter service between Paraguay
                        and other countries. Documentation on the subject is located in <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EST_1">EST</gloss>
                        Files, Lot 62 D 354, “<gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>.”</note> were
                    timed so as to influence the renewal of the stabilization agreements of those
                    years.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-6"/>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>This avoided a crisis at the time the stabilization agreement was up for renewal
                    and this action appears to have successfully forestalled the devious efforts of
                    the communist organization to unleash a general strike. The Embassy received
                    praise from the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> representatives, <pb
                        facs="1096" n="1008" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1008"/> praise to which the
                    Embassy is probably not entitled because we did no more than fulfill our clear
                    responsibilities.</p>
                <p>Summarizing, we would conclude that the Embassy policy has not been one of
                    unreasoned liberality with loans to the Paraguayan Government. Every loan has
                    been timed and sequenced to have the optimum effect politically, on fiscal
                    stability, and to prepare the way for economic development. In this, our liaison
                    has always been tight with the International Bank and its special mission of
                    1956, and with all other lending agencies.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">3.</hi> The United States Operations
                    Mission to Paraguay</p>
                <p>In a manner that would avoid the possibility of creating an impression that the
                    Embassy was trying to direct its affairs, the Embassy has made an evaluation of
                    the past and present programs of the USOM/P. In the process of so doing, the
                    Embassy has received the fullest cooperation of USOM/P’s Director and Assistant
                    Director.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-7" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-7"/>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>Under the firm belief that the United States cannot forever pamper so many
                    nations of the world, or subsidize their legitimate budgetary charges, we have
                    established termination dates for USOM/P’s services and projects. We are
                    convinced that if we are to attain the objectives of <gloss target="#t_ICA_1"
                        >ICA</gloss>, projects must have final date goals as well as goals of
                    accomplishment. The built-in habit of U.S. bureaucracy—as is true of all
                    bureaucracies—to perpetuate itself is an understandable, a human, but a vicious
                    tendency. We can understand why each servicio and each special project has a
                    hundred excuses for its own expansion and perpetuation. At the same time, I want
                    to put it clearly on the record that the Director of USOM/P and his Assistant
                    Director are cognizant of this tendency and are fully with me in putting this
                    practice to the guillotine.</p>
                <p>Appended as Exhibit II<note n="6" xml:id="pa_d8fn6">Not printed.</note> is a list
                    of the projects that are in being, as well as those which are contemplated in
                    the Paraguayan technical aid program, and we have indicated the projected dates
                    of termination.</p>
                <p>It is the firm recommendation of the Embassy, concurred in by USOM/P’s Office of
                    the Director, that these dates be strictly observed.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">4.</hi> Private Enterprise</p>
                <p>The Embassy has placed great emphasis on private enterprise, and as a matter of
                    policy and basic experience, we believe that representative freedom can never be
                    enjoyed unless enterprise is free.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <pb facs="1097" n="1009" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1009"/>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-8" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-8"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">5.</hi> American Business Group</p>
                <p>The Ambassador believes that a U.S. Embassy represents not alone the Government
                    of the U.S., but also the people and that it is the responsibility of the
                    Embassy to have helpful contact with Americans abroad. It has been his policy to
                    receive visiting Americans and to emphasize to those having business in Paraguay
                    that it is the duty and pleasure of the American Mission to serve them. It is
                    suggested that we hope their interest is to develop, not to exploit, and to make
                    friends for the U.S. business generally.</p>
                <p>Twenty-two months ago the Ambassador organized on an invitation basis occasional
                    group meetings of Americans doing business in Paraguay. These meetings were held
                    approximately once monthly in the office of the Ambassador. The current economic
                    conditions were discussed as well as the current American program and policy. On
                    September 4, 1959, the group gave the Ambassador a farewell <hi rend="italic"
                        >asado</hi> and a silver tray as a memento of appreciation. The group has an
                    excellent spirit. To qualify for attendance the guest must be a citizen of the
                    United States. It has been mutually beneficial. In September 1956, while the
                    State Department inspectors were working in Paraguay, the Ambassador held a
                    meeting so as to permit them to attend and observe for themselves. This practice
                    should be continued.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">6.</hi> Private Development Bank<note
                        n="7" xml:id="pa_d8fn7">Pertinent documentation is located in decimal files
                        834.10 and 834.14.</note></p>
                <p>Second only to monetary stability, it has been recognized that the most important
                    economic fact in Paraguay is the unavailability of equity and loan capital for
                    private enterprise. As is true of the Latin American complex of nations,
                    Paraguay has a few people of sizeable wealth and many who live just above the
                    subsistence margin. A history of revolutions and inflations has always carried
                    in its train a sequence of uneconomic investment, hoarding and capital
                    flight.</p>
                <p>In May 1956, the U.S. Ambassador proposed to a representative group of
                    businessmen that a privately-owned development bank be established. The idea was
                    enthusiastically received. But being Paraguayans, they <pb facs="pa_d8-9" n="9"
                        type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-9"/> conceived of a bank in which Paraguayans
                    would not have to invest any money—it would be totally financed by capital
                    pledged from the United States and/or international sources.</p>
                <p>We have changed that idea!</p>
                <p>Through several open meetings and through the establishment of a voluntary
                    businessmen’s committee, the Ambassador made it clear that help would be given
                    only provided Paraguayans put up a substantial equity investment. It took more
                    than one year to effect an organization, <pb facs="1098" n="1010" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_1010"/> to draw up a charter which was approved by the Central
                    Bank, and to obtain a pledge of equity capital.</p>
                <p>The draft charter has been sent to the World Bank (<gloss target="#t_IBRD_1"
                        >IBRD</gloss>) for general comments, and recommendations for the selection
                    of a foreign manager. It is before the <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss> for
                    the same purpose and, additionally, to obtain <gloss target="#t_DLF_1"
                        >DLF</gloss> funds to augment the equity capital pledged by the
                    Paraguayans.</p>
                <p>The response of World Bank has been slow. In the case of the <gloss
                        target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>, the Embassy has had a written commitment for
                    credits at the ratio of 2 to 1 of loans to paid-in capital, with the added
                    expression that this ratio might be expanded once the bank has demonstrated a
                    competent and creditable use of the original loan.</p>
                <p>It is the strong and immediate hope of the Embassy that the <gloss
                        target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss> move quickly to assist Paraguay in the
                    selection of a foreign manager and that it will play a maximum and an effective
                    part in the establishment of this bank without waiting further upon the World
                    Bank. While the Embassy has been insistent upon a foreign manager for the bank,
                    it now makes one Paraguayan exception, which has been approved by the <gloss
                        target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>: <persName corresp="#p_SG_2">Gustavo
                        Storm</persName>, former president of the Central Bank.</p>
                <p>It is the Embassy’s conviction that this private enterprise development bank for
                    Paraguay is of the highest priority; it is an essential and basic step to
                    activate the <pb facs="pa_d8-10" n="10" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-10"/>
                    productive forces of the private sector of this economy. Moreover, it is a basic
                    step to support a continuance of stabilization program.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">7.</hi> Projection</p>
                <p>Based on the assumption it is unlikely that there will be a large inflow of
                    private capital during the next two years, and that a steady and progressive
                    improvement in Paraguay’s economic position will continue to be a difficult
                    task, we believe that our assistance program must have continuity. The
                    fundamental reason for this is that we must give Paraguayan entrepreneurs the
                    assurance that they can count on continued development loan assistance so that
                    planning can take place in a way that will make possible the optimum utilization
                    of manpower and financial resources.</p>
                <p>When it comes to a projection for the next two years, we offer it with a humility
                    that rests upon an awareness that this forecast must ride in the teeth of the
                    hurricane of change that is sweeping over the planet. Nevertheless, our
                    recommendations for loans over the next two years would follow roughly in this
                    sequence and in these priorities:</p>
                <p>a. <hi rend="italic">To the Private Sector</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>That every effort be made to assist in the establishment of a local
                        private enterprise development bank under the direction and control of
                        competent and experienced foreign technicians. This bank could <pb
                            facs="1099" n="1011" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1011"/> accommodate
                        intermediate—and long-term development loans of a <hi rend="italic">modest
                            size</hi>, and it could serve as a vehicle through which future loans
                        could be channeled and most effectively applied in Paraguay;</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>Premised upon the elimination of the existing restrictive controls in
                        cattle raising and meat processing, that a line of credit be extended to the
                            <hi rend="italic">larger</hi> cattle raisers whose needs would outrun
                        the near-term loan capabilities of a development bank;</item>
                    <pb facs="pa_d8-11" n="11" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-11"/>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>That an objective but generous attitude be applied to loan applications to
                        assist in feasible industrialization of forest products, milk processing,
                        fruit packing, sugar-mill renovation, cement plant and fiber development and
                        utilization, and electric power facilities;</item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>In the event the Government’s electric generation and distribution
                        facility (Administración Nacional de Electricidad) is sold to an outside
                        capable and experienced utility operator, that a loan for its renovation and
                        expansion be seriously considered, if needed.</item>
                </list>
                <p>b. <hi rend="italic">To the Public Sector</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Génera</hi>l:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>A basic need of any economy is transportation and communications. In this
                        we must, of course, deal directly with the government. Under the present
                        telecommunications program of Paraguay, completion will give the adequate
                        communications facilities for the foreseeable future, but Paraguay needs
                        roads and more roads to open up the country. This need, which is natural, is
                        made all the more acute with the breakdown of the present antiquated railway
                        system. In this regard we have been negotiating an engineering unit
                        arrangement between the Paraguayan government, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1"
                            >ICA</gloss> and the United States Army, which will be most helpful but
                        not enough. Paraguay will need loans for new roads and for the improvement
                        of old roads.</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>The airport, because of its 9,000 ft. runway, is a suitable “Jet” station
                        and Asunción is coming in for more and more air travel. Within two years a
                        new hotel in down-town Asunción should be completed. Then Asunción will
                        definitely become a tourist attraction as the original “colonial city”
                        (still colonial) and a most suitable location from which to visit Falls
                        Iguazú.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Apron and parking facilities at the airport should be given attention.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-12" n="12" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-12"/>
                <list>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>Loans to the public sector should be extended in harmony with the general
                        philosophy, conditions and cautions set out in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Report</hi> of the Survey Team of the <gloss target="#t_IBRD_1"
                            >IBRD</gloss> dated March 17, 1959,<note n="8" xml:id="pa_d8fn8">A
                            summary of the report is contained in a memorandum from <persName
                                corresp="#p_CCC_1">Carson</persName> to <persName
                                corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName>, March 25, 1959, not
                            printed; <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EST_1"
                                >EST</gloss> Files, Lot 62 D 354, “<gloss target="#t_IBRD_1"
                                >IBRD</gloss>.”</note> which lays <pb facs="1100" n="1012"
                            type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1012"/> particular stress on the need for
                        increased agricultural production and reorganization of the present
                        agricultural credit facilities; and</item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>In harmony with that <hi rend="italic">Report</hi>, that the loans be
                        those needed for transportation—especially feeder roads—and communications
                        facilities; and</item>
                    <label>(5)</label>
                    <item>If a foreign and experienced private utility enterprise cannot be found to
                        take over the Administración National de Electricidad (ANDE) on reasonable
                        terms, and a public loan becomes a necessary final resort, then such a loan
                        be considered, but it should be granted only on the condition that foreign
                        technical and administrative management be clearly stipulated in said loan.
                        Within <gloss target="#t_ANDE_1">ANDE</gloss> there has been much waste and
                        payroll padding through political patronage and the Government can, by
                        cleaning its own house here and in other places, make room for needed
                        improvements through its own revenues.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">8.</hi> Conclusion</p>
                <p>All loans that may be hereinafter extended should be constructed with a knowledge
                    of Paraguay’s annual debt load and service requirements. A reference to Exhibit
                    I indicates that Paraguay has additional debt servicing capabilities from, and
                    including, 1962 and thereafter. The current Central Bank reserve position and
                    the improvement that has occurred in the Bank’s liquidity during 1959 give some
                    basis for confidence that Paraguay can pay any loans which may be granted in the
                    categories listed above—as long as the service payments are extensively limited
                    to 1962 and thereafter.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-13" n="13" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-13"/>
                <p>Finally, it is the considered opinion of this Embassy that, as long as the
                    Government of Paraguay rigidly; adheres to the stabilization program, she should
                    be generausly treated—in accordance with her ability to pay—in the private
                    sector, and that further loans in the public sector should be in accord with the
                    thinking expressed above.</p>
                <p>Appended as Exhibit I is a schedule of Paraguay’s external debt and annual
                    service requirements as they exist at the time of this Report.</p>
                <p>Appended as Exhibit II is a list of projects of USOM/P and their scheduled
                    termination dates.</p>
                <p>Appended as Exhibit III is a schedule of loans made to Paraguay during the past
                    two years by the <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss>, the Ex-Im Bank and the
                    World Bank.<note n="9" xml:id="pa_d8fn9">Not printed.</note></p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-14" n="14" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-14"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">POLITICAL</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Embassy’s Past Action</p>
                <p>Paraguay has a long history of political instability and a “state of siege” has
                    existed almost continually since 1940. President <persName corresp="#p_SGA_1"
                        >Stroessner</persName>
                    <pb facs="1101" n="1013" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1013"/> came to power in 1954
                    by a coup and was elected in a plebiscite and was re-elected without opposition
                    in 1958, for a five-year term to expire on August 15, 1963.</p>
                <p>The GOP’s political weaknesses and instability in the inter-American system are
                    of vital concern. All U.S. economic assistance and counseling has the basic
                    objective of promoting its economic development and thereby political stability
                    which will provide a favorable climate for the establishment of a more
                    democratic government so that it may be a greater force for strength in the
                    Western hemisphere.</p>
                <p><persName corresp="#p_SGA_1">Stroessner</persName>, a so-called “strong man”
                    governing under the 1940 constitution has indicated that he would like to move
                    towards democracy. The Ambassador in various speeches has encouraged Paraguay to
                    take steps towards democratic reforms particularly in his April 13, 1959 speech
                    in which he forcefully stated the U.S. position concerning democracy in the
                    Western hemisphere and made clear that the U.S. position towards Paraguay is not
                    in support of dictatorship as against democracy. In many private conversations
                    the Ambassador has urged <persName corresp="#p_SGA_1">Stroessner</persName> to
                    move toward democracy and has even made suggestions as to laws for free
                    elections, free press, etc. In early 1958 President <persName corresp="#p_SGA_1"
                        >Stroessner</persName> promised Municipal elections and allowed the two
                    opposition parties, Liberal and Febrerista, to hold conventions. Due to a
                    political disturbance, these were nullified. Later, on May 29, 1959, the
                    uni-cameral Congress was dissolved due to a serious open split in the Colorado
                    Party. The Colorado Party and the Army have been the base of Stroessner’s
                    political strength. However, Stroessner’s waxing and waning of democratic moves
                    now include the convocation of congressional elections in February 1960 in which
                    the two opposition parties may participate.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] The Embassy has concentrated on
                    “the <hi rend="italic">people</hi> of the U.S. to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >people</hi> of Paraguay” theme in order not to appear that the U.S. is
                    supporting “dictatorship” in Paraguay as against democracy and also to continue
                    to lay a basis of friendship and cooperation between the two peoples in case of
                    future changes in governments which may occur. In this regard, Embassy officials
                    have kept contact not only with <pb facs="pa_d8-15" n="15" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="pa_d8-15"/> the Colorado Party and government officials but also
                    with opposition party leaders whose members have been received and welcomed in
                    the Embassy.</p>
                <p>The Embassy has continued to encourage free labor movement in labor circles in
                    its personal contacts [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>The Communist Party (PCP) is small, disorganized, and illegal. Its principal
                    threat lies in its penetrations into the various political parties, including
                    the ruling Colorado Party, through which it contributes to political
                    instability. The <gloss target="#t_PCP_1">PCP</gloss> has been active in the
                    student and labor movements but has not gained a dominant position. Most of the
                        <gloss target="#t_PCP_1">PCP</gloss>
                    <pb facs="1102" n="1014" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1014"/> leadership is
                    presently in exile where they play an important role in the subversive planning
                    of the political exiles.</p>
                <p>The Embassy’s plan of action for the present and future is to continue to
                    encourage the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> to take steps towards
                    democratic reforms, short of interference. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>] Possibly one might hope that the dissident clique of the
                    Colorado Party, which has made its break based upon an insistence of democracy
                    within the government, might be the most liberal group. This is more a political
                    promise than a hope, based upon experience. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>] Then too, there is always the private enterprise motive
                    in South American governments, which is certainly not absent in Paraguay. An
                    overturn opens the door for two possibilities which are harmful to U.S.
                    purposes: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Communist infiltration;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>A blow to economic stability.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Because of the fact that the pledged stockholders of the Paraguayan Development
                    Bank project are of all political shades, it is believed that the establishment
                    of this bank will lend a measure of political stability guarding the
                    economy.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-16" n="16" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-16"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Embassy’s Plan of Action for the Present and Future</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Continue to encourage the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> to take
                        steps towards democratic reforms, short of interference.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Continue contacts with dissident political groups.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Continue to encourage the GOP’s support in the United Nations Organization
                        and the Organization of American States and elsewhere.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Continue to encourage free labor movement in its contacts.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>On every possible occasion reiterate our anti-communist position and our
                        support to the free world in public statement as well as private. This
                        should be the political theme of all personnel in the American
                        Embassy.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Continue to encourage the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> to improve
                        its control of Communism.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Continue to expose international communist penetration into Latin
                        America.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-17" n="17" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-17"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">4. United States Information Service</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Accomplishments and Goals</p>
                <p>The American School has been chartered as a bi-national institution. Kindergarden
                    will open with 20 pupils (19 Paraguayans) September 1. In March 1960 it is hoped
                    enrollment will be 70 Americans and 40 Paraguayans. Goal: Funds for “model”
                    American school building.</p>
                <p>Two American students are in National University under the Inter-American
                    Cultural Convention. Paraguayan student will be in <pb facs="1103" n="1015"
                        type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1015"/> University of Texas in September. First
                    time Paraguay has complied with <gloss target="#t_IACC_1">IACC</gloss>
                    obligation.</p>
                <p>Two American professors are in National University, one lecturing in Economics,
                    one advising on complete administrative and curricula revision to “Americanize”
                    higher education in Paraguay. American professor budgeted for 1960 <gloss
                        target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> to aid Engineering faculty.</p>
                <p>On the darker side: PL–480 funds of Fullbright Commission will be spent in <gloss
                        target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1960; need more sales of excess agricultural
                    products to finance long-range educational program launched in 1958–59.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Commentary</p>
                <p>The Embassy believes that the Bi-National Center in Paraguay is very important
                    undertaking and that every effort should be made to expand its activities and
                    coordinate them more in the public-relations sense than in the purely academic
                    sense, and we have really not begun to realize the full potential of this
                    Center. Every effort will be made with the changing of the Director to set up a
                    program which will comply with this goal.</p>
                <p>The Embassy believes that public relations, including the facet of publicity, is
                    a two-way street. A constant flow through the two main channels available in
                    Paraguay’s controlled radio and controlled press of American information and
                    propaganda has been extremely helpful here. It is in good hands, and we are
                    enjoying good, voluminous <pb facs="pa_d8-18" n="18" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="pa_d8-18"/> copy. In the past two years we have also tried to pump
                    into the U.S. press accurate information regarding Paraguay, its opportunities,
                    and its relations with the U.S. While Paraguay is a small nation and does not
                    deserve much space, we feel quite satisfied that it has had its amount
                    proportionately for the first time in history. This channel should be kept open.
                    It benefits our economic opportunities here for American enterprise and benefits
                    Paraguay and certainly benefits relations between the two countries and U.S.
                    objectives abroad.</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-19" n="19" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-19"/>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">5 pages text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-20" n="20" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-20"/>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-21" n="21" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-21"/>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-22" n="22" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-22"/>
                <pb facs="pa_d8-23" n="23" type="facsimile" xml:id="pa_d8-23"/>
                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_PWC_1"><hi rend="strong">Walter C.
                                Ploeser</hi></persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
