<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="PE–17" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pe_d17">
                        <head>PE–17. Memorandum of Conversation, by the Officer in Charge of
                            Peruvian Affairs (Pringle)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="pe_d17fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 723.5-MSP/9–2558.
                                Confidential. Drafted September 26.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-09-25">September 25,
                                1958</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Peruvian Desire for Development Loan Fund Assistance</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_PBR_1">Rául Porras
                                    Barrenechea</persName>, Foreign Minister of Peru</item>
                            <item>Dr. Juan Bautista de Lavalle, Peruvian Ambassador to the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss></item>
                            <item>Sr. Miguel Grau, Minister Counselor, Embassy of Peru</item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> – Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_WST_1">WST</gloss> – Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_WST_1">WST</gloss> – Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PSM_1">Pringle</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister, in discussing the reaction in Peru to the
                            imposition of lead and zinc quotas by the U.S., said that he wished to
                            bring about a greater understanding in his country of the reasons which
                            had led the U.S. to take this action. However, in order to do this and
                            in order <pb facs="1142" n="1054" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1054"/> to
                            demonstrate that the U.S. was still cooperating with Peru, he would have
                            to take something back as concrete evidence of U.S. assistance.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Porras handed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> a
                            short memorandum requesting a loan to finance a National Health
                                Plan.<note n="2" xml:id="pe_d17fn2">The referenced memorandum by the
                                Peruvian Ministry of Public Health and Social Assistance is attached
                                to the source text, but not printed.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> asked whether the plan had
                            been worked out in detail, and the Foreign Minister gave him a copy of a
                            three-page letter dated July 24, 1958, from Minister of Health Sánchez
                            to Dr. Vintinner, Director of <gloss target="#t_SCISP_1">SCISP</gloss>
                            in Peru.<note n="3" xml:id="pe_d17fn3">The referenced letter is attached
                                to the source text, but not printed.</note> The letter describes a
                            national health plan envisaging the construction of numerous hospital
                            and health centers in different parts of the country, the establishment
                            of public health and nursing schools, and the implementation of many
                            other plans for the improvement of public health. The letter requests
                            that the U.S. loan an amount of money sufficient to permit the
                            development of the plan during a three-year period. (Dr. Porras
                            indicated that the sum involved might be in the neighborhood of $30
                            million.)</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> said that this
                            matter would be studied but that he must say in all frankness that the
                                <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss> was very reluctant to make
                            loans in the fields of public health and housing. He explained that the
                            problems involved in those fields were so tremendous that the U.S. could
                            not possibly afford to finance their solution. He said it had been
                            estimated that a billion dollars could be spent annually on housing in
                            Latin America for a generation without solving the housing problem. For
                            that reason, he added, the U.S. tries to direct its economic assistance
                            loans toward <pb facs="pe_d17-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="pe_d17-2"/> productive enterprises so that Latin American
                            nations can increase their productivity and finance the solution of
                            their social problems as their economies grow.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Porras then mentioned a Peruvian application for <gloss target="#t_DLF_1">DLF</gloss> assistance for roads which he said had
                            been presented in Lima. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> said that he had no information regarding this
                            application but that the Department would query Embassy Lima about
                                it.<note n="4" xml:id="pe_d17fn4">The Development Loan Fund
                                authorized a $3.5 million to be supplemented by P.L. 480 funds for
                                highway construction, December 19, 1960. For further information,
                                see Development Loan Fund, <hi rend="italic">Report of Activities
                                    During Calendar Year 1960</hi> (Washington, 1961), p. 3
                                (table).</note></p>
                        <p>Dr. Porras said that he would be at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> in New York for perhaps a week and that he hoped it
                            would be possible for him to take back a favorable decision on a loan to
                            finance the National Public Health Plan when he returned. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ_1">Rubottom</persName> said that the request would
                            be studied but that he could give the Foreign Minister no encouragement
                            in his hope.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>