<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="PE–19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pe_d19">
                        <head>PE–19. Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador in Peru
                                (Achilles)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="pe_d19fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 823.2553/12–1158. Official Use
                                Only. The source text was transmitted to the Department of State
                                under cover of despatch 566 from Lima, December 11.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Lima</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-12-11">December 11,
                                1958</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Petroleum <persName corresp="#p_PWE_1">Price</persName>
                                Increases</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>President Prado</item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_ATC_1">T. C. Achilles</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>During my call on the President this morning, he expressed hope of my
                            support for U. S. financing for a number of development projects, which
                            gave me an opportunity to say that the U.S. attitude toward both public
                            and private investment in Peru could not but be greatly affected by a
                            number of factors, including the strength and stability of the
                            Government and its ability to secure legislation from Congress, a
                            balanced budget, and the treatment of foreign investment as exemplified
                            by the petroleum price problem.</p>
                        <p>I continued that I recognized the domestic political problems involved
                            but that petroleum prices had long been held by the Government at an
                            abnormally low level and that a level permitting continuation of a
                            viable petroleum industry in Peru could not but be of great importance
                            to the future U.S. attitude toward investment here.</p>
                        <p>He replied that he was fully aware of the importance and difficulties of
                            the petroleum industry and of the need for petroleum price increases. He
                            would see that they were granted. There was currently <pb facs="1146" n="1058" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1058"/> a tremendous political
                            uproar over the budget but the Government would nevertheless push
                            through a balanced budget before the end of the month. Then it would
                            take up the petroleum price increases. There would be a similar uproar,
                            probably with strikes and demonstrations, but the price increases would
                            nevertheless be granted.</p>
                        <p>I said I had been disturbed by Prime Minister Gallo Porras’ statement to
                            me yesterday that Congress would not approve the legislation and that
                            the increases should be enacted by decree after Congress had adjourned,
                            subject to approval next July.<note n="2" xml:id="pe_d19fn2">The
                                memorandum of conversation between Prime Minister Porras and
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_ATC_1">Achilles</persName>,
                                December 10, was transmitted to the Department of State with this
                                memorandum of conversation.</note> The Company had repeatedly been
                            promised some such action without results and believed that legislation
                            was necessary. Without specifically stating that it would be done by
                            legislation, although he said there would be another extraordinary
                            session of Congress in January, the President reiterated that the price
                            increases would be put through as soon as the budget had been passed, no
                            matter what the uproar might be.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>