<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="PE–5"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pe_d5">
                <head>PE–5. Letter from President <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName>
                    to President Prado<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="pe_d5fn1">Source: Department
                        of State, Presidential Correspondence, Lot 64 D 174. The source text bears a
                        stamped signature.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1958-04-22">April 22, 1958</date></dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>It gives me special pleasure to transmit to you through the Vice President of the
                    United States, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Richard Nixon</persName>,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="pe_d5fn2">Vice President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Richard M.
                            Nixon</persName> visited Lima, May 7–9, during his trip to South
                        America, April 27–May 15, 1958; for documentation on the South American
                        trip, see pp.</note> my warm greetings. I am gratified that the Vice
                    President was able to accept the cordial invitation which you so kindly extended
                    for him to visit Peru.</p>
                <p>Almost two years have passed since I had the pleasure of meeting you at
                        Panama<note n="3" xml:id="pe_d5fn3">Reference is to the meeting of the
                        American Presidents in Panama, July 21–22, 1956; for documentation, see <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#d160"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                            1955–1957, vol. VII, American Republics: Central and South America, pp.
                            160</ref>, <ref target="frus1955-57v07#pg_271">271</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_277">277</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_278">278</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_710">710</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_717">717</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_921">921</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_923">923</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_1081">1081</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_1132">1132</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v07#pg_1134">1134</ref>.</note> and of sending the
                    Secretary of State, <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">John Foster Dulles</persName>,
                    as my personal representative to your inauguration.<note n="4" xml:id="pe_d5fn4"
                        >Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Dulles</persName> attended
                        President Prado’s inauguration in Lima on August 28, 1956.</note> Since that
                    time, it has been my privilege to correspond with you on several occasions
                    regarding pressing world problems. I have been particularly <pb facs="1117"
                        n="1029" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1029"/> conscious of your deep personal
                    concern with international affairs and of the steadfastness with which you and
                    your representatives have supported constructive measures to advance the cause
                    of world peace with justice. I have also followed with great interest the
                    impressive progress made during your administration in the consolidation of true
                    democracy in Peru and in the maintenance of a free and stable economy.</p>
                <p>Peru and the United States share a firm dedication to the principles of liberty
                    and freedom, and we have also dedicated ourselves with high purpose to the
                    Organization of American States, an inspiring example of peaceful regional
                    cooperation among nations. Long united by bonds of closest friendship, our
                    countries will, I am confident, work together with even greater good will and
                    understanding in the years to come.</p>
                <pb facs="pe_d5-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="pe_d5-2"/>
                <p>In extending my personal regard to Your Excellency, I desire to convey to you and
                    to your countrymen the sincere best wishes of the people of the United States
                    for the continued welfare of your great nation.<note n="5" xml:id="pe_d5fn5">In
                        his reply of May 13 to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName>, President Prado commented favorably on the
                        subjects raised in President Eisenhower’s letter and he stressed the need
                        for U.S. participation in efforts to achieve [illegible in the original] in
                        Latin America. (723.11/5–2358)</note></p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
