<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="PE–39" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pe_d39">
                        <head>PE–39. Despatch from the Chargé in Peru (Neal) to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="pe_d39fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Central Files, 823.2553/2–1860.
                            Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 491</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Lima</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-02-18">February 18,
                                1960</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REF</head>
                            <item>AmEmbassy Tel. No. 736<note n="2" xml:id="pe_d39fn2">Telegram 736
                                    from Lima, February 18, reported on the present conversation.
                                    (823.2553/2–1860)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Conversation with President of Chamber of Deputies</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Re La Brea y Pariñas Problem</p>
                        <p>I told Sr. Javier ORTIZ de ZEVALLOS that I was worried about the trend
                            the La Brea y Pariñas Award matter<note n="3" xml:id="pe_d39fn3">Reference is to a controversy over the status of the International
                                Petroleum Company’s ownership of petroleum deposits in the La Brea y
                                Pariñas property on the northern coast of Peru. A 1922 arbitral
                                award granted the rights to the surface and subsoil of the area to
                                IPC’s predecessor in perpetuity. In the summer of 1959 opponents of
                                the Peruvian Government sought to have the award canceled in the
                                Peruvian Congress. In despatch 546 from Lima, March 11, 1960, the
                                Embassy submitted a background study of the controversy with
                                pertinent documents. (823.2553/3–1160)</note> had taken and that my
                            concern was shared by the Department of State in Washington.</p>
                        <p>He shook his head and said, “This is a very complicated problem.” I
                            agreed with this and said I was disturbed about the feeling in Congress
                            during the last days of the session and sensed a feeling of
                            expropriation.” He said, “No, you don’t have to worry about that.”<note n="4" xml:id="pe_d39fn4">At least two opposition deputies spoke in
                                favor of expropriation during the recent debate. [Footnote is in the
                                source text.]</note> He stated Peru had never broken an
                            international obligation and was not going to do so in this
                            instance.</p>
                        <p>I then asked him how the matter was to be resolved and didn’t he think
                            there could be a compromise solution such as “adapting” or <pb facs="1199" n="1111" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1111"/> bringing the
                            International Petroleum Company’s La Brea y Pariñas concessions under
                            the Petroleum Code.<note n="5" xml:id="pe_d39fn5">In despatch 546 of
                                March 11, the Embassy informed the Department that “since 1957, the
                                company has sought, unsuccessfully, to bring its operations under
                                the Petroleum Law [of 1952], which would permit it to renounce its
                                title to the subsoil of the property and to carry on its
                                exploration, development and production activities as a
                                concessionnaire.”</note> I said I felt IPC would be willing to give
                            up certain privileges in order to adapt its operations to the Code.<note n="6" xml:id="pe_d39fn6">In despatch 621 from Lima, April 21, the
                                Embassy reported that Jack Ashworth, General Manager of the company,
                                had made an offer in writing to Prime Minister Beltrán for 50
                                percent Peruvian Government participation in the company’s net
                                earnings. (823.2553/4–2160)</note></p>
                        <p>He said this solution would never be acceptable to the opposition. He
                            stated Pedro BELTRAN had suggested this but it was not acceptable and
                            such a move had no chance at all for approval. I asked why he was so
                            certain of this.</p>
                        <p>Sr. Ortiz de Zevallos said (IPC’s) La Brea y Pariñas concession
                            terminated in 1972.<note n="7" xml:id="pe_d39fn7">The concession
                                presumably would end in accordance with a provision in the
                                British-Peruvian Agreement of Settlement of March 2, 1922, providing
                                that on January 1, 1972, at the end of a 50-year period, the
                                property would become subject to payments under Peruvian laws then
                                in effect or enacted thereafter. (Enclosure 8 to despatch 546 of
                                March 11)</note> On that date, “Talara (the Company’s refinery and
                            installations) will belong to Peru.” The opposition realizes this and if
                            a bill is presented “adapting” IPC to the Petroleum Code it would call
                            for an extension of IPC’s concessions for an additional 20 or 30 years.
                            He said “IPC does not have a friend in Congress, not one, therefore they
                            are not going to be allowed to extend their concessions.”</p>
                        <pb facs="pe_d39-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="pe_d39-2"/>
                        <p>I then asked him whether Peru intended to operate its own oil industry. I
                            said if IPC realized it was not going to obtain an extension of its
                            concession rights then I could imagine the company would cease its
                            investments, terminate its exploration and development operations, and
                            that by 1972 the industry would be in such condition that it would be
                            very difficult for the Government (if it failed to renew the concession
                            before that date) to assume responsibility for operating the industry. I
                            said if the Government did have to take over the industry one of the
                            first necessary moves would be to increase the price of products—a step
                            which would be most unpopular with the people.</p>
                        <p>Sr. Ortiz de Zevallos said, “The company will have to keep the industry
                            going during this time—why shouldn’t it, it has made so much money in
                            the past and with its latest price increase, why shouldn’t it?”</p>
                        <p>The President of the Chamber of Deputies spoke again and again about the
                            unpopularity of IPC. He said the company had no friends anywhere in the
                            country. He said not a Member of Congress or a Cabinet <pb facs="1200" n="1112" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1112"/> Minister could stand up
                            and make a favorable remark in IPC’s behalf. If anyone did so, he would
                            be charged with taking a pay-off from IPC. He said IPC has always had
                            poor public relations: “They don’t know how to handle this situation.”
                            He said they expect that paying 40,000 soles for an advertisement in <hi rend="italic">El Comercio</hi>, which is one of IPC’s big critics,
                            helps, but it does not. He criticized IPC officials, saying they are
                            difficult to deal with. He said he sent one of his representatives to
                            IPC only a few weeks ago but his man received a “brush-off.” He stated
                            IPC had sent him copies of its position on La Brea y Pariñas for
                            distribution to each member of the Chamber of Deputies. He said, “I
                            returned all of them to the company and then telephoned to see whether
                            they had been received. This was not the way to handle the matter.”</p>
                        <p>He said if I would think about it a minute I would realize that IPC is
                            unique in the hate it has generated in Peru. He said companies producing
                            lead and zinc, cotton, sugar, fish, and copper are popular with the
                            people, and these companies can be defended, but not IPC and
                            petroleum.</p>
                        <p>According to Ortiz de Zevallos, IPC has always been unpopular because it
                            inherited a “dirty business.” He said the original Award was brought
                            about by graft to certain persons in France and to the Peruvians who put
                            over the deal. He said he and his father (former Ambassador)<note n="8" xml:id="pe_d39fn8">Reference is to Emilio Ortiz de Zevallos who was
                                Second Secretary of the Peruvian Embassy in France at the time of
                                the La Brea y Pariñas Award in 1922.</note> were talking only this
                            morning about the Award and that his father was in Paris when the Award
                            was made and remembered the talk of the “pay-offs” at that time. He said
                            his father warned him about the matter and had convinced him that it was
                            an illegal thing from the start.</p>
                        <pb facs="pe_d39-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="pe_d39-3"/>
                        <p>I told him I knew the stockholders of IPC would like to know just what
                            could be done to place this in the proper light. He said he didn’t know
                            but that “building a few houses in Talara” (the IPC housing project in
                            Talara was one of the first in Peru and was quite well done) and putting
                            advertisements in <hi rend="italic">El Comercio</hi> was not going to
                            win friends. (Comment: Ortiz de Zevallos is quite right about Talara
                            housing, it was never received as it should have been.)</p>
                        <p>I kept pressing the President for his idea of a solution. He said, “Pedro
                            Beltrán is a good friend of the United States. I am certain he will have
                            some formula.” At the same time, he stated that when the President
                            returns from Paris he is going to concentrate on La Brea y Pariñas
                                matter.<note n="9" xml:id="pe_d39fn9">President Prado returned to
                                Peru on March 11 after a 28-day official visit to France, the United
                                Kingdom, Italy, Switzerland, the Federal Republic of Germany, and
                                the Netherlands. In despatch 575 from Lima, March 29, the Embassy
                                reported on a March 22 radio and television address by President
                                Prado on his trip. (823.00/3–3960)</note></p>
                        <pb facs="1201" n="1113" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1113"/>
                        <p>Several times, he told me “the opposition” was going to delay the problem
                            as long as possible because it will make a great “banders” (issue) in
                            the 1962 election. He said with all the opposition to IPC this is
                            something which will appeal to the people.</p>
                        <p>I told the President that 1972 was going to roll around quicker than he
                            thought and that no large concern was going to wait until the last
                            minute to attempt to negotiate a contract on an oil concession or
                            monopoly with a nation. I said I felt certain it would be necessary to
                            start negotiation on a settlement before 1972 and this would not only be
                            in the interest of the company, but also beneficial to the people of
                            Peru. He admitted this.</p>
                        <p>I stated that if IPC is as unpopular as he feels it is (I personally
                            believe he has the correct feel on this because it has become a real
                            popular subject with no IPC backers), I was certain the shareholders
                            would want to do something to correct the situation, therefore what was
                            the answer? He said that expropriation was not the solution because Peru
                            knew better than to try to buck the big international oil concerns. He
                            realized that Peru would need foreign markets and that it could not
                            compete with the big companies if Peru tried to take over alone. He said
                            he saw a partnership deal as now exists in other countries.</p>
                        <p>I stated that as he already knew IPC was owned almost wholly by ESSO and
                            that ESSO is acquiring sole ownership; and that maybe the solution would
                            be to take the name of IPC entirely out of the picture and make it ESSO
                            of Peru. He said, “something like that.”</p>
                        <p>I told the President that our concern over La Brea y Pariñas did not
                            center altogether around IPC, but that we were worried about the adverse
                            effects an unfavorable decision would have on the climate for foreign
                            investment in Peru. Any discriminatory action here would make us start
                            worrying about other United States investments such as Toquepala, Cerro
                            de Pasco, Marcona, etc., etc.</p>
                        <pb facs="pe_d39-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="pe_d39-4"/>
                        <p>Sr. Ortiz de Zevallos said I need not worry because IPC was a case within
                            itself—“an isolated case.” He stated several times that this matter had
                            nothing to do with anti-American sentiment. He said, “if you will think
                            back on all the discussions and debates in Congress you will note that
                            not once was the name of the United States mentioned—no U.S. imperialist
                            talk—no anti-American sentiments.” He said he was afraid the <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1">Eisenhower</persName> visit to Chile was going to
                            be mentioned and touch off remarks of ill feeling but this did not
                            happen.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1"><hi rend="strong">Jack D.
                                        Neal</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>