<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="PM–60"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="pm_d60">
                <head>PM–60. Memorandum from the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs (Mallory) to the Acting Secretary of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="pm_d60fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>/PAN Files, Lot 65 D 176, “Relations-Panama
                        July 1960.” Secret. Drafted by Sharp. The source text is an uninitialled
                        carbon copy.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1960-09-23">September 23,
                        1960</date></dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Ceremony on Occasion of Initial Flying of Panamanian Flag in Canal
                        Zone.</item>
                </list>
                <p>This paper is in response to your oral request of this morning for the background
                    on the decision to hold a ceremony on the occasion of the initial flying of the
                    Panamanian flag in the Canal Zone.</p>
                <p>The actual genesis of the concept of a ceremony is not clear but Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_FJF_1">Farland</persName> reported on September 17
                    that Governor Carter was desirous of a “formal but simple flag raising ceremony
                    with President de la Guardia in attendance” and he requested instructions in
                    this regard. (Tab A).<note n="2" xml:id="pm_d60fn2">Not attached to the source
                        text. The document at Tab A, telegram 156 from Panama City, September 17, is
                        printed as <ref target="#pm_d59">Document PM–59</ref>.</note></p>
                <pb facs="1076" n="988" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_988"/>
                <p>The Department approved such a ceremony subject to agreement between the Governor
                    and the Ambassador on the procedure and that all physical duties involved be
                    carried out by U.S. personnel. (Tab B).<note n="3" xml:id="pm_d60fn3">Not
                        attached to the source text. For a summary of the document at Tab B,
                        telegram 142 to Panama City, September 17, see <ref target="#pm_d59fn3"
                            >Document PM–59, footnote 3</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_FJF_1">Farland</persName> on September 20
                    recommended that President de la Guardia be invited to raise the Panamanian flag
                    at the ceremony, (Tab C)<note n="4" xml:id="pm_d60fn4">Not attached to the
                        source text. The document at Tab C, not printed, was telegram 160 from
                        Panama City, September 20; 719.04/9–2060.</note> but the Department turned
                    down that recommendation on the grounds that (a) it would be a precedent for the
                    possible further exercise of sovereign rights in the Zone by Panama thus
                    prejudicing our treaty position and (b) would expose us to even greater
                    Congressional and public criticism in this country than that to which we have
                    already been subjected. The Department did, however, authorize a ceremony, the
                    extent of which was left to Ambassador Farland’s discretion. (Tab D).<note n="5"
                        xml:id="pm_d60fn5">Not attached to the source text. The document at Tab D,
                        not printed, was telegram 144 to Panama City, September 20;
                        719.04/9–2060.</note></p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the genesis of the decision, it appeared that the initial display
                    of the Panamanian flag with ours in the Canal Zone as a symbol of Panama’s
                    titular sovereignty, would require some formal ceremony were it to have the
                    desired impact on Panamanians, for a routine raising without any note being
                    taken of the event, could well be interpreted as an off-hand and rather
                    ungracious performance of an act, which was intended to have emotional
                    impact.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
