<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-04-25T20:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-04-25T20:13:00-05:00" n="VE–40" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="ve_d40">
                        <head>VE–40. Telegram from the Secretary of State to the Embassy in
                                Venezuela<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="ve_d40fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 731.00/4–2560. Confidential.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_JEA_1">Jamison</persName> and
                                initialled by the Deputy Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MLD_1">Mallory</persName>. Repeated to the Embassies
                                in Colombia, Cuba, and the Dominican Republic.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-04-25T21:13:00-04:00">April 25,
                                    1960, 9:13 p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>914. Recent Castro-Leon rebellion attempt,<note n="2" xml:id="ve_d40fn2">Reference is to Jesús María Castro-León. Documentation concerning
                                his activities is contained in decimal files 731.00/1–1160 and
                                731.00/4–2560.</note> particularly with implication <gloss target="#t_GODR_1">GODR</gloss> advance knowledge if not direct
                            involvement, regarded by Dept as additional manifestation international
                            tensions Caribbean area which Inter-American Peace Committee directed to
                            study by Santiago Fonmin Mtg Res IV. Request you inform Fomin or
                            President as appropriate U.S. Chairman <gloss target="#t_IAPC_1">IAPC</gloss> considering suggesting that Committee, noting apparent
                            increase in Caribbean tensions, renew its request of September 18, 1959
                            to all <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> Govts that they provide any
                            information they may have regarding such tensions in order to aid
                            Committee in preparation general report required under Res IV. In this
                            connection would be desirable for Venezuela and Colombia submit any
                            evidence re international aspects recent Castro-Leon rebellion and we
                            would appreciate knowing whether they would do this.</p>
                        <pb facs="1384" n="1296" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1296"/>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss> We believe Castro-Leon attempt and
                            other recent incidents Caribbean area emphasize desirability information
                            be provided <gloss target="#t_IAPC_1">IAPC</gloss> and studied by it in
                            relation broader problem Caribbean tensions. Above would offer
                            opportunity for Colombia provide data re <gloss target="#t_GODR_1">GODR</gloss> official requests for visas for those subsequently
                            involved in rebellion attempt and for <gloss target="#t_GOV_1">GOV</gloss> furnish any information.</p>
                        <pb facs="ve_d40-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="ve_d40-2"/>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_GODR_1">GODR</gloss> complicity it may have, as well as
                            occasion for U.S. to produce relevant information its possession.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HCA_1"><hi rend="strong">Herter</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>