<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The High Commissioner in Haiti ( (Russell) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-03-21T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-03-21T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-03-21T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-03-21T14:00:00-05:00" n="182"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.00 Elections/9: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Russell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-03-21T14:00:00-05:00"
                            >March 21, 1930—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 8:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>41. Referring to my urgent telegram 40, March 21, 2 p.m. I have just had a note
                    from the Haitian Government as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In accordance with the so-called Hoover plan proposed on March 15, 1930,
                            by President Hoover’s Commission<note n="22" xml:id="d182fn22">See
                                telegram No. 11, March 15, 1930, from the Chairman of the
                                President’s Commission, <ref target="#pg_207">p. 207</ref>.</note>
                            and approved by our two Governments, the various groups of the
                            Opposition were on March 20, to elect Mr. Eugene Roy in accordance with
                            the very terms of the plan to be a ‘candidate for the Presidency whose
                            name would be submitted to the Council of State,’ in the above quality
                            as candidate.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The note further points out that the procès-verbal referred to in my
                    above-referred-to telegram violates the plan in the three respects named by me
                    in that telegram.</p>
                <p>The note concludes as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“We are therefore in full revolution, anarchy is complete.</p>
                        <p>Despite the Constitutional Government of the Republic, despite the
                            American Government which has undertaken by treaty to maintain that
                            Constitutional Government, Opposition groups without any popular mandate
                            are arrogating to themselves the right to issue a decree proclaiming a
                            citizen temporary President and that in derogation of the Hoover plan
                            which only authorized the simple approval of a ‘coalition candidate’ to
                            submit on the 14th of April to the vote of the Council of State.</p>
                        <p>The Haitian Government through me (Minister for Foreign Affairs) hereby
                            formally renews the protest contained in my letter of yesterday and
                            considers itself henceforth relieved of any obligation accruing to it as
                            a result of the Hoover plan manifestly violated by the Opposition.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The protest of yesterday, above referred to, related to the wording of the
                    invitation of the Patriotic groups and was satisfactorily adjusted. See my
                    telegram 36 March 20, 9 a.m.</p>
                <p>I propose tomorrow to inform President Borno that I have transmitted the contents
                    of his note to the Department and that I consider the decision mentioned in the
                    last paragraph of the above-mentioned note to be precipitate and
                    ill-advised.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Russell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
