<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-03-31T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-03-31T10:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.00 Elections/15: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Russell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-03-31T10:00:00-05:00">March 31, 1930—10
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:26 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>50. Department’s 35, March 29, 3 [<hi rend="italic">4</hi>] p.m. Have
                            informed President Borno of the contents of the above telegram. He has
                            assured me that he will urge Council of State to elect Mr. Roy and is
                            sending the names of certain members of the Council of State to me with
                            the request that I talk with them. I informed him I would urge them to
                            carry out the plan. President Borno is concerned that his party will not
                            be considered when the new administration comes into office on May 15th.
                            I told him that the President’s Commission had spoken to the leaders of
                            the opposition on this matter and urged that Mr. Roy’s administration be
                            a coalition one and that when opportunity offered I intended to speak to
                            Mr. Roy along the same lines. President Borno feels that if he urges the
                            Council of State to elect Mr. Roy, as he intends doing, there is a
                            strong probability of Roy’s election.</p>
                        <p>President Borno then stated that, purely as a theoretical matter, he
                            would like to direct my attention to article 34 of the Constitution and
                            ask how my [<hi rend="italic">the?</hi>] Deputies or Senators could
                            enter into the functions of their office prior to the first Monday of
                            April 1932. I replied that this was a question to be discussed with the
                            new administration.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Russell</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>