<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-12-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.00/2915</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Munro</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-05">December 5, 1930</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                December 9.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 14</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my telegram No. 249,
                            December 5, 1930, 1 p.m.,<note n="51" xml:id="d222fn51">Not
                                printed.</note> I have the honor to transmit herewith copies in
                            French and <pb facs="0356" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/> English of the plan
                            prepared by the Haitian Government for the immediate Haitianization of
                            the Treaty Services.</p>
                        <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs called at the Legation and handed this
                            plan to me with the statement that it was intended to serve as a basis
                            for discussion and that he and the President would like to talk the
                            whole subject over with me and reach an understanding satisfactory to
                            both governments regarding the course to be pursued. I promised to study
                            the plan and said that I should probably wish to submit a matter of this
                            importance to the Department for its consideration.</p>
                        <p>This morning, when I called on the Minister for Foreign Affairs about
                            another matter, he asked me whether I was prepared to discuss the
                            Haitianization plan. I said that I had not yet completed my study of it,
                            but that I would endeavor to do so as soon as possible. I remarked,
                            however, that I thought that it would prove impossible to carry out the
                            Haitianization of the Treaty Services as rapidly as the plan
                            contemplated. The Minister said that the question of time was not
                            particularly important so long as there was no doubt about the ultimate
                            intention of the Government of the United States to turn over the
                            control of the Treaty Services in accordance with the Forbes plan.<note n="52" xml:id="d222fn52">See report of the President’s Commission
                                for the Study and Review of Conditions in the Republic of Haiti,
                                    <ref target="#pg_217">p. 217</ref>.</note> He said that the
                            Haitian Government wished to proceed in the closest harmony with the
                            Legation in this matter and also wished to effect the change in such a
                            way as to preserve the efficiency of the Treaty Services. His statement
                            confirmed my impression based on information from unofficial sources
                            that the purpose of the Government in presenting the plan was to
                            convince the public that it was carrying out the platform on which it
                            had been elected, rather than to attempt to force any immediate radical
                            changes in the Treaty Services. Mr. Chauvet, whose attitude is well
                            known to the Department, remarked to one of the Secretaries of the
                            Legation that the acceptance in full of the plan by the United States
                            would of course be a betrayal of trust and would show a disregard of our
                            obligations under the Treaty. I may say that the Government has
                            permitted the publication of the substance of the plan in the
                            newspapers.</p>
                        <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs has informed me that the Government will
                            subsequently present a plan dealing with the Garde d’Haiti. I suspect
                            that it is not prepared to request such rapid Haitianization of this
                            organization as of the other Treaty Services.</p>
                        <p>I intend to discuss the problem of Haitianization in each Treaty Service
                            with the Treaty Officials during the next few days. As the Department is
                            aware, the Treaty Services have already worked out more or less definite
                            programs for Haitianization and I intend to use these as a basis for
                            further discussion with the Haitian Government. <pb facs="0357" n="263" xml:id="pg_263"/> I shall keep the Department informed of all
                            developments and shall request instructions when matters have reached a
                            point where it appears proper to do so.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dana G. Munro</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Haitian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sannon</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Munro</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <p>The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments
                                to His Excellency M. Dana G. Munro, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                                Plenipotentiary of the United States of America and has the honor to
                                submit to him, in accordance with their interview, the plan prepared
                                by the Haitian Government for the immediate Haitianization of the
                                Public Services established by virtue of the Treaty between Haiti
                                and the United States, a plan based upon the recommendations of the
                                Forbes Commission and in conformity with the declarations of
                                President Hoover.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-02">December 2,
                                        1930</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Plan for Haitianization of the Treaty Services,
                                    Based on the Recommendations of the Forbes Commission and in
                                    Conformity with the Declarations of President Hoover</hi></head>
                            <p>During the last fifteen years, the Haitians have been sufficiently
                                trained in the functioning of the different Treaty Services.<note n="53" xml:id="d222fn53">For summaries of reports of the treaty
                                    services, see <hi rend="italic">Eighth Annual Report of the
                                        American High Commissioner at Port au Prince, Haiti, to the
                                        Secretary of State, 1929.</hi></note> It now remains to
                                complete their training in executive functions within wisely
                                prescribed periods for the Haitianization of the said Services.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Travaux Publics</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Maximum period for Haitianization: 1 year.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Immediate appointment of a Haitian Engineer-in-Chief who will
                                    direct the service, the duties of the present American Engineer,
                                    during the Haitianization period, to consist in giving technical
                                    advice to the Government and lending it his assistance.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>On the first of December of next year, the duties of the
                                    American Advisor-Engineer shall cease and the Haitian
                                    Engineer-in-Chief shall remain in sole charge of the technical
                                    service of the Department.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Immediate dismissal of all foreign employees, engineers or
                                    others who are not commissioned.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Replacement of all foreign employees who are not commissioned
                                    by Haitians, according to the needs of the service.</item>
                                <pb facs="0358" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Within three months, all the section chiefs of the department
                                    of Public Works shall be Haitians.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Immediate commencement of road building, with the object of
                                    completing the Haitian road system. This work shall be carried
                                    out in conformity with decisions which shall be given by the
                                    Haitian Government. For the time being, no large bridges shall
                                    be constructed of which the cost exceeds the present capacity of
                                    the Treasury.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Incorporation of the School of Applied Sciences in the Public
                                    Works Service, for the training and assured recruiting of
                                    technical personnel.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Creation of an apprentice school of Public Works at the side
                                    of the School of Applied Sciences, designed to train foremen and
                                    competent workmen for the different branches of the
                                    Service.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>Immediate suppression of the agency of the D. G. T. P. in New
                                    York for the furnishing of material to the Service. Opening of
                                    bids for the supply of this material in conformity with Haitian
                                    law, in the interest of commerce.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Service d’Hygiene</hi></p>
                            <p>Maximum Haitianization period: 2 years.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Immediate Haitianization of the sanitary districts.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Immediate appointment of a Haitian co-director of the Haitian
                                    General Hospital, who will assume exclusive direction of this
                                    establishment from the first of December of next year.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Immediate appointment of a Haitian co-director-general of the
                                    Service d’Hygiene. Upon the expiration of the two years
                                    prescribed for the Haitianization of this Service, the Haitian
                                    co-director-general will assume the sole direction
                                    thereof.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>In posts in this Service which cannot be occupied immediately
                                    by a Haitian, either due to lack of technical experience or for
                                    any other reason recognized by the two high parties, shall be
                                    directed jointly by the present head and a Haitian shall be
                                    attached to him until this latter will be sufficiently trained
                                    in the executive functions, either technical or
                                    administrative.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>During the two years for the Haitianization of this Service,
                                    intensive training of Haitian doctors shall be carried on
                                    throughout the Service.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Service Technique</hi></p>
                            <p>Maximum period for Haitianization: 2 years.</p>
                            <p>Division of the Service into two distinct branches: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Primary rural and urban instruction and professional
                                        instruction.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Agricultural instruction and experimental stations for the
                                        improvement and intensification of agriculture.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <pb facs="0359" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/>
                            <p>Branch (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of this Service shall be directed
                                by a Haitian.</p>
                            <p>The direction of branch (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) can be given to a
                                foreign specialist. In that case a Haitian sub-director shall be
                                attached.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">(a) primary rural and urban
                                    instruction and professional instruction</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Transformation of the Ecole Centrale into a Normal School for
                                    the creation of professors for all primary and professional
                                    schools of the Republic. This Normal School shall be divided
                                    into two sections: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>Classical Section.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>Professional Section.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The existing Normal School for girls shall be reorganized in
                                    such a way as to form the basis of the recruitment of the girl
                                    schools of the Republic.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Primary instruction shall constitute, together with the
                                    professional instruction, a unified system having at its head a
                                    special director and inspectors.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The setting up of such a structure may require the aid of
                                    competent foreigners at the beginning. These foreigners shall be
                                    employed by the Haitian Government on a temporary basis prior to
                                    the training of Haitians chosen to replace them after the period
                                    of Haitianization.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The professional schools will only be open to those holding a
                                    certificate of primary instruction of the first class or to
                                    those who at least can read and write. These schools shall be
                                    organized in such a way as to be wholly or largely
                                    self-supporting.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">(b) agricultural instruction and
                                    experimental stations for the improvement and intensification of
                                    agriculture</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>The improvement and intensification of agriculture shall be
                                    undertaken first of all by the division of the country, into
                                    agricultural districts, each one directed by an agricultural
                                    agent and his assistants.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>The creation of agricultural agents shall be accomplished by a
                                    special agricultural school, this school to be essentially
                                    practical, where only the primary school certificate of second
                                    class shall be required for admission.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>In addition, there shall be created a system of agricultural
                                    experimental stations, established on an absolutely commercial
                                    basis.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>The agricultural station shall have as its object, in addition
                                    to conducting the necessary experiments for the purpose of
                                    adapting the surest methods for the cultivation of our principal
                                    products and with the object of introducing into the country new
                                    plants of commercial value, to cultivate on a grand scale any
                                    product which can be <pb facs="0360" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                                    grown in the region where it will be established and permitting
                                    it not only to cover expenses but also to make a profit.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>A sales agency shall be charged with marketing the production
                                    of the experimental stations.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>At the head of the system of experimental stations and the
                                    sales agency there shall be established an administrative
                                    council, renewable every two years, on a very broad basis, with
                                    the object of assuring a strict control of all the commercial
                                    operations of the experimental stations and the sales
                                    agency.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>The Government shall advance the first funds necessary for the
                                    proper functioning of the experimental stations.</item>
                                <label>13.</label>
                                <item>A foreign technical advisor may be attached to the Department
                                    of Agriculture, whose duties shall consist in giving to the
                                    Secretary of Agriculture advice in all matters concerning
                                    practical agriculture and agricultural extension.</item>
                                <label>14.</label>
                                <item>The technical advisor shall be employed by a contract duly
                                    made with the Haitian Government. The period of this contract
                                    shall not exceed the Haitianization period of the Service. It
                                    shall be renewable at the option of the parties thereto.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">IV. Service of the Financial
                                    Adviser-General Receiver</hi></p>
                            <p>Maximum Haitianization period: 2 years.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Immediate and complete Haitianization of the Contributions
                                    Service.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Immediate and complete Haitianization of the customs
                                    personnel.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Progressive Haitianization of the office of the Financial
                                    Adviser-General Receiver during the period of two years.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>General principle: Wherever it shall be demonstrated that a
                                    Haitian cannot be appointed immediately, a Haitian shall be
                                    attached to the present office holder and the function shall be
                                    transferred to the Haitian as soon as his administrative
                                    instruction shall be considered sufficient.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The immediate re-establishment of the Haitian control
                                    institution, known as <hi rend="italic">Chambre des
                                        Comptes.</hi></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Re-establishment and reorganization of the <hi rend="italic">Bureaux de l’Enregistrement</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Conservation des Hypothèques.</hi></item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>