<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-11-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">150.946/240</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Castle</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation
                                With the Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Debuchi</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-11-04">November 4, 1930</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>As he told the Secretary he planned to do, the Ambassador came to see me
                            to discuss the Japanese exclusion question. Mr. Debuchi said he had come
                            to Washington with the hope that he might be able to straighten out
                            three matters, or at least help along those lines. One was naval
                            rivalry, one was misunderstandings over <pb facs="0410" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> China, the other the immigration question. The
                            Ambassador said that the London Agreement<note n="4" xml:id="d261fn4">Signed April 22, 1930; <ref target="frus1930v01#pg_107">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 107</ref>.</note> had happily
                            settled the naval question; that there seemed no longer to be any
                            Chinese question between the two Governments. Japan’s attitude toward
                            China was practically identical with that of the United States. There
                            remained the immigration question. The Ambassador said that he had
                            talked with a great many people while he was on the Pacific Coast and
                            had found great friendliness, in fact had seen no one who was opposed to
                            putting Japan on the quota. He said that he had always let other people
                            bring the matter up and had not introduced it himself because he knew
                            the danger of appearing to bring any kind of pressure. For the same
                            reason he said that he wanted his talk with me to be entirely unofficial
                            and secret, that he should not telegraph his Government anything about
                            it, but would write merely a personal letter to Baron Shidehara.<note n="5" xml:id="d261fn5">Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                            We discussed the matter from all angles. Mr. Debuchi thoroughly
                            understands that it cannot be introduced in Congress by the Department
                            of State; also that it should be brought up as originating on the
                            Pacific Coast but he fears that no California Senator or Congressman
                            will be prodded to introduce the matter and that it may simply go by
                            default. He said it seemed to him that all the psychological elements
                            were present to make a change in the law successful at the present time
                            and that if it could not be effected in the next session of Congress he
                            would feel there was little hope. I told him that he should not have
                            this feeling because the next, or short session of Congress, which might
                            well be very turbulent, was not a good time to get through legislation.
                            I pointed out that obviously nothing must be done until we were sure of
                            a favorable result since a reaffirmation of the exclusion would be worse
                            than the original law.</p>
                        <p>I gained nothing new from this conversation, nor did the Ambassador,
                            except I think that he realized, as he had perhaps not done before, that
                            we were watching the situation carefully.</p>
                        <closer><signed>W[<hi rend="smallcaps">illiam</hi>] R. C[<hi rend="smallcaps">astle</hi>], <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>