<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-04-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="300" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">882.5048/282</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Proclamation by President King of Liberia</hi><note n="25" xml:id="d300fn25">Printed copy transmitted to the Department
                                by the Chargé in Liberia in despatch Diplomatic No. 52, May 8;
                                received June 5.</note></head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">A Proclamation by the
                            President</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, in consequence of representations
                            having been made against the Government of the Republic of Liberia in
                            relation to Slavery and forced Labour, the President of the Republic of
                            Liberia proposed the setting up of a Commission of Enquiry to
                            investigate the alleged existence in Liberia of these social conditions
                            and in pursuance of said proposal and for the purpose of assuring an
                            impartial enquiry and an authoritative report, did request the
                            Secretariat of the League of Nations and the Government of the United
                            States of America to nominate each a member to serve on the said
                            Commission so proposed to be set up by the Government of Liberia;
                            and</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Legislature of the Republic of
                            Liberia by a Joint Resolution of the Senate and House of Representatives
                            approved December 12, 1929, did confirm said action of the President of
                            the <pb facs="0440" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/> Republic and did authorize
                            him to take all proper steps to effectuate the object of the proposed
                            Commission of Enquiry; and</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, in pursuance of the request made as
                            aforesaid to the Secretariat of the League of Nations and to the
                            Government of the United States of America certain nominations of
                            members to serve on the Commission were made by the League of Nations
                            and the Government of the United States of America, which nominations
                            were accepted by the Government of the Republic of Liberia, that is to
                            say:</p>
                        <p>Dr. Charles S. Johnson, on the part of the United States,</p>
                        <p>Dr. Cuthbert Christy, on the part of the League of Nations,</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Now therefore</hi>, I, Charles Dunbar Burgess King,
                            President of the Republic of Liberia do hereby proclaim and give notice
                            to the people of Liberia and to all residents within the borders of the
                            Republic, that the Commission of Enquiry composed as follows: <list>
                                <item>On the part of the Republic of Liberia<lb/>Honourable Arthur
                                    Barclay,</item>
                                <item>On the part of the United States:<lb/>Dr. Charles S.
                                    Johnson,</item>
                                <item>On the part of the League of Nations:<lb/>Dr. Cuthbert
                                    Christy,</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">has this day been constituted and set up under the
                            Chairmanship of the Representative of the League of Nations with full
                            authority to enquire into all matters coming within the scope of the
                            Terms of Reference furnished them in relations to the alleged existence
                            in the Republic of Liberia of slavery as a factor in the Social and
                            industrial economy of the Republic, and of Forced Labour, otherwise than
                            is sanctioned in the International Slavery Convention of 1926.<note n="26" xml:id="d300fn26"><ref target="frus1928v01#pg_419"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 419</ref>.</note> To which end
                            the said Commission of Enquiry by virtue of the provisions of an Act of
                            the Legislature of Liberia approved December 6, 1926, is empowered to
                            summon witnesses, to administer oaths and take testimony, to compel the
                            attendance of witnesses and punish for contempts.</p>
                        <p>And I do hereby call upon all citizens loyally to appear before said
                            Commission when duly summoned and to comport themselves in such a manner
                            as may facilitate the Enquiry; and towards that end I do advise that at
                            no public meetings held during the life of the Commission shall be
                            discussed any matters coming within the purview of the Commission of
                            Enquiry as hereinbefore set forth.</p>
                        <pb facs="0441" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <seg type="margin">(L. S.)</seg>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Given</hi> under my hand and the Seal of the
                                Republic at the City of <placeName>Monrovia</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian liberian-republic" when="1930-04-07">this
                                    7th day of April in the Year of our Lord One Thousand Nine
                                    Hundred and Thirty and of the Republic the
                                Eighty-Third</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>C. D. B. <hi rend="smallcaps">King</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President:<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin Barclay</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>