<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-07-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="395" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d395">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">882.124a/39½</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Liberian Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Barclay</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Chargé in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hall</hi></persName>)<note n="92" xml:id="d395fn92">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Chargé
                                in despatch Diplomatic No. 79, July 22, 1930; received August
                                16.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-07-15">July 15, 1930</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">363/D</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Chargé d’affaires</hi>: I have the honour to
                            acknowledge the receipt of your Legation’s note of the 14th of July
                                1930,<note n="93" xml:id="d395fn93">Based on instruction No. 509,
                                May 27, 1930, to the Chargé in Liberia, <ref target="#pg_416">p.
                                    416</ref>.</note> advising the Government of Liberia through
                            this Department that Dr. Smith, upon information received from the
                            Surgeon General of the United States, will not remain in Liberia after
                            he has completed one year’s stay. In the circumstance, your Department
                            of State thinking that my Government may care to continue the sanitary
                            work inaugurated by Dr. Smith, will be glad to use its good offices
                            unofficially in securing without responsibility the names of Sanitary
                            Engineers, who will be willing to accept the post for a salary of not
                            less than $6,000.00.</p>
                        <p>In reply to the foregoing, I have the further honour to express the
                            regrets of the Government of Liberia that Dr. Smith, whose work is
                            highly appreciated, cannot continue his services in Liberia beyond the
                            period mentioned in your note. This Government intends continuing the
                            progressive development of the Sanitary System which Dr. Smith is in
                            course of installing but in view of their limited resources find
                            themselves unable to take advantage of the friendly offer of your
                            Department of State to recommend competent men for the post if <pb facs="0514" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> the salary required be fixed
                            in the sum of $6,000.00. They have decided therefore to secure the
                            services of a competent man elsewhere.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin Barclay</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>