<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-11-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-11-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="562" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d562">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">381.1163/1</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at
                                Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Blake</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-11-07">November 7, 1930</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                November 22.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 559</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report to the
                            Department that the Reverend Fred. C. Enyart, an American citizen,
                            resident for some thirty-five years in Mequinez, Morocco, Secretary of
                            the “Morocco Mission” of the Gospel Missionary Union Incorporated of
                            Kansas City, Missouri, United States of America, recently visited me in
                            Tangier for the purpose of apprizing me of the opposition manifested by
                            the French Authorities to the evangelizing work of the American
                            Missionaries in Morocco.</p>
                        <p>The question was fully and frankly discussed between us in all its
                            aspects. I told Mr. Enyart that, while in principle, I was not disposed
                            to admit of any right of the French Authorities to restrict the right of
                            residence and the freedom of travel provided for by the treaties, or the
                            legitimate activities of any American citizens in Morocco, it <pb facs="0698" n="604" xml:id="pg_604"/> certainly did appear necessary
                            in the present condition of affairs in the French Zone, for Christian
                            Missionaries to observe the greatest tact and restraint.</p>
                        <p>I reviewed the extremely delicate position which had arisen for the
                            French and native Authorities, as a result of the so-called “Berber
                            Dahirs” which I reported to the Department in my Despatch No. 540 of
                            September 18th, 1930.<note n="26" xml:id="d562fn26">Not printed.</note>
                            Mr. Enyart was fully aware of these conditions, freely admitted the
                            delicacy of the situation, and expressed his intention to observe the
                            requisite prudence in his activities.</p>
                        <p>Enclosed herewith is a copy of a written communication submitted, at my
                            request by Mr. Enyart, on the subject of his conversations with me.<note n="26" xml:id="d562fn27">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>Although as a result of my interview with Mr. Enyart the situation for
                            the time being would appear to have been met, difficulties might not
                            improbably present themselves in the near future.</p>
                        <p>One cannot deny that religious activities of Christian propagandists are
                            liable, with the disturbed atmosphere created in Mohammedan circles by
                            the French Berber policy, to provoke serious political repercussions in
                            the French Zone of Morocco. In these circumstances it appears that the
                            Sultan has received formal assurances of the French Authorities as to
                            the suppression of all attempts to Christianize the Berber tribes, and
                            these assurances appear to have produced a desirable measure of
                            appeasement to the Moorish population.</p>
                        <p>To what degree such promises may be deemed a justification to restrain
                            the American Missionaries in Morocco from carrying on activities, which,
                            as Mr. Enyart points out, they have peacefully pursued in this country
                            for over thirty-five years, is a question of some complexity, in the
                            circumstances. Furthermore, as it is anticipated that similar
                            difficulties may present themselves in the near future, also in the
                            Spanish Zone of Morocco, I venture to solicit the Department’s
                            instructions as to the measure of official support, which it may be
                            deemed proper for me to afford to American Missionaries in Morocco, in
                            the event of their further appeal for my intervention with the French
                            and Spanish Authorities.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Maxwell Blake</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>