<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Portugal ( (Dearing) ) to the Acting Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d722</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">722</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="722"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d722">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">353.115V13/33</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dearing</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-02-07">February 7,
                            1930</date>.<lb/>[Received February 27.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2976</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s telegraphic
                    instruction No. 8 of February 5, 5 [<hi rend="italic">3</hi>] P.M., regarding
                    the alleged plan to establish an oil monopoly in Portugal, and to my telegraphic
                    reply thereto, No. 14 of February 8, 11 A.M.,<note n="4" xml:id="d722fn4">Latter
                        not printed.</note> I have the honor to report that, shortly after the
                    receipt of the Department’s instruction to which I refer, Messrs. Sellers and
                    James, of the Vacuum Oil Company, called upon me and stated that there was
                    reason to believe no final action in the matter had yet been taken despite the
                    information obtained from the Ministry for Foreign Affairs by the British
                    Ambassador, through one of the Secretaries, to the effect that an extension of
                    time had been granted to those holding the threatening concession. I acquainted
                    Messrs. Sellers and James with the nature of my instructions and told them that
                    I would immediately call upon the Minister of Commerce and the Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs in order to make oral representations to them in the sense of
                    the said instructions. About an hour after they had left the Legation Mr.
                    Sellers telephoned that he had learned that the extension of time had not been
                    granted to the <hi rend="italic">concessionaires</hi> and that he had reason to
                    believe that the question at issue remained open.</p>
                <p>I reached the Ministry of Commerce at about half past twelve and was very kindly
                    received by Dr. Joao Antunes Guimaraes, the Minister. I explained that I had
                    sought an interview with him in connection with the oil refining monopoly as I
                    understood that the time limit for the extension of the monopolistic concession
                    had expired on the previous day, that my instructions were urgent and that I had
                    been unable to make an appointment to see the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    during the course of the morning. In consequence, I had sought an immediate
                    interview with the Minister. I further explained that it had been reported to me
                    that the Legation was engaged in intervening actively on behalf of the Atlantic
                    Refining Company and that this was interpreted as inimical to the interests of
                    the Vacuum Oil Company, particularly inasmuch as, in the absence of positive
                    representations on behalf of the Vacuum Oil Company, it was being said that the
                    latter lacked the support of the Legation. It was my desire, I said, to expose
                    the falsity of these rumors and to make it clear that the Legation was prepared
                    at all times to protect all American interests without favor or favoritism
                    toward one American company as against another. I pointed out, however, that the
                    present <pb facs="0869" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/> concession belonged to what is
                    still a Portuguese company, that free and open competition was a traditional
                    principle of our Government and that we would regret to see monopolies created
                    in Portugal inasmuch as the result thereof would be injury to American interests
                    established in good faith and maintained throughout a long series of years. The
                    Minister replied that he understood perfectly this attitude, that to grant the
                    petition of the <hi rend="italic">concessionnaires</hi> for an extension of time
                    would be practically tantamount to granting them a new concession, that no
                    extension had been granted, that the matter was still open and that, while it
                    had been before him for some months, he desired to study it longer and to go
                    into it more thoroughly. Thereupon, he showed me a voluminous file on his desk,
                    saying that it was composed of the papers in the case. On top, there was a
                    letter from the Vacuum Oil Company. The Minister then went on to say that the
                    Portuguese Government saw in the concession the possibility of forcing foreign
                    oil companies to sell at reasonable prices and that it was felt that gasoline in
                    Portugal was far too dear in consequence of the good understanding existing
                    between some of the companies—evidently meaning the Shell and the Vacuum Oil
                    Company. In reply, I ventured the opinion that the high price of gasoline in
                    Portugal was the result of customs duties and other charges. With regard to the
                    use of the concession for the purpose of bringing about price reductions, I
                    demurred, saying that I felt that this could be accomplished better in other
                    ways and that, in any event, my impression was that the price levels in question
                    conformed very closely to the governing economic laws and that in fact they were
                    probably relatively as low as those of any other commodities. The Minister took
                    this in very good part and again intimated that he would study the matter
                    further in order to determine what would be best in the interest of the
                    Portuguese people, national economy and governmental policy. I asked the
                    Minister kindly to let me know when he had reached his decision. This he
                    promised to do through the Ministry for Foreign Affairs. Finally, I informed the
                    Minister that I would explain why I had come directly to him when I saw the
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs during the course of the afternoon.</p>
                <p>Upon leaving the Ministry of Commerce, I went to see Mr. Sellers and gave him the
                    gist of my interview with the Minister. Mr. Sellers said that he had already
                    supplied Dr. Salazar, Minister of Finance, with full details regarding the
                    manner in which the price of gasoline sold by the Vacuum Oil Company was
                    determined and that he was quite prepared to go to the Minister of Commerce in
                    order to remove any existing misconception with regard to price levels and to
                    see that Dr. Salazar had all the facts and data. After saying that he might
                    supply the Minister of Commerce with a copy of his letter to the Minister of
                    Finance, he said that upon reconsideration he would <pb facs="0870" n="776"
                        xml:id="pg_776"/> not care to run the risk of allowing the Shell Company to
                    obtain the Vacuum Company’s figures.</p>
                <p>About 4–30 in the afternoon I called upon the Minister for Foreign Affairs, to
                    whom I repeated in substance that which I had said to the Minister of Commerce.
                    Captain Branco was very cordial and said that he was glad I had taken up the
                    matter directly with his colleague.</p>
                <p>Shortly afterwards I went to see the British Ambassador. Sir Francis said that he
                    had already taken occasion to say to Mr. Sampayo, the permanent Director General
                    and real head of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, that to grant a monopolistic
                    concession would be injurious to British trade. On being asked whether this was
                    the only ground upon which he had made representations as yet, Sir Francis
                    answered that it was. He added that he had talked the matter over with Mr.
                    Shervington of the Shell Company and that he was referring the case to the
                    Foreign Office in London with a request for instructions. Mr. Shervington had
                    told him that at various times during the past twenty years the original <hi
                        rend="italic">concessionnaires</hi> had endeavored to dispose of the
                    concession both to the Vacuum Company and to the Shell Company, but that neither
                    of these companies had been interested as the Portuguese Government had refused
                    to guarantee that the import duty on crude oil would not be increased. This
                    feature of the concession rendered it one of very questionable value, especially
                    in a country having disturbed political conditions. Sir Francis was of the
                    opinion that the Standard and Shell groups could prevent the Atlantic Refining
                    Company from obtaining crude oil in most of the usual markets. To this I replied
                    that it had been mentioned to me that the necessary supplies might be obtained
                    from Russia.</p>
                <p>This morning, Mr. Sellers called again, giving me a copy of a letter to the
                    Minister of Commerce of February 6, explaining the manner in which the Vacuum
                    Oil Company determined the price of gasoline. He also supplied me with a
                    confidential memorandum on the subject, saying that, while he did not wish to
                    leave it with the Minister, he was quite prepared to call upon him and to offer
                    verbal explanations. He also said that he knew that Sir Francis Lindley had
                    already cabled to London for instructions. Mr. Sellers added that he had heard
                    from the Minister of Commerce in an encouraging sense and that he had received
                    equally good news in respect of Dr. Salazar, who seemed disinclined to grant a
                    concession or an extension of time in view of the attendant loss to the treasury
                    of the large revenue now being obtained from the customs duty on gasoline.</p>
                <p>I expect to have occasion shortly to report further in respect of the British
                    attitude in the matter, as Sir Francis Lindley has promised to keep me fully
                    informed. Meanwhile, it would seem as though definite action in the case would
                    be deferred for the time being and that during <pb facs="0871" n="777"
                        xml:id="pg_777"/> this interval the Vacuum Oil Company would have an
                    opportunity fully to present its side of the case and to obtain a hearing for
                    its arguments.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fred Morris Dearing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
