<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Special Agreement Between the United States of America and Sweden for the
                    Arbitration of Claims Growing out of the Alleged Detention of the Motor ships
                    “Kronprins Gustaf Adolf” and “Pacific” Signed at Washington, December 17,
                    1930</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d770</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">770</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="770"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d770">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Treaty Series No. 841</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Special Agreement Between the United States of America and
                        Sweden for the Arbitration of Claims Growing out of the Alleged Detention of
                        the Motor ships “Kronprins Gustaf Adolf” and “Pacific” Signed at Washington,
                        December 17, 1930</hi>
                    <note n="20" xml:id="d770fn20">Ratification advised by the Senate, February 14
                        (legislative day of January 26), 1931; ratified by the President, April 17,
                        1931; ratifications exchanged at Washington, October 1, 1931; proclaimed by
                        the President, October 2, 1931.</note>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government of Sweden has presented to the
                    Government of the United States of America certain claims on behalf of
                    Rederiaktiebolaget Nordstjernan, a Swedish corporation, for losses said to have
                    been incurred as a result of the alleged detention in ports of the United States
                    of America, in contravention of provisions of treaties in force between the
                    United States of America and Sweden, of the motorship <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kronprins Gustaf Adolf</hi> and the motorship <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pacific</hi> belonging to said Swedish corporation; and</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Government of the United States of
                    America has disclaimed any liability to indemnify the Government of Sweden in
                    behalf of the owners of the said motorships, therefore:</p>
                <p>The President of the United States of America and His Majesty the King of Sweden
                    being desirous that this matter of difference between their two Governments
                    should be submitted to adjudication by a competent and impartial Tribunal have
                    named as their respective plenipotentiaries, that is to say:</p>
                <p>The President of the United States of America,</p>
                <p>Henry L. Stimson, Secretary of State of the United States of America; and</p>
                <p>His Majesty the King of Sweden,</p>
                <p>W. Boström, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at Washington;</p>
                <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their respective full powers found
                    in good and due form, have agreed upon the following articles:</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There shall be submitted to arbitration pursuant to the Convention for the
                    Pacific Settlement of International Disputes, signed at The Hague, October 18,
                        1907,<note n="21" xml:id="d770fn21">
                        <ref target="frus1907p2#pg_1181">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1907, pt. 2, p.
                        1181</ref>.</note> and the Arbitration Convention between the United States
                    of America and Sweden, signed at Washington, October 27, 1928,<note n="22"
                        xml:id="d770fn22">
                        <ref target="frus1928v03#pg_883">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>,
                            p. 883</ref>.</note> the following questions: <list>
                        <item>First, Whether the Government of the United States of America detained
                            the Swedish motorship <hi rend="italic">Kronprins Gustaf Adolf</hi>
                            between June 23, 1917 and July 12, 1918, and the Swedish motorship <hi
                                rend="italic">Pacific</hi>
                            <pb facs="0937" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> between July 1, 1917 and July
                            19, 1918, in contravention of the Swedish-American Treaties of April 3,
                            1783 and July 4, 1827.</item>
                        <item>Second, Whether, if the first question be decided in the affirmative,
                            the Government of the United States of America is liable to the
                            Government of Sweden in behalf of the owners of the motorships for
                            damages resulting from such unlawful detention; and,</item>
                        <item>Third, Should the reply be in the affirmative what pecuniary
                            reparation is due to the Government of Sweden on behalf of the owners of
                            the motorships above mentioned.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The questions stated in Article I shall be submitted for a decision to a sole
                    arbitrator who shall not be a national of either the United States of America or
                    Sweden. In the event that the two Governments shall be unable to agree upon the
                    selection of a sole arbitrator within two months from the date of the coming
                    into force of this Agreement they shall proceed to the establishment of a
                    Tribunal consisting of three members, one designated by the President of the
                    United States of America, one by His Majesty the King of Sweden, and the third,
                    who shall preside over the Tribunal, selected by mutual agreement of the two
                    Governments. None of the members of the Tribunal shall be a national of the
                    United States of America or of Sweden.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The procedure in the arbitration shall be as follows: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Within ninety days from the date of the exchange of ratifications of
                            this Agreement, the agent for the Government of Sweden shall present to
                            the Agent for the Government of the United States of America a statement
                            of the facts on which the Government of Sweden rests the claim against
                            the United States of America, and the demand for indemnity. This
                            statement shall be accompanied by the evidence in support of the
                            allegations and of the demand made;</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Within a like period of ninety days from the date on which this
                            Agreement becomes effective, as aforesaid, the Agent for the Government
                            of the United States of America shall present to the Agent for the
                            Government of Sweden at Washington a statement of facts relied upon by
                            the Government of the United States of America together with evidence in
                            support.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Within sixty days from the date on which the exchange of statements
                            provided for in paragraphs (1) and (2) of this Article is completed each
                            Agent shall present in the manner prescribed by paragraphs (1) and (2)
                            an answer to the statement of the other together with any additional
                            evidence and such argument as they desire to submit.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0938" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>
                </p>
                <p>When the development of the record is completed in accordance with Article III
                    hereof, the Government of the United States of America and the Government of
                    Sweden shall forthwith cause to be forwarded to the International Bureau at The
                    Hague, for transmission to the Arbitrator or Arbitrators, as the case may be,
                    three complete sets of the statements, answers, evidence and arguments presented
                    by their respective Agents to each other.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Within thirty days from the delivery of the record to the Arbitrator or
                    Arbitrators in accordance with Article IV, the Tribunal shall convene at
                    Washington for the purpose of hearing oral arguments by Agents or Counsel, or
                    both, for each Government.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi>
                </p>
                <p>When the Agent for either Government has reason to believe that the other
                    Government possesses or could obtain any document or documents which are
                    relevant to the claim but which have not been incorporated in the record such
                    document or documents shall be submitted to the Tribunal at the request of the
                    Agent for the other Government and shall be available for inspection by the
                    demanding Agent. In agreeing to arbitrate the claim of the Kingdom of Sweden in
                    behalf of Rederiaktiebolaget Nordstjernan the Government of the United States of
                    America does not waive any defense which was available prior to the concluding
                    of the Agreement.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VII</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The decision of the Tribunal shall be made within two months from the date on
                    which the arguments close, unless on the request of the Tribunal the Parties
                    shall agree to extend the period. The decision shall be in writing.</p>
                <p>The decision of the majority of the members of the Tribunal, in case a sole
                    Arbitrator is not agreed upon, shall be the decision of the Tribunal.</p>
                <p>The language in which the proceedings shall be conducted shall be English.</p>
                <p>The decision shall be accepted as final and binding upon the two Governments.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VIII</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Each Government shall pay the expenses of the presentation and conduct of its
                    case before the Tribunal; all other expenses which by <pb facs="0939" n="845"
                        xml:id="pg_845"/> their nature are a charge on both Governments, including
                    the honorarium for the Arbitrator or Arbitrators, shall be borne by the two
                    Governments in equal moieties.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IX</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This Special Agreement shall be ratified in accordance with the constitutional
                    forms of the Contracting Parties and shall take effect immediately upon the
                    exchange of ratifications, which shall take place at Washington as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>In witness whereof, the respective plenipotentiaries have signed this Special
                    Agreement and have hereunto affixed their seals.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">Done in duplicate at
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-17">this seventeenth day of
                            December, nineteen hundred and thirty</date>.</dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry L. Stimson</hi>
                    </signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Boström</hi>
                    </signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[In his decision of July 18, 1932, the arbitrator, Eugène Borel, Honorary
                        Professor of International Law at the University of Geneva, decided: “that
                        the Government of the United States did not detain the Swedish motor ship
                            <hi rend="italic">Kronprins Gustaf Adolf</hi> between June 23, 1917, and
                        July 12, 1918, and the Swedish motor ship <hi rend="italic">Pacific</hi>
                        between July 1, 1917, and July 19, 1918, in contravention of the
                        Swedish-American treaties of April 3rd, 1783, and July 4th,
                        1827.”—Department of State Arbitration Series No. 5 (6), p. 100.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
