<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The German Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="80"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.111 Colleges 62/27</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">German Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>The German Embassy has the honor to refer to the esteemed note of September 3 of
                    this year—No. 811.111 Colleges 62/25 [<hi rend="italic">26</hi>]—and to call
                    attention to the enclosed application addressed to the Department of Labor by
                    the German Students’ Co-operative Association on December 3 of this year. The
                    Association expresses therein the request that it be granted the admission to
                    the United States of 50 German work students (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) for
                    the year 1931, according to the agreement concluded on February 4, 1926. Details
                    of the circumstances upon which this request is based are set forth in the
                    enclosure.</p>
                <pb facs="0208" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/>
                <p>The Embassy deems it worth while upon this occasion, and upon its own behalf,
                    again to call attention to the high cultural significance which it attaches to
                    the efficacy which has heretofore characterized the exchange of work students as
                    a means of promoting understanding and a mutual inspiration to intellectual
                    relations between the American and the German peoples. It therefore has the
                    honor to give the present request its warmest support.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-04">December 4,
                            1930</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Herbert Boehmer</persName> of
                            the German Students’ Cooperative Association to the Second Assistant
                            Secretary of Labor</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Husband</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-03">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 3, 1930</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Husband</hi>: In reference to our today’s
                        conversation we have much pleasure in handing you herewith application for
                        the admission of 50 German work students during the coming year, 1931.</p>
                    <p>In support of this application we beg to submit for your consideration the
                        following:</p>
                    <p>You indicated during the conversation which we had with you during the summer
                        in Washington that the 35 students admitted in April were the maximum which
                        you could allow to enter during the present year. The considerations which
                        guided you in this decision have been appreciated by our organization in
                        spite of the fact that this sudden reduction in the number of students
                        admitted meant a very serious blow to the whole institution of the student
                        exchange and to our work in maintaining this institution.</p>
                    <p>At present there are 124 students in this country, a group of 12 of whom is
                        due to leave during the month of January, 1931 and another group of 48 in
                        April, so that a total number of only 64 students will remain after that
                        date in the United States, of which again about the half will be due to
                        leave in the fall of 1931. If, therefore, the 50 new students are admitted
                        for that year, for which the application is now being made, the total would
                        remain about 100 or exactly the half of the heretofore figure.</p>
                    <p>The figure for which we now apply is moreover the absolute minimum for which
                        it is possible to maintain the work of our organization. A reduction below
                        this figure would place us before the question of completely giving up our
                        activities, as has already been suggested by some of those who are
                        supporting it financially in Germany and we submit that it would, in view of
                        the experiences of the past and the acknowledged inestimable value of this
                        exchange, be a very great loss if the whole institution had to be abandoned
                        for all time just on <pb facs="0209" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> account of a
                        pro tempore condition of economic depression which in the opinion of all
                        experts is already on the wane.</p>
                    <p>With reference to the latter we wish, however, to add that it is not our
                        intention to have the students all come over at once, but in such groups as
                        locations can be found for.</p>
                    <p>We fully realize and appreciate the objections of the Department of Labor but
                        beg to submit that the 50 students for whom this application is made could
                        not conceivably upset or even impair the unemployment situation in this
                        country. Our students are, moreover, taken care of by our organization, are
                        not immigrants come to stay and cannot in any respect become a public charge
                        whilst here. For this reason we have cause to believe that neither on the
                        part of the American Federation of Labor nor of any other institution will
                        there be any objections raised against the entry of 50 work students in
                        1931.</p>
                    <p>In respect of the whole question we beg to make reference to repeated
                        expressions since the conclusion of our agreement with the Department of
                        Labor on February 4, 1926, to the expression made in the matter by the
                        German Embassy and to the recent conversations with Dr. Edmund Stinnes, one
                        of our most enthusiastic sponsors in Germany, had with you in October. The
                        institution of work students exchange which is based on the principles of
                        reciprocity, offering the same facilities to all American students in
                        Germany who wish to avail themselves thereof, has proved to be of greatest
                        educational, social and economic value to both countries and should be
                        upheld by all means.</p>
                    <p>We finally wish to voice our gratitude for the kindness and assistance
                        rendered during the past years and express the sincere hope that the good
                        will of the Labor Department may be extended to us for the future.</p>
                    <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Herbert Boehmer</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
