<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-10-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="95" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.5241/173</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dawes</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-10-06">October 6, 1930</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 520</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your despatch
                            No. 761, dated March 25, 1930, with enclosure concerning the British
                            Colonies and Protectorates which have not adhered to the Convention
                            concluded between the United States and Great Britain on March 2, 1899,
                            relative to the disposal of real and personal property in the respective
                            countries. Several small islands and Protectorates of limited
                            territorial extent are included in this list. It may be found difficult
                            for the local authorities of the United States to differentiate between
                            the British Colonies and Protectorates in which the Convention of March
                            2, 1899, is in effect and those listed in the second paragraph of the
                            Foreign Office note dated March 24, 1930.</p>
                        <p>You are, accordingly, instructed to take up the matter again with the
                            Foreign Office and to inquire whether any special reasons exist for
                            excluding Americans resident in the Colonies and Protectorates listed in
                            paragraph 2, their heirs, legatees or donees, from the benefits of this
                            Convention. You will add that the Department has had under consideration
                            the procedure by which local authorities in the United States might be
                            advised that British subjects from the Colonies and Protectorates listed
                            in the second paragraph of the Foreign Office note or their heirs,
                            legatees or donees were not entitled to take advantage of the provisions
                            contained in the Convention. However, as it was thought that this may
                            lead to some misunderstanding on the part of the local authorities, the
                            Department desires before taking such action, to ascertain whether the
                            British Government <pb facs="0230" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> intends to
                            adhere to the Convention on behalf of any of these Colonies and
                            Protectorates.</p>
                        <p>Please submit a report setting forth the action taken by you pursuant to
                            this instruction.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William
                                    R. Castle, Jr.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>