<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (MacVeagh) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-07-21T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-07-21T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-07-21T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-07-21T04:00:00-05:00" n="120"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15 a 1/463: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-07-21T18:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 21, 1927—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received July 21—10:20 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>102. A member of my staff who had an informal talk with the Vice Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs today took the occasion to refer to the reported agreement on
                    July 16th at Geneva by the Japanese delegation with the last British proposal.
                    The Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that Admiral Kobayashi had
                    expressed the opinion to Admiral Field that the Japanese Government would accept
                    these proposals. <pb facs="0210" n="124" xml:id="pg_124"/> Mr. Debuchi said that
                    the Japanese Government had not however given its assent and that the proposals
                    were still subject to tripartite discussion. He intimated that the Japanese
                    Government still hoped to bring the maximum combined cruiser-destroyer tonnage
                    down to 450,000 tons and stated that the British 6-inch gun proposal had not
                    received the approval of the naval experts here. He said that the Japanese
                    Government also realized that the obsolete cruiser tonnage clause presented
                    difficulties. As regards submarine tonnage, he said that the Japanese had hoped
                    for 70,000 tons. The Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs reiterated, however, that
                    no decision had been reached by the Japanese Government and that they especially
                    wished our Government to understand, as he having [<hi rend="italic">had</hi>]
                    made and felt sure Saito had made plain, that they have no intention of placing
                    us in a difficult position by reaching a preliminary accord with the British. He
                    said that this was a three-power Conference and would remain so.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
