<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Coolidge</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15 a 1/573a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Coolidge</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-08-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 10, 1927</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I suppose with the telegrams
                    that we received from Geneva and instructions we gave, together with the report
                    which the Secretary of the Navy made to you, you are well informed on what took
                    place at Geneva and the reason for the failure of the Conference. While the
                    British Government assured Mr. Houghton they were perfectly willing for the
                    United States to have parity on all classes of ships, Bridgeman did not make
                    this offer in Geneva at all until he was instructed by London and even in that
                    case I am assured by one of the press men who was present that when he was asked
                    the question as to whether Great Britain was willing to make a treaty for parity
                    in ships other than the 10,000 ton class, he said “Well, we would have to
                    consider that”. Undoubtedly he went there intending not to grant it and every
                    proposition there made was intended to deprive the United States of an equal,
                    effective navy. … It became more and more evident that the only possible way to
                    have a treaty with Great Britain on this subject was to agree to a total tonnage
                    beyond all reason and one which would not be a limitation but an expansion.
                    Furthermore, the Navy insists that we do not want small cruisers and to agree to
                    build them would give the British a superiority owing to her naval bases and
                    make it impossible for us to have as effective a navy as Great Britain. The
                    lowest possible limit which Great Britain proposed was 426,000 tons of cruisers
                    which might be increased by building fewer destroyers and submarines. In <pb
                        facs="0244" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/> other words, they proposed the global
                    or total tonnage system which they had opposed strenuously at the Preliminary
                    Conference. This would give them the right to build cruisers in tonnage not
                    built in the other classes. Of course, the New York <hi rend="italic">World</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> have frequently suggested that there should
                    have been diplomatic correspondence preceding the Conference so that each
                    country would have known exactly what the other country was willing to agree to.
                    If that could have been done, no Conference would have been necessary. Of
                    course, there is no ground for this except the statements of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Times</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">World</hi> and Vice
                    President Dawes’ speech.<note n="3" xml:id="d150fn3">At Buffalo, N. Y., on the
                        occasion of the dedication of the International Peace Bridge, Aug. 7,
                        1927.</note> … The most careful preparations were made, as you know. The
                    British Government was sounded out and a letter from Jones states that the
                    British went back on everything they had agreed to with him in London.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d150fn4">Letter not found in Department files.</note> We had
                    every assurance from the British Government that they desired an agreement on
                    equal terms with the United States and any such tonnage as they proposed was far
                    beyond any suggestions they had ever made and beyond the tentative understanding
                    made at the Washington Conference.</p>
                <p>Of course, I did everything in my power to make some agreement but I could not
                    recommend an agreement that did not give us parity in fact as well as in
                    principle or that would provide for an enormous expansion in cruiser building.
                    Any such tonnage as was demanded by the British Government was absolutely
                    uncalled for and unnecessary. We demonstrated to them that there was not over
                    two hundred thousand tons of cruisers in all the rest of the world outside the
                    United States and Japan; that there could be no possible threat to the British
                    Government, her commerce or her possessions. Either the British Navy has gone
                    mad or Great Britain has felt compelled to continue ship building to furnish
                    employment. Perhaps both had something to do with it. I, of course, regret the
                    outcome but I do not see how we could have prevented it. Personally I think it
                    would have been perfectly simple to have entered into an agreement for a
                    building program prior to 1931 on the following bases: that Great Britain should
                    not build any additional ships beyond those already laid down; that the United
                    States would not build more 10,000 ton ships than Great Britain has built or is
                    building. This, of course, to include the 9800 ton ships, four of which Great
                    Britain has. This is all we could build or could reasonably expect to build
                    between now and 1931 but if we did desire to build more than this, we should
                    build the smaller size cruisers. As near as I can find out from the Navy, they
                    do not think there is any possibility of our building more before that time.
                    Great Britain did not agree to this. Apparently she did not intend to <pb
                        facs="0245" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/> agree to anything. It is evident that
                    British opinion is not unanimous on this subject. I enclose you an article
                    published by a man by the name of Bywater who I understand is an authority in
                    Great Britain on naval affairs.<note n="5" xml:id="d150fn5">Hector Charles
                        Bywater, naval correspondent for the English <hi rend="italic">Daily
                            News</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Observer</hi>, and European naval
                        correspondent for the Baltimore <hi rend="italic">Sun;</hi> enclosure not
                        printed.</note> I cannot say that this represents a majority of British
                    opinion. I do not think it does. I think the majority of the British opinion is
                    that Great Britain ought to have supremacy on the sea. I do not know what effect
                    this is going to have on our building program before the Congress but I think
                    there is a pretty strong feeling that we should extend our building program.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
