<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Colombian Legation to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="250"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">717.2114/68</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Colombian Legation</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="63" xml:id="d250fn63">Left at the Department by the Colombian Minister,
                        Aug. 2, 1927.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1927-08-02">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="64" xml:id="d250fn64">Supplied by
                            the editor.</note>]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Colombia-Nicaraguan Matter and the Roncador, Quita
                        Sueño and serranilla keys</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Possible formulas:</p>
                <p>Number 1: The Colombian and Nicaraguan plenipotentiaries to sign at Washington a
                    treaty consecrating the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> as follows: Mangle
                    Islands and the Mosquito to Nicaragua; San Andrés and Providencia to
                    Colombia.</p>
                <p>At the same time the United States and Colombia to sign an arbitration convention
                    to settle in this way the dominion over the Roncador, Quita Sueño, and
                    Serranilla Keys. The two parties may incorporate in this convention such
                    provisions as they deem expedient.</p>
                <p>Number 2: Colombia and Nicaragua to sign at Managua a treaty consecrating the
                    formula: Mangles, Mosquito to Nicaragua; San Andrés and Providencia to
                    Colombia.</p>
                <p>At the same time the Governments of the United States and Colombia to exchange
                    notes at Washington stating that the question of dominion over the Roncador,
                    Quita Sueño and Serranilla Keys will be settled by means of an arbitration
                    convention between the two Governments. In these notes the parties can make such
                    statements as they deem opportune which are to be incorporated afterwards in an
                    arbitration convention.</p>
                <p>Number 3: The Secretary of State of the United States and the Ministers of
                    Colombia and Nicaragua, duly authorized by their respective Governments, to sign
                    a declaration or act, in which they will record the fact that the three
                    Governments have accepted the following formulas to settle pending
                    questions:</p>
                <p>Nicaragua recognizes the rights of Colombia to the exclusive and complete
                    dominion over San Andrés and Providencia.</p>
                <p>Colombia recognizes the rights of Nicaragua to the exclusive and complete
                    dominion over the Mosquito and the Mangle Islands.</p>
                <pb facs="0415" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/>
                <p>The Governments of Colombia and Nicaragua engage themselves immediately to give
                    effect to this agreement by means of a public treaty.</p>
                <p>The United States and Colombia agree that the dominion of the Roncador,
                    Serranilla and Quita Sueño Keys shall be settled by an arbitration convention
                    between Colombia and the United States to whose terms the two Parties will agree
                    later.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
