<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="320" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.472/7</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="3" xml:id="d320fn3">Left at the Department by the British Ambassador
                                and the Australian Commissioner Nov. 30, 1927.</note></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1927-11-30">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum re Entry of Australian
                                Business Men Into the United States</hi></p>
                        <p>On December 30, 1926, the Prime Minister of Australia, The Eight
                            Honourable S. M. Bruce, had the honour of an interview with the
                            Secretary of State at Washington, when the question of the disabilities
                            attaching to the entry of Australian business men into the United States
                            outside of the quota was discussed.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister was accompanied at that interview by His Excellency
                            the British Ambassador and the Commissioner for Australia in the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>At the close of the interview the Honourable the Secretary of State
                            requested that a statement of the position from the Australian point of
                            view should be prepared and sent to him by the Commissioner for
                            Australia.</p>
                        <p>Under date of January 14, 1927, a communication was duly forwarded to the
                            Secretary of State, setting out clearly the position existing at
                            present, and asking (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) whether the Government of
                            the United States of America is able and would be willing to extend to
                            citizens of the Commonwealth of Australia the privileges granted to
                            British citizens under the treaty of 1815, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                            in the event of it not being possible to effect such an extension under
                            that treaty, the Government of the United States would be agreeable to
                            negotiate a special treaty with the Commonwealth for a similar
                            purpose.</p>
                        <p>Subsequent to receipt of this letter the British Ambassador was given to
                            understand semiofficially that the matter was under consideration, but
                            that the Department was not in a position to give a definite opinion
                            thereon until it had been ascertained whether Congress would be prepared
                            to amend Section 3, Clause 6. of the United States Immigration Act of
                            1924.</p>
                        <p>Under date of February 18 [<hi rend="italic">26</hi>], 1927, a
                            communication was sent from the Department of State, Washington,
                            intimating: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>that the Department considered that the treaty of 1815 with
                                    Great Britain relates to trade and commerce with British
                                    possessions in Europe, and that its provisions are not
                                    applicable to any of the component parts of the British Empire
                                    overseas;</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>that as regards the possibility of the negotiation of a treaty
                                    with the Commonwealth of Australia for the purposes defined in
                                    the communication of the Commissioner for Australia, dated
                                    January 14, Section 3, clause 6. of the Immigration Act of 1924
                                    did not apply to a treaty concluded subsequently.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <pb facs="0527" n="441" xml:id="pg_441"/>
                        <p>It was further added that in view of this situation the Secretary of
                            State was not prepared at that time to discuss that aspect of the
                            subject, but that the Department was deeply interested and would be glad
                            to communicate with the British Ambassador at a later date in regard to
                            it.</p>
                        <p>Since then no further communications appear to have passed between the
                            parties in reference to this matter, but a letter has now been received
                            by the Commissioner for Australia from the Prime Minister of the
                            Commonwealth, asking that this matter should be reopened in view of the
                            fact that the officials of the State Department appear to recognise that
                            Australia in this matter is under a disability that should be removed as
                            early as possible.</p>
                        <p>It should be noted that the annual quota for Australia, which is at
                            present the only means by which Australian business men may enter the
                            United States for any extended period in connection with their business,
                            only numbers a hundred and twenty-one and is at the present time filled
                            by applicants for at least two years ahead.</p>
                        <p>It should be further noted that business between the United States of
                            America and Australia is steadily increasing from year to year, and now
                            amounts to very considerably over 250 million dollars per annum.</p>
                        <p>There is no restriction of any kind on American business men entering the
                            Commonwealth of Australia and staying in that country as long as may be
                            necessary for them to conduct and complete their business; and at the
                            present time there are considerably over one thousand American citizens
                            resident in the Commonwealth of Australia taking part in such business
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>It is now desired to learn whether there is any possibility of this
                            matter being brought before Congress during the session about to
                            commence, with a view of obtaining some amendment of the Immigration Act
                            of 1924 which will permit Australian business men to enter for bone fide
                            business purposes without restriction as to the length of their stay in
                            the United States, and also whether any further information is required
                            from Australia in connection with this matter.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>