<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-05-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="363" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d363">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">150.01 Commuters/56</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Visa Office</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Du Bois</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conference Held
                                May 12, 1927, Regarding Canadian Border Travel
                            Difficulties</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1927-05-12">May 12, 1927</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>At 10:30 a.m., by invitation of the Secretary, the following officials
                            met in the Diplomatic Room of the Department: <list>
                                <item>The Secretary</item>
                                <item>The Minister of Canada</item>
                                <item>Assistant Secretary Wilbur J. Carr (State)</item>
                                <item>Assistant Secretary Robe Carl White (Labor)</item>
                                <item>Mr. Wrong, Secretary, Canadian Legation</item>
                                <item>Mr. Jolliffe, Commissioner of Immigration of Canada</item>
                                <item>Mr. Flournoy, Assistant to the Solicitor</item>
                                <item>Mr. du Bois, Chief of the Visa Office.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The Secretary made an introductory statement to the Conference in which
                            he pointed out the importance of maintaining the traditional friendly
                            relations which had always existed with Canada. He hoped the conferees
                            would discuss any and all questions arising from travel difficulties on
                            the Canadian border in the friendliest spirit and he wanted the
                            Conference to be sufficiently broad in scope to cover any question on
                            which difficulties might arise with a view to their solution in a way
                            that would maintain our friendly relations with Canada.</p>
                        <pb facs="0584" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/>
                        <p>The Secretary stated further that he hoped the work of the Conference
                            would iron out all difficulties; that he would personally discuss its
                            results with the Secretary of Labor at which discussion he invited the
                            Minister of Canada to be present.</p>
                        <p>Since it was Diplomatic Day, the Secretary then excused himself and the
                            Conference proceeded informally, presided over by Assistant Secretary
                            Carr.</p>
                        <p>The Canadian Minister read a prepared statement outlining the widespread
                            adverse effect Labor’s General Order No. 86 has had on the sentiment and
                            economic structure in Canada. He said it is being taken up editorially
                            and by the man on the street in cities far removed from the border and
                            has become, in fact, an acute international issue. He exhibited a copy
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Border Cities Star</hi> which bore a full front
                            page editorial under one-inch headlines, “An Unfriendly Act of a
                            Friendly Nation” and presented other clippings similar in tone from
                            Quebec and other interior cities.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Wrong went further into details and suggested that under Labor’s own
                            definition—”an alien who, having a fixed domicile in some other country
                            which he has no intention to abandon, comes to the United States for a
                            temporary period only”—the border-crossers were in the category of
                            non-immigrants.</p>
                        <p>Mr. White outlined the position of the Department of Labor at some
                            length. He said that ever since July 1, 1924, Labor had been seeking a
                            means to curtail the border-crossing privileges and was now driven by
                            pressure from organized labor to a definite announcement of its program
                            of control of border crossing by workers. He said these people who
                            entered the United States solely for purposes of work and took the
                            places of American workers were not contemplated by Congress as coming
                            within the non-immigrant class.</p>
                        <p>The discussion then became general and centered around the number of
                            persons who, under Labor’s Order, would be required to present quota
                            immigration visas. It was submitted by the representatives of Canada
                            that these persons caused them the greatest concern since they were over
                            90% British-born and as much the responsibility of the Canadian
                            Government as native-born Canadians. Each group had certain statistics
                            which seemed to indicate that between 4000 and 6000 such persons were
                            involved. It was pointed out that while this number was but a drop in
                            the bucket as far as the American labor market was concerned, each
                            individual, when thrown out of employment and forced to stay in Canada
                            would become the nucleus of unfriendly feeling against the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>The time within which these people might hope to receive visas under
                            their respective quotas was discussed. Our system of allotment
                            proportional to demand was explained and also the fact that <pb facs="0585" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/> obligations had been created
                            in very large numbers both in England and in Canada by registrations on
                            the part of prospective quota immigrants who had not hitherto enjoyed
                            any border crossing privileges and who could not be set aside in favor
                            of those who had. Statistics were adduced to show that a six-months
                            period for the production of quota visas could not be considered as
                            meeting the situation in the slightest degree.</p>
                        <p>Mr. White pointed out that the six-months period was not expected by
                            Labor officials to be an adequate period, but rather to be a period in
                            which the situation would clarify itself; the definition of a period
                            (any period) after which quota visas must be produced being the only
                            actual curtailment in the number of foreign workers enjoying employment
                            in the United States, and, consequently, the only actual benefit
                            accorded to the A. F. of L. He stated that it was also conceived as a
                            period of readjustment—a period during which due notice having been
                            served, non-Canadian border crossing workers would secure employment on
                            the Canadian side of the border.</p>
                        <p>The Conference adjourned at 12:50 p.m. after agreeing that notices to the
                            press should be limited to the statement that this was a preliminary
                            session only and no announcement of its results could be made.</p>
                        <p>Tentatively, with the understanding that Mr. White would discuss them
                            with the Secretary of Labor, the following three points were agreed upon
                            a$ being the lines along which a solution might be reached: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Cease, as from the date of General Order No. 86, from the
                                    creation of further border-crossing privileges.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Continue in effect the privileges hitherto granted until the
                                    individuals in each class involved may either bring themselves
                                    within the Act of 1924<note n="25" xml:id="d363fn25">43 Stat.
                                        153.</note> or otherwise adjust their situations.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The Departments concerned will report the situation to
                                    Congress when it convenes with a view to ascertaining whether it
                                    is disposed to grant any further measure of freedom in travel
                                    across our land borders than is permitted by the present
                                    law.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. du</hi> B[<hi rend="smallcaps">ois</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>