<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-11-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="381" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d381">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.252/4</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Collier</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-11-02"><hi rend="italic">November 2,
                                1927</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 788</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There is transmitted herewith for
                            submission to the Foreign Office for negotiation between the United
                            States and Chile a draft of a treaty of Friendship, Commerce and
                            Consular Rights which already has been the subject of preliminary
                            instructions. A copy of the draft is enclosed for the use of the
                                Embassy.<note n="13" xml:id="d381fn13">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>Detailed instructions in regard to each article of the draft will be sent
                            to you by an early pouch. The following statements in explanation of the
                            more important differences between the enclosed draft and the Treaty of
                            Friendship, Commerce and Consular Rights signed by the United States and
                            Germany, December 8, 1923, are made for your information and for use in
                            explanations to the Chilean authorities.</p>
                        <p>The reservation concerning statutes relating to the immigration of aliens
                            made by the Senate of the United States in giving its advice and consent
                            to the ratification of the treaty between the United States and Germany
                            is incorporated in the draft as the last paragraph of Article I. The
                            reservation making provision for the termination at the end of one year
                            of the paragraphs of Article VII relating to the treatment of vessels
                            and Articles IX and XI (Articles X and XII of the enclosed draft) is not
                            included in the enclosed draft. Further reference will be made to this
                            reservation.</p>
                        <p>The fourth paragraph of Article VII is designed to assure equality of
                            treatment in respect of licenses, quotas and contingents for the
                            importation or exportation of restricted goods. In practice it has been
                            difficult to obtain such equality of treatment for the commerce of the
                            United States in certain European countries in which systems prohibiting
                            or restricting the importation or exportation of certain goods have been
                            in force, and from which prohibitions or restrictions abatements are
                            made by contingents or licenses. <pb facs="0611" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/> This Government desires that the paragraph be included in the treaty
                            with Chile as it is undertaking to have it included in all the treaties
                            of Friendship, Commerce, and Consular Rights, which it is now
                            negotiating.</p>
                        <p>Stipulations in regard to prohibitions, restrictions and licenses are
                            contained in the International Convention Relating to the Simplification
                            of Customs Formalities signed at Geneva, November 3, 1923, in Article 9
                            of the Anglo-Austrian Treaty of May 22, 1924, and in a provision
                            contained in the second paragraph of Exchanges of Notes signed by the
                            United States with a number of countries, namely,—</p>
                        <p>Poland, February 10, 1925, Treaty Series No. 727; Finland, May 2, 1925,
                            Treaty Series No. 715; Esthonia, March 2, 1925, Treaty Series No. 722;
                            Rumania, February 26, 1926; Treaty Series No. 733; Latvia, February 1,
                            1926, Treaty Series No. 740; Lithuania, December 23, 1925; Treaty Series
                            No. 742; and Haiti, July 8, 1926, Treaty Series No. 746.</p>
                        <p>The seventh paragraph of Article VII providing for equality of treatment
                            of vessels with regard to bounties, drawbacks and other privileges,
                            although not contained in the treaty between the United States and
                            Germany is included in a number of the older treaties to which the
                            United States is a party, and this Government desires to have it
                            included in the treaties of Friendship, Commerce, and Consular rights,
                            which it shall sign hereafter with maritime countries.</p>
                        <p>The sentence at the end of the second paragraph of Article XIII “If such
                            consent be given on the condition of reciprocity the condition shall be
                            deemed to relate to the provisions of the laws, National, State, or
                            Provincial, under which the foreign corporation or association desiring
                            to exercise such rights is organized” is designed for use in treaties
                            with countries in which the right of a corporation organized under the
                            laws of the United States to engage in business is conditioned on
                            reciprocity. This provision would have the effect of obtaining for
                            American corporations in Chile in the event that the laws of Chile in
                            relation to the right of a foreign corporation to engage in business
                            contain a condition of reciprocity, the right to engage in business
                            according to whether the laws of the State of the United States under
                            which such corporation is organized extend the right to engage in
                            business to foreign corporations.</p>
                        <p>The reservation making provision for the termination of paragraphs and
                            articles relating to shipping made by the Senate in giving its advice
                            and consent to the ratification of the treaty with Germany is included
                            in the Treaty with Esthonia as the third paragraph <pb facs="0612" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/> of Article XXIX. As stated above on page 2
                            of this instruction no corresponding reservation is included in the
                            enclosed draft. The Department will instruct you by telegram whether to
                            include such a paragraph in the draft before submitting it to the
                            Chilean Government or at any time during the negotiations.</p>
                        <p>If it be included it will be added as the third paragraph of Article XXX.
                            The words “Except as provided in the third paragraph of this Article”
                            will be inserted at the beginning of the first paragraph of Article XXX
                            and the new paragraph will read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The sixth and seventh paragraphs of Article VII and Articles X
                                    and XII shall remain in force for twelve months from the date of
                                    exchange of ratifications, and if not then terminated on ninety
                                    days previous notice shall remain in force until either of the
                                    High Contracting Parties shall enact legislation inconsistent
                                    therewith when the same shall automatically lapse at the end of
                                    sixty days from such enactment, and on such lapse each High
                                    Contracting Party shall enjoy all the rights which it would have
                                    possessed had such paragraphs or articles not been embraced in
                                    the Treaty”.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Further comment in regard to the differences between the enclosed draft
                            and the treaty of the United States with Germany will be included in the
                            detailed instructions.</p>
                        <p>When presenting the draft to the Foreign Office please state that this
                            Government reserves the right to propose changes therein throughout the
                            course of the negotiations. Please inform the Department by telegram of
                            the receipt of this instruction. You will, of course, not present the
                            draft to the Foreign Office, until the Department sends you a further
                            communication authorizing you to do so.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>