<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-06-22T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-06-22T11:00:00-05:00" n="50" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15 a 1/313: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gibson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-06-22T17:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">June 22,
                                        1927—5 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 5:05
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>22. Dulles and I visited Ishii and Saito this morning with a view to
                            learning what the Japanese thought of the British proposals<note n="46" xml:id="d50fn46">See S. Doc. 55, 70th Cong., 1st sess., pp. 28,
                                30.</note> relative to the Washington Naval Treaty. My hope was that
                            they would share the American view that the present Conference should
                            not take up these questions; but Ishii said that while they were limited
                            by their instructions to a consideration of the extension to <pb facs="0135" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> auxiliary vessels of the
                            Washington principles, yet they could consider any matters in regard to
                            naval armaments by virtue of their full powers. They had, however,
                            requested instructions from their Government, since they were uncertain
                            as to whether the latter desired a consideration of modifications in the
                            Washington treaty as suggested by the British. Viscount Ishii, in view
                            of his superior knowledge of English, was the chief spokesman, and gave
                            it as his opinion that, while he was unable to predict his Government’s
                            attitude in the premises, the economy effected if the British proposals
                            were adopted seemed rather desirable.</p>
                        <p>To this I remarked that it was not wise to consider the British proposals
                            at the present time, however meritorious they might be, and that the
                            subjects covered by them would, under the stipulations of the Washington
                            treaty, be considered in 1931, at which time France and Italy were bound
                            to participate. Moreover, I pointed out that any agreements that might
                            be made now would be largely academic, and might have to be changed in
                            1931, and that anyhow no replacements would take place until that year
                            or even later; it therefore appeared desirable to postpone discussion of
                            the Washington treaty until 1931, and to bend our entire efforts to the
                            application of the established Washington treaty principles to auxiliary
                            craft.</p>
                        <p>In reply, Viscount Ishii stated that apart from the question of economy,
                            it should be remembered that the Conference in 1931 would not be held
                            until August, and that since the Japanese Diet would not convene until
                            the close of the year, any agreements made at the Conference would not
                            be immediately put into effect. This would embarrass the Government by
                            forcing it either to lose a certain amount of time after the Conference
                            before making its estimates, or making appropriations from the former
                            session of the Diet; that clear estimates for the earlier session were
                            difficult of preparation, since appropriations would have to be asked
                            for vessels of maximum size should no further limitation be arrived at,
                            while, on the other hand, were the duration of capital ships to be
                            extended, the only appropriations necessary would be for making repairs,
                            etc. These were considerations which he thought justified to some extent
                            the British proposals. Upon receipt of instructions from Tokyo, he will
                            again discuss these questions with me.</p>
                        <p>A clear definition of our position will have to be made should the
                            Japanese delegation be directed to support the British proposal, and I
                            am accordingly submitting to you separately a draft statement<note n="47" xml:id="d50fn47">See telegram No. 25, June 23, 7 p.m., from
                                the chairman of the American delegation, <ref target="#pg_50">p.
                                    50</ref>.</note> which might, without weakening our fundamental
                            stand, surmount the difficulty indicated by the Japanese delegate.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>