<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-07-13T09:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-07-13T09:50:00-05:00" n="148" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d148">
                        <head>148. Memorandum of Telephone Conversation Between President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and the Under Secretary of
                            State for Economic Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d148fn1">Source:
                                Johnson Library, Mann Papers, Telephone Conversations with <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">LBJ</persName>, May 2, 1965–June 2, 1966. No
                                classification marking. Transcribed in <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>’s office.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-07-13T10:50:00-04:00">July 13, 1965, 10:50
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>The President said he had received Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>’s note.<note n="2" xml:id="d148fn2">Not
                                found.</note> He said that he thought it was a little late to get
                            the letter<note n="3" xml:id="d148fn3">Not further identified.</note>
                            changed. The President said he would be glad to see him when he wishes
                            to come. The President said he would like Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> to get the best economic people
                            thinking about the food shortage—make a special case out of it—there is
                            starvation and famine—and then submit a recommendation to the Congress
                            saying here is the situation, here is what they are asking for, here is
                            a real serious situation and ask Congress to consider it, act on it and
                            dispose of it. The President said he would like to send a special case
                            up rather than taking the responsibility himself.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> said the thing that
                            bothered him was that the Indians might not realize that the timing of
                            this visit may be important. He said he had not said anything to the
                            Indians but he thought that somehow they ought to be made aware of this.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> admitted that it may be
                            too late this morning to try to get the letter changed and perhaps we
                            should be working on some kind of talk between the President and
                                <persName corresp="#p_SLB1">Shastri</persName> and the President and
                            Ayub. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> said if they did
                            not lose their heads over there, we might be able to really accomplish
                            something.</p>
                        <p>The President said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>
                            should tell <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> that <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> had announced this morning the
                            postponement of the consortium, and that the President was hoping to see
                            Ayub before the consortium was held at the end of September. The
                            President said they might not want to be definite about next year in
                            these circumstances. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>
                            said that was his idea exactly. He said he had no intention to press the
                            Ambassador but only to make him aware. The President said he did not
                            want to take the responsibility personally for this. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> asked what would happen if these
                            visits came through and we worked out some kind of a sensible
                            arrangement with both countries. He said he did not know if this was
                            possible with Pakistan but he thought it was possible with India. He
                            said in this case, we might go ahead with the original program. The
                            President repeated that he did not want to take this responsibility—he
                            wished the Congress <pb facs="0338" n="300" xml:id="pg_300"/> to pass on
                            it. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> said he would pass
                            the message on in an oblique way to <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The President said he would be most happy to see him as soon as the
                            appropriation bill gets through the House. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> said he understood. He said he was
                            not going to urge the Ambassador to do anything. He is just going to
                            make him conscious of the situation.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion unrelated to South Asia.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>