<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>166. Minutes of Meeting of the 303 Committee</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="receU2jshk3GXzdwQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="covert-actions">Intelligence collection</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="166"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                <head>166. Minutes of Meeting of the 303 Committee<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1"
                            >INR</gloss>/IL Historical Files, 303 C.24, August 26, 1965. Secret;
                        Eyes Only. Prepared on August 10 by <persName>Peter Jessup</persName> of the
                        National Security Council Staff. Copies were sent to Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>, Vance, and Admiral <persName
                            corresp="#p_RVAWFJ1">Raborn</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-08-09">August 9, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Minutes of the Meeting of the 303 Committee, 9 August 1965</item>
                </list>
                <list type="simple">
                    <head>PRESENT</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName>, Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>, and Admiral <persName
                            corresp="#p_RVAWFJ1">Raborn</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Also present were Lt. General Marshall S. Carter (<gloss target="#t_NSA1"
                            >NSA</gloss>), Lt. General Joseph F. Carroll (<gloss target="#t_DIA1"
                            >DIA</gloss>), Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Robert W.
                            Komer</persName>, and Dr. Huntington Sheldon</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Pakistan</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>a.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> asked Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> to provide the committee with a brief
                        summary of the Pakistan problem. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1"
                            >Komer</persName> pointed out that we were seeking ways to persuade
                        Ayub—the only person one can do business with in Pakistan—to come to us
                        before the 23rd of September, the consortium deadline. Among the few visible
                        means of leverage would be suspension of construction on the U.S. [<hi
                            rend="italic">less than 1 line of <pb facs="0369" n="331"
                                xml:id="pg_331"/> source text not declassified</hi>] installations
                        in Peshawar. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> pointed out
                        that the Paks regarded Peshawar as their hole card; if we could shake their
                        confidence that this was so by such a gesture (while not affecting
                        intelligence collection per se), it could indicate to Ayub that the U.S.
                        meant business.</item>
                    <label>b.</label>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> stated that he
                        had discussed these matters with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                            >Rusk</persName>, who wanted to talk further with Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>. He also suggested that the
                        suspension of construction ploy could have the opposite effect of that
                        intended: instead of “shaking up” the Pakistanis, they might interpret that
                        we were being deferential towards them.</item>
                    <label>c.</label>
                    <item>The earlier suggestion of Mr. Vance that [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                            line of source text not declassified</hi>] was also thought to contain
                        backfire possibilities: it might be difficult to get them back in at a later
                        date, and it might be read as an admission that [<hi rend="italic">less than
                            1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] did not constitute a
                        priority project.</item>
                    <label>d.</label>
                    <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RVAWFJ1">Raborn</persName> felt that
                        stopping the construction was a minimal gesture at best that would only
                        muddy waters and could set in motion more undesirable events.</item>
                    <label>e.</label>
                    <item>On the question of alternate sites, Mr. Komer pointed out that presumably
                        the Pakistanis could publicize any moves we make in the direction of Iran
                            [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>] with unfortunate results. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1"
                            >Komer</persName> emphasized that ways to test the reliability of our
                        ally were few and far between. He suggested [<hi rend="italic">1 line of
                            source text not declassified</hi>].</item>
                    <label>f.</label>
                    <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RVAWFJ1">Raborn</persName> stated that he
                        looked with little optimism on the alternate site [<hi rend="italic">less
                            than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] as long-range risks
                        and that Pakistan was, in effect, a bonded ally and all methods of
                        negotiating should be explored. He felt the threat of suspension of foreign
                        aid was the single strongest weapon in our arsenal and reiterated that the
                        suspension of construction threat was a minor tactic.</item>
                    <label>g.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> warned that higher
                        authority was unlikely to respond to blackmail tactics by Pakistan. With the
                        Pakistanis lambasting us on a regular basis it was going to be difficult
                        when we reached the deadline of the 23rd of September to feed the hand that
                        bites us. If we were then unable to make a pledge because it would seem like
                        caving to <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> public pressures, the risks of
                            <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> retaliation against Peshawar would
                        go up.</item>
                    <label>h.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> summarized the disparate
                        views and stated that we must all search for quiet ways to convince Ayub in
                        the next six weeks. We sought to produce a tactical situation to reopen
                        talks with Ayub and to indicate our state of mind. He concluded that
                        agreement could not be reached in this meeting, and the matter would be
                        referred back to the Secretaries of State and Defense. He emphasized that we
                        want to avoid creating an atmosphere of haggle.</item>
                    <pb facs="0370" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/>
                    <label>i.</label>
                    <item>Generals Carroll and Carter summarized the exact status of the building
                        program.</item>
                    <label>j.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> indicated the spiraling
                        nature of the situation down to 23 September and repeated that even small
                        efforts could be worth trying now.</item>
                    <label>k.</label>
                    <item>The Committee did agree to the following: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>to proceed rapidly with all preliminary planning for alternate
                                sites;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>not to break ground for the construction of the <gloss
                                    target="#t_BOQ1">BOQ</gloss> at Peshawar (new construction, as
                                opposed to work in progress);</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>not to use [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>] for approaches to Ayub in view of certain
                                recent changes, [<hi rend="italic">1 line of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>];</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>the results of this discussion would be brought to the attention
                                of Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> as possible
                                assistance in their deliberations.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows discussion unrelated to Pakistan.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Peter Jessup</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
