<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>276. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State and Chairman of
                    the Policy Planning Council (Rostow) to President ) to President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-01-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-01-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="276"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                <head>276. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State and Chairman of
                    the Policy Planning Council (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from"
                        >Rostow</persName>) to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d276fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, India, Vol. VI, Cables, 9/65–1/66. No
                        classification marking. A handwritten “L” on the memorandum indicates that
                        it was seen by the President.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-01-06">January 6, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Indian Food Situation: The Problem of Timing</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have been reading the history of the last great famine in India—in 1943—and
                    discussing with experts the timing of various aspects of the Indian food
                    situation this year.</p>
                <p>Three facts emerge.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>During February and March of this year there will be about 500,000 tons of
                        unutilized Indian port capacity which could be used to build stocks if grain
                        shipments get there on time. From April on port capacity will be
                        tight.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>If chemical fertilizers are to be applied in time to raise output in the
                        November 1966 harvest, they must arrive in India by June.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>If the food situation is as serious as all our experts tell us it will be,
                        there will be certain signs of malnutrition and famine in the spring; but
                        the most dangerous period will come in the months August–October 1966. <pb
                            facs="0565" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> From these facts, it seems clear
                        that we ought to make a maximum effort now to use the 500,000 tons of idle
                        port capacity available during February and March. That would be enough
                        grain to feed something like 10 million people in the three critical months
                        before the November harvest. Although we will be exploring with the Indians
                        the possibility of extraordinary methods for food delivery, it is possible
                        that what we lose in February and March will be lost for good.</item>
                </list>
                <p>So far as the U.S. is concerned, it may take a prompt decision by you to proceed
                    with a <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> 480 agreement beyond the 1.5 million
                    tons in order to mobilize the wheat and the shipping in time to exploit the idle
                    port capacity available in February and March.</p>
                <p>In addition, it may be necessary for the Indians to put direct, very high-level
                    pressure on the Canadians and Australians to divert some ships from their
                    commercial traffic to Indian ports. I suspect only decisions by the Prime
                    Ministers could force the special arrangements required to divert cargoes. We
                    may wish Chet Bowles to call this possibility to <persName corresp="#p_SLB1"
                        >Shastri</persName>’s attention when he returns from Tashkent.</p>
                <p>Frankly, what worries me, as a planner, is that a good many human beings may
                    starve in those critical months before the next harvest because all of us didn’t
                    make the special urgent effort necessary to use the idle port capacity briefly
                    available in the next several months.<note n="2" xml:id="d276fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> sent a memorandum to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> on January 8 in which he
                        also stressed the importance of taking advantage of the opportunity to ship
                        grain to India before Indian port capacity was cut by the onset of the rainy
                        season in late May. (Ibid., Memos to the President, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, Vol. 18, January 1–8,
                        1966)</note> (Probably 3 million Indians starved to death in the 1943
                    famine.)</p>
                <p>A similar sense of urgency will be required to round up the chemical fertilizers
                    and get them there by June. If they don’t lay the fertilizer down in time, we
                    could have a second thin harvest in 1966–67. In the case of fertilizers,
                    pressure will probably have to be exerted on Japan, Germany and Britain, since I
                    am told that our fertilizer production and shipping capacity are committed to
                    the hilt. Again, the Indians should be leaning on them; and we should be backing
                    their play.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
