<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-06-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                        <head>346. Summary Notes of the 558th Meeting of the National Security
                                Council<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d346fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, National Security
                                File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings, Vol. 3, 6/9/66, The
                                Problem of Indian Nuclear Weapons. Secret/Sensitive; For the
                                President Only. Those attending the meeting, in addition to the
                                President, included the Vice President, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, Rostow, <persName corresp="#p_RVAWFJ1">Raborn</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName>, Treasury
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_FHH1">Henry Fowler</persName>,
                                    <gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss> Director William Foster,
                                    <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> Director John Palfrey,
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> Director Leonard Marks,
                                and <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Chairman General Earle
                                Wheeler. (List of attendees for the 558th <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting; ibid.)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-06-09">June 9, 1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Problem of Indian Nuclear Weapons</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President: indicated that this was the first of a series of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meetings to be devoted to the
                            discussion of complex problems requiring careful exploration before they
                            were to come to him for discussion. He expressed his concern about the
                            growing pressures in India favoring the nuclear route. Its own economic
                            progress and the stability of the whole area depended on India not going
                            nuclear. The Paper<note n="2" xml:id="d346fn2">Reference is to an
                                interdepartmental policy paper entitled “The Indian Nuclear Weapons
                                Problem: Current Issues,” which was circulated to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> members June 7 under a covering
                                memorandum from <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Executive
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley Smith</persName>.
                                (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files:
                                    <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 70 A 4443, India
                                471.61)</note> admirably summarized the problems. He invited Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> to lay out the
                            issues.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: briefly summarized the
                            Interdepartmental paper of June 7, 1966, on this subject, giving the
                            pros and cons of the suggested alternatives<note n="3" xml:id="d346fn3">The alternatives suggested in the policy paper as having the
                                potential to restrain the development of an Indian nuclear device
                                included economic pressure the United States could bring to bear,
                                the dampening effect that an arms control agreement between the
                                United States and the Soviet Union would have on an Indian nuclear
                                program, and a bilateral or multilateral security arrangement to
                                guarantee India against a nuclear attack.</note> (Plowshare<note n="4" xml:id="d346fn4">Plowshare was the program being developed to
                                demonstrate the peaceful potential of controlled nuclear
                                explosions.</note> was not mentioned). Although his presentation was
                            even-handed, he appeared to favor some form of multilateral approach
                            which attempted to deal with India’s real security problems.</p>
                        <p>He recommended further—and urgent—staff studies.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>: agreed and thought
                            recommendations could come forward for Presidential consideration within
                            two to three weeks.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Foster: Stressed the urgency, since disarmament meetings resume in
                            Geneva in June, and the U.S. must have an improved position within a
                            month or six weeks at the outside. He thought the two or three principal
                            alternatives now under study (in the Committee of Principals) could
                            easily be staffed out and recommended within a month.</p>
                        <pb facs="0710" n="672" xml:id="pg_672"/>
                        <p>Mr. Marks: Urged (a) a conference of world intellectuals to stress the
                            economic costs and security liabilities of nuclear weapons; (b) using
                            the 20th anniversary of the Baruch proposals<note n="5" xml:id="d346fn5">Reference is to U.S. proposals for the international control of
                                atomic energy put forward in a statement on June 14, 1946, by
                                Bernard M. Baruch, the U.S. representative on the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Atomic Energy Commission. For text of
                                the statement, see <hi rend="italic">A Decade of American Foreign
                                    Policy, Basic Documents: 1941–1949</hi>, pp. 865–871.</note> as
                            the occasion for a bold new U.S. initiative.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President: Stressed how little additional expenditure would be
                            necessary beyond that already invested for India to go nuclear. He
                            preferred a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> umbrella with private U.S.
                            reassurances to India. This leaves the door open to the Soviets without
                            forcing either the Indians or Russia to take a public stand.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName>: Stressed the
                            urgency of deciding on any such arrangement, since it would require
                            soundings with the Russians well in advance of the opening of the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> in September. Also necessary would be
                            precise commitments to the Indians.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Foster: Cited Minister Banerjee, the Indian Minister who had
                            officially indicated that “for a period, a General Assembly resolution
                            would be adequate.”</p>
                        <p>Mr. Rostow: Urged: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>the urgency of our own explorations but reminded the Council
                                    of the complexity of decisions countries must face before they
                                    chose to go nuclear. Our problem was to buy time until the
                                    Indians came to accept the necessity for Western
                                    assistance;</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>the nuclear issue was so complex that it could not be dealt
                                    with solely by the specialists concentrating on arms control or
                                    by the country or area specialists. We must find ways of
                                    combining these two types of specialists in the study of this
                                    problem.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President: Instructed the Department<note n="6" xml:id="d346fn6">An
                                apparent reference to the Department of State. See <ref target="#d359">Document 359</ref>.</note> to speed the study of
                            the Indian nuclear problem and said he would issue a <gloss target="#t_NSAM1">NSAM</gloss> shortly.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WWH1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Howard Wriggins</hi>
                                </persName><note n="7" xml:id="d346fn7">Printed from a copy that
                                    bears this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>