<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-08-09T14:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-08-09T14:30:00-05:00" n="366" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                        <head>366. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Pakistan</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d366fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> INDIA–<gloss target="#t_Pak1">PAK</gloss>. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to Saigon for
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and to Karachi.
                                Passed to the White House at 7:04 p.m.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Rawalpindi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-08-09T19:30:00+00:00">August 9, 1966,
                                1930Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>435. 1. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and I had fine meeting for
                            2–1/2 hours in Bangkok. We agree such meetings are highly desirable.</p>
                        <p>2. On Kashmir <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and I agree it would be
                            desirable to have secret meetings between trusted emissaries of Mrs.
                                <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> and Pres Ayub who might
                            be named at exploratory meeting between these Chiefs of State. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> doubts however that actual
                            results will flow from such meetings until India sorts out relations
                            with Kashmiris.</p>
                        <p>3. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and I agree problem of
                                Indo-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> relations is broader than
                            Kashmir and discussions should involve other subjects. Perhaps Ayub and
                            Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName>, or their emissaries,
                            could settle on framework for discussing together subjects. We agree I
                            should discuss with Ayub whether and where he will meet with Mrs.
                                <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> and his version of
                            modalities of future discussions between the two countries.</p>
                        <p>4. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and I agree on importance
                            of preventing arms race on subcontinent. To this end it is my belief we
                            should seek to bring about secret discussions on arms limitation between
                            representatives of both countries chosen by their respective Chief of
                            State. I desire to discuss with Ayub his willingness to authorize such
                            discussions.</p>
                        <p>5. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> does not believe <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> will hold meaningful discussions if
                            U.S. provides lethal spare parts for Pakistan and unless (A) Pakistan
                            renounces use of force in regard to Kashmir and (B) U.S. offers some
                            tangible assurance of assistance to <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                            in event of <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss> and/or <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> attack. He believes if we do not
                            furnish spares to Pakistan India might be persuaded as first step to
                            agree to assessment of size of its own and <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> military establishments by World Bank. I believe
                            bilateral discussions between representatives of the two countries
                            probably will be more fruitful. If such discussions cannot now be
                            brought about, I believe we should seek to promote same objective of
                            stable military force relationship through separate discussions between
                            U.S. and each country.</p>
                        <p>6. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> and I do not reach any
                            broad agreement on complex of issues relating to U.S. military policy
                            toward subcontinent. We agree <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>
                            military dependence on <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s would
                            be disastrous for India, and one of our prime objectives with respect to
                            India is to prevent <pb facs="0751" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> Pakistan
                            from growing closer to <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s.
                                <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> believes Indian leaders
                            would agree with this and would also agree China is main threat to
                            India. He indicates that principal fear of Indian leaders is possibility
                            of <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> military combination. However, <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> considers that (A)
                            Pakistan will not move closer to China even if Pakistan fails to secure
                            lethal spare parts because Ayub and landowners supporting him will not
                            tolerate further closeness to Communism; (B) we can in any event prevent
                            such a development by threatening to shut off economic aid to Pakistan;
                            and (C) <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s would not increase
                            military aid to Pakistan to any extent because of their own
                            requirements.</p>
                        <p>7. On sale of equipment to Pakistan by friendly third countries, <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> says he will do everything
                            he can, using argument U.S. not responsible for what other sovereign
                            nations do, to manage what he expects will be serious problem to Indian
                            reaction.</p>
                        <p>8. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> may have
                            further comments.</p>
                        <p>9. For my part, with respect to these critical questions of U.S. military
                            policy in this part of world, I remain convinced for reasons I set forth
                            in Washington that course outlined in draft memorandum for President
                            entitled “Military Supply Policy for India and Pakistan” is right.<note n="2" xml:id="d366fn2">See <ref target="#d365">Document 365</ref>.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LEM1">Locke</persName> sent his comments
                                on the memorandum to the President in a memorandum dated July 25.
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library,
                                National Security File, Country File, Pakistan, Vol. VI, Memos,
                                1/66–9/66)</note> I believe it most important I be able to talk to
                            Ayub along lines of this memorandum shortly after his return from Dacca
                            August 12. The security of India will not be advanced if Pakistan is
                            continually pressed toward China by Indian military weight. In my
                            judgement this vicious circle must be broken.<note n="3" xml:id="d366fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> transmitted his
                                comments on his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_LEM1">Locke</persName> in Bangkok in telegram 3200 from Saigon,
                                August 11. <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> stated that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LEM1">Locke</persName>’s account
                                accurately reflected the meeting. His only qualification was to note
                                that he had been pressing the Indian Government for a heads of state
                                meeting not, as <persName corresp="#p_LEM1">Locke</persName>
                                reported, to settle Indo-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>
                                differences, but to create a positive atmosphere in which to discuss
                                differences and find solutions. (National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> INDIA–<gloss target="#t_Pak1">PAK</gloss>) Rostow sent copies of both
                                Ambassadors’ accounts of the meeting in Bangkok to President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> on August 11.
                                Rostow’s advice was that “we ought to move very cautiously about
                                spare parts for Pakistan; but move very strongly via our two
                                Ambassadors and <persName corresp="#p_WGD1">George Woods</persName>
                                towards getting India-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> agreement
                                on the level of their military budgets.” (<persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, National Security
                                File, Country File, Pakistan, Vol. VI, Memos, 1/66–9/66)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LEM1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Locke</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>