<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>42. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                    International Security Affairs (Solbert) to Secretary of Defense ) to Secretary
                    of Defense McNamara</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">42</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recEnoRBV734Mk0Gc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082092"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Materials handling equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rechaRqhHZqAlDnM2" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133293"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="rec8YLqqCAyYMVeaL" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Defense spending</term>
                    <term ref="rec3QSbxhrMctVdHq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">F–5 aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recakeAztvHvxtY4X" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="42"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                <head>42. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                    International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SPOA1" type="from"
                        >Solbert</persName>) to Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                        type="to">McNamara</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d42fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                            >OSD</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 69 A 7425, India
                        091.3 MSP. Secret. Received in the Office of the Secretary of Defense on May
                        7 at 10:52 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-05-06">May 6, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Long Term Military Assistance for India</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Discussions with the Indians</hi>. We will be reviewing
                        the Indian Five-Year Defense Plan with the Indian experts on May 11–15 and
                        with Defense Minister Chavan on May 19–21.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">General Approach</hi>. The main purpose of these
                        discussions will be to persuade the Indians to revise their Plan downward.
                        At the same time we will review the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65
                        program with the Indians. We also plan to be forthcoming (on a credit sales
                        or grant basis) on certain specific items which we can agree are reasonable
                        and have a high priority, such as aircraft as discussed below, which might
                        be funded subsequent to <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65. While this is
                        a deviation from the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> recommendation (Tab
                            A)<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">Not found attached. The attachment was
                            apparently a draft of the memorandum dealing with air defense aircraft
                            for India that the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> sent to <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> as <gloss target="#t_JCSM1"
                                >JCSM</gloss>-396–64 on May 8. (Ibid., India 452)</note> that we
                        should not make any commitments beyond the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                        65 plan until the Indians revise their Plan, it seems a desirable step to
                        evidence our good faith in the current negotiations.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Assistance Credit Sales</hi>. We would hope
                            that during the meeting with Minister Chavan we might be sufficiently
                            forthcoming in the credit sales area to arrive at a Memorandum of
                            Understanding to be signed by yourself and the Minister on an initial
                            sales package using <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 64, and possibly
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65, money to finance the credit
                            terms. We anticipate that the major portion of credit sales which could
                            be agreed upon at this time would be in the area of defense production
                            machinery but might also include such items as vehicles, tanks,
                            materials handling equipment, communications equipment, raw materials
                            and road construction equipment. We understand that the Indians consider
                            defense production as a most important field.</p>
                        <p>In the longer run, upon agreement as to a more reasonable Indian Plan, a
                            military assistance sales program can be established for India involving
                            both cash and credit sales. This could provide over a 5-year period an
                            annual credit line of $35–$50 million, repayable over a 5 to <pb
                                facs="0137" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> 10 year period at an interest
                            rate not exceeding 5% as the initial U.S. negotiating position. Henry
                            Kuss has in mind for consideration later some of the items in the Indian
                            Plan such as transport aircraft (C–130s), supersonic aircraft (such as
                            F–104s), and possibly Hawk missiles. While we may come to some of these
                            items for India some day, they are not presently justified by the <gloss
                                target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss> threat and their excessive
                            expense is inconsistent with our pressures for reduction of Indian
                            defense spending and our support of the Indian economic program.</p>
                        <p>We plan at present to aim for a credit sales program for <gloss
                                target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 64, and possibly <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                                >FY</gloss> 65, covering low cost but high priority items and not
                            discuss at this time the above-mentioned more expensive items.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Air Defense Aircraft</hi>. As you recall, when
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">Bowles</persName> was here it was
                            agreed that we would discuss with the Indians the capability, cost, and
                            availability of F–6A and F–5 aircraft and offer to assist in development
                            of the HF–24. Since the Ambassador has returned to India, he has
                            reverted to his original position that supplying several squadrons of
                            F–104s is the only method to achieve his objective of minimizing Soviet
                            influence in the Indian Air Force. In our judgment, and that of State,
                            supplying F–104s to India in the present time frame will cause serious
                            problems with the Pakistanis and is not presently required by the <gloss
                                target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss> threat (though there is now
                            increasing evidence that the <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s
                            have some <gloss target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss> 21s).</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, I recommend that F–104s not be offered to the Indians on any
                            basis at present, though this would not necessarily preclude some future
                            cash or credit sales arrangement if our efforts involving the HF–24 are
                            not successful. In lieu thereof I recommend that we offer as
                            alternatives F–6A aircraft on a grant aid basis or F–5 aircraft on a
                            grant aid or credit sales basis, along with the assistance on the HF–24,
                            as discussed below.<note n="3" xml:id="d42fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> initialed his
                                approval on May 8.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>While we will make every effort to persuade the Indians to accept our
                            F–6A or F–5 aircraft, along with development of the HF–24, the general
                            feeling of the Country Team in India is that this aircraft package will
                            be unacceptable to the Indians. If this turns out to be the case, we can
                            consider possible alternatives during Chavan’s discussions with you. One
                            alternative, proposed by the State Department, is for the U.S. to say to
                            the Indians that if, after an examination of technical feasibility, the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and the U.S. agree with India to
                            collaborate in the production of the HF–24, and if this collaboration
                            fails to produce a supersonic interceptor adequate to meet the <gloss
                                target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss> threat, at such time as this
                            failure is determined the U.S. will assist in finding other means to
                            meet the Indian need for supersonic aircraft. I regard this as a
                            commitment <pb facs="0138" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/> to make available
                            to the Indians, on a credit or cash purchase basis, a Mach 2 aircraft
                            some two or three years from now if the HF–24 project fails. While this
                            proposition has some merit, it is an extremely vague commitment and I
                            recommend we defer any action on such a statement to the Indians pending
                            our assessment of the Indian experts’ reactions to the presently
                            proposed aircraft package.<note n="4" xml:id="d42fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> initialed his
                                approval on May 8.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">HF–24</hi>. Our exploration of the feasibility of
                            assisting the Indians with the development of an engine for the HF–24
                            has been held up because the Indians have not granted permission for the
                                US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> team to visit the plant in
                            India. The Embassy in New Delhi believes this is because of current
                            negotiations with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> for an engine.
                            The Indians have, however, offered to send drawings of the airframe to
                            Rolls Royce in London. The project still seems feasible, and accordingly
                            we will suggest to the Indians when they are in Washington that they
                            permit a team of US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> personnel to visit
                            India as soon as possible to study the problems of adapting the HF–24
                            airframe to the Rolls Royce engine and the problems of manufacturing the
                            aircraft and engine in India.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sparrow</hi>. I understand that the Navy has as of this
                        date determined that the Sparrow missile should not be released to India. So
                        far Sparrow III, which we have been considering giving to India for the
                        F–6A, has not been given to any other country (including <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>), and the Navy feels that release would
                        result in serious risk of compromising Sparrow III–6B which is used on our
                        first line fighters. (We do have clearance on Sidewinder.)</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPOA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Peter Solbert</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
