<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>437. Telegram From the Embassy in India to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d437</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">437</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-04-10T09:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-04-10T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-04-10T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-04-10T09:30:00-05:00" n="437"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d437">
                <head>437. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in India</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d437fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                        DEF 12–5 INDIA. Secret; Priority; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1"
                        >Exdis</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-04-10T14:30:00+00:00">April 10, 1967,
                        1430Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>14747. Dept pass <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKE1">CINCSTRIKE</gloss>/USCINCMEAFSA,
                    AmEmbassy London, AmEmbassy Rawalpindi, AmEmbassy Tehran. Ref: State 166539<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d437fn2">
                        <ref target="#d431">Document 431</ref>.</note> and 168709.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d437fn3">
                        <ref target="#d433">Document 433</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0881" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>I decided it best convey contents <gloss target="#t_reftel1"
                            >reftel</gloss>s to Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1"
                            >Chagla</persName> rather than Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_GI1"
                            >Gandhi</persName> since once she took position it would be government
                        policy, whereas we retain some flexibility by making approach to <persName
                            corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName>. I also decided to convey our
                        position in writing and accordingly handed him aide-mémoire at beginning our
                        meeting. Full text aide-mémoire transmitted next following telegram.<note
                            n="4" xml:id="d437fn4">Telegram 14748 from New Delhi, April 10.
                            (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                                >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, DEF 12–INDIA)</note> While
                        meeting was conducted in polite terms, there was no doubt that <persName
                            corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> and Bajpai, who was also present,
                        were deeply concerned over effects of our decision.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>After reading aide-mémoire <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName>
                        stressed that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> policy is to attempt to
                        prevent arms race which is harmful to both India and Pakistan. <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> is prepared for serious talks. I asked if
                        he had yet had reply to his letter to Foreign Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_PS1">Pirzada</persName>. He replied in the negative but
                        stated he understood reply was about to be received and Indian <gloss
                            target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> in <gloss target="#t_Pindi1"
                            >Pindi</gloss> was returning tomorrow to Delhi and he expected he would
                        be carrying reply with him.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> said the question was how far
                        U.S. policy would contribute to achieving our shared objective of preventing
                        an arms race. He pointed out <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> was worried
                        not merely about arms that the Paks obtained from all over the world but
                        about the arms that were going to Pakistan through Iran, Turkey and Saudi
                        Arabia. in this connection he cited unusual circumstance of Iranian planes
                        recently taking part in Pakistani National Day celebrations. He said he
                        would be going to Tehran in a few days and wanted to have a frank talk with
                        the Shah.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> said deep concern would be
                        aroused by resumption of provision of spare parts for lethal equipment in
                        hands of Paks even on sales basis since this would understandably strengthen
                            <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> military capacity. I pointed out
                        that we were simply readjusting our policy so that it would now be
                        consistent with that of other Western countries. He believed new policy
                        strongly favored Paks and reminded me that they had previously told us Paks
                        would use our weapons against India. We had been unable to prevent Paks from
                        using such equipment against India.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> was concerned that effect of
                        resumption spare parts supply for Pakistan lethal equipment would inevitably
                        lead to a step up in arms race. It was felt that the timing of our move was
                        “singularly unfortunate” coming immediately before anticipated reply of Paks
                        to <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> letter. Our new policy it
                        was feared would encourage <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>
                        intransigence. He pointed out that criteria of limitation of military <pb
                            facs="0882" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/> expenditures means that Paks will
                        be able to obtain more equipment within the same expenditure ceiling.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> asked if we agreed that the
                        Indians should discuss arms limitations irrespective of Kashmir, and I told
                        him we understood that the Kashmir problem could not be solved first.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Bajpai expressed grave concern which <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1"
                            >Chagla</persName> shared that proposed announcement April 12 would have
                        extremely damaging effect not only on Indian public attitudes but also on
                        L.K. Jha’s visit to Washington. They strongly urged that announcement be
                        held up at least a few days.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In closing <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> agreed with my
                        suggestion that the value of this policy would be determined by the manner
                        in which we implemented it and added that if it helped the Indo-<gloss
                            target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> dialogue it was all well and good, if not,
                        all India’s efforts to establish a dialogue would be for naught. We agreed
                        that we would again be in touch in a few days after they had had an
                        opportunity to give a thorough study to our aide-mémoire.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>During meeting I also handed Foreign Minister on separate paper text of
                        proposed press statement. I did not give him text of contingency questions
                        and answers. Bajpai pointed out that the press statement as presently
                        drafted draws major attention to our provision spare parts for previously
                        supplied equipment to Paks and fact India also included as <persName
                            corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> put it was “SOP with no real
                        meaning”, since we have not in past provided lethal items to Indians on
                        anywhere near scale provided Paks.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Effect of proposed press statement he said will be highly damaging our
                        interests in India. (Note: I am sending separate message April 11 containing
                        suggested redraft of press statement which is attempt to place our policy in
                        perspective that would help diminish difficulties here.)</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Action requested: As <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> will
                        undoubtedly be calling me back in day or two for further discussion, I would
                        like to be able to assure him catagorically that if Paks give a negative
                        response to <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName> letter<note n="5"
                            xml:id="d437fn5">C.S. Jha told <persName corresp="#p_BCA1"
                                >Bowles</persName> on April 11 that Pakistan had just rejected the
                            proposal in <persName corresp="#p_CMAC1">Chagla</persName>’s letter. Jha
                            stated that the Pakistani response would amplify the negative reaction
                            in India to the decision taken by the United States on military supply
                            policy. (Telegram 14899 from New Delhi, April 12; ibid.)</note> calling
                        for arms limitation, and by negative response I include a reply indicating
                        prior necessity to settle Kashmir, that I be authorized assure <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> in such circumstances we would not proceed
                        authorize sale spare parts for previously supplied lethal military
                        equipment. Anything further I could say to effect Paks agree not go to
                            <gloss target="#t_ChiCom1">ChiCom</gloss>s for additional equipment
                        would be helpful.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BCA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Bowles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
