<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>505. Letter From President Ayub to President to President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-07-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recozOKDL3hzRM0mM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-07-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="505"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <head>505. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_AKFMM1" type="from"
                        >Ayub</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d505fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Head of State Correspondence File, Pakistan, Vol. 3,
                        President Ayub Correspondence, 12/31/67–[sic]. No classification marking.
                        Delivered to the White House by the Pakistani Embassy on July 31.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Rawalpindi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-07-19">July 19, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Mr. President,</p>
                <p>I thank you for your message of July the 16th,<note n="2" xml:id="d505fn2">See
                            <ref target="#d503">Document 503</ref>.</note> delivered by your
                    Ambassador in Pakistan and appreciate very much the directness and candour with
                    which you have referred to the issue of the US communications facility near
                    Peshawar.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In a spirit of equal honesty and frankness I would like to explain to you
                        the position as we see it.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>To the best of our knowledge, the Peshawar facility monitors a variety of
                        activities and operations. Or to put it in your own words, it provides
                        “accurate technical and scientific information on the intentions and
                        capabilities of others”. I concede that this facility is valuable to your
                        country but by its very nature it lays us open to the hostility and
                        retaliation of powerful neighbours.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The close relationship between our two countries in the security field, to
                        which you have alluded in your letter, Mr. President, has progressively been
                        whittled away. Only last year when your Ambassador communicated to us the
                        new United States arms supply policy, he said that “a fundamental and
                        historical change” had come about in our relationship. Your Secretary of
                        State told our Foreign Minister last October in Washington that there was
                        now “no special relationship” between Pakistan and the United States.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>We in Pakistan cannot remain unmindful of the swift changes which are
                        taking place in the world and especially around us today. We cannot ignore
                        the threats which are developing to our existence, particularly from the
                        feverish arms build-up in India. The arms supply policy of your country
                        provides us with no comfort. If anything, it aggravates the imbalance
                        between India and Pakistan.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The Peshawar facility on our soil in no way contributes to our security
                        useful though it may be to your country. For us it constitutes a
                        danger.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Changes in world politics make it imperative for Pakistan to improve its
                        relations with neighbouring countries and for this purpose to remove
                        irritants and obstacles to the development of friendly relations. I believe
                        this is an objective to which your own Administration <pb facs="1037"
                            n="999" xml:id="pg_999"/> is dedicated and I recall with satisfaction
                        the many significant steps which you have taken for achieving détente and a
                        lessening of tension around the world. The Peshawar facility negates the
                        attainment of this objective. It would have been logical in the light of
                        circumstances to which I have referred above for Pakistan to request that it
                        be given up a long time ago. But on the contrary we decided to carry out our
                        commitments under the agreement fully in an honourable manner even though
                        thereby we have run the risk of damage to our political interests and
                        national security.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>You, Mr. President, have referred to the aid which your country has been
                        generous enough to give to Pakistan over the years. We have always
                        gratefully acknowledged the valuable role which this assistance has played
                        on our economic development. Pakistan-United States amity and co-operation
                        has in no small measure contributed to the maintenance of stability in this
                        important region of Asia and there is no doubt in my mind that the removal
                        of the Badaber facility will not come in the way of our close co-operation
                        in the field. It is, therefore, with faith in your statesmanship and
                        far-reaching vision that I ask you to appreciate the problems of a small
                        country which is hemmed in by powerful neighbours.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>I have directed my officers to start immediate discussions with your
                        representatives on the mechanics of dismantling the Peshawar facility so
                        that the operation may be carried out in a smooth and orderly manner.<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d505fn3">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1"
                                >Hilaly</persName> called on <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                                >Rusk</persName> on August 2 to follow up on the delivery of Ayub’s
                            letter. He said the decision not to renew the agreement concerning the
                            Peshawar facility had been a “heart-rending” one, and he attributed it
                            in part to Ayub’s need to protect his domestic political position.
                            (Telegram 214843 to Rawalpindi, August 3; National Archives and Records
                            Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                            1967–69, DEF 15 <gloss target="#t_Pak1">PAK</gloss>-US)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>With best regards and good wishes for your continued health,</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AKFMM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Mohammad Ayub Khan</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
