<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>540. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-03-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recfZWpZzigwQIfjx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002653"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airline</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-03-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="540"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                <head>540. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d540fn1"
                        >Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Afghanistan,
                        Vol. I, Memos and Miscellaneous, 12/63–4/68. Secret. Drafted by
                        Spain.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1967-03-29">March 29,
                            1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Afghan Prime Minister’s Comment on His Talk with the President</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_MMH1">Mohammad Hashim
                            Maiwandwal</persName>, Prime Minister of Afghanistan</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJW1">James W. Spain</persName>, Country
                        Director, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_PAF1"
                            >PAF</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Before Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MMH1">Maiwandwal</persName>’s
                    departure from <persName>Blair</persName> House today for his luncheon with the
                    Secretary of State, I had the opportunity to ask him for his understanding of
                    his discussion with the President yesterday.<note n="2" xml:id="d540fn2">See
                            <ref target="#d539">Document 539</ref>.</note> My query was prompted by
                    some remarks the Prime Minister <pb facs="1111" n="1073" xml:id="pg_1073"/> made
                    to me last evening which I thought suggested a possible misunderstanding. This
                    turned out not to be the case.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said that his discussion with the President had been
                    thoroughly enjoyable and constructive. He felt that he and the President had
                    come to grips with some major problems and understood each other very well
                    indeed. He said that the point he had been trying to make in response to the
                    President on Vietnam was that a number of other countries in the world,
                    specifically including Afghanistan, did not see the Vietnam situation in exactly
                    the same way we did. He said that he had tried to point out to the President
                    that the United States had a tendency to be unduly concerned at different times
                    with different problems; some years ago it had been organizing the northern tier
                    into <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss> to defeat Communist aggression;
                    earlier it had been the Marshall Plan and the Korean war; now it was Vietnam.
                    The interests of Afghanistan and of other non-aligned Asian countries did not
                    change as did those of the United States. This was the reason why they were not
                    able to come as far as we would like them to at any given time on Vietnam,
                        <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss>, the Korean war, etc.</p>
                <p>On more specific subjects, the Prime Minister indicated that he had discussed the
                    Ariana Airline request for a loan from the Export Import Bank and understood the
                    situation as it had been explained to him by Ambassador Neumann in New York and
                    by the President. He was content and he would wait.</p>
                <p>On Afghanistan’s present food needs, he said that the President had told him that
                    the U.S. would do what it could to help on as generous terms as possible,
                    specifically that cost would be repayable in 40 years.</p>
                <p>On the Kajakai project, he said that the President was sympathetic and had said
                    that the papers were being prepared. He understood that the President had not
                    made a commitment and that the President expected that he (<persName
                        corresp="#p_MMH1">Maiwandwal</persName>) would not discuss the matter
                    publicly at this time.</p>
                <p>He said that the President had also mentioned the upcoming loan for land
                    improvement equipment in the Helmand Valley and that they both understood that
                    action on this was virtually completed.</p>
                <p>I asked the Prime Minister for his views as to timing of any future steps on the
                    Kajakai project. He said that he would very much like to be able to announce it
                    together with the next food agreement shortly after his return to Kabul, April
                    15. He said that if the food agreement were to be ready sooner, he would like to
                    withhold announcement until after his return. He added that the Kajakai loan was
                    particularly important to him personally and that he deduced from his
                    conversation with the President that an announcement shortly after his return
                    home would probably be possible.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
