<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="88" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                        <head>88. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d88fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1964–66, DEF 12–1 INDIA. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SDT1">Schneider</persName> on February 25 and
                                approved in U on March 8.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-02-22">February
                                    22, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Indian Nuclear Energy Program</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0226" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_NBKBK1">B. K.
                                    Nehru</persName>, Ambassador of India</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Homi Bhabha</persName>, Secretary
                                of the Department of Atomic Energy, Government of India</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, Under Secretary
                                of State</item>
                            <item>Robert Anderson, U</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SDT1">David T. Schneider</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NEASOA1">NEA/SOA</gloss>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Calling at his own request, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> opened the conversation with a description of
                            India’s nuclear power reactor program. Analyzing the economics of
                            nuclear power plants he concluded that although capital costs were
                            somewhat high, in areas where hydroelectric power potential was fully
                            exploited or did not exist and where the sources of coal were remote,
                            nuclear power was very much less expensive in India than coal power.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> then directed the
                            conversation to what he called the dilemma India faced regarding what to
                            do to counteract the “noise” of Communist China’s nuclear explosion. He
                            explained that India needed to make some dramatic “peaceful” achievement
                            to offset the prestige gained by Communist China among Africans and
                                Asians.<note n="2" xml:id="d88fn2">On November 23, 1964, <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> Commissioner John G. Palfrey wrote
                                to <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Llewellyn E. Thompson</persName>
                                suggesting discussing with <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> during his February visit U.S.-Indian
                                cooperation in the peaceful uses of atomic energy. Palfrey attached
                                to his letter a “Discussion Paper on Prospects for Intensifying
                                Peaceful Atomic Cooperation With India.” (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> Files: Lot 67 D 2; also
                                available on the Internet, National Security Archive
                                (www.gwu.edu/nsarchiv), Electronic Briefing Book No. 6, “India and
                                Pakistan—On the Nuclear Threshold,” <ref target="#d3">Document
                                    3</ref>)</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                            noted however that African opinion on the Communist Chinese detonation
                            was divided. The Africans had been impressed but they were also
                            disturbed regarding the possible effects of fallout. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> granted that this may be so but
                            said very few Africans had been willing to join in criticism of
                            Communist China. He believed that if any of these countries could secure
                            nuclear weapons they would. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> replied that the problem was to get the major
                            non-nuclear countries to agree to forego nuclear weapons; then the way
                            would be clear for other nations to follow. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> said that in order to do this a
                            way must be found so that a nation will gain as much by not going for
                            nuclear weapons as it might by developing them. It was not helpful to
                            differentiate between members of the “nuclear club” and non-nuclear
                            nations. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> agreed and said
                            that we want to prevent countries from gaining status by developing
                            nuclear weapons.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> then examined India’s
                            accomplishments in the area of nuclear energy and contrasted them with
                            those of China. He noted there were really only two nuclear powers in
                            the world, the United States and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Britain and France were on quite a different level;
                                <pb facs="0227" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> still at a much lower
                            level was Communist China. India could quite easily have achieved
                            China’s capability.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> explained that the
                            Chinese were greatly indebted to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> for helping them on their weapons program. At the end
                            of the five-year period of Soviet assistance (about 1959 or 1960) the
                            Soviets had been putting up a diffusion plant, which was not completed,
                            however. The Chinese had asked for a model nuclear bomb but the Soviets
                            had refused; the Chinese had then alleged that the Soviets were backing
                            out of an agreement with them. The Soviet Union must nevertheless have
                            left the blueprints for a nuclear device with Communist China.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> explained that if
                            India went all out, it could produce a device in 18 months; with a U.S.
                            blueprint it could do the job in six months. It was clear from this
                            analysis how the Chinese gained time because of the Soviet help. In fact
                            the Chinese in 1958 had admitted to the Indians that their first nuclear
                            reactor was Soviet-built and that only the Soviets were fully acquainted
                            with its operation. When Chou En-lai had visited the Indian Atomic
                            Energy establishment at Trombay some years ago, he had said it would
                            take China 15 years to accomplish what India had. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> noted that even if this was
                            exaggerated, China at that time was at least three years behind
                            India.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> noted that even today
                            we do not know if all of the U–235 used in the Chinese device was
                            produced in China. He said that an Indonesian representative at the
                            recent inauguration of the Indian plutonium separation plant at Bombay
                            had said she had learned in Peiping recently that the Chinese reactor
                            there was operated only when VIP’s visited it. “What other reason except
                            shortage of fuel could there be for this?” asked Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> explained that if
                            India is to maintain its prestige relative to the Chinese in the fields
                            of science and technology two things should be done: (1) ways must be
                            found for it to demonstrate to other Asian and African countries India’s
                            scientific achievements, (2) a greater awareness of Chinese indebtedness
                            to the Soviet Union for its nuclear achievements must be created. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> responded that the
                            Department should look into what could be done about it.</p>
                        <p>Concluding his presentation, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> said that during the next four or five years
                            there were very few countries which had the capability of developing a
                            nuclear device. Even Japan and Germany had no plutonium separation
                            plants and so were some four years away from being able to produce a
                            device. In fact India was much the closest. India’s plutonium separation
                            plant is quite large, large enough to process all of the plutonium from
                            the reactors India is now building. In five years India could produce
                            100 nuclear bombs per year.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BDHJ1">Bhabha</persName> stated that it was the
                            policy of his government, with which he agreed, not to seek nuclear
                            weapons. If his government is to <pb facs="0228" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> justify this policy, however, ways must be found by which his country
                            can gain at least as much by sticking to peaceful uses as it could by
                            embarking on a weapons program.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>