<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Great Britain ( (Wright))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d822</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">822</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-08-21T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-08-21T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-08-21T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-08-21T16:00:00-05:00" n="822"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d822">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">361.11/3474: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wright</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-08-21T17:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 21, 1920—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>894. Your 1134, July 28, 4 p.m.<note n="72" xml:id="d822fn72">Not printed.</note>
                    1201, August 10, 3 p.m. and 1210, August 11, 7 p.m.</p>
                <p>Nansen is head of International Red Cross as well as representative of League of
                    Nations. The Department is dealing with him in his Red Cross capacity. You may
                    communicate to him as an agent of the International Red Cross the substance of
                    the following message.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The Department of State highly appreciates your endeavors on behalf of the
                        American citizens detained in Russia and has given careful attention to the
                        communication from Moscow addressed to you, which was forwarded by the
                        Embassy August 10, 3 p.m. and your message to the Department, transmitted
                        August 11, 7 p.m.</p>
                    <p>In reply the Department informs you that Mr. Tchicherin is sadly misinformed
                        about conditions in America. In order to avoid the question of the
                        jurisdiction of the Russian Consulates over citizens of Russia, who refuse
                        to recognize them, a special order has been issued arranging that permits
                        for departure shall be issued by American officials on affidavits of birth
                        and nationality without reference to the Russian Consuls or Embassy. In
                        fact, 600 such permits have been issued Russians between April 17th and
                        August 12th. The Department has no information as to the numbers who have
                        actually left.</p>
                    <p>Undoubtedly there are serious difficulties in travel, which cannot be wholly
                        overcome until shipping returns to normal. In regard to the alleged
                        difficulties, which bearers of such permits have had with Consuls of other
                        countries, the Department has no information, no jurisdiction, and can
                        assume no responsibility.</p>
                    <p>There would appear to be no legal reason preventing you from chartering a
                        ship under a recognized flag and taking on any passengers who had secured
                        passports or permits of departure.</p>
                    <p>In the absence of regular diplomatic and commercial relations, the appearance
                        of a ship in our ports, under an unknown flag and purporting to be under the
                        registry of the Soviets, might well cause complications this Government is
                        not inclined to risk. However the problem of the transportation of
                        passengers of Russian origin, wishing to return home, could be easily solved
                        by a chartered ship under a recognized flag.</p>
                    <pb facs="0782" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/>
                    <p>This Department is persuaded that no good will be accomplished by entering
                        into controversy over the other inaccuracies in Mr. Tchicherin’s message to
                        you. But for your information it is pointed out that no ‘masses’ of Russians
                        have been arrested on any charge; that no individuals have been arrested for
                        loyalty to the Russian Soviets. Such Russians as have been accused of
                        violation of American law, have been tried without any discrimination on
                        account of nationality.</p>
                    <p>The Department will shortly send you a detailed statement in regard to
                            Kalamatiano,<note n="74" xml:id="d822fn74">Not printed.</note> but
                        wishes at this moment to emphasize that in so far as private citizens, not
                        accused of crime, are concerned, this Government has done all in its power
                        to facilitate their departure, in sharp distinction to the policy at present
                        in force in Moscow.”</p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Colby</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
