<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The High Commissioner at Constantinople ( (Bristol) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">917</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="917"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d917">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867.0031/orig.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner at Constantinople</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bristol</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-01-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">19 January, 1920</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received February 24.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The resumption of trade with Turkey was
                    accomplished by notice published in the papers in Constantinople on the 26th of
                    February, 1919, stating that the blockade had been removed beginning with
                    February 21, 1919. This notice was published by the French Vice-Admiral,
                    Commander of the Allied Squadron of the Mediterranean. The French Vice-Admiral
                    at that time was the French High Commissioner. This notice did not state that
                    the resumption of trade had been directed by the Supreme War Council at Paris.
                    Further, I have ascertained that the Ottoman Government was given no further
                    information regarding the resumption of trade than the above notice. The Ottoman
                    Government was, therefore, under the impression that this was an act of the
                    Allied Powers.</p>
                <p>As soon as the blockade was raised I took up the question with the Allied High
                    Commissioners by conversations, desiring to establish the fact that the United
                    States was, by the provisions of the Supreme War Council, directly interested in
                    the regulations affecting trade with Turkey, Bulgaria, Asia Minor and the ports
                    of the Black Sea. At first there was no United States trade that was affected.
                    In some individual cases where American interests were affected, I took them up
                    immediately and had them satisfactorily adjusted. However, in order to establish
                    the principle, I began direct negotiations with the Allied High Commissioners on
                    29 April, 1919, to the end that the United States should be properly represented
                    in respect to the regulations of trade with Turkey, Bulgaria, Asia Minor and
                    Black Sea ports. Finally, as set forth in enclosure (<hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi>),<note n="3" xml:id="d917fn3">Not printed.</note>1 made a direct
                    appeal for a proper recognition of United States rights on the ground that
                    American interests were not being properly safeguarded under the arrangements
                    then in force regulating trade with Turkey, Bulgaria and the Black Sea ports of
                    Roumania and Russia. I followed this up by having personal conferences with the
                    Allied High Commissioners, setting forth more in detail the matters that were
                    interfering with trade, not only to the prejudice of the United States but of
                    other countries.</p>
                <p>On December 17, 1919, the Allied High Commissioners replied to my letter agreeing
                    to the appointment of a Committee to be made <pb facs="0858" n="758"
                        xml:id="pg_758"/> up of a representative of Great Britain, France, Italy and
                    the United States. In reply to this letter I appointed a member of my Staff to
                    represent the United States on this Committee. The first meeting of this
                    Committee was held on 20 December, 1919. The Committee was organized and it was
                    decided to designate this committee as the “Advisory Trade Committee of the
                    Associated Governments.” It was arranged to have a revolving chairmanship. The
                    United States representative on the Committee was able to have Mr. George
                    Wadsworth, Vice Consul, designated as permanent Secretary of the Committee. I
                    was very much gratified at this as the secretary is an important factor in the
                    work of such a committee and by this arrangement United States interests should
                    be properly looked out for.</p>
                <p>The first thing taken up by the Committee was the question of the import taxes
                    being collected by the Ottoman Government [not] in accordance with the
                    Capitulations. The Capitulations had not been carried out in this respect and I
                    had taken this matter up several times previously. The Allied High Commissioners
                    had informed me that they were closing their eyes to this fact on account of the
                    precarious condition of the Ottoman finances. I did not admit this as a proper
                    reason and had so informed the Allied High Commissioners previously. About this
                    time the Ottoman Government addressed a note to the Allied High Commissioners
                    and to the United States High Commissioner suggesting the resumption of import
                    taxes according to the Capitulations. However, the Ottoman Government desired to
                    modify the method of levying the <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> duties in
                    carrying out the provisions of the Capitulations. As a result of this request
                    from the Ottoman Government a meeting was held by the High Commissioners of the
                    Associated Governments. The result of this meeting was a joint note, see
                    enclosure (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>),<note n="4" xml:id="d917fn4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                    </note> addressed to the Sublime Porte. No reply has been received from this
                    note up to the present time.</p>
                <p>In connection with the taxes by the Ottoman Government, which were specific taxes
                    and not in accord with the Capitulations, I beg to state that United States
                    interests were not injured by these specific taxes; therefore, the principle of
                    the Capitulations was always maintained and the change to an <hi rend="italic"
                        >ad valorem</hi> tax in accordance with the Capitulations has been claimed
                    simply upon principle, and to provide for a change of conditions which would
                    materially affect adversely American commerce. At the aforesaid conference the
                    Allied High Commissioners pointed out that they did not consider they were in a
                    position to demand of the Turkish Government an <pb facs="0859" n="759"
                        xml:id="pg_759"/> enforcement of the Capitulations. This position assumed by
                    them is very interesting. Of course the United States, at the present time, can
                    make no demands that are not supported by the Allied High Commissioners. I have
                    taken the ground, however, that whereas I have joined with the Allied High
                    Commissioners in urging the Ottoman Government to resume taxation on imports in
                    accordance with the Treaty, I will likewise take such independent steps along
                    this line in urging the Ottoman Government to collect only such taxes as are
                    legal. It is my opinion that the only legal taxes are those that were prescribed
                    and in force before the war.</p>
                <p>The real motive of the Turkish Government in not charging import taxes in
                    accordance with the Capitulations is that they are standing out for the
                    abrogation of the Capitulations. With their usual short-sighted policy they do
                    not realize that they are prejudicing their cause by this attitude. They would
                    improve their cause if they would return to the Capitulations, doing so under
                    protest. Also, as the taxes now being paid are paid under protest, the Turkish
                    Government will some day have to settle the bill. Likewise, they do not realize
                    that the final revenue collected would be greater under the Capitulations than
                    under the present method of specific taxes. I will continue to maintain the
                    position towards the Ottoman Government that the United States expects the
                    Capitulations to be carried out in respect to the import taxes, as well as all
                    other matters. These questions have been taken up many times directly with the
                    Ottoman Government in an informal manner as required in view of diplomatic
                    relations being severed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mark L. Bristol</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="5" xml:id="d917fn5"
                                >File translation revised.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American, British, French, and
                                Italian High Commissioners</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Turkish
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-01-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">2 January, 1920</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">Con 124–20</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In reply to various proposals made to them with a view to substituting an <hi
                            rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> tariff for the specific tariff applied at
                        present, the High Commissioners of France, Great Britain and Italy, with
                        whom the High Commissioner of the United States of America has associated
                        himself on this occasion, have the honor to bring the following to the
                        knowledge of the Sublime Porte.</p>
                    <pb facs="0860" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/>
                    <p>The specific tariff which was applied during the period of hostilities has
                        never been recognized or admitted by the Allied and Associated
                        Governments.</p>
                    <p>Consequently the Allied High Commissioners, who, after the conclusion of the
                        Armistice, had demanded the reapplication of the <hi rend="italic">ad
                            valorem</hi> tariff and who had only tolerated the application of a
                        specific-tariff at the request of the Ottoman Government and as an exception
                        and temporary measure, are disposed to receive a fresh demand from the
                        Ottoman Government relative to the reapplication of the <hi rend="italic">zd
                            valorem</hi> tariff.</p>
                    <p>But the Ottoman Government today proposes that the import duties be fixed not
                        as formerly after valuation at the customs house of the value of the goods
                        imported and according to the price of their invoices, but according to the
                        list of values of those goods established, in categories to be fixed in
                        advance and to be revised monthly or quarterly.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned High Commissioners declare that they have not the power to
                        accept the proposed modification in the manner of establishing the value of
                        merchandise. The new system suggested would, in effect, amount to a radical
                        change in the methods formerly applied with the consent of the Powers and
                        would consequently involve serious consequences for the foreign commerce. It
                        would therefore not only be necessary that the principle of the system
                        before it is put into effect be submitted to the approval of the Powers but
                        even the list of prices of the merchandise according to which the customs
                        duties would be fixed, would have to be examined, considered and approved by
                        the interested governments, which would necessarily involve long delays.</p>
                    <p>After having examined this important question the undersigned High
                        Commissioners have decided not only to give their consent to the
                        reapplication of the <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> tariff but to insist
                        that this tariff be reestablished at the expiration of a period of ten days
                        from the date of publication of the law or decree to be promulgated to that
                        effect, and that it be applied under the same conditions as before the
                        opening of hostilities.</p>
                    <p>They are, moreover, ready to submit for the examination and study of their
                        respective Governments the proposed scheme for the establishment, by means
                        of a list drawn up in advance, of the value of imported merchandise as well
                        as the list itself of these values which was communicated to them.</p>
                    <closer>[No signatures indicated]</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
