<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the American Relief Administration ( (Hoover) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="943"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d943">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">123 H 271/4</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Relief Administration</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hoover</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-07-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 26, 1920</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: On July 5th, 1919, in order to
                    meet the desperate need of the Armenian population in Transcaucasia and the
                    Armenian Republic, at my suggestion and in accordance with the wishes of the
                    President, Colonel William N. Haskell was appointed High Commissioner to
                    Armenia, representing the United States, Great Britain, France and Italy. His
                    commission was signed by M. Clemenceau as President of the Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>The authority centered in the High Commissioner as Joint Representative of the
                    several Allied Powers gave him the powerful support which he required to
                    overcome those racial and political antagonisms, the natural outgrowth of the
                    birth of new States, which were threatening the total annihilation of the
                    Armenian people. The work of this Mission was also to ascertain and provide
                    requirements up to the point when the succeeding crops would render general
                    contributions of food stuffs from overseas unnecessary; to take over and extend
                    the charitable work of the Near East Relief in caring for refugees, orphans and
                    destitutes; to represent the American Relief Administration; to administer the
                    charitable relief from all other countries; to assist in re-establishing stable
                    conditions in the Republic of Armenia.</p>
                <p>Colonel Haskell, supported by an efficient and devoted staff, has carried out his
                    difficult duties in an admirable manner. Flour was the most urgent food
                    requirement of this region. The 41,000 tons contributed through the United
                    States Grain Corporation and the <pb facs="0886" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/>
                    51,000 tons of the American Relief Administration have been delivered. The
                    amount is sufficient to supply essential needs until the next harvest, which it
                    is estimated will then carry the country for six to eight months. Refugees have
                    been fed and clothed and to a considerable extent restored to useful
                    occupations. Agriculture has been re-established. Forty hospitals and seventeen
                    orphanages have been opened or put in order and provisioned for one year ahead.
                    Over fifty thousand children have been fed daily.</p>
                <p>Under the direction of the American Relief Administration and including the
                    period of the administration of the Allied High Commissioner, there was
                    contributed from all sources for the aid of the Armenian people in this region
                    one hundred and eight thousand tons of food and supplies. This was in the form
                    of Governmental credits or private donations the approximate values of which
                    were as follows: <table cols="5" rows="10">
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="5">
                                <hi rend="italic">From Great Britain</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3">Besides a small amount of private charity of which we
                                have no record, there was furnished on the part of the British
                                Government in the form of freight credits a total of</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">$560,000.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="5">
                                <hi rend="italic">From the United States</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>1.</cell>
                            <cell>American Relief Administration covering allocation from the
                                $100,000,000 relief appropriation, March 1919, to date,
                                credits</cell>
                            <cell role="num">$8,075,000.</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>2.</cell>
                            <cell>Grain Corporation Credits</cell>
                            <cell role="num">4,725,000.</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>3.</cell>
                            <cell>American Red Cross donations</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2,100,000.</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>4.</cell>
                            <cell>Commonwealth Fund donations</cell>
                            <cell role="num">750,000.</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>5.</cell>
                            <cell>Near East Relief donations</cell>
                            <cell role="num">4,802,000.</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell cols="2">Total from the United States</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">20,452,000.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell cols="2">Grand total</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">$21,012,000.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>Aside from the great work of reconstruction, the repatriation of the many
                    thousands of refugees, and the benevolent activities which must for years be
                    carried on by the Armenian Government, for the present the most appealing work
                    for any outside relief organization must be the care of hospitals, orphanages,
                    schools and a certain number of destitute.</p>
                <p>Colonel Haskell has successfully performed the task for which he was appointed.
                    The orphanages, hospitals and other charities in the Armenian Republic and
                    Transcaucasia have been turned over to the management of the Near East Relief.
                    All the American Military Staff are to be withdrawn at once. He proposes, as of
                    August first when the few remaining relief measures of the Government <pb
                        facs="0887" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/> program are completed, to present his
                    resignation to the Council of Ambassadors in Paris.</p>
                <p>With Colonel Haskell’s resignation my intervention in the management of this
                    branch of European Relief will also come to an end.</p>
                <p>I respectfully suggest, Mr. Secretary, that the State Department notify the
                    Council of Ambassadors in Paris of the resignation of Colonel Haskell to be
                    handed to them August 1st, 1920.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Herbert Hoover</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
