<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-14T06:25:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-14T06:25:00-05:00" n="1" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                        <head>1. Telegram From the Embassy in Japan to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d1fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                Box 533, Country Files, Far East, Japan, Vol. I. Confidential;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Tokyo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-01-14T11:25:00+00:00">January 14, 1969,
                                1125Z</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>267. 1. I had hour and one-half talk with Prime Minister yesterday on my
                            farewell call.<note n="2" xml:id="d1fn2"><persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">U.
                                    Alexis Johnson</persName> ended his mission as Ambassador to
                                Japan on January 15, 1969.</note> He went into considerable length
                            explaining difficulties with agriculture and his consequent regret that
                            they were not able to do more on agricultural offers during trade talks,
                            but with some time to work out their agricultural problems they will be
                            able to be much more forthcoming.</p>
                        <p>2. On Okinawa he again emphasized importance he attached to obtaining
                            some agreement this year. He said that he recognized pressure on new
                            administration of other problems and that it would probably take some
                            time before administration would be able to come to grips with Okinawa
                            problem. (He knew statements on Okinawa being made by “doves like
                            Reischauer and <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fulbright</persName>” and
                            from which Japanese press and public were deriving much comfort did not
                            necessarily represent majority opinion in U.S.) He still hoped to make
                            visit to Washington “not earlier than November” and, if necessary,
                            perhaps it could be a little later. He very much hoped that
                            cabinet-level committee could be held in Japan during summer and that
                            this would give him opportunity to talk to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>. Either before or after
                            cabinet-level meeting he hoped that <gloss target="#t_FonMin_1">FonMin</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AK_1">Aichi</persName> could visit Washington to
                            meet with <gloss target="#t_Secy_1">Secy</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>. He did not mention visit
                            by <persName corresp="#p_KN_1">Kishi</persName>. (Previously Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_ST_1">Shimoda</persName> had told me that he
                            had discouraged visit by <persName corresp="#p_KN_1">Kishi</persName> at
                            this time, as he did not feel <gloss target="#t_GOJ_1">GOJ</gloss>
                            position sufficiently developed to make visit productive.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0033" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/>
                        <p>3. With respect to timing of his visit he said that while he was trying
                            to lead public opinion in Japan on Okinawa, he feared what effects might
                            be on public opinion here of incidents during general strike on Okinawa
                            and adverse reactions to new labor ordinance.<note n="3" xml:id="d1fn3">On November 19, 1968, an American B–52 bomber crashed on Okinawa,
                                creating a rallying point for opposition to the stationing of B–52s
                                on the island. In early January 1969, the Joint Struggle Council of
                                the Council to Protect the Lives of Okinawans announced plans for
                                demonstrations and sit-down strikes to begin on February 4
                                throughout Okinawa that would interdict movement into and out of the
                                U.S. Air Force Base at Kadena, as well as block traffic on the major
                                Okinawan highways. The Military Workers Union (Zengunro) and the
                                Okinawa Teachers Association decided to participate in the strike
                                after a new Comprehensive Labor Ordinance (CLO) was issued on
                                January 11, which restricted union picketing, union political
                                activities, and, some felt, the activities of ordinary Okinawan
                                citizens. Although the CLO was to take effect on January 25, the
                                Civil Administration of Okinawa responded to widespread criticism by
                                postponing the effective date of the ordinance and consulating with
                                interested parties. The February 4 strike was called off, although
                                some demonstrations occurred. Director of the Bureau of Intelligence
                                and Research <persName corresp="#p_HTL_1">Thomas Hughes</persName>
                                sent an intelligence note discussing these events to Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> on February 3.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Files 1967–69, DEF 15 RYU IS–US) Additional information is ibid.,
                                POL 19 RYU IS.</note> There could also be other developments in
                            Okinawa during course of year that “could lead public opinion in
                            unforeseen directions” that could make his visit inappropriate in
                            November, thus for time being he wanted to remain flexible on a possible
                            date.</p>
                        <p>4. Taking advantage of his mention of “gap” between Japan’s and U.S.
                            public opinion, I said I entirely agreed and was very concerned over
                            what I felt were the growing adverse trends in U.S. opinions towards
                            Japan. I said that in part, because of sensationalized news and TV
                            coverage of small minority group demonstrations in Japan against our
                            bases, etc., there was growing feeling that Japan was economically “fat
                            and happy,” financially profiting from our sacrifices in Vietnam, while
                            seeking to expel us from our bases in both Japan and Okinawa. I said
                            that growing reaction to this among many Americans was, if Japan wants
                            us to get out why don’t we. I knew that this did not represent majority
                            or government opinion in Japan, but this was not getting across to
                            American people. Under these circumstances, I was sure that there would
                            be very adverse reaction in U.S. simply “to giving back Okinawa to
                            Japan.” Thus I thought it important that <gloss target="#t_GOJ_1">GOJ</gloss> find better context in which to present problem to us
                            and suggested that one possible means was to present question in terms
                            of <gloss target="#t_GOJ_1">GOJ</gloss>’s willingness to undertake
                            increased defense responsibilities, by accepting same kind of immediate
                            defense mission in the Ryukyus after reversion, as it now accepted in
                            Japan proper. This was apart from conditions with respect to our bases
                            in Okinawa, which involved whether our bases there were to be
                            “effective.” In this connection I, of course, discussed the whole
                            question of graduated deterrence and the necessity of paying attention
                                <pb facs="0034" n="3" xml:id="pg_3"/> to how Pyongyang and Peking
                            might interpret whatever we did. I also discussed necessity of getting
                            away from present context in which Japan thought it was doing us a favor
                            by permitting us to be here, and instead putting across to <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and American people sense that Japan
                            valued and wanted our presence.</p>
                        <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Sato</persName> received all this in good
                            spirit and said that even <gloss target="#t_JDA_1">JDA</gloss> and “his
                            own officer” lacked sophistication in military matters. To astonishment
                            of Hori (Chief Cabinet Secretary) and Togo, who were also present, he
                            said that <gloss target="#t_GOJ_1">GOJ</gloss>’s “three nuclear
                            principles” (non-possession, non-production and non-introduction) were
                            “nonsense.” However, this should not be interpreted to mean Japan wants
                            to have nuclear weapons.</p>
                        <p>6. In response to probing me whether there was a split between military
                            and civilian elements in <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> concerning
                            Okinawa, I said that this was not case. As far as I was personally
                            concerned I fully supported importance of maintaining strong deterrent
                            in Okinawa, not with purpose of using it in war but in preventing war,
                            which is a political matter.</p>
                        <p>7. I also spoke to him about our lack of progress in our space
                            cooperation discussions, pointing out that <gloss target="#t_MITI_1">MITI</gloss>’s apparent unwillingness to bring space hardware under
                            its export-control regulations was preventing <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Sato</persName> from getting us anything in way of
                            a meaningful package. He said he would look into it right away.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_JUA_1"><persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>