<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="106" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                        <head>106. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HR_1">Robert
                                Hormats</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d106fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 537,
                                Country Files, Far East, Japan, Vol. VI, October–31 December 1971.
                                Confidential. Sent for information. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> initialed the memorandum, indicating that
                                he saw it.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-11-16">November 16, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Pete Peterson</persName>’s Meeting
                                with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>,
                                Japan</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Pete Peterson</persName>’s memorandum (Tab
                                A)<note n="2" xml:id="d106fn2">Attached but not printed.</note>
                            reports on his meeting of November 1 with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>. The major points are:</p>
                        <p>—<persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> asserted that we needed
                            reform in the monetary system and that we had no interest in going back
                            to the pre-August 15 situation. He added that there had to be a better
                            mechanism for changing exchange rates when that became necessary.</p>
                        <p>—<persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> indicated that Japan was
                            clearly opposed to floating rates but would consider revaluation.
                                <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> stated that it
                            would be helpful if Japan were to lift restrictions on the import of
                            agricultural items, computers, integrated circuits, and aircraft.
                            Japan’s reported intention to double its defense procurement in the U.S.
                            over the next five years was also helpful.</p>
                        <p>—<persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> said it would take time to
                            achieve the sought after turnabout in the U.S. balance of payments, and
                            asked what was needed immediately in the trade field in order for the
                            surcharge to be removed. <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> indicated that, in addition to the above items,
                            a reduction of taxes on automobiles and the easing of various
                            administrative procedures on imports would be useful.</p>
                        <p>—The Ambassador’s priorities for action by the U.S. were a ratification
                            of the Okinawa treaty, removal of the surcharge, and an end to the
                            discriminatory “buy American” provisions of the investment tax
                            incentive.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>