<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>90. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v19p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-08-21T12:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-08-21T13:35:00-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council" subject="nsc">NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recoikCosN7CYywin" type="compound-subject" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="east-asian-relations" subject="u-s-japan-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">U.S.-Japan relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="textiles" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033350" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Textiles</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="devaluation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333" lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="bilateral-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="invasion" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations" subject="u-s-soviet-union-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144" lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="radio" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385" lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="summit-meeting" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171" lcsh-match="good_close">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359" lcsh-match="exact">Airport</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-21T13:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-21T12:35:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                <head>90. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d90fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 536, Country Files, Far East,
                        Japan, Vol. V, 1 Jul–Sep 71. Secret; Sensitive. The meeting took place in
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s San Clemente office.
                            <persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Lord</persName> transmitted the memorandum
                        to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> on September 8, under a
                        memorandum indicating that another <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>
                        meeting would take place that day and noting: “I have given a sanitized
                        account of this meeting to <persName corresp="#p_HJH_1">Holdridge</persName>’s shop to help them prepare your basic talking paper.”
                        (The sanitized version is ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s talking points for the August 21 meeting with
                            <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> were contained in an
                        August 19 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HJH_1">Holdridge</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_HR_1">Hormats</persName> in which they noted,
                        “Your conversation with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> on July 23 was extremely valuable, I am told, in
                        dampening down elements within the Japanese leadership who, as a result of
                        the President’s China initiative, argued for a more independent Japanese
                        foreign policy. However, there are now new complications in US-Japanese
                        relations resulting from the President’s recently-announced economic
                        measures.” For a memorandum of conversation of the July 23 meeting, see <ref target="#d83">Document 83</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>San Clemente, California</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1971-08-21T10:35:00-07:00" to="1971-08-21T11:35:00-07:00">August
                            21, 1971, 10:35–11:35 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Nobuhiko Ushiba</persName>,
                        Japanese Ambassador to the United States</item>
                    <item>Mr. Yutaka Normura, Economic Counselor of the Japanese Embassy</item>
                    <item>Mr. Takasugi, Japanese Consul General in Los Angeles</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Assistant
                        to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Winston Lord</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                </list>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It is nice to see you.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It is nice of you to
                    give me this time. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Sato</persName>
                    sent me a cable concerning my seeing you. Is there any message from you or the
                    President that you would like me to convey?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We had a surprise
                    announcement for you on July 15 and another surprise announcement on August 15.
                    I promise you there will not be another one on September 15.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The last one was on a
                    Monday morning with the market already open and there was confusion. I recognize
                    Sunday evening was good for you and Europe, but for us it was a delicate
                    time.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: You are keeping your
                    nerve. You are buying so many dollars. I am not an economist.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We are not entirely
                    unhappy. We are buying dollars.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I am told that you can
                    force us to devalue the dollar by dumping.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <rs corresp="recoikCosN7CYywin" type="compound-subject">U.S.-Japan
                        Relations</rs>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I talked to the President
                    yesterday. He knows you are here. We want to restore good relations. We consider
                    our friendship <pb facs="0304" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/> with Japan the keystone
                    of our Pacific policy. We have had some unfortunate misunderstandings and
                    difficulties. We must make sure that our basic traditions are not affected. One
                    reads reports about our replacing Japan with China—this is an absurd
                    proposition. The Chinese are opponents, though maybe with our policy we can make
                    them a little less aggressive. But you are our friends. We will not trade our
                    friends for opponents. Therefore as regards the basic direction of our policy,
                    nothing has changed. I explained our China moves to you.</p>
                <p>I assume that what I say is not reported by your press officer.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I will send it
                    immediately to the Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: There is one thing I find
                    that is not working too well in our relations. On <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs>, for example, there
                    was a price paid out of proportion to the intrinsic value. I was partly to
                    blame. I did not take this issue seriously when I first came into office and
                    hoped it would go away.</p>
                <p>We have had discussions on such matters as <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs> and yen <rs corresp="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic">devaluation</rs>. But we don’t really have fundamental
                    discussions on where we both want to go. Who should we talk to if the President
                    wants to talk, knowing that the conversations with the Prime Minister will be
                    kept in that channel. For example, if there were developments we could tell you
                    or some other designate about, something personal for the Prime Minister, and
                    you would not tell the bureaucracy and we would not tell the bureaucracy.<note n="2" xml:id="d90fn2">This paragraph and the subsequent exchanges on this
                        topic (concerning a secret channel of communication between the United
                        States and Japan) were removed from the sanitized memorandum of conversation
                        sent to the Department of State. At this point, the sanitized version of
                        this document continues with the discussion of the textile issue.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I understand.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We could feel freer to
                    discuss basic philosophy or approaches.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I am designated.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I am delighted. It is up
                    to the Prime Minister to designate. I believe we should have that exchange
                    because right now there is almost no such contact; everything is more
                    bureaucratic.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It is done in a more
                    normal way.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I am not being
                    critical.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I understand the
                    reasons for what you say. I will tell the Prime Minister that it is very
                    important to have a direct channel.</p>
                <pb facs="0305" n="274" xml:id="pg_274"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">Textiles</rs>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We are prepared to work
                    seriously to improve our relations. I don’t know where the textile negotiations
                    stand; they bore me. I have no specific proposals to make. Can we settle this in
                    the next two to three months?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I am in a similar
                    position. I have been given no information by the government on the Kennedy
                    negotiations with the Trade Minister and the Prime Minister. I gather Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_KDM_2">Kennedy</persName> still insisted on a
                    formulation along the lines that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FP_1">Flanigan</persName> proposed to me in December of last year. This makes
                    negotiations almost impossible.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: With election year coming
                    certainly the President will do something. Unfortunately the <rs corresp="rec87NM5izpPcVkSr" type="topic">textile industry</rs> only concerns
                    a few states. It would be better if it were spread over the country. I do not
                    want to get into this. With Japan we always talk <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs> instead of the direction of the next ten years. I
                    was very naive at the outset. In the first month of the Administration there was
                    a proposal that a mission go to Japan on <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs>. I said we could not open our relations with
                    Japan on an issue like <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs>. Now here we are. I leave it to people who understand
                    this.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The pattern of our
                    exports has changed radically. The bulk of our exports is in yarns, raw material
                    which the textile people buy. It is a mistake to treat Japan on the same level
                    as Korea, Hong Kong or Taiwan.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We are moving and your
                    side should recognize that the Japanese Government should show minimum progress.
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> will raise this with
                    your Foreign Minister on a private basis when he comes. There will be no experts
                    present.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Let us put this
                    aside.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We will try to be
                    constructive. You should try to be constructive. If I never hear about this
                    again I will be only too happy.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I hope you will be
                    interested in the final stage.<note n="3" xml:id="d90fn3">The sanitized version
                        did not contain this remark by <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>, or the subsequent exchange between <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>. It moved immediately into the discussion of
                        China.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If we get to the point
                    where there are only two issues left, I will be glad to go to the President if
                    you come to me. We are not there yet.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <pb facs="0306" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">China</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Let us forget <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs> and talk about the
                    next ten years. With dramatic events let us not forget the fact that
                    U.S./Japanese friendship is a key element in our <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">foreign policy</rs>. First, it is inevitable that as you grow
                    stronger you become the object of hostility. Secondly, our relationship must be
                    redefined. Many Americans remember you from right after the war, and they forget
                    you have your own views, that you have 2,000 years of <rs corresp="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic">history</rs>. It is a psychological
                    adjustment we must all make. In these conditions how do we harmonize our policy?
                    You are undoubtedly a great power which will pursue its own interests. We and
                    you have to raise our sights above the purely economic matters of the post-war
                    period.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I agree. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Sato</persName> is trying to raise sights.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We read accounts that the
                    Chinese are worried about you. Maybe this is so. In any event that is their
                    problem, not ours. We are prepared, we are eager to strengthen relations with
                    you. There is much the Chinese accuse you of which you don’t wish to do.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Our taking over Korea
                    or Formosa is nonsense.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I don’t have the
                    impression that you are preparing an expeditionary force.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Right.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: You are a major industrial
                    country and there is no avoiding that.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I can understand the
                    Chinese fear because of many generations of past policy. I don’t blame them. But
                    they should not look at the past but at the Japan of today and the future. Then
                    there will be solutions and grounds for mutual understanding. For that we must
                    try to have more contact with China.</p>
                <p>Did you see any strong views of the Chinese while you were in Peking?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: They said some of the
                    things which they said to Reston,<note n="4" xml:id="d90fn4">James Reston wrote
                        a series of articles for the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> during a
                        6-week visit to China during July and August. His articles of July 17 and
                        August 4, 6, and 13 discussed China’s fear of Japanese militarism.</note>
                    but in better balance. I didn’t give them as much encouragement as Reston.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Chou used the interview
                    skillfully with Reston to impress his opinions on the U.S. public.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If you took the names out
                    of the interview, you couldn’t tell who was speaking for which side.</p>
                <pb facs="0307" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Right. Most of the
                    statements that Chou made to Reston he has made now for several years, so we
                    Japanese know that way of thinking.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: He has said these things
                    to Japanese delegations.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Many times. This is the
                    first time in the American press. It must make a rather strong impression.<note n="5" xml:id="d90fn5">The sanitized version of this memorandum neither
                        contains this remark by <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> nor
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s response.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: The <hi rend="italic">New
                        York Times</hi> doesn’t know what to do. It is probably anti-Japanese as
                    well as anti-Administration. If we were anti-Chinese they would support China
                    but they haven’t made up their minds on what to do now. This affects only the
                    Eastern <rs corresp="recGBNKZ8zgNDCCVL" type="topic">intelligentsia</rs>.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I heard New York
                    business people with very strong views attacking Mr. Reston.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Against?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: His behavior was
                        outrageous.<note n="6" xml:id="d90fn6">The sanitized version neither
                        contains this remark by <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                        nor <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>’s response.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I agree.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: For example, his
                    acceptance of the Communist line on the Laos <rs corresp="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic">invasion</rs>; his suggestion that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> deceived Chou; his view that the
                    President was not being courageous.<note n="7" xml:id="d90fn7">In the sanitized
                        version, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> comments:
                        “Reston’s acceptance of the Communist line on the Laos <rs corresp="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic">invasion</rs> was curious; so
                        were his suggestion that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> deceived Chou and his view that the President was
                        not being courageous.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It was outrageous. I
                    have spoken with the Chinese; Japanese often do. They say that <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Sato</persName> is responsible for all the
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: The English never do
                    that.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: No they never do.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Humility is not the
                    outstanding trait of Mr. Reston. Will he visit Japan too? He is still in
                    China.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Maybe the Chinese asked
                    him not to visit Japan. They did so to some Germans.</p>
                <p>Do you have an idea when the President’s visit to China will take place?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have not set a date. We
                    want to let things cool off.<note n="8" xml:id="d90fn8">The sanitized version
                        does not contain the rest of this paragraph, or <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>’s response.</note> We will set a date by November. I
                    don’t think it will be this year. <pb facs="0308" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/> I
                    think it will be the first quarter of next year. As soon as we have a date set,
                    we will let you know. We would like to let you know through a private
                    channel.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We will try not to
                    surprise you.<note n="9" xml:id="d90fn9">In the sanitized version, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> says, “We will not surprise
                        you.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Please.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">The <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet
                        Union</rs>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The other day I had a
                    long talk with Ambassador Dobrynin. He is obviously very concerned about the
                    purpose of the President’s policy. He said that his point of view was that this
                    announcement would upset Japan and the Asian countries. He wonders what would
                    compensate for this disadvantage and achieve success. What is the purpose of the
                    President? He is obviously concerned with our country.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Dobrynin tells me that he
                    thinks you are planning to link up with China and divide up Siberia between the
                    Chinese and the Japanese. Is that true? (Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName> laughs.)</p>
                <p>Please give us advance warning.</p>
                <p>I don’t believe that anything we do in Peking will affect Japanese interests. You
                    know that American interests forced us to try to get maneuvering room. We will
                    not change the Taiwan policy in the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. We will
                    stick with it and fight for it. As for Japan we will not go along with the
                    proposition that you are the villain in Asia. We will see if we can get a
                    neutral posture from China for Southeast Asia during the period we want to wind
                    up the war.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: That is certainly very
                    important. You had a very successful policy containing the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs> and Europe. At
                    this end (Asia) the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet
                        Union</rs> is on your mind?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Not particularly. Only in
                    the sense that we won’t let Moscow speak for all communist countries. We can’t
                    give serious <rs corresp="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic">military
                        assistance</rs> to China. We don’t look at this as an anti-Soviet move.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I understand that your
                    talks on <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> and Berlin are going well.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: They are going quite
                    well.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The Russians have not
                    changed their attitude since the Chinese developments?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: No, if anything the
                    negotiations have been accelerated.</p>
                <pb facs="0309" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We have territorial
                    questions with the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet
                        Union</rs>. I raised it with Dobrynin. He said that the Soviets would give
                    us back the Islands if it were only a question of relations between Japan and
                    the <rs corresp="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic">Soviet Union</rs>. The main
                    question now is that the problem with China which might raise claims on the
                    border question. They have such difficulty with China. The Chinese have proposed
                    that there be no big change in the borders but that the Russians admit that the
                    treaties which are a hundred years old are unfair. They will not initiate any
                    big change at this time. The Russians believe that if they give the Islands back
                    to Japan, China will come out again with big demands on the borders. That is the
                    difficulty on the Islands.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Will you alter your
                    relations with Russia?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I don’t think so. The
                    territorial question is the big obstacle. Relations in the economic field will
                    present no difficulty.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Why did Dobrynin talk to
                    you? Why do you not work through the Soviet Ambassador in Japan?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Because I raised it. He
                    is also an important man in the Communist Party.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: He is on the Central
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: This question came up
                    after other discussion.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I once was in Moscow for a
                        <rs corresp="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic">radio</rs> show involving
                    Japanese, Americans and Russians. There were one or two Japanese there. The
                    Russians were attacking me until the Japanese mentioned the Kurile Islands. Then
                    the Soviets attacked Japan and I was neutral.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The Russians are
                    certainly using the Chinese problem for their own purposes.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We are inevitably
                    involved to some extent in this power game.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: The problem is for both
                    sides not to let themselves be used against the other by the communist
                    countries. China wants to use the U.S. against you. The Soviet Union wants to
                    use Japan against us. This is important.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We are not nervous about
                    your relations with the Russians.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It is very clear
                    historically. It is not only a question of territory. There are no friendly
                    feelings towards the Russians, while there is a certain deep rooted friendly
                    feeling for China.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">U.S.-Japanese Visits</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: There will be a White
                    House dinner for your delegation on September 10.</p>
                <pb facs="0310" n="279" xml:id="pg_279"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We deeply appreciate
                    this. Also the visit of the Emperor.<note n="10" xml:id="d90fn10">A memorandum
                        of conversation of <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s
                        discussion with the Emperor is in the National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 1025,
                            Presidential/<gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss> Memcons, Memcon—The
                        President/Emperor Hirohito, Sept. 26, 1971.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It was announced
                    yesterday. It will not be too long.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We understand. It is
                    because of our schedule.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It is mostly symbolic.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It is very important
                    symbolically.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Will your Foreign Minister
                    be along?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes. Will Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> accompany the President?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We may ask <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Alexis Johnson</persName> to accompany him too. You have
                    two Ambassadors in Washington. You and <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Alexis
                        Johnson</persName>.<note n="11" xml:id="d90fn11">The sanitized version does
                        not contain the rest of this paragraph, <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>’s response, and <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s counter-response (which ends with the word
                        “Reischauer”).</note> I don’t know what you do to our people. For example,
                    former Ambassador Reischauer always tells me to be nice to you.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: That gives us three
                    Ambassadors. Reischauer was very effective.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I am not permitted to
                    forget Japan. Of course, I do not want to. I am scolded at regular intervals by
                    Reischauer.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: In the economic field
                    what kind of developments do you foresee now?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Now that we have made such
                    big steps, let’s concentrate in meetings on the big issues, and not on
                    nitpicking. It would be terribly helpful symbolically if we have one or two
                    announcements which show that we are working together and agreeing together.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PPG_1">Peterson</persName> will talk with you.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes. We will give you
                    some concrete ideas.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That will be very helpful.
                    We will be constructive on our side.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> said yesterday that the prospects for
                    Okinawa were better. The State Department will submit this to the Senate right
                    after the <rs corresp="recdbjtxjnHuY2yic" type="topic">Ministerial Meeting</rs>
                    with strong recommendations by the President. That will be very helpful.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We certainly plan to do
                    that in September. Your moves would help.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Do you plan to go
                    overseas before China? Why don’t you visit us sometime?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: In principle I would be
                    glad to visit Japan. In Washington whenever I go abroad officially it generates
                    a great deal of <pb facs="0311" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> jealousy. If there
                    could be some excuse, if I could speak to some group, not the press, in
                    principle I would be glad to visit. In fact I am quite eager to do so. I have
                    not really been there since 1962 when I was there for about a week. In principle
                    I would like to go. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NY_1">Nakasone</persName> invited
                    me. I can’t go as the guest of the Defense Minister; that would be under the
                    wrong auspices.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We can find better
                    auspices I am sure.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If you can find a better
                    way, particularly one that would not trigger my colleagues’ resentment,<note n="12" xml:id="d90fn12">The sanitized version does not contain this
                        subordinate clause.</note> that would be helpful. I have thought of going.
                    How long would it take?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: About twelve hours
                    altogether.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If I went, I would go by
                    military plane.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: The polar route is much
                    shorter.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Maybe I could go during
                    the late fall, the end of November, for four or five days. But I am afraid of
                    your press.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We are all afraid of
                    your press.<note n="13" xml:id="d90fn13">The sanitized version does not contain
                        this comment by <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">More on <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">Textiles</rs>, China, and U.S.-Japan Relations</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: You did a good job with
                    the American press. They all think we have hurt you badly.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We have stopped doing
                    that now. We are concentrating on the future now. We have very little sympathy
                    in the American press, recently because of economic problems.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: First of all they do not
                    understand them. I know nothing about economics. Our businessmen are furious. We
                    are under enormous pressures from our businessmen.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It seems almost
                    customary to attack Japan in conversations among your business people.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Economic leaders are
                    usually political idiots. They don’t understand our basic interests and wouldn’t
                    know how to bring them about if they did.<note n="14" xml:id="d90fn14">In the
                        sanitized version, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> notes:
                        “Economic leaders don’t understand our basic interests.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: That is true of
                    Japanese businessmen.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Your textile industry, for
                    example.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: They are so emotional.
                    That is what makes it so difficult.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It will be impossible to
                    write a <rs corresp="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic">history</rs> on the textile
                    negotiations. I understood them for two weeks last year when the Prime Minister
                    was here.</p>
                <pb facs="0312" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: We wrote the communiqué
                    in the office.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Why did the Prime Minister
                    come back to this subject?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: He was determined to
                    finish this business. After returning to Japan the situation became even
                    worse.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: There have been more
                    Japanese emissaries than American secret envoys. You have seen your share of
                    Americans. We are showing you some even rougher than Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM_1">Stans</persName>.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Some people on your
                    side are bitter.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: The biggest price you paid
                    was with the President. It was a mistake for the Prime Minister to raise the
                    issue a second time without knowing he could settle it. The first time with the
                    President it was OK. We didn’t want to raise the issue again. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KN_1">Kishi</persName> also promised.</p>
                <p>The President considers we are friends. You paid an intangible price. I would
                    like to think our basic policy is not affected by irritations and it is not, but
                    these little things are damaging.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Yes they are very
                    unfortunate.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have to be sensible and
                    now find a way to deal with fundamental problems. You certainly have great good
                    will in the White House. Both the President and I want to strengthen our
                    relations with Japan. The President will travel all night to spend one hour with
                    the Emperor. This symbolizes our attitude. The President has a bed in Air Force
                    One, but the rest of us will be very tired.</p>
                <p>(There was then some small talk on Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>’s travel arrangements to the <rs corresp="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic">airport</rs> to go back to
                    Japan.)</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: How did you find Prime
                    Minister Chou?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: He was very
                    intelligent.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: He expresses his views
                    in a very subtle way.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Much subtler than the
                    Russians. He is quite tough. He is very eloquent in his expressions. Have you
                    dealt with the Chinese before?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: In very small ways. I
                    have talked to some Chinese in Taiwan. They are all very cultured people.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: A lack of intelligence is
                    not their national problem.</p>
                <p>He is very intelligent. Most press speculation (on <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> trip to Peking) is quite wrong. They all assume there
                    was some deal. You have experience and know this can’t happen. What deals are
                    possible?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: They are so fundamental
                    issues, for which you must have time to solve.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have managed to talk
                    about <rs corresp="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic">textiles</rs> for two years.
                    Why would we solve Taiwan in ten hours?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: It seems now that the
                    attitude of Taiwan is very flexible on the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                <pb facs="0313" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have a very good
                    position.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: If we fail in the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, what will happen?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What do you mean?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Will you recognize
                    Peking?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: No. It will not affect the
                    basic relations. We will not recognize Peking for the foreseeable future. I
                    can’t say what will happen in three or four years. We have no intention now. In
                    the future as far as I can see we have no intention of recognizing Peking.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Will both you and
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> be going?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: To Anchorage, yes.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I mean Peking.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: There will be a lot of
                    press people.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We don’t know what to do,
                    but I hope there will not be too many. We could take 2,000; several hundred want
                    to go. We will try to keep the circus to the minimum. They will have nothing to
                    do there. We can’t tell them what we discuss in the meetings. The Chinese have
                    had many barbarian invasions. They have never seen American journalists, not to
                    speak about the advance men. People have wondered whether something political
                    might interrupt the trip. That part is alright. What will interfere is the
                    behavior of our people.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: You are very security
                    minded.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If 750,000,000 people
                    attack us, there is no way to stop them. I think the security will be very
                    good.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I think so.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If it happens it will be
                    by design not by accident. If it is by design, no one can help the
                    situation.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: You foresee no
                    political difficulties?</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: No. We would not have
                    agreed to the trip. They have their own reasons. They do not do us a favor.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: Of course.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: They are not in the
                    business of doing favors for others.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: They will continue to
                    be very tough on Japan in the near future.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We will not cooperate in
                    that. If you were to expand militarily . . . but this is not at all likely.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_UN_1">Ushiba</persName>: I can assure you that
                    this is out of the question.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I can conceive of no
                    difference of views between us. We won’t cooperate in isolating you. We want to
                    strengthen our relations with you.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
