<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Beirut ( (Wadsworth) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1063</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1063</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-11T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-11T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec3b4QX8ohh76TF3" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-11T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-11T13:00:00-05:00" n="1063"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1063">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890E.00/183: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Beirut</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-11T20:00:00+02:00"
                            >November 11, 1943—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 13—2:17 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>311. Supplementing my 310, November 11, noon. I was awakened half past 5 this
                    morning to receive “urgent message” from French Delegation General protocol
                    officer. He is French by nationality but of Lebanese origin. I have long known
                    he deplores French Levant policy.</p>
                <p>He had received orders to visit foreign representatives and religious dignitaries
                    to inform them that Armistice Day military review was cancelled. Trembling he
                    added “They have arrested the President and all the Ministers. French marines
                    and Senegalese troops broke brutally into their houses. I have seen with my own
                    eyes a decree signed by Helleu appointing Edde to the Presidency.”</p>
                <p>At this point a strongly nationalist Lebanese journalist arrived. His story:
                    “French Sûreté agents called to arrest him; he escaped and ran to home of
                    Interior Minister where he found cordon of Senegalese troops under French
                    officer; servants said Minister had resisted and been brutally beaten.”</p>
                <p>At Legation building next door to my house, there was only Lebanese policeman on
                    guard. Confusing switchboard plugs I found French central would give no
                    communication. By private [line?] I called Military Attaché; then by special
                    line to British military headquarters had myself put through to Cairo where,
                    Legation not replying, I dictated to USAFIME headquarters message for
                    transmission to you.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile I had telephoned British officer on duty at area headquarters. He was
                    unaware of developments but I have since learned that both British Legation and
                    Ninth Army headquarters were early informed of arrests.</p>
                <p>Breaking my narrative: Preceding evening Brigadier Hatton commanding Ninth Army
                    in General Holmes’ absence in Egypt after <pb facs="1026" n="1014"
                        xml:id="pg_1014"/> dining with me had said he was so concerned at explosive
                    possibilities of the situation he would urge General’s immediate return. His
                    orders were substantially as follows: If public security be threatened no
                    British troops will be employed unless French territorial command is unable to
                    maintain order and then specifically requests assistance; if employed they will
                    operate only under British officers and primarily to protect communications, et
                    cetera, of vital interest to Ninth Army operational command.</p>
                <p>Resuming narrative: Before I was dressed British Military Attaché called to say
                    Spears would like to see me and Iraqi Chargé d’Affaires. We arrived at British
                    Legation residence shortly before 8:00.</p>
                <p>There I found intense concern and activity. Spears had talked by phone with Casey
                    in Cairo, and London was being urgently informed; the French were “quite mad”
                    and “almost anything might happen”; Helleu was making address over Radio Levant
                    at 8:00.</p>
                <p>Spears was particularly incensed that Helleu had sat and talked with him an hour
                    after impromptu dinner last night in British Legation in honor of King of
                        Yugoslavia<note n="19" xml:id="d1063fn19">King Peter II.</note> and had
                    given his word of honor that French contemplated no action which might threaten
                    public security. Not an inkling was given of what was to transpire during
                    night.</p>
                <p>Again breaking narrative: Word of King’s prospective arrival, primarily to visit
                    Yugoslavian battalion near Haifa under Ninth Army operational command, was
                    received by British only after his airplane had left Cairo. Spears and Hatton
                    hurried to airport, there found Helleu and galaxy of French generals and
                    officials; King was to stay at French residency; arrangements for his security
                    had been made by French. Incident further illustrates French non-cooperative
                    uncommunicativeness.</p>
                <p>Resuming narrative: At British Legation I found also Lebanese Vice President of
                    Council Abi Chahla and Defense Minister Druze Emir Medgid Arslan; my early
                    morning informant had erred in thinking all Ministers arrested. They in turn
                    erred in believing a third colleague was still at liberty.</p>
                <p>Abi Chahla made to us and later put in writing contention that under Lebanese
                    constitution all executive power devolved upon him and arrested Ministers. Both
                    Ministers protested bitterly against Helleu’s “illegal and brutal acts” and
                    “violation of our independence and constitution and of principles for which
                    Allies are fighting”; intervention to reestablish constitution and free
                    arrestees was urged.</p>
                <p>It was an interested mixed group therefore which gathered before Spears’ radio to
                    hear Helleu broadcast and texts of new decrees. <pb facs="1027" n="1015"
                        xml:id="pg_1015"/> Comments were few during reading, their sense being that
                    whole was strongly colored by unblushing hypocrisy.</p>
                <p>Helleu’s speech began: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Hour has struck to end insensate maneuvers aimed only at depriving
                            Lebanon of secular support of France, to subject it to dictatorship at
                            whose hands it would have foundered—you would have despised France had
                            she let things drift”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>He then recounted political developments since Ministry had taken office, notably
                    his declared intention to implement promised independence, his advice before
                    leaving for Algiers that consideration of constitutional amendments should await
                    his return and later warnings that such action was illegal, all left
                    unheeded.</p>
                <p>Then came strong attack against Premier Solh and Ministry which had encouraged “a
                    tyranny on the street”.</p>
                <p>It was “a conspiracy against France”. Could one keep illusions when hearing him
                    called by German radio “the great chief”?</p>
                <p>Finally he denied forcefully that France had not kept her promises, renewing,
                    “solemn assurance of resolve to accord complete independence” through friendly
                    negotiation and urging that people give proof of calm and remain deaf to
                    excitements.</p>
                <p>The first decree declared void Parliament’s November 8th vote amending
                    constitution, dissolved member of [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Chamber of
                    Deputies, suspended constitution pending new elections, reestablished provisions
                    for nominated third of Chamber and provided for French appointment of “Chief of
                    State-Chief of Government” to exercise executive authority and, in Council of
                    Ministers appointed by himself, to issue decrees having force of law.</p>
                <p>Juridical bases for this decree cited in its preamble included notably articles
                    90 and 102 of constitution (i. e. chief of those abolished 3 days earlier by
                    Chamber), Catroux’s 1941 declaration of independence and Algiers’ decision of
                    November 5 that constitution might be amended only with French assent.</p>
                <p>Preamble concluded: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Lebanese President, Government and Parliament by their act of November 8
                            violated constitution, necessitating recourse to new elections”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Second decree named Emile Edde new chief executive. Department will recall he
                    once held presidency and was 2 months ago French favored candidate for
                    reelection. “Chief French stooge” was Spears’ comment.</p>
                <p>On Helleu’s speech and decrees Tahsin Qadri commented “The French are quite mad”.
                    Emir Arslan asked “How can you expect me to control the Druzes?”</p>
                <pb facs="1028" n="1016" xml:id="pg_1016"/>
                <p>The ensuing conversation with Spears and Qadri former said he already had Casey’s
                    authority to lodge strong written protest. He reiterated indignation at Helleu’s
                    “perfidy”, adding “for French to undertake act of this kind without any warning
                    to Ninth Army is unthinkable if only on security grounds; and this under aegis
                    by [<hi rend="italic">of?</hi>] countries of Atlantic Charter which have
                    recognized Lebanese independence; it is challenge to cause for which we are
                    fighting”.</p>
                <p>He then asked if we wished to associate ourselves in protest. Britain he said had
                    chief responsibility because it had “guaranteed” that independence “but we are
                    all in the same boat”; there could be no doubt Helleu acted under instructions
                    from Algiers where, he hoped, urgent representations would be made for
                    restoration of constitution and release by arrestee [<hi rend="italic">of
                        arrestees?</hi>].</p>
                <p>His final point was that no one should recognize any government named by Edde
                    “not only stooge but also one called traitor by his colleagues where he quit the
                    Chamber before its final note [<hi rend="italic">vote?</hi>] for
                    independence”.</p>
                <p>Qadri agreed, said he viewed French action as “directed against Allies and us”,
                    commented again “French are mad” and added “blood will flow before tomorrow
                    unless British troops intervene”.</p>
                <p>I commented that French appeared to be using same <hi rend="italic">coup
                        d’état</hi> tactics as last March when ousting Naccache regime<note n="20"
                        xml:id="d1063fn20">See <ref target="#pg_953">pp. 953</ref> ff., <hi
                            rend="italic">passim.</hi>
                    </note> but in a situation so changed, by reestablishment of constitutional
                    regime, from that of 9 months ago that their use could not as then be condoned;
                    I should consequently feel strongly hesitant to recommend recognition of Edde
                    regime.</p>
                <p>I added that, as British position here was special, as Spears had said, I felt it
                    would be unwise for me to associate myself directly with his protest; I would
                    however endeavor to see Helleu and report fully to my Government.</p>
                <p>Here we were interrupted by series of reports on spreading demonstrations as word
                    of French decisions circulated in the city. These were cited in my telegram
                    under reference.</p>
                <p>There followed visits from Maronite Archbishop and Mufti. Former called French
                        action“<hi rend="italic">coup de folie</hi> which may well lead country to
                    revolution”. He added “You who stand for Lebanese independence should meet force
                    with force; I speak with voice of all Lebanese Christians when I say this <hi
                        rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> cannot be tolerated.</p>
                <p>Mufti greeted me with “Are we slaves?” and I garnered following bits from his
                    ensuing protest “This cannot be done. What is this constitution I protest
                    strongly for all Moslems. We cannot let this bloodshed worsen. Reaction will be
                    bitter and violent here and in all Arab countries and strongly prejudicial to
                    United Nations’ cause”.</p>
                <pb facs="1029" n="1017" xml:id="pg_1017"/>
                <p>Upon my return to Legation I found two further protests, one from speaker and six
                    deputies who had installed themselves in Chamber before it was encircled by
                    cordon of Senegalese troops. Informed of events of the night and prevented from
                    lawfully meeting with their colleagues they protested to those countries which
                    had recognized Lebanese independence and to sister Arab states.</p>
                <p>Note: Shortly thereafter these deputies left Parliament under threat of forceful
                    eviction but met again during afternoon in house of one of them with some 20
                    other deputies.</p>
                <p>My second protest was from representatives of Plalange and Najjada, respectively
                    leading Maronite and Moslem youth organizations. That these traditional rivals
                    came as joint delegation illustrates unanimity of anti-French protest.</p>
                <p>Later a representative delegation of nearly 100 doctors, lawyers, engineers and
                    journalists visited Legation. Many among them were leaders in their professions
                    and demonstrating for first time in their lives.</p>
                <p>Tomorrow I am to see six foreign correspondents, four British and two American,
                    flown here today in British plane from Cairo at Spears’ suggestion.</p>
                <p>There has been no further marked deterioration of public security during
                    afternoon. Most shops remained closed. No crowds circulated, but there was
                    little disorder beyond tearing down of French propaganda posters of de Gaulle.
                    Largest crowd, perhaps 1,000, demonstrated at President’s house where there was
                    some shooting by Senegalese troops posted on neighboring roofs, two
                    demonstrators who endeavored to enter house being shot in leg.</p>
                <p>Lady Spears braved this fusillade and with President’s wife, whom she found in
                    terrified state, returned to British Legation amid demonstrators’ applause.
                    There are ugly tales of harsh and inconsiderate treatment by soldiery of member
                    of President’s family. American Legation automobile passing this crowd was also
                    applauded.</p>
                <p>British and American Army reports confirm general friendly attitude of populace
                    toward two countries, but there is undercurrent of feeling that our declared
                    principles are on trial. I sensed this too when receiving protests mentioned
                    above.</p>
                <p>A 6:30 curfew has cleared streets and on tour just made Legation Secretary found
                    city “quiet as tomb” with few troops in evidence, only apparent evidence of
                    disorder being half dozen still smouldering overturned French Army automobiles
                    and as many uneffective barricades.</p>
                <p>There are unconfirmed reports of tension accompanied by unimportant
                    demonstrations in some provincial towns, notably Tripoli <pb facs="1030"
                        n="1018" xml:id="pg_1018"/> where Moslem leader and Deputy Karami was also
                    arrested during night. I have just learned that he and Minister were taken to
                    Rashaya where, according to Helleu, they will be treated considerately, like
                    gentlemen and not as criminals.</p>
                <p>British Legation is concerned lest these arrestees and President (who is reported
                    held elsewhere possibly Chtaura) be flown to French Africa; watch-out orders
                    have been given British control authorities.</p>
                <p>From British Legation I learn also that, having been unable to obtain appointment
                    during morning to see Helleu, Spears sent him vigorous written protest against
                    French action and methods and reserved liberty of action. Presumably because of
                    reference therein to Helleu’s misleading answers to Spears’ questions of
                    preceding evening, this note evoked acid reply which has led to near rupture
                    between two Missions. Denying charge, reply said “My honor has no need of
                    lessors [<hi rend="italic">lessons?</hi>]”.</p>
                <p>At 6 p.m. I visited Helleu by appointment and will report conversation in
                    following section.</p>
                <p>Following are highlights of my conversation with Helleu, delayed in coding
                    because of shortness of staff.</p>
                <p>I said I had had day of report and rumor, protest and worry. He replied he had
                    found painful need for drastic action.</p>
                <p>I said it was not only situation in country that troubled me but also probable
                    reactions in neighboring Arab states. He saw no basis for serious concern unless
                    others fished in troubled waters.</p>
                <p>In Algiers he had obtained really practical propositions to make to Levant
                    states. In confidence these were: He was to say National Committee was now
                    prepared to ratify 1936 treaties<note n="21" xml:id="d1063fn21">Franco-Syrian
                        Treaty of Friendship and Alliance, signed at Damascus, December 22, 1936,
                        and Franco-Lebanese Treaty of Friendship and Alliance, signed at Beirut,
                        November 13, 1936. These treaties were never ratified by France. For texts,
                        see France, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères, <hi rend="italic">Rapport à
                            la Société des Nations sur la situation de la Syrie et du Liban</hi>
                            (<hi rend="italic">année 1936</hi>), pp. 201 and 229,
                        respectively.</note> with minor modifications earlier suggested by states;
                    then to negotiate for such transfer of common interests as exigencies of war
                    might permit.</p>
                <p>Note: This struck me as hypocrisy or ignorance, and latter seemed improbable; he
                    must know for long Syria and now Lebanon would have nothing of treaties.</p>
                <p>He insisted forcefully French policy was thus to accord independence to states; I
                    had his “word of honor” for it.</p>
                <p>He endeavored to explain, as in morning’s radio broadcast, that National
                    Committee had given Lebanese Government every chance to act reasonably but the
                    latter had refused Committee’s suggestion. <pb facs="1031" n="1019"
                        xml:id="pg_1019"/> This offense to France, similarly ignoring his request
                    for delay was slap in face. He had but returned these acts in kind.</p>
                <p>Reverting to his reference to fishers in troubled waters I asked: “Frankly do you
                    mean the British; and do French today generally believe British are endeavoring
                    to oust them from Levant and take their [apparent omission].” He replied in
                    substance: “They are, there can be no doubt, it is more than policy of man on
                    the spot. Churchill and Eden<note n="22" xml:id="d1063fn22">Anthony Eden,
                        British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> have told
                        Massigli<note n="23" xml:id="d1063fn23">René Massigli, in charge of foreign
                        affairs for the French Committee of National Liberation.</note> not to take
                    Spears too seriously, that policy is determined only in London; but we know from
                    long experience it is more than that.”</p>
                <p>Note: Never before have I had so clear authentic answer to this question. I
                    believe it constitutes one of two basic motives prompting present French action;
                    other being imperialistic desire to retain hold on country. I said reports on
                    reactions in other Arab countries to last week’s period of tension had been bad
                    enough, up to [<hi rend="italic">after?</hi>] today’s events they would be more
                    bitter; result might well be serious undermining of United Nations’ position in
                    Arab world. Should there not, as Spears suggests, have been prior consultations,
                    between Allies? He replied he knew Spears was angry and “thinks I misled him by
                    saying last evening that if anyone disturbed security it will not be I.” He
                    added “Could I tell him what had been prepared in greatest secrecy for me to do
                    that night[?] There should be no serious trouble if no one intervenes.”</p>
                <p>I said reports of procedure of arrests, made in dead of night with seemingly
                    intentional discourtesy and rough handling, were also troubling. He thought I
                    would find reports exaggerated; there had been no lack of consideration for
                    arrestees; they would be treated as gentlemen, not criminals.</p>
                <p>I asked him to keep me informed of state of security. He agreed to do so. His
                    reports were that during day only one person had been killed and two wounded,
                    regretful though this was.</p>
                <p>Note: American military tells me that while figures at time we talked were
                    probably 5 killed and 20-odd wounded, extent of shooting (probably only some
                    five to ten thousand shots) was relatively light.</p>
                <p>Finally I urged him in interest of common war effort, to keep himself promptly
                    informed on reactions in other Arab countries. He replied he held that effort in
                    mind.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
