<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-24T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-24T21:00:00-05:00" n="265" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">123 B 21/334: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">William Phillips</persName>, Personal
                                Representative of President <persName>Roosevelt</persName> in
                                India</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-24T22:00:00-04:00">February
                                    24, 1943—10 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>119. The Department is contemplating assigning to New Delhi Joseph W.
                            Ballantine, Foreign Service Officer of Class I, whose designation would
                            ordinarily be Counselor of Embassy or Legation. In your opinion would
                            Counselor of Mission be appropriate and to the Government of India an
                            acceptable designation for him?</p>
                        <p>The Department is also contemplating assigning to New Delhi Frank S.
                            Williams, Foreign Service Officer of Class III, with a view to his
                            performing functions usually undertaken by a Commercial Attaché. It is
                            also anticipated that he will be responsible under the Chief of Mission
                            for the coordination of the work of the various <pb facs="0247" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> American civilian agencies in India. If no
                            objection is perceived the Department plans to designate him Counselor
                            of Mission for Economic Affairs.</p>
                        <p>In the same connection the Department feels that Secretaries of the
                            Mission might appropriately have the designation of First, Second or
                            Third Secretary. While it is appreciated that corresponding officers of
                            the Indian Agency General in Washington are also officers of the British
                            Embassy and as such rank as First, Second or Third Secretaries, it has
                            been noted that they customarily use these titles in connection with
                            their duties at the Agency General.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>