<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Calvin H. Oakes of the Division of Near Eastern
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccAEF3WTG3YVwaX" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85065851"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Industrial development</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="tariffs" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132405" lcsh-match="good_close">Tariff</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="291"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.24/405</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Calvin H. Oakes of the Division of Near
                        Eastern Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-24">February 24,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Reference is made to the proposed lend-lease agreement between India and the
                    United States. Technical aspects of the matter have already been discussed by TA
                    in its memoranda expressing disapproval of the proposal. NE<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d291fn6">The Division of Near Eastern Affairs.</note> feels that
                    there are objections on political grounds to any such agreement. While in some
                    Indian circles it would no doubt be viewed as a recognition of India’s approach
                    to independent or quasi-independent status and hence would to that extent be
                    pleasing, it is thought that there are other considerations which would
                    contribute unfavorably to American-Indian understanding.</p>
                <p>It is assumed that this Government would not be willing to enter into any such
                    agreement on the basis of a materially modified Article VII, and failing any
                    such concession on our part, it would be immediately and bitterly alleged that
                    the United States and Great Britain had conspired to force upon India, through
                    action of the existing unrepresentative Government in India, a tariff policy
                    ruinous to India’s future industrial development. As the Indian industrialists
                    are, as a group, among India’s most potent nationalists, and as that group has
                    been vociferous in expressing suspicion of American intent towards India, it is
                    felt that any such ground for complaint on their part would be highly
                    undesirable at this time.</p>
                <p>A second factor involved pertains to India’s insistence that any such agreement
                    embody the provision that the value of goods given and services rendered to the
                    United States shall not exceed the value of articles supplied by the United
                    States. While it is assumed that reverse lend-lease from India is comparatively
                    small at the present time, it would appear possible that at some future time the
                    extent of reversed lend-lease in India might increase sufficiently to cause
                    uncertainty in the Indian mind as to who was benefiting most. It may be that
                    this Government would be willing to include such a provision. If it is not
                    included, however, and if the question indicated above ever arises, resentment
                    would be centered against the United States if a separate lend-lease agreement
                    were in existence, while if reverse lend-lease is supplied under the agreement
                    with Great Britain, resentment would probably be directed largely against that
                        country.<note n="7" xml:id="d291fn7">Notation on the original by the Adviser
                        on Political Relations (Murray): “I agree most emphatically.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
