<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-09-15T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-09-15T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-15T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-15T23:00:00-05:00" n="334"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d334">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.71245/24: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-16T00:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 16, 1943—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5684. Your 5650 of August 27. Substance of your telegram has been discussed with
                    representatives of United Press and Ambassador Phillips. It is the Department’s
                    desire that vigorous efforts be continued with a view to effecting a
                    reconsideration of the decision reached by the Governments of the United Kingdom
                    and India, and that there be emphasized to the Foreign Office the strong feeling
                    of this Government in the matter. There are cited below considerations which
                    should be presented to the Foreign Office: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>While it is true that wireless transmissions from any point in India
                            would be subject to interception by the enemy such interception could in
                            no way give aid or comfort to the enemy since all material transmitted
                            would have been precensored by the Government of India.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Further, nearly every despatch would have previously passed through
                            British censorship in London or American censorship or both. It is the
                            Department’s understanding that all news despatches from this country
                            destined for India pass through London whence they are sent by cable or
                            radio to India.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Thus there would be double and in many cases triple censorship besides
                            the fact that most news material would already have been transmitted by
                            wireless throughout the world and thus would be available to the enemy
                            before distribution in India.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>United Press recognizes that in certain Indian centers from which it
                            has requested wireless transmission facilities there may not now be
                            sufficient censorship and security personnel but it believes that in at
                            least three of those centers, Bombay, New Delhi and Calcutta, adequate
                            personnel for such control already is available. It is suggested,
                            therefore, that at least for the time being transmissions be limited to
                            those three points.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The wireless facilities which are being requested in India on behalf
                            of United Press are available in the United States to any responsible
                            British or other friendly foreign news agency desiring to use
                            them.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>It was United Press’ original intention and preference to offer to
                            Indian newspapers a service of foreign news only. Prospective Indian
                            newspaper clients of the UP have pointed out that UP must also be
                            prepared to deliver a service of Indian news. Otherwise, because of the
                            monopoly clause in Reuter contracts newspaper publishers using UP
                            foreign service might not obtain any Indian news. If it were not for the
                            Reuter monopoly clause the UP could enter the Indian field as a
                            supplementary service, competing with Reuter in foreign news only—given
                            facilities for distribution of even a foreign news service from the
                            cable head at Bombay.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It is believed that the foregoing explanations satisfactorily dispose of the
                    security problem involved. In the Department’s estimation, <pb facs="0307"
                        n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> however, the whole problem of the operation of UP
                    in India far transcends the question of any possible technical difficulties
                    involved. It raises the question whether in the territories of the United
                    Nations free competition will be allowed to enterprises of nationals of the
                    United Nations on a basis of reciprocity. As has already been pointed out above
                    should Reuters desire the use of the same kind of facilities in the United
                    States that are being asked for UP in India it could obtain them without
                    difficulty. While the Department is obviously not unmindful of the special
                    circumstances obtaining at this time in India it should be pointed out that UP
                    has no desire to render that situation more difficult by its presentation of
                    news, and that furthermore, ample and adequate safeguards are provided by
                    existing censorship both in England and in India. I hope, therefore, that when
                    you bring this case again to the attention of the Foreign Office you will
                    emphasize in an urgent manner the importance which the Department attaches to
                    it.</p>
                <p>As Ambassador Phillips is proceeding to London he will be available for
                    consultation. As you know Ambassador Phillips is thoroughly familiar with all
                    the aspects of this case. Please keep Department closely advised by telegraph of
                    all developments in this case.</p>
                <p>Repeated to New Delhi.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
