<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="361"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d361">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/2095½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-07">January 7,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Richard Casey, former Minister of Australia in Washington and at present
                    British Minister of State in the Middle East, called to see me today.</p>
                <p>I spoke to Mr. Casey of my very great concern with regard to the policy being
                    pursued by the British Government in Iran. I said I felt that, in the first
                    place, from the standpoint of the achievement of satisfactory results, the
                    British policy of the withholding of food supplies and the constant recurrence
                    to military force was not conducive towards the creation of a situation of
                    relative tranquillity in Iran which alone could give us the assurance that this
                    vital means of access to southern Russia would remain open to the United
                    Nations. Furthermore, I said, the attitude taken by so many of the British
                    officials in Iran towards United States officials, and particularly towards the
                    American Minister in Tehran,<note n="2" xml:id="d361fn2">Louis G. Dreyfus,
                        Jr.</note> was anything but helpful. I said I did not have to tell Mr. Casey
                    that the United States had no selfish interest of any kind or description in
                    Iran, but that this Government did feel that during the war period it was just
                    as vitally concerned in the maintenance of satisfactory conditions in that
                    country as Great Britain. I said I consequently felt that close and friendly
                    cooperation between the officials of the two Governments in that area was
                    indispensable for the sake of our common military objectives, and that I also
                    felt that our views with regard to the policy to be pursued towards the
                    Government and officials of Iran should be taken into consideration by the
                    British Government before it embarked upon any undertakings of any serious
                    character in that region. Mr. Casey told me that he had arranged to see Mr.
                        Murray<note n="3" xml:id="d361fn3">Wallace Murray, Adviser on Political
                        Relations.</note> this afternoon, and I told <pb facs="0332" n="320"
                        xml:id="pg_320"/> him that Mr. Murray would undoubtedly give him chapter and
                    verse for the statements and suggestions I had just made to him.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
