<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations ( (Murray))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-02-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recn8b1d7iCOsszeq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100445"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum products</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="366"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.91/98</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Murray</hi>)<note n="25" xml:id="d366fn25">Addressed to the
                        Assistant Secretary of State (Acheson), the Assistant Secretary of State
                        (Berle), the Under Secretary of State (Welles) and the Secretary of State.
                        Notation by John D. Jernegan of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs:
                        “Approved by the Secretary and Mr. Welles. 2/17/43.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-11">February 11,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The attached memorandum is a summary of the thoughts of NE<note n="26"
                        xml:id="d366fn26">Division of Near Eastern Affairs.</note> and myself
                    regarding the general bases and direction of our policy toward Iran, which we
                    should like to submit for your consideration. If you approve, we shall guide our
                    actions accordingly and shall send appropriate instructions to our Minister at
                    Tehran. I have also in mind the possible desirability of asking the planning
                    organizations under Mr. Pasvolsky<note n="27" xml:id="d366fn27">Leo Pasvolsky,
                        Special Assistant to the Secretary of State; also chairman, Committee on
                        Special Studies.</note> to give special attention to Iranian problems along
                    the lines indicated.</p>
                <p>Briefly, the memorandum sets forth the following points: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>The past and present attitudes of Great Britain and Russia toward
                            Iran, together with the current weakness of the Iranian Government and
                            disorganization of the country’s internal structure, justify fears that
                            Iran may prove a danger point when we come to the post-war
                            settlement.</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>The best hope of avoiding trouble in this regard lies in strengthening
                            Iran to a point at which she will be able to stand on her own feet and
                            in assuring both of the interested Great Powers that neither one need
                            fear the acquisition by the other of a predominant position in
                            Iran.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>The United States is the only nation which may be able to render
                            effective assistance to Iran without rousing the fears and opposition of
                            Great Britain or Russia, or of the Iranians themselves.</item>
                        <pb facs="0343" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>Since we have a vital interest in the fulfillment of the principles of
                            the Atlantic Charter<note n="28" xml:id="d366fn28">Joint Declaration by
                                President Roosevelt and British Prime Minister Churchill, August 14,
                                1941, <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_367">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 367</ref>.</note> and the
                            establishment of foundations for a lasting peace throughout the world,
                            it is to the advantage of the United States to exert itself to see that
                            Iran’s integrity and independence are maintained and that she becomes
                            prosperous and stable.</item>
                        <label>5)</label>
                        <item>Therefore, the United States should adopt a policy of positive action
                            in Iran with a view to facilitating not only the war operations of the
                            United Nations but also a sound post-war development of the country
                            which would eliminate the need or excuse for the establishment of any
                            sort of “protectorate”.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. John D. Jernegan of the Division of Near
                            Eastern Affairs</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-23">January 23,
                                1943</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">American Policy in Iran</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>This Government has come during the past year or more to play a relatively
                        active part in Iranian affairs. In the past, the United States has had no
                        important political interests in Iran and has been seriously concerned with
                        events in that country only from time to time. Our recent activity,
                        therefore, is rather a new departure and has arisen primarily out of our
                        participation in the war and natural concern that political matters in all
                        theaters of war operations should develop favorably with respect to the
                        United Nations. Iran has been, and is, important in this connection because
                        of its value as a supply route to Russia, its strategic location and its
                        vast production of petroleum products. When occasion has arisen to set forth
                        our policy, we have based it upon the foregoing considerations, and I feel
                        that they constitute ample justification for the attitude we have
                        adopted.</p>
                    <p>I believe, however, that it is worthwhile at this time to put down on paper
                        certain much broader considerations which, it seems to me, should likewise
                        impel us to follow a positive policy in Iran, not only while the prosecution
                        of the war is still foremost in our minds but also in the period when
                        victory is in our grasp and we come to the conclusion of the peace.</p>
                    <p>I should like to suggest that Iran constitutes a test case for the good faith
                        of the United Nations and their ability to work out among themselves an
                        adjustment of ambitions, rights and interests which will be fair not only to
                        the Great Powers of our coalition but also to the small nations associated
                        with us or brought into our sphere by circumstances. Certainly, nowhere else
                        in the Middle East is there to be found so clear-cut <pb facs="0344" n="332"
                            xml:id="pg_332"/> a conflict of interests between two of the United
                        Nations, so ancient a tradition of rivalry, and so great a temptation for
                        the Great Powers concerned to give precedence to their own selfish interests
                        over the high principles enunciated in the Atlantic Charter.</p>
                    <p>For considerably more than one hundred years, Russia has been pressing down
                        upon Iran from the north, repeatedly threatening new annexations of
                        territory, repeatedly attempting in one way or another to dominate Iran.
                        Three times in the present century alone Russian troops have entered Iranian
                        territory against the will of the Iranian people.</p>
                    <p>For the same period of time, Great Britain has opposed the Russian movement
                        southward, fearing for her position in the Persian Gulf and Indian Ocean and
                        especially fearful of the potential threat to India. British troops have
                        been on Iranian soil at least twice since the turn of the century and
                        British influence has been exerted over and over again to counter the
                        Russian expansion.</p>
                    <p>Although Russian policy has been fundamentally aggressive and British policy
                        fundamentally defensive in character, the result in both cases has been
                        interference with the internal affairs of Iran, amounting at times to a
                        virtually complete negation of Iranian sovereignty and independence. It is
                        superfluous to point out that this has created an ingrained distrust of both
                        powers in the Iranian people and has not been without effect upon the
                        attitude of the other weak peoples of the Middle East.</p>
                    <p>If this were merely history, it would be of no importance. Unfortunately,
                        there are signs that history may be in the process of repeating itself. The
                        basic factors are unchanged: Russia is still without a warm-water port;
                        Britain still clings to her predominant position in the Middle East and east
                        of Suez. Even if we assume the eventual independence of India and Burma and
                        a British withdrawal from Iraq, Palestine and Egypt, there is every reason
                        to suppose that Britain would not welcome an advance into that area by
                        Russia.</p>
                    <p>Once again Russian and British troops are in Iran, the former in the north,
                        the latter in the south and center. It is true that their presence is made
                        necessary by imperative considerations of military expediency and that their
                        withdrawal at the conclusion of the war has been solemnly promised, but I
                        need not recall the hundreds of instances in which the forces of a Great
                        Power have entered the territory of a weaker nation for one purpose and have
                        remained, indefinitely, for other purposes.</p>
                    <p>Largely because of this occupation of Iranian territory, the governmental
                        machinery of Iran, and its economic structure, have been seriously weakened.
                        This has become both a reason and an excuse for direct intervention by the
                        Russian and British authorities in <pb facs="0345" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/>
                        Iranian political matters. At the present moment, no Iranian Cabinet can
                        survive without the direct support of the Allied powers. While it is obvious
                        that the United Nations could not permit a hostile government to function at
                        Tehran, it is equally obvious that the Iranian political and economic
                        organization must be strengthened to a point at which it will be able to
                        function efficiently by itself, if Iran is to survive as an independent
                        nation. It is unnecessary to point out that a political vacuum is as
                        impossible as a physical vacuum; if Iran falls into a state of anarchy, some
                        power must assume responsibility for its government, and it may be assumed
                        that the first to offer themselves for this task would be one or both of the
                        present occupying powers.</p>
                    <p>Apart from the general situation in Iran, I believe we should be fully alive
                        to the character of the present Russian occupation of the northern
                        provinces. In Azerbaijan, the Soviet authorities have greatly restricted the
                        operations of the Iranian civil authorities and have virtually immobilized
                        the small Iranian military forces which they reluctantly permitted to return
                        to the area. They have alternately encouraged and discouraged the restive
                        Kurds, always a thorn in the flesh of the local government. More important
                        still, they have been so successful in propagandizing the population that
                        our Consul at Tabriz<note n="29" xml:id="d366fn29">Bertel E.
                            Kuniholm.</note> has reported that a soviet could be established
                        overnight in Azerbaijan if the Russians gave the word. In this connection,
                        it is well to remember that Azerbaijan is inhabited largely by a
                        Turkish-speaking population whose cultural ties with Soviet Transcaucasia
                        and Turkish Kurdistan are almost as strong as those with the rest of Iran.
                        It is also the most important grain-producing area of Iran and would be a
                        welcome addition to the food resources of Transcaucasia.</p>
                    <p>There are other items which might be mentioned: the strained relations
                        between the Russian and British authorities in Iran; the suspicion with
                        which the Russians appear to view every move made by the British or
                        Americans, for example their obvious hesitancy in agreeing to our operation
                        of the southern section of the Trans-Iranian railroad;<note n="30"
                            xml:id="d366fn30">For correspondence on this subject, see <ref
                                target="#pg_437">pp. 437</ref> ff.</note> the apparent attempt by
                        the Russian government to weaken British influence by leaving the British to
                        bear the brunt of Iran’s economic problems; the continued refusal of the
                        Soviet authorities in Iran to permit transportation of grain from Azerbaijan
                        to meet the urgent needs of Tehran; the impending move by the Russians to
                        take over control of Iranian arms plants.<note n="31" xml:id="d366fn31">For
                            correspondence on the Iranian arms plants, see <ref target="#pg_628">pp.
                                628</ref> ff.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>On the British side, the blunt, uncompromising attitude which has
                        characterized British policy towards Iran does not augur well for a <pb
                            facs="0346" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> future amicable adjustment of
                        Anglo-Iranian relations. Nor is it reassuring to recall the recent British
                        proposal to arrogate to the Allies power to modify the Iranian cabinet at
                        will.</p>
                    <p>It may be that the situation outlined above represents nothing more than the
                        inevitable result of the stress and strain of coalition warfare and that
                        once the victory is won all parties will be glad to revert to their former
                        positions, leaving Iranian sovereignty as intact as it was before the
                        Anglo-Russian occupation. Both Britain and Russia have repeatedly promised
                        to do so, and both powers, and Iran as well, have adhered to the principles
                        of the Atlantic Charter.</p>
                    <p>I should like to submit, however, that the United States has a vital interest
                        in seeing to it that the United Nations <hi rend="italic">do</hi> live up to
                        the Atlantic Charter and, consequently, in making it as easy as possible for
                        them to do so.</p>
                    <p>What I have in mind is the situation which will arise when the war is won, or
                        nearly won, and the time comes to think of British and Russian withdrawal
                        from Iran, with consequent full rehabilitation of Iranian self-government.
                        Have we not some reason to anticipate that the respective British and
                        Russian forces may remain suspiciously eyeing each other, each proclaiming
                        its entire willingness to withdraw as soon as the other has done so? Is it
                        not possible that one or both powers will allege, perhaps with reason, that
                        Iran is in such a state of confusion that she must be “protected” for a
                        time? And is it probable that either would withdraw and allow the other to
                        carry out this “protection”?</p>
                    <p>Carrying this thought one step further, if Russia should really harbor
                        ambitions for expansion in Iran, is it not all too likely that she would
                        insist upon Iran’s need for Soviet guidance, and that she would violently
                        oppose the interposition of another interested power in the role of tutor?
                        And if Great Britain should give way on this, would not Britain all the more
                        cling to her position in Iraq and other parts of the Middle East, as
                        protection against a future Russian thrust toward Suez, thus checking the
                        progress which we hope to see in the direction of independence for all Near
                        Eastern peoples?</p>
                    <p>I think we may assume that the Iranian Government has long since thought of
                        all the foregoing considerations and that its ever-stronger appeal for
                        American assistance is largely based upon them. So far, we have rested our
                        response to this appeal primarily upon our interest in winning the war. I
                        wonder if we should not also begin, privately, to base our response upon our
                        interest in winning the peace? The United States, alone, is in a position to
                        build up Iran to the point at which it will stand in need of neither British
                        nor Russian assistance to maintain order in its own house. If we go at this
                        task whole <pb facs="0347" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> heartedly, we can hope
                        to remove any excuse for a post-war occupation, partition, or tutelage of
                        Iran. We can work to make Iran self-reliant and prosperous, open to the
                        trade of all nations and a threat to none. In the meantime, we can so firmly
                        establish disinterested American advisers<note n="32" xml:id="d366fn32">For
                            correspondence on the American adviser program in Iran, see <ref
                                target="#pg_510">pp. 510</ref> ff.</note> in Iran that no peace
                        conference could even consider a proposal to institute a Russian or British
                        protectorate or to “recognize the predominance” of Russian or British
                        interests. If Iran needs special assistance of a material character, we can
                        provide it and so remove any cause for claims for compensation by other
                        powers. We can forestall loans carrying with them control of the customs or
                        other servitudes upon the Iranian Government. If railroads, ports, highways,
                        public utilities, industries, are to be built, we can build them and turn
                        them over to the Iranian people free of any strings.</p>
                    <p>I realize that objections can be raised to such a policy. Some which occur to
                        me at the moment are: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) it is unprecedented in our
                        relations with the Middle East; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) it impinges on a
                        “sphere of influence” hitherto considered exclusively British and Russian;
                            (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) there is no guarantee that it will succeed;
                            (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) it might involve expenditure and loss of
                        money; (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) if it came into public notice, it might
                        arouse domestic criticism on the part of isolationists.</p>
                    <p>To answer these seriatim: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The present war and the problems of future peace for the United
                                States are likewise unprecedented. We have now realized, and
                                publicly stated over and over again, that we cannot be indifferent
                                to the welfare of any part of the world, no matter how remote,
                                because sooner or later it will affect our own peace.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The very fact that Iran has been a “sphere of influence” in
                                dispute between two Great Powers, makes it all the more desirable
                                that a third, disinterested, power should be called in to eliminate
                                the dispute. Both Britain and Russia would be relieved of an anxiety
                                and constant source of friction if each could be assured that the
                                other would have no special position in the area, and it is not
                                inconceivable that both would regard this assurance as worth
                                whatever ambitions might be given up. In this connection, it seems
                                hardly possible that either could suspect the United States of
                                having imperialistic designs in a country so far removed from us and
                                where we could never hope to employ military force against an
                                adjacent Great Power.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>If war cannot be waged without taking risks, I submit that the
                                same is true of the making of peace. In any case, if we try and
                                fail, we shall have lost nothing more than if we do not make the
                                attempt. If the ambitions of Britain and Russia, their mutual
                                distrust, or their established interests, are so strong that they
                                would <pb facs="0348" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/> override a purely
                                disinterested effort on our part to improve conditions in Iran, then
                                we may assume that peace, in that part of the world, was doomed from
                                the beginning.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The expenditures involved, even if all of them should be a total
                                loss, would be insignificant by contrast with the cost of the
                                present war, and infinitesimal beside the material and human cost of
                                a failure to make a satisfactory peace throughout the world.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>This objection will be met with in connection with any effort by
                                the United States to participate in a cooperative post-war
                                settlement, and we must be prepared to accept it. In the case of
                                Iran, it could be countered by emphasis on the humanitarian aspects
                                and should appeal to the normal American sympathy with anything
                                savoring of assistance to the underdog. If properly presented, a
                                policy of help for Iran might, indeed, receive the same sort of
                                popular approval as has been accorded to our support of
                                China.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Finally, I should like to reiterate the conviction previously expressed that
                        if the principles of unselfish fair-dealing enunciated by the Atlantic
                        Charter are ignored when it comes to Iran, or any other country in similar
                        circumstances, the foundations of our peace will begin to crumble
                        immediately. In my opinion, this is the overriding argument which should
                        lead us to seize every opportunity to direct events in such a way that there
                        will be no occasion for power politics or conflict of interests among the
                        United Nations in their relations with Iran.</p>
                    <p>If this conclusion is sound, I believe that we should not only comply to the
                        best of our ability with Iranian requests for advisers and supplies but
                        should also take the initiative in suggesting the employment of American
                        specialists and application of American methods in various fields; further,
                        we should not be content merely to support or oppose British or Russian
                        policies and demands in Iran, but should put forward positive suggestions of
                        our own for the improvement of conditions. To this end, we should regard
                        ourselves as at least equally responsible with the British and Russians for
                        the solution of Iranian problems and need not, in any way, leave the
                        initiative to them merely because they happen to be the occupying powers.
                        Moreover, here in Washington we should actively enlist the cooperation of
                        all appropriate agencies of the Federal Government in support of this
                        policy, and we should not confine ourselves solely to steps whose close
                        connection with the war effort can be clearly demonstrated. If necessary, we
                        should make it clear to the other agencies that we regard measures to
                        promote a satisfactory ultimate settlement in Iran as being only slightly
                        less important than those immediately directed towards the winning of the
                        war, and that we consider it most unwise to defer all such measures until
                        the war is over.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
