<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-24T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-24T10:00:00-05:00" n="697" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d697">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890G.6363/393: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister Resident in Iraq</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baghdad</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-24T18:00:00+03:00">February
                                    24, 1943—6 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received February 25—2:23 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>77. Department’s 47, February 12. In a talk with my British
                                colleague<note n="31" xml:id="d697fn31">Sir Kinahan
                                Cornwallis.</note> last evening I learned that his information is to
                            the effect that arbitration in this case has been decided upon and that
                            Skliros left England around February 19 with power to act as arbitrator
                            on behalf of company interests. Furthermore that the Iraqi Government
                            had appointed the present Minister of Foreign Affairs Abdul Ilah Hafidh
                            to act as arbitrator for them. No referee has yet been decided upon and
                            the Ambassador feels that the company does not wish to submit to
                            arbitration if this can be avoided but Skliros is being put in a
                            position to do so if unable otherwise to reach an agreement.</p>
                        <pb facs="0660" n="648" xml:id="pg_648"/>
                        <p>In view of the above I think it advisable to summarize the memorandum of
                            my conversation with Nuri which formed the enclosure to my despatch No.
                            187 of February 17<note n="32" xml:id="d697fn32">Not printed.</note>
                            which left in last week’s pouch. I have not yet had the promised reply
                            to my note delivered to Nuri at that time when I expressed orally
                            considerations embodied in second, third and fourth sections of telegram
                            under reference.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Begin Summary</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Nuri has definite prejudice on subject. He asserts that he has always
                                felt that Basra area is distinctly different from Mosul and Baghdad
                                vilayet concessions and that he has always hoped to keep Basra as
                                national oil reserve. He never approved of grant of BPC<note n="33" xml:id="d697fn33">Basrah Petroleum Company.</note> concession.
                                However now that concession has been given he opposes any revision
                                which he feels could only result in detriment to Iraq.</p>
                            <p>He is aware of Skliros’ forthcoming visit but is not acquainted with
                                nature of proposals for revision.</p>
                            <p>Nuri says that validity of BPC concession can be kept alive by
                                continued payment of 200,000 gold pounds per annum as ground rent
                                plus further payment of like sum to Iraqi Government annually as
                                forfeit for not fulfilling drilling requirements. <hi rend="italic">Force majeure</hi> claim is denied by Nuri because drilling
                                operations have been prevented by external causes namely British
                                Government (failing to send certain plans and live up to
                                requirements) and BPC claims should be presented to British
                                Government for compensatory action.</p>
                            <p>Nuri professes to be perfectly prepared to go to arbitration and says
                                he does not understand why American interests are unwilling.</p>
                            <p>If settlement by arbitration is not desired Nuri is willing to waive
                                this upon payment to Iraq Government of additional 200,000 pounds
                                annually as above stated as company’s forfeit for not drilling. Nuri
                                feels that company will easily recover this from output of wells
                                when drilling finally begins and in end thinks that the financial
                                loss to the company would be only the amount of 5 percent annual
                                interest on the 200,000 pounds additional. He said same thing was
                                done in Mosul B.O.D. concession in 1930 for 3 years and claimed that
                                he is asking only for same treatment as was given then.</p>
                            <p>In short, Nuri’s position is that in addition to annual payment of
                                ground rent BPC owes Iraqi Government development of concession area
                                and royalties accruing from such development. If ground rent alone
                                is paid annually concession is perhaps not wholly invalidated but is
                                left undeveloped while other interests are prevented from developing
                                it to Iraq’s advantage.</p>
                            <p>Nuri agrees with open door policy and competitive enterprise and does
                                not want to tie up resources of Iraq in restricted field. Revision
                                of concession means for him only one thing—an effort by
                                concessionaires to avoid penalties for defaults such as the present.
                                By simple payment of ground rental one concession development could
                                be held up indefinitely. He cannot see that conditions vary much
                                today from what they were when concession was negotiated. <hi rend="italic">End of summary</hi>.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <pb facs="0661" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/>
                        <p>For the Department’s very confidential information there seems to be a
                            probability of a Cabinet reshuffle in the near future which without
                            changing the Prime Minister will take Abdul Hah Hafidh, now Minister of
                            Foreign Affairs, to the Portfolio of Finance and the present Minister of
                                Finance<note n="34" xml:id="d697fn34">Salih Jabr.</note> to the
                            Ministry of Interior which portfolio he once held and asked [<hi rend="italic">Askari</hi>]<note n="35" xml:id="d697fn35">Tahsin
                                al-Askari, Minister of the Interior.</note> either back to Cairo as
                            Minister Plenipotentiary (which is his preference) or given the
                            Portfolio of Foreign Affairs. The above, of course, is only tentative
                            and has not yet been made public.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>