<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Spain ( (Hayes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d784</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">784</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-13T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-13T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Passports</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-13T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-13T18:00:00-05:00" n="784"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d784">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.01/941: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hayes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-14T00:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 14, 1943—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received January 15—3
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>101. In conversation with the Foreign Minister<note n="24" xml:id="d784fn24">Gen.
                        Francisco Gomez Jordana.</note> this morning, I pointed out that the Vichy
                    regime was no longer entitled in international law to continued recognition by
                    any Government, and the only portion of the French state meeting the test of
                    recognition was that portion voluntarily cooperating with the United Nations in
                    pursuing the war against Germany following the latter’s violation of the
                    Franco-German armistice. I said that, despite the foregoing, my Government was
                    not now suggesting that Spain withdraw recognition of the Vichy regime but that
                    my Government did consider that continued recognition of that regime, as
                    perfunctory as it might be, should not deter Spain from having at least informal
                    relations <pb facs="0746" n="734" xml:id="pg_734"/> with that portion of the
                    French state which is, in fact, entitled to recognition. I reminded the Minister
                    that Colonel Malaise was acting as liaison between this Embassy and the High
                    Commission in North Africa, and that Monsieur Pettit<note n="25"
                        xml:id="d784fn25">Representing North Africa in commercial and other
                        matters.</note> was negotiating a possible economic exchange between Spain
                    and North Africa (my January 6, midnight<note n="26" xml:id="d784fn26">Not
                        printed.</note>). I said I was informed that Pietri<note n="27"
                        xml:id="d784fn27">Vichy Ambassador in Spain.</note> had protested against
                    the facilities being given by the Spanish authorities to these representatives
                    of the North African regime, despite the fact that they are more entitled to
                    receive facilities than is Pietri himself.</p>
                <p>I requested assurance that at such time as the High Commission in North Africa or
                    such other regime as might be constituted to administer that area, should
                    appoint an agent, whether Colonel Malaise or some other person, the Spanish
                    authorities, including officials of the Foreign Office, would treat [with] such
                    an agent. I suggested that such agent should have the right to (1) issue
                    passports, (2) circulate freely in Spain in the same manner as other foreign
                    representatives, and (3) visit the concentration camp at Miranda de Ebro and the
                    Spanish prisons in order to interview and assist persons if [<hi rend="italic"
                        >of</hi>] French nationality professing loyalty to the regime he represents.
                    Meanwhile I requested assurances that Malaise and Pettit would not be disturbed
                    in their present duties.</p>
                <p>The Minister said he was informed concerning Malaise’s status and perfectly
                    agreeable to it, and that Malaise would not be disturbed. He said that Pettit
                    was negotiating with the Foreign Office with his approval, that Spain is
                    interested in pursuing negotiations and wanted them to take place in Madrid and
                    be coordinated with our own economic negotiations.<note n="28" xml:id="d784fn28"
                        >For correspondence on negotiations regarding the reestablishment of trade
                        between French North Africa and the Iberian Peninsula, see <ref
                            target="frus1943v01#pg_2">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 2</ref>
                        ff.</note> The question of receiving an agent who might have the right to
                    issue passports, et cetera, presented a problem which he would have to study. He
                    expressed appreciation that I had not insisted on Spain’s withdrawing
                    recognition of the Vichy regime, because such action would embarrass Spain’s
                    relations with the Axis.</p>
                <p>I then told him I had been informed that Pietri had suggested the establishment
                    of a Vichy Consulate at Ceuta (Department’s No. 32, January 7, 4 a.m.), and said
                    the fact that Vichy representation in Spain is at all tolerated furnished no
                    reason, in international law or equity, for permitting the regime to extend its
                    representation in Spanish territory. I pointed out further the possible
                    disturbing effect on the Moors in North Africa, if both North African and Vichy
                    regimes were represented by consuls pursuing opposing policies in North Africa.
                    He said he quite appreciated the latter point and would take the matter under
                    advisement.</p>
                <pb facs="0747" n="735" xml:id="pg_735"/>
                <p>I left an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> with the Foreign Minister. Our
                    conversation was very friendly and he evidenced a sincere desire to arrive at a
                    working basis for relations with the French North African regime.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Tangier and Algiers.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
