<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Egypt ( (Kirk)) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">889</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-18T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-18T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-18T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-18T05:00:00-05:00" n="889"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d889">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.515/2: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="45" xml:id="d889fn45">At this time Minister Kirk was
                        accredited also as Minister to Saudi Arabia; for correspondence regarding
                        the status of the diplomatic representation of the United States in Saudi
                        Arabia, see <ref target="#pg_830">pp. 830</ref> ff.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-18T12:00:00+02:00"
                            >January 18, 1943—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received January 19—3:05
                        p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>110. As background to message transmitted in my 73, January 14, 5 p.m.,<note
                        n="46" xml:id="d889fn46">Not printed; the message transmitted was a private
                        telegram from Mr. Garry Owen, Jidda representative of the California Arabian
                        Standard Oil Company (Casoc), to an officer of the company at San Francisco,
                        regarding Casoc-British negotiations for supplying Abdul Aziz ibn Saud, King
                        of Saudi Arabia, with needed income. The British Foreign Office had taken
                        the position in the negotiations that the currency problem of Saudi Arabia
                        must be met by the issue of internal notes controlled by the Currency
                        Control Board, as in Palestine, and backed by the British Bank
                        (890F.515/1).</note> Owen states that original plan proposed in November by
                    British Minister in Jidda<note n="47" xml:id="d889fn47">Francis H. W. Stonehewer
                        Bird.</note> and Rugman, Financial Secretary to Sudan Government, called for
                    furnishing 25,000,000 new rials and supply requirements, the whole to total
                    4,000,000 pounds sterling or slightly more. This recommendation was based on
                    estimate of about 64,000,000 rials of which it was expected to obtain about
                    3,000,000 from Casoc, 3,250,000 from Pilgrimage and remainder of about
                    57,750,000 rials, or slightly over 4,000,000 pounds, from the British in the
                    form of rial currency and supplies.</p>
                <p>This proposal was vetoed by London which proposed substitute plan outlined in my
                    telegram under reference. Message from London making proposal was received just
                    prior Owen’s departure from Jidda and despite Najib Salha’s<note n="48"
                        xml:id="d889fn48">Saudi Arabian Director of Mines and Public Works.</note>
                    optimism reaction of King problematical since suggestion of Rugman last
                        year<note n="49" xml:id="d889fn49">See telegram No. 75, July 29, 6 p.m.,
                        from the Minister Resident in Saudi Arabia, <ref target="#pg_882">p.
                            882</ref>.</note> for use of rupee notes was turned down on ground <hi
                        rend="italic">inter alia</hi> of countervening religious law. Plan for
                    organizing bank also not yet clear and presumably may depend largely at this
                    stage on Rugman’s recommendations.</p>
                <p>In reporting foregoing it occurs to me that should the bank proposal prove
                    acceptable to the Saudi Arabian Government an opportunity might be afforded for
                    American participation therein as a step not only in token of recognition and
                    support of the friendly attitude of Saudi Arabia in war but also as contribution
                    to long range stability of that country along lines indicated in my despatch
                    number 778 of January 4.<note n="50" xml:id="d889fn50">Not printed.</note> Other
                    contributing considerations would be facilitation and protection of existing
                    American interests in Saudi Arabia and equalizing effect in respect of
                    increasingly discernible tendency toward British economic intrenchment in this
                    area under war <pb facs="0869" n="857" xml:id="pg_857"/> impact to a degree
                    which might materially negate best intentioned postwar agreements for equality
                    of opportunity.</p>
                <p>In commending this matter to the Department’s attention it is suggested that in
                    view of [alleged?] inability of British to furnish silver and gold our
                    contribution in bank scheme might take form of providing all or part of gold
                    and/or silver requirements of bank under Lease-Lend and participation in
                    management of bank in order to assure satisfactory control. Winant<note n="51"
                        xml:id="d889fn51">Frederick Winant, at this time ranking civilian
                        representative of the Lend-Lease Administration in the Middle East, at the
                        Middle East Supply Center (MESC), Cairo; for correspondence regarding the
                        decision of the United States in 1942 to participate with the British in the
                        Middle East Supply Center, see <ref target="frus1942v04#pg_1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> sees possibilities
                    in this, as also do Owen and Ohliger of Casoc. May I have Department’s views at
                    earliest convenience as guidance for further exploration?</p>
                <p>In conclusion I feel impelled to state that after watching operation of system by
                    which American assistance to Saudi Arabia has been channelized through British,
                    I have gained impression that we have thereby lost considerable prestige in the
                    eyes of Saudi Arabians who have been given increasingly to feel that the British
                    were their only friends in need. In the interests of all concerned and in sight
                    of both immediate and long term considerations, the best all around solution
                    would seem to be one of understanding cooperation with British on basis of
                    equality and bank proposal might well afford suitable opportunity for
                    inauguration of such a policy before situation crystalizes to such a degree as
                    to render such cooperation more difficult. In addition I recommend early
                    consideration of extension of direct Lease-Lend of supplies to Saudi Arabia in
                    collaboration with and parallel to British but I would emphasize desirability in
                    so doing of not arousing Saudi Arabian hopes of greater assistance than we
                    prepared to extend and necessity of meeting promptly any engagements
                    contracted.</p>
                <p>In the event that Department favors extension Lend-Lease to Saudi Arabia, I
                    suggest that in view of political considerations involved and of Ibn Saud’s
                    susceptibilities an opportunity be given him to approve such a step prior to its
                    announcement.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Jidda.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
