<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-05-01T17:39:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-05-01T17:39:00-05:00" n="44" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                        <head>44. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Liberia<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d44fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D790219–0140.
                                Confidential; Immediate; Exdis. Sent for information Priority to
                                Abidjan, Conakry, Freetown, Accra, Kuwait, and Cairo. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SRP_1">Smith</persName> and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HWC_1">Harrop</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-05-01T22:39:00+00:00">May 1, 1979,
                                2239Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>110297. Subj: Liberian Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> Calls on Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>. Ref: Monrovia 3329, Kuwait 1941.<note n="2" xml:id="d44fn2">In telegram 3329 from Monrovia, April 27, the
                                Embassy reported on <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s reasons for the visit of <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> to the United States.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790193–0800) In telegram 1941 from Kuwait, April 23, the Embassy
                                reported on <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s visit
                                to Kuwait and his request for aid for Liberia. (National Archives,
                                RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D790187–0295)</note></p>
                        <p>1. Summary: Liberian Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> called on the Secretary for an hour and a half
                            April 30. Most of the meeting was taken up by <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName>’s explanation of the background
                            of the Easter weekend riot in Monrovia.<note n="3" xml:id="d44fn3">See
                                    <ref target="#d43">Document 43</ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said the principal causes
                            were the radicalization of Liberian university students in recent years,
                            and their disaffection with the government. The situation was
                            exacerbated by the presence in Monrovia of large numbers of half
                            educated unemployed. Although <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> was certain that there had been some indirect
                            Soviet encouragement of the demonstration, he admitted the authorities
                            could not document a specific connection. He appealed for assistance in
                            the form of a grant to help reconstruct Monrovia, and a development loan
                            to finance projects that would put the unemployed to work. He made no
                            specific suggestions. End summary.</p>
                        <p>2. Request to call on President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName>
                            acknowledged the Secretary’s welcome, conveyed President <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s greetings to the Secretary,
                            and emphasized that at <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s
                            direction he had taken special pains to keep the U.S. Embassy in
                            Monrovia informed of Liberian Government views of the background and the
                            events of the riot in Monrovia during Easter weekend. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName> had entrusted him with a
                            message to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> and
                            that he hoped to deliver it in person. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said that, “At this time of national crisis,” the
                            fact that President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> had
                            received <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s special
                            emissary would in itself have a favorable psychological effect by
                            underlining U.S. support for Liberia. The Secretary replied that the
                            President was extremely busy, that he could make no promises, but that
                            he would see what he could do.</p>
                        <p>3. Background of riot: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName>
                            explained the background of the riot as follows. In 1974 Bacchus
                                <persName corresp="#p_MGB_1">Matthews</persName>, a recent graduate,
                            was Vice <pb facs="0166" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/> Consul in New York.
                            He was dismissed for misappropriation of funds. He subsequently claimed
                            that he was fired for political reasons, and became anti-government. The
                            Progressive Alliance of Liberia was founded in New York in 1974. From
                            its published statements there can be no doubt of its “alien
                            indoctrination.” It was joined by disaffected students, including some
                            who had lost their scholarships. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> described at some length President <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s interest in the welfare of
                            the people as a whole, and his efforts to enlist the support and
                            participation of Liberian youth, particularly recent graduates. Despite
                            these efforts, the PAL established an office in Monrovia and succeeded
                            in infiltrating the university. There its views were condoned and
                            supported by some professors, many trained in the U.S., who “taught that
                            the free enterprise system was no good.” The PAL and similar groups were
                            critical of the West in general and the U.S. in particular.</p>
                        <p>4. In response to the Secretary’s question, <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said the centers of student disaffection were
                            Monrovia and Cuttington College, but that similar views were being
                            expressed in the interior, because there is no restriction of travel in
                            Liberia. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> added that
                            although the spread of education in Liberia had been impressive in
                            recent years, it had also resulted in a substantial increase in the
                            number of “half educated” unemployed in the cities, who were an easy
                            prey to ideologues. Although <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName> had emphasized education, often at the expense
                            of strengthening the security forces, more attention must now be paid to
                            improving the effectiveness of these forces.</p>
                        <p>5. External involvement: In response to the Secretary’s question,
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said that there “had
                            to have been” external support for the dissidents. Their leaders had no
                            jobs, but lived reasonably well, traveled both in Liberia and abroad,
                            and published a paper. However, the Liberian authorities could not
                            identify a specific link between the alleged instigators of the
                            demonstration and a foreign government. In retrospect, the Liberian
                            Government thought there might be more than coincidence in the facts
                            that a Russian student told a student meeting in Lome that he had to be
                            in Monrovia by the 14th, that North Korean and Cuban delegations were in
                            Monrovia at the same time, that some alleged leaders of the
                            demonstration had been seen in the Soviet Embassy the night before, and
                            that three officers of the Soviet Embassy had visited PAL headquarters
                            on the eve of the demonstration.</p>
                        <p>6. Proposal to increase rice prices: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> explained in detail the background of the
                            Minister of Agriculture’s proposal to increase the price of rice, and
                            the lengthy discussion of this proposal in the Cabinet and with
                            concerned groups in Liberia including the PAL. He said that despite the
                            denial of a permit to demonstrate against the proposal, <persName corresp="#p_MGB_1">Matthews</persName> and the PAL went ahead
                            anyway.</p>
                        <p>7. Organization of demonstration: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said the demonstration had caught the Liberian
                            Government by surprise. Although spear<pb facs="0167" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/>headed by unemployed toughs “made brave by dope and
                            liquor” it had clearly required considerable planning, as shown by the
                            skill with which roadblocks were thrown up and by the success with which
                            the leaders later eluded arrest. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> thanked the Secretary because the Embassy had
                            denied <persName corresp="#p_MGB_1">Matthews</persName> asylum. In
                            response to the Secretary’s question <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said the purpose of the demonstration was to
                            create a “state of anarchy” in Monrovia. In reply to <persName corresp="#p_HWC_1">Harrop</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said the demonstrators were not armed with
                            firearms.</p>
                        <p>8. Support from other governments: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> described the support Liberia had received from
                            other states. Guinea had sent a delegation on the 15th and the next day
                            had sent a second delegation accompanied by 50 troops. The total Guinean
                            strength in Monrovia was just under 300. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> did not make clear whether <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName> had requested Guinean troops
                            or not, but said that when the first group arrived <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName> “did not turn them away” and
                            implied that the second group of 220 came to complement the first.
                            President <persName corresp="#p_HF_1">Houphouet-Boigny</persName> sent a
                            message of support, food and medical supplies. At this point <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> checked himself and assured the
                            Secretary that Liberia was most grateful for U.S. medical supplies, and
                            for military assistance. The Secretary noted that U.S. military
                            equipment would arrive very shortly.</p>
                        <p>9. Request for aid: <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName>
                            recalled President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s
                            forthcoming comments to <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>
                            during and following his visit to Monrovia in April 1978 on the subject
                            of assistance.<note n="4" xml:id="d44fn4">See <ref target="#d34">Document 34</ref>.</note> He said Liberia needs a
                            “reconstruction program.” There was a good possibility that insurance
                            could cover some claims arising from the riots, but “the little man
                            needs help.” Liberia had an obligation to hold the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> summit on schedule. Liberia had two
                            specific needs: A grant to provide immediate assistance, and help to
                            repair some or all of the dols 50 million in damage caused by the riot;
                            and a long term development loan to finance projects that would take the
                            unemployed off the streets. The Secretary asked if the Liberian
                            Government had appealed to any other donor, and mentioned the African
                            Development Bank. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said
                            that thus far an appeal had been made only to the U.S., Liberia’s
                            greatest friend. He was sure the U.S. would not want to turn down its
                            closest ally in Africa, especially just before the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> summit. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> asked if the U.S. could reexamine the
                            possibilities of encouraging long term investment.</p>
                        <p>10. The Secretary replied that he thought it important to distinguish
                            between short and long term needs. Encouraging investment took
                            considerable time. He could give no assurances, but the Department and
                                <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> would examine the possibilities
                            carefully. The United States valued the special relationship. He asked
                            precisely what the Liberians thought <pb facs="0168" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> they required. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> replied that it was difficult to be specific. He
                            had come, “as a patient comes to a doctor, to be told what he
                            needs.”</p>
                        <p>11. Middle East: Picking up a complimentary comment <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> had made regarding U.S.
                            contribution to peace in the Middle East, the Secretary said we are now
                            in the second stage of the peace making process, and must deal with the
                            enormously complex Palestinian question. He said he was somewhat
                            troubled by statements made after President <persName corresp="#p_TWR_1">Tolbert</persName>’s visit to Kuwait which appeared to indicate
                            little understanding of the situation. The Camp David summit had
                            established the first and only realistic framework for dealing with this
                            extremely difficult problem, and we would appreciate support from our
                            friends. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> replied that the
                            Liberians had not expected a communique to be proposed in Kuwait, and
                            said that he had greatly watered down the original draft proposed to him
                            by the Kuwaitis.</p>
                        <p>12. <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss>: The Secretary said he thought
                            it would be disastrous and unfair if Egypt were expelled from the
                            Non-Aligned Movement. To say that Egypt does not have a right to make
                            peace to recover lost territory is shocking. <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Dennis</persName> said Liberia wished to support
                            the U.S. view, and suggested that assisting Liberia to hold the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> summit might be the best means to this
                            end.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_CWM_1"><hi rend="strong">Christopher</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>