<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-03-07T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-03-07T05:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                        <head>72. Telegram From the Embassy in Zaire to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d72fn1">Source: National Archives, RG
                                59, Central Foreign Policy File, D770077–0796. Confidential;
                                Priority; Limdis. Sent for information to Brussels, Cape Town,
                                Lagos, Lusaka, Paris, and Pretoria.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Kinshasa</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-03-07T10:00:00+00:00">March 7, 1977,
                                1000Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1914. Subj: Deputy Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> Call on President <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>.</p>
                        <p>1. Summary: During breakfast meeting with Pres <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>, Mar 5, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> discussed range of bilateral
                            issues including economic and security assistance, human rights, and
                            PanAm contract. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> also
                            reviewed current US efforts in Southern Africa and delivered message of
                            appreciation from Pres <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                            for <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>’s intervention with
                                <persName corresp="#p_AID_1">Amin</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">In telegram 47709 to Kinshasa, March 3, the
                                Department transmitted a message from <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> thanking <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> for assistance to U.S. citizens in Uganda.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770074–0264)</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> asked that <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> carry back two messages to new
                            US administration: <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> was
                            determined to implement tough measures to stabilize Zaire’s economy and,
                            in doing so, will need continued US help; he remains ready to advise and
                            support us in dealing with African problems. End summary.</p>
                        <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> and I flew to Mbandaka
                            today, Mar 5, to meet with Pres <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> for a breakfast session on board his river boat.
                            Meeting lasted one and one quarter hours. Acting <gloss target="#t_FonMin_1">FonMin</gloss> Lombo was also present.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> was in good form and
                            seemed relaxed.</p>
                        <p>3. In seating us at the breakfast table on deck, <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> jokingly said he would keep us
                            away from the hot sun in order to “protect human rights”. He then
                            started off the conversation by asking <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> what good news he had brought from
                            Washington.</p>
                        <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> expressed appreciation
                            for being received by the President, particularly at time when President
                            was busy with consultations with members of his Political Bureau. He
                            reviewed his trip in Africa thus far, observing that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> is watching developments in the Horn
                            of Africa closely in view of Ethiopian-Somalian rivalries in
                            anticipation of Djibouti’s independence. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said his next stop would be Cameroon, a country
                            with which the US enjoys excellent relations.</p>
                        <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said he considered his
                            visit to Zaire the high point of his trip and remarked that it would be
                            stating the obvious to reiterate the <pb facs="0255" n="223" xml:id="pg_223"/> particular importance the US attaches to its
                            relations with Zaire. In this connection, if the President were
                            interested, he would propose to discuss various aspects of our
                            relationship. The President nodded support. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> started by delivering to <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> Pres <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s message of appreciation for
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>’s intervention with
                                <persName corresp="#p_AID_1">Idi Amin</persName> in our behalf.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> read the message
                            carefully and expressed his appreciation.</p>
                        <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said that the new
                            administration in Washington intends to continue its assistance programs
                            to Zaire and noted that we had just submitted to Congress proposals for
                            economic assistance to Zaire for fiscal year 1978. Referring to useful
                            meetings held the day before with the Governor of the Central Bank and
                            the Minister of Finance,<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3">In telegram 1922
                                from Kinshasa, March 7, the Embassy reported on <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName>’s March 4 meeting with
                                Zaire’s Acting Foreign Minister, the Governor of the Central Bank,
                                and the Minister of Finance. (National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, D770077–0874)</note> he said he was impressed
                            with the program the Zairian Govt has proposed to further stabilize its
                            economy. This program, he observed, is an essential precondition to
                            eliciting substantial international economic and financial assistance to
                            Zaire in the years ahead.</p>
                        <p>7. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> broke in at this point
                            to ask that <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> convey to
                            Pres <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> and Secty <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> the following message: Zaire
                            still has serious economic problems and <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> is determined to take all necessary steps,
                            however tough they may be, to implement new stabilization measures and
                            thereby effect the country’s economic recovery. In doing so, Zaire will
                            need all the help it can get and must therefore look to the US for
                            continued assistance.</p>
                        <p>8. With regard to military assistance, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> noted that I had already informed the President
                            of the administration’s intention to provide Zaire with $30 million in
                            credits for fiscal year 1978, an undertaking which had been submitted
                            for congressional approval.<note n="4" xml:id="d72fn4">In telegram 41170
                                to multiple posts, February 24, the Department transmitted the
                                proposed <gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> funding levels for
                                individual countries for FY 1978, including $30 million for Zaire.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770063–0639)</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> remarked that Congress’
                            increasing role in foreign policy requires much closer consultation
                            between the executive and legislative branches on foreign policy
                            matters, and it will therefore be necessary to work more closely than
                            ever with Congress in underlining the importance of our continuing our
                            military assistance program to Zaire. He said that, as part of this
                            effort, I had been asked to return to Washington in a couple of days for
                            consultations. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> stressed
                            the continuing need for military aid, referring to the hundreds of tanks
                            in neighboring Angola and in Congo as well. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> noted that, as the President was aware, we had
                            included some tanks in our assistance package for this fiscal year.</p>
                        <pb facs="0256" n="224" xml:id="pg_224"/>
                        <p>9. With regard to military assistance, I recalled that Secretary
                            Kissinger had promised to encourage our European allies to explore ways
                            of providing more help to Zaire and that subsequently, last January, US
                            defense experts had held consultations with the Belgians<note n="5" xml:id="d72fn5">In telegram 167 from Brussels, January 7, the
                                Embassy reported on exploratory talks with the Belgians on military
                                assistance to Zaire. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770007–0570)</note> and the French.<note n="6" xml:id="d72fn6">In telegram 845 from Paris, January 11, the Embassy
                                reported on consultations with the French on military assistance to
                                Zaire. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770010–0515)</note> I said that these discussions had proved very
                            useful in the sense of promoting better coordination of our respective
                            efforts and that we were generally encouraged by the attitudes of our
                            European allies. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> said
                            that during his recent visit to Brussels the Belgian Defense Minister
                            had mentioned these consultations to him. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> added that he was concerned by political
                            developments in Belgium and the possibility the current government might
                            be changed.</p>
                        <p>10. On the political level, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> continued, Washington continues to have high
                            regard for President <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> and
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Young</persName>’s meeting with
                            the President in Lagos was an excellent first step in establishing close
                            contacts between the new administration and the GOZ.<note n="7" xml:id="d72fn7">In telegram 1462 from Lagos, February 8, the Embassy
                                reported on <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Young</persName>’s
                                conversation with <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>,
                                during which they focused their discussion on the situation in
                                Rhodesia. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770075–0679) For <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Young</persName>’s
                                report on his mission to Africa, see <ref target="#d2">Document
                                    2</ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said that Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Young</persName> had much appreciated
                            the opportunity of meeting with <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>. Not only does the US esteem the role that
                            President <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> can play in our
                            bilateral relationship, but we value the moderate and constructive role
                            that he has played and can continue to play in Africa.</p>
                        <p>11. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said there were two
                            other matters involving our bilateral relations that he wanted to
                            mention. First, he said that the new administration attaches a great
                            deal of importance to human rights considerations in its relations with
                            countries around the world. Accordingly, programs of bilateral
                            assistance would depend to a certain extent on how recipient governments
                            protect human rights. I interjected to say that Congress also is deeply
                            interested in this issue and has asked the administration to submit to
                            it public reports on the status of human rights in many individual
                            countries, including Zaire, where we of course have important assistance
                            programs. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> went on to say
                            that President <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> should be
                            fully aware of this factor in our foreign policy, although he did not
                            think that this should pose a problem in our relations with Zaire.</p>
                        <pb facs="0257" n="225" xml:id="pg_225"/>
                        <p>12. Addressing the issue of human rights, <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> expressed confidence in Zaire’s situation. He
                            said the Zairian people were attached to their leader because they knew
                            he was doing his best to lead and develop the country and to improve
                            their lot. So long as there was this attachment by the people there
                            should be no problem regarding human rights.</p>
                        <p>13. As his final point in discussing our bilateral relationship,
                                <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> alluded to the news
                            which had come out during his stay in Kinshasa regarding the Zairian
                            Government’s decision to discontinue its contract with PanAm to manage
                            and operate Air Zaire. He said he was “surprised” at this decision since
                            it seemed to be in our mutual interest to expand all possible areas of
                            American-Zairian relations.</p>
                        <p>14. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> responded with lengthy
                            explanation of why he found it impossible to renew the PanAm contract,
                            making essentially same points he had previously made to me: i.e., after
                            six years PanAm’s efforts had accomplished next to nothing; contract was
                            tilted in favor of PanAm’s interests vis-a-vis those of Air Zaire;
                            contract was too expensive in light of Zaire’s budgetary and
                            [garble—fiscal?] crunch, with too much evidence of high-living by
                            expatriate employees; those foreigners still needed should be hired
                            individually by Air Zaire, but not under contract with another airline.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> said he had nothing
                            against the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>; but he had concluded
                            it was in Zaire’s sovereign interest to terminate the contract with
                            PanAm. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> acknowledged that
                            it was of course a decision for Zaire to make. I said I understood PanAm
                            would start immediately to remove its personnel and in doing so would
                            make every effort to minimize any possible damage or disruption to Air
                            Zaire’s operations. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>
                            indicated he appreciated PanAm’s intention to terminate its services
                            “correctly”.</p>
                        <p>15. Turning to area issues, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> brought the President up to date concerning our
                            approach to resolution of the Southern African problems. Inter alia, he
                            made the following points:</p>
                        <p>(A) The new administration has publicly indicated its determination that
                            the US continue to play an active role in facilitating negotiated
                            settlements;</p>
                        <p>(B) The British “formula” for assuming an active role in the transition
                            government still seems to provide a basis for bringing the parties
                            together;</p>
                        <p>(C) Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> last month
                            issued an unequivocal statement signaling the <persName corresp="#p_SRP_1">Ian Smith</persName> government that the US under
                            no circumstances would come to Rhodesia’s assistance if Rhodesia did not
                            cooperate in efforts to move rapidly to independence and majority
                                rule;<note n="8" xml:id="d72fn8">Reference is presumably to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s February 10
                                statement before the Subcommittee on African Affairs of the Senate
                                Foreign Relations Committee. See Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 28, 1977, pp.
                                170–172.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0258" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                        <p>(D) This administration has also announced its intention to marshal its
                            resources in an effort to repeal the Byrd amendment;<note n="9" xml:id="d72fn9">The Byrd amendment to the Military Procurement Act
                                (1971), allowed the importation of Rhodesian chrome in violation of
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> sanctions.</note></p>
                        <p>(E) Consultations with the British last week were designed to regenerate
                            the negotiating momentum and our approach to the problem is still based
                            on the assumption that the alternative of protracted bloody warfare is
                            totally unacceptable.<note n="10" xml:id="d72fn10">See <ref target="frus1977-80v16#d138"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XVI, Southern Africa,
                                    Document 138</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>16. With regard to Namibia, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> said that there has been no movement in the last
                            few months but the US continues to believe South Africa is prepared to
                            make some basic concessions which, if met by some flexibility on the
                            part of <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss>, could produce results.
                                <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> stressed that the
                            fact we are working with South Africa in resolving problems of Rhodesia
                            and Namibia should in no way be misinterpreted as US support for
                            apartheid. On the contrary, our policy continues to be based on strong
                            opposition to apartheid and the new administration has already expressed
                            strong views in this regard. At the same time, US policy is based on the
                            premise that top priority should be given to resolving the pressing
                            issues of Rhodesia and Namibia.</p>
                        <p>17. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> interjected that he
                            fully agreed with this set of priorities and noted basic differences
                            between problems of Rhodesia and South Africa. The whites in Rhodesia
                            were clearly a colonialist minority and there is no question that the
                            country should move quickly to rule by the black majority. In South
                            Africa, on the other hand, the whites had just as much of a claim to
                            staying there as the blacks. The institution of apartheid was the
                            problem, and efforts should therefore be directed toward changing it. On
                            Rhodesia, <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> noted that
                            Zaire opposed exclusion of any of major Zimbabwe nationalist groups and
                            had been instrumental in convincing the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> not to endorse solely the Patriotic Front.</p>
                        <p>18. On Angola, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> recalled
                            that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> announced
                            some weeks ago that the US is prepared to consider normalizing relations
                            with that country, but, frankly, we do not expect this to be an easy
                            process. We are approaching this matter with great care. In response to
                                <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName>’s query as to
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>’s views on the
                            internal situation in Angola, <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> said it is evident the <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> regime is split essentially between those favoring the
                            Soviets and Cubans and those opposing them. In any case, the Angolans
                            themselves are not in control of their own affairs. He thought Lara is
                            the man to watch as being potentially one of the most influential
                            members of the regime.</p>
                        <pb facs="0259" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/>
                        <p>19. I raised the question of Zaire’s relations with Angola, noting that
                            Luanda seems finally to have acknowledged Zaire’s formal recognition of
                            the <gloss target="#t_PRA_1">PRA</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> attributed this acknowledgement to his own
                            rebuttal of Luanda’s charges that forces from Zaire had attacked across
                            the border, noting also that in his rebuttal he had called <persName corresp="#p_NAA_1">Neto</persName>’s bluff by endorsing <persName corresp="#p_NAA_1">Neto</persName>’s appeal for an <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> investigation. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> expressed doubt, however, that
                            Angola’s acknowledgement of Zaire’s recognition meant that Angola would
                            soon be willing to move seriously toward improving relations.</p>
                        <p>20. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> said that during his
                            recent visit to Nigeria President <persName corresp="#p_OO_1">Obasanjo</persName> had offered to help in normalizing
                            Zairian-Angolan relations by talking to <persName corresp="#p_NAA_1">Neto</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> had
                            agreed and the Nigerians did in fact elicit assurances that the <gloss target="#t_PRA_1">PRA</gloss> wished to improve relations. However,
                                <persName corresp="#p_OO_1">Obasanjo</persName> had not been aware
                            of all the charges <persName corresp="#p_NAA_1">Neto</persName> was at
                            the same time making publicly against Zaire, and Nigeria’s efforts had
                            not accomplished much. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName>
                            said he was interested in the President’s allusion to better relations
                            between Zaire and Nigeria and wondered if it would be correct to say
                            that these relations are now good. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> replied in the affirmative.</p>
                        <p>21. <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> closed the
                            conversation by asking <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> to
                            convey another message to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>: while Zaire may not be the predominant leader in
                            Africa, it has the capability of exerting strong influence and—just as
                            he helped the previous administration to avoid or resolve certain
                            problems in its relations with Africa—so <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> remains ready to continue to advise and support
                            the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> as it pursues its African
                            policies. <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName> thanked the
                            President and said he would convey this assurance of continued
                            cooperation to the new administration.</p>
                        <p>2. Comment: <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> was obviously
                            pleased to have this chance to talk to <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Seelye</persName>, the second high-ranking official to come out
                            from Washington since the new administration took office. Without
                            resorting to the hard sell, <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName> nevertheless made his message clear: he needs and
                            wants our continued economic and military assistance, and is at the same
                            time ready to continue cooperating with us on a spectrum of issues where
                            US interests are involved. Certainly such is the case in Southern
                            Africa, where—although his capacity to influence events is clearly
                                limited—<persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>’s views and
                            objectives remain generally in line with ours and where he is willing to
                            work at least privately with other Africans in support of moderate
                            solutions.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_CWL_1"><hi rend="strong">Cutler</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>