<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-05T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-05T16:00:00-05:00" n="271" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/11974: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Third Secretary of Embassy in China</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allison</hi></persName>)
                                <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Aboard</hi>
                                    U. S. S. “<hi rend="smallcaps">Oahu</hi>,”</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-05T16:00:00">January 5,
                                    1938—4 p.m.</date><lb/>[Received January 5—3:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>4. Arrived Wuhu at 10:30 a.m. at the end of a severe air raid carried out
                            by Chinese planes. Nine Chinese heavy bombers dropped approximately 17
                            bombs on the airfield and an unknown number at four different places in
                            the city of Wuhu. No American property was damaged and no Americans
                            hurt.</p>
                        <pb facs="0224" n="220" xml:id="pg_220"/>
                        <p>I went ashore with staff and while Espy and McFadyen<note n="98" xml:id="d271fn98">James Espy, Vice Consul, and A. A. McFadyen,
                                clerk.</note> inspected American property elsewhere in company of
                            Reverend L. R. Craighill, I interviewed Dr. R. E. Brown of the Wuhu
                            General Hospital. According to Dr. Brown, during first week of
                            occupation Japanese troops engaged in “ruthless treatment and slaughter
                            of civilians and wanton looting and destruction” of private property in
                            the city. Persons of foreigners have been respected but where property
                            was left unguarded it has usually been pilfered. Japanese Army, Navy and
                            Consular officials called on him separately to apologize for the tearing
                            of an American flag from hospital junk on December 13th. Two American
                            nurses, Miss Frances Culley and Mrs. Wilma May, hope to leave Wuhu for
                            Shanghai January 8th on the steamship <hi rend="italic">Whangpoo.</hi></p>
                        <p>Standard Vacuum and Texas installations unharmed. Standard installation
                            entered and 14½ tons fuel oil taken by Japanese Navy for which receipt
                            was left. Offices in city of both companies intact but completely
                            rifled. Small safe in Standard Vacuum office broken open and contents
                            gone but cabinet safe unopened. Dollar Company building intact but
                            offices pilfered. Property of American Church and Christian Advent
                            Mission intact and all American occupants safe.</p>
                        <p>Will submit detailed report by mail.<note n="99" xml:id="d271fn99">Not
                                printed.</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">Oahu</hi> left Wuhu at 2 p.m. and as we are returning,
                            large fires are visible all along south bank of river presumably of
                            Japanese origin.</p>
                        <p>Sent to Embassy [at] Hankow, repeated Shanghai.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Allison</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>