<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Consul General at Hankow ( (Josselyn))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-01-19T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-01-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-19T18:00:00-05:00" n="303"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.115/132: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Consul General at Hankow</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Josselyn</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 19, 1938—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Your January 14, 10 a.m. According to the Department’s records the Central
                    Aircraft Manufacturing Company, a China Trade Act corporation organized by three
                    American aviation companies, entered into a contract with the Chinese Government
                    under date December 8, 1933, under the terms of which the company agreed to
                    build and equip a factory near Hangchow for the manufacture, assembly, and
                    repair of airplanes, and to furnish American supervision and technical
                    personnel; and the Chinese Government agreed to bear all expenses, other than
                    first costs, of the maintenance and operation of the factory, and to insure
                    against all insurable hazards including war. The contract also provided that the
                    factory shall become vested in the Chinese Government at the end of 5 years, and
                    contained a reservation of the right of that Government to take over the factory
                    at any time within the 5-year period. If this or any similar contract is
                    applicable to the factory at Hankow, it would seem that the factory should be
                    considered as fundamentally a Chinese enterprise involving no substantial
                    American interest which can properly claim American protection.</p>
                <p>Copies of the contract referred to above are on file at Peiping and Nanking,
                    detailed information in regard to which may possibly be procurable from the
                    Embassy staff at Hankow.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
