<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="411" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d411">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1164 University of Shanghai/21</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of
                                Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ballantine</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With the Counselor of the Japanese
                                Embassy</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Suma</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-05-05">May 5, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Suma referred to Mr. Ballantine’s conversation with him of April
                                18<note n="7" xml:id="d411fn7">Memorandum of conversation not
                                printed.</note> in regard to the question of the vacating by the
                            Japanese military of the property of the University of Shanghai. Mr.
                            Suma said that following that conversation the Embassy had telegraphed
                                <pb facs="0318" n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/> the Foreign Office and
                            urged, in view of the wide interest throughout this country in the
                            University, that this matter be given prompt attention. Mr. Suma said
                            that a reply had now been received from the Foreign Office to the effect
                            that it had taken this matter up with the military authorities, who
                            indicated to the Foreign Office that the Japanese army desired to
                            purchase the property belonging to the University and were taking up the
                            matter with the American representatives of the University at Shanghai.
                            Mr. Ballantine expressed surprise and said that he had not heard of such
                            an approach by the Japanese military authorities to the representatives
                            of the mission and he would therefore make inquiries regarding this
                            point. He asked Mr. Suma, however, whether in the event that the mission
                            did not wish to sell the Japanese military authorities would vacate the
                            property. Mr. Suma did not have any comments to make on this point. Mr.
                            Suma said, however, in this general connection that the Japanese
                            military had indicated that they would vacate by the end of May the
                            property belonging to a Baptist mission school near Chapei.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>