<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="626" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d626">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1115/3589: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lockhart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-09-03T13:00:00+08:00">September 3, 1938—1
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1186. During August this office at the request of American citizens and
                            organizations applied to the Japanese authorities for passes to
                            restricted areas for 101 persons, of which 46 were received. Also during
                            August this office “chopped” 61 applications of American citizens or
                            organizations for permits from the Japanese authorities to remove cargo
                            and other property from Hongkew and Yangtzepoo. Many of these
                            applications were for August permits providing for the organization
                            concerned to remove its goods during the month in accordance with the
                            requirements of its business. It is believed that practically all of
                            these applications were granted as no notice of any rejection has come
                            to the attention of this Consulate General.</p>
                        <p>The above figures cover original applications. They do not include
                            reapplications or follow-up work.</p>
                        <p>The difficulty of obtaining personal passes for the interior, especially
                            sections of this consular district north of the Tsung River, has
                            increased at least temporarily. A Japanese consular official stated that
                            as the Japanese military authorities have abolished or decreased many of
                            their garrisons in the interior in order to utilize as many <pb facs="0468" n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/> as possible of the available
                            troops for the drive on Hankow, Chinese guerrillas have become very
                            active in many parts of the interior and consequently the Japanese
                            authorities consider such areas dangerous and are not issuing passes for
                            travel in them.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Peiping and Nanking, code text by mail to Tokyo.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lockhart</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>