<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Third Secretary of Embassy in China (
                    (Drumright))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d639</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">639</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="639"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d639">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.76/105</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Third Secretary of Embassy
                        in China</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Drumright</hi>)<note n="91"
                        xml:id="d639fn91">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Ambassador in
                        China in his despatch No. 75, September 17; received November 7.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-09-15">September 15,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Drumright called on Dr. S. S. Liu at the Foreign Office today and discussed
                    the radio situation at Shanghai, particularly with <pb facs="0480" n="476"
                        xml:id="pg_476"/> reference to the numerous protests of the Foreign Office
                    in regard to the arrangements entered into by Mackay Radio and Telegraph Company
                    and R. C. A. Communications, Inc., with the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Mr. Drumright referred to various notes received from the Foreign Office on this
                    subject, including the note dated September 10, 1938, and stated that the
                    substance of these notes had been or were being communicated to the Department
                    of State, the Consulate General at Shanghai, and the American radio companies in
                    question. Mr. Drum-right briefly reviewed the events leading up to the present
                    situation at Shanghai, including the withdrawal of Chinese troops and
                    authorities from the Shanghai area, the action of the Japanese in seeking a
                    measure of control over the radio communications service at Shanghai by virtue
                    of their military occupation of the area, and the difficult situation in which
                    the foreign radio companies would have found themselves faced should they have
                    failed to take Japanese desires into consideration. Consequently, in order to
                    preserve their interests and property and to maintain a constant radio service
                    with the outside world, a matter of vital interest to people in China and abroad
                    alike, the foreign radio companies, after much consideration and consultation,
                    had decided upon their own responsibility to continue the radio service at
                    Shanghai. They had, according to information available, arrived at a temporary
                        <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> arrangement with the Japanese in order to
                    meet the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> situation existing at Shanghai. It was
                    difficult to perceive how the foreign radio companies at Shanghai could have
                    pursued any other course, for to have refused to cooperate with the Japanese as
                    the military masters of the Shanghai area would have resulted in difficulties
                    and possible loss of investments, not to mention disruption of essential radio
                    service.</p>
                <p>Mr. Drumright hoped that Dr. Liu would bring the realities of the radio situation
                    at Shanghai, as outlined above, to the attention of the Ministry of
                    Communications and other competent organs, with a view to closing the case.</p>
                <p>Dr. Liu replied that he would, of course, bring the above-mentioned views to the
                    attention of the Ministry of Communications, but expressed regret that the
                    American authorities seemed unwilling to cause the American radio companies to
                    sever communications with the Japanese. He considered the activities of the
                    American radio companies to constitute a breach of China’s sovereignty and to be
                    inimical to the traditional friendship existing between the United States and
                    China. He requested that these views be brought to the attention of the
                    Ambassador and the Department of State.</p>
                <p>Mr. Drumright replied that the views of the Chinese Government, as outlined by
                    Dr. Liu, would be brought to the attention of the competent American
                    authorities. He stated that it was, as Dr. Liu was <pb facs="0481" n="477"
                        xml:id="pg_477"/> aware, the desire of the American Government to respect
                    the sovereignty of China but that it appeared that the preservation of Chinese
                    territory and sovereignty seemed to rest with the Chinese. The present situation
                    had arisen out of the occupation of Shanghai by the Japanese who exercised <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> control there. In order to prevent disruption of
                    the normal processes of life, it seemed necessary to recognize the actualities
                    of the situation and to be governed accordingly.</p>
                <p>In concluding the discussion, Dr. Liu, in response to a question from Mr.
                    Drumright, stated that to his knowledge only one foreign radio company—a
                    Netherlands organization—had severed radio communications with Shanghai. When
                    questioned whether similar protests had been lodged concerning the use by the
                    Japanese of the railways in which there were foreign interests, Dr. Liu stated
                    that he was not aware that protests had been made in connection therewith. He
                    stated it to be his opinion, however, that the cases of the radio companies and
                    the railways were not analogous.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. F. Drumright</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
