<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d769</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">769</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-12-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recg3iRrscBAKUZil" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85095095"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Opium</term>
                    <term ref="recXIobv9WaQHpI49" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics">Narcotics traffic</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec99jdV9ZgPMHimw" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85089815"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Narcotics</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-12-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="769"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d769">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.C1197/1282</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3522</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-12-20">December 20,
                            1938</date>.<lb/>[Received January 9, 1939.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    the Department’s confidential instruction no. 1574 of September 12, 1938, with
                    its enclosures<note n="99" xml:id="d769fn99">Enclosures not printed.</note>
                    (File No. 500.C1197/1240), relating to the drug situation in China as reported
                    in the statements of the American representative at the last session of the
                    Opium Advisory Committee at Geneva. The Embassy has carefully noted, and
                    appreciates, the background <pb facs="0574" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/>
                    information and the Department’s views as set forth in that instruction.</p>
                <p>The Embassy has delayed its reply to the instruction under acknowledgment in the
                    expectation that, without soliciting it, the Japanese authorities would make
                    orally or otherwise to the Embassy some explanation or statement further in
                    regard to their attitude on the situation in China as exposed by the American
                    delegate. Although a member of the Embassy staff has had on many occasions
                    conversations on other matters pertaining to the narcotics traffic with the
                    official of the Foreign Office in charge of that work, no reference has been
                    made by that official to the situation in China or to the expose of our
                    delegate.</p>
                <p>It has been noted, however, that there has been a slackening in cooperation on
                    the part of the Japanese authorities since they first called our attention, as
                    reported in the Embassy’s telegram No. 400, June 22, 6 p.m., to the statements
                    of our delegate at Geneva. Though there have been only two or three cases of a
                    minor nature and the Turevic case since that time we have noted that the
                    Japanese authorities have not been as prompt as heretofore in replying to our
                    inquiries.</p>
                <p>In this relation and with respect to the question of undertaking to consult with
                    the Japanese authorities in advance before giving publicity to information
                    concerning the illicit traffic conducted by Japanese in China and the illicit
                    traffic to the United States from the areas in China controlled by the Japanese,
                    the Embassy refers to its opinion given in the penultimate paragraph of
                    confidential despatch No. 3181 of August 11, 1938,<note n="1" xml:id="d769fn1"
                        >Not printed.</note> to the effect that we are not in a position to
                    determine whether the advantages derived from unrestricted publication of
                    information with regard to illicit Japanese activities in China are greater than
                    the advantages which flow from the effective cooperation of the Japanese
                    Government in preventing the illicit shipment of narcotics to the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>We desire to point out, however, that the Japanese authorities here in Japan with
                    whom we have had to deal in connection with the illicit traffic in narcotics
                    have shown a sincere desire to cooperate in the suppression of this traffic.
                    Just what influence or control they may have over their nationals or the
                    military authorities in China it is not possible to say, but we do believe that
                    if the Japanese authorities here in Japan could first be furnished in entire
                    confidence, as in the case of all our local dealings, with whatever information
                    we have regarding the activities in the illicit traffic in narcotics of their
                    nationals in China they might be in a better position to take some action
                    vis-à-vis the military authorities.</p>
                <p>The military authorities in China are not likely to be affected by publicity in
                    connection with the narcotics traffic any more than they <pb facs="0575" n="571"
                        xml:id="pg_571"/> appear to be sensitive to publicity given to other
                    features of their activities in China. On the other hand the local authorities
                    with whom we have to deal are sensitive to the adverse effect of such publicity
                    and if placed in a position where direct approach could be made to the higher
                    military command in Tokyo before the military in China are aware that their
                    activities are the subject of protest, some good results might be expected.</p>
                <p>It was with the foregoing in mind that the suggestion was made that the Japanese
                    authorities here be furnished in confidence with information regarding the
                    activities of their nationals in China in connection with the illicit traffic in
                    narcotics, in accordance with the agreement referred to in the copy of the
                    letter from the Director of the Treaty Bureau dated July 30, 1938, enclosed with
                    our confidential despatch No. 3181 of August 11, 1938.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d769fn2">Neither printed.</note> The suggestion was not intended to
                    convey the idea that action be taken in derogation of the Narcotics Limitation
                    Convention of 1931, nor was it our intention to suggest that information should
                    be suppressed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
