<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d813</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">813</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-03-08T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-03-08T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-08T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-08T05:00:00-05:00" n="813"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d813">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894.512/40: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-03-08T19:00:00+09:00"
                            >March 8, 1938—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received March 8—12:09 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>158. Our 154, March 7, 8 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The following points suggest themselves in considering a rejoinder to the
                        Japanese reply: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Our contention that the taxes are inapplicable to American
                                citizens does not rest on the fact that the proceeds are to be paid
                                into a special fund set up for meeting military expenditures but on
                                the fact that the revenues are to be applied to military
                                expenditures. The reference in our representations to the special
                                fund was designed to establish that fact.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The hostilities with China created the need for the additional
                                revenues now being provided by these taxes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>There is no basis for the Japanese contention that as the taxes
                                were created by normal legislative processes and assessed and
                                collected by the regularly established agencies of the Government
                                they cannot be regarded as military exactions or contributions. If
                                such interpretation were valid, the provision of the relevant treaty
                                provision which was obviously intended to be a safeguard against
                                levies for military purposes could be readily circumvented.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The British Ambassador is about to make representations similar to ours. I
                        understand that he will call attention to the exemption enjoyed by Japanese
                        residents in Great Britain from taxes the revenues of which are being
                        applied to the British rearmament program. Comment along the following lines
                        might be added:</item>
                </list>
                <p>The American Government firmly believes in the justice of the assertion that the
                    taxes are not applicable to American citizens and its position is not in any way
                    susceptible of alteration by the statement of the Japanese Government that the
                    British Government in a previous instance took a different position. As the
                    Japanese Government however appears to believe that the views of the British
                    Government <pb facs="0621" n="617" xml:id="pg_617"/> afford grounds for the
                    contention that American citizens are liable to these taxes, the Japanese
                    Government will no doubt be disposed to withdraw that contention in the light of
                    the fact that the views of the British Government in the instant case coincide
                    with those of the American Government in taking exception to the application of
                    the taxes to their respective nationals.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
