<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Asboth to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recPwjhmSWu0ZTtDD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005657"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fertility</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recTLLF5fbKMAJTYL" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136284"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">TOW</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Active measures</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="127"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Asboth</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 45.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Buenos Ayres,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-09-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 25, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In consequence of the wanton attack made upon the
                    vice-president of the Argentine Republic by the Nation Argentine newspaper,
                    reported in my despatch No. 43 of the 12th instant, which was the immediate
                    cause of a change in the cabinet denoting a very important modification in the
                    policy of the government, I deemed it proper to manifest to Dr. Paz, the
                    vice-president, by an official letter, the indignation with which I viewed the
                    occurrence, and accordingly addressed myself to him in the following terms:</p>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Buenos Ayres, September</hi> 17, 1867.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Watching with interest, although from a sick bed,
                    the daily course of political events in the river Plata, I have seen with
                    surprise and sorrow the attack made by the Nacion Argentina upon your excellency
                    while in charge of the highest trust of the nation, and I regret exceedingly
                    that I am unable to express in person to your excellency how emphatically I
                    condemn so wanton an act.</p>
                <p>Your excellency’s standing in public as well as in private life is, however, too
                    lofty, and the unbounded confidence and sincere esteem for your excellency in
                    the hearts of the people at large is too strong to admit of any other issue to
                    such an aggression but its recoil on the heads of those who attempt it. The mass
                    of the people, natives as well as foreigners, is with you and against your
                    assailants.</p>
                <p>While, therefore, assuring your excellency again in my official capacity of the
                    special regard of the government and people of the United States, I beg
                    respectfully to express my own confident expectation that the measures taken by
                    your excellency on this occasion will not fail to promote and secure the best
                    interests of the Argentine Republic, as well as of the La Plata and Parana
                    regions at large.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your excelleny’s obedient servant,</p>
                <p rend="right">A. ASBOTH.</p>
                <p>His Excellency Señor Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Don Marcos Paz,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Vice-President of the Republic, in Charge of the National
                        Executive Power.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I received yesterday in reply from the vice-president a letter, of which the
                    following is a translation, and I beg to enclose a copy, marked A, of the
                    original Spanish:</p>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Ayres,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 23, 1887.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The words of your excellency, to which I attach
                    great importance, both for the mighty standing of the country your excellency
                    represents, for your excellency’s own personal worth, and for the sympathy which
                    I profess for the people and government of the United States, have given me
                    great satisfaction.</p>
                <p>The justice meted out by worthy and enlightened men is a healing compensation for
                    the injuries which evil disposed people often sew in the path of public men.</p>
                <p>I truly thank your excellency for your letter of the 17th, and assure you that I
                    am, with the most perfect consideration, your excellency’s obedient servant,</p>
                <p rend="right">MARCOS PAZ.</p>
                <p>His Excellency Gen. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Asboth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The change in the cabinet, as given in my report No. 42 of the 10th instant,
                    replacing Señor de Elizalde as minister for foreign affairs by Doctor Don
                    Marcelino Ugarte, and Señor Costa as minister for justice, religion, and
                    education by Doctor Don José E. Uriburn, leaves no doubt of an approaching
                    modification in the policy of the Argentine government more beneficial, I hope,
                    to the general interest of this distressed republic.</p>
                <p>The rumors of peace in connection with the prolonged stay of Mr. Gould, the
                    secretary of the British legation in Paraguay, as alluded to in my report No. 43
                    of the 12th instant, and his repeated visits to President Lopez’s camp, as well
                    as to the headquarters of General Mitre and Marshal de Caxias, are gaining more
                    consistence; indeed the principal conditions as a base for a peace treaty
                    purporting to be already approved by the commanders of the several contending
                    armies, and to have been referred for final decision to their respective
                    governments, <pb facs="0305" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> are given with quite an
                    official air, well calculated to make the Argentine people fully believe in the
                    realization of what they are so anxiously longing for, viz., the speedy
                    restoration of peace, even at the risk of the dissolution of the triple
                    alliance.</p>
                <p>For myself, however, I see too much mystery involved in so sudden a mediation of
                    a single European power, applied <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> at the seat of
                    war without preliminary official support, after the most formal offers of
                    friendly mediation for the termination of this bloody war had been made by the
                    United States of America and the Pacific republics to all the respective
                    governments of the several contending parties, and had been emphatically
                    rejected by the allies, to be able in the absence of anything like substantial
                    proof to attach much weight to these flying rumors.</p>
                <p>The following are the conditions as a base for a treaty of peace published in the
                    Tribuna and the Standard:</p>
                <p rend="center">PEACE WITH PARAGUAY CONFIRMED.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Terms of treaty the same.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Tribuna published a bulletin yesterday evening confirming in almost every
                    particular the bases of peace as given in our paper of Saturday. It is a
                    remarkable coincidence that the Tribuna received a telegram from M. Video, and a
                    letter from the seat of war, simultaneously, announcing the terms of arrangement
                    in almost the same words. As our colleague takes the liberty of stating that our
                    terms were not the correct ones, we now place the Tribuna and Standard versions
                    side by side, for comparison; the difference is indeed very trifling:</p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>TRIBUNA.</cell>
                        <cell>STANDARD.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1. The allied forces shall retire from Parauguay on the ratification
                            of this treaty.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 1. The allied army immediately evacates Paraguay, and the
                            Brazilian fleet the Paraguayan waters.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2. Lopez to retire to Europe, and delegate his power to vice-president
                            of Paraguay, according to the constitution of that country.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 2. Marshal Francisco Solano Lopez, President of Paraguay and
                            commander-in-chief of the Paraguayan forces, resigns the post of
                            President to the vice-president, and that of commander-in-chief to
                            General Barrios, and he, the said marshal, at once leaves for Europe for
                            the term of two years from the date of the treaty.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3. Paraguay abandons all claim to the Gran Chaco and Misiones, and
                            evacuates Matto Grosso.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 3. Paraguay yields up her claims to all and every portion or
                            portions of the Gran Chaco territory.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4. The navigation of the rivers is declared free to the flags of all
                            nations.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 4. The free navigation of the rivers, from their source to the
                            ocean, is granted, acknowledged and ratified by Paraguay and theallied
                            powers, and said free navigation to beguaranteed by two European powers,
                            (supposed England and Prussia.)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5. The question of limits with Brazil to be settled by the new
                            Paraguayan government, in case of difficulty, by the arbitration of a
                            neutral power.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 5. The question of limits between Brazil and Paraguay to be
                            referred to the arbitraortion of a neutral power.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6. Paraguay is not responsible for the expenses of the allies.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 6. The expenses of the war to be borne by the various
                            belligerents respectively.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7. All prisoners of war to be set at liberty.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 7. Prisoners of war of all grades to be exchanged without
                            ransom.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8. Paraguay declares that she made war in self-defence, but, seeing
                            her independence now safe, admits that justice was not with her but with
                            the allies.</cell>
                        <cell>Art 8. No claims for indemnity to be made or admitted by any of the
                            belligerents.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>9. The independence of Paraguay is guaranteed.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 9. The obstructions in the river Para guay to be removed by the
                            Paraguayans within three months from the ratification of this
                            treaty.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10. Each of the belligerents is to send a diplomatic agent to settle
                            all questions pending before the war.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 10. Each of the belligerent powers engages to send a diplomatic
                            agent or representative to conclude a treaty of commerce and
                            amity.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0306" n="236" xml:id="pg_236"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>11. (This article treats of the various Paraguayan fortresses.)</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 11. The free navigation of the river Paraguay does not import the
                            admission of vessels of war.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>12. The Paraguayan army to be reduced to a peace footing.</cell>
                        <cell>Art. 12. An armistice shall be at once concluded, and the ratification
                            of this treaty duly exchanged with the least possible delay.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>These terms were brought by Mr. Gould from Lopez, and accepted (in the
                            bulk) by General Mitre and Marquis Caxias, who have referred them to
                            their respective governments.</cell>
                        <cell>The above terms, “mutatis mutandis,” may be relied on as the draught
                            at present en route for Rio.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Notwithstanding the rumors of preparation for peace, the Paraguayan war still
                    drags along. There is no armistice, and fighting in the palm and orange grove,
                    on the line of communication of the allies, continues with increased severity
                    and daily loss of-life.</p>
                <p>The Brazilian iron-clad fleet rests still at anchor, as before, between Humaita
                    and Curupaiti, bombarding Humaita, without, however, doing much harm to the
                    fortress, but affording ample time to the Paraguayans to hem in more and more
                    the Brazilian fleet in their isolated position, and to secure daily a fuller
                    control over the river above and below Humaita.</p>
                <p>By her Majesty’s steamer Dotorel, daily expected from Paraguay, I hope to receive
                    interesting news for your department from our minister in Asuncion.</p>
                <p>The condition of the interior provinces is again very alarming. Reactionary
                    leaders, Saá, Videla, and Varela, are all on their march to invade the Argentine
                    confederation from Chili and Bolivia with troops newly organized and well
                    armed.</p>
                <p>For further particulars I respectfully beg to refer to enclosure B, my daily
                    memoranda of political events in the river Plata from the 13th to the 23d of
                    September, 1867.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. ASBOTH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Daily memoranda of political events in the River Plata from the 13th to
                        the 23th September, 1867.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 13.—The senate of congress sat yesterday in
                        secret session, and ratified sundry stipulations in connection with the
                        triple alliance treaty.</p>
                    <p>The Montevidean government has published a decree prohibiting subalterns
                        obeying any orders save those of the chief of police, which seems to imply
                        that there is something wrong with the military men. Governor Flores, it is
                        said, is about to visit the country districts, and has absolutely and
                        positively declined to give another man to the war. The Tribuna states that
                        its candidate for the presidency of the Argentine Republic is Sor Sarmiento,
                        and not Governor Alsina.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 14.—The following relative to the return of
                        cholera, and the perilous condition of the Brazilian iron-clad in front of
                        Humaita, is taken from to-day’s Standard:</p>
                    <p>“The next advices from Paraguay are looked for with the greatest anxiety, not
                        as respects the war but touching the cholera. Should the news be unfavorable
                        we hear the government is prepared to take the most decisive steps, and
                        close this port to all vessels coming from Itipiru or Corrientes. Something
                        must be done, as the warm weather is setting in. All who can are going to
                        the country for the summer.</p>
                    <p>“The mail has brought positive orders to Admiral Ignacio to return with his
                        iron-clads as fast as possible, and a letter in one of the Rio papers, which
                        we shall publish to-morrow, gives a very terrible version of what the
                        iron-clads suffered going up. The return now promises to be an episode in
                        our naval history. Should anything happen to the first iron-clad, so that
                        she founders in the stream, then the remainder are locked up. However, as
                        orders have been sent to come down, we suppose the admiral will not
                        disobey.”</p>
                    <p>Congress here has finally passed the bill subscribing to 15,000 shares for
                        the Central Argentine railway. This railway, due entirely to the
                        indefatigable exertions of our worthy countryman Mr. Wheelwright, is
                        intended to connect Rosario with Cordoba. It is now open from Rosaria as far
                        as Villanueva, a town thirty leagues from Cordova. Mr. Wheelwright has been
                        obliged to suspend the works for want of funds, but after the passing of the
                        above <pb facs="0307" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/> bill it is to be hoped that
                        he may soon bring to a termination this important undertaking which
                        contributed so powerfully to put a speedy end to the revolutionary outbreak
                        in Cordova of the 16th of last month.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 15.—Senator Navarro has brought into
                        congress a bill for the abolition of imprisonment for debt. The measure
                        meets with the support of the principal organs of the press.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 16.—Alarming news arrived yesterday from
                        the interior provinces of the north. It appears that Varela, the
                        indefatigable chief of the Monteneros, who was reported to have been
                        completely routed by the national forces in Rioja, has succeeded in
                        reforming his forces, and when least expected has burst into the province of
                        Salta with 1,300 men. A few provincial militias, amounting to about 600,
                        endeavored to make head against him, but were completely defeated, and the
                        greatest portion of them passed over to Varela’s ranks. Thus a whole
                        department remained at the mercy of this active chieftain. The governor of
                        Salta informs that of Tucuman that if Varela marches on the capital of the
                        province he will be obliged to evacuate it, and fall back upon Tucuman, as
                        he has no elements with which to oppose Varela’s forces.</p>
                    <p>The Standard, in commenting on this news, makes the following remarks:</p>
                    <p rend="center">“THE INVASION OF SALTA.</p>
                    <p>“Whatever may be the sequel of the Paraguayan war, it may be doubly memorable
                        in the history of this republic as the precursor and mould of the rudest
                        political throes this country has ever witnessed. Scarcely had we dispelled
                        the rebel force under Juan de Dios Videla, and congratulated ourselves on
                        the success of Paunero, when the astounding intelligence of an uprising in
                        Cordova, attended with the grossest mob violence, arrived by special <hi
                            rend="italic">chasque</hi> in this city. As the circumstance attending
                        this second edition of rebellion compromised more than the ordinary routine
                        of things in Argentine civil strife, since the minister of war had been
                        kidnapped by the rebels, a most immediate effort was made to subjugate the
                        disturbers. Thanks to the fealty of Luque and the discretion of Conesa, law
                        and order were restored with rapidity only to be equalled by the suddenness
                        of the outbreak. Conesa and his troops have come back, are feted in Rosario,
                        and the joy-inspiring rockets from the office of the Nacional, but a few
                        days past, told the glorious news of peace in the provinces; Cordova quiet
                        and orderly; Rioja and lujuy rid at last of every vestige of the rebels;
                        Paunero and Arredondo on their way back; special commissioners in Rosario
                        appealing to the charity of the people for relief of the ruined, houseless,
                        homeless inhabitants of Cuyo; dealers coming down in every steamer to
                        purchase goods in this city, and everything conspired to persuade us that
                        the civil strife had happily been extinguished, and no alloy to the
                        country’s progress and prosperity save the Paraguayan war, when in an
                        instant the scene changes. Saa and Varela, with a heterogeneous band of
                        rebels, have crossed the mountains of Bolivia, and burst like “a wolf on the
                        fold” on the once happy, prosperous, and contented province of Salta, On
                        their march they impressed all; none were too old or too young. They swept
                        the whole male population before them, and huddled them into their ranks.
                        The lovely valleys of Salta have as yet been the scene of these feats; not a
                        farm, not a house has been respected. The few who could, left their homes
                        and rushed into the city of Salta.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 17.—With regard to the intelligence from
                        the provinces the Standard of to-day says:</p>
                    <p>“The news of Varela’s invasion of Salta was confirmed to-day. Everyone was
                        annoyed at the frivolous manner in which official despatches are written in
                        the interior. Hardly have the public finished reading of the utter
                        destruction of the rebels in Rioja, when facts prove that the same
                        depredators are advancing in force at Salta or Catamarca. The most alarming
                        feature in this case is that several dealers from the provinces have
                        returned goods recently purchased, and, in one instance, actually
                        disembarked goods, paying the freight to Rosario, acting on advices from the
                        interior. These dealers are generally the best informed on this head, and
                        evidently fear that a storm is brewing. Don Uladislao Frias has been named
                        national commissioner to Salta, to endeavor to quiet that province.”</p>
                    <p>The Nacion Argentina published to-day a well-written and powerful article,
                        signed Gutierrez, drawing a most gloomy picture of the state of the country,
                        and proving with a great deal of truth and reason that things in the
                        Argentine Republic were never so much out of joint as at present. The writer
                        says that Varela and Saa will have at least 15,000 men under their orders by
                        this time, and that President Melgarejo, of Bolivia, has lately concluded a
                        loan for six millions of dollars and supplies the rebels with arms,
                        ammunition, and funds to carry on the war. By last accounts from the seat of
                        war in Paraguay it is reported that Mr. Gould, secretary of the British
                        legation, passed over the lines to the allied camp, accompanied by three of
                        General Lopez’s aides-de-camp, and, after holding a conference with
                        President Mitre and Marquis de Caxias, recrossed the lines and went back to
                        Lopez’s camp.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 18.—It appears that there are at present at
                        the seat of war an English, a French, and an Italian gunboat.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the affairs in the interior provinces the Standard publishes
                        the following remarks:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">The Situation.</hi>—The invasion of Salta by Varela and
                        Saa has caused little short of a panic in the republic. The few peaceful
                        inhabitants who, reposing confidence in the official <pb facs="0308" n="238"
                            xml:id="pg_238"/> despatches of our generals, and believing that the
                        rebels had been pulverized and law and order restored to her throne, find
                        with a pang that all these victories and triumphs have been in fact but
                        slight skirmishes, which, by Argentine generals, have been inflated into
                        decisive struggles. Hypocrisy holds such undisputed sway that until events
                        declare themselves the deluded citizens know but imperfectly what is the
                        real state of affairs. Had the governor of Salta placed less importance on
                        the recent victories over Varela, had he valued the despatches of the
                        national government officers at their proper estimate, he would not now cut
                        the despicable figure of a runaway Argentine ruler. He may, and doubtless
                        will, survive his passing troubles, but in the eyes of a descriminating
                        public he has proved himself the arbiter of his own misfortunes. Unlike the
                        other cities and provinces of this republic, Salta is peopled by an
                        industrious, hard-working class. The valleys where the invaders have made
                        such a fell swoop are teeming with fertility and plenty. The towns are
                        clean, orderly, and populous. The city is represented as second only to
                        Cordova in its streets, public buildings, and population. Political rancor
                        and anarchy have never before obtained such foothold there as in other
                        provinces; and ruled by a man of energy and decision of character, no
                        ruffian band such as that under the command of Varela could ever
                        successfully carry out an invasion.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 19.—The rumors of peace are gaining
                        consistence, and the principal conditions of a peace treaty, approved by
                        President Mitre and Marquis Caxias, referred to their respective
                        governments, are even mentioned. These are, 1st, that Lopez should resign in
                        favor of the vice-president of the republic of Paraguay, and go to Europe
                        fore a fixed period; 2d, that Paraguay shall renounce all claim to the Grand
                        Chaco territory; 3d, that the navigation of the river Paraguay is to be free
                        in all its course under the guarantee of European power; 4th, that the
                        question of limits with Brazil is to be referred to the arbitration of a
                        neutral power. These rumors, however, are all lacking official
                        confirmation.</p>
                    <p>With reference to the interior provinces the Standard of to-day says:</p>
                    <p>“Precisely as we anticipated, the rebels under Varela have taken possession
                        of Salta and levied heavy army contributions. Some of the principal families
                        fled along with the governor to Tucuman, but we read with deep regret that
                        in the whole province of Salta there is nothing to oppose the
                        revolutionists, and the party opposed to Governor Ovejero have all joined
                        Varela and Saa. All the riff-raff of the provinces, the scum of the country,
                        is in arms. People are now leaving Tucuman, as it is greatly feared the
                        rebels will make a dash on that province before the government party will be
                        able to make headway; in fact, things never looked worse. Varela and his
                        officers are enlisting the whole population, and they are not short of arms
                        since supplies are obtained from Bolivia.”</p>
                    <p>From the same paper the following regarding the war in Paraguay is also
                        taken:</p>
                    <p>“The steamer San José, with ball cartridges, shot, shell, and gunpowder from
                        the Rio arsenal, has arrived at Montevideo bound up for Itapiru.</p>
                    <p>“In Montevideo it is stated that three more iron-clads are coming down to the
                        Plata, and on board of one of them comes the Duke de Saxe, son-in-law of the
                        Emperor, to take supreme command of the Brazilian army, vice Caxias, who
                        retires into private life.”</p>
                    <p>Two important measures were yesterday introduced into congress: one requiring
                        the executive to account in a special message for the use made of the <hi
                            rend="italic">habeas corpus</hi> suspension act; the other calling upon
                        the executive for a report on the general state of the Paraguayan war.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 20.—News of an alarming character has come
                        by the last mail from the Pacific coast. Letters from Chili state that
                        Colonel Videla, who took so prominent a part in the Mendoza revolution,
                        which broke out in November of last year, is preparing to invade the
                        province of Mendoza by the Pass del Planchon, for which purpose he has got,
                        together with the promise of unlimited booty, 2,000 Chileno miners, all well
                        armed and accoutred.</p>
                    <p>The Tribuna to-day states that the Argentine government sent, about a
                        fortnight ago, instructions to its agent in Chili to demand explanations
                        with regard to the warlike preparations said to be carried on there by
                        Argentine exiles resident in that republic with a view of invading the
                        Argentine territory.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 21.—The Rio Janeiro papers mention the
                        appointment of his Excellency Conselheiro Sinumbu to a special mission to
                        the river Plata from the Brazilian government.</p>
                    <p>It is reported that the object of the mission is to make peace.</p>
                    <p>There are no less than eleven Brazilian transports in Montevideo awaiting
                        orders.</p>
                    <p>The following Brazilian version of the passage of Curupaiti by the
                        iron-clads, taken from to-day’s Standard, is highly interesting:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Curupaiti—Interesting Brazilian Version.—</hi>The
                        passage of the iron-clads past the batteries of Curupaiti took place upon
                        the 15th of August.</p>
                    <p>“At 6.35 a. m. the division of the iron-clads received orders to proceed
                        towards Humaita, and in a few minutes afterward the leading vessels were
                        under the enemy’s fire.</p>
                    <p>“The order was as follows: The Brazil, carrying the admiral’s flag, and with
                        the little steamer Lindoya on her larboard side; the Mariz e Barros; the
                        Tamandaré; the Colombo; the Cabral, towing a flat carrying a mortar; the
                        Barroso; the Herval; the Silvado; and the Lima Barros, with the flag of
                        Commodore Alvim.</p>
                    <p>“When the movement commenced the wooden vessels drew up and opened their fire
                        on <pb facs="0309" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> Curupaiti, whose batteries,
                        however, paid no attention to the wooden vessels, but rained the missiles of
                        their 33 cannons upon the iron-clads passing at gunshot from the
                        batteries.</p>
                    <p>“The time occupied in the passage was about two hours and a half, and the
                        foremost vessels were already cannonading the great casemated stone fort
                        called the ‘London’ battery, built for the first Lopez by an English
                        engineer, while the rear vessel, the Lima Barros, was passing Curupaiti. The
                        division received more than 240 80 and 63-pound shots during the passage.
                        Some of the vessels broached to in the rapid current, and some even turned
                        completely round, but finally succeeded in recovering their direction. Of
                        these accidents the Paraguayans ably availed themselves. The Tamandaré’s
                        engine got out of order, and the vessel became disabled while in front of
                        the batteries. A shot from one of the enemy’s cannon entered one of the
                        casemate ports and severely wounded Captain Elisario Barbosa and four of the
                        crew. The Colombo, broaching to right under the principal battery, received
                        considerable injury, and the Lima Barros, bringing up the rear, received 47
                        shots, some of which did much harm to the vessel. The loss of the division
                        was 33 men killed and wounded. The vessels had their decks and weak parts
                        protected to some extent with bags of sand.</p>
                    <p>“It is said that the channel furthest from the batteries had 10 torpedoes
                        laid down, but as the iron-clads took that which was close to the other
                        bank, they escaped that danger.</p>
                    <p>“In the order of the day of the 14th, the admiral, in referring to the
                        passage to take place next day, used the following language:</p>
                    <p>“‘Brazilians! Be full of hope. The patron saints assigned by the holy church
                        to preside over the 15th of August are the Holy Virgin of Glory, our Lady of
                        Victory, and Assumption of the Mother of God.</p>
                    <p>“‘It is therefore with glory and with victory that we will go to
                        Asuncion.’</p>
                    <p>“The iron-clads lie about one and a half mile from the casemated stone fort
                        Huamita, and maintain a constant fire on it and a barbette battery close to
                        it. Some of the vessels go within half a mile to give their fire greater
                        effect. Meanwhile, as the Paraguayan batteries are constructed to cross
                        their fire at particular points, they are able to do little against the
                        vessels, and these can batter at long range almost with impunity.</p>
                    <p>“Before the stone fort and its supporters are silenced, no probability of
                        success would occur to an attempt to force the passage by Humaita, as the
                        casemate alone has 25 heavy cannon, and all the batteries some 60 pieces.
                        The channel is narrow and tortuous, and besides a strong diagonal boom,
                        consisting of three chains twisted together and partially supported <hi
                            rend="italic">by</hi> three boats, the river is reported to be
                        obstructed, and sown with torpedoes.</p>
                    <p>“The communications of the division are effected by the Chaco, and some 500
                        men are employed in that duty and in making a road. The vessels have large
                        supplies of munitions and coal, and have six months’ rations of food. Wood
                        is also abundant on the banks of the river.</p>
                    <p>“The Tamandaré when disabled was taken in tow by the Silvado, and she and all
                        the other vessels had repaired their injuries.” —<hi rend="italic"
                            >Anglo-Brazilian Times.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Yesterday the three following bills were introduced into congress and
                        referred to committee:</p>
                    <p>1. Authorizing the national authorities to reside in Buenos Ayres, and
                        providing that congress shall designate the permanent seat of government at
                        the beginning of the sessions of 1868.</p>
                    <p>2. Authorizing the national government to offer a prize of 8,000 patacones to
                        the inventor or introducer of the best method for preserving meat for
                        exportation.</p>
                    <p>3. Authorizing the government to employ the sum of 1,000,000 hard dollars in
                        the purchase in the United States of 10 iron-clads fully armed, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 22.—The news which arrived yesterday from
                        the provinces have a more cheering character. It appears by last accounts
                        that the governor of Salta left the capital of his province to take up a
                        very advantageous position a few leagues from it, where he was fortifying
                        himself, and expected to make a successful resistance against the rebels, as
                        forces were hurrying to his assistance, both from the province of Iujuy and
                        from that of Tucuman, and General Taboada, on the first news of Varela’s
                        invasion, had taken active measures and was hastening to advance from the
                        province of Santiago to the theatre of disturbance.</p>
                    <p>General Arredondo arrived yesterday in Buenos Ayres from the province of
                        Cuyo. It is said he comes on a special mission to the national government,
                        although his absenting himself from his command at this moment gives rise to
                        various comments.</p>
                    <p>The Tribuna of to-day publishes an article by the pen of a prominent lawyer,
                        Dr. José F. Lopez, headed “The municipality, the cholera, and the alliance,”
                        in which he pictures the Argentine Republic as a flying phantom with the
                        alliance on its back, crossing in mid air over the once happy country, now a
                        desert chasm, filled with the shed blood of 12,000 brave Argentines, while
                        among those shattered bones are seen a few lonely palaces of the originators
                        and contractors of the Paraguayan war, who are the only parties benefited by
                        this bloody drama, and concludes with the words “More than a year ago, when
                        our army was stuck in the mud at Estero Bellaco, and the fleet was of no
                        use, being convinced of the sterility of the sacrifices imposed by the war,
                        and seeing the ferment of anarchy to which it gave rise, we urged its being
                        brought to a termination either by a decisive deed of arms or by peace, and
                        thus we might have been spared the disaster of Curupaiti, the civil war, the
                        pillage and destruction of towns and villages, and the anarchy which is
                        dragging us into an abyss. And if, to-day, in order to put down the
                        conflagration of our home we can succeed <pb facs="0310" n="240"
                            xml:id="pg_240"/> in obtaining peace, it will be as welcome as a brigade
                        of firemen. And since the government has not been successful in putting out
                        its own fire, it may still rehabilitate itself by extinguishing that of the
                        nation.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 23.—The Nacional of to-day reviews the
                        political career of Dr. Rawson, and endeavors to prove that his
                        administration as minister of the interior has been one series of blunders,
                        and that he will leave behind him no trace either of his talents, energy, or
                        statesmanship, but only carry with him his undoubted reputation of honesty,
                        which is all that remains to him. It concludes with these words: “When Dr.
                        Rawson retires into private life the Nacional will make it its duty to
                        praise, and recognize in him the eminent physician, the philanthropist, and
                        the disinterested gentleman. Such is our opinion and may Heaven pardon us if
                        we have erred with the best possible intentions.”</p>
                    <p>These attacks upon our able and popular premier seem, however, to emanate,
                        not from any leading parties in power, but only from some retired
                        malcontents.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. ASBOTH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
