<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-01-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="238" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d238">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Campbell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 15.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New Orleans</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25,1867</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have this morning received an
                            extra-official letter from Señor Lerdo de Tejada, dated at Santa
                            Catalina, December 24th, 1866, a copy of which (translated) I have the
                            honor to enclose, marked No. 1. The material fact communicated is that
                            President Juarez contemplated only a short delay at Durango, and a
                            departure thence to some city more in the interior of the republic,
                            which is not-named.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to remain, most respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>LEWIS D. CAMPBELL.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Translation]</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Señor Lerdo de Tejada</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Mr. Campbell</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Catalina,</hi>
                                    </placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-12-24"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 24, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> On the way from the city of Chihuahua
                                to that of Durango, where the president of the republic will arrive
                                day after to-morrow, I yesterday received the communication which
                                you addressed me from Brownsville, Texas, the 9th of this month,
                                with copy included of that which you addressed me at Tampico the
                                5th, the original of which I received at the same time.</p>
                            <p>With the extra-official character which you have addressed to me
                                these two communications, I have the honor to reply to them.</p>
                            <p>After referring in them to your voyage to the port of Vera Cruz with
                                Lieutenant General Sherman, and to your subsequent voyage to Tampico
                                and Brownsville, you advised me that Lieutenant General Sherman was
                                going to New Orleans, and that you yourself were going to Monterey,
                                desiring soon as possible to present your credentials as envoy
                                extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of the United States of
                                America near the government of the republic of Mexico. With this
                                motive you refer to the convenience and importance of beings <pb facs="0420" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/> able, so soon as possible,
                                to commence your official relations, and you express to me your
                                desire to know the place where you can present your credentials.</p>
                            <p>I have given information of your communications to the President, who
                                appreciates as is due your arrival as representative of the United
                                States of America, and desires much that you may be able very soon
                                to present yourself in your official character.</p>
                            <p>Although it is to be presumed that the President will not long delay
                                his departure to some city more in the interior of the republic,
                                nevertheless he considers that for the present it will be necessary
                                for him to remain a short time in the city of Durango to attend to
                                the administrative reorganization of various states, as well as to
                                give directions to the contributions they are making to push on
                                military operations in the war in which the republic is engaged.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient
                                servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>S. LERDO DE TEJADA.</signed>
                            </closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Lewis D. Campbell,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>