<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Plumb</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="326"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Plumb</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 7.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-09-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 19, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I transmit a copy of correspondence between this
                    department and Mr. Delfosse, the minister of Belgium, on the subject of Belgians
                    in Mexico. You will exercise your best discretion in extending to them your good
                    offices, so far as they may be necessary for their protection, and in the case
                    of Mr. Eloin, for the purpose of obtaining leave for him to quit that
                    country.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward L. Plumb,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Delfosse</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Seward</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgian Legation to the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-09-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 14, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State:</hi> Among a number of persons
                        arrested after the capture of Mexico is a Belgian, Mr. Eloin, formerly a
                        secretary of the emperor Maximilian.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hooricks, chargé <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> with the affairs of
                        the Belgian legation, has recently left Mexico, and has informed the King’s
                        government that he had confided the interests of our countrymen to Mr.
                        Otterbourg, representing the United States, who told him that he would
                        willingly take care of them.</p>
                    <p>The government of the King would feel deeply indebted to you, Mr. Secretary
                        of State, if you would have the kindness to lend it your good offices on
                        this occasion, and to be so kind as to recommend to the representative of
                        the United States in Mexico to use all his influence to prevent Mr. Eloin
                        from being treated with harshness, and to obtain authority for him to leave
                        Mexico. The agent of the federal government will, better than another, be in
                        position to judge, according to circumstances, the proper moment to take
                        these steps, the form to give to them, and, in a word, to appreciate what
                        may best contribute to assure success.</p>
                    <p>The minister for foreign affairs, on giving me instructions, in virtue of
                        which I have the honor to address you this communication, expresses his
                        confidence that you will not refuse, Mr. Secretary of State, to acquiesce in
                        this request Mr. Rogier adds, that he will be personally very grateful to
                        you for what you will have the kindness to do for Mr. Eloin, and for
                        dissipating the apprehensions of his numerous friends.</p>
                    <p>Please accept, Mr. Secretary of State, the assurances of my highest
                        consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MAURICE DELFOSSE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi>c., <hi
                                    rend="italic">&amp;</hi>c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Delfosse</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-09-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 19, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have had the honor to receive your note of
                        the 14th instant. In compliance with your request, instructions have been
                        given to the charge d’affaires of the United States in Mexico to lend his
                        good offices to the subjects of Belgium, in that republic, to the same
                        extent and under the same restrictions as are now applied there in the cases
                        of citizens of the United States.</p>
                    <p>In regard to the delicate case of Mr. Eloin, I have already sent forward a
                        communication making known the interest which Mr. Rogier has expressed to
                        this government. Your note in this respect seems to be judiciously
                        conceived. It seems to me that in no other way could I so well lend the good
                        offices of this government in that respect, as by sending forward to Mr.
                        Plumb a copy of your note, and commending it at the same time to his
                        discreet attention.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, with high consideration, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Maurice Delfosse,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
