<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-10-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="336" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d336">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Plumb</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 22.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United StateS,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">City of Mexico,</hi>
                                </placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-10-23"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 23, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> As the department is doubtless already
                            advised, a special mission has been sent to this country by the
                            government of Bolivia, to congratulate President Juarez upon the triumph
                            recently obtained by this republic, in the defence of its independence
                            and republican institutions.</p>
                        <p>This mission reached here by way of Acapulco from Panama, a few days
                            before my arrival, and the envoy, Señor Don Quentin Quevedo, a
                            distinguished citizen of Bolivia, who is accompanied by a full suite,
                            was received by President Juarez on the 7th instant.</p>
                        <pb facs="0535" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                        <p>The presence of the mission here has elicited very general demonstrations
                            of a friendly character in its regard, and last evening, in view of
                            Señor Quevedo’s early departure, a grand banquet in his honor was given
                            by the President of the republic in the national palace, to which I was
                            invited, and at which were present all the principal personages of the
                            several departments of the government, and a large number of the most
                            distinguished citizens of Mexico, now present at the capital.</p>
                        <p>The occasion was marked by the expression of great good feeling as
                            regards the relations between the different American States, and very
                            gratifying allusions were made to the United States, and to the
                            fraternal feeling that has been manifested by the government and people
                            of the United States towards Mexico, throughout the whole of the severe
                            struggle in which this republic has lately been engaged.</p>
                        <p>To these allusions, in a few words at a proper moment, I returned my
                            acknowledgments, and at the same time expressed my satisfaction, as the
                            representative of the United States, in being present on such an
                            occasion.</p>
                        <p>Señor Queveda intends to leave here on the 8th proximo for Havana and St.
                            Thomas, on his way to Brazil, to which country he has been accredited by
                            his government as minister plenipotentiary. His secretary of legation
                            and son precede him a few days in their departure, and go by way of New
                            York, whence they propose to take the steamer tor Brazil the 21st
                            November.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>E. L. PLUMB.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>