<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Van Valkenburgh to  to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190" lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93000083" lcsh-match="good_close">Religious freedom</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-08-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="48" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Van Valkenburgh</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 44.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Yedo,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-08-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 23, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On my recent arrival at Nagasaki, in the
                            Shenandoah, returning from the west coast, I heard a rumor that a large
                            number of native Christians of the Roman Catholic faith had recently
                            been arrested, tortured, and imprisoned, under an old law of Japan, for
                            the exercise of Christian belief. I at once wrote a note to Right
                            Reverend Bishop Petitjean, the Roman Catholic bishop of Japan, who
                            resides in Nagasaki, asking for such information as might be in his
                            possession. The next day, 27th July, he called upon me and kindly gave
                            me the following facts :</p>
                <p>In Japan there are now, as nearly as can be estimated, 20,000 native
                            Roman Catholics, descendants from the Christians formerly resident in
                            this country. These are scattered, more or less, all over the empire.
                            There are, comparatively, no new converts. The largest portion of these
                            Christians reside in the island of Kiusiu, and Nagasaki is the central
                            point at which there is a French bishop and several French priests.
                            Whenever it has been possible, these Christians have kept up their forms
                            of worship in secret, and their religious fires have been constantly
                            alive since the last massacre at Pappenburg. Near Nagasaki there are
                            many of these Christians, and the priests frequently meet among them,
                            preaching and administering their sacraments in the night. The
                            government must have had notice of these meetings for a long time, but
                            took no measures about them until the Bonzes, or priests of the Buddhist
                            and Sintoo temples, complained bitterly that their revenues from
                            burials, &amp;c., were rapidly falling off. About the middle of July,
                            these complaints having become so numerous, the governor, in the night
                            time, caused the arrest of 63 men, women, and children, in the little
                            valley of Owri Kami, situated about four miles from Nagasaki. They were
                            confined in small prisons erected for the purpose. It was not known
                            what, if any, torture had been inflicted, or what was to be the
                            punishment.</p>
                <p>Deeming it my duty, I at once asked an audience with the two governors of
                            Nagasaki, and, on the 29th of July, they visited me pursuant to my
                            request. I expressed to them my regret at the occurrence, and endeavored
                            to induce them to release the poor prisoners. They declined, having
                            arrested them as criminals under the laws of Japan, upon complaint and
                            proof, unless by direction from the government. They assured me,
                            however, that they had not been tortured, and promised that the wants of
                            those confined, as well as of their families, should be provided for,
                            and that no future arrests should be made until directions were received
                            from the Gorogio.</p>
                <p>Subsequently, I learned that two more arrests had been made. I at once
                            asked another interview with the governors, and on the 8th of August
                            they again visited me. They then informed me the two subsequent arrests
                            were not by their order, and that the charge against the persons
                            arrested was not that of being Christians. They renewed their promises
                            of kind treatment made at the former interview.</p>
                <p>On my return to this city, and on the 20th instant, I had an interview
                            with one of the governors of foreign affairs upon the subject, and
                            addressed a communication to the Gorogio, a copy of which I forward in
                            this.</p>
                <p>To this I have received, as yet, no answer, but am informed,
                            unofficially, that orders have been forwarded to Nagasaki for the
                            release of the prisoners.</p>
                <p>Enclosed (No. 2) I send memoranda of my conversations with Noshe Osumi No
                            Kami and Tokuraga Iwami No Kami, the two governors of Nagasaki.</p>
                <pb facs="0127" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                <p>I trust that my action in this matter will meet withthe approval of the
                            President and of the department.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient
                            servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R. B. VAN VALKENBURGH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Van Valkenburgh</persName> to <persName type="to">the ministers of foreign affairs,</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 72.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Yedo,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-08-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 20, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>It is the express desire of my government that I shall in no manner
                                interfere with the internal regulations of Japan, and that I shall
                                carefully guard against even suspicion of doing so; yet I cannot
                                fail to state to your excellencies that the President will learn
                                with regret the recent action of the governor of Nagasaki in causing
                                the arrest of native Christians at that port for no crime or
                                misdemeanor, other than the profession of their faith and on the
                                plea of their infringement of an ancient law which, if these people
                                were at all aware of its existence, is, at all events, now obsolete
                                and in entire disaccord with the enlightened policy inaugurated by
                                his present Majesty the Tycoon.</p>
                    <p>The absolute religious freedom of which the United States has set the
                                example to the world and the entire independence of all religious
                                belief from the interference and control of government, have in a
                                great measure contributed to the unexampled prosperity and power at
                                which my country has arrived. Intolerance in regard to religious
                                matters would at this moment be regarded in a very serious light by
                                the Christian world, and perhaps be followed to a greater or less
                                extent by the withdrawal of the sympathy of the great western
                                powers, of which the government of the Tycoon stands so much in
                                need.</p>
                    <p>My remonstrances with the governor of Nagasaki have no doubt had for
                                result what instructions for the release of the native Christians
                                have ere this been issued.</p>
                    <p>The governor of Nagasaki acted in this unfortunate matter on his own
                                responsibility, and while I now call your excellencies’ attention to
                                the danger to which an ill-considered act of an agent, with only
                                very limited authority, may lead, I have the honor to request your
                                excellencies to inform me officially that these native Christians
                                have been released; that their property has been restored to them,
                                and that an absolute forgetfulness of the past may he considered as
                                a guarantee againt similar ill-advised acts for the future.</p>
                    <p>With respect and esteem,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. B. VAN VALKENBURGH, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident
                                        of the United States.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Their Excellencies the <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministers for Foreign
                                        Affairs,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,&amp;c., &amp;c., Yedo.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minutes of an interview had this day with Noshe
                                    Osumi No Kami and Tokuraga Iwami No Kami, governors of
                                    Nagasaki.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Minister. Am sorry to learn that, by the governor’s orders, a number
                                of native Christians have been arrested and imprisoned.</p>
                    <p>Governor. Am deeply sorry for this matter. These people have
                                announced publicly that they are Christians. I am obliged by laws to
                                arrest them, though sorry to do so.</p>
                    <p>Minister. I had hoped that the Japanese had become more enlightened
                                in regard to these matters. In all countries, especially in America,
                                we can worship God as we choose.</p>
                    <p>Governor. According to Japanese law, for a long time past, foreign
                                religion is prohibited. When that law is repealed we will not arrest
                                any one because of his religion.</p>
                    <p>Minister. I have a copy of that law translated from the Japanese, and
                                will do all I can to have the Gorogio repeal it. The whole world
                                will be astonished to hear that the governor has arrested these
                                people because they do not use the same form of worship with
                                himself. I understand the governor must carry out the law, but hope
                                he will treat these prisoners well until they can be released by the
                                proper tribunal.</p>
                    <p>Governor. Have taken care that these prisoners are treated properly,
                                better than ordinary ones. Have written to the Gorogio about these
                                matters, but not yet received an answer. About 63 have been
                                arrested. Impossible for me to release them without instructions
                                from the Gorogio. Had no instructions from the Gorogio to arrest
                                them.</p>
                    <p>Minister. Am sorry it has happened; it will injure Japan in the eyes
                                of all nations, and at the time when the Tycoon wants their sympathy
                                and support.</p>
                    <p>Governor. The number of Christians in Japan is daily increasing, and
                                we fear it will lead to internal troubles.</p>
                    <pb facs="0128" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                    <p>Minister. Governor should not meddle with religion. That is the only
                                true way to avoid trouble.</p>
                    <p>2d Governor. Have just left the capital. Tycoon’s mind is quite
                                different from what it was formerly. Laws have been changed greatly.
                                Think this law will be changed also, but the Tycoon has not yet had
                                time.</p>
                    <p>Minister. I speak as a friend of the Tycoon and of Japan. Believe the
                                Tycoon to be a true, earnest, and most intelligent man. My
                                government will greatly regret this occurrence, and I hope the law
                                will soon be repealed. Does the governor allow any one to visit
                                these prisoners, and will he allow me ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. Common people are prohibited from seeing them; only the
                                officers in charge can see them. Japanese high officials do not like
                                to see prisoners unless in court. You are of higher rank than myself
                                and would not like you to see them; but if you wish to go, will
                                accompany you.</p>
                    <p>Minister. Have these prisoners been beaten or tortured, and have they
                                plenty to eat ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. They have not been beaten or tortured, and they have plenty
                                to eat. Will not arrest any more before I get the Tycoon’s opinion.
                                Their families are well taken care of, an officer having been
                                appointed for that purpose. A great many complaints have been made
                                relative to the increase of Christianity in Japan, obliged to arrest
                                these people according to law; it is my duty. Will submit the matter
                                to the opinion of the Tycoon and must abide by his decision.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Nagasaki,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-07-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 29, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memoranda of interview held August</hi> 8, 1867,
                                    <hi rend="italic">with the governors of Nagasaki.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Minister. Sorry to hear that since last interview more Christians
                                have been arrested.</p>
                    <p>Governor. They were not arrested by my order nor because they were
                                Christians, but by an officer because they disobeyed an order of
                                this government. They were not put in prison.</p>
                    <p>Minister. How many were there of them ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. Two, only.</p>
                    <p>Minister. Are they women ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. Yes.</p>
                    <p>Minister. They disobeyed some order of the government ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. They are confined for that.</p>
                    <p>Minister. Not because they are Christians, but because they disobeyed
                                an order ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. Yes.</p>
                    <p>Minister. How many Christians are confined and in prison ?</p>
                    <p>2d Governor. They were arrested during my absence. Do you wish to
                                speak to the Gorogio about it ?</p>
                    <p>Minister. Yes.</p>
                    <p>2d Governor. Sixty-five. Have spoken to the Gorogio, at Miako. Cannot
                                release them on my own responsibility.</p>
                    <p>Minister. I understand. I want all the information that I may be able
                                to lay the matter before the Gorogio. Have any Christians been
                                arrested in any other part of this island ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. Do not know. Of what country are they; what Daimio’s
                                province ?</p>
                    <p>Minister. I do not know. Have heard that some of them have been
                                arrested.</p>
                    <p>Governor. I have heard nothing of it.</p>
                    <p>Minister. Have any Christians died since their confinement ?</p>
                    <p>Governor. No, not as yet.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
