<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Stuttgart (Dominion) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recqhvaPBazS2SPQl" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051711"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of the press</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="146"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/2924</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Stuttgart (<persName type="from"
                            >Dominion</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 899</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuttgart</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-02-21">February 21,
                            1933</date>.<lb/>[Received March 13.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit below, as of possible
                    interest, the striking similarity observable between internal political
                    developments in Germany since National Socialist success culminated in the
                    appointment <pb facs="0298" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> of Adolf Hitler as
                    Chancellor of the Reich and the events which unfolded themselves in Italy in the
                    Fall of 1921 and led to the establishment of Fascism in that country. My former
                    assignment to Rome enables me now to make interesting comparisons.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most striking development since the accession of Mr. Hitler to the
                    premiership has been the great increase of political brawls and fights reported
                    throughout the country. Street fighting in large cities and small villages
                    between National Socialists on the one hand and, generally, Communist or
                    Socialist bodies or individuals on the other has become a daily occurrence since
                    February 1 and is steadily augmenting in intensity and extent. The number of
                    fights increases considerably on week-ends when laborers spend a good deal of
                    time in beer halls and cafes. In Italy these week-end brawls were known as the
                    dominical quarrels and their recurrence in Germany at this time is the result of
                    causes similar in every respect to those formerly at play in Italy.</p>
                <p>The extent to which these encounters are definite provocations cannot be
                    determined with any degree of accuracy. It is believed, however, that the
                    aggressiveness and militancy which are primary tenets and methods of operation
                    of Fascist organizations would not preclude intentional preparation, through
                    these brawls, of the necessary circumstances which would enable the government
                    to invoke a state of exceptionally grave conditions and adopt measures tending
                    to suppress many forms of liberty granted by the German Constitution. Such a
                    move, it is believed, is favored in National Socialist circles in order to
                    ensure success of this party at the elections on March 5. As a matter of fact,
                    matters are fast reaching the stage at which doubt is felt at the holding of a
                    free election in Germany on that day.</p>
                <p>The essential characteristic of Italian Fascism in regard to internal politics is
                    found in the suppression of constitutional rights which has led to the negation
                    of all personal liberty in Italy since the beginning of 1922. Concurrently a
                    strict censorship of the Italian press was established which soon developed into
                    simple suppression of all opposition papers. Consequently there has been no
                    freedom of the press in Italy for a period of over ten years and, strangely
                    enough, the Vatican organ <hi rend="italic">L’Osservatore Romano</hi>, published
                    within the confines of the Vatican City, may be considered at present as the
                    only uncensored daily paper published in the Italian peninsula.</p>
                <p>Today a drift toward a similar state of affairs in Germany is distinctly
                    perceptible. The number of newspapers temporarily suspended has increased
                    considerably since January 30 and the temporary prohibition of publication is
                    directed not merely to Communist papers as in the past but increasingly to
                    Socialist newspapers and, surprisingly, even to conservative Center party
                    newspapers.</p>
                <pb facs="0299" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/>
                <p>That German public men are concerned about the curtailment of the liberty of the
                    press as well as the suppression of free public opinion is shown by the speech
                    of the State President of Württemberg, Dr. Bolz, at Hechingen, Hohenzollern, on
                    February 17. Dr. Bolz ranks high in the Center party and is perhaps one of the
                    most conservative Reichstag deputies. He admitted frankly, however, that the
                    present trend was leading the country to civil war and revolution, and it was
                    his opinion that the German people would not stand for the suppression of their
                    liberties as the Italian people had done.</p>
                <p>Another feature of resemblance to Italian developments is seen in the high-handed
                    and illegal assumption of authority by organized National Socialist bodies.
                    Within the past two weeks reports have been heard of bands of National
                    Socialists traveling about from village to village in trucks owned by their
                    party and entering the homes of private citizens there to inquire whether the
                    inmates are members of the National Socialist party or not or requesting to know
                    whether there are Jews in the household, and in general assuming an intimidating
                    and terrorizing attitude which conforms so minutely with the methods adopted by
                    the Italian Fascists during the first three years of their organization that one
                    is led to suspect that coaching from Italian masters may have led to the
                    adoption of similar methods in Germany.</p>
                <p>In the streets of Stuttgart the spectacle of Fascist bravoes, clad in the
                    military uniforms of the National Socialist army and going about in groups of
                    four or five, with arrogant and swaggering attitude, may be seen daily, though
                    more particularly on Sundays and holidays. As in Italy, these Fascists carry
                    arms openly and it is evident from their manner that their marching about is
                    intended as a deliberate provocation to create disturbances and to intimidate
                    peaceable citizens.</p>
                <p>Throughout the last two weeks the sessions of the small Württemberg Landtag or
                    State Parliament have strongly reminded me of the vicissitudes of the Italian
                    Parliament throughout 1922 and 1923. In both instances an utter defiance of
                    constitutionality was manifested by the Fascist deputies. In the Württemberg
                    State Parliament, which is now presided by a National Socialist President, this
                    official exhorts from the chair he occupies his party members to eject bodily
                    members of the opposition from the session halls.</p>
                <p>The Italian Fascists lost no time in replacing the entire government personnel by
                    Fascists. In this process it was apparent that the pressure of members of the
                    Fascist party for positions was less taken into account than the definite intent
                    of building up a Fascist State and the furtherance of a policy of immediate and
                    thorough fascistization of Italy.</p>
                <p>Again in this respect there are signs of similarity in Germany. Recent press
                    notices indicate that chiefs of police in many cities are being <pb facs="0300"
                        n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/> replaced and it appears that the destituted
                    officials are functionaries whose loyalty to a republican régime is undoubted.
                    Similar changes among army officers in the military establishment within this
                    consular district have been noted in my despatches No. 886 and No. 898 of
                    February 7 and 20, 1933, respectively.<note n="9" xml:id="d146fn9">Neither
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There is, of course, a certain amount of resistance which emanates primarily from
                    Socialist and Communist circles and which also is found in Center and Democratic
                    circles. It is doubted, however, whether this opposition will assume the
                    concrete form of an armed civil struggle, in spite of statements made by the
                    State President of Württemberg, as reported above. It would seem as if the
                    number of Germans definitely in favor of Fascism is too large and that a
                    sufficient majority cannot be found to oppose the National Socialists either by
                    constitutional methods or by means of open rebellion. The situation here is
                    interestingly different from that in Italy where a Fascist minority has imposed
                    its will on the majority of the Italian people. Indeed it is my personal belief
                    that were a free election held in Italy today the Fascist government would not
                    be returned, whereas it is not unlikely that, even in the event of a free
                    election being held in Germany on March 5, the National Socialist party may
                    obtain a majority of the votes.</p>
                <p>But even were the election results not any more decisive than those of 1932, it
                    is possible that the National Socialists will force their stay in power through
                    the well equipped party army they have built up. There has been no lack of
                    public assertion in the past weeks by leaders of the National Socialist party
                    that they intend to maintain themselves in power irrespective of election
                    results. This is in keeping with Fascist methods and with Italian
                    precedents.</p>
                <p>Assumption of authority by the National Socialists is viewed with particular
                    alarm in academic circles where faculties and the teaching staff are government
                    appointees. It is recalled how in Italy competent teachers and scholars of
                    international reputation were arbitrarily dismissed by the Fascists in power
                    because of refusal to take part in Italian politics. It is felt that a similar
                    fate is in store for the university teachers who have sufficient courage to
                    assert their independence of political affiliation. The Fascist policy of
                    ousting from office those teachers who are not militant Fascists has already
                    found expression, according to local press reports, in Berlin where National
                    Socialist students are reported to have bodily thrown out of the State Art
                    School a number of their teachers on allegations that they were Marxists and
                    Jews. This action is considered as ominous and as boding ill for the future of
                    German education under National Socialist auspices.</p>
                <pb facs="0301" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/>
                <p>Still another method of action by the National Socialists which resembles closely
                    Italian Fascist practice is the impeding by violence of campaign meetings, as
                    happened at Oberndorf in Württemberg on February 17. Here the Württemberg
                    Minister of National Economy, who is a member of the German Democratic party,
                    had been scheduled to address a meeting of members of his party. At the very
                    beginning of the session a group of National Socialists in the audience tried to
                    prevent the speaker from making his address and continued their tactics
                    throughout the meeting. They even attempted to use bodily violence on the
                    Minister but were prevented by the policemen present. The newspaper account of
                    the resort to violence recalls vividly similar scenes in Italy at the very
                    beginning of the establishment of the Fascist régime.</p>
                <p>In Germany these days, as in Italy under the Fascist régime, the National
                    Socialists claim that their party alone can meet the communist danger. The
                    argument is exaggerated and may be discounted as the highly efficient German
                    police together with the Reichswehr, not to mention the thousands of orderly
                    German citizens in every city suffice amply to prevent the setting up of a
                    communist regime in Germany. The exploitation of communism by reactionary bodies
                    in many countries is now too well known to need elaboration here. That communism
                    will continue to exist in the country is probable because of existing industrial
                    conditions. At the same time it appears true that the growth of National
                    Socialism and of Fascist developments in Germany is contributing to bring new
                    recruits to the communist party. The same results followed the establishment of
                    Fascism in Italy, where anarchism and communism, although not openly avowed, are
                    believed to be much more widespread today than at the beginning of the Fascist
                    regime. In Italy also a strange process of Communist workmen turning to
                    membership in the Fascist unions was noted and several instances of like changes
                    have come to my knowledge in this district. This may be explained by the
                    similarity between the radicalism of Fascists and Communists and by analogies
                    such as disregard of law and constitutionality found among both. One only needs
                    to recall here the similarity in methods of government in Soviet Russia and
                    Italy and note the gradual drift of very recent German government methods in the
                    same direction.</p>
                <p>That the German people will act as the Italians and submit to Fascist rule is
                    believed possible. The basis of this possibility is found in the toleration by
                    the German people of the military clique headed by the former Kaiser which ruled
                    them up to the end of 1918. A people which submitted to such a rule in the
                    twentieth century may be considered as unlikely to oppose another militarist
                    government such as the National Socialists are organizing.</p>
                <pb facs="0302" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/>
                <p>It may be inferred, by analogy, that should the spread of Fascist authority meet
                    no opposition in Germany it may not be long before considerably restricted
                    personal liberty will be observable in the country as in Italy. It will then be
                    possible to obtain a fairly accurate idea of future developments in Germany,
                    both as to internal and foreign affairs, by confrontation with Italian
                    precedents. In the sphere of foreign affairs, however, allowance will have to be
                    made for differences in aims in both countries in spite of the similarity which
                    is to be found in some of their policies as, for instance, in the field of
                    colonial expansion.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leon Dominian</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
