<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Germany (Sackett) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFUxKQXnfXXOdPs" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85019949"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Death penalty</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="149"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d149">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/2935</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany (<persName type="from"
                            >Sackett</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2222</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-03-03">March 3,
                            1933</date>.<lb/>[Received March 25.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As pointed out in my telegram No. 27 of February
                        28,<note n="10" xml:id="d149fn10">Not printed.</note> the burning of the
                    Reichstag gave the Nazis the pretext which they needed for further repressive
                    measures against political opponents. In addition to the planned decree,
                    sharpening the penalties for treason, sedition and subversive activities which
                    now provides the death penalty for the betrayal of military secrets, the
                    Government promptly issued a presidential decree putting into effect a state of
                    exceptional emergency, suspending those articles of the Constitution which
                    practically constitute the German Bill of Rights. (See my telegram No. 28 of
                    March 1, 4 p.m.)<note n="10" xml:id="d149fn12">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>According to a semi-official statement, “it has been proved beyond doubt that
                    Communist leaders were directly connected with the incendiarism and that
                    Communists had planned other acts of terrorism.” Furthermore, the Dutchman
                    arrested as the incendiary is reported by the Prussian authorities to have
                    admitted in his confession that he had connections with the
                    Social-Democrats.</p>
                <p>On these grounds, and by virtue of the unlimited powers granted him by the
                    Emergency Decree, Minister Goering immediately ordered a wholesale arrest of
                    Communist deputies in the Reichstag and Prussian Diet, as well as prominent
                    pacifists, journalists, authors, educators and lawyers who defended Communists
                    in political trials, and a number of Social-Democrats. Several thousand persons,
                    many of whom are intellectuals and not registered members of a political party,
                    are now being detained in custody on the basis of this decree, which permits
                    their confinement in prison for an unlimited time, without being informed of the
                    reason. At a meeting of his party last night, Minister Goering boasted that
                    alone in the Rhineland and Westphalia 2000 persons have been put behind the
                    bars.</p>
                <p>All Communist newspapers have been prohibited in Prussia for four weeks,
                    Social-Democratic newspapers for two weeks. A similar prohibition has been
                    imposed on all periodicals, handbills and placards of the two parties. In other
                    states, except those controlled by the Nazis and Nationalists, only the
                    Communist press has been suppressed. In Prussia, Social-Democratic as well as
                    Communist meetings have been prohibited, and the placards of these parties on
                    billboards and on the advertisement kiosks have been torn down by the
                    police.</p>
                <pb facs="0306" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                <p>In Prussia and other parts of Germany, the Auxiliary Police—composed of members
                    of the Nazi Storm Detachments and the Stahlhelm—are being mobilized in large
                    numbers, and cases are reported where uniformed Nazis acting as police have
                    searched the homes of individuals and organizations opposed to the present
                    régime. To demonstrate that the Communists have been definitely downed, a Nazi
                    Storm Detachment paraded before the Karl Liebknecht House, Communist
                    headquarters in Berlin recently closed by the police, and, with appropriate
                    ceremonies, hoisted the Nazi flag over the building.</p>
                <p>Of the opposition parties, aside from the very small Staatspartei, only the
                    Center Party is still able to conduct its campaign in Prussia and other states
                    dominated by the Nazis, despite the drastic restrictions imposed by the decrees.
                    The Centrist Party can still hold political meetings and appeal to the voters by
                    means of placards and election literature; its press has not been suppressed. As
                    far as the Left parties are concerned, however, the campaign was definitely over
                    immediately after the fire in the Reichstag. For these parties the election on
                    March 5 is a farce, as they have been completely deprived during the last and
                    most important week of the campaign of the constitutional right to appeal to
                    their following. In most parts of Germany, the Social-Democrats have been so
                    completely muzzled and repressed that, outwardly at least, they have ceased to
                    exist.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, the Nazis are winding up the campaign in very impressive
                    style. The numerous brown uniforms, the huge Nazi placards with which the cities
                    and the countryside are dotted, the frequent parades of the Brown Army, the mass
                    meetings and the daily broadcasting of election speeches by Nazi leaders, tend
                    to create the impression even now that there is only one large party in
                    Germany.</p>
                <p>Minister Goering’s attempt to link up the Social-Democrats with the fire in the
                    Reichstag, on the basis of the alleged confession of the arrested incendiary,
                    has evoked an emphatic statement from the executive committee of that party,
                    which rejected as an untruth “the assertion of the criminal on the basis of
                    which the complete tying up of the election work of the party is being
                    justified.” Under the existing gag-rule in Germany, this is as far as the
                    Social-Democratic leaders dare to go in repudiating Goering’s charge.</p>
                <p>While most people are ready to believe that the Communists are capable of such a
                    monstrous act, few people, except fanatic followers of Hitler and Hugenberg, can
                    conceive of the Social-Democrats resorting to such terrorist methods. Even
                    journals of the moderate Right, despite the risk of being suppressed, declare
                    that cooperation of the Social-Democrats with the arrested incendiary is
                    exceedingly improbable.</p>
                <p>The fact that Minister Goering, in his last election speech, abstained from
                    attributing the fire to the Social-Democrats as well as to the Communists, <pb
                        facs="0307" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/> would seem to indicate that he
                    realizes that this charge could not long be sustained. However, it gave him the
                    desired pretext to paralyze completely the hated Social-Democrats in the crucial
                    week of the campaign and in this respect at least the work of the incendiary
                    came at a most opportune moment.</p>
                <p>Hitler and Goering are very indignant that certain foreign journals refuse to
                    believe that the German Communist Party had anything to do with the arrested
                    incendiary, some even attributing the crime to the Nazis themselves. While there
                    is no reason to doubt the official statement on this point, one can readily
                    understand why some foreign correspondents in Berlin take such an attitude.
                    Deliberate acts of terrorism have up to now seldom been attributed to the
                    Communist Party as such. In recent years their crimes consisted for the most
                    part of so-called literary treason or sedition, of subversive acts such as
                    attempts to disintegrate the Reichswehr and the police, and frequent instigation
                    to a general strike. The German Communists have not, to my knowledge, resorted
                    to anarchist methods with which Bolshevists in the United States and other
                    countries are usually identified. It is a well-known fact that political
                    assassinations in the past, such as the murders of Rathenau and Erzberger, and
                    attempts on the lives of other prominent politicians, have been committed by
                    Right radicals.</p>
                <p>It is a fact that many people in Germany really believe—though they are afraid to
                    say so openly—that the Dutchman arrested is an <hi rend="italic">agent
                        provocateur</hi>, or that he acted on his own initiative, without the
                    knowledge of the Communist Party. They contend that the Communists had little to
                    gain from such an act of terrorism and that the Communist leaders must have
                    known that the Nazis would not fail to exploit it in order to hasten the advent
                    of a purely Fascist regime in Germany. It is pointed out that the circumstances
                    under which the incendiary was arrested, and the readiness with which he
                    allegedly associated the Social-Democrats with the crime, without, however,
                    divulging the identity of his accomplices, has led many to view the Government’s
                    assertions with skepticism. According to the official investigation, inflammable
                    material had been set on fire at more than twenty different points and the
                    arrested Dutchman must therefore have had at least from seven to ten
                    accomplices.</p>
                <p>However that may be, the fact remains that at the moment the propaganda value of
                    the fire in the Reichstag is perhaps as valuable to the Nazis as the Zinoviev
                    letter was to the British Conservatives in the elections in the fall of 1927.
                    The Nazis have exploited the incident to the utmost, in their press and
                    political meetings, as well as in broadcasts of strongly colored reports from
                    the scene of the fire. Past masters of propaganda that they are, they have
                    managed to stir up the country <pb facs="0308" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/> to a
                    pitch comparable only to war-time hysteria. The enthusiasm of the growing Nazi
                    following knows no bounds, while the rest of the population—intimidated and
                    nervous—is awaiting the week-end with anxiety and misgivings.</p>
                <p>Conscious of their growing strength, the Nazis will stage, on the eve of the
                    elections, impressive demonstrations throughout Germany, with torchlight
                    processions and, what Dr. Goebbels calls, “liberation bonfires” along the German
                    frontiers. Hitler will speak in Koenigsberg, the capital of East Prussia, on the
                    night before the election. The speech will be broadcast over a national hook-up
                    and Dr. Goebbels, as chief propagandist of the party, has ordered that
                    loud-speakers be set up in all public squares throughout the country, and that
                    people with radios in their homes open the windows “in order that every man in
                    the street may hear the words of the Führer.”</p>
                <p>The fire has caused the heaviest damage to the assembly hall of the Reichstag,
                    completely destroying that chamber, while the main structure of the massive
                    building, which outwardly resembles the Library of Congress in Washington, has
                    suffered comparatively little damage. It has been estimated that it will take at
                    least a year to restore the building. In the meantime, the Cabinet has decided
                    to convene the new Reichstag in the historical Garnisonskirche in Potsdam,
                    within the walls of which repose the remains of Frederic the Great, the choice
                    having been made at the instance of the Hugenberg Nationalists as symbolic of
                    the revival in Germany of the spirit of Potsdam.</p>
                <p>A brief analysis of the Presidential Decree suspending constitutional liberties,
                    on the basis of which the Government has been given practically dictatorial
                    power, is transmitted by despatch No. 2223 of March 4, 1933,<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d149fn11">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> going forward in this pouch.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederic M. Sackett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
