<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="276" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.91262/120</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Western
                                    European Affairs (Moffat) of a Conversation With the German
                                    Chargé (Leitner)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-19">August 19,
                                        1933</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Dr. Leitner came to see me in much agitation at 9:10 this morning. He
                                said that he had received another telegram from the German Foreign
                                Office with reference to his talk with Mr. Hull a week or so ago
                                regarding Edgar Mowrer, the correspondent in Berlin of the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Daily News</hi>. He had at the time asked
                                Mr. Hull to persuade the paper to withdraw Mowrer immediately else
                                the Germans would have to expel him, and left an article which had
                                given particular offense. Mr. Hull said he would look into the
                                matter and spoke to both Mr. Hackworth<note n="52" xml:id="d276fn52">Green H. Hackworth, Legal Adviser of the Department of
                                    State.</note> and myself. We found out that the paper had
                                transferred Mr. Mowrer from Berlin to Tokyo at just about the time
                                of the interview and assumed that the matter had dropped.</p>
                            <p>Now Dr. Leitner read me a further telegram, roughly to the following
                                effect: “No reply as yet to your representations about Mowrer. We
                                cannot delay much longer and will have to expel him by the beginning
                                of the week unless action is taken.” I told Leitner that this was a
                                very big thing that he was asking us to do as it brought into play
                                the entire relationship between the Government and the press. I
                                could give him no indication until I had spoken to Mr. Phillips<note n="53" xml:id="d276fn53">William Phillips, Under Secretary of
                                    State.</note> but I recognized the <pb facs="0508" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/> urgency of the matter. Dr. Leitner intimated
                                that he thought there were ways and means here whereby the
                                Government could ask newspaper owners to remove objectionable
                                correspondents. I told him that we recognized the shortness of the
                                time and that I would get in touch with him again this morning.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierrepont Moffat</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>