<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="335" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d335">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">800.8810/1153</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Berlin (<persName type="from">Messersmith</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1550</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-29">August 29,
                                        1933</date>.<lb/>[Received September 11.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my
                                confidential despatch No. 1521 of August 21<note n="14" xml:id="d335fn14">Not printed.</note> in which I reported on the
                                discriminatory measures which had been taken against the American
                                and foreign steamship lines in Germany through a decree of the
                                Ministry of Commerce dated August 7, 1933. In this despatch I
                                informed the Department that at a meeting in the Ministry of
                                Commerce the representatives of the foreign steamship lines were
                                informed that the discriminatory measures would be immediately
                                removed through a new decree.</p>
                            <p>This decree has appeared, and after carefully studying it I came to
                                the conclusion that it was entirely satisfactory from the point of
                                view of the American steamship lines. I am now informed by Mr.
                                Atterholt of the <pb facs="0580" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> United
                                States Lines, that he is convinced that under the new decree the
                                American lines will experience no difficulty and that there is no
                                discrimination under the procedure now established, against them in
                                favor of the German lines or vis-à-vis other foreign lines. The new
                                decree requires the foreign steamship lines and agencies in Germany
                                to make a monthly report to the authorities on the number of
                                passages they have sold and the total income from passage money
                                collected. They will also have to show every month the sums which
                                they have expended in Germany for operation and upkeep of their
                                passenger offices in Germany. The decree permits them to sell
                                passage to any person who may apply therefor irrespective of the
                                cost of the passage, without the companies or the passengers
                                securing previous authorization from the fiscal authorities. The
                                decree permits the American companies to pay out of their passage
                                money collected in Germany, their costs of operation in Germany and
                                then transmit without further authorization 50% of the balance. If
                                the company wishes to transfer more than 50% of the balance, it may
                                make special application for such transfer. As the American lines
                                spend a good deal of the money which they receive from passenger
                                income in Germany for the operation of their vessels from Hamburg
                                and Bremen as well as for the maintenance of their passenger offices
                                and operating offices in Germany, the prescriptions with regard to
                                the transfer of funds do not offer any inconvenience to the American
                                lines. The American lines have not up to now had any difficulty in
                                transferring any of their funds which they wished to transfer, and
                                Mr. Atterholt believes that they will not have any difficulty in the
                                future under the new decree in this respect.</p>
                            <p>I am glad to be able to report the satisfactory settlement of this
                                matter. The wide publicity which the planned discriminatory action
                                had in the English and so far as I know, in the American press,
                                undoubtedly had a very excellent effect in bringing about this rapid
                                adjustment. There is transmitted herewith a clipping from the <hi rend="italic">Berliner Tageblatt</hi> of August 24,<note n="15" xml:id="d335fn15">Not reprinted.</note> giving the contents of
                                the new decree. As the matter is satisfactorily adjusted, I have not
                                deemed it necessary to make a translation of this article or to
                                submit a translation of the new decree.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">George S. Messersmith</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>