<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Latvia (Skinner)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d440</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">440</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="440"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d440">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">660P.1111/1</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Latvia (<persName type="to">Skinner</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 182</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-04-04">April 4,
                            1933</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to the Legation’s despatch No.
                    1192 of March 3, 1933,<note n="1" xml:id="d440fn1">Not printed.</note> reporting
                    on the conference of American Government officers in Latvia, and more
                    particularly to page 4 [<hi rend="italic">2</hi>] of enclosure thereto where the
                    following discussion with respect to trade promotion is set down in the report
                    of the conference: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Commercial Attaché, Mr. Morse, reported that he had not noticed any
                            tendency on the part of the Latvian Foreign Exchange Committee to
                            discontinue its discrimination against importers of products from the
                            United States. Four specific instances came to his attention since the
                            last meeting where representatives of American firms had received orders
                            from Latvian Government departments for goods manufactured in the United
                            States and in each the Foreign Exchange Committee had refused to
                            authorize the importers to pay for the goods in dollars. In each of
                            these instances the importers were instructed by the Latvian Foreign
                            Exchange Committee to place the order in countries other than the United
                            States, regardless of the fact that to do so would increase the cost to
                            the departments requiring the goods.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The report of the proceedings of the conference fails to record what action, if
                    any, was taken by the Legation in connection with these four cases which, in so
                    far as the facts are set forth by Mr. Morse, appear to constitute discrimination
                    against American trade by officials of the Latvian Government. There is nothing
                    in the report to show whether the Legation called upon the Commercial Attaché to
                    furnish it with specific and detailed information regarding these cases with a
                    view to making representations, either formally or informally, to the Latvian
                    Foreign Office with regard to such discrimination against American trade.</p>
                <p>The Department has noted in a number of other reports of the proceedings of the
                    conferences of American officers at Riga similar statements regarding
                    discrimination by Latvian officials against American trade. Mention in this
                    connection is made among others of the Legation’s <pb facs="0707" n="603"
                        xml:id="pg_603"/> despatch No. 1096 of January 26, 1933,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d440fn2">Not printed.</note> in which on page 2 you discuss such
                    discrimination, and in the enclosure to which on pages 4 and 5 the Commercial
                    Attaché reported in general terms allegations of discriminatory actions. It is
                    noted that no reference is made in these reports of any action taken or
                    contemplated by the Legation in the protection of American interests suffering
                    as a result of this alleged discrimination; nor has the Legation reported in
                    subsequent individual despatches any action taken by it in connection with the
                    various points raised in the discussions at the conferences in question of
                    alleged discrimination against American trade.</p>
                <p>The Department suggests that cases involving discrimination brought to the
                    attention either of the Legation or the Consulate from whatever source be
                    subjected to a careful and exhaustive scrutiny with a view to the determination
                    of their merits and the basis of any possible protest to the competent Latvian
                    authorities. If the Commercial Attaché should, in the work of his office in
                    connection with the promotion of American trade, become conversant with and
                    report to the Legation cases, similar to those referred to in the above
                    quotation, which appear to involve discrimination, he should be directed to
                    submit promptly to the Legation in writing a report containing detailed
                    information of a factual character covering the cases. The Legation should then
                    itself make, or call upon the Consulate to make, such supplementary
                    investigation as may be necessary to determine the additional facts essential to
                    a proper consideration of the case which may not have been available to the
                    office of the Commercial Attaché.</p>
                <p>As the Department has already pointed out to the Legation in its instruction No.
                    90 of August 2, 1932,<note n="2" xml:id="d440fn3">Not printed.</note> the
                    function of protecting the interests of American trade is inherently a
                    prerogative and an obligation of the Department and its representatives abroad.
                    The Department expects its representatives in the field to take prompt and
                    appropriate measures in the protection of American commercial interests when
                    cases involving discrimination against our trade come to their attention.</p>
                <p>In order that the Department may have an accurate record of laws, regulations and
                    acts tending to discriminate against American trade, the Legation is directed to
                    submit quarterly beginning April 1, 1933, a survey of its activities in
                    protecting American trade. This survey, which is not intended to supplant
                    reports on important individual developments of this nature, should outline for
                    the preceding quarter the new legislation, regulations, and practices which
                    operate to restrict or to discriminate against American trade, list the specific
                    instances of discrimination coming to the attention of the Legation, and report
                    the action taken by <pb facs="0708" n="604" xml:id="pg_604"/> the Legation and
                    the results thereof. It is anticipated that the Legation and the Consulate will
                    cooperate to the fullest extent in the performance of this important work.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilbur J. Carr</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
