<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Rumania (Owsley) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d489</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">489</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="489"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d489">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">671.116/24</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Rumania (<persName type="from"
                            >Owsley</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 26</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-11-03">November 3,
                            1933</date>.<lb/>[Received November 29.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the Department’s
                    instruction No. 10 of October 13, 1933,<note n="46" xml:id="d489fn46">Not
                        printed.</note> relative to the difficulties which three American concerns
                    have encountered in exporting their products into Rumania <pb facs="0795"
                        n="691" xml:id="pg_691"/> under the present Rumanian import quota system.
                    The firms mentioned were namely: <list>
                        <item>Firestone Tire and Rubber Export Company, Akron, Ohio.</item>
                        <item>Atlas Asbestos Company, North Wales, Pennsylvania.</item>
                        <item>McLaughlin Gormley King Company, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>As is well understood by the Department, we here have a very heavy burden cast
                    upon us to overcome the discrimination the Rumanian import quota law places upon
                    proposed American exporters into Rumania. There is an apparent direct
                    discrimination against American goods and against American manufacturers and
                    traders. The record is replete with unmistakable evidence of discrimination. The
                    case of the General Railway Signal Company,<note n="47" xml:id="d489fn47">See
                            <ref target="frus1932v02#pg_508">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1932, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 508</ref> ff.</note> now history, is
                    only the beginning. This case loomed large because of the size of the contract
                    and the extent of the effort made by the Legation to secure this contract for
                    the American concern. Many other cases have accumulated, and now are
                    accumulating, the three cases at hand among them.</p>
                <p>In the mail on yesterday, Thursday, November 2, 1933, I transmitted a written
                    communication to the Director General of the Rumanian State Railways, asking for
                    the full payment to the Bedford Petroleum Company of 20,000 American dollars for
                    a special quality of lubricating oil sold to the Government. This case would not
                    be of any particular importance or significance but for the fact that a French
                    concern having a like demand against the Rumanian Government was paid a week or
                    so ago, and the American representative of the American concern had not been
                    paid. There may be circumstances warranting a delay in payment of the American
                    concern and a favoring of the French concern, but we were not able to discover
                    them.</p>
                <p>Within the last three weeks I personally called upon Mr. Gafencu, Under-Secretary
                    of State for the Ministry of Industry and Commerce, and pled the cause of the
                    representatives of several American concerns, for entry permits and for
                    increases in import allotments based on the import percentage of 1931 and 1932.
                    The personal visit to the Under-Secretary was partially rewarded with
                    success.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to further call the attention of the Department to the past
                    effort of the Legation through my predecessor, Mr. Charles S. Wilson, and the
                    present Secretary of the Legation, Mr. J. C. Holmes, when acting as Chargé
                    d’Affaires ad interim at this Legation before I assumed charge. It has become a
                    fixed opinion at this office now that we shall continue to have our troubles and
                    that our difficulties will grow until a change in the present policy of the
                    Government now in power is brought about. It is not beyond the realm of
                    speculation to predict a very decided <pb facs="0796" n="692" xml:id="pg_692"/>
                    shake-up and change in the present Government, or its fall and complete loss of
                    power. Only by constantly keeping at it and making frequent demands and personal
                    calls upon those in authority in the Rumanian Government, yes, only by eternal
                    vigilance, can we expect a partial measure of success for American concerns.</p>
                <p>Less than three weeks ago I personally interviewed Mr. Madgearu, Minister of
                    Finance, on a similar matter, and reminded him as forcefully as possible of the
                    assurances given to the Government of the United States by the Rumanian Ministry
                    of Foreign Affairs as set forth in the Legation’s telegram No. 12 of June 15,
                    1933, six P.M., and the response was practically negative. At the same time Mr.
                    Madgearu suggested that the United States Government and the Government of
                    Rumania should hurriedly enter into reciprocal trade agreements in order that
                    our apparent differences might be settled as far as possible.</p>
                <p>I thanked him for his very valuable suggestion, bearing in mind all the while the
                    views of the Department concerning our trade treaty status.</p>
                <p>At the time of the present writing the S.A.R. de Telefoane, (the Telephone
                    Company of Rumania,) has appealed to the Legation for immediate assistance in
                    connection with the transfer and change from the old system to the new automatic
                    system, which automatically under their franchise and trade operation agreement
                    grants to the Telephone Company an increase in telephone rates. Already I have
                    called upon the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr. Titulescu, and have interceded
                    for the Telephone Company. A serious crisis has arisen. The press of Rumania is
                    denouncing the American telephone company and Americans in a very unfavorable
                    way. The matter is in suspension now, and will be the subject of a special
                    despatch to the Department when enough accurate information is obtained, or a
                    correct report of the matter, to be presented.</p>
                <p>In obedience to the present instruction which I now have in hand, conferences and
                    engagements with the proper Rumanian authorities have been asked for and our
                    request is expected to be granted immediately. Further reports concerning these
                    instructions will follow.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alvin M. Owsley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
