<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Treaty Division (Barnes)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d539</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">539</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="539"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d539">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5831/69</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Treaty Division (Barnes)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-10-18">October 18,
                            1933</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Boström called on Mr. Barnes in pursuance of an understanding between him and
                    the Secretary of State that he keep in touch with Mr. Barnes with reference to
                    ascertaining when the Department would be in a position to begin conversations
                    with him for the negotiation of a reciprocity treaty between the United States
                    and Sweden.</p>
                <p>Mr. Boström stated that he was authorized by his Government to begin
                    conversations. He stated that about 70 per cent, of the Swedish imports into the
                    United States were wood pulp and newsprint, which were on the free list; and
                    that there were a few articles the chief of which as he recalled impromptu were
                    matches and certain manufactures of steel imported from Sweden on which the
                    duties are high. He stated that his Government would probably ask for
                    continuation of wood pulp and newsprint on the free list and for reductions in
                    the duties on matches and certain steel manufactures.</p>
                <p>The Minister also stated, on the other hand, that the rates of the <pb
                        facs="0826" n="722" xml:id="pg_722"/> Swedish tariff with very few
                    exceptions are low and that there was little which Sweden could accord the
                    United States in the way of reductions of import duties. The Minister referred
                    to the fact that the flour-mixing regulations in force in Sweden under which
                    millers are required to use a certain percentage of native wheat in all flour
                    had been mentioned by Mr. Barnes in a conversation with Mr. Weidel, Commercial
                    Counselor of the Swedish Legation, several weeks previously, and the Minister
                    stated that he was confident that his Government would be unable to agree to any
                    change in these milling regulations which contemplated an increase in
                    importations of wheat.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that primarily his Government would desire an assurance that
                    there would be no increase in import duties on Swedish products under the
                    National Recovery Act<note n="4" xml:id="d539fn4">48 Stat. 195.</note> in the
                    United States. He stated that an assurance on this point would be a condition
                    precedent to beginning negotiations. The Minister said that he had mentioned the
                    last point to the Secretary of State about a week previously and that the
                    Secretary informed him that consideration would be given to harmonizing the
                    proposed reciprocity negotiations with the execution of the National Recovery
                    Act.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles M. Barnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
