<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Consul at Geneva (Gilbert)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d677</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">677</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-02-04T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-02-04T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec90c76a0ac666292" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="public-health" subject="public-health">Public Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-02-04T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-02-04T21:00:00-05:00" n="677"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d677">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.01 Foreign Control/504: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Consul at Geneva (<persName type="to">Gilbert</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-02-04T21:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 4, 1933—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>17. For Reber. Your telegram No. 39, February 3, 7 p.m. If the attitude of the
                    Committee remains as you reported, the prospect of the usefulness of future
                    attempts to seek a solution of the Liberian problem by international action
                    seems frankly discouraging. I feel that the time has come when we must make our
                    point of view a matter of record: you should accordingly write a letter to
                    Viscount Cecil, in reply to his <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of
                    yesterday, along the following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. It is difficult for the American Government to see how the
                                Committee can view the situation brought about by Liberia’s
                                unilateral destruction of the Finance Corporation contract as
                                representing merely a dispute between Liberia and the Firestone
                                interests, or as having only a remote connection with the
                                realization of the plan of assistance.</item>
                            <item>“2. While the Committee must obviously be the judge of its own
                                terms of reference, the invitation addressed to the American
                                Government by the Acting Secretary General of the League on January
                                30, 1931, contained the following sentence: The Committee might
                                among other <pb facs="1002" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/> matters
                                examine the question of administrative assistance necessary for
                                giving effect to the social reforms suggested by the Commission of
                                Inquiry and also the question of financial and public health
                                assistance with a view to the carrying out of these reforms.’<note
                                    n="30" xml:id="d677fn30">See telegram No. 18, January 31, 1931,
                                    from the Minister in Switzerland, <ref
                                        target="frus1931v02#pg_669">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1931, vol. <hi
                                            rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 669</ref>.</note>
                                ‘Financial assistance’ from the Firestone interests has repeatedly
                                been stressed by the Committee as one of the essentials precedent to
                                the execution of its plan: in fact, as the American Government views
                                the record, it is essential in the eyes of the Committee.</item>
                            <item>“3. The Committee’s plan as drafted, as accepted by the American
                                Government as a basis for direct negotiations between the Firestone
                                interests and Liberia, as endorsed on that basis by the American
                                Government to the Finance Corporation, and as accepted by the
                                Finance Corporation, envisages modification on terms mutually to be
                                agreed upon of the Corporation’s contractual rights and advance by
                                the Corporation to Liberia of not insignificant further funds.
                                Action such as Liberia’s unilateral destruction of the Corporation’s
                                existing contract obviously precludes either direct negotiations or
                                further advance of funds until the action has been withdrawn, and
                                thus automatically creates a condition in which the entire scheme
                                must fail of realization.</item>
                            <item>“4. If there is any ‘dispute’ between the Finance Corporation and
                                Liberia, it can be brought up during the direct negotiations which
                                the Corporation informed the Committee it would attend promptly
                                after the condition referred to above had been removed.</item>
                            <item>“5. The suggestion considered by the Committee that Liberia should
                                be invited to ‘suspend the operation of the measures’ does not seem
                                to the American Government to be equivalent to ‘withdrawal’, since
                                the former not only implies recognition of an illegal act but
                                implies also that if the negotiations did not result in agreement,
                                the ‘suspension’ itself would lapse. Moreover, whatever the theory
                                envisaged by the Committee in the suggestion that Liberia should
                                ‘suspend’, the fact (in contrast to the theory) is that unless
                                Liberia’s illegal actions are withdrawn, direct negotiations between
                                the Finance Corporation and Liberia under the terms of the League
                                plan can not take place. In this the Firestone interests can count
                                upon the absolute support of the American Government.</item>
                            <item>“6. The American Government has cooperated sincerely and
                                disinterestedly in the work of the Committee and it still hopes to
                                be able to continue to do so, in pursuance of its policy of seeking
                                to promote a solution of the Liberian problem by international
                                cooperation. Nevertheless, the American Government cannot divest
                                itself of the duty of protecting the legitimately acquired interests
                                of its citizens, and unless the Committee is prepared to impress
                                upon Liberia that its actions in connection with the League plan
                                must be based on good faith and the sanctity of contracts, it is
                                difficult to see how future cooperation can be real or
                                effective.</item>
                            <item>“7. Bearing these factors in mind, the American Government is
                                confident that it can count upon the support of the Committee.
                                Unless and until Liberia’s illegal actions have been withdrawn, it
                                is obvious that no progress can be made, and in the opinion of the
                                American Government <pb facs="1003" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/> the
                                onus for failure of the plan of assistance will rest squarely upon
                                Liberia.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>For your own information: in connection with paragraph 5 above, it may be that
                    the desired object of withdrawal might be obtained by nullification of the
                    illegal Liberian legislation by the Liberian court. However, it seems to me that
                    the manner in which the withdrawal is made is Liberia’s concern.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
