<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Great Britain
                    (Bingham)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-06-28T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-06-28T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-06-28T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-06-28T17:00:00-05:00" n="699"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.01 Foreign Control/577: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Great Britain (<persName type="to"
                        >Bingham</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-06-28T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 28, 1933—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>176. For General Winship. Your 194 and 195, June 28. I appreciate the valuable
                    progress you have made in the recent negotiations at London and for the first
                    time feel that we are within appreciable distance of success. I am particularly
                    encouraged by the fact that the Firestone interests here now seem thoroughly in
                    favor of the plan of assistance and are pressing for its acceptance by Liberia.
                    With the progress thus made, I am anxious to do everything possible to push
                    matters to an ultimate conclusion.</p>
                <p>Firestone Junior telegraphed last night to Akron that Cecil had requested you “to
                    accompany Mackenzie to aid in securing adoption of plan. Winship is cabling
                    American State Department for instructions.” He continues “We feel very strongly
                    that Winship should be instructed to return to Liberia as important to
                    successful outcome and also to keep our Government in position of actively
                    supporting and working for this program”. I should appreciate your advice and
                    recommendations as to the advisability of your returning for a month with Grimes
                    and Mackenzie and remaining until a decision has been reached in Liberia prior
                    to the meeting of the Council in September. I personally took up the matter with
                    General Mac Arthur,<note n="54" xml:id="d699fn54">General Douglas MacArthur,
                        Chief of Staff, United States Army.</note> who says that he has no objection
                    to your return to Liberia under the conditions outlined and leaves the matter to
                    your best judgment.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
