<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.42157SA29/1041</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Canadian Minister (<persName type="from">Herridge</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 8</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-01-13">January 13,
                                        1933</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honour to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your note of January 13th, 1933, relating to the effect
                                of the Great Lakes–St. Lawrence Deep Waterway Treaty upon the
                                diversion of the waters of the St. Lawrence River at Massena.</p>
                            <p>My Government shares the views of the United States Government that
                                it was not the purpose of the Treaty to fix, in any respect, the
                                policy to be pursued in regard to the maintenance of such diversion.
                                It is the view of the Canadian Government that the continuance or
                                discontinuance of that diversion is a purely domestic matter for
                                determination by competent authorities in the United States.</p>
                            <p>The Canadian Government, therefore, joins with the United States
                                Government in a declaration of the following principles: <pb facs="0204" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The effect of the Great Lakes–St. Lawrence Deep Waterway
                                        Treaty, signed at Washington July 18th, 1932, is not, in any
                                        respect, to recognize, confirm, or establish any rights or
                                        claims of any person or corporation, in respect to the
                                        diversion of water for power purposes through the Massena
                                        Canal and Grass River, or to limit the freedom of the United
                                        States or the State of New York, or other competent
                                        authority, to treat the question of the continuance, control
                                        or elimination of such diversion as a domestic
                                        question;</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The Canadian Government does hereby and will, upon
                                        request, formally consent to the modification or elimination
                                        of the works provided for in the report of the Joint Board
                                        of Engineers, in connection with the said diversion through
                                        the Massena Canal;</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The Canadian Government recognizes that the competent
                                        authorities in the United States are free to eliminate the
                                        diversion of water for power purposes through the Massena
                                        Canal and Grass River, and to use the water so released
                                        through the main river works in conformity with the
                                        provisions of Article IV of the said Treaty.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">W. D. Herridge</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>