<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-10-18T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-10-18T18:00:00-05:00" n="725" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d725">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">882.01 Foreign Control/687:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in France (<persName type="to">Straus</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-10-18T18:00:00-05:00">October 18, 1933—6 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>304. For General Winship. We have just received the following
                                telegram dated October 17, 2 p.m., from Werlich:<note n="84" xml:id="d725fn84">McCeney Werlich, Chargé in Liberia.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“President of Liberia is expected to deliver his annual
                                        message to the Legislature end of this week; understand he
                                        has delayed so far pending result of present Geneva
                                        negotiations.</p>
                                    <p>[“] Rumor is increasingly insistent that the Legislature will
                                        refuse League Plan and call upon President Barclay to resign
                                        in favor of Vice President Smith, and that the latter will
                                        accept the Presidency only on condition that ex-President
                                        King is made Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.</p>
                                    <p>[“] Ex-President King, who is doubtlessly behind Barclay
                                        resignation project, has told me twice that he is flatly
                                        against any plan under League of Nations patronage
                                        especially since the United States is reported to have
                                        agreed to a non-American Chief Adviser. He has told me he
                                        favors a Liberian Legislature commission waiting on you in
                                        Washington to request some form of all American advisership;
                                        although he was not clear as to what authority or scope such
                                        advisers should have, he stated that purpose would be to
                                        rehabilitate Liberian finances. Obviously, he had in mind
                                        again interesting United States directly in Liberia.</p>
                                    <p>“I envisage possibility of such a Legislature commission and
                                        would appreciate your instructions for such eventuality.</p>
                                    <p>“I would recommend my being instructed to discourage any
                                        commission go[ing] to the United States primarily on account
                                        of the expense and I would be inclined to refuse visas on
                                        grounds suggested by you.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>If you concur, please send the following telegram to Monrovia as the
                                Department’s No. 48.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Your 84, October 17, 2 p.m. The American Government believes and
                                    is definitely committed to the policy that international
                                    cooperation offers the most feasible means of assistance to
                                    Liberia. We feel that the Plan of Assistance adopted by the
                                    Council of the League on October 14 last is fair and workable,
                                    and it is the expectation of the American Government that
                                    Liberia will accept this Plan.</p>
                                <p>“It is not in accordance with our policy for the American
                                    Government to accept any exclusive responsibility in Africa and
                                    we would thus not receive a ‘Commission’ from Liberia to discuss
                                    ‘some form of all American advisership’.</p>
                                <p>“You will be guided by the foregoing in dealing with any
                                    situation which may arise in Monrovia.</p>
                                <p>“We are sending you this telegram through General Winship.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>If you have any suggestions regarding our proposed reply quoted
                                above, please telegraph them at once.</p>
                            <pb facs="1066" n="962" xml:id="pg_962"/>
                            <p>In order that there may not be any possible misunderstanding on the
                                part of the members of the League-Liberian Committee of our position
                                in regard to this matter, we feel that it is desirable that you
                                write Cecil informally in the sense of these two telegrams.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>