<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="748" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d748">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.90f2/12</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Great Britain (<persName type="from">Atherton</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 2553</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-02">February 2,
                                        1932</date>.<lb/>[Received February 10.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                                Department’s instruction No. 953, October 12, 1931 (File No. 890
                                    F.01/37),<note n="3" xml:id="d748fn3">File number changed to
                                    711.90f2/6; <ref target="frus1931v02#pg_552">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 552</ref>.</note> relating
                                to an exchange of notes between the Government of the United States
                                and the Government of the Kingdom of the Hedjaz and Nejd and its
                                Dependencies, pending an opportunity for the negotiation of a formal
                                treaty of commerce and navigation, and to forward herewith a copy of
                                a memorandum, dated January 29, 1932, together with a draft of a
                                provisional agreement,<note n="4" xml:id="d748fn4">Draft of
                                    provisional agreement not printed.</note> which the Hedjazi
                                Minister left with me in reply to the Ambassador’s memorandum of
                                October 22, 1931.<note n="5" xml:id="d748fn5">Not printed; see
                                    instruction No. 953, October 12, 1931, <ref target="frus1931v02#pg_552">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1931, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 552</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>It will be noted from the Hedjazi Minister’s memorandum that the
                                Government of the Kingdom of the Hedjaz and Nejd has approved the
                                text proposed by the Government of the United States, with the
                                exception of a few minor modifications.</p>
                            <p>In amplification of his memorandum, the Hedjazi Minister stated that
                                modification I (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) refers to the Holy Places
                                only for Mohammedans.</p>
                            <p>As regards modification I (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), the omission of
                                the clause “and they shall not be treated in a manner less favorable
                                than similar officers of any other foreign country” should be
                                interpreted in no way to indicate that there would at any time be
                                any difference in the treatment accorded to American consular
                                officers and that accorded to consular officers of any <pb facs="1091" n="987" xml:id="pg_987"/> other country. According
                                to the Hedjazi Minister, this clause has been omitted from all
                                treaties since the Treaty of Jeddah, dated May 20, 1927,<note n="6" xml:id="d748fn6">Treaty of Friendship and Good Understanding
                                    with Great Britain; League of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">lxxi</hi>, p. 131.</note> and his
                                Government, I gather, attaches some importance to its omission,
                                since <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> certain Mohammedan consuls
                                might have certain consideration in travel areas, etc.</p>
                            <p>In regard to modification II, the Hedjazi Government would prefer to
                                leave out the words “and interests”, since, as stated by the Hedjazi
                                Minister, in the opinion of his Government it is an undefinable
                                term.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ray Atherton</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Hedjazi Minister in Great Britain
                                            (<persName type="from">Wahba</persName>) to the American
                                        Chargé (<persName type="to">Atherton</persName>)</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The Government of His Majesty the King of Hedjaz and Nejd, as has
                                    been previously intimated, heartily reciprocates the wish of the
                                    Government of the United States of America to conclude a
                                    provisional Agreement in regard to consular and diplomatic
                                    representation, juridical protection, commerce and navigation,
                                    between the two countries and signifies its readiness to do so
                                    at the earliest possible opportunity by means of the exchange of
                                    notes between the Ambassador of the United States of America and
                                    the Minister of the Hedjaz and Nejd in London.</p>
                                <p>His Majesty’s Government having examined the text proposed by the
                                    Government of the United States of America has approved it, with
                                    a few minor modifications, for reasons which I shall explain in
                                    person and which I hope will prove acceptable to the American
                                    Government. These modifications have been embodied in the
                                    enclosed proposed text<note n="7" xml:id="d748fn7">Not
                                        printed.</note> and are as follows:—</p>
                                <p>I. In Part 1 Two modifications have been introduced:</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The following words have been inserted
                                    at the end of the first clause in the second sentence:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“in the places wherein consular representatives are by
                                            local laws permitted to reside;”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">The clause in question now reads as follows:—
                                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The consular representatives of each country, duly
                                            provided with exequatur, will be permitted to reside in
                                            the territories of the other, in the places wherein
                                            consular representatives are by local laws permitted to
                                            reside”.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <pb facs="1092" n="988" xml:id="pg_988"/>
                                <p rend="flushleft">This of course means that the consular
                                    representatives of the United States of America will be allowed
                                    to reside wherever other consular representatives are
                                    allowed.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The third clause in the second
                                    sentence, which reads as follows:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“and they shall not be treated in a manner less favorable
                                            than similar officers of any other foreign country.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">has been omitted.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">This clause has been omitted from all treaties
                                    concluded after the Treaty of Jedda and therefore has no
                                    existence in the Treaties which His Majesty’s Government
                                    concluded with Persia,<note n="8" xml:id="d748fn8">Treaty of
                                        Friendship, August 24, 1929, <hi rend="italic">British and
                                            Foreign State Papers</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cxxxi</hi>, p. 490.</note> Germany,<note n="9" xml:id="d748fn9">Treaty of Friendship, April 26, 1929, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 371.</note> Turkey,<note n="10" xml:id="d748fn10">Treaty of Friendship, August 3,
                                        1929, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 491.</note> Iraq<note n="11" xml:id="d748fn11">Treaty of Friendship and
                                        Neighbourship, April 7, 1931, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                                        vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cxxxiv</hi>, p. 899.</note> and
                                        France.<note n="12" xml:id="d748fn12">Treaty of Friendship,
                                        November 10, 1931, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        823.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>II. In Part 2, in the second sentence the words “and interests”
                                    have been omitted. Thus the second sentence now reads as
                                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“In respect of their persons and possessions and rights”
                                            … instead of</p>
                                        <p>“In respect of their persons and possessions, rights and
                                            interests” …</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p>III. In Part 6 the last clause which reads as follows:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“but in the case of divergence in the interpretation of
                                            any part of the agreement the English text shall
                                            prevail”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">has been omitted.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">This clause has been omitted from all treaties
                                    concluded after the treaty of Jedda.</p>
                                <p>Apart from these modifications the text remains the same as it
                                    was proposed by the Government of the United States of
                                    America.</p>
                                <p>The Minister of the Hedjaz and Nejd is authorized to sign and
                                    transmit to the American Ambassador the enclosed note<note n="13" xml:id="d748fn13">Not printed.</note> upon being
                                    advised by the latter of his authorisation to reply thereto in
                                    identical terms.</p>
                                <closer><dateline rendition="#left">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="hijri gregorian" when="1932-01-29">21 Ramadan,
                                            1350. / 29 January, 1932</date></dateline></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>