<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.47H31/36</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Economic Adviser
                                    (Livesey)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-15">August 15,
                                        1933</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Mr. Masters<note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">Robert Masters, New Zealand
                                    Minister of Industries and Commerce.</note> called by
                                appointment arranged by Mr. H. O. Chalkley, Commercial Counselor of
                                the British Embassy, with the Secretary’s office. He was accompanied
                                by Mr. J. W. Collins, New Zealand Trade Commissioner, Toronto,
                                Canada; Mr. W. J. Stevenson, Official Representative, Customs
                                Department, Dominion of New Zealand, New York; and Dr. R. M.
                                Campbell, Economic Adviser to the New Zealand Delegation to the
                                Monetary and Economic Conference. The Americans present were Mr.
                                Frederick Livesey, Acting Economic Adviser; Mr. John D. Hickerson,
                                Acting Chief, Division of Western European Affairs; Dr. <pb facs="0224" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/> Wallace McClure, Assistant
                                Chief of the Treaty Division; Mr. Paul T. Culbertson and Mr. John R.
                                Minter of the Division of Western European Affairs.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Masters said he had called at the Department of Commerce in the
                                morning on advice from the British Embassy that that Department
                                would be charged with commercial negotiations but had been referred
                                by the Department of Commerce to the Department of State, after an
                                opportunity had been given for discussion with various commodity
                                experts. He was interested in discussing the possibilities of a
                                trade agreement with the United States. New Zealand was a producer
                                of raw materials and its interest would be in the sale of such
                                products in the United States. In return it would be glad to
                                facilitate the sale of certain American products in New Zealand by
                                favorable tariff terms. New Zealand does not have a high tariff for
                                protective purposes as do, for example, Australia and Canada. Its
                                tariffs are for revenue.</p>
                            <p>Asked regarding the tariff on automobiles, Mr. Masters said it was
                                about 45% on American cars, being unusually high on this
                                product.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Masters was told that the officials charged with such matters in
                                the Washington Departments had made certain general studies of trade
                                relations in preparation for reciprocity negotiations and were now
                                making intensive studies in preparation for exploratory
                                conversations which had been announced with five different
                                countries. The New Zealand situation had not yet been intensively
                                studied and could not immediately be so studied in view of current
                                pressure of other studies. The United States would be keenly
                                interested in obtaining a reciprocal trade agreement with New
                                Zealand, would be glad to give intensive study to the subject as
                                soon as possible, and in the meantime welcomed the opportunity for
                                informal discussion with Mr. Masters.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Masters suggested that we run over the situation with regard to
                                New Zealand products. In reply to a suggestion that it would be
                                undesirable to have any public indication of discussion of
                                particular commodities, Mr. Masters suggested the conversations
                                should be strictly confidential on both sides. No publicity had been
                                given to his visit to the Department and the New Zealand visitors
                                did not expect to have any further contact with reporters in this
                                country.</p>
                            <p>The first commodity taken up was wool. Mr. Masters stated that New
                                Zealand wool valued at 12 cents is subject to thirty-four cents
                                American duty. The United States is not self-sufficient in wool and
                                New Zealand would be glad if the duty on its wool could be lowered
                                to facilitate sale in the United States. In the discussion, the
                                suggestion was made that as the United States expects to negotiate
                                under the unconditional most-favored-nation clause and to generalize
                                the negotiated rates to all countries which do not discriminate
                                against American trade, <pb facs="0225" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/> it
                                would have to make a careful study of a commodity like wool which is
                                of importance to the trade of several countries such as Australia,
                                the Argentine and South Africa, as well as New Zealand, and
                                carefully determine the most advantageous policy. The Americans
                                present did not have the expert knowledge regarding wool to judge
                                whether, for example, there were any special characteristics of New
                                Zealand wool which would justify a tariff treatment different from
                                that given to wools from other countries. Mr. Masters said that in
                                that precise connection he and his assistants were proceeding to
                                Boston August 17 to examine into the conditions in the American wool
                                market. He was of the impression that New Zealand wool was of a
                                distinctive grade not produced in the United States and therefore
                                not directly competitive.</p>
                            <p>In reference to butter, Mr. Masters was told that apparently the
                                United States is working into a position of self-sufficiency and
                                overproduction for the domestic market. American dairy farming was
                                generally regarded as one of the relative prosperous branches of
                                agriculture but the newspapers were currently reporting rioting in
                                New York State with farmers blockading roads and spilling milk on
                                way to market, and similar troubles had been reported from other
                                States. The Agricultural Adjustment Administration is considering
                                codes for milk producers in the districts supplying the different
                                metropolitan centers—Mr. Masters was shown some twenty mimeographed
                                tentative codes of this sort. The details of this situation are
                                naturally obscure to all except specialists but it did not seem to
                                offer favorable prospects for tariff concessions. The New Zealanders
                                developed considerable interest in this situation <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The question as to the possibilities of marketing New Zealand mutton
                                in the United States was raised by a question on the American side.
                                Mr. Masters expressed great confidence in the possibility of
                                marketing New Zealand mutton, in view of its quality, were there not
                                a prohibitive tariff.</p>
                            <p>The conversation having lasted an hour or more, Mr. Masters broke off
                                the discussion of individual commodities and raised the question of
                                the possibility of negotiations. New Zealand was eager to have a
                                trade agreement—the mere knowledge of this fact might be of interest
                                to the United States at the moment of tariff discussions with the
                                Argentine. He was assured that the United States also desires a
                                tariff agreement and will be glad to take the matter up when it is
                                practical to do so. Mr. Masters inquired how the New Zealand
                                Government would learn that the United States is ready to negotiate.
                                Would it be necessary that all negotiations be conducted at
                                Washington? How can the New Zealand Government keep in touch with
                                the situation? He was assured that this Government will give the New
                                Zealand Government timely information <pb facs="0226" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/> and reference was made in this connection to
                                the correspondence already exchanged between the New Zealand
                                Government and the American Consul General at Wellington.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>