<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="153" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00 R 29/2601</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">J. P. Morgan</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-12-22"><hi rend="italic">December 22,
                                    1922</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received December
                            26.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Hughes</hi>: I have naturally been thinking
                            a good deal over the things we talked about the other day, and have had
                            a new idea, which I expounded to Mr. Thomas,<note n="29" xml:id="d153fn29">Albert Thomas, French citizen, Director of the
                                International Labor Office of the League of Nations.</note> who came
                            to see me this morning. He asked what course I would recommend, which
                            would be of advantage at present in France, and I said that it seemed to
                            me that if Mr. Poincaré would say to his own people something on the
                            following lines, it might have a beneficial effect. He might say to
                            them— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is quite true that Germany is in default and that we have the
                                    right and the power to occupy the Ruhr Basin, or inflict any
                                    other of the penalties embodied in the Treaty. We are not yet
                                    sure, however, that this is the best and wisest way of
                                    accomplishing the purpose, which is that, not only of France,
                                    but of all the Allies; namely, getting the most out of Germany
                                    that she can possibly pay. This question we are going to have
                                    studied, and, when we arrive at a conclusion in that connection,
                                    we will take such action, with your permission, as may be
                                    finally decided upon as being the wisest and best course to
                                    attain this great and necessary object.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>It seems to me that this would give him a very good platform to start out
                            upon, to get his international commission from all the <pb facs="0311" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/> countries to examine the subject and
                            report to the various governments.</p>
                        <p>I feel that it is important to keep you advised of anything I do in the
                            matter, hence this letter.</p>
                        <p>Yours faithfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Morgan</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>