<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-09-01T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-09-01T16:00:00-05:00" n="432" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d432">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/1354: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Russell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port au
                                        Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-09-01T16:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">September 1,
                                        1922—4 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received September 5—10:30
                                    a.m.<note n="59" xml:id="d432fn59">Text printed from corrected
                                    copy received Sept. 21, 1922.</note>]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>102. Department’s August 30, 4 p.m. Draft of the law is as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>[The draft opens with a preamble which is not printed.]</p>
                                <p>Article 1. The Secretary of Finance and Commerce is authorized to
                                    make an emission of $5,000,000 of gold bonds series B which
                                    shall be used concurrently with a part of the funds series A of
                                    $16,000,000 gold from the loan authorized by the law of June 26,
                                        1922,<note n="60" xml:id="d432fn60"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_500">p. 500</ref>.</note>
                                    first to the settlement of the interior debt 1912, 13 and 14,
                                    and then for the floating debt and diverse claims as they will
                                    be decided by the Claims Commission relative to the last two
                                    categories of debts.</p>
                                <p>Article 2. These bonds of series B will bear interest at the rate
                                    of 6 per cent per annum and shall be issued by the National Bank
                                    of the Republic of Haiti. A sufficient sum shall be drawn
                                    annually from the general receipts of the Republic which shall
                                    be reserved by the National Bank of the Republic of Haiti and
                                    used in the payment of the interest and amortization of the
                                    bonds series B under the same guarantee and privilege and time
                                    as for those of the series A.</p>
                                <p>Article 3. The bonds of series B shall be nominative,<note n="61" xml:id="d432fn61">i. e., registered.</note> transferable
                                        [<hi rend="italic">payable?</hi>] in Haiti as well for the
                                    capital as for the interest. They shall, as [<hi rend="italic">like</hi>] those of series A, be redeemed in 30 years by
                                    drawings at par or by purchase on bourse below par. The
                                    Government reserves the right to redeem said bonds from the 15th
                                    year of their date after reasonable previous notice being
                                    given.</p>
                                <p>Article 4. The expenses and other details of the emission of
                                    bonds shall be fixed by the Secretary of State of Finance and
                                    Commerce in accord with the Financial Adviser.[”]</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Article 5 is the usual abrogation clause.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Russell</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>