<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-10-09T09:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-10-09T09:40:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">839.00/2615: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Commissioner in the Dominican Republic</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santo
                                        Domingo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-10-09T10:00:00-04:40"><hi rend="italic">October 9,
                                        1922—10 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received October 10—4:15
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>28. Department’s October 4, 5 p.m. paragraph 2. In view of the
                            representations which I made to the members of the Commission in
                            accordance with the advice which I received from the officers commanding
                            the American forces of occupation, to the effect that conditions in the
                            bandit country in the Province of Seybo were such that immediate
                            withdrawal of all the American forces of occupation in that district
                            would undoubtedly create disturbances, the Commission requested that one
                            company of cavalry be retained at Chicharones in that province with a
                            base of supplies at San Pedro de [Macoris], until such time as the
                            Provisional Government should request their withdrawal and concentration
                            with the other troops in Santo Domingo City. This request was of course
                            agreed to by the Military Governor.</p>
                        <p>Since the Military Governor is inclined to interpret the instructions
                            which he has now received from the Navy Department as a result of the
                            letter received by the Secretary of the Navy from the Secretary of
                            State, to mean that the American marines must be concentrated within
                            three places notwithstanding the request of the members of the
                            Commission above referred to, I should be glad if the Department would
                            advise the Navy Department that this request of the Commission should be
                            complied with as previously agreed.<note n="47" xml:id="d55fn47">Request
                                complied with, Oct. 11, in letter to Secretary of the Navy, and the
                                Military Governor so instructed by the Acting Secretary of the Navy,
                                Oct. 12 (file no. 839.00/2622).</note>
                            <pb facs="0186" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/> It is the intention of the
                            Commission once the Policia Nacional Dominicana is recruited to its full
                            strength by the end of December, to strengthen the forces of the Policia
                            Nacional Dominicana in the Province of Seybo with the hope that when
                            such steps have been taken the American forces can be withdrawn.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>