<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="574" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d574">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.1211/36</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-05-05"><hi rend="italic">May 5,
                                1922</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received May 13.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5437</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your No. 2044, of April 15, 1922, relative to your desire to
                            leave nothing undone to promote friendly relations with Mexico and to
                            bring about an early and satisfactory solution of existing questions. I
                            am enclosing herewith a copy of my informal note No. 187, of April 20,
                                1922,<note n="10" xml:id="d574fn10">Not printed.</note> to Mr. Pani,
                            in which I addressed him in the sense of your above-mentioned
                            instruction.</p>
                        <p>I am now in receipt of Mr. Pani’s informal reply, dated May 4, 1922, a
                            copy and translation are enclosed herewith. Mr. Pani stated to me that
                            in his informal note he was replying frankly and in detail to my
                            informal note and in a like friendly manner. Mr. Pani stated that the
                            “religious” article in your proposed Treaty of Amity and Commerce was
                            directly in violation of the Mexican Constitution (of 1917), Article
                            130, seventh paragraph, final sentence, which reads as follows:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Only a Mexican by birth may be a minister of any religious creed
                                    in Mexico.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0767" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/>
                        <p>In this connection, Mr. Pani stated that foreigners, who are ministers of
                            religious creeds in Mexico are now practising their profession without
                            molestation on the part of the Mexican authorities.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">George T.
                            Summerlin</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="11" xml:id="d574fn11">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Mexican Secretary of State for Foreign
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Pani</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American
                                    Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-05-04"><hi rend="italic">May 4,
                                    1922</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Summerlin</hi>: Pursuant to
                                instructions which the President of the Republic has given me, I
                                have the honor to refer to your informal note number 187 of the 20th
                                    ultimo,<note n="12" xml:id="d574fn12">Not printed.</note> in
                                which you were pleased to inform me of the attitude of the
                                Government of the United States towards the contents of my informal
                                note of February 9th, and towards my other statements, likewise
                                unofficial.</p>
                            <p>The Government of Mexico appreciates highly the feelings which
                                animate the Government of the United States with regard to the
                                resumption of diplomatic relations between the two countries, as
                                well as its purpose to spare no efforts to bring about this
                                desirable object through a prompt and satisfactory solution of the
                                questions which are now pending. You may rest assured that so far as
                                my Government is concerned it is animated by feelings and aims no
                                less ardent and firm.</p>
                            <p>I fear, however, that despite its high purpose, the Government of the
                                United States has not given due consideration to that which is
                                essential in the attitude of the Government of Mexico towards the
                                problem in question, for thus only can I explain how my informal
                                note of February 9th could have been interpreted as an admission
                                that it is “consistent with the friendship between the two peoples
                                and compatible with a proper sense of national dignity, that
                                recognition should be given concurrently with the signing of a
                                treaty,” be this treaty convention no. 1 relating to claims, or the
                                proposed Treaty of Amity and Commerce; and how this interpretation
                                could have given rise to the statement contained in your note under
                                reply that “all objection to recognition through the signing of a
                                treaty apparently having disappeared,” and that the Government of
                                the United States “is disposed to sign first the claims convention
                                or conventions, provided it is clearly understood that the signing
                                of a Treaty of Amity and Commerce, with provisions previously agreed
                                upon and <pb facs="0768" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> put in draft form
                                (as in the ease of the claims conventions) shall follow without
                                delay.”</p>
                            <p>I have reread carefully the text of my note of February 9th and
                                therein I find nothing, either in spirit or in letter, that could be
                                understood in the above sense, and in support of this I take the
                                liberty to quote at length the two paragraphs which, without any
                                doubt, constitute the principal motive of that note, although
                                incidentally I may have mentioned therein—out of deference to your
                                repeated verbal requests and the desires expressed in a previous
                                informal note from you of February 6th—some of the most serious
                                objections, of a political and legal character, which could be made
                                against the proposed Treaty of Amity and Commerce.</p>
                            <p>The first one of the said paragraphs reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Mexican Government, as I have expressed to you on other
                                        occasions, is disposed to sign immediately the conventions
                                        on claims the drafts of which it submitted to the Government
                                        of the United States as a result of the general invitation
                                        which this Government extended to the governments of all
                                        countries whose nationals have claims pending against
                                        Mexico. With the signing of convention number 1, upon the
                                        Government of Mexico’s being implicitly recognized and
                                        diplomatic relations being resumed, concurrently all the
                                        difficulties emanating from the present revolution would be
                                        eliminated. With the signing of convention number 2 the
                                        difficulties of the past which still persist and which might
                                        impede the friendly <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> of
                                        the two peoples would disappear. And thus the field being
                                        cleared of obstacles, past and present, the Government of
                                        Mexico would be enabled to enter into a discussion of the
                                        Treaty of Amity and Commerce, if such a treaty should serve
                                        as a factor in strengthening the future bonds between the
                                        two countries.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>And, as I said before, after incidentally mentioning some objections
                                to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce of a political and legal
                                character, from the Mexican point of view, my note of February 9th
                                concludes with the following paragraph, which does naught else but
                                confirm, in a most concrete and positive manner, the contents of the
                                paragraph just quoted, namely: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“I sincerely hope that the Department of State will
                                        appreciate the force of these observations in the same
                                        cordial spirit in which they are made, as well as the
                                        natural just scruples of the President of the Republic for
                                        the dignity of the country, in obtaining recognition for his
                                        Government on the basis of previous pledges; and that, in
                                        view of all this, the American Government will accept these
                                        observations and will respect his scruples. This being the
                                        case, the signing of convention number 1, to which I made
                                        reference at the beginning of this note, would signify
                                        implicitly the recognition of the Government of Mexico, and,
                                        diplomatic relations between the two Governments being thus
                                        resumed, the signing of convention number 2 could be
                                        proceeded with, and the designation of the respective <pb facs="0769" n="655" xml:id="pg_655"/> Ambassadors,
                                        through the medium of whom details of the Treaty of Amity
                                        and Commerce which the American Chancellery desires could be
                                        studied …”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>I have made the preceding rectification because my Government
                                considers that its present position as clearly defined in the above
                                paragraphs quoted from my note of February 9th, a position approved
                                not only by Congress, as shown by the intense and eloquent
                                manifestations of approval which followed the reading of the
                                pertinent part of the Presidential message in the solemn session of
                                September 1st of last year, but also by the entire people of Mexico,
                                as expressed in many ways by public opinion; I say, my Government
                                considers that its present position represents the fullest measure
                                of its sentiments of friendship toward the American people, since it
                                is placed in the best possible position to satisfy the claims,
                                repeatedly formulated, by the Chancellery of the White House,
                                naturally with the approval of Congress and the people, and without
                                exceeding the bounds imposed by the dignity of Mexico, a nation
                                whose sovereignty has not been questioned for more than one hundred
                                years of autonomous life.</p>
                            <p>In this sense, I take the liberty of reminding you that the paragraph
                                of the said Presidential message which relates to the
                                Mexican-American international situation, after declaring explicitly
                                that “Our Government is concerned as much as that of the United
                                States with the protection of American interests in Mexico, since
                                this protection is one of its most urgent duties toward that great
                                country, not only because of the material bonds which their
                                geographical position necessarily creates, but also owing to those
                                moral bonds—even stronger—of our sympathy with its democratic
                                institutions and the noble qualities of its people.” After that
                                explicit declaration, I repeat, the diplomatic problem growing out
                                of this embarrassing international situation is reduced to the
                                following statement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The two Governments, then, are in accord in this aim, and
                                        the Government of Mexico, with a view to cooperating more
                                        effectively in its realization, that is, in order that this
                                        realization may take a form such as may strengthen the
                                        prestige of the Mexican Government, and enable it better to
                                        fulfill the duty of protection, referred to above, and be at
                                        the same time the basis of closer future relations between
                                        the two countries, has preferred to eliminate, by the
                                        natural development of its political and administrative
                                        policy, the occasion for promises which might humiliate it,
                                        and it proposes to follow this course until the field
                                        appears sufficiently free of obstacles to permit its being
                                        recognized without prejudice to its national dignity and
                                        sovereignty, and to be able later, under equal conditions,
                                        to conclude and celebrate such treaties as it may deem
                                        necessary for the greatest cordiality in the resumed
                                        diplomatic relations between the two countries.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <pb facs="0770" n="656" xml:id="pg_656"/>
                            <p>Such is our course; and in keeping with our national sentiment, the
                                Government of Mexico has always endeavored to clear it of all
                                obstacles; in domestic affairs by seeking to put into force the
                                political and administrative policy which we have adopted, a policy
                                better and more effective for the protection of foreign interests
                                than any written guarantee and one which affords the maximum
                                development consistent with human possibilities and the nature and
                                magnitude of the work undertaken; in foreign affairs by adjusting
                                ourselves to everything which is not in opposition to that policy
                                and which does not affect the dignity of the Nation. This
                                conciliatory policy was, precisely, the one which inspired this
                                Chancellery, towards the end of last year, to propose to the
                                Chancellery of the United States a convention which would create a
                                Mixed Commission to decide all American claims for damages arising
                                from the last Mexican revolution.</p>
                            <p>The Government of Mexico sincerely believes that a similar convention
                                might with advantage be substituted, with the object of resuming
                                diplomatic relations between the two countries, for any treaty of
                                amity and commerce, thought out and written in the tenor proposed by
                                the Department of State of Washington, not only from the Mexican
                                viewpoint, but also—and chiefly—from the American. To this end, I
                                again take the liberty to bring to the attention of the Department
                                of State, through you, the following points:</p>
                            <p>1. The imposition of fixed obligations as an indispensable condition
                                for granting recognition to a legitimate government, which has the
                                support of all the governed, and whose authority is exercised
                                peacefully throughout the land over a sovereign people and in
                                accordance with the laws in force, is an affront to the dignity of
                                that people, and, if such an event should take place, the Government
                                so recognizing the other, would, by this act alone, alienate the
                                confidence and sympathy of the people concerned, and would undermine
                                future international friendship. Moreover, such an unfortunate event
                                would set a regrettable precedent regarding small nations and
                                international ethics and, moreover, would be contrary to the
                                humanitarian doctrine of which the Government of the White House has
                                proved itself to be a manifest supporter and advocate, namely, the
                                doctrine that the government of a weak country merits the friendship
                                of governments of strong nations all the more when its power of
                                resistance in defense of its national dignity and sovereignty is
                                less.</p>
                            <p>It may be said, in this respect, that the situation has not been
                                improved by reason of the concession made by the Department of State
                                which you formulated in your last informal note of April 20th as
                                follows: <pb facs="0771" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“My Government is disposed to sign first the claims
                                        convention (or conventions), provided it is clearly
                                        understood that the signing of a treaty of amity and
                                        commerce with provisions previously agreed upon and put in
                                        draft form (as in the case of the conventions) shall follow
                                        without delay.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>2. The material part of the proposed Treaty of Amity and Commerce,
                                the part which really interests the American Government because it
                                constitutes the written guarantee which it desires in respect of the
                                rights of its nationals in Mexico, contains flagrant violations of
                                the Constitution of this country and interpretations of some of the
                                precepts thereof not regulated yet by the Honorable Congress of the
                                Union which is the sole authority to which the Mexican people has
                                delegated powers so to do. The truth of this assertion persists, as
                                I have proved to you verbally, notwithstanding the refutation and
                                the modifications included in the body of your note of April 20.
                                Again, inasmuch as the Mexican Government holds that frankness is
                                one of the best characteristics of real friendship, it does not
                                hesitate to state frankly its belief that, in the present state of
                                things, any wording of the pertinent clauses of the treaty which
                                might be altogether satisfactory to the wishes of the American
                                Chancellery—according as those wishes have been expressed—would be
                                subject to the same defect, and would place the President of the
                                Mexican Republic, were he to sign said treaty, in a position in
                                opposition to the organic act defining his powers, and in opposition
                                to his solemn declaration to comply with, and to enforce compliance
                                with, the Constitution, or, at least, of invading, by undue
                                interpretations, the exclusive sphere of the legislative power.</p>
                            <p>It is certain, therefore, that even if the President were to sign the
                                said Treaty of Amity and Commerce, or a similar instrument, such a
                                treaty would not be ratified by the Senate, and the conditions under
                                which recognition had been granted to the Government of Mexico,
                                being unfulfilled, diplomatic relations between the two countries
                                would again be broken; the international situation would be graver
                                than it is now; and the unconstitutional guarantees of protection to
                                American interests, embodied in that treaty, would be without
                                effect, and American interests would be, indeed, in a state less
                                favorable than the present one.</p>
                            <p>3. The substantial agreement which exists between the American
                                demands and the topics of the political and administrative program
                                which the present Government of Mexico has adopted in respect of
                                interests of foreigners, is evident. Now, the signing of the treaty
                                in question would divest the governmental acts in execution of the
                                said program of their character of spontaneity, by giving them <pb facs="0772" n="658" xml:id="pg_658"/> the character of a forced
                                obedience imposed by a foreign power, and no one doubts that, in
                                such a case, all chances of success which the Executive would have,
                                in virtue of his right to propose laws to Congress, would be doomed
                                to failure; and the signing of the treaty would not only obstruct
                                further the development of our domestic policy (which policy
                                includes due protection to foreign interests in Mexico), but also
                                would greatly complicate the international question, even though the
                                aforesaid treaty might have been signed by the President and
                                ratified by the Senate.</p>
                            <p>4. The identity, therefore, of the aims by both Governments in that
                                which relates to the due protection of American interests in Mexico,
                                are identical. On July 12, 1921, this Chancellery extended an
                                invitation to all governments whose nationals had claims pending for
                                damages caused during the recent Mexican revolution, to enter into
                                agreements to set up mixed commissions which should study and decide
                                such claims. This invitation was based on article 5 of the decree of
                                May 10, 1913, issued by the First Chief of the Constitutional Army,
                                Señor don Venustiano Carranza, and on amended article 13 of the law
                                of December 24, 1917. Last year the Government of Mexico submitted
                                to the Government of the United States, as a lawful and spontaneous
                                act, a proposed convention, which, while incidentally resuming
                                diplomatic relations between the two countries, without impairing
                                the dignity and sovereignty of either, and in form almost identical
                                with the one proposed by the Department of State at Washington, (the
                                signing of a treaty) might, at the same time, contribute to making
                                more effective the protection desired for said American interests
                                and be an augury of closer international relations.</p>
                            <p>5. The Government of Mexico has gone even farther. Considering that
                                the above-mentioned convention did not include within its
                                jurisdictional capacity many other claims which were pending between
                                the two countries which might even diminish the cordiality of their
                                diplomatic relations, my Government submitted for the consideration
                                of the Department of State at Washington, at the same time when it
                                submitted that convention, another convention to create,
                                subsequently, a Mixed Commission which should hear and decide all
                                pending claims mentioned, according to the principles of
                                international law.</p>
                            <p>Finally, as a complement to the five preceding points, I can do no
                                less than submit for the consideration of the Department of State,
                                in the problem under consideration, that it is necessary to
                                dissociate the moral entities called “American Government” and
                                “Mexican Government” from the physical persons who direct or form
                                these <pb facs="0773" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/> entities, since, in
                                the present case, the change in the physical persons who constitute
                                the Public Administration of Mexico has been brought about legally,
                                and without any break in continuity of the entity “Mexican
                                Government” which was established after the revolution of 1913; and
                                it appears somewhat inexplicable that the same moral entity
                                “Government of the United States” should maintain and suspend
                                successively its diplomatic relations with the same moral entity
                                “Government of Mexico”; and that the former of these acts, that is,
                                the resumption and maintenance of diplomatic relations, should have
                                taken place precisely when great portions of the national territory
                                were still separated from legal authority and when the application
                                of the laws was still impaired by harsh and revolutionary
                                radicalism; and that the latter of these acts, that is, the
                                suspension of diplomatic relations, should have taken place when the
                                legal authority had succeeded in establishing itself in all the
                                country and when the application of those same laws had been
                                modified as much as possible in order to reach an equilibrium in
                                respect of all national interests.</p>
                            <p>I am pleased, Mr. Summerlin, to close and sum up my above statement
                                by declaring that the road followed by the Government of Mexico, in
                                a thorny field, has not been blindly marked out by any preconceived
                                arbitrary idea; rather, and very much to the contrary, it is the
                                result of compromises through constant efforts made by the
                                Government to reconcile its moral obligations and the political
                                conditions and necessities of the country with the demands—without
                                doubt well-intentioned—of the American Chancellery; and this
                                Government has the deep conviction that its efforts in this
                                direction have brought it considerably closer—as I have said in
                                another part of this note—to the position embodied in the American
                                demands. There is only lacking, then, that the Government of the
                                White House, actuated by the good will which it has manifested
                                toward the Mexican people, and in accordance with its desires to see
                                diplomatic relations between the two neighbor countries resumed, as
                                well as to see present and future protection of American interests
                                in Mexico rendered more effective, shall give its friendly sanction
                                to the policy established by this Government, in order that such
                                act—which will be duly appreciated in Mexico and throughout the
                                entire world—may satisfactorily solve a problem, an act which
                                without any doubt will be of great benefit to both countries, to the
                                American continent, and to humanity.</p>
                            <p>I remain [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. J. Pani</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>