<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Chargé in Mexico ( (Summerlin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1922v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d624</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">624</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1922-03-03T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1922-03-03T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-03-03T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-03-03T11:00:00-05:00" n="624"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d624">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.113/9306a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-03-03T11:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 3, 1922—11 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>32. A Joint Resolution of Congress approved January 31, 1922 (See <hi
                        rend="italic">Congressional Record</hi> of January 18, 1922, Page 1499)
                    repeals <pb facs="0832" n="718" xml:id="pg_718"/> the Joint Resolution of
                    Congress approved March 14, 1912, which was the legal basis for the Presidential
                    Proclamation of July 12, 1919, entitled “Exportation of Arms or Munitions of War
                    to Mexico unlawful,”<note n="69" xml:id="d624fn69">
                        <ref target="frus1919v02#pg_551">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 551</ref>.</note> a copy of which
                    should be in the Embassy’s files, and renders that Proclamation ineffective.
                    Consequently, if this Government is to continue to exercise the control
                    heretofore maintained over shipments of arms or munitions of war to Mexico, a
                    new proclamation will have to be issued under the provisions of the Joint
                    Resolution approved January 31, 1922, which would declare that there exist in
                    Mexico such conditions of domestic violence, which are or may be promoted by the
                    use of arms or munitions of war procured from the United States, as are
                    contemplated by the said joint resolution. The reference to the existence of
                    conditions of domestic violence in Mexico cannot be omitted from the
                    proclamation, and there is no other procedure by which this Government may
                    continue to exercise control over such exportation of arms or munitions of war
                    to Mexico.</p>
                <p>You are therefore instructed to seek an interview with General Obregon to explain
                    the situation fully to him and to request an expression of his views on the
                    subject. You should inform him that this Government will meet the wishes of the
                    Mexican authorities with respect to the embargo, terminating it or reimposing it
                    as they may desire. You should however make it absolutely clear that the present
                    embargo cannot be continued without the issuance of a new proclamation
                    containing a recital similar to that contained in the Proclamation of July 12,
                    1919, as above referred to. Should the present Mexican authorities desire to
                    have the embargo lifted and so inform you, no new proclamation as to Mexico will
                    be issued and the control of shipments of this character heretofore exercised by
                    the Department will automatically cease.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
