<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1922-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1922-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="84" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">439.41 St 3/12</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Geddes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1922-05-03"><hi rend="italic">May 3,
                                1922</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 330</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the note which you were so good as to
                            address to me on March 18th, in regard to the claim of Mr. Thomas Steel,
                            you enclosed a copy and translation of a note from the Dominican Foreign
                            Office to the American Legation at Santo Domingo. In this note the
                            opinion was expressed that Messrs. Steel and McPhail were without good
                            grounds in preferring a claim against the Dominican Government and it
                            was pointed out that such a claim is cognizable by the Courts of the
                            Dominican Republic.</p>
                        <p>I did not fail to submit a copy of your note to my Government, who desire
                            me to draw attention to certain of the principles laid down in this note
                            from the Dominican Foreign Office and in particular to the assertion
                            that “it is a principle of international law universally admitted that
                            every person who establishes himself in any foreign country, respects,
                            by that simple act, not only the laws, regulations and practices there
                            existing, but also accepts all of the abnormal conditions to which life
                            in that country may be exposed”.</p>
                        <pb facs="0211" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/>
                        <p>My Government are anxious to learn whether, in forwarding this note to
                            His Majesty’s Embassy, the United States Government may be held to
                            approve of and to subscribe to the principles laid down in the Dominican
                            note and to consider that such principles are susceptible of universal
                            application.</p>
                        <p>I should be grateful if you would be so good as to place me in a position
                            to inform my Government of your view in regard to the point raised
                            above.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. C. Geddes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>