<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="150" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">835.00/1–1946: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-19">January 19, 1946</date>.<lb/>[Received January
                                19—4:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>201. Following are brief statements of points covered by Foreign Minister
                            in radio address last night:</p>
                        <p>Argentina’s pacific and democratic traditions well known and established
                            throughout her history. Referring to good neighbor policy, Foreign
                            Minister stressed traditional friendship with US and understanding of
                            that country’s dominant position but pointed out possession of such
                            great power engenders natural suspicion and jealousy among smaller
                            nations. Principle of good neighborhood that of nonintervention.</p>
                        <p>June 4, revolution entirely Argentine affair.</p>
                        <p>Argentine Armed Forces based on conscription drawn from all sectors
                            population and consequently democratic force.</p>
                        <p>Original revolutionary Govt composed largely of Army and Navy officers
                            has been gradually replaced by civilian administration until today there
                            are only a few military officers in Govt.</p>
                        <p>Cannot be said consequently that there is “military cell” or “Govt behind
                            the Govt”. Charges of Nazi-Fascism absurd as are claims that Army is
                            imbued with spirit of aggression. Argentina has no territorial
                            aspirations and no frontier disputes.</p>
                        <p>With reference to rights of man which Argentina has been accused by
                            Uruguayan Foreign Minister of violating, Cooke made four points on basis
                            of examination United Nations Charter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>(1) Rights of man not clearly defined; (2) Charter expresses only
                                    purpose of cooperation for respect and fostering of those
                                    rights; (3) No method of juridical defense established; (4) No
                                    procedure for application of sanctions suggested.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>How, asked Cooke, is multilateral intervention suggested by Uruguay<note n="19" xml:id="d150fn19">For documentation on this proposal, see
                                    <ref target="frus1945v09#pg_185"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, pp.
                                    185</ref> ff.</note> to be carried out? If on basis unanimity
                            then intervention <pb facs="0207" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> obviously
                            impossible since unanimity would never be achieved. If by majority
                            decision then it means end of good neighbor policy.</p>
                        <p>Any claims that Argentina does not enjoy fruits of democracy ridiculous
                            when it is recalled elections have been convoked for February 24, that
                            there is full freedom of press and speech and that country enjoys
                            greater liberty now than at any time during past 15 years. Admittedly
                            there have been moments when revolutionary govt has prevailed by force;
                            no revolution is conducted only to be ended following day with return of
                            deposed forces. True that state of siege still in force but this is
                            constitutional measure, is not martial law and does not mean police
                            officials can commit abuses at will.</p>
                        <p>Referring to Axis spies and those persons guilty of activities against
                            United Nations all will be deported.</p>
                        <p>Argentina disposed as always to collaborate with rest of world, stands as
                            always with other peoples of America and at service of United
                            Nations.</p>
                        <p>Text<note n="20" xml:id="d150fn20">Not printed.</note> will be forwarded
                            by airmail.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>