<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Argentina (
                    (Messersmith))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-06-03T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-06-03T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-03T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-03T16:00:00-05:00" n="219"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/6–146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-03T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 3, 1946—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>745. Von der Becke visit discussed today in the light of <gloss
                        target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> no. 1497 June 1 noon<note n="41"
                        xml:id="d219fn41">Not printed.</note> with General Handy, Deputy Chief of
                    Staff (General Eisenhower absent from Washington.) Full agreement that
                    misunderstanding must be avoided, that State and War must maintain identical
                    position and that visit here must not prejudice in any way your position or
                    negotiations in Buenos Aires. A letter from UnderSec has just been delivered to
                    Handy for Eisenhower which concludes as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Ambassador Messersmith has already had one conversation with
                            President-elect Perón on the subject of Argentine-United States <pb
                                facs="0270" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> relations, in the course of
                            which he informed the President-elect that he hoped to be able to
                            continue discussions shortly after Perón’s inauguration on June 4. A
                            conversation such as outlined in the enclosed memorandum should be
                            helpful to the extent it serves to impress on the Argentine Govt the
                            necessity of complying with its inter-American commitments, in order
                            that we can then be in a position to take up other important matters of
                            mutual interest with them.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Memo reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Should General von der Becke call on General Eisenhower, it is
                            recommended: <list>
                                <label>1)</label>
                                <item>General Eisenhower should not take the initiative in raising
                                    the question of US-Argentine relations or the question of
                                    military collaboration between the two countries.</item>
                                <label>2)</label>
                                <item>Should either of these questions be raised by General von der
                                    Becke, General Eisenhower would reply that, as previously
                                    explained to Colonel Bertollo, General Eisenhower shares the
                                    hope expressed by General von der Becke that some basis for
                                    cooperation between the armies of the two countries can be
                                    established; and that General Eisenhower has been in conference
                                    with high officials of the US Govt looking toward that goal.
                                    General Eisenhower could then continue:</item>
                                <label>3)</label>
                                <item>In seeking some basis for cooperation with the Argentine Army,
                                    General Eisenhower has been confronted with a problem of
                                    compliance with certain inter-American agreements, including
                                    resolutions VII, XVIII, and XIX of the Mexico City Conference
                                    which relate to the elimination of German and Japanese influence
                                    in this Hemisphere.</item>
                                <label>4)</label>
                                <item>As stated to Colonel Bertollo, the Dept of State considers
                                    that among the important steps which should be taken pursuant to
                                    these resolutions are, for example, the elimination of German
                                    and Japanese ownership in certain business enterprises and the
                                    repatriation of certain enemy nationals.</item>
                                <label>5)</label>
                                <item>The matter of specifying the agreements which are pertinent
                                    and what would constitute compliance are matters which should be
                                    worked out between the Foreign Offices of the respective
                                    Govts.</item>
                                <label>6)</label>
                                <item>Once these matters have been worked out between the respective
                                    Foreign Offices then General von der Becke would find General
                                    Eisenhower willing to meet him more than half way in
                                    establishing the basis for an effective cooperation between the
                                    Argentine and US armies.</item>
                                <label>7)</label>
                                <item>Until these matters have been worked out, General Eisenhower
                                    is not in a position to discuss what this cooperation shall
                                    consist of.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Handy indicated agreement with terms set forth and will deliver personally to
                    Eisenhower on latter’s return tomorrow together with copy <gloss
                        target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss> 1497.</p>
                <p>Von der Becke reached Washington today being met behalf War Dept by Lt. Gen.
                    Vandenberg. He requested an interview with Eisenhower which has been scheduled
                    for June 5.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
