<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-08T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-08T11:00:00-05:00" n="320" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">824.01/8–846: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Flack</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                    Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-08T12:00:00-04:00">August 8,
                                1946—noon.</date><lb/>[Received 2:26 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>771. I had informal conversation this morning with <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> Solares at his request. I told
                            him I had no further information from Washington <pb facs="0389" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/> yet about recognition. He expressed opinion that
                            at this stage, our recognition would be most helpful and that Argentina
                            and others evidently now awaiting our action.</p>
                        <p>Solares reverted to list of Americans in possible danger at mines which
                            he had asked me to give him and assured me that steps were under way
                            through Ministry of Government to assure them all protection. He added
                            Government realizes this question closely connected with general
                            attitude of miners. He added that if Lechín<note n="55" xml:id="d320fn55">Juan Lechín, Permanent Secretary, Federación
                                Sindical de Mineros.</note> were placed in custody, this would
                            release a series of dangerous uprisings at the mines and that Government
                            has decided to play ball with Lechín not as <gloss target="#t_MNR1">MNR</gloss> did, but for economic welfare of Bolivia. Miners
                            increasingly aware Junta’s efforts.</p>
                        <p>Minister asked my opinion on asylum question and I said that while we
                            were not parties to specific asylum treaties, I felt that to contribute
                            to internal order Diplomatic Corps’ request for safe exit of all in
                            asylum was best solution, since under existing treaties preventative
                            arrest can be obtained administratively pending submission extradition
                            documents in case common criminals. Minister said matter will be further
                            considered Junta before reply to Diplomatic Corps’ last memo, August
                                6th.<note n="56" xml:id="d320fn56">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>I feel strongly that recognition by US very important at this stage and
                            should now be extended as soon as possible. Peru’s action yesterday,
                            postdated 6th, imitated Chile’s recognition same day.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Flack</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>