<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="384" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34532/2–246</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Forrestal</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-09">February 9, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Some time ago our
                            Ambassador at Rio de Janeiro, Mr. Berle, took up with this Department
                            the question of the Naval Operating Base in that city, and suggested
                            that if the current strength of the Base was no longer necessary, as
                            seemed likely, it would be reassuring to Brazil if the personnel were
                            reduced to the minimum required for carrying on essential
                            operations.</p>
                        <p>Officials of your Department, when approached in the matter, stated that
                            the Naval Operating Base was being maintained at its current level
                            primarily because of surplus property disposal problems, and added that
                            the Base was also active in the Naval Air Transport Service and in the
                            routing of shipping still under the Maritime Commission. It was further
                            stated that it was the intention of the Navy Department to close the
                            Naval Operating Base completely as soon as conditions permitted, but no
                            estimate was given of the approximate time when this could take
                            place.</p>
                        <p>I am now in receipt of a telegram from Ambassador Berle in which he
                            states that Admiral Greer,<note n="18" xml:id="d384fn18">Rear Adm.
                                Marshall R. Greer, <gloss target="#t_Pan1">Pan</gloss> American
                                Division, Navy Department.</note> while in Rio de Janeiro for the
                            inauguration of President Dutra, looked into the situation of the Naval
                                <pb facs="0454" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> Operating Base and was
                            kind enough to discuss his conclusions with the Embassy. Admiral Greer
                            is understood to be reporting directly to the Navy Department, but his
                            views, with which the Ambassador is in full accord, are believed to be
                            as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>First: The Naval Operating Base is an anomaly in time of peace;
                                    it continues to exist chiefly because there is no other unit to
                                    which it could turn over some items of property and equipment in
                                    its possession.</p>
                                <p>Secondly: The Base’s functions could and should be transferred in
                                    part to the Senior Naval Member of the Joint Brazilian-United
                                    States Commission on his arrival about March 1, and in part to a
                                    unit which could be set up at any time in the Naval Attachés
                                    Office.</p>
                                <p>Thirdly: Announcement should be made as soon as reasonably
                                    possible that the Navy intended to close the Base at a stated
                                    future date, at which time all matters not disposed of to the
                                    Brazilian Government would be distributed as indicated above;
                                    the fixing of a definite date would considerably speed up the
                                    process of liquidation of current business.</p></quote></p>
                        <p>It is believed that if this program were carried out existing commitments
                            could be handled by about one-fourth of the present strength of the
                            Naval Operating Base, when properly distributed to the Office of the
                            Naval Attaché and the Senior Naval Member of the Commission.</p>
                        <p>I attach great importance to the reduction of our armed forces in Brazil
                            as rapidly as conditions permit, it being understood, of course, that we
                            should not sacrifice any legitimate interest of ours by so doing. The
                            continued presence in Brazil of forces not seriously needed will
                            inevitably lead to misunderstanding and will be exploited by those
                            elements who are only too ready to accuse the United States of designs
                            “to occupy Brazil indefinitely.” For this reason, the early announcement
                            of our intention to terminate the Naval Operating Base at Rio de Janeiro
                            on a fixed future date would have a wholesome effect on our general
                            relations with Brazil.<note n="19" xml:id="d384fn19">In telegram 268,
                                February 25, 1946, 6 p.m., to Rio de Janeiro, the Secretary of State
                                indicated the impossibility of decommissioning this base by April 1,
                                and the expectation that this would be effected by the end of the
                                month (811.34532/2–2046). On March 22 the Navy Department ordered
                                the disestablishment of the base on April 25, according to telegram
                                421, March 26, 1946, 8 p.m., to Rio de Janeiro
                                (811.34532/3–2646).</note></p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>