<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Ambassador in Brazil ( (Pawley) ) to the Brazilian Acting
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs ( (Leão Gracie))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d407</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">407</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="reciBCcIZHALncT7I" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009004888"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Search and rescue</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="407"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d407">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.76/10–1746</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pawley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Brazilian Acting Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leão Gracie</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 134</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-16">September 16,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to refer to a recent
                    conversation which I have had with His Excellency, the President of the
                    Republic, and to now propose an understanding, subject to the approval of Your
                    Excellency, providing for the operation of the supplemental naval radio station
                    at Recife by the Navy of the United States of America based upon the following
                    provisions:</p>
                <p>The radio station, which is located on the Ilha das Cobras near Recife,
                    Pernambuco, Brazil and which occupies 175.06 hectares of land shall be operated
                    by the Navy of the United States of America for a period of ten years in the
                    interest of the defense of this hemisphere and with the joint concurrence of the
                    Government of the United States of Brazil and the Government of the United
                    States of America. The date of commencement of operation shall be on the date
                    that the suggested agreement becomes effective. The right of tenure enjoyed
                    under this agreement by the Navy of the United States of America will include
                    full right of access to the radio station as well as the right to make any
                    change in the equipment or the facilities of the station as may be deemed
                    desirable or necessary by the Navy of the United States of America.</p>
                <p>The station at Recife, within the limits of its current existing capacity, will
                    furnish to the Government of the United States of Brazil the same high frequency
                    radio bearing services for search and rescue purposes as are provided to the
                    Government of the United States of America. When and as alerted to specific
                    cases by the Government of the United States of Brazil, it will maintain
                    continuous watch as necessary to furnish high frequency direction finder
                    bearings to ships or aircraft in actual or potential distress.</p>
                <p>In further return for the use of the radio station, the Government of the United
                    States of America will turn over to the Government of the United States of
                    Brazil the fixed installations and the equipment of the high frequency radio
                    direction finder stations at Bahia and Belém. It will further agree to maintain
                    this equipment in operating condition for a period of three months following the
                    effective date of approval.<note n="54" xml:id="d407fn54">In a letter of October
                        7, 1946, from the Assistant Secretary of State to the Secretary of the Navy,
                        the concurrence of the Brazilian Government was indicated
                        (832.26/10–746).</note> Any instructions necessary to initiate <pb
                        facs="0474" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> the operation of these stations will
                    be provided by the Navy of the United States of America and so long as the
                    latter shall operate the radio station at Recife it will make available to the
                    Government of the United States of Brazil advisory assistance in the maintenance
                    and operation of the stations at Bahia and Belém.</p>
                <p>This agreement may be extended for periods of five years by the mutual agreement
                    of both Governments and it may be terminated by request of either Party at any
                    time prior to the date of expiration.<note n="55" xml:id="d407fn55">
                        <p>A marginal note in the original reads: “In taking receipt of a hecto of
                            this <gloss target="#t_desp1">desp</gloss>. &amp; encl. from Mr.
                            Braddock on Nov. 4, 1946, Commander William M. Laughlin stated that
                            according to the Naval Attaché, Rio, formal transfer of the Bahia and
                            Belém stations had taken place on Oct. 8, from which date the
                            three-month period for maintenance, as provided in ¶4, would therefore
                            begin to run.</p>
                        <p rend="right">11/4/46. D. B[raddock]”</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>I take this opportunity [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pawley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
