<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Brazilian Affairs (
                    (Braddock))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="452"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.51/10–2446</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Brazilian
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Braddock</hi>)<note n="22" xml:id="d452fn22"
                        >Addressed to the Director of the Office of American Republic Affairs
                        (Briggs) and to the Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic
                        Affairs (Braden).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-24">October 24,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In connection with the attached telegram no. 1770 of October 16 and no. 1790 of
                    October 22 from Rio on the subject of the Brazilian loan, it is my belief that
                    the <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> should accept the assurance
                    offered by Brazil in these telegrams as meeting the Bank’s condition for
                    granting the new $50,000,000 loan to Brazil. My view is based on the following
                    reasons: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Though not iron-clad, this assurance is pretty good and at any rate
                            the best that we can get at this time.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>If the new loan, which has already been publicized a good deal in
                            Brazil, fails to come off there will be general disillusionment there
                            concerning the friendship of the United States and its desire to help
                            Brazil.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I talked with Ambassador Pawley in Rochester about this and he also strongly
                    favors acceptance of the assurance offered. He especially requests that no final
                    rejection be made by <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> without
                    giving the Department and himself the opportunity to find a way out.</p>
                <p>Immediately after my talk with Ambassador Pawley Mr. O’Toole and I met with Mr.
                    Havlik and Mr. Stenger<note n="23" xml:id="d452fn23">Hubert F. Havlik, Acting
                        Chief of the Division of Investment and Economic Development, and Jerome J.
                        Stenger of the same Division.</note> of <gloss target="#t_ED1">ED</gloss> to
                    discuss this matter. It was decided that no reply should be given to Brazil
                    pending the return of Mr. William McChesney Martin of the <gloss
                        target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> from Brazil next week and discussion
                    of the subject with him, on which occasion <gloss target="#t_ED1">ED</gloss> and
                        <gloss target="#t_OFD1">OFD</gloss> would see that our views as expressed
                    above were taken into full consideration.<note n="24" xml:id="d452fn24">A
                        marginal comment reads: “This is right move. S. B[raden].”</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel</hi> M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Braddock</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
