<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Brazil ( (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d479</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">479</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-19T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec2WdyKi8trpNQBA" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Refinery</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-19T18:00:00-05:00" n="479"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d479">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.6363/11–1945: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-19T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >November 19, 1945—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2631. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss>s 3403 and 3411, Nov 13, and <gloss
                        target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 3420, Nov 14.<note n="66" xml:id="d479fn66"
                        >Telegram 3420 not printed.</note> Facts in possession of Dept regarding
                    petroleum refining situation in Brazil appear at variance with <gloss
                        target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>s understanding of situation. Following are
                    principal points of difference: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>You stated that “refining and marketing of oil in Brazil is at present
                            air-tight monopoly of Standard Oil probably acting in conjunction with
                            British Shell interests.” Dept understanding is that <pb facs="0548"
                                n="530" xml:id="pg_530"/> neither Standard nor any other American
                            company has any refining operations whatever in Brazil, only operating
                            refineries being three small Brazilian-owned plants at Matarazzo, São
                            Paulo, and Rio Grande do Sul. Thus no Standard monopoly of refining. As
                            regards marketing, Dept understands Standard does about 40 percent of
                            gasoline business and 50 percent of residual fuel oil (these percentages
                            including sales by Caloric company which owned by Standard); balance of
                            business divided among Shell, Atlantic, and Texas, with Gulf perhaps
                            having small participation resultant from recent purchase of Brazilian
                            marketing organization.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>You speak of “Standard Oil and its partner Atlantic.” Dept has no
                            evidence of any joint operations by Standard and Atlantic (except
                            certain occasional cooperative transactions requested to be performed by
                                PAW<note n="67" xml:id="d479fn67">Petroleum Administration for
                                War.</note> under Directive 70); both companies deny any
                            inter-corporate connection.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>You state that a stand by this Government against measures restricting
                            importation would not satisfy Standard and Atlantic because “result
                            would probably be to bring down price of oil.” Dept informed that prices
                            in Brazil are determined by National Petroleum Council with view to
                            protecting the three small Brazilian refineries, and that large profits
                            of importers of finished products result from such mandatory minimum
                            prices.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>If understanding of Dept on any or all of above points is known by you to be
                    incorrect please inform by urgent cable. Otherwise Dept feels that position
                    taken in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2599, Nov 10, is only sound
                    position that can be taken and regrets it apparently did not make sufficiently
                    clear ideas meant to be conveyed therein. Dept opposes monopoly arrangement as
                    strongly as <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>, whether Brazilian or American.
                    Dept believes in fullest application of open-door principle to which you
                    referred and feels that objective is unattainable so long as decree-laws 395 and
                    4071 remain on books. Consequently, Dept reiterates that fundamental objective
                    of <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> should be to seek elimination of
                    restrictive provisions in those decrees. Belief here is that any other approach,
                    such as minority interest in refineries for U.S. companies, would be only
                    compromise solution of doubtful duration. Moreover, because of monopolistic
                    aspects, we oppose exclusive concessions for establishment of refineries,
                    whether wholly or partially Brazilian-owned, and likewise, any sort of exclusive
                    marketing arrangements between refineries and American distributors. In
                    precisely what respects is <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> not in accord
                    with foregoing?</p>
                <p>Dept proposed that <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> attempt to forestall final
                    action on recommendations of Petroleum Council merely as initial stop-gap
                    measure <pb facs="0549" n="531" xml:id="pg_531"/> so as to keep situation fluid
                    and permit attack on root of difficulties, decree-laws 395 and 4071.</p>
                <p>Dept’s position is re-stated as follows:</p>
                <p>Decree-laws 395 and 4071 prevent American nationals from owning or even having
                    minority participation in refineries in Brazil and have retarded development of
                    refining industry Brazil. This situation, while considered by Dept to be
                    essentially unsound, was not cause for serious concern so long as existent
                    Brazilian refining capacity was adequate to supply only small fraction of
                    Brazilian petroleum product requirements. With announcement, however, that
                    Ypiranga and Sampaio groups had each obtained on a duopoly basis refining
                    concessions authorizing construction of a 10,000–barrel refinery, (subject to
                    determination of financial responsibility and guarantee of crude supply), these
                    two refineries in addition to the three small existent refineries would be
                    adequate to supply all of Brazil’s requirements of oil products except residual
                    fuel oil and specialty products. Thus one of three results would necessarily
                    ensue: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) either present United States suppliers would
                    be excluded altogether from Brazilian markets and crude supplies obtained by the
                    Brazilian refineries from other sources, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) a rigid
                    market and quota arrangement would be initiated designed to protect the relative
                    market positions of present suppliers and thus to freeze the competitive <hi
                        rend="italic">statics quo</hi>, or (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) some such
                    monopolistic supply arrangement would develop as apparently has been anticipated
                    by Gulf in that one or at most two companies would have exclusive supply
                    contracts with the Brazilian refineries. The Dept felt that all three of these
                    alternative results were undesirable and that it was therefore important to
                    proceed promptly to do what could be done to obtain a modification or repeal of
                    the basic decree-laws which gave rise to this situation. Pending adequate
                    discussion of the issues of commercial policy and international investment
                    policy that are involved, Dept is anxious to obtain a temporary suspension of
                    the arrangements where-under all refining operations in Brazil would be
                    concentrated in the hands of the Ypiranga and Sampaio groups.</p>
                <p>It is accordingly requested that you hold such conversations as you deem
                    appropriate with the Brazilian authorities along the lines indicated in <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2599.</p>
                <p>For your information, local representatives of Standard and Atlantic are
                    apparently still under impression that their parent companies would be satisfied
                    with a minority participation in Brazilian-owned refineries (which incidentally
                    will almost inevitably be accompanied by a tacit or overt understanding freezing
                    crude supply positions). Actually, as indicated in third paragraph of <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2599, officials of Standard and Atlantic
                    here have reconsidered and will await outcome of Dept’s efforts to obtain a
                    general loosening up of the <pb facs="0550" n="532" xml:id="pg_532"/> situation
                    in Brazil that will permit free competitive entry to both the refining and
                    marketing business in Brazil. Further, the initial acceptance by American
                    companies of minority interests in the development of Brazil’s petroleum
                    resources, would have serious effect on this Government’s over-all policy with
                    respect to protection of American interests in other Latin American countries;
                    i.e., Mexico.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
