<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-24T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-24T11:00:00-05:00" n="500" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">832.6363/10–2446: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de
                                        Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-24T13:00:00-03:00">October 24, 1946—1
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 9:18 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1798. Refinery concessions have been granted by National Petroleum
                            Council to Drault Ernanny and Sampaio with capacity 8,000 to 10,000
                            barrels per day each, both concessions for Bio de Janeiro area, no
                            concessions for São Paulo area having been yet approved. It had <pb facs="0571" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/> been naturally supposed by
                            interested persons and concerns here that no further concessions would
                            be granted pending approval proposed petroleum legislation, since
                            otherwise equal opportunity participate in refining would be denied
                            foreign concerns.</p>
                        <p>However, information now received to effect that National Petroleum
                            Council considering seriously granting application of Sampaio to move
                            concession already granted for Rio to São Paulo area, and at same time
                            doubling authorized capacity. If approved, this would pretty well
                            pre-empt major refining possibilities of Brazil and have effect of
                            excluding American concerns from participation refining business in
                            these major areas which serve 85 percent Brazil’s needs.</p>
                        <p>Standard Oil has pointed out to Embassy seriousness of action apparently
                            contemplated by Petroleum Council, since they have been contemplating
                            possibility of establishing refinery as well as engaging in drilling.
                            Same observations would apply presumably to other American concerns
                            interested in competing for refinery business.</p>
                        <p>Embassy feels that approval now by Petroleum Council to expand refinery
                            concessions in São Paulo and Rio as well would be contrary to announced
                            policy of Brazilian Government regarding foreign capital participation
                            and not consistent with objectives of new constitution as well as
                            proposed petroleum legislation. In view these important considerations,
                            does Department wish Embassy to bring matter to attention Brazilian
                            Government in hope forestalling action by Petroleum Council prejudicial
                            American interests? Telegraph urgently because Petroleum Council
                            apparently giving preferred attention Sampaio application.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniels</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>