<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Chairman of the American Delegation to the Second Pan American Congress of Mining Engineering and
                        Geology (
                        Daniels
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="51" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">563 Rio de Janeiro/9–2846</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Chairman of the American Delegation to the Second <gloss target="#t_Pan1">Pan</gloss> American Congress of Mining Engineering and
                        Geology</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 243</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-28">September 28,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In your capacity as Chairman of the United States
                    Delegation to the Second <gloss target="#t_Pan1">Pan</gloss> American Congress
                    of Mining Engineering and Geology to be held at Rio de Janeiro, Brazil,
                    beginning October 1, 1946, I shall appreciate your communicating to the other
                    members of the Delegation the position to be upheld at the forthcoming
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>This is an official governmental conference and consequently the delegations will
                    represent the official views of the respective governments. Our Delegation at
                    the Congress must act as a unit in representing the United States and should
                    invariably present a solid front. Any divergent views among its members should
                    be resolved in private meetings of the Delegation, thus leaving no possibility
                    that embarrassing differences of opinion might appear in open discussion. The
                    members of the Delegation will, of course, represent before the Congress the
                    views of the Government of the United States rather than those of the respective
                    individuals or of organizations or groups with which they may be affiliated.
                    This is not intended to bar the expression of personal views which are not
                    inconsistent with these instructions or Delegation policy. In these cases not
                    covered by instructions or Delegation policy, personal views may, of course, be
                    expressed, but these should generally be clearly qualified as personal.</p>
                <p>As Chairman, you shall be responsible for adherence to the policy of the United
                    States by all members of the Delegation, and in the event of any division among
                    the members on such matters, your decision shall be final and binding upon the
                    Delegation.</p>
                <p>Papers prepared by members of the Delegation for presentation before the Congress
                    which have not been reviewed by the Department, may be approved by you in the
                    light of the instructions contained in this letter. Papers not approved by the
                    Department or by you, if presented, must be clearly identified as expressing the
                    personal as distinct from the official views of the writer.</p>
                <p>You are authorized to request any member of the Delegation to attend or speak for
                    you as Chairman, in the event of your absence, or inability to attend sessions
                    of the Congress and in any other instances in which you are unable to exercise
                    the functions of your position.</p>
                <p>In accepting the invitation of the Brazilian Government to send an official
                    United States Delegation to this Congress, the Department <pb facs="0086" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/> was keenly aware of the importance of the meeting with
                    respect to its relation to our general economic foreign policy.<note n="2a" xml:id="d51fn2a">For documentation on various aspects of United States
                        economic foreign policy, see <ref target="frus1946v01">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> This government has just released to the public the <hi rend="italic">Suggested Charter for an International Trade Organization of
                        the United Nations</hi>. This document outlines proposed objectives, guiding
                    principles and administrative procedures for the proposed organization. Among
                    the paramount aims are the reduction of tariffs and other trade barriers, and
                    expansion of the production, exchange and consumption of goods, directed toward
                    creation of an expanding world economy and higher standards of living and
                    economic conditions favorable to maintenance of world peace. The development and
                    exploitation of mineral resources, which will be among the important topics of
                    discussion at the Congress, are related to those aims, particularly as regards
                    tariffs, wage levels, investment of capital, and taxes. It therefore becomes of
                    great importance that the United States Delegation endeavor to have excluded
                    from the resolutions and recommendations of the Congress anything that might
                    prejudice the success of the impending meetings scheduled to secure acceptance
                    of the proposed charter of the World Trade Organization.</p>
                <p>To ensure this, it would appear desirable for the United States representatives
                    to propose, if opportunity permits, that the Congress reaffirm the principles
                    outlined in the Economic Charter of the Americas (Resolution LI of the <hi rend="italic">Final Act of the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War
                        and Peace, Mexico City, March 1945</hi>). Such action by the Congress would
                    reaffirm these principles as a framework for the subsequent resolutions and
                    recommendations to be evolved during the course of discussions at the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>The ten principles of the Economic Charter of the Americas include several which
                    may prove very useful to refute any attempts on the part of other delegations to
                    sponsor resolutions subscribing to the expansion of state monopolies. A review
                    of the record of the First Congress held in Santiago, Chile, January 1942, shows
                    that a strong effort was made by the Argentine Delegation to introduce proposals
                    advocating monopolies on mineral products, nationalization of the mining, power
                    and transportation industries and state control of wages, production and
                    dividends. Advice now reaching the Department of State indicates that Argentina
                    is sending a strong Delegation to this Second Congress and may seek again to
                    introduce the theme of nationalization for Latin American mining. If a
                    resolution ensuing from any such proposals be brought to a vote before the
                    meeting, the Delegation should abstain, enter a reservation, or present a
                    statement accompanying its negative vote, depending on the circumstances.</p>
                <pb facs="0087" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/>
                <p>The Delegation which you will head will without doubt be able to contribute
                    materially to the studies of the Congress regarding the technical problems of
                    the mineral industry. In addition to research and operating problems, important
                    topics should be the furtherance of the exchange of scientific and specialized
                    personnel between the American republics and the promotion of the exchange of
                    students and faculty among the universities of the several countries, leading
                    toward a greater understanding between the peoples of the Americas. Among other
                    measures the Delegation could support or even sponsor is, for example, agreement
                    to promote uniform standards of mineral statistics. This would contribute
                    greatly to the usefulness of data interchanged among the various countries.
                    Another valuable contribution would be the compilation of the mining codes of
                    the American republics with the objective of promoting a greater knowledge of
                    these laws for the benefit of interested parties and perhaps tending toward
                    increased general conformity and elimination of undesirable and restrictive
                    provisions in the various codes.</p>
                <p>Although it is not considered appropriate for the United States Delegation to
                    initiate the discussion, the Delegation should be prepared to support in the
                    strongest manner, any proposal or resolution directed to the encouragement of
                    the relaxation of restrictive mining regulations in the American republics.
                    Likewise, support should be given to measures looking toward the moderation or
                    removal of exchange controls, undue restrictions on private foreign investment,
                    excessive taxation and other practices not in harmony with the spirit of the
                    Economic Charter of the Americas.</p>
                <p>It is possible that emphasis may be placed on the steadily increasing wage scales
                    in Latin American mining operations as a serious threat to continued profitable
                    production from existing mines and to development of new deposits. The answer to
                    this is, of course, far from simple, in view of the unique conditions of mining
                    and the unusual hazards attached to new ventures in this field, and also in view
                    of the fact that different conditions exist in every operation. However, the
                    ultimate objective of this country’s economic policy, an expanding world economy
                    to create the atmosphere for enduring world peace, is keyed to higher standards
                    of living which in turn depend on greater productivity which will make possible
                    rising wage levels for all types of labor. The continued high production of
                    United States and Canadian mines in the face of greatly increased wage rates
                    during the last thirty years can be cited as examples indicating that improved
                    production methods permit the payment of higher wages to skilled and efficient
                    labor.</p>
                <p>In July of this year the President approved the Stockpiling Act providing for the
                    accumulation of stocks of strategic materials in <pb facs="0088" n="70" xml:id="pg_70"/> which this country is deficient. The Congress also
                    appropriated $100,000,000 for purchase of these materials to initiate the
                    program. In order to meet anticipated stockpile goals, it will be necessary for
                    the United States to import very large quantities of strategic materials, by far
                    the largest items being minerals and metals. Although the countries of Central
                    and South America together with Canada and Newfoundland in their normal capacity
                    as sources of supply may be called upon to furnish a sizeable proportion of the
                    total requirements, it is not proposed to arrange any special measures for this
                    purpose. Purchases will be made in accordance with the availability of materials
                    of desired quality, not by reference to geographic area. Much has been said in
                    the past and may be repeated in the future, concerning the desirability of
                    hemispheric self-sufficiency both from a resources as well as military security
                    viewpoint. This Government is unqualifiedly opposed to the principle of economic
                    spheres and the Delegation to the present Congress should strive to support the
                    idea of an interchange of manufactured goods and raw materials between all the
                    nations of the world as the only road to creation of the expanding world economy
                    essential to lasting peace.</p>
                <p>During the course of the Congress, the subject of the convocation of the Third
                    Congress will be raised. Should the suggestion be made that the United States
                    act as host, you will seek discreetly to avoid the sponsorship of the next
                    Congress by this Government and in expressing appreciation for the suggestion,
                    point out that you are not authorized by your official instructions to extend an
                    invitation on the part of the United States Government. In this connection, it
                    is considered that the expense of holding sessions of the Congress more
                    frequently than once every two years is not justified in the absence of special
                    circumstances.</p>
                <p>You will appreciate, I am sure, that the members of the Delegation are not
                    authorized to offer any written or oral statement or to enter into any agreement
                    which might be construed as committing this Government to a definite course of
                    action or which might involve an obligation to expend funds not previously
                    appropriated or allocated. Since this is a technical meeting devoted to problems
                    in the field of engineering and geology, it is considered unlikely that any
                    matters of a political or diplomatic character will arise. The Delegation should
                    attempt to confine the discussion in so far as possible to the technical
                    problems on the agenda. However, should difficult or controversial points arise
                    to which there may appear to be no ready solution, it is recommended that the
                    guidance of the Department be sought by telegraph.</p>
                <p>Upon the completion of the Congress, you are requested to submit to the Secretary
                    of State an official report covering the work of the <pb facs="0089" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> Delegation and the action taken by the Congress. Enclosed
                    for your convenience is a suggested outline<note n="3" xml:id="d51fn3">Not
                        printed.</note> for your report which will serve as a convenient checklist
                    of items to be covered and will provide a degree of uniformity with reports of
                    other American delegations, all of which will either be printed separately or
                    summarized in the Department’s Conference Series. The official report should be
                    supplemented by a confidential report containing any other items which in your
                    opinion should be made a matter of confidential record.</p>
                <p>You undertake your responsibilities with the assurance of my keen interest and
                    wholehearted support. I have every confidence in your ability to reflect credit
                    on the United States in this undertaking.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Clayton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
