<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Ambassador in Colombia (
                        Wiley
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d610</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">610</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-03-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-25T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="development-program" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="610" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d610">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">821.7962/2–1146: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-25">March 25,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_A1">A</gloss>–93. Reference is made to your letter of January
                    25, 1946<note n="51" xml:id="d610fn51">Not printed.</note> to Mr. Stokely Morgan
                    of the Department with which was enclosed a memorandum concerning possible
                    nationalization of the airfields in Colombia, including that at Barranquilla, in
                    which the United States <pb facs="0686" n="668" xml:id="pg_668"/> Government has
                    made substantial investments under the Airport Development Program.</p>
                <p>The following facts regarding the Soledad Airport at Barranquilla are set forth
                    for your background information. The field is the only one in Colombia built
                    under the Airport Development Program, and the investment of the United States
                    Government in the field is listed at approximately $650,000. Ownership of the
                    field is vested in Avianca,<note n="52" xml:id="d610fn52">Aerovias Nacionales de
                        Colombia, S.A., formerly <gloss target="#t_Scadta1">Scadta</gloss>.</note>
                    in which airline <gloss target="#t_Pan1">Pan</gloss> American World Airways owns
                    a majority of the stock. The Civil Aeronautics Board has stated informally that
                    full commercial rights will be desired in Soledad Airport and possibly in other
                    Colombian airfields. For your confidential information the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                    have recommended the inclusion of Soledad Airport in a system of hemisphere air
                    bases which would be established by multilateral agreement and at which the
                    United States (along with other American republics) would have transit rights in
                    peacetime and full military rights in emergency. Plans for this air base system
                    anticipate conclusion of the mutual assistance treaty contemplated by the Act of
                        Chapultepec,<note n="53" xml:id="d610fn53">Department of State, Treaties and
                        Other International Acts Series (TIAS) No. 1543.</note> and the
                    establishment of a permanent inter-American military agency, so that no
                    immediate action to realize this plan is possible.</p>
                <p>In connection with the investment of United States funds under the Airport
                    Development Program, your attention is called to the Department’s circular
                    airgram of January 17, 2:30 p.m.,<note n="54" xml:id="d610fn54">Not
                        printed.</note> wherein it was stated that the Department was now in a
                    position to declassify the Airport Development Program contracts or portions
                    thereof at any time, should such action appear to be in the national
                    interest.</p>
                <p>In view of the sizeable investment of United States Government funds in Soledad
                    Airport and of the desired civil and military rights indicated above, the
                    Department would wish to inform the Colombian Government in confidence of that
                    portion of the Airport Development Program pertaining to Soledad Airport if and
                    when it appears that action by the Colombian Government to nationalize the
                    airports in Colombia is imminent. None of the foregoing information should
                    however be conveyed to the Colombian Government except upon specific
                    authorization from the Department.</p>
                <p>Please keep the Department informed of any further developments toward
                    nationalization of the airports in Colombia, and of your recommendations with
                    respect to informing the Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
