<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Dominican Embassy to the Department of State
                    
                    Handed to the Assistant Secretary of State
                        (Braden) by the Dominican Ambassador (Garcia Godoy) on January 14, 1946.
                        Copy transmitted to Ciudad Trujillo in instruction 500, January 25.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d691</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">691</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recy94pCDcRAr4voG" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-expression" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003012251" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of speech</term>
                    <term ref="recqhvaPBazS2SPQl" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-the-press" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051711" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of the press</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="691" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d691">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">830.24/1–846</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Dominican Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="20" xml:id="d691fn1">Handed to the Assistant Secretary of State
                        (Braden) by the Dominican Ambassador (Garcia Godoy) on January 14, 1946.
                        Copy transmitted to Ciudad Trujillo in instruction 500, January 25.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation—Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Government of the Dominican Republic has received with profound surprise the
                        <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> which accompanied the note handed to
                    Ambassador Garcia Godoy by His Excellency Spruille Braden on December 28
                        last,<note n="21" xml:id="d691fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1945v09#pg_993">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 993</ref>.</note> relative to the
                    request for an export license made by the Dominican Embassy at Washington for a
                    certain quantity of ammunition which our Government wished to acquire from the
                    Winchester Repeating Arms Company.</p>
                <p>After studying conscientiously and carefully the reasons set forth in the
                    document under reference for justifying the refusal of the license requested,
                    the Dominican Government considers it to be its duty not to accept the reasons
                    adduced and even to express the displeasure with which it has received them and
                    its desire to refute and contradict them in order duly to clarify a situation
                    which in any case, involves an irritating attitude of prepossession and
                    prejudice against the aims and purposes which this Government has for the public
                    welfare.</p>
                <p rend="center">I</p>
                <p>It was stated that “most of the ammunition sought by the Dominican Government
                    could be used solely for two purposes: either against a neighbor republic or
                    against the people of the Dominican Republic”.</p>
                <p>The Dominican Republic at present maintains excellent relations of friendship
                    with all the republics of the continent, with the exception of a single one
                    …</p>
                <p>If, contrary to what the facts indicate, the expression “neighbor republic”
                    specifically refers to Haiti, to impute to this Government designs of attacking
                    our adjacent neighbor, then the prejudice is all the more unjust and gratuitous
                    because no indication—absolutely none—of an objective nature on the part of the
                    Dominican Government could justify it.</p>
                <p>[Here follows denial of Dominican aims of territorial conquest in Haiti, and a
                    detailed account of Dominican-Haitian relations.]</p>
                <pb facs="0835" n="817" xml:id="pg_817"/>
                <p rend="center">II</p>
                <p>The document to which the present reply is being made presupposes that the
                    ammunition requested by this Government might be used against the people of the
                    Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>The history of the Dominican Republic does not record the existence of a single
                    Government that has placed at the service of its people the interest and zeal
                    which President Trujillo’s Government has done. How is it possible to think that
                    the latter may arm itself against its own people? To insinuate such folly is
                    equivalent to denying in the Dominican people all its chivalrous virtues. In the
                    Dominican Republic there exists at present a close and unbreakable bond of
                    solidarity between the people and the Government; not for simple sentimental
                    reasons, but for more profound reasons of advantage and satisfaction for the
                    masses.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The surest and most evident demonstration of solidarity with their Government was
                    given by the Dominican people during the war. The spirit of discipline and
                    sacrifice with which this country placed itself at the side of the United States
                    from the very day of Pearl Harbor<note n="22" xml:id="d691fn3">December 7,
                        1941.</note> and which was maintained without change and without faltering
                    up to the last minute of the war is a palpable and indisputable result of the
                    bonds of understanding which unite the Dominican Government and people.</p>
                <p>[Here follows an account of the advantages to the Dominican people derived from
                    the political influence of President Trujillo.]</p>
                <p rend="center">III</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The Government and people of the United States necessarily have warmer
                        sentiments for those Governments which rest upon the consent of the governed
                        expressed periodically and freely. This Government has during recent years
                        observed the situation of the Dominican Republic and has not been able to
                        perceive that democratic principles have been followed there either in
                        theory or in practice. The present conclusion is based on the lack of
                        freedom of speech, freedom of the press and freedom of assembly, as well as
                        on the suppression of all political opposition and on the existence of a
                        single party. To furnish a large quantity of ammunition in view of such a
                        situation might be construed as constituting intervention in the internal
                        affairs of the Dominican Republic and as an endorsement of the said
                            practices.”<note n="*" xml:id="d691fn4">The English text of the <hi rend="italic">aide-memoire</hi> was not available to the translator
                            when this translation was made.—TC [Footnote in the file
                            translation.]</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>The first impression that is obtained from a reading of the paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> transcribed above is that the said document
                        <pb facs="0836" n="818" xml:id="pg_818"/> does not take into account the
                    fact that the Dominican Republic is a member of the United Nations and that, as
                    such, has fulfilled and is fulfilling all its duties and obligations and
                    therefore deserves respect and consideration on the part of its friends and
                    allies.</p>
                <p>The present Dominican Government was freely elected by constitutional methods, in
                    the month of May 1942, with the circumstance that this election had more ballots
                    cast than any other in our history. On that occasion there occurred a normal
                    change of government in the Dominican Republic in virtue of the rule of rotation
                    of power.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The affirmation that during recent years it has not been possible to perceive
                    that democratic principles have been observed in the Dominican Republic—either
                    in theory or in practice—is altogether inexact.</p>
                <p>[Here follows a laudatory account of the Dominican Party and its
                    accomplishments.]</p>
                <p rend="center">IV</p>
                <p>The Government of the Dominican Republic has laid great stress on keeping in
                    harmony with that of the United States of America with respect to its needs for
                    military and strategic supplies. This determination was considerably
                    strengthened and increased after the United States entered the war and, with
                    that country, the Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>In this connection it may be asserted that the Washington Government knows for
                    certain and with all exactitude the military possibilities of this country and
                    is perfectly aware of the fact that we cannot get along with the arms which we
                    now possess.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>. . . the armament possessed by the Dominican Army is inadequate and even
                    insufficient for the internal security of the country; it is absolutely
                    impossible for the Dominican Government to cooperate in the defense of the
                    Hemisphere with the war materiel which it now possesses.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The export license requested by the Dominican Ambassador and discussed in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> handed by His Excellency the Assistant
                    Secretary of State refers to ammunition—supplementary materiel—the acquisition
                    of which will not in any way be able to change the present status of our
                    armament, because it is not substantial materiel. This ammunition is intended to
                    keep at a minimum of defensive efficiency the national forces, declared
                    inadequate by American experts.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ciudad Trujillo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-08">January 8,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
