<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-12T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-12T13:00:00-05:00" n="742" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d742">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">822.002/11–1246: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-12T13:00:00-05:00">November 12, 1946—1
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>543. The press of the past few days has discussed the possibility of the
                            appointment of Leonardo Stagg as Minister of Economy to succeed <pb facs="0891" n="873" xml:id="pg_873"/> José Carbo Puig, recently
                            resigned. This morning’s press carries statement by Stagg to effect that
                            he has in fact been offered this position and has it under
                            consideration. Stagg was on the British Black List and our <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> and was deleted with a non-meritorious
                            status.</p>
                        <p>Both the British Legation and myself feel it would be embarrassing to
                            have to deal with a Cabinet Minister in this category but we are both
                            hesitant about mentioning the matter to this Government without
                            instructions as this Government might well consider any such
                            representation as intervention in the domestic politics of Ecuador. If
                            the Department decides to take any action, I strongly recommend the
                            matter be taken up with the Ecuadoran Ambassador in Washington as I am
                            apprehensive representation made here would produce an embarrassing
                            situation between this Embassy and the Government. The matter is
                            pressing as the appointment may be made within 48 hours.<note n="74" xml:id="d742fn74">The Acting Secretary of State in telegram 413,
                                November 14, 1946, 7 p.m., characterized the contemplated action
                                “incomprehensible,” but indicated that the Department was not
                                disposed to take any step that might be construed as interference in
                                domestic matters (822.002/11–1246).</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">scotten</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>