<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Ambassador in Mexico (
                        Thurston
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d847</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">847</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-08-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="employment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" subject="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties and other international acts</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="847" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d847">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.504 Mexico/7–146</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thurston</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 176</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-16">August 16,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to … much previous
                    correspondence between the Department and the Embassy on the subject of
                    clandestine and illegal entries into the United States by Mexican nationals to
                    seek agricultural employment.</p>
                <p>In the communications under reference, the great problem presented to the
                    Immigration and Naturalization Service by the large number of illegal entrants
                    has been amply set forth, and to date the principal problem has been the
                    detention and return to Mexico of such individuals who have been apprehended in
                    the Imperial Valley. There is now enclosed for your information a further
                    communication on this general subject, dated July 1, 1946, from the Attorney
                    General, together <pb facs="1049" n="1031" xml:id="pg_1031"/> with a copy of a
                    memorandum prepared by the District Director of Immigration of the Los Angeles
                        District,<note n="2" xml:id="d847fn2">Neither printed.</note> indicating
                    that the San Diego area has become as great a problem in this regard as the
                    Imperial Valley. The Attorney General stresses the necessity of immediate action
                    because he considers that the situation along the Mexican border is becoming
                    more aggravated daily.</p>
                <p>Since the receipt of the letter under reference, the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service has discussed further developments in this matter with
                    representatives of the Department by telephone. They have stated that further
                    word has been received from the Immigration inspector in charge of the San Diego
                    area that the Mexican immigration officials are refusing to receive Mexican
                    nationals who have resided less than six months in Lower California through the
                    Mexican ports of entry in Lower California. In view of the increasing number of
                    individuals involved, this is placing a very heavy strain on the facilities of
                    the United States Immigration Service. It calls for more detention capacity and
                    the transportation of more individuals at great expense to Nogales, Sonora and
                    to Ciudad Juárez. The fact that those who are returned to Mexico are apparently
                    made the subject of no controls by the Mexican Government is of special concern
                    since the individuals in question make their way back across the border within a
                    very few days of the dates of their departure.</p>
                <p>The Immigration officials point out, in regard to the voluntary deportation of
                    Mexican individuals, that the Mexican federal law does not provide for any
                    selective system such as the one being used in Lower California ports by Mexican
                    officials. The Immigration officials consider therefore, that they are entitled
                    to deliver all Mexican nationals apprehended while illegally in this country to
                    the nearest Mexican port of entry without restrictions. At the same time they
                    point out it is a waste of time and money to transport individuals apprehended
                    in California to Nogales and El Paso for delivery to Mexico, in view of the fact
                    that the Mexican Government has taken no steps to get such individuals away from
                    the border or back to their homes in the interior of Mexico, but has permitted
                    them full freedom as stated above, which has resulted in the early return of
                    most of them to the United States in the same illegal manner.</p>
                <p>The Department shares the concern of the Attorney General and the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service as to these illegal entrants, but as stated in
                    instruction no. 8478<note n="2a" xml:id="d847fn2a">Dated March 18, 1946, <ref target="#pg_1028">p. 1028</ref>.</note> and previous communications it
                    is not too confident that further approaches to the Mexican Government will
                    bring about more than a very temporary solution of this perennial problem. It
                    will be recalled that the conference in May <pb facs="1050" n="1032" xml:id="pg_1032"/> and June of 1944, which was initiated by the Mexican
                    Government, made a series of definite recommendations to both Governments with
                    the unanimous concurrence of the Mexican delegation, the members of which
                    individually promised to do everything within their power toward the carrying
                    out of the recommendations. As the record will show, the Immigration Service has
                    been most zealous in complying with both the spirit and the letter of those
                    recommendations, while there is no indication of effective parallel action by
                    the Mexican Government.</p>
                <p>In view of the persistence of the undesirable situation in the Imperial Valley
                    and the aggravation of the situation in the San Diego area, the Department
                    considers it desirable to go on record again with the Mexican Government in
                    regard to this matter.</p>
                <p>You are therefore requested to prepare an appropriate note to the Mexican Foreign
                    Office reviewing developments since 1944, or earlier, and pointing out that the
                    Immigration Service of the United States has increased its border patrol and has
                    taken many other measures to discourage and to prevent clandestine and illegal
                    entrance into the United States by Mexican nationals. You should request that
                    the Mexican Government give this matter every possible attention with a view to
                    discouraging the movement of individuals toward the Mexican border, especially
                    with California, and with a view to establishing the most active possible patrol
                    service to prevent illegal departure of individuals from Mexico. You may also
                    wish to invite attention to the possibility of the establishment by the Mexican
                    Government of control measures at strategic points some distance from the
                    border, this in view of reports that most of the individuals under reference
                    proceed to Lower California through Santa Ana, Sonora, where transportation
                    facilities are available from the Southern Pacific Railroad to said border
                    ports.</p>
                <p>The Department views sympathetically the desire of the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service to return Mexican nationals apprehended while illegally
                    in the United States through the nearest Mexican port. Such action on the part
                    of the Immigration Service, however, may be considered by the Mexican Government
                    as at least a partial denouncement of the Agreement entered into in 1944 in
                    spite of the fact that there has been little or no Mexican action under that
                    Agreement. If, in spite of the circumstances which have developed, the Mexicans
                    still have an interest in preserving the Agreement, it might be effective to
                    inform them that unless there is immediate evidence of control action by Mexico
                    it will be necessary to consider the Agreement no longer in effect. In your
                    discretion you may, therefore, include in your note to the Mexican Government a
                    statement along the above lines. If, however, it is your opinion that the
                    Mexican Government no longer values the Agreement, you may limit yourself <pb facs="1051" n="1033" xml:id="pg_1033"/> to informing the Mexican Government
                    that the Immigration Service plans to return workers in the future through the
                    nearest Mexican port of entry. You may assure the Mexican Government that the
                    Immigration and Naturalization Service of this Government will continue to take
                    all possible measures to prevent the clandestine entrance of Mexican nationals
                    into the United States.</p>
                <p>The Department will appreciate being furnished at the earliest possible date with
                    a copy of the communication which you address to the Foreign Office on this
                    matter, in order that the Attorney General may be informed of the steps taken.
                    The Immigration Service is especially anxious to proceed without delay with the
                    return of all illegal entrants through the nearest Mexican port of entry because
                    of the reasons set forth above. It would be very desirable, therefore, to have
                    an early word from you on this point for the guidance of the Immigration
                        Service.<note n="3" xml:id="d847fn3">In despatch 1274, October 18, from
                        Mexico City, Ambassador Thurston indicated that in response to this
                        instruction an exchange of notes with the Mexican Foreign Office had taken
                        place, which strengthened the conviction that no effective action would be
                        taken by the Mexican authorities to assist in the curtailment of the illegal
                        movement of its nationals across the border. It was proposed that vigilance
                        of the border patrol be increased and that State Governments and immigration
                        authorities be urged to impress workers with the need of giving Mexico the
                        fruit of their labors. The only concession brought about by the exchange of
                        notes, Ambassador Thurston noted, was qualified, in that the Mexican
                        Government expressed its willingness to accept deportees at Tijuana and
                        Mexicali. if they entered the United States through those ports. (811.504
                        Mexico/10–1846)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Acting Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Spruille Braden</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[An agreement between the United States and Mexico respecting Mexican
                        non-agricultural workers, which terminated the agreement of April 29, 1943,
                        was effected by exchange of notes signed at Washington November 15, 1946.
                        For texts of notes, see Department of State, Treaties and Other
                        International Acts Series No. 1684, or 61 Stat. (pt. 4) 3575.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
