<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="878" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d878">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">817.51/4–1046</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the
                                Assistant Chief of the Division of Caribbean and Central American
                                Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Newbegin</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-10">April 10, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Upon the receipt of Managua’s telegram 235, April 9<note n="35" xml:id="d878fn35">Not printed.</note> stating that President Somoza
                            had instructed Mr. James of <gloss target="#t_PRA1">PRA</gloss><note n="36" xml:id="d878fn36">Edwin W. James, Chief of the Inter-American
                                Regional Office, Public Roads Administration (<gloss target="#t_PRA1">PRA</gloss>).</note> to pay the Export-Import
                            Bank the amount of arrears due on its loan to Nicaragua from funds
                            payable to Nicaragua by <gloss target="#t_PRA1">PRA</gloss> for road
                            construction, I telephoned Ambassador Warren this morning to inform him
                            (1) that President Somoza was not in a position to instruct James to pay
                            the Exim Bank and that any payment due to Nicaragua by the Public Roads
                            Administration should be made in the usual manner, (2) that we had
                            maintained all along and continued to so maintain that there was no
                            connection between the two sums due the respective governments <pb facs="1106" n="1088" xml:id="pg_1088"/> and that the Exim Bank loan
                            was a direct obligation of the Nicaraguan Government and stands by
                            itself.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Warren replied that he had been unfortunate in his use of the
                            word “instructed” since President Somoza had merely requested that this
                            be done. He said further that the President had acknowledged fully on
                            two occasions that there was no connection whatsoever between the two
                            matters but that it would be of great assistance to the Nicaraguans were
                            Mr. James to make the payment directly to the Bank. He said that in view
                            of the fact that James had agreed to do so, it would be exceedingly
                            embarrassing to go back at this time to the President and state that we
                            would not comply with his request. He was, however, ready to do so
                            provided the Department wished him to. I suggested that payment direct
                            to the Exim Bank would set a precedent which we were very anxious to
                            avoid and suggested that possibly Mr. James could make his payment to
                            the Nicaraguan Embassy which in turn could pay the Exim Bank. The
                            Ambassador said that he was having luncheon with Mr. James and that he
                            would review the matter with him and call me later.</p>
                        <p>He telephoned again this afternoon emphasizing once more that there was
                            no question in President Somoza’s mind as to the lack of connection
                            between the two sums and that he and James were both of the opinion that
                            since the President was particularly desirous of paying off the amounts
                            due the Bank he could only interpret our refusal now to make this
                            payment as an attempt to humiliate him. For this reason he felt it was
                            undesirable to take it up with him again. I replied that under these
                            circumstances it might be best to let the matter rest until Mr. James
                            returned to Washington when it could be discussed further here. I
                            suggested also that there would appear to be some question whether James
                            could be authorized by <gloss target="#t_PRA1">PRA</gloss> to make any
                            payment to the Exim Bank. The Ambassador said that he was in accord and
                            that no further action would be taken in Managua.<note n="37" xml:id="d878fn37">A memorandum of April 23 by the Special Assistant
                                of the Division of Investment and Development (Stenger), reported to
                                Mr. Newbegin that the Export-Import Bank had informed him (1) that a
                                payment of approximately $77,000, the amount of the amortization and
                                interest in arrears, had been received from Nicaragua, and (2) that
                                the Bank had informed Mr. James that as Nicaragua had paid the
                                overdue account it would not be necessary to use the <gloss target="#t_PRA1">PRA</gloss> funds at that time
                                (817.51/4–2346).</note></p>
                        <closer><signed>R[<hi rend="smallcaps">obert</hi>] N[<hi rend="smallcaps">ewbegin</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>