<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Panama ( (Hines))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d888</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">888</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-05-17T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-17T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-17T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-17T13:00:00-05:00" n="888"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d888">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.19/5–1046: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hines</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-17T14:00:00-04:00"
                            >May 17, 1946—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>278. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 317 May 10, 1946. You have
                    proceeded correctly in indicating to ForMin that this Govt in preparation for
                    round table discussions is quite ready to study preliminary memoranda on pending
                    matters of importance to Panama. In the meantime we should begin drawing up a
                    list of topics, such as defense areas, aviation agreement, Mariposa claims,
                    etc., which this Govt will wish to submit to Panama. You might ask Canal Zone
                    authorities whether they can present to Embassy at early date requests they may
                    wish to make of Panama.</p>
                <p>It is believed that round table discussions as well as negotiations themselves
                    should take place in Panama. War Dept concurs. Accordingly, you are authorized
                    when agreeable to all parties concerned <pb facs="1119" n="1101"
                        xml:id="pg_1101"/> on the Isthmus to inaugurate informal preliminary
                    exploratory discussions of Panamanian requests. Dept desires to be kept fully
                    informed and consulted in advance of the making of definite commitments either
                    by implication or otherwise.</p>
                <p>Dept appreciates spirit of frankness with which ForMin has approached you on
                    these problems. He should be so informed. At the same time, in your discretion,
                    in the same spirit of frankness and in order that there be no misunderstanding,
                    you should make clear that a specific commitment from Panama for a satisfactory
                    settlement of the Mariposa claims will be expected before negotiations go beyond
                    the stage of informal conversations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
