<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Murray M. Wise of the
                        Division of Caribbean and Central American Affairs</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v11</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d924</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">924</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="discrimination" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376" lcsh-match="exact">Race discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recJ6MU2FCTi4lexO" type="compound-subject" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="racial-discrimination" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110237" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Racial Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" subject="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="924" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d924">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.19/1–2345</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Murray M. Wise of the
                        Division of Caribbean and Central American Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-23">January 23,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">General Crittenberger, Commanding Officer,
                            Caribbean Defense Command</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">General Walsh, War Department<note n="71" xml:id="d924fn71">Maj. Gen. Robert L. Walsh, Army Air Forces.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">General Hertford<note n="72" xml:id="d924fn72">Brig. Gen. Kenner F. Hertford, <gloss target="#t_Pan1">Pan</gloss>
                                American Group, Operations Division, War Department.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">W. J. Donnelly, Counselor of Embassy,
                            Panama</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_ABr1">A–Br</gloss>—Mr. Braden, Assistant Secretary of
                            State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>—Mr. Briggs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_RL1">RL</gloss>—Mr. Dreier</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>—Mr. Cochran</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>—Mr. Wise</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">5. Race Discrimination</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Braden called attention to the old complaint from the Panamanians that Canal
                    Zone authorities discriminate in the treatment of “gold” and “silver” employees.
                    He said that recently Charles W. Taussig, Chairman, United States Section of the
                    Anglo-American Caribbean Commission,<note n="73" xml:id="d924fn73">An advisory
                        body representative of the United Kingdom, the United States, France, and
                        the Netherlands. It sponsored a conference, held in February and March,
                        1946, of representatives of 15 territories of these four powers to make
                        recommendations on problems of education, public health, agriculture,
                        nutrition, handicrafts, and local manufacturing.</note> had discussed the
                    race problem in the whole Caribbean area with President Truman, who had
                    expressed an interest in having a memorandum prepared on the subject. Mr. Braden
                    said that Mr. Taussig was endeavoring to determine what influence Moscow was
                    wielding on important labor leaders in the Caribbean area. He believed that if
                    there were no objection, Mr. Taussig might be given the opportunity to explain
                    his apprehensions to those present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Taussig briefly outlined some of the activities of organized labor in the
                    Caribbean area referring particularly to the Caribbean Labor Conference which
                    had been held in Barbados in October 1945. He <pb facs="1168" n="1150" xml:id="pg_1150"/> mentioned that the Anglo-American Caribbean Commission
                    had a fairly complete file on the conference. He saw significance in several
                    occurrences there: (1) the singing of the “International” and the display of
                    hammer and sickle insignia; (2) the speeches that were made in opposition to the
                    United States remaining in the 99-year leased bases. He called attention to the
                    fact that although the conference was not sponsored by the colonial governments
                    or Great Britain, the Acting Governor of Barbados made the opening speech and
                    other governmental officials attended, including the British Co-Chairman of the
                    Anglo-American Caribbean Commission, Sir John Macpherson. References were made
                    at the Conference to the fact that one objection to the United States retaining
                    possession of the bases was the fact that Americans brought with them racial
                    discrimination.</p>
                <p>Mr. Taussig called attention to the fact that the United States had ratified the
                    Charter of the United Nations, and that it was the United States which took a
                    prominent part in drafting Chapter XI of the Charter which is the Declaration
                    regarding non-self governing territories. Mr. Taussig felt that the United
                    States should assume a moral leadership in relation to dependent peoples, and
                    that the racial problem was of prime importance in this field. Mr. Taussig
                    further stated that it was his opinion that the attitude and action of the
                    United States in these matters particularly in the Caribbean area would have
                    considerable repercussions in Latin America. Mr. Taussig, again referring to
                    racial tension, stated that although the evidence was not complete, there
                    appeared to be a definite link between Moscow and Caribbean labor groups. He was
                    interested in hearing any comments which General Crittenberger and Mr. Donnelly
                    might have to make.</p>
                <p>General Crittenberger said that since his Command covered the whole Caribbean
                    area he was very much interested in the labor situation which was a vital factor
                    in any of his plans. He said his officers had been following labor tendencies
                    with the greatest of care and that the successful dealing with laborers in the
                    program for the defense of the Caribbean area would require the sympathetic
                    consideration and cooperation of all parties concerned, such as the Army, the
                    State Department and the Anglo-Caribbean Commission. General Crittenberger
                    supported the contention of Mr. Taussig that the Communists were taking
                    considerable interest in the area. He said that recently there was an occurrence
                    in the Canal Zone which he felt was of Communist origin. During the agitation of
                    the troops under his command to be sent home after <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">VJ
                        Day</gloss>, posters appealing to the troops to protest were posted in
                    various parts of the Reservation. The troops were addressed in these posters as
                    “comrades”. Mr. Braden asked Mr. Donnelly to express his views with respect to
                    the race question in Panama.</p>
                <pb facs="1169" n="1151" xml:id="pg_1151"/>
                <p>Mr. Donnelly said that the Embassy has always taken the position that the most
                    dangerous issues in Panama are <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the landlord-tenant relationship, and</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the West Indian negro problem,</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">and that the agitation of either at this time could result
                    in</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                    <item>complete disruption of the present work of the Panamanian Constitution
                        Assembly in its preparation of the new constitution. (He explained that the
                        Assembly had left its discussion of Panama’s immigration policy until the
                        last), and</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                    <item>bloodshed and revolution such as occurred in the early days of the Panama
                        Canal.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Donnelly said that the Embassy believed, and he was convinced General
                    Crittenberger and Governor Mehaffey<note n="74" xml:id="d924fn74">Maj. Gen.
                        Joseph C. Mehaffey, Governor of the Panama Canal.</note> would agree with
                    it, that the appointment at this time of any outside committee, commission or
                    group, no matter what it is called, would be detrimental to the interests of the
                    Republic of Panama, as well as the United States Government. Mr. Donnelly said
                    there were certain factors in the Canal Zone labor situation vis-à-vis the
                    Republic of Panama which needed correction, but expressed his firm conviction
                    that the study and recommendations should be made by the Embassy and the
                    appropriate Canal Zone authorities.</p>
                <p>The meeting was adjourned with the understanding that General Crittenberger would
                    discuss with officers of the North and West Coast Republics problems of
                    particular interest in that area of the General’s Command. Detailed discussions
                    of the Panamanian problems mentioned above, as well as others which should be
                    taken up, were to be continued between Mr. Donnelly and officers of <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
