<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs (
                    (Hickerson) ) to the Director of the Policy Planning Staff ( (Nitze))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d134</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">134</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="134"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Disarmament Files, Lot 58 D 133<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d134fn1">Consolidated collection of documentation in the Department
                        of State on the regulation of armaments and disarmament for the years
                        1942–1962.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for United
                        Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Policy Planning Staff</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Nitze</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-31">July 31,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: S/P Draft Memorandum on “Manner of Advancing
                    Disarmament Proposals on the Basis of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        112”<note n="2" xml:id="d134fn2">The subject draft, dated July 26, is not
                        printed. For a memorandum prepared by the Policy Planning Staff titled
                        “Manner of Advancing Disarmament Proposals,” which was transmitted to
                        British representatives on August 20, see <ref target="#pg_515">p.
                        515</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I have one major comment on the subject paper. I believe that it is inadvisable
                    for the United States to take the position that it is necessary to come to an
                    agreement on the treatment of Germany and Japan as a prior condition to United
                    States participation in a general program for the regulation and reduction of
                    armaments and armed forces. This concept is set forth throughout the draft
                    paper, particularly on pages 3 and 5–10.</p>
                <p>The reasons for my conclusion can be briefly stated as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The purpose of developing United States proposals for a system of
                            regulation, limitation and balanced reduction of armaments and armed
                            forces is stated in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 112 as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The purpose of this study is the establishment of a foundation
                                    upon which positions may be built which would, if accepted by
                                    the Soviet Union, be acceptable to the United States or, if
                                    rejected by the Soviet Union, be advantageous to the United
                                    States and the Western powers for their propaganda value.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <lb/> Since there is not one chance in a thousand that the Soviet Union
                            will accept the proposals, their chief purpose is certainly their
                            propaganda value. By establishing conditions precedent in the ways
                            advocated in the subject paper, we are surrendering the propaganda
                            battle in the field of regulation of armaments to the Soviets, who will
                            claim that we do not really wish to carry out the proposals we advocate
                            speciously since we attach impossible conditions precedent to our
                            proposals. The USSR will say, as they have in the past, that they have
                            advocated and continue to press for simple and direct disarmament
                            proposals without linking these to other problems.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The draft paper recognizes the risk of war in the next two years,
                            while we are rebuilding our armed strength, but deprecates the
                            possibility that the very fact of making proposals in the regulation of
                            armaments field may lessen the risk of war during this period. I believe
                            that we would gain substantially in terms of a negotiating device if we
                            can make our proposals in such a way that the Soviets cannot summarily
                            reject them because conditions precedent have been laid down before they
                            can be considered.</item>
                        <pb facs="0516" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 112 postulates that there are
                            definite advantages which the United States could realize from the
                            disclosure of forces and armaments if, as seems unlikely, the USSR
                            should accept the U.S. proposals. These advantages exist independent of
                            prior conditions. Are they not sufficient to warrant the United States
                            making the proposals without attaching prior conditions which give the
                            USSR a perfect excuse for rejecting the proposals and for gaining
                            propaganda advantages by so doing?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I suggest that a preferable formula for the relationship of German and Japanese
                    peace treaties to the program of regulation of armaments would be along the
                    following lines: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The field of regulation and control of armaments is one of many areas
                            of conflict between the USSR and the West.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>We cannot expect to carry out proposals which we may make in the
                            armaments field without making progress in the other areas of tension
                            between the Soviet Union and the West.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>However, we should advance proposals for the regulation and control of
                            armaments in such manner as to make clear that, while advanced
                            separately, they are linked to simultaneous progress in other
                            fields—notably the completion of peace treaties for Austria, Japan and a
                            unified Germany.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
