<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Draft Memorandum by the Special Assistant to the Secretary of State (
                    (Aimeson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="rec626bb089a1004d2" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Atomic
                        weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec8a611f7fa402cf8" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic Energy Act of</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="257"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d257">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Atomic Energy Files, Lot 57 D 688</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Special
                            Assistant</gloss> to the Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aimeson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-10">September 10,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum for the Secretary</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Proposals to Test First British Atomic Weapon at Las
                    Vegas</p>
                <p>The status of the British request to us to assist them in testing their first
                    atomic weapons at Las Vegas is as follows: <list>
                        <item>Following on the CPC meeting of August 27 appropriate staff
                            representatives from the Department of Defense and the Atomic Energy
                            Commission have sought jointly to work up a counter-proposal which would
                            go a long way toward meeting the British request without overstepping
                            the limits of the Atomic Energy Act of 1946. The U.S. counter-proposal
                                (attached)<note n="1" xml:id="d257fn1">
                                <p>The attachment does not accompany the source text and has not
                                    been found in Department of State files. On September 18, Robert
                                    A. Lovett, who had succeeded General Marshall as Secretary of
                                    Defense on the previous day, and Gordon Dean, Chairman of the
                                    United States Atomic Energy Commission, transmitted an agreed
                                    counterproposal to Secretary of State Acheson, the Chairman of
                                    the Combined Policy Committee. Also on September 18, R. Gordon
                                    Arneson, American Secretary of the Combined Policy Committee,
                                    transmitted the counterproposal to F. W. Marten, the British
                                    Secretary. In each case, the attachment does not accompany the
                                    communication of transmittal in the files.</p>
                                <p>On October 15, Dean transmitted to Arneson and the Department of
                                    Defense an amplification of the basic U.S. counterproposal. This
                                    understanding had been arrived at through discussions over the
                                    previous two weeks between representatives of the Department of
                                    Defense, the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, and the United
                                    Kingdom. The U.S. Atomic Energy Commission approved this
                                    enlarged version subject to concurrence by State and Defense.
                                    The revised draft consisted of the September 18 text with
                                    proposed modifications indicated. This six-page understanding,
                                    not printed, concerned itself with technical, logistical, and
                                    financial considerations, and outlined the areas of
                                    participation, obligations, and responsibilities of each party
                                    in test operations. (Atomic Energy Files, Lot 57 D 688)</p>
                            </note> has been approved by the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> and
                            is now awaiting approval of the Department of Defense. Certain minor
                            changes have been made in the proposal at Mr. LeBaron’s request. <pb
                                facs="0785" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> With these changes, which are
                            not substantive, he has approved the proposal but wishes to show it both
                            to the Joint Chiefs of Staff and to Mr. Lovett before giving final
                            concurrence. It is expected that the proposal will be agreed to by both
                            the agencies primarily concerned and sent to me for transmittal to the
                            British before the end of the week.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The U.S. counter-proposals appear to me to be reasonable and should, I feel,
                    prove acceptable to the British. Both the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                    and the Department of Defense have striven to go as far as the law will permit.
                    The services which are being offered to the British should make it possible for
                    them to conduct an adequate first test and obtain all the necessary basic data
                    concerning it.</p>
                <p>Should Foreign Minister Herbert Morrison speak to you today about the test
                        proposal<note n="2" xml:id="d257fn2">Morrison was in Washington for meetings
                        of the Foreign Ministers of the United States, the United Kingdom, and
                        France, September 10–14. The memorandum of the Acheson–Morrison conversation
                        on atomic energy questions, September 10 (p. 880), indicates that the
                        subject of the test did not arise. However, the matter of the exchange of
                        information was discussed. For documentation on the Foreign Ministers
                        conference, see <ref target="frus1951v03p1#pg_1163">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1163</ref> ff.</note> you may wish to
                    respond along the following lines: <list>
                        <item>The United States is very hopeful that it will be possible to work out
                            means whereby the first British atomic weapon can be tested at Las
                            Vegas. Certan counter-proposals have been drawn up and it is expected
                            that these will shortly be submitted to the United Kingdom. The United
                            States hopes very much that the United Kingdom will find the U.S
                            counter-proposals acceptable. For its part the United States will have
                            gone as far as it is possible to do under the Atomic Energy Act of 1946.
                            In other words the U.S. counter-proposals, which it is hoped will be
                            transmitted within the next few days, represents the best offer that the
                            United States is able to make.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon Arneson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
