<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Embassy in the United
                    Kingdom ( (Penfield))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="262"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.13/10–1651</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Embassy in
                        the United Kingdom</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Penfield</hi>)<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d262fn1">Transmitted as the enclosure to despatch 1777 from London,
                        October 16.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-09">October 9,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I called on General Morgan<note n="2" xml:id="d262fn2">Lt. Gen. Sir Frederick
                        Morgan, British Controller of Atomic Energy.</note> in his office this
                    afternoon. During the course of our conversation he made the following comments
                    regarding his new duties which he formally assumed about October 1: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>He had just concluded a tour of what he referred to as his “Northern
                            diocese”, and said that he had been pleasantly surprised and greatly
                            encouraged by the attitude of the people working in the program. He said
                            they had a real enthusiasm and esprit which he felt indicated that they
                            were doing effective work.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>He said that, although he believed there were only two unsettled
                            points in connection with Dr. Penney’s negotiations in Washington, he
                            was rather pessimistic regarding the outcome. He exhibited not the
                            slightest resentment over the difficulties being encountered by Dr.
                            Penney, but on the contrary showed a very understanding and sympathetic
                            attitude toward the public and private difficulties faced by the
                            American authorities. He confirmed that the only steps that the British
                            have taken to develop their own facilities is to send out a few
                            reconnaissance parties.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>General Morgan said that the thing which bothered him most about his
                            set-up was the security situation. He indicated that the Government’s
                            decision regarding revised procedures which was made as the result of
                            the recent U.S.–U.K. security talks in London has not yet been
                            implemented because the Cabinet had not given final approval. He
                            explained that the contemplated changes had important internal political
                            potentialities, and gave as his private opinion that nothing would be
                            done before the elections. He was, however, optimistic that no matter
                            which Party wins, the situation would be very quickly cleared up after
                            the elections are over.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>He anticipates that if, as is generally expected, the Conservative
                            Government comes into power after October 25th, there will almost
                            certainly be a reorganization of the atomic energy program embodying at
                            least some of the ideas advanced by Lord Cherwell<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d262fn3">Philosopher, physicist, and statesman. Personal
                                assistant to Prime Minister Churchill, 1940; Paymaster-General,
                                1942–1945.</note> in the House of Lords debate on the subject early
                            last summer. (In view of Lord Cherwell’s close association with
                            Churchill and the latter’s great reliance upon him in scientific
                            matters, this would seem to be almost a foregone conclusion.) General
                            Morgan, however, does not expect any immediate drastic action, as he
                            tends to believe that the atomic energy <pb facs="0791" n="775"
                                xml:id="pg_775"/> program reorganization will form part of a larger
                            governmental reorganization involving the rationalization of the
                            previously conflicting responsibilities of the Ministry of Supply,
                            Ministry of Materials and Board of Trade.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>General Morgan emphasized several times during the conversation his
                            desire to develop closer and mutually profitable Anglo-American atomic
                            energy relations, but he had a very realistic and sympathetic
                            understanding of the American side of the problem. In this connection he
                            expressed the hope that Colonel Damon’s<note n="4" xml:id="d262fn4">Lt.
                                Col. John C. Damon, Assistant Army Attaché, United States Embassy in
                                the United Kingdom.</note> arrival could be speeded up so that the
                            gap left by Colonel Langguth’s<note n="5" xml:id="d262fn5">Lt. Col. Paul
                                O. Langguth, former Assistant Army Attaché, United States Embassy in
                                the United Kingdom.</note>departure could be filled as promptly as
                            possible.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ames</hi>] K. P[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >enfield</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
