<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff ( (Bradley) ) to the
                    Director of the Joint Staff ( (Davis))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="295"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">S/AE Files, Lot 68 D 358<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d295fn1">Files relating to atomic energy policy matters for the
                        years 1950–1967, maintained initially by the Office of the Special Assistant
                        to the Secretary of State for Atomic Energy Affairs and later by the Office
                        of Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Politico-Military Affairs.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bradley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Joint Staff</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-16">16 May
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The attached paper, which is in substance a study made by the British Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff on atomic warfare,<note n="2" xml:id="d295fn2">The British
                        paper, dated February 22, is not printed.</note> was handed to me this date
                    by Air Chief Marshal Elliot. Elliot emphasized that this paper is nothing but a
                    basis for discussion with us, and is in no way to be considered as his
                    Government’s policy in the matter. This is the only copy which Marshal Elliot
                    has, but he has authorized us to reproduce it in sufficient quantity to
                    distribute to our Chiefs and Deputies for discussion purposes.</p>
                <p>As further background, this matter was first broached to our Government last
                    summer. This particular paper was discussed by Ambassador Franks with Secretary
                    Acheson a few days ago.<note n="3" xml:id="d295fn3">No record of the
                        conversation has been found in Department of State files.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Air Chief Marshal Elliot expressed the hope that after we have discussed the
                    matter we would see fit to make a similar study which would serve us as a basis
                    for discussion with them at an early date on a political-military level.</p>
                <p>I suggest, therefore, that you make a very limited distribution of this study and
                    then let me have this original back so I can return it to Air Chief Marshal
                    Elliot.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>O[<hi rend="smallcaps">mar</hi>] N. B[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >radley</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
