<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Economic Resources and Security
                    Staff ( (Wright) ) to the Special Assistant to the Counselor of the Department
                    of State ( (Kirlin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="export-control" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046493" lcsh-match="exact">Export controls</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="367"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">460.509/3–2351</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Economic Resources
                        and Security Staff</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wright</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Special Assistant to the Counselor of the
                        Department of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirlin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-23">March 23,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Meeting with Mr. Roy Bullock, Staff Member of the
                    Special Subcommittee of the House Foreign Affairs Committee</p>
                <p>As arranged through your office on March 21, Mr. Bullock came to my office this
                    morning to ask a number of questions concerning export controls and to outline
                    briefly the type report he was to prepare for the use of the Battle
                    Subcommittee. Mr. Bullock explained that the report should be completed by the
                    middle of April and would be required to support any action the House Foreign
                    Affairs Committee may take on H.E. 1939 and H.E. 1621 (to cut off financial and
                    economic assistance to countries exporting “war material” to the Soviet
                        Bloc).<note n="1" xml:id="d367fn1">A Special Subcommittee of the House
                        Foreign Affairs Committee, chaired by Laurie C. Battle of Alabama, began
                        executive hearings on March 5 in order to examine the two House bills under
                        reference. For information concerning the report of the Special
                        Subcommittee, subsequently known as the Battle Report, see the editorial
                        note, <ref target="#pg_1176">p. 1176</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Bullock expressed special interest in ascertaining which part of the
                    executive branch was responsible for the “grand strategy” in the field of
                    economic relations with the Soviet Bloc, and what individual “master-minds” this
                    East-West strategy. Although taking exception to Mr. Bullock’s phraseology, I
                    indicated that this office has primary jurisdiction for policy formulation in
                    the trade security field in consultation with other Government agencies. I did
                    not mention the current discussion in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    for the creation of a high-level strategy board in the State Department. Should
                    such a board be established, however, it would undoubtedly reduce the number of
                    such questions by Congress.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bullock emphasized that East-West trade is a “hot” political issue and that
                    the Battle Subcommittee does not intend to “whitewash” existing United States
                    and allied controls without careful investigation. In this connection, Mr.
                    Bullock stated he felt there was <pb facs="1075" n="1059" xml:id="pg_1059"/>
                    entirely too much secrecy concerning export controls. Mr. Bullock expressed
                    particular interest in British, German, and Japanese controls.</p>
                <p>In the course of this hour-long conversation, a considerable amount of
                    confidential information similar to that given by Mr. Thorp in executive session
                    was discussed with Mr. Bullock. In view of the nature of the conversation and
                    future requests for information Mr. Bullock may make to this office, I would
                    like to suggest, if you think it appropriate, that you attempt to arange with
                    Congressman Battle for informal submission of Mr. Bullock’s report to the State
                    Department in advance of distribution for review at least from a security
                    standpoint.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
