<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-03-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-02T23:00:00-05:00" n="373" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>On May 9, James P. Kem, United States Senator from Missouri, introduced an
                        amendment to the Third Supplemental Appropriation Act (<gloss target="#t_H.R.1">H.R.</gloss> 3587) which would deny further economic
                        aid to any country which shipped materials of war to the Soviet Union,
                        China, or any Soviet satellite. The following day the amendment, which Kem
                        described as identical to the Wherry Resolution, was approved by the Senate
                        without objection and sent to the House. On May 18 a Senate–House conference
                        on the Third Supplemental Appropriation Bill resolved to favor denying
                        economic aid to any country which sent arms or military matériels to the
                        Soviet bloc subject to exceptions made by the President on the advice of the
                        National Security Council. The Kem Amendment, as revised by the joint
                        conference, was unanimously approved along with the Third Supplemental
                        Appropriation Bill by both Houses of Congress on May 21. President Truman
                        protested against the Kem Amendment but signed the appropriation bill on
                        June 2. For the text of the Kem Amendment and the subsequent discussion of
                        the amendment in Congress, see the <hi rend="italic">Congressional
                            Record</hi>, vol. 97, pt. 4, pages 5100–5102, 5195–5199, and 5507–5514.
                        For the text of President Truman’s statement of June 2, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                            Harry S. Truman, 1951</hi>, pages 316–320.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>