<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-22T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-22T19:00:00-05:00" n="514" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d514">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">394.31/1–2251: Circular telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic
                                Offices</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d514fn1">Sent to the Embassies at
                                Paris, London, Brussels, Copenhagen, Athens, Rome, The Hague, Oslo,
                                Stockholm, and Ankara; the Legations at Vienna and Luxembourg; the
                                High Commissioner at Frankfurt (Germany), for action. Sent to the
                                U.S. Delegation at Torquay for information.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-22T19:00:00-05:00">January
                                    22, 1951—7p. m</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>413. For <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission from State and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>1. <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> Conference Torquay, England has presented plan for
                            multilateral tariff negots <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>
                            countries, US and Canad in attempt solve problem inequalities tariff
                            levels <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries which may
                            obstruct further <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> liberalization
                            efforts. Private mtg was held Torquay Jan 16 at which UK, <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>, Ital, Fr, Aust, Nor, Swed,
                            Den, Ger, Canad, US were represented. In presenting plan, <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> recalled <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> Council Ministers decision Oct 27, 1950 pledging
                            progress at Torquay session toward removal disparities <gloss target="#t_Eur1">Eur</gloss> tariffs.</p>
                        <p>2. US <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> as result instrs from Wash and
                            with <gloss target="#t_TAC1">TAC</gloss> approval, took position that
                            although <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> proposal is being
                            made very late in Torquay negots, nevertheless proposal has merit and
                            shld be fully explored in hope that positive results may be obtained by
                            this method at least on ltd list of items before end Torquay
                            session.</p>
                        <p>3. At mtg Canad agreed with US that proposal had merit and urged that
                                <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries proceed negot and
                            present concrete proposal before other <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>s, for consideration as to reciprocal payment. UK, Fr, Ital,
                            although emphasizing difficulties did not oppose <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> proposal. Den, Nor, Ger
                            generally supported.</p>
                        <p>4. Further exploratory mtg to be held Jan 25. <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> has proposed use of possibly one section Brussels
                            Study Group nomenclature and Brussels <gloss target="#t_Eur1">Eur</gloss> average as basis discussion; Fr suggested <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> common liberalization list or variant
                            thereof. Negots likely be confined products important intra-<gloss target="#t_Eur1">Eur</gloss> trade and not prime interest US.</p>
                        <p>5. Since Torquay negots scheduled end Feb 28, time is short. If
                            significant accomplishments this <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                            session, US prepared consider reciprocal concessions for indirect
                            benefits of any tariff reductions or bindings resulting these
                            multilateral negots at Torquay. However, US is not prepared to
                            participate in multilateral negots of any scope after Torquay and wld
                            not now be able give commitment re US concession in payment indirect
                            benefits derived therefrom as result negots among <pb facs="1345" n="1329" xml:id="pg_1329"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries. Question compensation
                            wld have to be left open for consideration in light facts existing at
                            time results presented to <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>s. This
                            limitation on US future participation emphasizes importance results
                            being achieved at Torquay.</p>
                        <p>6. In view above consideration and urgency some solution problem
                            inequality in tariffs <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries,
                            US feels most important that proposal for multilateral procedure and
                            immed negots be supported. Expect tendency particularly on part UK, Fr,
                            Ital to drag their feet. Missions urged therefore, to use concerted
                            pressure in order to indicate to govts importance concrete results these
                            negots and express US view that every effort shld be made to make as
                            much progress as possible during life Torquay. Missions may wish point
                            out importance making progress in interest removing important roadblock
                            to further trade liberalization. Missions shld indicate that Torquay
                            delegs <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries shld be prepared
                            with lists commodities for discussion Jan 25 mtg.</p>
                        <p>Missions shld also emphasize that US support this project in no way
                            detracts great importance it attaches successful conclusion Torquay
                            negots now in progress. Therefore, it shld also be urged by the Missions
                            that every effort be exerted by the govts on their delegs to consummate
                            successful Torquay bilaterals as well.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>