<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-06T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-06T18:00:00-05:00" n="576" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d576">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">394.31/9–651: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United
                                    Kingdom</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-06T19:00:00-04:00">September
                                    6, 1951—7 p. m</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1373. Urtel 1248 Sep 6.</p>
                        <p>1. Agree need for full consultation other <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss>s Geneva before official discussion at <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> plenary session; however wld hope
                            such consultation not take full two weeks. Thorp<note n="1" xml:id="d576fn1">Assistant Secretary of State Thorp was to head the
                                United States Delegation.</note> can stay only two weeks and <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> will appreciate desirability
                            settlement before he leaves.</p>
                        <p>2. Answers <gloss target="#t_Depcirtel1">Depcirtel</gloss> 199
                            tentatively show approx 14 favorable votes (including UK) for US action.
                            Melander states Nor will definitely support and implies support Denmark
                            and Swed as well. Is optimistic re success and implies that as chmn he
                            will do best get proposal through. List of 14 excludes possible
                            additional favorable votes of Australia, New Zealand, Sou Afr, Fr, Neth,
                            Belg, Lux, Ital, Sou Rhodesia. Since 16 votes needed, only necessary
                            obtain 2 votes immediately foregoing list. Dept will probably approach
                            Fr, Ital, Neth at highest level this purpose and wld appreciate similar
                            approach by <pb facs="1416" n="1400" xml:id="pg_1400"/> Brit. Fr vote
                            obviously critical. Australia, New Zealand unsure but impression is they
                            will eventually vote our favor. Obviously, impossible obtain
                            Commonwealth support without UK vote. Consider Burma, Ceylon, Finland,
                            India, Indonesia, probably will abstain, most unlikely vote for.</p>
                        <p>3. US position not inflexible re details text reso. However, US
                            discussions other countries, esp. smaller countries W <gloss target="#t_Eur1">Eur</gloss> indicate that proposal for gen waiver,
                            implying similar action by all or several <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>’s wld meet much greater resistance than bilateral
                            waiver. Our estimate is that if we put forward gen waiver we might lose
                            at least 9 potential votes (Belg, Can, Denmark, Fr, Ital, Lux, Neth,
                            Nor, Swed). Nevertheless, bilat waiver of UK-Czech relations cld be
                            considered if this is what UK wants.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>