<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>128. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Systems Analysis
                    (Enthoven) to Secretary of Defense ) to Secretary of Defense McNamara</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="recWnMoFvE8rSByAg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89000403"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Survivability</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005004553"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Warheads</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113036"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Research and development</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Missile defense</term>
                    <term ref="recInQ6JTYKBeryID" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Mobile
                        missiles</term>
                    <term ref="reckP3QiieAZd7kwE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003001255"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Launchers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="128"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d128">
                <head>128. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Systems Analysis
                        (<persName corresp="#p_EAC1" type="from">Enthoven</persName>) to Secretary
                    of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1" type="to">McNamara</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d128fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1"
                            >FRC</gloss> 330 70 A 4662, 381 SRF 1966. Top Secret. “Sec Def has seen,
                        24 May 1966” is stamped on the memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-05-23">May 23, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Interaction of U.S. Assured Destruction and Damage Limiting Forces
                        (U)</item>
                </list>
                <p>Last year’s Memorandum to the President on Strategic Offensive and Defensive
                        Forces<note n="2" xml:id="d128fn2">
                        <ref target="#d103">Document 103</ref>.</note> paid particular attention to
                    larger-than-expected threats to our Assured Destruction capability. These
                    threats were postulated without explicit study of their desirability or
                    feasibility from the Soviet viewpoint and without evidence of Soviet trends in
                    those directions from intelligence indicators. Postulation of such threats
                    furnishes an appropriate analytical tool for an extreme test of our Assured
                    Destruction capability; nevertheless there is a risk that it may obscure
                    possible U.S. opportunities to influence Soviet behavior. Taking
                    larger-than-expected threats as “given” fails to credit our Damage Limiting
                    forces with the virtual attrition that they in fact exact of the Soviets in
                    planning their own forces.</p>
                <p>The Soviets apparently view our forces, as we do theirs, as a potential first
                    strike threat. They therefore must design their capabilities to protect their
                    own Assured Destruction capability against a U.S. first strike. To the extent
                    that Soviet resources are thus expended, and hence diverted from alternative
                    uses in improving the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>’s Damage
                    Limiting posture, our own Assured Destruction task becomes easier.</p>
                <p>It is in our interest for the Soviets to spend sizable sums in guarding their
                    Assured Destruction capability, provided these expenditures are primarily
                    reflected in <hi rend="italic">defensive</hi> measures such as missile launch
                    facility hardening, missile dispersal or missile mobility, rather than in
                    increases in their offensive forces’ payloads. Diversion of Soviet resources to
                    defensive measures would reduce the cost of maintaining our relative Assured
                    Destruction position for a given level of Soviet expenditure on strategic
                    programs and would also contribute to U.S. and Allied Damage Limiting by
                    reducing their ability to inflict damage on us.</p>
                <p>The implications for U.S. policy concern the value of continuing to maintain a
                    counter-military threat against the Soviet strategic offensive <pb facs="0423"
                        n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/> forces; specifically they concern the value of
                    achieving low <gloss target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss> to force the Soviets to adopt
                    very expensive vulnerability-reducing methods such as mobility and hard point
                    defense. Although Soviet responses cannot be predicted with confidence, a Soviet
                    response that optimized their Assured Destruction capability against a U.S.
                    threat with much lower <gloss target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss> than we have now,
                    would result in a reduction in Soviet first strike Damage Limiting capability
                    over a wide range of Soviet Assured Destruction budgets.</p>
                <p>An illustration of the pressure imposed by U.S. strategic offensive forces on
                    Soviet forces was made in the <gloss target="#t_DDRE1">DDR&amp;E</gloss> study,
                    “A Summary Study on Strategic Offensive and Defensive Forces of the U.S. and
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>” of September 8, 1964.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d128fn3">This 192-page study and Appendix are not printed.
                        (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>
                        Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 330 69 A 7425, 381 Strategic
                        Retaliatory Forces (9 Jan 94) Sep-Nov 1964)</note> The study contains an
                    analysis (<ref target="#pg_68">p. 68</ref>) showing that if the Soviets
                    optimized their Assured Destruction capability against a small U.S.
                    counter-military offensive capability they could purchase large, soft missiles
                    at $1.33 million per kilopound ($M/<gloss target="#t_KP1">KP</gloss>). The cost
                    to the Soviets of the same payload triples—to $4M/<gloss target="#t_KP1"
                        >KP</gloss>—if survivability through hardening and dispersal must be
                    purchased. Virtual attrition seems to be exerting major influence on Soviet
                    force planning, as shown by the Soviets’ large scale deployment of SS–11s and by
                    their pursuit of small and mobile missile technology.</p>
                <p>My staff has undertaken a further analysis of the pressures that programmed U.S.
                    forces indirectly bring to bear on the Soviet Damage Limiting capability. This
                    analysis proceeds in three steps.</p>
                <p>In the first step, a Soviet force is designed to negate the U.S. Assured
                    Destruction capability in a Soviet first strike assuming that the Soviets were
                    not in fact concerned with maintaining an effective Assured Destruction
                    capability. It is basically the approach used in the extreme cases of last
                    year’s Draft Presidential Memorandum.</p>
                <p>Then, the programmed U.S. forces are applied against this Soviet posture, and
                    surviving Soviet forces strike U.S. urban targets. Resulting U.S. fatalities are
                    so low that the assumed enemy posture could not constitute a high-confidence (to
                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>) Soviet Assured Destruction
                    capability.</p>
                <p>Finally, at the same Soviet budget level used in the first step, a new Soviet
                    force is designed for first strike Damage Limiting, subject to a constraint on
                    Soviet second strike Assured Destruction stemming from the pressure exerted by
                    our capabilities. This constraint markedly reduced the Soviets’ ability to erode
                    our Assured Destruction capability within the fixed Soviet budget level.</p>
                <pb facs="0424" n="398" xml:id="pg_398"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Analysis</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet First Strike Only Damage Limiting Threat.</hi> A
                    re-examination of SS–9 requirements, taking all reliabilities into account,
                    indicates that the Soviets would need some 350 SS–9s, each carrying 10 Mk-17
                        <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>’s, to achieve high expected damage
                    against programmed U.S. land-based forces with high confidence. Assuming the
                    existence of such a Soviet capability, and applying reasonable adjustments to
                    National Intelligence Projections for Planning (<gloss target="#t_NIPP1"
                        >NIPP</gloss>) factors to reflect the assumed introduction of <gloss
                        target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>, the expected damage against U.S. forces is
                    .92 with a 1500 foot SS–9 <gloss target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss>, but only .77 with
                    a 2100 foot <gloss target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss>. (We now project a <gloss
                        target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss> of 3000 feet for the SS–9 in 1970, with no
                    evidence of an appreciable Soviet effort to reduce this figure.) These missiles
                    alone cost some $9 billion (about $1.5 M/<gloss target="#t_KP1">KP</gloss>)
                    beyond the cost of the remainder of Soviet Offensive forces.</p>
                <p>Next, we design a least-cost Soviet defense to keep Soviet fatalities at [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] of
                    their total population in the face of a counter-urban attack by the surviving
                    U.S. forces. This fatality level corresponds to the delivery of [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                    warheads in the absence of Soviet defenses, and roughly equates to the level
                    that might be expected from leakage through a very good defense against a U.S.
                    retaliatory attack. This defense consists of 1800 area interceptors and 1000
                    terminal interceptors at 15 cities, at a total five-year cost of approximately
                    $6.4 billion plus a non-recurring cost for research and development, tooling and
                    production facilities, etc., which is irrelevant to this calculation. Of this
                    cost, approximately 80 percent is for area defenses. This is consistent with
                    results obtained in analyses of light Nike-X deployments.</p>
                <p>Thus, for a total increment of some $15 billion over a base <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> budget, the Soviets can reduce the
                    Assured Destruction capability of our programmed missile forces to a highly
                    unsatisfactory level through 1969–1974. The base budget is the cost of their
                        <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> program, their missile programs,
                    their <gloss target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss> programs, their bomber program and
                    their air defense programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Assured Destruction Capability of the Soviet Force</hi>. We
                    have analyzed a pre-emptive U.S. strike as a Soviet planner might do, in
                    evaluating the Soviet Assured Destruction capability. The programmed U.S. forces
                    are laid down in a pre-emptive strike against the Soviet intercontinental
                    strategic military target system designed above (i.e., the <gloss
                        target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>ed SS–9s plus the other Soviet <gloss
                        target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>s, <gloss target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss>
                    bases, intercontinental bomber bases, etc.). If the Soviet area defenses did not
                    cover their SS–9 missile fields, as would be the case with the present locations
                    of the SS–9 silos, U.S. fatalities would be less than 10%. If the Soviet area
                    missile defense is assumed to protect Soviet military targets and to operate
                    without <pb facs="0425" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/> leakage residual Soviet forces
                    are estimated to inflict 22% U.S. fatalities (200 equivalent one <gloss
                        target="#t_MT1">MT</gloss> weapons) in the absence of U.S. <gloss
                        target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>. Thus the Soviet deterrent would depend
                    entirely on the precise siting and effectiveness of their <gloss
                        target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> as a component of hard point defense. (Even a
                    very light U.S. <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> deployment would be able to
                    negate the remaining Soviet forces.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet First Strike Damage Limiting with Assured Destruction
                        Constraint</hi>. As a last step, the Soviets take measures to maintain their
                    Assured Destruction capability. They are allowed to replace the forces assumed
                    above with more survivable forces at the same cost as the Soviet Damage Limiting
                    force. The resulting posture (shown in table below is very similar to the
                    missile force predicted in the <gloss target="#t_NIPP1">NIPP</gloss>), but the
                    SS–9s are assumed to carry <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>s. Additional
                    mobile missiles and an area only defense are also purchased at the expense of
                    Soviet terminal defenses. The SS–9s and the area defenses can be considered as
                    the Damage Limiting increment added to the Assured Destruction backbone of their
                    posture.</p>
                <p>If this <hi rend="italic">entire force</hi> is sent against the U.S. in a Damage
                    Limiting first strike (i.e., no part is withheld for a later Assured Destruction
                    capability), the residual U.S. missile forces can still deliver more than [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                    equivalent weapons against the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> instead
                    of the [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                    equivalents that the U.S. could deliver against the Soviet Damage Limiting only
                    posture. Again, this figure exceeds the [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of
                        source text not declassified</hi>] equivalent criterion for an effective
                    U.S. Assured Destruction capability that was suggested in last year’s
                    Presidential Memorandum.</p>
                <p rend="center">TABLE 1: Soviet Intercontinental Forces of the Damage Limiting
                    Posture (#1) and of the Assured Destruction Posture (#2) <table cols="7"
                        rows="10">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Launchers</cell>
                            <cell role="num">69</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">71</cell>
                            <cell role="num">72</cell>
                            <cell role="num">73</cell>
                            <cell role="num">74</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Posture #1</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Soft SS–7 (1x2)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">102</cell>
                            <cell role="num">80</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard SS–7 (1x3)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">55</cell>
                            <cell role="num">30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard SS–9 <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss> (1x1)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">300</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Posture #2</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Soft SS–7 (1x2)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">102</cell>
                            <cell role="num">80</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard SS–7 (1x3)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">70</cell>
                            <cell role="num">55</cell>
                            <cell role="num">30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard SS–9 <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss> (1x1)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard SS–11 (1x1)</cell>
                            <cell role="num">300</cell>
                            <cell role="num">375</cell>
                            <cell role="num">425</cell>
                            <cell role="num">475</cell>
                            <cell role="num">525</cell>
                            <cell role="num">550</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0426" n="400" xml:id="pg_400"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Soviets, by viewing our forces as a first strike threat to their Assured
                    Destruction capability, must spend much more to achieve a first strike Damage
                    Limiting capability. This does not argue that the Soviets are incapable of
                    achieving both a satisfactory (to them) Assured Destruction capability and a
                    Damage Limiting capability. But it does mean that, by carefully designing our
                    own forces, we can foreclose any “easy” roads to Damage Limiting for the
                    Soviets. Furthermore, low U.S. <gloss target="#t_CEP1">CEP</gloss>s prevent
                    simple proliferation of hard <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss> silos from
                    being a useful Soviet response; Soviet mobility or defense would be required.
                    Thus, a simple increase in total Soviet offensive payload is not a likely
                    response to the strong U.S. counterforce capability.</p>
                <p>Characteristics of U.S. Damage Limiting forces that place this constraint on
                    Soviet forces should, therefore, receive continued attention. For example, the
                    high accuracy attainable with the Mk-17 (rather than the Mk-11A) can be thought
                    of as making an indirect contribution to Assured Destruction.</p>
                <p>Proposed changes in U.S. forces (such as the addition of large payload missiles)
                    should be evaluated in light of possible Soviet responses, and especially in
                    light of the constraints they impose on the Soviet mix of Assured Destruction
                    and Damage Limiting. Analyses not based on such consideration are likely to be
                    incomplete, and the decisions based on such incomplete analyses, misleading.</p>
                <p>In this year’s Presidential Memorandum, I propose to include an interaction
                    analysis. Thus, in addition to postulating Soviet threats and finding what
                    forces would be required to overcome them, various possible new U.S.
                    systems—both for Assured Destruction hedges or for Damage Limiting—will be
                    considered in terms of the effects they would be likely to have on the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EAC1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Alain Enthoven</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
