<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-12T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-12T16:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.60F31/530a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Minister in Czechoslovakia</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Carr</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-12T16:00:00-05:00">December 12, 1937—4
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>49. Our list of requests for concessions by Czechoslovakia in the
                                proposed trade agreement was presented to the Czechoslovak
                                delegation last Thursday.<note n="21" xml:id="d180fn21">December
                                    9.</note> We have asked for suppression of import permit
                                requirements and quantitative limitations on the items appearing on
                                our list. Many of these are already free from such restriction or
                                limitation. In spite of the fact that the memorandum which
                                accompanied cur preliminary request list of last August<note n="22" xml:id="d180fn22">Not found in Department files.</note> stated
                                that requests for suppression of quantitative restrictions on
                                certain products would be made the Czechoslovak delegation has
                                expressed complete surprise at our requests as now presented and
                                states that it is not authorized to negotiate on that basis. We have
                                asked that the delegation put the matter before the Czechoslovak
                                government for consideration and decision.</p>
                            <p>The Czechoslovak delegation has taken the position that because of
                                the restrictive systems maintained by other European countries
                                Czechoslovakia <pb facs="0263" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> cannot
                                change her protective system to the extent of completely abolishing
                                quantitative restrictions. We have pointed out the broad underlying
                                principles of our program which looks to the breaking down or
                                removal of excessive barriers and that we feel fully justified in
                                expecting Czechoslovakia to take a partial step in this direction at
                                this time. We have stressed the fact that we are not asking
                                Czechoslovakia to abandon her whole system of quantitative
                                restrictions. Our requests cover a very limited part of
                                Czechoslovakia’s total import trade and involve commodities of
                                direct interest to the United States. Out of the thousands of
                                products covered by the Czechoslovak tariff we are requesting the
                                abolition of quantitative restrictions on only 25 or 30 items and
                                since these are products of primary interest to the United States,
                                Czechoslovakia’s trade in these products with third countries would
                                in many cases be affected only in a relatively minor degree.</p>
                            <p>We are not asking Czechoslovakia to take this step gratuitously. We
                                have offered and are prepared to grant to Czechoslovakia substantial
                                concessions on 49 items. What we will ultimately give is necessarily
                                contingent on the nature and extent of Czechoslovakia’s concessions
                                to us.</p>
                            <p>Please discuss this matter with the appropriate Czechoslovak
                                authorities in the above sense, stressing the fact that our requests
                                for the suppression of quantitative restrictions refers to a very
                                limited number of products and hence in no sense implies any
                                revolutionary changes in this respect in Czechoslovakia’s trade
                                control system as a whole.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>