<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Czechoslovakia ( (Carr) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-12-14T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-12-14T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-14T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-14T10:00:00-05:00" n="181"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.60F31/531: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Czechoslovakia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Carr</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Praha</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-14T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 14, 1937—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 14—2:21 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>73. Your 49, December 11 [<hi rend="italic">12</hi>] 4 p.m. Last night I called
                    on the Chief of the Economic Section of the Foreign Office, presented him an <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> embodying the substance of your telegram and
                    adding oral explanations and arguments in favor of granting your request for
                    suppression of import permit requirements and quantitative limitations upon
                    certain products. Minister Friedmann referred to the three groups in your
                    preliminary list of August and said he understood our demands for quantitative
                    restrictions would revolve around the point of determining quotas for American
                    commodities involved and that his delegation had full authority to negotiate on
                    that basis. I pointed out that a cardinal principle in your policy was the
                    gradual <pb facs="0264" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/> removal of artificial trade
                    barriers and that you desired Czechoslovakia to make a contribution by
                    modification of her import permit requirements and suppression of quantitative
                    restrictions on a limited number of articles. He replied that in principle he
                    favored this but in practice it was impossible in view of the economic position
                    of Czechoslovakia’s neighbors mentioning Germany and the central and southern
                    European countries which necessitates trade being conducted on a controlled
                    exchange basis through import permits and quantitative restrictions. Hence, he
                    said it was absolutely out of the question for Czechoslovakia to give up this
                    system. He had no report from the delegation and if none comes will telegraph
                    for one today.</p>
                <p>Your telegram relates to suppression of import permits and quantitative
                    limitations whereas confidential memorandum enclosed with your 209 of September
                    15, 1937,<note n="23" xml:id="d181fn23">Instruction not printed; memorandum not
                        found in Department files.</note> seems to relate to suppression of import
                    permits on certain items but not to suppression of quantitative limitations.
                    Foreign Office view except as to permits does not therefore conflict with
                    confidential memorandum as we understand. Please clarify.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carr</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
