<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Estonia ( (Leonard))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="203"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d203">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.60131/85</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Estonia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leonard</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 26</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-22">December 22,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to the Legation’s despatches
                    Nos. 179 and 180 of May 27, 1937, and No. 236 of August 19, 1937,<note n="23"
                        xml:id="d203fn23">None printed.</note> and to previous correspondence
                    relative to the possible negotiation of a trade agreement between the United
                    States and Estonia.</p>
                <p>The proposals submitted by the Estonian Government and transmitted to the
                    Department with the despatches referred to above have been given careful study
                    by the interdepartmental trade-agreement <pb facs="0283" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"
                    /> organization. These studies have revealed that the commodity trade between
                    the two countries is such as to make a trade agreement between the two countries
                    feasible. However, it appears that the position thus far taken by the Estonian
                    Government on certain aspects of the general treatment to be accorded to
                    American commerce (particularly with reference to quotas and exchange control)
                    does not assure us that on its part that Government is willing to grant us
                    substantially nondiscriminatory treatment, an essential condition to the
                    conclusion of a trade agreement. The interdepartmental Committee on Trade
                    Agreements has, therefore, approved the continuation of discussions with the
                    Estonian Government looking toward the initiation of formal negotiations,
                    provided that a satisfactory understanding can be reached with Estonia on the
                    basis for the negotiations. As has been indicated in previous instructions to
                    you, such an understanding would necessarily be based upon the principle of
                    non-discriminatory treatment.</p>
                <p>There are enclosed for your information and guidance two copies of a report<note
                        n="24" xml:id="d203fn24">Not attached to file copy of instruction.</note>
                    submitted to, and approved by, the Committee on Trade Agreements with reference
                    to the possible negotiation of a trade agreement with Estonia. The conclusions
                    and recommendations expressed in the report are only of a preliminary character,
                    since the final form and content of a trade agreement would have to be
                    determined by the extent to which Estonia is willing to meet our viewpoint and
                    by any relevant facts which may be brought out in briefs and oral statements
                    submitted by interested parties to the interdepartmental trade-agreements
                    organization prior to the initiation of formal negotiations. It is believed,
                    however, that the report will be useful to you as an indication of what, in
                    general outline, would be considered as a satisfactory agreement by this
                    Government. You will, of course, wish to use some of the material contained in
                    the report in your discussions with the Estonian officials. However, you should
                    bear in mind that, in this preliminary stage of discussions, our objective is
                    primarily to work out an understanding on fundamentals and that matters of
                    detail should, in general, be left to be worked out in the formal
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>In taking up the subject of a trade agreement with the Estonian authorities, you
                    should say that the Government of the United States has given the most careful
                    consideration to the Estonian proposals and that an exhaustive study has been
                    made of Estonian-American commercial relations. You should express the
                    Department’s appreciation of the courtesy of the Estonian Government in
                    deferring its notice of intention to modify the present commercial treaty in
                    order <pb facs="0284" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/> to permit the completion of
                    these studies, and the Department’s regret that it has not been possible to
                    reply to the Estonian proposals at an earlier date. The delay in making a reply
                    has been occasioned by the fact that the Department has been concurrently
                    studying the possibility of undertaking negotiations with a considerable number
                    of other countries.</p>
                <p>The Department desires that you convey the following observations to the Estonian
                    authorities with specific reference to the proposals made by the Estonian
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States shares the desire of the Estonian Government
                    that the trade between the two countries be expanded as much as possible. To
                    that end, it would be willing to enter into negotiations with Estonia for the
                    reciprocal exchange of commercial concessions in a trade agreement, provided
                    that an understanding can be reached prior to the initiation of formal
                    negotiations as to the general treatment which will be accorded in each country
                    to the commerce of the other. The Department has, therefore, authorized you to
                    conduct the necessary discussions with a view to arriving at such an
                    understanding.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Provisions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>From the viewpoint of the United States, the most important aspects of the
                    general treatment to be provided for in a trade agreement would be those
                    concerned with unconditional most-favored-nation treatment in customs matters
                    and with the application of the principle of equality of treatment to quotas,
                    and exchange control. While the Government of the United States does not
                    consider it necessary that the exact text of provisions regarding these matters
                    be agreed upon during preliminary conversations, it does desire that an
                    understanding be reached as to the general basis upon which the negotiations
                    will proceed and believes that the Estonian Government is probably of the same
                    view.</p>
                <p>By way of introduction to a discussion of these subjects, you should point out
                    that the United States at present accords to Estonia all of the advantages given
                    to the most-favored-nation, the Republic of Cuba excepted, and that it is the
                    policy of the United States to continue extending these advantages to Estonia,
                    regardless of whether the present treaty continues in force, provided that
                    Estonia accords non-discriminatory treatment to the commerce of the United
                    States. The rates of duty specified in the fifteen trade agreements, the
                    benefits of which are extended to Estonia, apply to goods accounting for
                    approximately 20 percent of total dutiable imports into the United States. These
                    benefits, coupled with the fact that the United States imposes no quantitative
                    restrictions upon the admission of Estonian goods nor <pb facs="0285" n="274"
                        xml:id="pg_274"/> restrictions upon the transfer of payments therefor,
                    provide a broad basis for the development of a market in this country for
                    Estonian goods.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States appreciates that the Estonian Government is
                    not now in a position to permit unrestricted imports and it desires, in general,
                    only a guarantee that such restrictions and regulations as the Estonian
                    Government may see fit to impose upon imports will not operate to the
                    disadvantage of this country as compared with third countries.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>It is, of course, highly desirable that an agreement be concluded, if possible,
                    prior to May 22, 1938. Therefore, if it appears at all possible that a
                    satisfactory understanding on basic principles can be reached with the Estonian
                    Government as a result of your preliminary discussions, you should consult the
                    Department by telegraph with reference to the details of any counter-proposals
                    made by the Estonian authorities. If, on the other hand, the Estonian Government
                    displays little willingness to meet the Department’s views on the points which
                    have been indicated as essential, it may be preferable for you to transmit to
                    the Department by mail any counter-proposals which are made to you. In
                    determining which procedure to follow, you should bear in mind that a complete
                    understanding with regard to possible concessions is not essential to the
                    issuance of a preliminary announcement that negotiations are under
                    contemplation. However, the Department would not wish to make such an
                    announcement unless discussions with Estonia had progressed sufficiently to
                    indicate substantial possibility of successful negotiations.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis B. Sayre</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
