<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-06-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="267" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d267">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.11L5232/899</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The German Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dieckhoff</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Counselor of the Department of State</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Moore</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-06-28">June 28, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Judge Moore</hi>: I have the honor to
                                confirm the receipt of your letter of the 23rd instant, in which you
                                ask for a statement, for your own information, as to whether, in the
                                matter of the sabotage proceedings, the German Government would be
                                ready to carry out the agreement if the award holders and the
                                sabotage claimants waive all their remaining balances.</p>
                            <p>As the information at hand from Berlin does not suffice to reply to
                                this question, which is of a hypothetical character, 1 have
                                submitted the content of your letter to my Government, with a
                                request for a statement of its position. As soon as a reply on this
                                point has been received, I shall not fail to advise you without
                                delay of the view of my Government.</p>
                            <p>As the German Agent advises me, the Commission intends to hear a
                                number of witnesses on July 8th and the following days, who have
                                been summoned by the serving of subpoenas, as the date of June 22nd
                                originally set for that purpose had to be changed. I should like to
                                avail myself of this opportunity to remark that I am of the opinion
                                that the hearings should by no means be postponed once more, because
                                    <pb facs="0373" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/> a new question has
                                been raised by your inquiry of the 23rd instant, to which a
                                definitive answer cannot be given until after the receipt of
                                information from Berlin; the proceedings before the Commission
                                should, in my opinion, quietly continue to follow their
                                    [regular]<note n="53" xml:id="d267fn53">Brackets appear in the
                                    file translation.</note> course in the meantime.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dieckhoff</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>