<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-23T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-23T19:00:00-05:00" n="383" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.6521/232: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-23T19:00:00-05:00">November 23, 1937—7
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>179. Your 457, October 27, 4 p.m., and 481, November 19, noon.<note n="64" xml:id="d383fn64">Latter not printed.</note></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>The Department desires you to inform the Italian Foreign
                                    Office orally or in writing in your discretion that this
                                    Government regrets that it is not in a position to proceed with
                                    the negotiations on the basis of initial free entry only set
                                    forth in your telegram under reference. You should express the
                                    hope that the Italian Government may, at some future time, be in
                                    a position to reopen the negotiations upon the broader basis set
                                    forth in the Department’s draft convention.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>If a convention on the basis of the Italian proposals were
                                    concluded it would materially minimize the chances of this
                                    Government concluding consular conventions with other countries
                                    upon the broader basis. While a consular convention on the
                                    narrow basis <pb facs="0517" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/> would be
                                    entirely out of line with other consular conventions now in
                                    course of negotiation, it is possible that the conclusion of
                                    these pending negotiations with other countries may facilitate a
                                    reopening of negotiations with the Italian Government on a basis
                                    more in line with its proposals.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>While paragraph 2 is for your information, you may, in your
                                    discretion, communicate all or part of it to the Italian Foreign
                                    Office.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>In expressing the regret of this Government that the
                                    negotiations for a consular convention must be suspended for the
                                    time being, you should indicate your appreciation of the cordial
                                    and sympathetic cooperation afforded by the officers of the
                                    Italian Foreign Office in exploring the situation.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>For the further information of the Embassy only. The
                                    Department does not consider it worth while in this connection
                                    to enter into a new consular convention which is not broader
                                    than the treaty of 1878 and fails to grant more rights than are
                                    now accorded by Italian legislation.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>