<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of Trade Agreements
                    ( (Hawkins))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d404</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">404</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="404"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d404">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.60C31/162</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        Trade Agreements</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hawkins</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-02-17">February 17,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">[Participants:]</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Witold Wankowicz, Counselor of Polish
                            Embassy;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Sylvester Gruszka, Consul General of
                            Poland;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Harry C. Hawkins.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In accordance with the arrangement made at the meeting in Mr. Sayre’s office on
                    February 3, Mr. Wankowicz and Mr. Gruszka called <pb facs="0539" n="528"
                        xml:id="pg_528"/> to discuss further the basis for trade agreement
                    negotiations. The discussion related to the nature of our General Provisions and
                    the extent to which the Polish Government might be in a position to agree to
                    them. Both Mr. Wankowicz and Mr. Gruszka felt that it might be possible to
                    accept our General Provisions in substance. I suggested to them that the best
                    way of explaining our position on the principles which should govern the
                    negotiations would be to send copies of our trade agreements with other
                    countries to their Government and supplement them with the explanations which we
                    had given to them in the course of our discussions. I reminded them that we are
                    not in a position to set in motion the machinery for preparing material on the
                    schedules until the Trade Agreements Committee has authorized negotiations and
                    has set up the interdepartmental country committee to do the necessary work; but
                    that if the Polish Government should find itself in a position to negotiate on
                    the basis of the principles embodied in our General Provisions, the Trade
                    Agreements Committee doubtless would give favorable consideration to entering
                    into definitive negotiations. Mr. Wankowicz said that he would take up the
                    matter with his Government in the manner above suggested.</p>
                <p>In the course of the discussion, Mr. Wankowicz said that his Government was much
                    concerned with the matter of countervailing duties and that if a trade agreement
                    were negotiated it would like to have us specify either in the agreement or in
                    connection therewith precisely the circumstances and conditions under which our
                    countervailing duties would, and would not, be imposed. I informed him that this
                    was a matter entirely within the competence of the Treasury Department and that
                    that Department would have the final decision regarding any stipulations of the
                    kind suggested. I said that, in my opinion, the Treasury Department would not
                    agree to describing the general nature of measures which would and which would
                    not be made the occasion for applying countervailing duties, but that it might
                    consider specifying whether specific measures applied by Poland would
                    necessitate the application of such duties. However, this was a matter for the
                    Treasury Department to decide and that Department would be consulted at the
                    appropriate time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wankowicz also said that Poland is interested in obtaining assurances that
                    agricultural products should be either free of duty or that existing duties
                    should not be raised. In this connection, I referred him to the provisions of
                    the Trade Agreements Act<note n="6" xml:id="d404fn6">Approved June 12, 1934; 48
                        Stat. 943.</note> which impose a 50 percent limit on duty reductions by the
                    United States.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
