<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="458" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d458">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">890H.6363/77</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Berlin</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jenkins</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1252</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-11-20">November 20, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    December 4.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report as being of
                                possible interest to the Department that an agreement was signed in
                                Berlin this morning concerning the oil concessions in Afghanistan
                                for which negotiations, of which the Department is no doubt already
                                aware, have been carried on during the past six months by the Inland
                                Exploration Company of Delaware.</p>
                            <p>Final stages of the negotiations were conducted by His Excellency the
                                Afghan Minister for Foreign Affairs, who is now temporarily in
                                Berlin, and the two vice-presidents of the Inland Exploration
                                Company, Mr. Frederick G. Clapp, geologist, and the Honorable
                                Charles C. Hart, former American Minister at Teheran. The agreement
                                was signed at the Afghan Legation in Berlin by the Afghan Minister
                                for Foreign Affairs on behalf of Afghanistan and by Mr. Clapp and
                                    <pb facs="0610" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/> Mr. Hart on behalf of
                                the Company, in the presence of one of the officers of the Consulate
                                General who had been requested to execute certificates of
                                acknowledgement for the American signers. It will become effective
                                after formal ratification by the Government of Afghanistan and the
                                Inland Exploration Company.</p>
                            <p>Under its terms surveys must be made in five, provinces and at least
                                one well must be in operation within a year, according to Mr. Clapp.
                                Pipe-line rights through the neighboring countries remain to be
                                secured during the next six months but negotiations for them have
                                already been initiated and only the amount of the royalties to be
                                charged for them remains unsettled.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Clapp expects to call at the Department to inform it of details
                                of the agreement when he returns to the United States. Meanwhile,
                                although he does not regard the matter as one of absolute secrecy,
                                at least as far as official quarters are concerned, he wishes to
                                avoid having it become generally known and especially to prevent its
                                appearance in the newspapers until ratification has been completed
                                some time in January.</p>
                            <p>Very respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas
                                Jenkins</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>