<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-01-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="562" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d562">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9111/616a</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to The Chargé in
                                    Iran</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Merriam</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-01-18">January 18, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Merriam</hi>: I think you may be
                                interested to know that while the Secretary was in Buenos Aires
                                during the recent Pan-American Conference there<note n="2" xml:id="d562fn2">The Inter-American Conference for the
                                    Maintenance of Peace, December 1–23, 1936.</note> Nadir Arasteh,
                                the Iranian Minister at that post, called upon the Secretary and
                                made every effort to show his friendly attitude. The conversation
                                naturally turned to the present strained relations between the
                                United States and Iran and the Minister expressed his emphatic view
                                that Iran could not afford to go on, as at present, without proper
                                representation in this country. The Secretary concurred in the
                                Minister’s views and added that he had done everything in his power
                                to prevent the present impasse. The Secretary furthermore told the
                                Minister that he had the impression that the true facts of the case
                                had never reached His Majesty’s ears. Otherwise it was impossible to
                                believe that all of the Secretary’s conscientious endeavors to
                                remove His Majesty’s misgivings would have been in vain. The
                                Minister said he was of the same view and that he contemplated
                                making an early trip to his country at which time he would make a
                                further effort to clear up the misunderstanding.</p>
                            <p>During the course of conversation the Minister referred somewhat
                                vaguely to the desirability of our making some “gesture” in order to
                                smooth matters over. I gathered that the Secretary did not pursue
                                that phase of the matter and apparently left the Minister under the
                                impression that we had made all the gestures that could properly be
                                expected of us under the circumstances.</p>
                            <p>While you might, if you think it would be helpful and if the occasion
                                presents itself, make reference to the fact that a conversation took
                                place between the Secretary and the Iranian Minister in Buenos Aires
                                    <pb facs="0730" n="719" xml:id="pg_719"/> regarding the present
                                state of our relations with Iran, it would seem undesirable to refer
                                to any of the details of the conversation, which will doubtless be
                                reported fully by Mr. Arasteh.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace
                                Murray</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>