<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>16. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to President ) to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-09-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council" subject="nsc">NSC</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" subject="health-care" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94005552" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Epidemic</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <head>16. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d16fn1">Source: Carter Library, Plains File,
                        Box 9, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Weekly Reports, 6–12/78. Secret.
                        A handwritten “C” indicates that <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> saw the memorandum. </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-09-01">September 1, 1978</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Weekly Report #71</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Opinion</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Coordination</p>
                <p>Coordination in the area of national security and foreign policy will not work
                    well unless the Departments feel that I speak for you when insisting that
                    sensitive decisions be fully coordinated.<note n="2" xml:id="d16fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> described the tensions
                        between his advisers when we wrote, “There were some inherent differences in
                        the character of the White House National Security Council staff and the
                        State Department. I attempted to tap the strongest elements in each as
                        changing circumstances demanded.” (<persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Keeping Faith</hi>, p. 53)
                            <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> was more specific about
                        the tensions when he wrote in his memoir, “I supported the collegial
                        approach with one critical reservation. Only the president and his secretary
                        of state were to have the responsibility for defining the administration’s
                        foreign policy publicly. As time went on, there developed an increasingly
                        serious breach of this understanding. Despite his stated acceptance of this
                        principle, and in spite of repeated instructions from the President,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> would attempt
                        increasingly to take the role of policy spokesman.” (<persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Hard
                        Choices</hi>, p. 35)</note>
                </p>
                <p>This did not happen in the Dresser case<note n="3" xml:id="d16fn3">A reference to
                        the $144 million contract for drill bits between the Soviets and Dresser
                        Industries, which caused controversy because not all members of the Cabinet
                        were informed about the deal. For additional information on the Dresser
                        case, see <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d141">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. VI, Soviet
                            Union, Document 141</ref>.</note> because the principals at State and
                    Commerce, who in any case wanted a positive decision, felt that they knew better
                    and directly what you wanted done; accordingly, <persName corresp="#p_SJR_1">Schlesinger</persName>’s objections could be disregarded and <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> coordination short-circuited.</p>
                <p>Similarly, on travel abroad and on speeches or testimony bearing on foreign
                    policy, instructions that they be cleared through the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> have lately, in some cases, not been followed.</p>
                <p>Finally, effective coordination and frank discussion of issues is made more
                    difficult by the epidemic of self-serving leaks designed to force you to take a
                    given course, not to speak of the derogatory press comments by anonymous
                    officials. I strongly suspect the former was the case with some <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> officials in regards to <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, or more recently to identify you directly
                    with the State/Commerce Dresser decision, <pb facs="0085" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/> thereby making any review of additional information or reclama look like an
                    effort to reverse you.</p>
                <p>It would be helpful if at an early Cabinet meeting you discussed the issues of
                    discipline, coordination, and discretion.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is unrelated information.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
