<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>168. Letter From the President of the Association of American Foreign Service
                    Women (Dorman) to the Under Secretary of State for Management (Read))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-05-09T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="personnel-foreign-service" subject="foreign-service" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831" lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="good_close">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recyb5QQsNI4WeVPs" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-capabilities" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="employment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="international-military-education-and-training" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="168" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                <head>168. Letter From the President of the Association of American Foreign Service
                    Women (Dorman) to the Under Secretary of State for Management (<persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d168fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Records of the Under
                        Secretary for Management (M), 1978–1979, Box 8, Chron May 8–11, 1979. No
                        classification marking. Typed at the top of the page is this note: “5/9—sent
                        to <gloss target="#t_MDGP_1">M/DGP</gloss>-<persName corresp="#p_BHG_1">Barnes</persName> for action, prep. of recommendation for M and (?)
                        reply directly on behalf of M. Copies sent to L-<persName corresp="#p_MJH_1">Michel</persName>, PER/EM-Hull and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-05-09">May 9, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>:<note n="2" xml:id="d168fn2">Dorman crossed out “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>” and wrote “Ben” above it.</note>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Enclosed are the comments which the Association of American Foreign Service Women
                    wishes to make on the proposed Foreign Service Act of 1979. As you will note, we
                    have examined the proposed legislation with the concerns of Foreign Service
                    spouses and families in mind.</p>
                <p>We greatly appreciate the opportunity to comment and to contribute to the shaping
                    of this legislation. If there are any questions concerning the views and
                    suggestions in the attached analysis, we will be happy to answer them.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Lesley Dorman </hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">President</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Enclosure</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared by the Association of American Foreign
                            Service Women</hi>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d168fn3">No classification marking.</note>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1979-05-09T23:59:59-04:00" notBefore="1979-04-26T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">COMMENTS ON THE PROPOSED FOREIGN SERVICE ACT OF 1979</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Association of American Foreign Service Women appreciates having the
                        opportunity to comment on the proposed draft legislation of 1979. We agree
                        that management should try to develop an informed and supportive consensus
                        in the Foreign Service community before <pb facs="0678" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/> taking this bill to the Hill. A thorough review of the
                        principles behind the legislation and a careful explanation of the
                        implementation of structural reforms would be most reassuring.</p>
                    <p>Foreign Service families can testify to the uniqueness of a life in the
                        Foreign Service. Government service abroad is vastly different from service
                        in the United States. Indeed, the <hi rend="italic">Forum Report on the
                            Concerns of Foreign Service Spouses and Families</hi> (1977)<note n="4" xml:id="d168fn4">Not found.</note> and the continuing dialogue between
                            <gloss target="#t_AAFSW_1">AAFSW</gloss> and the Secretary of State
                        bring to light the many human costs that frequently do not appear in a
                        cost-benefit analysis or zero-based budget. We feel that the introduction to
                        a new Foreign Service Act should describe fully these unique sacrifices and
                        adjustments required of Foreign Service families so as to make clear the
                        justification for the Secretary’s authority to assist families in special
                        ways.</p>
                    <p>Most Foreign Service spouses are women. The Department cannot afford to
                        ignore them because they are the basis of an effective, humanistic
                        representation of American life while abroad. The Foreign Service wife takes
                        an extraordinary interest in the career of her husband, because it affects
                        her so directly. She feels that by accompanying her spouse abroad she is in
                        effect serving as a representative of the United States Government.
                        Regulations circumscribe her daily life.</p>
                    <p>Her growing concern is that continual international mobility combined with
                        structural barriers to employment opportunities will virtually exclude her
                        from establishing an economic base of her own through a career or even a
                        consistent work record. Cultural adjustments, family responsibilities, and
                        representational activities consume her time and energies. While her role as
                        a support for family and community is essential, particularly in those areas
                        where support systems normal to U.S. life do not exist, her economic
                        dependency is concurrently reinforced. It takes tremendous creativity,
                        initiative, adaptability and courage (sometimes even the willingness to
                        endure family separation) for her to continue her education or to undertake
                        economic independence.</p>
                    <p>The Foreign Service spouse is not adequately protected by the current or
                        proposed Foreign Service Retirement System. The “traditional” Foreign
                        Service wife finds that the very skills valued in a Foreign Service context
                        are useless in a situation in which she has to support herself economically.
                        A divorced U.S. homemaker is rarely awarded alimony by the courts; child
                        support is awarded in less than half the cases, and a woman may even lose
                        custody of her children if she cannot provide an equal economic base. A
                        widowed spouse is dependent on <pb facs="0679" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/> her
                        husband to provide her with a survivor benefit. The penalties levied on
                        divorced or widowed older homemakers are apparent to us all. The modern
                        Foreign Service wife is beginning to question whether indeed she can afford
                        to continue being a “Dependent”.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_AAFSW_1">AAFSW</gloss> feels that independent women are
                        representative of the best in American society. The alternative to
                        independence is, in the long run, more costly and wasteful of human
                        resources. We have sought creative responses from the system to match the
                        creativity of the women who are trying to make that system work. For these
                        reasons we have surveyed the needs of Foreign Service families. We have made
                        recommendations to the Department in order to expand employment and career
                        development opportunities to enable women to establish their own economic
                        base. We have encouraged the expansion of training opportunities, because we
                        feel that the prepared person is the self-reliant person who can more
                        quickly and effectively become a contributing member of the community. We
                        have supported programs to improve community action especially as such
                        action benefits children. We have tried to help the Department understand
                        how the regulations of the personnel system, family life and morale are
                        inextricably interwoven. We are continuing to study the legal rights and
                        limitations on women in the Foreign Service context.</p>
                    <p>Foreign Service wives in midlife today have already sacrificed the earning
                        potential of their most productive years in cultural adjustments, family
                        support responsibilities and in the creation of a favorable social ambiance
                        for the conduct of American foreign policy. In order to protect these women
                        the Foreign Affairs agencies must recognize earned rights for spouses and
                        former spouses to survivor annuities and shared pensions. The talents of our
                        remarkable group of women can only be utilized in a more flexible system
                        which eliminates the barriers to the workplace. We wish also to protect the
                        homemaker as a vital community resource, while recognizing that she should
                        be able to move in and out of that role in different stages in life without
                        economic penalty.</p>
                    <p>In the context of the above philosophy we would like to comment specifically
                        on those sections of the proposed Act which we feel directly affect spouses
                        and families.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here are the section-by-section recommendations the <gloss target="#t_AAFSW_1">AAFSW</gloss> made regarding the draft Foreign
                        Service Act of 1979.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
