<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>179. Memorandum From the Director General of the Foreign Service and Director
                    of Personnel (Barnes) to the Under Secretary of State for Management () to the
                    Under Secretary of State for Management (Read))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-05-10T22:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="personnel-foreign-service" subject="foreign-service" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831" lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="grain" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208" lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-05-10T22:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <head>179. Memorandum From the Director General of the Foreign Service and Director
                    of Personnel (<persName corresp="#p_BHG_1">Barnes</persName>) to the Under
                    Secretary of State for Management (<persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d179fn1">Source: National
                        Archives, RG 59, Records of the Under Secretary for Management (M), 1980,
                        Box 4, Chron May 5–10, 1980. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1980-05-10T23:59:59-04:00" notBefore="1980-04-24T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Families at Post</item>
                </list>
                <p>As the attached memo notes, one element of the “stay-at-home Foreign Service”
                    image abroad in the land has been a growing perception that a significant number
                    of Foreign Service officers and staff who have families are in fact going to
                    posts abroad without their spouses and children.</p>
                <p>To get at the real story—and as part of a broader effort to document the
                    difficulties of staffing hardship posts—we sent a cable to all posts<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">Not found.</note> asking how many employees with families
                    were at post either alone or with only part of their immediate family present.
                    The responses, summarized in the attached memo, were broken down by the
                    differential level of the post, by the employee grade level, and by the reason
                    (or reasons) for the absence of all or part of a family.</p>
                <p>In the absence of comparable data from an earlier period, interpretation of our
                    overall finding that 91% of employees with family at non-evacuation posts have
                    all or part of their families with them is hazardous at best. Is the glass
                    half-full or half-empty? That is, are we looking at a chronic, but manageable
                    problem, or at the tip of an iceberg which threatens to sink the ship? At first
                    blush, we incline to a cautiously optimistic view, since we find the number of
                    absent families to be less than we had expected (<gloss target="#t_FLO_1">FLO</gloss> shares this view). Within this total, we are also struck by the
                    relatively small number of employees (29 worldwide) who cited “spouse’s career”
                    as the primary reason for the absence of their families from post, since we had
                    anticipated that this phenomenon would have a more marked impact on service
                    abroad than is yet the case, and by the significantly larger number (79) whose
                    families are away from post because of “children’s education.” Finally, we note
                    that the percentage of employees without family remains constant from
                    non-differential through 20% posts, but rises sharply at <pb facs="0737" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> 25% posts<note n="3" xml:id="d179fn3">The differentials
                        describe the amount of additional pay based on one’s salary for serving at a
                        hardship post.</note>—thus suggesting that greater financial rewards may not
                    in themselves solve our problem.</p>
                <p>Because our data represent only one point in time, and are not part of a trend
                    line, we recommend that they be taken with a large grain of salt. Nonetheless,
                    we believe this information, albeit imperfect, should be shared with the Foreign
                    Service as a whole, and plan to use it as the basis for an appropriately
                    caveated article in the <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi>.<note n="4" xml:id="d179fn4">See “Family Separation Problem is Subject of a Survey,”
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi>, June 1980, p.
                        22.</note> For the longer term, we propose to repeat the worldwide survey
                    two years hence (allowing time for a turnover of most personnel now at posts),
                    and expect that the information gathered at that time—and the resultant trend
                    line—will give us a better sense of the real dimensions of our problem.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State<note n="5" xml:id="d179fn5">No classification marking. Drafted on April 24 by
                                Robert Homme (<gloss target="#t_PERFCAEUR_1">PER/FCA/EUR</gloss>).</note>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1980-04-24">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">FAMILIES AT POST—SURVEY DATA</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is a growing perception that a significant number of Foreign Service
                        employees with families do not have those families with them at overseas
                        posts. While this perception is a general one, it is perhaps most persistent
                        in connection with hardship posts.</p>
                    <p>The purpose of this survey, which relied on responses from posts to three
                        specific questions, was to determine the true extent of the
                        no-family-at-post phenomenon in general and at hardship posts (as compared
                        to non-hardship posts) in particular. Accordingly, the data is presented in
                        the same basic format as used in the earlier report on staffing hardship
                            posts.<note n="6" xml:id="d179fn6">Not found.</note> One caution is
                        appropriate: It will be noted that not all the data can be fully reconciled.
                        This is attributable to the essentially voluntary nature of the survey and,
                        hence, the possible failure of some employees to divulge pertinent
                        information.</p>
                    <pb facs="0738" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary of Findings</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The data reveals that 88% of our employees serving overseas who have families
                        have their families (or at least part of them) at post. There is some
                        difference between differential and non-differential posts with regard to
                        presence of families (see Section II.A.),<note n="7" xml:id="d179fn7">Reference is to a section in the data tables, which are attached but
                            not printed.</note> but overall the differences are not great. 91% of
                        the families are present at non-differential posts, while the overall figure
                        for differential posts is 85%. At 10% and 20% differential posts, the rates
                        are 94% and 90% respectively, about the same as at non-differential posts,
                        while at 15% and 25% posts the rates are sharply lower (75% and 77%
                        respectively). This zig-zag pattern contrasts with the smoothly rising curve
                        we found with regard to underbid jobs, where the underbidding rate rose
                        with—that is, despite—the differential.</p>
                    <p>The reasons provided in the survey responses suggest the explanation.
                        “Evacuation or danger” was the reason given in almost 40% of the cases
                        overall, and rose from zero at non-differential and 10% posts to less than
                        20% at 20% posts and less than 33% at 25% posts. At 15% posts, however, it
                        accounted for over 90% of the cases.</p>
                    <p>Review of the figures by region confirms the suspicion: all but one of the
                        family absences at 15% posts are in <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>.
                        Except for this bulge, the drop-off comes at 25% posts in <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss> (50% family presence) and <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> (60%). In <gloss target="#t_AF_1">AF</gloss>, on the other hand, almost 88% of the families are
                        represented at 25% posts. (Both of the families in <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss> 25% posts are present; <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>
                        has no 25% posts.)</p>
                    <p>Moreover, removing the evacuation posts does in fact remove the anomaly
                        (Section IV.). The percentage of family presence is in the low 90’s from
                        non-differential posts through 10%, 15%, and 20% posts, dropping (not
                        surprisingly, and not much) to 82% at 25% posts. (The zig-zag curve when
                        evacuation posts were included resulted from the coincidence that there are
                        6 such posts with 25% differentials and 6 with 15%, but only 3 with 20%.)
                        Breaking the data out in this fashion, which is a truer measure of the
                        dimension of the “stay-at-home” problem, reveals that over 90% of the
                        employees with families at non-evacuation posts have family with them. And,
                        perhaps surprisingly, there is no significant difference between overall
                        hardship and non-hardship categories.</p>
                    <p>The next most important reason given for absences overall was “children’s
                        education”, accounting for just over one-fourth of the absences. This reason
                        was given for about half the absences at non-differential posts and at 20%
                        posts, and a third of the cases at 10% <pb facs="0739" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> posts, but less than a fifth at 25% posts, and almost
                        none (1 out of 102) at 15% posts. (As we have seen, in these last two
                        categories “evacuation or danger” has already effectively kept families
                        away.)</p>
                    <p>All other reasons combined only accounted for one-third of the absences, with
                        “spouse’s career” leading the specific reasons given with less than 10%.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As a snapshot of the families at post situation at a specific point in time,
                        the survey tells us a good deal about the present dimensions of the problem
                        and the reasons for it.</p>
                    <p>Whether what it tells us is dramatic—or significant—depends largely on what
                        was expected. However, it does seem to indicate that, when evacuations are
                        factored out, the stay-at-home family phenomenon is no more pronounced at
                        hardship posts overall than it is at non-hardship posts.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
