<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-09-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                        <head>180. Briefing Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State for
                            Management (<persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>) to Secretary
                            of State <persName corresp="#p_MES_1">Muskie</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d180fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Records of the Under Secretary for Management (M), 1980, Box 6,
                                Chron September 8–13, 1980. No classification marking. Printed from
                                a copy bearing <persName corresp="#p_RBH_1">Read</persName>’s
                                stamped initials.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-09-09">September 9, 1980</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Professional Development Group to Vet <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss> Proposal</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As a result of our Saturday morning meeting on the budget,<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2">September 6. No minutes of the meeting were
                                found.</note> I am forming an assistant-secretary level group to go
                            over the structure and content of the career development and training
                            proposal in our <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 budget request.
                            The group’s mission will be to give the proposal a strenuous vetting,
                            drawing on its own and outsiders’ perspective, to make sure the nature,
                            timing and amount of training presented to <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> later this month are solidly grounded and backed by the
                            career service. The group will meet twice weekly over the next three
                            weeks, starting Thursday, September 11, bringing in outside advice as
                            necessary.</p>
                        <pb facs="0740" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/>
                        <p>I am asking the following to join this group, which I will chair:</p>
                        <p>Matt Nimetz, Under Secretary</p>
                        <p>Roz Ridgway, Counselor</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BHG_1">Harry Barnes</persName>, Director
                            General</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SRI_1">Ron Spiers</persName>, Assistant Secretary,
                                <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>Diego Asencio, Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_CA_1">CA</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TTM_1">Tom Tracy</persName>, Assistant Secretary,
                            A</p>
                        <p>Deane Hinton, Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_EB_1">EB</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Hal Saunders</persName>, Assistant
                            Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Tony Lake</persName>, Director, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>Roger Feldman, Comptroller</p>
                        <p>Paul Boeker, Director, <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>Vivian Derryck, Deputy Assistant Secretary-designate, Equal Employment
                            Opportunity</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName>, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_IJ_1">James Isbister</persName>, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the Foreign Service
                                        Institute<note n="3" xml:id="d180fn3">No classification
                                        marking. Drafted on September 3 by Paul H. Boeker (<gloss target="#t_MFSI_1">M/FSI</gloss>).</note>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1980-09-03">undated</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="italic">CAREER DEVELOPMENT AND TRAINING FOR FOREIGN
                                    SERVICE AND DEPARTMENT PERSONNEL</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Need</p>
                            <p>Critics of the Department of State over many years have consistently
                                faulted us for failure to develop systematically our personnel.
                                Recognizing that our people are our main resource in carrying out
                                United States diplomacy, we have no excuse—especially in times of
                                budget stringency—for not bringing these people to fuller
                                effectiveness by careful development of careers through assignments
                                and training. Most recently the Senate has addressed this need in an
                                amendment to the proposed Foreign Service Act which mandates a full
                                career development and training plan and requires us to report in 90
                                days from passage on progress and the resources needed.</p>
                            <p>The unique combination of foreign affairs generalist and expert in
                                some of the many special functions and areas that are vital to
                                foreign <pb facs="0741" n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/> affairs
                                (economics, science and technology, military/disarmament affairs,
                                narcotics, to name a few) defines a very difficult and changing
                                career development task. Yet a personnel force that has substantive
                                depth in these specialties, as well as the generalist’s foreign
                                policy sense, is crucial to the Secretary of State’s remaining
                                effective in all the specialized fields that are critical to
                                management of foreign policy. Given the breadth and depth of these
                                requirements, increased training, together with more tailored
                                assignment experiences, has to be a part of a successful
                                approach.</p>
                            <p>Adequate investment in training our people has not been possible
                                previously because we have too few people in the system to fill all
                                line jobs, much less provide training, creating continual pressure
                                on even our existing training programs. Therefore, to implement a
                                structured approach of training for all Foreign Service officers at
                                strategic points in their careers, as foreseen in the <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pell</persName> Amendment in the new Act, we
                                need, as a minimum, additional people in the Service at least
                                equivalent to the resulting increase in person/years of training.
                                Otherwise we could meet the important career development and
                                training requirement only by neglecting or further understaffing
                                other important functions—an unsustainable approach. The cost of the
                                plan is largely this personnel cost—expanding employment by the
                                amount of additional time in training.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Proposal</p>
                            <p>Based on the nature and variety of jobs Foreign Service officers are
                                expected to do throughout their careers, we have developed a
                                strategic approach to enhancing their effectiveness by professional
                                training for all at 3 critical points of their careers—the
                                beginning, early mid-level and the senior threshold. The expansion
                                of initial training is concentrated on basic job skills plus
                                grounding in the requirements and tools of analytical reporting. (We
                                are also requesting additional junior officer positions overseas to
                                assure that more of them get both more varied and more reporting
                                experience early in their careers.) Mid-level training—an entirely
                                new program—is designed to deepen professional skills in an
                                officer’s main function (political, economic, administrative,
                                consular) as well as broaden our skills base by training in a
                                second, probably less traditional area of foreign affairs. The main
                                function of senior-level training would be program management,
                                defined broadly to include the domestic and bureaucratic dimensions
                                of successful foreign affairs management, although some of this
                                would be covered at mid-level as well.</p>
                            <p>We also propose to correct the shocking inadequacy of language
                                training and area orientation for Foreign Service staff people, most
                                of whom are now sent to work and live overseas without any such
                                    train<pb facs="0742" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/>ing. Under the
                                proposal we could provide basic language training and relevant area
                                orientation for about two-thirds of our staff going overseas, rising
                                eventually to a skill base where virtually all would have this
                                preparation.</p>
                            <p>While expansion of the junior officer training (by 3 weeks) and the
                                senior management training (5 weeks) can be absorbed, the new
                                mid-level program (5 months for 180 <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>-5s each year) and the expanded training for Foreign
                                Service staff (about 140 annually in 10 week language/area courses,
                                plus increased administrative, consular and communications training)
                                are not possible without increasing the work force by the planned
                                increase in training investment each year: 75 <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> (for 75 person/years of additional
                                training) and 45 Foreign Service Staff positions.</p>
                            <p>To provide continuity and to assure Congress, <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> and ourselves that we mean
                                business, we would take these additional positions, plus what
                                training investment we now make, and segregate them in a “training
                                complement” that defines the annual investment the Foreign Service
                                should make to operate the career development and training program
                                at the level required. In other words we are not just asking for
                                some more training positions, we are proposing to establish a
                                permanent career development and training program which consists of
                                a defined annual investment in personnel time, the addition of
                                people needed to assure permanence, segregated in a training
                                complement, and a completely revised curriculum of the Foreign
                                Service Institute to meet the needs of this program.</p>
                            <p>The proposed increase in training for the Department’s Civil Service
                                employees emphasizes management training and job-related functional
                                training. Because of the nature of the Civil Service system, new
                                training positions are not required, other than establishment of a
                                Presidential Management Intern complement.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Curriculum of Foreign Service Institute</p>
                            <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>, concerned
                                about missed opportunities in the role of the Foreign Service
                                Institute, had ordered a complete review and reform of its
                                    curriculum.<note n="4" xml:id="d180fn4">Not found.</note> This
                                task is already underway, although part of it will meet the
                                instructional side of the career development and training proposal
                                and therefore accounts for part of the proposal’s cost. This review
                                concluded that while the quality of <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss>’s courses should be improved, the main reason it
                                was not achieving the desired, strategic increase in the
                                effectiveness of our people was the problem of delivering the
                                training under current personnel constraints. The career develop<pb facs="0743" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>ment and training proposal,
                                entailing increased personnel, the training complement and the three
                                levels of required professional training for all <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSOs</gloss>, was the major result of the
                                review’s conclusions, but <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss> has
                                undertaken other course reforms to meet the delivery problem as
                                well.</p>
                            <p>Since most of our <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSOs</gloss> now go
                                overseas with no training in the area they are supposed to interpret
                                and analyze, we face a serious risk to the stable of in-depth area
                                knowledge and communications effectiveness that is one of the
                                traditional strengths of the Foreign Service. To address this
                                problem <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss> has created a more
                                challenging and country-specific set of area courses which are now
                                integrated with the basic language training that all of our officers
                                take several times during their careers.</p>
                            <p>To allow more Foreign Service staff and family members to get basic
                                language and relevant area orientation (aimed at living in a society
                                rather than analyzing it), <gloss target="#t_FSI_1">FSI</gloss> is
                                also developing a new set of short language courses, again
                                integrated with area orientation, for all the world’s major
                                languages. This will allow many more staff members and working
                                spouses to make the shorter investment in time required for a
                                facility in the language and culture adequate for social and
                                logistical requirements. These courses will be introduced in
                                January.</p>
                            <p>An expanded junior officer course and an analytical reporting course
                                (oddly enough the first of its kind) are now in operation.
                                Development of the 5-month mid-level program, which we hope to offer
                                to the first group of 60 <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>-5s
                                next July (if <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> approves our
                                proposal and the Congress has not rejected it) has begun but will
                                not be completed until early next year. In the functional part of
                                this program (economics for economic officers, political analysis
                                for political officers, etc.) our objectives will be to deepen our
                                officers’ capacity for analysis, particularly of overseas events and
                                to enhance their understanding of the full context of major foreign
                                policy issues, including the United States domestic dimension. The
                                basic vehicles will be issues and case studies with concepts, theory
                                and topical background used to probe the meaning and trends
                                underlying the current state of critical issues. The approach will
                                be to analyze issues such as energy, disarmament negotiations and
                                immigration in such depth that both broader specific understanding
                                and the habits of rigorous thinking are imparted. A second element
                                of the program would entail each officer’s going outside his or her
                                primary field to learn about other aspects of foreign affairs, which
                                could be economic analysis for a consular officer or narcotics,
                                nuclear, or administrative matters for a political officer. This is
                                designed to fit the new emphasis on “out-of-cone” assignments to
                                prepare better generalists and to serve the Department’s need for
                                more substantive depth in non-traditional functions. The third
                                segment of the program, the only one to be a common experience for
                                all officers, would provide <pb facs="0744" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/> training in mid-level management as well as the specific
                                requirements for bureaucratic effectiveness in a complex Washington
                                environment.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>