<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="96" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                        <head>96. Memorandum From the Chairman of the Intelligence Oversight Board
                                (<persName corresp="#p_FTL_1">Farmer</persName>) to Vice President
                                <persName corresp="#p_MW_2">Mondale</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d96fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, Staff Material, President’s Intelligence Oversight
                                Board, Box 2, Meeting 5/16/79. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-05-14">May 14, 1979</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Presidential Standards for Review and Approval of Sensitive
                                Collection and Counterintelligence Operations</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> agenda for Wednesday, May 16,
                            includes consideration of Presidential standards for review and approval
                            of sensitive collection operations pursuant to sections 1–303 and 1–306
                            of Executive Order 12036 and counterintelligence operations pursuant to
                            section 1–304 of the Order. For the past six months, staff efforts to
                            obtain agreement on the standards, or even basic principles, have been
                            unsuccessful. The basic split has been between <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> on the one hand and Justice and State on the other.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">I.</hi> BACKGROUND</p>
                        <p>During the latter stages of <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            consideration of what became Executive Order 12036, the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approved a provision requiring that
                            sensitive collection operations be treated in a manner similar to that
                            used for special activities (<gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            approval or recommendations to the President on each proposed
                            operation). On January 7, 1978, just prior to the signing of the Order,
                            the Director of Central Intelligence sent a memorandum to the President
                            recommending that the sensitive collection provision be changed to limit
                            the role of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> in the approval
                                process.<note n="2" xml:id="d96fn2">See <ref target="#d72">Document
                                    72</ref>.</note> The memorandum was not coordinated with or even
                            provided to the members of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>. The
                                <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s justifications for limited
                                <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> review were the security
                            problems raised by revealing sensitive operations to all <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members and a concern that a procedure
                            for <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approval of all operations
                            would lead to legislation requiring congressional approval as well. Up
                            to and including the present time, the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s 1978 memorandum to the President has not been
                            formally revealed to all the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            members. The Secretary of State first learned of the existence of the
                            memorandum in April 1979.</p>
                        <p>The President did not adopt the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s
                            suggested language for the Order. Instead, he informed the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> Chairman that he agreed with the suggested approach but
                            preferred to include the details in Presidential standards rather than
                            in the Executive Order. As an <pb facs="0450" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/>
                            apparent consequence of the President’s decision, the Executive Order
                            was rewritten into its current form:</p>
                        <quote>
                            <p>1–303. <hi rend="italic">Sensitive Foreign Intelligence
                                    Operations</hi>. Under standards established by the President,
                                proposals for sensitive foreign intelligence collection operations
                                shall be reported to the Chairman [of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>]<note n="3" xml:id="d96fn3">Brackets are in the
                                    original.</note> by the Director of Central Intelligence for
                                appropriate review and approval.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>In June of 1978, the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> asked the
                            Attorney General for an opinion on the sensitive collection review
                            procedures for the purpose of conducting an annual review. The resulting
                            opinion discussed the history of the Executive Order, including the
                                <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s January memorandum to the
                            President (which was provided “in confidence” only to the Attorney
                            General). The opinion concluded that the President had not adopted the
                            limited approval and review procedure proposed by the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> and that he was free, under the
                            Executive Order, to either adopt the procedure or to establish a
                            different procedure as he saw fit. A copy of the opinion is attached at
                            Tab A.<note n="4" xml:id="d96fn4">Not found attached.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>For more than six months after the Order had been signed, there was no
                            apparent effort to draft the standards, despite the Executive Order
                            requirement for Presidential standards and the President’s decision to
                            include the details of the review and approval process instandards
                            issued by him. In August 1978, the <gloss target="#t_IOB_1">IOB</gloss>
                            met with the President and informed him that, in the absence of
                            standards under the Order, sensitive collection operations were being
                            approved by an informal procedure that did not necessarily include
                                <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> consultation.<note n="5" xml:id="d96fn5">See <ref target="#d88">Document 88</ref>.</note> We
                            also indicated that while we had not found any abuse in this procedure,
                            we felt that the procedure raised serious institutional problems. The
                            President expressed surprise and invited the Board to draft the
                            standards, but we deferred to the Intelligence Community.</p>
                        <p>Subsequently, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and Justice circulated
                            a series of draft standards, but the staffs at State, Justice and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> were unable to reach agreement. In
                            March of this year, the Secretary of State circulated to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members a memorandum calling for an
                                <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> meeting on the matter and
                            setting out certain principles that he believed should govern the
                            Presidential standards. This memorandum was followed by a State
                            Department draft of the standards which was circulated in April to the
                                <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members with a memorandum from
                            the Secretary of State <pb facs="0451" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> again
                            calling for an <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> meeting. The State
                            Department circulations are attached at Tab B.<note n="6" xml:id="d96fn6">Not found attached. Neither the CIA/Justice draft
                                nor the March State Department memorandum was found.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Throughout this period, there were also staff level discussions of
                            Presidential standards for <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approval
                            of counterintelligence operations, pursuant to section 1–304(e) of the
                            Executive Order. For your convenience, copies of the relevant Executive
                            Order provision and the latest draft of the counterintelligence
                            standards issues paper are attached at Tab C.<note n="7" xml:id="d96fn7">Not found attached.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> SENSITIVE COLLECTION STANDARDS</p>
                        <p>The basic issue to be decided is the institutional role of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> in the review and approval of
                            proposals for sensitive collection operations. Two different approaches
                            for the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> role have emerged from the
                            staff discussions. The first, supported by the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, treats the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> as a
                            resource to be used in the review and approval process at the discretion
                            of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> Chairman (Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs). Under this approach, the Chairman would
                            approve sensitive collection proposals and consult the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> as he deems necessary. The second
                            approach, supported by the State Department, gives the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> control over the review and approval
                            process. Under this approach, the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            would approve all sensitive collection proposals except certain
                            categories of “routine” operations, as determined by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>, which could be approved by the
                            Chairman and reviewed quarterly by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The first approach would establish a procedure similar to that now in
                            effect. The current procedure, as it has been described to us by Stan
                            and <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Zbig</persName>, bears an unfortunate
                            resemblance to the practice of the Forty Committee that was criticized
                            by the Senate Select Committee on Intelligence.<note n="8" xml:id="d96fn8">The 40 Committee, named after National Security
                                Decision Memorandum 40, February 17, 1970, reviewed and approved
                                covert action proposals. For the text of NSDM 40, see <ref target="frus1969-76v02#d203">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, vol. II,
                                    Organization and Management of U.S. Foreign Policy, 1969–1972,
                                    Document 203</ref>. According to the <persName corresp="#p_CF_2">Church</persName> Committee Final Report (see <ref target="#d41fn5">footnote 5, Document 41</ref>), the 40
                                Committee considered only about 25 percent of the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’s individual covert action
                                projects, and Congress received briefings on only a few proposed
                                projects.</note> With the exception of certain technical collection
                            operations, sensitive collection proposals are reported to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> Chairman at the sole discretion of the
                            Director of Central Intelligence. The <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s reports are usually oral rather than written. The
                            Chairman then determines whether the Secretary of State should be
                            informed (again orally) and whether the proposal should be referred to
                            the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> or whether to inform the
                            President. As far as we can tell, there are no existing <pb facs="0452" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> guidelines or standard for determining
                            when the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> consults with the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> Chairman or when the Chairman consults
                            with some or all of the members of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>. Last year, the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            conducted an annual review of sensitive collection operations.<note n="9" xml:id="d96fn9">Not further identified.</note> Brief written
                            summaries were distributed at the outset of the meeting and collected at
                            the end. Without any prior consideration or staff support, the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> was asked to review and approve the
                            current operations. At least some of the members present at the meeting
                            were concerned that they did not really know what they had approved.</p>
                        <p>The Intelligence Oversight Board feels very strongly that the current
                            process should not be perpetuated in the Presidential standards. Under
                            the Executive Order, the members of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>, when meeting for the purpose of considering sensitive
                            collection proposals, are the Secretary of State, the Secretary of
                            Defense and the Attorney General, as well as the President’s Assistant
                            for National Security Affairs and the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>. We believe that the potential for embarrassment to the
                            United States and the other considerations that determine the
                            sensitivity of certain collection operations require the considered
                            judgment and approval of the President’s senior advisers on foreign
                            policy, national security and law. The <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>, and to a lesser extent, the President’s Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs are expected to act as advocates for
                            collection activities that they perceive as necessary to meet the
                            Nation’s needs for reliable foreign intelligence. The responsibilities
                            assigned to each generate institutional pressures to undertake
                            collection activities. In order to assure that factors other than the
                            need for foreign intelligence are given full and careful consideration,
                            proposals for sensitive collection operations should be presented to and
                            approved by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The specific issues that should be decided by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> are as follows:</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Determination of Which Collection Operations Qualify
                                as Sensitive:</hi> There is general agreement that the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s discretion to report proposals for
                            collection operations should be guided by general considerations tending
                            to define sensitive operations. The State Department and the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> disagree, however, on whether the
                            Presidential standards should also include specific designations of
                            types of proposed operations that are inherently sensitive and should
                            always be reported. (One commonly cited example is an operation in which
                            a head of state is a target or source.)</p>
                        <p>The Board believes that the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s
                            discretion should be guided both by carefully defined criteria that will
                            always require a report and by factors to be considered in determining
                            whether to report operations not covered by the mandatory reporting
                            criteria. In the staff discussions, <pb facs="0453" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/> the issue of mandatory reporting criteria has
                            received more attention than is warranted, possibly because of a belief
                            that such criteria imply a lack of faith in the judgment of the official
                            responsible for reporting. We believe that the issue should be resolved
                            in terms of the best method for structuring the decision-making process
                            rather than in terms of the personalities currently involved in that
                            process. Mandatory reporting criteria give some precision to an
                            otherwise imprecise process and should therefore be included.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Form of Reporting:</hi> State and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> disagree on whether sensitive
                            collection proposals should be reported orally or in writing and on
                            whether the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> should be permitted to
                            report categories of proposed operations rather than each specific
                            proposal.</p>
                        <p>We strongly believe that the Presidential standards should include a
                            requirement for reporting proposals in writing. Written proposals create
                            a record of what was proposed and, therefore, of what was approved. A
                            written record not only promotes careful consideration and establishes
                            accountability, but also assists the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> if it later becomes necessary for him to determine
                            whether changed circumstances are consistent with an operation that has
                            been approved. We are aware that a written document increases the risk
                            of compromise of an operation and address that problem in the discussion
                            of security procedures below.</p>
                        <p>Categorical reporting can be a useful device and should be permitted by
                            the standards. If a group of operations are substantially similar (in
                            terms of the type of target, risks of exposure, benefits to be derived,
                            and potential effects of compromise) categorical reporting can permit
                            careful consideration while at the same time avoid repetitive and
                            time-consuming reporting and approval of specific operations. But
                            categorical reporting should not inadvertently become a mechanism for
                            obscuring differences among proposed operations or limiting the flow of
                            relevant information to the Chairman and members of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>. The standards should therefore
                            include a provision for the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> to
                            determine when categorical reporting will be permitted.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Approval and Review by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>:</hi> The issue here is whether the standards
                            should require <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approval of
                            sensitive collection proposals or permit the Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> to approve proposals and consult the
                                <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> as he deems necessary. For the
                            reasons stated above, the Board believes that the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> should be the approving authority.
                            Although the issue has not been raised by either <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> or State, the Board believes that the
                            standards should include a specific provision for advance distribution
                            of written proposals to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> so that
                            the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members will have both the time
                            and staff support necessary to carry out their approval and review
                            responsibilities.</p>
                        <p>The Board does not disagree with a procedure that permits delegation of
                            limited approval authority to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>
                            Chairman. Depending <pb facs="0454" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> upon the
                            types of operations that are proposed and reported by the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>, there may be categories of operations
                            that are “routine” in that they are clearly consistent with established
                            policy and do not involve high risk or especially serious consequences
                            of exposure. To preserve flexibility and conserve the time of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members, the Board believes that the
                            standards should include a provision for the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> to stipulate categories of proposals for “routine”
                            operations that can be approved by the Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>. The Chairman’s approval of “routine”
                            operations should not, however, completely replace the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> process. We believe that the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members should review, on a quarterly
                            basis, all proposals that have not received advance <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approval.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>:</hi> Section 1–306 of the Executive Order includes
                            a separate requirement for an annual review by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> and a report to the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>. If the issues described above are
                            resolved as recommended, it should not be necessary to include detailed
                            requirements for the annual review. The Department of State believes
                            that the annual review should include a sampling procedure to evaluate
                            the <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>’s characterization of
                            operations as “sensitive.” The Board agrees with the State Department on
                            this issue.</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Security of Information Concerning Sensitive
                                Collection Operations:</hi> There is no dispute that strict security
                            procedures are required because of the extreme sensitivity of the
                            information involved. We support the inclusion of security procedures in
                            the Presidential standards. Security procedures should not, however,
                            undermine the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> approval and review
                            process. In prior Administrations, security concerns have been used as a
                            rationalization for engaging in cursory consultation (either by
                            telephone or in informal conversations), for limiting the information
                            provided to concerned Cabinet officials or for entirely bypassing
                            established approval and review procedures. We believe that any
                            formulation of security procedures should be based on the principle of
                            control, rather than elimination, of written documents and of control,
                            rather than denial, of information to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> members.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">III.</hi> COUNTERINTELLIGENCE STANDARDS</p>
                        <p>The issues for <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> review and approval
                            of counterintelligence operations are similar to those described above
                            for sensitive collection operations. The issues paper at Tab C
                            adequately describes the issues and options.</p>
                        <p>The Board favors substantive standards that include a clear statement as
                            to the types of counterintelligence operations that must be reported to
                            and approved by the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>. The Board also
                            favors procedures for the reporting, review and approval of
                            counterintelligence operations similar to the procedures that apply to
                            sensitive collection operations.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>