<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-04-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="136" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d136">
                        <head>136. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry
                                Owen</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d136fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 75, Turkey:
                                4–8/79. Confidential. Sent for information. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> each initialed in the
                                top right-hand corner.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-04-23">April 23, 1979</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Emergency Aid to Turkey (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Your initiative in asking the Congress for $100 million in supplemental
                            economic aid to Turkey, raising the potential US total contribution to
                            $248 million,<note n="2" xml:id="d136fn2">On April 10, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> transmitted to Congress a
                                bill to authorize $100 million in supplementary economic support for
                                Turkey. (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, 1979,</hi> Book I, pp.
                                647–648)</note> is putting pressure on Germany to fulfill its
                            leadership role by offering a matching amount. It also has helped to
                            convince the Turks that the international aid effort is serious. The
                            impact on other donors has been less impressive. (C)</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Schmidt</persName> responded (Tab A)<note n="3" xml:id="d136fn3">Tabs A and B are attached but not
                                printed.</note> on March 30 that it would be difficult to raise the
                            German contribution above the $100 million (plus $70 million in
                            previously planned project aid) already announced, but he would try.
                            Subsequently our embassy reported that <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Schmidt</persName>’s special envoy for this exercise, Herr Kiep,
                            and the Foreign Office are pressing for an additional $100 million
                            German appropriation (exclusive of export credits comparable to our $50
                            [million] ExIm credit offer). We have repeatedly told the Germans that
                            you want full matching by Germany. Senator Muskie plans to tell
                                <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Schmidt</persName> on May 7 that
                            Congress will not appropriate more economic aid for Turkey than the
                                <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> provides. (C)</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GDV_1">Giscard</persName> responded to you on
                            April 11 (Tab B) with what we already knew: France will provide mixed
                            export credits totalling $70 million and will try to cause them to be
                            used quickly. Our experts doubt that more than half will be usable by
                            Turkey in 1979. <persName corresp="#p_GDV_1">Giscard</persName> also
                            claimed one-fourth credit for the prospective <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> contribution of $100 million in development aid to
                            Turkey—much of which is not applicable to the immediate Turkish balance
                            of payments deficit. No reply to <persName corresp="#p_GDV_1">Giscard</persName> seems indicated. The State Department will
                            express disappointment to the French Embassy. (C)</p>
                        <p>The UK will wait until it has a new government before reconsidering its
                            $15 million offer. (C)</p>
                        <pb facs="0452" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                        <p>Ohira’s reply indicated that Japan would increase its $50 million offer
                            if France and the UK increased theirs. (C)</p>
                        <p>German hat-passing efforts are unlikely to be fruitful until Germany
                            itself raises its contribution and the Congress reacts to your
                            supplemental request. (Senate hearings on the supplemental for Turkey
                            are to begin April 27.) These two actions are interrelated; the <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> memo that you approved provides that
                            we will testify to the Congress that we will provide only such part of
                            the proposed $248 million to this year’s emergency aid pool as the
                                <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> will match. (C)</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, Turkey has taken some significant economic rationalization
                            measures and agreed to resume negotiations next week with the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> on a comprehensive reform program.
                            These negotiations are likely to take two to three months. The Turks now
                            realize that they will not get emergency economic aid until they adopt a
                            program acceptable to the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>. (C)</p>
                        <p>We will keep you informed of further developments.<note n="4" xml:id="d136fn4">In a May 5 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> regarding emergency aid to
                                Turkey, <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> reported that
                                the German Minister of State for Foreign Affairs told him that “the
                                    <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> still refuses to match us
                                on aid to Turkey, as a matter of principle, but that there is no
                                ceiling on the amount of German aid.” <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> suggested that the United States could
                                accommodate the German position by asking the Germans to match the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> appropriated aid of $198
                                million but not match the ExIm Bank loan of $50 million. <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> reasoned: “Since they will
                                probably make export loans anyway, in order to sell their exports,
                                we would not lose out on the cash and they would not lose out on the
                                principle. We could still tell the Congress that our appropriated
                                aid was being matched.” <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>
                                further reported that <persName corresp="#p_SH_3">Schmidt</persName>
                                was waiting to hear <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s
                                response and <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>
                                recommended that <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                                approve telling the German Ambassador that the United States would
                                adapt “its position to the Chancellor’s view by asking only for
                                matching of our appropriated aid.” <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> approved the recommendation and initialed “J”
                                at the bottom of the memorandum. (Carter Library, National Security
                                Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Brzezinski Office File, Country Chron
                                File, Box 51, Turkey: 5–12/79)</note> (U)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>