<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-06-08T09:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-06-08T09:15:00-05:00" n="190" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d190">
                        <head>190. Telegram From the Embassy in Greece to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d190fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records of the
                                Office of the Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Warren
                                    Christopher</persName>, 1977–1980, Lot 81D113, Box 9, Memos From
                                    <gloss target="#t_WMC_1">WMC</gloss> to Offices/Bureaus—1979.
                                Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>. Sent
                                for information Immediate to <gloss target="#t_USNMR_1">USNMR
                                    SHAPE</gloss>; to Ankara, Bonn, Nicosia, <gloss target="#t_USNATO_1">USNATO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USDOCOSouth_1">USDOCOSouth</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_USDELMC_1">USDELMC</gloss>. In an attached
                                handwritten note dated June 11, <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> instructed <persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName>: “Let’s discuss where to go from here—now that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>’s time apparently
                                has run out.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Athens</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-06-08T14:15:00+00:00">June 8, 1979, 1415Z</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>5024. <gloss target="#t_miladdees_1">Miladdees</gloss> handle as <gloss target="#t_Specat_1">Specat</gloss> Exclusive. Subject: (S) Foreign
                            Relations: Discussion With <persName corresp="#p_MP_1">Molyviatis</persName> on <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                            Reintegration and <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Greek Bilateral
                            Affairs.</p>
                        <p>1. (S-entire text)</p>
                        <p>2. Summary: While the <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> is preparing
                            to reject <gloss target="#t_SACEUR_1">SACEUR</gloss>’s latest proposal
                            on <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> reintegration, it has yet to
                            conclude what course to take beyond this.<note n="2" xml:id="d190fn2">On
                                May 3, <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> reported on
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>’s “all-out effort”
                                to seek a compromise between Greece and Turkey regarding the terms
                                of Greek re-entry to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> before
                                his planned resignation as Supreme Allied Commander Europe in early
                                June. At that juncture, the main stumbling block for negotiations
                                was the issue of control over Aegean airspace. Turkey wanted to
                                control airspace at 30 miles beyond its Aegean border; Greece
                                rejected this area as too large. (“Greece’s Re-Entry into <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Snagged,” May 3, 1979, p.
                                A7)</note> At the same time it remains obsessed with the notion that
                            the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has failed to use its influence
                            to resolve this issue and, because our inclination is to favor Turkey,
                            we are party to its irresolution. As a consequence, our bilateral
                            relations with Greece become contaminated and further on our base rights
                            may stand in jeopardy. End summary.</p>
                        <pb facs="0616" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/>
                        <p>3. The foregoing emerged during the course of a long and at times
                            disagreeable conversation with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Karamanlis</persName>’ principal aide Petros
                            Molyviatis on June 7. I asked for the meeting in order to have a candid
                            discussion of where our relationships were leading us. There is little
                            to be encouraged about.</p>
                        <p>4. Introducing my purpose, I said I had become increasingly disturbed by
                            comments we were hearing and reading, the sum of which was that United
                            States policy in the area was taking Greece for granted and that it was
                            measured only by its desire to preserve our interests in Turkey—in a
                            word, that our intentions here were dishonorable. These interpretations
                            were, in turn, leading to stories that our bilateral affairs had become
                            chilled and as a result, there was an “impasse” in our relations. While
                            no such line had been conveyed to me by government officials I had come
                            now to assume that it was being encouraged by officials. If this was not
                            so I would be happy to have something to the contrary because just a few
                            weeks ago Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_RG_1">Rallis</persName>
                            had described our relationships as “excellent.” I noted that while
                            confirming the story of the <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>
                            negotiations being in suspense last weekend the government spokesman
                            had, in effect, also confirmed that overall we were at an impasse.<note n="3" xml:id="d190fn3">In telegram 4622 from Athens, May 29, the
                                Embassy reported that Greek officials had decided to suspend
                                negotiations for Voice of America transmissions. (National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, P840133–2577)</note> Finally, I said we could not accept being
                            appealed to privately to help with Greece’s regional problems while we
                            were being bullied to such an extent publicly.</p>
                        <p>5. Without addressing my remarks directly Molyviatis raised the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> issue and produced a map. Doubtless
                            it was the same one that figured in the Secretary’s meeting with Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_RG_1">Rallis</persName> May 31 in The
                                Hague.<note n="4" xml:id="d190fn4">See <ref target="#d189">Document
                                    189</ref>.</note> Inked lines on the map purport to demonstrate
                            how the recent (leaked) <gloss target="#t_SACEUR_1">SACEUR</gloss>
                            proposals would give command and control authority in the Aegean to
                            “others” and hence are “totally unacceptable.” To my question Molyviatis
                            asserted that <gloss target="#t_SACEUR_1">SACEUR</gloss>’s “latest”
                            proposals made only “cosmetic changes” and were equally unacceptable. An
                            official reply to this effect was in preparation and would be forwarded
                            to Brussels soon.</p>
                        <p>6. In further discussion of this I sought to disabuse Molyviatis of his
                            assumption that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has—if not
                            authored the proposals—at the least inspired them. (Comment: His
                            skepticism on this important point says something about the mindset we
                            encounter here.) He was contending that the juxtaposition of the Deputy
                            Secretary’s remarks May 15 describing Turkey’s attitude toward the
                            dispute (on which Molyviatis put a higher gloss) and the existence
                            (before being leaked) <pb facs="0617" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> of
                                <gloss target="#t_SACEUR_1">SACEUR</gloss>’s paper was confirmation
                            that we had underwritten it.<note n="5" xml:id="d190fn5">Reference is to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>’s May 15
                                appearance before the House Committee on Foreign Affairs. <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> appeared before the
                                committee in order to justify proposed economic and military aid
                                packages for Turkey.</note> He allowed he was “reassured” with my
                            saying that our wish was that the parties find a mutually agreeable
                            resolution, that we would use our influence toward that end but that we
                            had not attempted to design the formula for getting there. Molyviatis
                            registered some disbelief when I added that at given times we were
                            uninformed about the state of play. (Comment: Obviously as a result of
                            this conversation, <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> Director General
                                <persName corresp="#p_TJA_1">Tzounis</persName> called in <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> this morning to show him the latest
                                <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> proposal and to explain
                            in great and emotional detail why <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss>
                            could “never” accept it. His arguments, which are being reported
                            separately, boiled down to Greek unwillingness “under any peacetime
                            conditions” to have Turkey responsible for defending any part of Greek
                            airspace or even to have Turkish military planes flying through
                                it.)<note n="6" xml:id="d190fn6">The Embassy reported the Greek
                                position as explained by <persName corresp="#p_TJA_1">Tzounis</persName> in telegram 5126 from Athens, June 12.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, D790266–0253)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>7. About where to go from here, Molyviatis described the <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> as facing three alternatives: allow
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s efforts to continue
                            although he couldn’t see how it would ensue “since General <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> has torn to shreds” the
                            arrangements the <gloss target="#t_GOG_1">GOG</gloss> could support;
                            freeze the issue for an indefinite period; withdraw their initiative and
                            seek a role for themselves along the “model” of the French.</p>
                        <p>8. Reminding Molyviatis that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> was
                            being subjected to unjustifiable blame for Greece’s real and imagined
                            difficulties led us into an unprofitable exchange on the problem of
                            leaks. (I confess to having felt slightly vulnerable with our deplorable
                            record over the last year.) Beyond the misfortune of these disclosures
                            some of which I was confident came from Greek sources, I said I was more
                            irritated presently by a combination of stories and rumorings that I had
                            to assume emanated from government sources; that our official relations
                            were stalemated; that an inevitable consequence would be a denial of
                            base rights. On the latter Molyviatis restated that our military
                            presence is contingent on Greece’s <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> membership while acknowledging my point that they
                            serve common purpose. On the broader question he excused the government
                            from any control over the press and demurred at my saying we knew that
                            government sources were impugning our motives toward Greece. He
                            professed to be unaware that the government spokesman had linked
                            suspension of the <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> negotiations with
                            other outstanding matters including our draft agreement on other
                            non-security issues.</p>
                        <pb facs="0618" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/>
                        <p>9. Toward the end I emphasized that we remained willing to assist Greece
                            and that our intentions were affirmatively more honorable than we were
                            being given credit for in and out of government in Athens. To be accused
                            of working against the interests of Greece was unjustified and
                            inaccurate and unworthy of a mature relationship. We would continue to
                            help with Greece’s aspirations in its international affairs as well as
                            in bilateral objectives and that our record to date has been
                            creditable.</p>
                        <p>10. Comment: Once again it is clear that the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> issue is at the center of Greek frustrations and is
                            infecting our relationships. Our objectives here I’m afraid will remain
                            hostage to its continued irresolution.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRJ_1"><hi rend="strong">McCloskey</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>