<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="21" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                        <head>21. Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d21fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency,
                                Directorate of Intelligence, Job 80T00634A, Box 3, unlabeled folder.
                                Secret; [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not
                                    declassified</hi>]. A note on the first page reads: “This
                                memorandum was prepared by the Western Europe Division of the Office
                                of Regional and Political Analysis in coordination with the Office
                                of Strategic Research and the Office of Economic Research.
                                ‘Questions and comments may be addressed to [<hi rend="italic">name
                                    not declassified</hi>].” A distribution list is attached but not
                                printed.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">RP M 78–10231</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-05-25">May 25, 1978</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s Troubled Southeastern
                                Flank: Greek and Turkish Foreign Policies</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The quarrels between Greece and Turkey over Cyprus and
                                the Aegean have triggered significant changes in the two countries’
                                broader foreign policies. Their efforts to outmaneuver each other
                                have weakened <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s southeastern
                                flank and disrupted the harmony of the Western defense and economic
                                systems in general. At the same time, the critical importance to
                                both countries of their Western ties puts limits on how far they can
                                go. Neither—but especially the Greeks—can afford to leave the field
                                to its rival by bolting the West altogether. And Turkey will be
                                cautious in pursuing its self-proclaimed intention to adopt a more
                                independent foreign policy.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>When Greece and Turkey have quarreled in the past they have moved in
                            fairly predictable ways. The pattern followed by the Greeks has been to
                            secure external involvement, believing that this can only help them
                            against their more powerful adversary. This strategy has served them
                            well. Their independence from the Ottomans and all subsequent recoveries
                            of territories from the Turks have been won with the help of outside
                            intervention.</p>
                        <p>Precisely because of the Greeks’ success, the Turks for their part, have
                            constantly opposed the involvement of other powers in their disputes
                            with the Greeks. Indeed, it is their experience of constantly being
                            “ganged up” on by the West that accounts for the Turks’ [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] ambivalent
                            feelings toward their allies in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Differing Strategies</p>
                        <p>The two countries have exhibited similar behavior in their present
                            rivalry over Cyprus and the Aegean. The Greeks have sought to mobilize
                            and involve all their friends and allies in their behalf. Their
                            withdrawal from <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s integrated
                            military command in 1974 and their decision to revise defense relations
                            with the US were aimed in part at nudging both into playing a greater
                            role in settling the disputes. These <pb facs="0122" n="89" xml:id="pg_89"/> moves have been measured, and have been partly
                            compensated for by a concerted drive to “join Western Europe” by way of
                            membership in the European Community. While that move is aimed mainly at
                            bolstering Greece’s economy and its Western democratic tradition, it is
                            also seen by Greeks as another “security blanket” of sorts against the
                            Turks. In that context, the rush to join is part of the broader
                            Greek-Turkish rivalry.</p>
                        <p>The Turks, on the other hand, have consistently maintained that
                            Greek-Turkish problems must not be linked to Turkey’s relations with its
                            US and West European allies. Believing that Turkey has other options by
                            virtue of its size and strategic location, the Demirel government
                            underscored this point in 1975 by suspending US base operations in
                            Turkey in response to the Congressionally imposed arms embargo. Beyond
                            that, the Turks have sought to counter Greek maneuvering within the
                            Western orbit with some of their own. They have tried to obstruct
                            Greece’s effort to negotiate a new relationship with <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, in part because of a genuine
                            concern that the Greeks are trying to get a free ride but also in
                            retaliation for Greek lobbying in behalf of the US arms embargo.</p>
                        <p>And while the Turks have not officially opposed Greece’s prospective
                            membership in the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>, they are clearly
                            upset at the prospect of being isolated from that institution and they
                            have insisted that the Community must include Turkey in its political
                            consultative process once the Greeks get in.<note n="2" xml:id="d21fn2">The Greek Parliament ratified Greece’s accession to the European
                                Community on June 28, 1979, and Greece officially became a member on
                                January 1, 1981.</note> More important, the Turks have sought to
                            increase their leverage with their allies—and also to carve a new niche
                            for Turkey in international politics—by dangling the threat of a further
                            loosening of ties to the West and a closer relationship with the Soviet
                            Union and the Third World.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Greece—A “Hooked Fish”</p>
                        <p>Greece, on the other hand, has been reluctant to wander outside the
                            Western orbit because of the close cultural, ideological, economic, and
                            security ties with the West that prompted <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">John Foster Dulles</persName> to refer to Greece as a “hooked
                            fish.” <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Dulles</persName> was speaking in
                            the context of the East-West conflict; but the fact is even more
                            relevant in the Greek-Turkish rivalry since the Greeks cannot afford to
                            concede Western support to the Turks. Indeed, “We belong to the West”
                            has been a consistent slogan of the <persName corresp="#p_CC_1">Caramanlis</persName> government even as it seeks to bring pressure
                            to bear on the West to do its bidding toward the Turks.</p>
                        <pb facs="0123" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/>
                        <p>Because of this sentiment, the Greeks have allowed US bases to operate
                            relatively unimpeded despite their unhappiness with the US response to
                            their case against the Turks. And most recently, Greek reaction to the
                            Administration’s decision to press for a lifting of the embargo against
                            Turkey has been rather muted and will probably remain so even if
                            Congress lifts the embargo.</p>
                        <p>Nor has the <persName corresp="#p_CC_1">Caramanlis</persName> government
                            felt very comfortable outside of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s integrated military command. A trend toward slowly
                            bringing Greece back into the alliance began in 1976 when most of the
                            Greeks’ nuclear-capable forces were earmarked for <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> use. This was followed by a decision
                            last fall to participate selectively in alliance military exercises. It
                            culminated in a decision last winter to seek full reentry in all but
                            name as soon as possible. To be sure, the latter was also prompted by
                            indications from some West European leaders that Greece’s <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> application might be processed more
                            speedily were it to return to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> as
                            well as Greek concern that Turkey was dominating the alliance’s
                            southeastern flank by default. Indeed, the question of naval command and
                            air control in the Aegean are emerging as the major stumbling blocks in
                            the Greek-<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> negotiations, with the
                            Greeks insisting that their former authority in these areas be restored
                            once they return, and the Turks in particular opposing such a move.</p>
                        <p>Greece’s troubles with its allies have not led to any noticeable
                            improvement in Greece’s relations with the Soviet Union. The staunch
                            anticommunism of the Greek political, military, and economic elite, the
                            Communist civil war experience, and Moscow’s courting of the Turks are
                            the reasons. And while there may be a slight thaw in the relationship
                            when Greek Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_RG_1">Rallis</persName> goes to Moscow this summer to sign some minor
                            cultural, consular, and trade agreements, Greek-Soviet relations are not
                            likely to improve substantially. On the other hand, <persName corresp="#p_CC_1">Caramanlis</persName> by his “Balkan initiative”
                            has tried to bring about a greater measure of cooperation between Greece
                            and its Balkan Communist neighbors. Designed to secure Greece’s flank in
                            the event of a clash with Turkey and often resorted to by Greek leaders
                            in the past in times of Greek-Turkish friction, the effort has been most
                            successful with Yugoslavia, with which the Greeks have developed closer
                            political, economic, and even a limited amount of military cooperation.
                            Lately, Greek-Albanian relations have also improved.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] But it will
                            remain so only so long as it is ruled by conservatives or centrists—such
                            as <persName corresp="#p_CC_1">Caramanlis</persName> and his
                            colleagues—who are committed to the West. Someone like leftist
                            opposition leader <persName corresp="#p_PA_1">Andreas
                                Papandreou</persName> might seek permanently looser ties with the US
                            and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> and might also break with the
                                <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> were he to come to power—and his
                            prospects will depend in part on the Greek electorate’s perception of
                            Western behavior in the Greek-Turkish con<pb facs="0124" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/>troversy. To be sure, the staunchly pro-West
                            military presumably would be a constraint on <persName corresp="#p_PA_1">Papandreou</persName>, but the officer corps might itself acquiesce
                            in a reduction of ties to the West in the event of another humiliation
                            by Turkey to which it felt the West was unresponsive.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Turkey More Assertive</p>
                        <p>The Demirel government only flirted with the idea of loosening Turkey’s
                            ties to the West; the independent-minded <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName> is considering it more seriously. But there is a
                            good deal of posturing in <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName>’s statements. He is fully cognizant that the
                            alternatives to Turkey’s economic and military ties with the West are
                            limited. Moreover, both he and the majority of the Turkish elite prize
                            their self image as “Western” and “European”.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName> has talked about adopting
                            a “new defense concept” for Turkey. The concept’s meaning seems to have
                            been left purposefully vague; essentially, however, it envisages a role
                            for Turkey similar to that of the French in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> or the Romanians in the Warsaw Pact. <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName> has noted, for example, that
                            although Turkey will both of necessity and choice, remain within the
                            Western defense and economic systems, it must not act as a military
                            bastion or agent of the West in its region. Moreover, Turkey should make
                            its “own contribution to detente” by reducing tensions in its area and
                            improving relations with the Soviet Union. A corollary is the effort to
                            develop closer political and economic relations with Arab and other
                            Third World states—an effort that has produced few political or economic
                            results so far. Always implicit and sometimes explicit are possible
                            reductions in Turkey’s commitment to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, in the size of the US or <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> presence in Turkey, and in the size of Turkey’s armed
                            forces.</p>
                        <p>The extent to which <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName>
                            implements his new approach will depend in the first place on whether
                            the US arms embargo is lifted. If it is not, <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName> would find it difficult politically and
                            psychologically not to take further retaliatory measures, focusing on
                            the US bases in Turkey or on Turkey’s commitment to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. Whatever he chose to do, his moves
                            would probably be tempered by the recent willingness of Western
                            governments and financial institutions to help bail out the faltering
                            Turkish economy, which is a far more serious issue in the short term for
                            Turkey than that of arms. They have offered to provide substantial
                            credits and to refinance part of Turkey’s sizeable short and mid-term
                            debt. An even more important reason for Turkish caution is that Turkey
                            will need additional credits and refinancing to solve its economic
                            problems.</p>
                        <p>Turkey in fact remains heavily dependent on the West in many important
                            ways, and <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName> will have to
                            take this fact into account as he tries to assert a greater degree of
                            autonomy. Turkey needs Western <pb facs="0125" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/>
                            credits and hard currency to meet its development needs in amounts which
                            the Soviet Union has been unable or unwilling to supply despite its
                            economic largesse to Turkey in other ways. Turkey, moreover, does not
                            have a viable alternative to Western, and particularly US, arms. [<hi rend="italic">2 lines not declassified</hi>]—and the military
                            balance would doubtless tilt toward Greece while the process was
                            underway. Even if they could set aside their historic suspicion of the
                            Soviets, the Turks would be reluctant to pay the political price that
                            Moscow would almost certainly demand for such vast amounts of economic
                            and military assistance. <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName>,
                            therefore, is unlikely during his widely publicized visit next month to
                            Moscow to enter into any agreements with the Soviet Union that would be
                            incompatible with Turkey’s continued membership in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Nor does it appear likely that <persName corresp="#p_EB_1">Ecevit</persName>’s courting of the Third World will produce any
                            more dividends than it did for his predecessor. For example, the Arabs’
                            reaction to Turkey’s economic plight to date and their attitudes on
                            Cyprus do not suggest a dramatic improvement in relations.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>] to be sure, and one
                            that clearly intends to test the length and strength of the line. The
                            Turks in fact will probably succeed in stretching the line; but a break
                            is not much likelier for Turkey than it is for Greece. Meanwhile, until
                            they are settled, the squabbles between the two will continue to weaken
                            and disrupt Western institutions.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>