<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>117. Telegram From the Embassy in the Republic of China to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-06-15T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-06-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec8pJFHnWBDxr1c0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military spending</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-06-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-06-15T06:00:00-05:00" n="117"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                <head>117. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Republic of
                        China</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d117fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 811.0093/6-1562. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Taipei</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-06-15T19:00:00+08:00">June 15, 1962, 7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>968. Joint Embassy-<gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> message. Purpose of this
                    message is to take stock of situation and outline our thoughts on appropriate
                    course of action re special military expenditures program and US aid to <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> following <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1"
                        >Janow</persName> visit.<note n="1" xml:id="d117fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1">Seymour J. Janow</persName>, Assistant
                        Administrator for the Far East in the Agency for International Development,
                        visited Taiwan June 4-6.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Believe combination of delay in action on economic assistance programs and
                    emphatic views expressed to senior <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> officials
                    has convinced latter we are seriously concerned at possible adverse effect of
                    military preparedness program on economy and has served to warn them effectively
                    against any future action of this sort without adequate consultation.
                    Postponement of long term Title I<note n="2" xml:id="d117fn2">Reference is to
                        Title I of <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480, the Agricultural Trade
                        Development and Assistance Act (approved July 10, 1954; 68 Stat. (pt. 1)
                        454), as amended.</note> agreement and cutback of program loan also served
                    this purpose.<note n="3" xml:id="d117fn3">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TT1"
                            >Tsiang</persName> called on <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>
                        Administrator <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Fowler Hamilton</persName> on May
                        31 to request an early decision on a pending nonproject (program) loan and a
                        new <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480, Title I agreement. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HF1">Hamilton</persName> told him the increased <gloss
                            target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> military budget necessitated a reappraisal
                        of the basis for aid. Telegram <gloss target="#t_AIDTO1">AIDTO</gloss> 456
                        to Taipei, June 2, summarizes the conversation and states that the
                        nonproject loan authorization was being reduced from $30 to $20 million.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, 811.0093/6-162) A memorandum of the
                        conversation and other related material is in Washington National Records
                        Center, Agency for International Development Files, Administrator Files: Lot
                        286-65-481, China, Nationalist, <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                        1962)</note> Economic Ministers were especially worried; they probably heard
                        <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1">Janow</persName>’s recommendations <pb
                        facs="0281" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> Embassy telegram 921<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d117fn4">In telegram 921, June 5, <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1"
                            >Janow</persName> reported that he had seen the President, Vice
                        President, Foreign Minister, and ministers concerned with economic affairs
                        and he recommended proceeding with the $20 million program loan and in
                        interim <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480 agreement. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, 811.0093/6-562)</note> (i.e., to proceed with reduced
                    program loan and interim Title I agreement) with more relief than dismay. We
                    believe conversations during <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1">Janow</persName> visit
                    and subsequently will strengthen their hand in holding special expenditures down
                    to surtax revenues. They may even be able, with help of our continued prodding,
                    to cut back planned civilian procurement under preparedness program or stretch
                    out into <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1964.</p>
                <p>Re public concern at delay in approval aid program, statements made at <persName
                        corresp="#p_JSJ1">Janow</persName> departure<note n="5" xml:id="d117fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_JSJ1">Janow</persName>’s June 6 statement pledged
                        continuing assistance for the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> economic
                        development program and in it he declared, “I look to Taiwan as one of the
                        success stories of Asia in the postwar years.” (Filed with a June 7
                        memorandum from <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> Executive Secretary
                        Donald B. Easum to <persName corresp="#p_KC1">Kaysen</persName>; <persName
                            corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files,
                        Countries Series, China)</note> supported by interim Title I signing<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d117fn6">Telegram 940 from Taipei, June 9, reported that notes
                        amending the Title I <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480 agreement were
                        exchanged that day. For text of the notes, see <gloss target="#t_TIAS1"
                            >TIAS</gloss> 5090; for text of the agreement they amended, signed at
                        Taipei on April 27, 1962, see 13 <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss>
                        461.</note> did fill psychological need for affirmation US aid continuing as
                    well as promise to meet immediate assistance needs.</p>
                <p>Problem now as we see it is to find ways of continuing to emphasize US concern
                    that adverse effect of military preparedness program on economy be minimized and
                    of inducing <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> to reduce or stretch out future
                    military spending. Situation appears to require coordinated action along three
                    lines: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Re economic assistance we should continue proceed with caution not
                            only to assure that approved programs are in accord with new situation
                            but also to maintain impression that we are not relaxed in accepting
                            non-performance of commitment to restrain defense expenditures and
                            continue to be concerned that expenditures and economic impact be
                            minimized. In this line would suggest no action for time being on
                            long-term Title I agreement, proceeding with deliberation in
                            implementation program loan, and parallel attitude with respect to
                            smaller aid projects.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> review of information provided by
                                <gloss target="#t_MND1">MND</gloss> on special expenditures shows
                            very small proportion of purchases to date are items programmed for
                            future <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> delivery. Action with respect
                            such items and other elements military expenditures will be discussed
                            with Chief <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> on his return from
                            Washington appropriate recommendations made.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We should seek authoritative reaffirmation <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                                >GRC</gloss> still considers valid its commitment to limit military
                            expenditures as specified under 19 <pb facs="0282" n="246"
                                xml:id="pg_246"/> points and that other commitments there stipulated
                            which form basis of accelerated development program must also be
                            honored. In effect this would be a return to the status quo ante after
                            special preparedness program. This might be appropriate topic for
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KAAG1">Kirk</persName> to take up with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang</persName> following review
                            of US attitude regarding special expenditures program and present
                            mainland return prospects.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRN1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Clough</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
