<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-08-07T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-08-07T13:00:00-05:00" n="183" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                        <head>183. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Poland</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d183fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                    Files,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss><gloss target="#t_CHICOM1">CHICOM</gloss>-US. Confidential; Priority;
                                Limit Distribution. Repeated to Taipei, Hong Kong, Stockholm,
                                Moscow, and Geneva and passed to the White House on August
                            8.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Warsaw</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-08-07T20:00:00+02:00">August 7,
                                    1963, 8 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>255. <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> Talks. 116th Meeting. 3 hours, 35
                                minutes.<note n="1" xml:id="d183fn1"><persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> commented and sent recommendations for the
                                next meeting in telegram 258, August 8. Noting that the meeting was
                                the longest in over 4 years, he stated that <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> spoke “at times more
                                emotionally than he has for some time.” (Ibid.) He sent a detailed,
                                apparently verbatim report of the meeting in airgram A-124, August
                                10. (Ibid.)</note> Deptels 138 and 184.<note n="2" xml:id="d183fn2">Telegram 138 to Warsaw, July 26, provided guidance for the meeting
                                on various subjects. Telegram 184, August 3, instructed <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> to urge that <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName>’s side reconsider its public
                                rejection of the test ban treaty. (Both ibid.)</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> opened referring to
                                his Government statement July 31 advocating prohibition nuclear
                                weapons and proposing conference Government Heads all countries<note n="3" xml:id="d183fn3">For text, see <hi rend="italic">Documents
                                        on Disarmament, 1963</hi>, pp. 268-272.</note> and to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CEZE1">Chou En-lai</persName> message
                                delivered me for transmission.<note n="4" xml:id="d183fn4">Reference
                                    is to an August 2 letter from <persName corresp="#p_CEZE1">Chou</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>, identical to letters sent to other
                                    heads of government, which reiterated the proposal set forth in
                                    the Chinese statement of July 31. It was delivered to the
                                    Embassy in Warsaw with an August 2 covering letter from
                                        <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName>. The text was transmitted
                                    in telegram 221 from Warsaw, August 2. (Department of State,
                                    Central Files, <gloss target="#t_DEF1">DEF</gloss> 18-3)</note>
                                Expressed aspiration Chinese people prevent nuclear war. Said he
                                must point out August 5 tripartite test ban treaty goes against
                                aspirations people of world because it can be used by nuclear powers
                                consolidate their nuclear monopoly. It legalizes continued
                                manufacture, transportation, underground testing and use of weapons
                                by US while binding hands of peace-loving countries, denying them
                                adequate means protect selves against nuclear threat. Treaty thereby
                                actually increases hazard of nuclear war and is fraud menacing world
                                peace. Asked how a few nuclear powers could take into own hands
                                serious <pb facs="0415" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> issues affecting
                                human destiny. How can desire of people of whole world be ignored
                                and a few nuclear powers be permitted monopolize everything. Without
                                participation China no major questions in international affairs can
                                be settled in our times. Said President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> had gone out of his way to resume tone and
                                airs of world overlord presuming describe non-nuclear powers as
                                stable or unstable, responsible or irresponsible.<note n="5" xml:id="d183fn5">Reference is to a statement by <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> in a July 26 radio and
                                    television address referring to the danger of nuclear weapons
                                    “in so many hands, in the hands of countries large and small,
                                    stable and unstable, responsible and irresponsible, scattered
                                    throughout the world.” (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the
                                        President of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">John F. Kennedy</persName>, 1963</hi>, p. 604)</note>
                                This was outright imperialistic attitude. Even <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> cannot deny that far from
                                prejudicing nuclear strength of <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>,
                                treaty makes possible carrying on of nuclear race. If US sincere in
                                wanting take first step, should first remove nuclear threat it now
                                possesses by dismantling all overseas bases and reaching an accord
                                establishing nuclear-free zones. Said Chinese Government hoped every
                                government would give favorable response its proposal (<persName corresp="#p_CEZE1">Chou</persName>’s letter) and that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> also will be favorable. Said if we
                                desired consult with Chinese on this question, he was at my disposal
                                any time to enter on this discussion.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said US should remove
                                its nuclear threat to China and the Far East. This threat much felt
                                in China and entire Far East. Spoke of Guam fortifications, units
                                with nuclear weapons in Korea and Taiwan, important cities and
                                hinterland of his country under direct threat of our nuclear forces,
                                air force in Pacific deployed many nuclear-capable planes, attack
                                aircraft carriers and subs with nuclears in Pacific. In short,
                                eastern and southern flanks of China covered by our nuclear weapons
                                and we held maneuvers in adjacent areas with nuclear weapons. Said
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> statement at
                                press conference China determined on war as means bringing about
                                ultimate success<note n="6" xml:id="d183fn6">Reference is to a
                                    statement by <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> at
                                    an August 1 press conference that if in 10 years China still had
                                    700 million people with a Stalinist regime, was still surrounded
                                    by weak countries, still had “a government determined on war as
                                    a means of bringing about its ultimate success,” and was also a
                                    nuclear power, the situation would be potentially more dangerous
                                    than any since the end of World War II. (Ibid., p. 616)</note>
                                was calumny and slander. Said it was only US which relied on nuclear
                                blackmail as means bringing about its own ultimate success.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said he was
                                instructed put forth draft agreed announcement at this meeting
                                designed reduce nuclear threat. Hoped <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would give careful study and consideration. (Text
                                    pouched.)<note n="7" xml:id="d183fn7">It would have declared
                                    that (1) the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and U.S.
                                    Governments would jointly propose the establishment of a
                                    nuclear-free zone in the Asia and Pacific region, including
                                    China, the United States, the Soviet Union, and Japan, and (2)
                                    the U.S. Government would “withdraw all its military bases,
                                    including nuclear bases, from the areas surrounding the People’s
                                    Republic of China, and withdraw all its nuclear weapons and
                                    their means of delivery from these areas.” The text was
                                    transmitted in telegram 259 from Warsaw, August 8. (Department
                                    of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss><gloss target="#t_CHICOM1">CHICOM</gloss>-US)</note></item>
                            <pb facs="0416" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>I handed <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> information
                                six deportee cases paragraph 6 first reference telegram. <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said would study and respond
                                later. Followed with substance paragraph 8 re President’s speech,
                                newsmen, imprisoned Americans, and helicopter personnel.<note n="8" xml:id="d183fn8">Paragraph 8 of telegram 138 to Warsaw
                                    instructed <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> to draw
                                    attention to “misquotes and misinterpretations” in the Chinese
                                    press of President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s June 10 speech calling for “a strategy
                                    of peace.” It also instructed <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> to propose new efforts to relax tensions:
                                    an agreement on exchange of newsmen, release of U.S. nationals
                                    in Chinese prisons, and release of two U.S. Army helicopter
                                    personnel whose aircraft strayed on May 17 into Korean territory
                                    under KPA/CPV control.</note> Also mentioned general incursions
                                south of Korean truce line which scarcely could be assumed not
                                deliberate.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>I spoke at some length on our policy to promote general
                                disarmament, pointing out number of factors on which this complex
                                question must depend.</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>I continued quoting from <gloss target="#t_CHICOM1">ChiCom</gloss>
                                June 14 letter<note n="9" xml:id="d183fn9">Reference is to a June 14
                                    letter from the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party
                                    to the Central Committee of the Soviet Communist Party; for
                                    text, see <hi rend="italic">Peking Review</hi>, vol. VI, No. 25,
                                    pp. 6-22.</note> at some length and saying nothing could be
                                better designed renew vigilance of those wishing retain freedom.
                                Said many people believe there are halting and tentative but
                                nonetheless promising evidences of forces at work which could lead
                                to peaceful and prosperous world as a whole. If great and talented
                                Chinese people not permitted make their contribution in such
                                cooperation, this would constitute one of saddest chapters in
                                history of our times.</item>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>I expressed regret at <gloss target="#t_CHICOM1">ChiCom</gloss>
                                rejection test ban treaty, pointing out its wide acceptance already
                                indicated. Said we earnestly hoped nuclear power would never again
                                be used and have striven since 1946 reach agreement this end.</item>
                            <label>(8)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said he had nothing
                                new to say re newsmen or American prisoners in absence new
                                developments. Said as for missing servicemen in Korea, all such
                                matters whether previous or latest cases are matters between <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> and Korean Peoples Republic, and
                                not appropriate discussion here. Claimed <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> speech had been fully covered by Chinese
                                press. Said they regarded it as important because revealed US
                                strategy in staging fake peace. People of world coming to conclusion
                                US actually has policy of war. Said my quotations June 14 letter
                                represented scientific evaluation social development in world.
                                However change within a given country is for the people to decide
                                and also whether it is to be by peaceful or other means. Returning
                                to test ban, said people of world do not want prevention
                                proliferation nuclear power but prevention nuclear war and complete
                                destruction nuclear weapons. July statement his government designed
                                meet this question.</item>
                            <pb facs="0417" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/>
                            <label>(9)</label>
                            <item>I said our basic policy was seek general and complete disarmament
                                but this was impossible without verification. We had been
                                negotiating on this point at length. Our President’s speech
                                attempted to contribute toward this goal. Said could not reconcile
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName>’s statements today
                                with clear purport June 14 letter, giving examples inconsistencies.
                                Said I hoped <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName>’s
                                statements re peaceful intent represented government policy and June
                                14 letter did not. Spoke further on “first step” aspects test ban
                                treaty.</item>
                            <label>(10)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> spoke at some length
                                on alleged subversive activities against China on part US. Referred
                                again to test ban treaty as “dirty fraud.” Accused US of backing
                                    <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> acts on mainland, saying
                                recently <persName>Chiang</persName> had tried so-called “climax” in
                                activities but plot was thoroughly exposed. Said results had proven
                                his oft-stated warnings in these meetings that our support of
                                    <persName>Chiang</persName> would do no good. In June alone,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CHICOM1">ChiCom</gloss> wiped out six commando
                                groups and shot down P2V. Said we were held answerable for all
                                    <persName>Chiang</persName>’s acts. Said precisely because we
                                ourselves aware of this responsibility that I felt it necessary give
                                him assurance we were not supporting <persName>Chiang</persName> but
                                said our performance hardly supports the assurances given.</item>
                            <label>(11)</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> referred to two cases
                                alleged ramming and sinking Chinese fishing vessels by American
                                ships. First boat belonged to Ningpo Marine Fisheries Co. of
                                Chekiang province. On 15 May 1961 rammed and sunk by SS <hi rend="italic">Letitia Lykes</hi> of Lykes Bros. SS Co., at
                                position 29 degrees 12 minutes north and 123 degrees 15 minutes
                                east. Second boat on 19 September 1962, fishing vessel of Chia Tsu
                                Commune, in Luk Fung county, Kwangtung province, fishing northeast
                                of Chia Tsu port, sunk by SS <hi rend="italic">President Hoover</hi>
                                of American President Line. On 24 September 1962 Chinese gave us
                                message on this matter.<note n="10" xml:id="d183fn10">Telegram 582
                                    from Warsaw, September 24, 1962, reported that <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> had received a letter
                                    from <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> concerning the
                                    latter incident. Telegram 451 to Warsaw, September 26, 1962,
                                    informed <persName corresp="#p_CJM1">Cabot</persName> that the
                                    surviving crew members were being returned to mainland China via
                                    Hong Kong. (Both in Department of State, Central Files,
                                    611.93/9-2462)</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said these cases were
                                result of faulty navigation and US companies therefore should
                                compensate. Hoped we would intervene and hasten results.</item>
                            <label>(12)</label>
                            <item>Refuted charges of intervention and occupation of Taiwan. Said re
                                ship sinkings I was without instructions as far as compensation
                                concerned but wondered whether his side would be interested in
                                general discussion of material claims which each side has against
                                the other. (<persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> did not
                                bite at this.)</item>
                            <label>(13)</label>
                            <item>Had expected propose October 2 for next meeting but <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> said his side very anxious
                                for earlier meeting in order receive response from <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> on proposal joint statement handed
                                me today. After some discussion <pb facs="0418" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> settled on September 11 with my promise if I
                                received word earlier I would get in touch with him.</item>
                            <label>(14)</label>
                            <item>After meeting had adjourned, <persName corresp="#p_WPWB1">Wang</persName> stopped me to ask whether I had had vacation. I
                                said understood he had also. He said he had just come from China
                                where his people were working hard in constructing their country.
                                They had much to do and would never attempt to break out of their
                                own borders into other areas. Said I should not believe newspaper
                                accounts in the US which claimed China was a peril in the Far
                                East.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJM1"><hi rend="strong">Cabot</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>