<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-03-28T19:33:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-03-28T19:33:00-05:00" n="297" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d297">
                        <head>297. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Korea</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d297fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                    Files,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 S KOR. Secret;
                                Operational Immediate; Limit Distribution. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_NCA1">Norred</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_YJA1">Yager</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_REE1">Rice</persName> and in draft with <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> and Richard N.
                                Gardener, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International
                                Organizations Affairs; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>. Repeated to Tokyo and CINPAC for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-03-28T19:33:00-05:00">March 28, 1963, 7:33 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1825. (A) Seoul’s 710 <gloss target="#t_rptd1">rptd</gloss> Tokyo 245,
                                <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> 216;<note n="1" xml:id="d297fn1">In telegram 710 from Seoul, March 25, <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> suggested that Pak was under
                                “heaviest pressure” from his supporters not to reverse his decision
                                for a referendum. <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>
                                doubted he wanted to reverse, but was also sure Pak could not do it
                                even if he wanted to. <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>
                                stated in paragraph 6 of the telegram that he read his instructions
                                to mean that the United States did not find acceptable Pak’s March
                                16 proposal for a referendum, even if Pak and the junta allowed
                                wider latitude for free debate and a reduction of military rule to
                                less than 4 years. <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>
                                considered as the only solution an interim military-civilian
                                government that would act as a transition to full civilian rule.
                                (Ibid.) A copy of telegram 710 was sent by <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName> to the President.
                                (Kennedy Library, President’s Office Files, Countries Series, Korea
                                Security, 1961-1963)</note> (B) Seoul’s 728 <gloss target="#t_rptd1">rptd</gloss> Tokyo 257, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                226;<note n="2" xml:id="d297fn2">In telegram 728 from Seoul, March
                                27, <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> reported on
                                separate conversations with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                Chief of Staff of the Army General Kim Chong-o and Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KCKC1">Kim Chong-so</persName> covering
                                the political impasse between junta and civilian politicians.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> stated that he saw
                                no solution until there were meaningful discussions between the two
                                sides. <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> believed it
                                possible that the situation would “go along in this confused fashion
                                for awhile” with an uncertain outcome. (Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 S KOR)</note> (C)
                            Seoul’s 736 <gloss target="#t_rptd1">rptd</gloss> Tokyo 262, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> 231.<note n="3" xml:id="d297fn3">In telegram 736 from Seoul, March 28, <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> reported on a 2-hour
                                conversation he had with Pak Chong-hui that day. Pak told <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> he was trying to negotiate
                                with the politicians and asked that the United States help him by
                                issuing a public statement in favor of an interim coalition
                                government. <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> believed
                                that the <gloss target="#t_SCNR1">SCNR</gloss> was looking toward
                                such a coalition as a temporary solution. (Ibid.)</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We consider it unwise tie ourselves any particular solution,
                                especially at this time, because: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>We and Korean opposition have good cause be suspicious of
                                        good faith Chairman Pak and his advisors;</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>We do not yet have views of principal opposition
                                        leaders;</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>We are not clear concerning real views of Kim Chong-o and
                                        other service chiefs, despite their public support of Pak’s
                                        March 16 decision.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Our objectives are: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Creation of stable government with sufficient base of
                                        political and popular support;</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Removal of Korean military from political arena;
                                        and</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Maintenance of international support of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>To these ends, we believe transition to civilian government should
                                be effected through elections at earliest practical date. Military
                                    <pb facs="0673" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/> junta is broken by
                                military factional quarrels and probably faces declining stability
                                and popularity. Also, if repeatedly promised elections are not held
                                before 1963 <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> we will have hard
                                time explaining and will run risk of losing much of international
                                support that is vital for <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>We agree you should give no encouragement to compromise on basis
                                of making proposed referendum freer or shortening extension of
                                military rule (para 6 ref A). Under present circumstances, it almost
                                inconceivable any assurances of free political discussion would be
                                fulfilled. Recent suspension political activity and arrest party
                                leaders has created impossible atmosphere for referendum. As for
                                mere shortening period of extension, we consider one or two year
                                extension to have no greater justification and to be basically open
                                to similar objections as four year extension. We do not believe
                                atmosphere for smooth transition to effective civilian government
                                likely improve with only passage of time.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Prime emphasis should continue to be placed on need for genuine
                                consultation by junta with civilian leaders, including necessarily
                                opposition leaders Ho Chong and <persName corresp="#p_YP1">Yun
                                    Po-sun</persName>, who are obviously of greater stature than
                                others on scene. We thoroughly approve your stressing this point in
                                discussing plan for reorganizing <gloss target="#t_SCNR1">SCNR</gloss> with General Kim Chong-o (para 5 ref B).</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>In order to be in better position to bring about meaningful
                                consultation between junta and civilian opposition leaders, you
                                should at earliest opportunity secure directly or indirectly views
                                of major opposition leaders and report them with your
                                recommendations and comment. Although we certainly would not support
                                their arbitrary veto of a reasonable solution, we should be careful
                                not undercut them in dealing with government side, since future
                                government will almost surely sooner or later come from their camp.
                                You should urge them make constructive approach and give junta
                                leaders an honorable way out and assurances as to future role and
                                safety.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>We would find return to February 27 formula thoroughly acceptable
                                and believe best arrangement might be along those lines, if junta
                                and opposition can agree upon it. Idea of compromise by returning to
                                February 27 agreement if “corrupt” politicians withdraw is hard to
                                understand. Who is to decide who is corrupt? You might point out
                                entire political purification concept has been strongly censured
                                outside Korea as well as inside, and ask specifically whether such
                                men as Ho Chong, <persName corresp="#p_YP1">Yun Po-sun</persName>
                                and Kim Pyong-no are judged to be corrupt and if so why. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Despite lack of clarity in this
                                compromise proposal, it should not be rejected out of hand. It might
                                in fact be acceptable if only few second-rank politicians are
                                required to retire. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>We believe it important for you to continue your talks with
                                General Kim Chong-o, since he played part in developing February 27
                                formula <pb facs="0674" n="638" xml:id="pg_638"/> and later opposed
                                martial law and was not consulted regarding extension military rule,
                                and since he is chief figure in group you consider new main military
                                force. As for his ostensible support of junta’s March 16 decision,
                                we do not see how he could realistically be expected to do
                                otherwise. Despite show of military unity on March 22, we have
                                impression factionalism exists in military forces as a whole, that
                                many military strongly believe military should not be involved in
                                politics, and many still hold to long Korean tradition that armed
                                forces do not have internal security role, especially against
                                popular movements.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Although we are skeptical about practicability and durability
                                civil-military combination, we recognize it has some potential as
                                short interim arrangement pending elections. Under such arrangement
                                Chairman Pak should, however, be bound by collegiate action of
                                enlarged <gloss target="#t_SCNR1">SCNR</gloss>, and cease his recent
                                practice of one-man decisions based apparently on advice from
                                outside <gloss target="#t_SCNR1">SCNR</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>At appropriate point, you should let Chairman Pak know that in our
                                view return of <persName corresp="#p_KCKC1">Kim
                                    Chong-p’il</persName> to Korea would be most unfortunate, both
                                in terms of prospects for Korean political stability and
                                international support of <gloss target="#t_ROKG1">ROKG</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Defense concurs.<note n="4" xml:id="d297fn4">Although he agreed
                                    with <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>’s
                                    recommendations and the solution proposed in paragraph 6 of
                                    telegram 710, Meloy stated that his mission charged him with the
                                    security of South Korea and that he was particularly sensitive
                                    to the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Service Chiefs, who
                                    were unequivocal supporters of Pak. <persName corresp="#p_MGGS1">Meloy</persName> stated that the United States could not
                                    afford disunity in the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed
                                    forces. While he approved of the solution of a mixed
                                    civilian-military government—with Pak at its head—as a
                                    transition to full civilian rule, he did not believe political
                                    issues should govern U.S. policy if it resulted in a loss of
                                    faith in the United States by the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> military. (Telegram <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> 50188, to <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FAHD1">Felt</persName>, March 25; ibid.)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD1"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>