<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="42" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                        <head>42. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1" type="from">Kennedy</persName> to President <persName type="to">Chiang</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d42fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/7-1461. Top Secret; Eyes
                                Only. Filed with a covering note of the same date from <persName corresp="#p_SB1">Bromley Smith</persName> of the White House
                                staff to <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName>.
                                Drafted in the White House and revised in the Department of State. A
                                July 11 memorandum from <persName>Bundy</persName> to
                                    <persName>Johnson</persName> states that the draft “responds to
                                the President’s own sense of the situation, as I understand it.”
                                    <persName>Johnson</persName> returned the revised draft with a
                                July 14 memorandum stating that the changes were “relatively minor”
                                and “directed primarily to somewhat cutting back on the making of
                                commitments to <persName>Chiang</persName> and thus preserving our
                                freedom of action.” Both memoranda, together with the draft with
                                handwritten revisions, are ibid., Presidential Correspondence: Lot
                                66 D 204. See also <ref target="#d43">Document
                            43</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-07-14">July 14,
                                    1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: Vice President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> has brought to my attention
                            your thoughtful letter of June ninth,<note n="1" xml:id="d42fn1">In his
                                June 9 letter to <persName>Johnson</persName>,
                                    <persName>Chiang</persName> argued vigorously against the U.S.
                                intention to seek diplomatic ties with Mongolia, declaring that such
                                a move would indicate that the United States was “retreating from
                                principles in the global struggle against world Communism” and would
                                be viewed as paving the way for a “two Chinas” arrangement.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/6-991)</note> and I have
                            decided to reply directly to you myself because to my distress a number
                            of misunderstandings seem to have arisen recently between our two
                            governments. Our countries plainly have so much in common that it is
                            quite intolerable for us to permit any relationship to exist except the
                            kind of closest cooperation and confidence appropriate between old and
                            trusted friends.</p>
                        <p>It seems to me essential for us to resolve outstanding difficulties
                            promptly and work out together suitable courses of action on the many
                            grave problems confronting us at this time. It would of course be most
                            effective if you could yourself come to see me or if I could go to
                            Taipei. The weight of responsibilities on both of us and, indeed, my
                            schedule of official visits here, make this seem impracticable.
                            Therefore, I urge that you send to Washington a fully trusted
                            representative to speak for yourself and your government in talks with
                            me and other American officials concerning the critical decisions we
                            need to take on strategy and tactics in the United Nations this fall. I
                            had looked forward to seeing your son, General <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Chiang Ching-kuo</persName>, anticipating that he
                            would be able to speak frankly and fully for you on these matters on his
                            projected visit to the United States. I would still be delighted to see
                            him if he can come in the near future, but in any case I urge you to
                            designate someone in whom you repose great confidence to come to see me
                            so that we can have the benefit of your considered views. In all these
                            conversations, of course, we would continue to rely for diplomatic
                            advice and guidance on your competent Ambassador, <persName corresp="#p_YGKC1">George Yeh</persName>, who has represented you
                            most skillfully in exchanges of views to date here in Washington.</p>
                        <pb facs="0132" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/>
                        <p>My staff has pointed out to me that some concern was caused in Taipei by
                            the announced decision in principle to grant a visa to
                                <persName>Thomas</persName> Liao. Our view was that he could make
                            less propaganda unfavorable to the Republic of China if he visited the
                            United States without any official attention than if we continued to
                            exclude him. It is of course difficult under our political and legal
                            system to deny entry to anyone without very serious cause. In view of
                            your concern, however, we have instructed our Embassy in Tokyo to
                            withhold his visa for the time being<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">In
                                telegram 214 to Tokyo, July 22. (Ibid., 793.00/7-2261) A July 14
                                memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis
                                    Johnson</persName> to Legal Adviser <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Abram Chayes</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName> stated that the President had decided
                                that “for reasons of national policy” Liao should not be given a
                                visa “at this time.” The memorandum stated that Liao should not be
                                told he had been denied a visa but that his application would remain
                                under active consideration; the purpose was to delay granting a visa
                                but to retain flexibility for future action. (Ibid.,
                                793.00/7-1461)</note> and we will not issue it until we have had
                            further talks with you about the best way to handle the matter. I assure
                            you that Liao will receive no official encouragement or attention from
                            the United States Government nor, of course, any sponsorship of his
                            visit.</p>
                        <p>On the issue of Outer Mongolia, I wish to inform you that the United
                            States Government is merely exploring the possibility that some
                            strategic advantage for the Free World might be gained by sending
                            Western diplomatic representatives to this region between Soviet Russia
                            and Mainland China. We are not committed to this line of action and can
                            of course defer United States recognition indefinitely if that seems
                            wise. Actually our main concern is with the United Nations, where our
                            primary need is to avoid letting the Outer Mongolia issue adversely
                            affect the vote on the much more vital matter of Chinese representation
                            in the United Nations. Our hope is that you can find some way to avoid
                            the necessity of your delegation at the United Nations vetoing the entry
                            of Outer Mongolia to the United Nations. We fear the consequences a veto
                            probably would have on the attitude of the African states which
                            unfortunately seem to have acquiesced in the Soviet linkage of the
                            admission of Mauritania and Outer Mongolia. Working out a reasonable
                            position on this complex matter is one of the main tasks that we should
                            set for ourselves if you can send someone to give us the benefit of your
                            ideas on the subject.</p>
                        <p>On the broader problem of Chinese representation, we must promptly reach
                            a meeting of the minds. We have informally explored a variety of
                            schemes, none of them too satisfactory. We are anxious to get the
                            benefit of your judgment on all of the alternatives. We are convinced
                            that, unfortunately, the moratorium will fail if presented again this
                            fall. We should compare detailed notes on this point, but I am afraid
                            this is likely to be the case. We should consider parliamentary tactics
                            to employ that would insure that the issue comes up in the right context
                            and that it <pb facs="0133" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/> will be considered a
                            substantive rather than a procedural matter. In any case, it is of high
                            importance that your government and mine reach an understanding on the
                            positions most advantageous for us to adopt.</p>
                        <p>I need not remind you that my primary aim is to support the Republic of
                            China in every possible way and to oppose the entry of the Chinese
                            Communists into the United Nations. Vice President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> made these points clear, I
                            know, when he visited you and delivered my letter to you<note n="3" xml:id="d42fn3">Dated May 8; see <ref target="#d26fn3">footnote 3,
                                    Document 26</ref>.</note> a few weeks ago. The key points made
                            in my letter are expressions of the policy of the United States
                            Government and will not change. Our difficulties are in finding ways to
                            carry out those policies in the face of determined enemies and
                            troublemakers. You can help us there by drawing on your long experience
                            in dealing with the Chinese Communists as well as your knowledge of
                            Asian psychology and temperament generally. With a common goal and good
                            understanding we should be able to map a course that will work to the
                            advantage of our two countries.</p>
                        <p>Please let me know your reaction to these views and particularly whether
                            you can send to Washington a plenipotentiary representative or
                            representatives in the near future.<note n="4" xml:id="d42fn4">The
                                letter was transmitted to Taipei in telegram 29, July 14.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/7-1461) Telegram 60 from
                                Taipei, July 19, reported that <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Drumright</persName> had delivered the letter to
                                    <persName>Chiang</persName> on July 18.
                                    <persName>Chiang</persName> expressed pleasure and told
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Drumright</persName> he was thinking
                                of sending Vice President <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Ch’en
                                    Ch’eng</persName> to Washington. (Ibid.,
                            611.93/7-1961)</note></p>
                        <p>With great respect,</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KJF1"><hi rend="strong">John F.
                                        Kennedy</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>