<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>44. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-07-28T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-07-28T12:05:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-28T12:05:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-28T10:00:00-05:00" n="44"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                <head>44. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d44fn0"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                        Security Files, Countries Series, China. Secret. Drafted by Rinden and
                        approved in S on August 8 and by the White House on August 10. According to
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s Appointment Book, other
                        participants were present for part of the discussion, which included
                        Southeast Asia as well as preparations for <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Ch’en
                            Ch’eng</persName>’s visit. (<persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1961-07-28T11:00:00-04:00" to="1961-07-28T13:05:00-04:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">July 28, 1961, 11 a.m.–1:05
                            p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Conference at White House on China Representation at United Nations and
                        Outer Mongolia-United Nations Membership Application</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George W. Ball</persName>, Under Secretary
                        for Economic Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">Walter P. McConaughy</persName>,
                        Assistant Secretary for Far Eastern Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJH1">Harlan Cleveland</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary for International Organization Affairs</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Everett F. Drumright</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, Special
                        Assistant to the President</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt W. Rostow</persName>, Deputy Special
                        Assistant to the President</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Robert W. Komer</persName>, The White
                        House</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Robert W. Rinden</persName>, Acting Director for Chinese
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>With respect to the China representation issue at the United Nations, the
                    Secretary recommended the “important question” device as <pb facs="0136" n="100"
                        xml:id="pg_100"/> the best tactic to use since it offered us a reasonable
                    chance of getting a clear, blocking one-third. In response to the President’s
                    question whether Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName>
                    thought this tactic would get us more votes than the moratorium, the Secretary
                    said that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName> thought
                    that it would. He said that any “two Chinas” proposal was unacceptable to the
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>The President asked about the usefulness of the Swedish proposal for a commission
                    to study the problem and report back to the 17th United Nations General
                    Assembly.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJH1">Cleveland</persName> said that the <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> was allergic to the Swedish proposal because of
                    its fears about the composition of the commission.</p>
                <p>The Secretary thought <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> fears were well founded
                    as the Commission would likely recommend some sort of two Chinas solution.</p>
                <p>The President asked that some variant of the Swedish proposal, acceptable to the
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>, be devised. He said that to use only
                    the “important question” device would be too transparent a blocking measure. It
                    was important, he declared, to formulate a more attractive proposal, apparently
                    moving towards a final solution of the China representation issue. Nigeria and
                    certain other countries would be willing to support us on the China
                    representation issue if we presented a proposal offering suitable rationale.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> said that, in view of United
                    States interest and the damage to the United Nations that might result, the
                    China representation issue was, on its merits, an important question.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that there are governments who recognize Peiping but do not
                    want Peiping in the United Nations. They would vote against United Nations
                    membership for Peiping if they had a justification to use vis-a-vis Peiping. He
                    thought that the proposal for a commission to study the China representation
                    issue might be more attractive to such countries if the commission were also to
                    look into the problem of the allocation of United Nations seats, not just the
                    problem of the China seat. No one, however, he said, would be fooled by whatever
                    device we used.</p>
                <p>In reply to the President’s question as to what Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName> and his USUN colleagues thought about
                    the various proposals, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJH1">Cleveland</persName> said
                    that they seemed to prefer the “successor state” formula. The President was
                    concerned to have Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName>’s
                    agreement on the proposal to be used as he would have to carry the fight in the
                    United Nations.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJH1">Cleveland</persName> said that there was also the
                    timing problem; other countries want to know what we will do before they will
                    decide their position. In response to the President’s query when the United
                    States proposal should be floated, the Secretary said that it should be deferred
                    until after the talks with Premier Ch’en.</p>
                <pb facs="0137" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/>
                <p>The President said that, as the moratorium was impossible, to fight for it would
                    be the ultimate futility. What we must work on now is the “important question”
                    and what to add to it in order to win.</p>
                <p>We must also convince the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> the United States
                    and <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> have a common objective: to keep the
                    Chinese Communists out of the United Nations. We want to give away as little as
                    possible of the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> position in order to attain
                    our common purpose. The <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> must recognize that
                    there is good faith on both sides and that there is no ambiguity in the United
                    States position. If we were defeated on the China representation issue, it would
                    be almost as bad for the United States as the <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                        >GRC</gloss>. Some friendly countries like Nigeria, Pakistan and Great
                    Britain say they can’t vote with us, and Japan says we can’t win. But we can’t
                    allow ourselves to be beaten; we must do what we have to in order to win. The
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> will be asked to give up as little as is
                    essential to winning.</p>
                <p>With respect to Outer Mongolia’s United Nations membership application, the
                    President said the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> must not veto the
                    application. He also indicated that United States recognition of Outer Mongolia
                    should be put aside in the interests of victory on the China representation
                    issue.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that we did not want to organize abstentions to defeat the
                    Outer Mongolian membership application although we and the <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> would abstain. There was the possibility that,
                    in addition to Mauritania, Kuwait and Sierra Leone might also be involved. In
                    any case, if Mauritania was kept out of the United Nations, we would infuriate
                    the Africans and our goose would be cooked.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
