<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>86. Telegram From the Embassy in the Republic of China to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-02-28T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-02-28T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-28T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-28T01:00:00-05:00" n="86"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                <head>86. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Republic of
                        China</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d86fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 793.00/2-2862. Secret; <persName>Roger</persName> Channel. Received
                        at 1:40 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Taipei</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-02-28T14:00:00+08:00">February 28, 1962, 2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>596. For Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>. No doubt you
                    have seen reports transmitted [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text
                        not declassified</hi>] of further approaches made [<hi rend="italic">less
                        than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> on occasion of latter’s recent
                    visit to Taiwan.<note n="1" xml:id="d86fn1">
                        <persName>Bundy</persName>’s message, dated February 24, to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1"
                            >McGeorge Bundy</persName> reported a meeting the previous evening with
                            <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>, in which
                            <persName>Chiang</persName> argued for a counterattack on the mainland.
                        He declared that the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> did not want U.S.
                        participation but “tacit agreement” and perhaps secret or indirect logistic
                        support; <persName>Bundy</persName> was noncommittal and stressed the
                        importance of joint consultations. (Filed with a February 24 covering
                        memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_FGD1">Desmond FitzGerald</persName> of
                        the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> to <persName>Bundy</persName>;
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                        Security Files, Countries Series, China) See the Supplement. A Chinese
                        record of <persName>Bundy</persName>’s conversation with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> and a conversation with
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Chiang Ching-kuo</persName> is summarized in
                        TDCSDB-3/649, 521. (<persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library,
                        National Security Files, Countries Series, China)</note> These proposals by
                    President <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang</persName> and his son are regarded
                    here as a further, more concrete approach to <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                    and as indicating <persName>Chiang</persName>’s desire for consultations at high
                    level and his hopes for US assent to plan he is suggesting or some feasible
                    modification thereof. <persName>Chiang</persName>’s latest approach also
                    suggests quickening of his resolve to “do something about mainland” in months
                    ahead. I have reviewed <persName>Chiang</persName>’s latest approach together
                    with [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>],
                    Commander <gloss target="#t_TDC1">TDC</gloss> and Chief <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss>. There was agreement that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                    must soon take cognizance in one form or another of
                    <persName>Chiang</persName>’s latest suggested plans. It was agreed that best
                    choice of action as of now would be [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of
                        source text not declassified</hi>] to continue discussions. In doing so he
                    should attempt without commitment to obtain specific details of
                        <persName>Chiang</persName>’s latest plans for consideration by US
                    authorities. Once specific plans were obtained, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                        line of source text not declassified</hi>] US military authorities here
                    would study them for feasibility and pass their views to higher US authorities
                    for consideration. Consensus was that in discussing problem with
                        <persName>Chiang</persName> and his son a sympathetic attitude on our part
                    would be desirable as to keep <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> side engaged
                    and thus permit US side to study proposals and submit observations and counter
                    proposals. There was general agreement that cold shouldering or ignoring of
                        <persName>Chiang</persName>’s proposals was least desirable course of action
                    and could lead to undesirable actions and consequences. It was also consensus
                    that in discussing problem further <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> side
                    should be pressed to present concrete intelligence to support its estimates of
                    mainland conditions and possibilities of sparking uprising among people. (In
                    this respect it was concluded that <persName>Chiang</persName> is predicating
                        <pb facs="0223" n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/> his plans of touching off uprising
                    on assumptions rather than realistic intelligence appraisals.)</p>
                <p>In light of foregoing discussion it was agreed [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                        line of source text not declassified</hi>] continue discussions with
                        <persName>Chiang</persName> and his son designed to elicit further concrete
                    details. In doing so [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>] make it clear continuing talks implied no new
                    commitments. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>] also discreetly keep to fore requirement on part of
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> to observe restraints set forth in
                    Mutual Defense Treaty and related agreements.</p>
                <p>Although <persName>Chiang</persName> is quite obviously reluctant to discuss this
                    problem with me, I expect to touch on it when I see him before departing
                        Taiwan.<note n="2" xml:id="d86fn2">Telegram 429 to Taipei, January 23,
                        reported that since <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Drumright</persName> was
                        completing his 4 years of service in Taipei, the Administration had decided
                        to replace him. It instructed him to hold this information closely and
                        stated that he would be informed before the White House announcement so that
                        he could give the Chinese Government 24 hours advance notice. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, 123-<persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Drumright, Everett
                            F.</persName>)</note> I shall [not] accept <persName>Chiang</persName>’s
                    plan in its present form, [but] I would hope that it would be possible for
                    Washington to respond in such way as not to constitute a flat negative.
                    Otherwise, we risk possibility of <persName>Chiang</persName>’s jumping off on
                    his own on some risky adventure.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Drumright</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
