<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                        <head>90. Draft Message From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1" type="from">Kennedy</persName> to the Assistant Secretary of State
                            for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HWA1" type="to">Harriman</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d90fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library,
                                National Security Files, Countries Series, China, Return to
                                Mainland, 1/62-5/62. Secret. Filed with a March 9 covering
                                memorandum from <persName>Bundy</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName> that reads as
                                follows: “This draft has the President’s approval, and, subject to
                                any changes that you may suggest, I hope it may go promptly to
                                Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>.” The
                                source text and the covering memorandum bear no indication of
                                approval or objection and no transmission time. The message was not
                                sent through Department of State channels; it was presumably sent
                                through [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>].</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-03-09">March 9,
                                    1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>In your conversations with Generalissimo, I hope you will make it clear
                            that you come with my full authority and that you and I have discussed
                            together the question of ChiNat return to the mainland. You may want to
                            begin by indicating that you and I have repeatedly shown our own support
                            for <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> and therefore count on full
                            understanding by Generalissimo of our position, as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We continue to assume that all discussions of return to the
                                    mainland are governed by the understanding in the exchange of
                                    notes between U.S. Secretary of State and Chinese Minister of
                                    Foreign Affairs dated December 10, 1954. We know that
                                    understanding on this point has been excellent so far, but we
                                    should never omit straight-forward repetition of it.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>We believe that most careful study is necessary of both
                                    intelligence and operational planning for proposed new venture.
                                    You may draw, if you wish, on the Cuban misadventure as proof of
                                    the dangers of <pb facs="0229" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> bad
                                    intelligence, and of decisions based more on hope than reality.
                                    You should emphasize our insistence on continued detailed study
                                    and exchange of views.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Our earlier approval of 20-man drops<note n="1" xml:id="d90fn1">An unsigned paper, evidently a draft of a
                                        March 30 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, states that a plan developed by
                                        the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>], providing for six 20-man
                                        teams to be airdropped into South China, was approved in the
                                        third week of July 1961 by “a U.S. intragovernmental
                                        committee” (presumably the Special Group) and by the
                                        President. (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss> Files: Lot
                                        65 D 235, <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> Mainland
                                        Recovery, January 1962) <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>’s March 30 memorandum omits this
                                        point but states that the United States had suggested 20-man
                                        probes in mid-1961 in response to <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> plans for 200-300 man airdrops; a few
                                        months later, when preparations were complete, the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> declined to carry out the
                                        probes on the ground that they would be too small to be
                                        useful. (Library of Congress Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>-<persName>Johnson</persName>
                                        Administrations, Subject Files, China) See the
                                        Supplement.</note> was heavily connected with the fact that
                                    we were not involved. 200-man teams with U.S. air support are a
                                    wholly different matter, and while we too will await results of
                                    further study, you should indicate that support for such drops
                                    would be a major shift in policy for us and would have to be
                                    supported by compelling evidence.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>If you concur, you should indicate that it still seems best to us to
                            think in terms of smaller actions which might in themselves increase our
                            knowledge of the possibilities. The smaller the action, and the more
                            completely it is handled by the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>, the
                            more likely our agreement.</p>
                        <p>You should of course make it clear that we would like nothing better than
                            the downfall of the mainland regime, and we are fully aware of the
                            advantages such a change would bring in the whole world situation. But
                            it is one thing to desire a result and quite another to make sound
                            judgment on proposed measures to bring that result about.</p>
                        <p>The more you can learn from the Generalissimo about his precise estimate
                            of the situation, the better, but you should make it clear to him that
                            solid evidence is more interesting to us than eloquently expressed
                            hopes.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>