<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                        <head>97. Memorandum for the Record<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d97fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> Papers, Box 1,
                                China—Planning on Mainland Operations, 3/62. Top Secret. According
                                to <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s Appointment
                                Book, the meeting was held from 10:30 to 11:25 a.m. (Ibid.)
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> describes this
                                meeting briefly in <hi rend="italic">To Move a Nation,</hi> pp.
                                314-315.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-03-31">March 31,
                                    1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>White House Meeting on <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                                Plans</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The meeting was in the Cabinet room. Present were the President, the
                            Secretary, <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Ray Cline</persName>, General Pat
                                <persName corresp="#p_CLGMS1">Carter</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d97fn1">Deputy Director for Central Intelligence Lieutenant
                                General <persName corresp="#p_CLGMS1">Marshall S. Carter</persName>,
                                    <gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>.</note> (who by the way
                            looks pretty good) and Mike Forrestal. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> is out of town. The Secretary began, tossing the
                            ball immediately to <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Ray Cline</persName>.
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Cline</persName>’s presentation focused
                            attention on whether the operation would succeed rather than how we
                            handle the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. Our maps<note n="2" xml:id="d97fn2">Not further identified.</note> came in handy. The
                            Secretary intervened with great vigor and a strong opinion, that this
                            operation just wouldn’t wash, etc., the plan was nonsense, and the idea
                            that we could keep it covert was also nonsense. The <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> hand would show and so would the
                            American hand. I said that the issue really was not whether or not the
                            Chinese Nationalists could get back into the Mainland. They couldn’t.
                            The issue was whether we reject the plan outright or whether we
                            temporize. My fear was that if there were an outright rejection, the
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> would immediately start a public
                            campaign to arouse the China lobby. There was also a great danger in
                            temporizing, i.e., that we get ourselves more and more committed to the
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> in the familiar pattern of the
                            covert operations in Indonesia and Cuba.</p>
                        <pb facs="0241" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, by the way, beforehand
                            was very worried that the Secretary would recommend outright rejection.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> prefers
                            temporizing.</p>
                        <p>The President proposed preparing two C-123’s in the United States.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Ray Cline</persName> said that he had to take
                            back something tangible. The President then suggested that we also train
                            Chinese crews here in the United States in the operation of these
                            planes.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Cline</persName> said that this would be
                            satisfactory.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary agreed providing that the planes were prepared in this
                            country and not sent to Taiwan before a further decision was made.</p>
                        <p>The President said that <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Cline</persName>
                            should make it clear to the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> that no
                            commitment was being made other than to prepare the planes and be
                            willing to consider their use in the light of the intelligence available
                            in October. The President also instructed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Cline</persName> to get a commitment from the
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> that there would be no further
                            public discussion of a return to the Mainland.</p>
                        <p>I suggested that another commitment be obtained to permit American
                            participation in the other planning that the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> was doing.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> made the point very
                            strongly that <persName corresp="#p_CRS1">Ray Cline</persName> was to
                            tell the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> that with the appointment
                            of a new Ambassador the United States intended to transfer to the
                            Ambassador the special role formerly played by the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion of other subjects.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">RH</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>