<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-06-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.569/16</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Netherlands Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">De Graeff</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#left">No. 1595</seg></opener>
                            <p>The Minister of The Netherlands presents his compliments to the
                                Honorable, the Secretary of State and acting upon instructions
                                received from the Minister for Foreign Affairs in The Hague, has the
                                honor to inform him, that the Royal Government having taken
                                cognizance of the draft of a convention to regulate the traffic of
                                alcoholic beverages, proposed to Her by the United States
                                Government, suggests the following modifications in the text of that
                                document.</p>
                            <p>1. The Royal Government proposes to insert in the first paragraph of
                                the Article 2 the words: “hovering off the coasts of the United
                                States” after the word: “flag”, so as to read this paragraph as it
                                was originally drawn up in the draft treaty submitted to the Royal
                                Government by the American Minister at The Hague in November <pb facs="0315" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> 1923. By the insertion of
                                these words the right of boarding, etc. will be limited to those
                                cases whereto the treaty in fact pertains and will not be extended
                                to regular mail steamers in normal course, which if necessary can be
                                examined after their arrival within American territorial waters.</p>
                            <p>2. The wording of the third paragraph of the Article 2 seeming
                                complicated and apt to give rise to controversies the Royal
                                Government recommends the substitution in the paragraph’s first
                                sentence of the words: “at a distance greater than 12 geographical
                                miles (each 1/60 equatorial degree) from the coast of the United
                                States, its territories or possessions” for the words: “at a greater
                                distance from the coast of the United States, its territories or
                                possessions than can be traversed in an hour by the vessel suspected
                                of endeavoring to commit the offense”, and the striking out of the
                                paragraph’s second sentence.</p>
                            <p>In case the United States Government should not be able to agree with
                                this modification, it seems at any rate desirable to add a clause to
                                this article, stipulating that the rights conferred by it can never
                                he exercised at a distance greater than 12 geographical miles from
                                the coast of the United States, its territories or possessions.</p>
                            <p>3. It seems further desirable to make an exception on the stipulation
                                in Article 3 prohibiting the unloading of liquor within the United
                                States, in so far that unloading for transhipment in another
                                Netherland vessel may be possible. The addition to the end of the
                                article 3 of the words: “unloading for transhipment in another
                                Netherland vessel is allowed” is therefore proposed.</p>
                            <p>It be moreover well understood that by “seastores” not only the
                                liquor destined for the use of the crew and the passengers is meant
                                but also the provisions for medical purposes.</p>
                            <p>4. The Royal Government agrees with the provisions of the first part
                                of the Article 4, ruling that claims for compensation will be
                                referred to the joint consideration of two persons nominated for the
                                purpose and that in case no joint report can be agreed upon, these
                                claims shall be submitted to the Permanent Court of Arbitration. The
                                arrangement however prescribed in the second part of this article
                                seems hardly to be acceptable. The latter part of this article is
                                evidently taken from the “special agreement for the submitting to
                                arbitration of pecuniary claims outstanding between Great Britain
                                and the United States” of August 18, 1910.<note n="67" xml:id="d129fn67"><ref target="frus1911#pg_266"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1911, p.
                                    266</ref>.</note> This agreement existing between the Union and
                                the United Kingdom, it is a matter of course that the claims arising
                                eventually from any new agreement concluded between these two Powers
                                be submitted to the same special procedure. As, however, no such a
                                special <pb facs="0316" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> agreement exists
                                between the United States and The Netherlands it will be difficult
                                to the Royal Government to accept the special arrangement, mentioned
                                in the second part of the Article 4, the more so as this arrangement
                                greatly differs from the way generally adopted for settling claims
                                by arbitration and as it does not harmonize with the system adopted
                                in other treaties concluded by the Netherlands. The Royal Government
                                suggests therefore to replace the last part of this article
                                beginning with the words: “All sums of money etc. … [”] by the
                                sentence: “Each Government shall bear its own expenses and half of
                                the expenses of the tribunal”. So the stipulation shall be in
                                harmony with the tenor of the article 57 of the Convention of 1899
                                (Art. 85 of the Convention of 1907),<note n="68" xml:id="d129fn68"><ref target="frus1907p2#pg_1181"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1907, pt. 2, p. 1181</ref>.</note> which
                                article is declared applicable by the Arbitration Convention,
                                concluded between the United States and The Netherlands.<note n="69" xml:id="d129fn69"><ref target="frus1909#pg_442"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 1909, p. 442</ref>.</note> It
                                does further seem unnecessary to exclude the applicability of the
                                articles 53 and 54 of the Convention of 1907. In case the High
                                Contracting Parties might not succeed in agreeing upon a compromise,
                                it is not clear why a solution should not be found in the way
                                prescribed by the aforesaid articles.</p>
                            <p>5. To the opinion of the Royal Government the meaning of the second
                                and subsequent paragraphs of the Article 5 does not seem very clear.
                                According to the letter of these paragraphs a simple denunciation of
                                the convention by one party is not allowed; in case such party
                                wishes to terminate the convention the only way for her is to
                                propose a modification unacceptable for the other party. On the
                                other side each proposed but not accepted modification automatically
                                does terminate the whole convention even in case such modification
                                may not be of such a nature that the party which made the proposal
                                wishes such consequence. It being obvious that this would not be in
                                accordance with the intentions of the United States Government the
                                Royal Government proposes to read these paragraphs as follows: “If
                                neither of the High Contracting Parties has given notice three
                                months before the expiration of the said period of its intention to
                                terminate the treaty, it shall be deemed to be renewed for a further
                                period of a year and so on automatically, each party being free to
                                terminate it by giving notice at least three months before the
                                expiration of each period. If either of the High Contracting Parties
                                has given notice of its desire to terminate the treaty it shall
                                lapse at the end of that period”.</p>
                            <p>6. The Royal Government recommends an exchange of notes at the time
                                of the conclusion of this convention regarding the substitution of
                                the Permanent Court of Arbitration by the Permanent <pb facs="0317" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/> Court of International Justice, in
                                case the United States adhere to the Protocol of the latter
                                Court.</p>
                            <p>7. The Royal Government wishes the convention to be concluded in the
                                English and Dutch languages.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-06-12"><hi rend="italic">June 12, 1924</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>