<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="147" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">150.01/852</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Italian Embassy</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Pro-Memoria</hi></p>
                        <p>Congress is now taking into consideration two important bills on
                            restrictive and selective immigration, one presented by Senator D. A.
                            Reed and the other by representative Albert Johnson; more so a number of
                            other bills and amendments have been presented and <pb facs="0339" n="225" xml:id="pg_225"/> there is every indication that Congress
                            will soon take some final decision with regard to the immigration policy
                            of the United States.</p>
                        <p>The Italian Government has always manifested by words and by action, its
                            sincere desire of cooperating in a friendly way with the Government of
                            the United States in all matters concerning emigration; in venturing
                            therefore to express its point of view on some of the contemplated
                            provisions of law, the Italian Government is animated solely by the
                            desire of avoiding any possible motives of discussion and any eventual
                            difficulties in the practical application of the United States
                            Immigration laws.</p>
                        <p>The principal provisions to be considered are:</p>
                        <p>1) On the 15th of December 1923 the Italian Ambassador has already fully
                            expressed to the Secretary of State<note n="83" xml:id="d147fn83"><hi rend="italic">Pro memoria</hi> printed in H. Rept. 350, 68th
                                Cong., 1st sess., p. 15.</note> his government’s point of view with
                            regard to the question of basing the quota law on the 1890 census; there
                            is no need therefore to go further at present into this matter.</p>
                        <p>2) Some members of Congress have considered, implicitly or explicitly,
                            the opportunity of granting immigration certificates independently from
                            the fact whether passports are obligatory in the country to which the
                            immigrants owe allegiance.</p>
                        <p>This would practically invalidate the sovereign right of the Italian
                            Government to control the emigration of its citizens and interfere with
                            the necessary national measure to safeguard public order and with the
                            regulations relating to passports.</p>
                        <p>If American consular certificates should be issued before the prospective
                            immigrant has obtained an indispensable Italian passport this would
                            doubtlessly lead towards encouraging and facilitating the exit of
                            certain individuals to the departure of whom the Italian authorities may
                            oppose themselves for reasons of public order or on account of
                            unfulfilled military service.</p>
                        <p>3) The issuance of numbered certificates or visa certificates may be an
                            efficient means for maintaining the number of emigrants within the quota
                            limits and of reducing the number of rejections of immigrants from the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>In accordance to the sovereign rights of every state to regulate the
                            admittance of aliens within its territory, the United States government
                            has doubtlessly the faculty to subordinate the admittance of an
                            immigrant to certain requisites and formalities. But the exertion of
                            such right must not come into contrast with the Italian Government’s
                            exclusive right of jurisdiction over its own subjects in Italy.</p>
                        <pb facs="0340" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                        <p>Therefore the American consuls in the fulfilment of their customary
                            functions should not broaden these out with reference to the
                            certificates into an extraordinary investigation that would become a
                            jurisdictional act exceeding the recognized consular functions.</p>
                        <p>The proper selection of immigrants as desired by the United States can
                            only be efficiently accomplished by a friendly cooperation between the
                            United States consular officers and the Italian Authorities, due regard
                            being taken toward the legitimate requirements and the unquestionable
                            prerogative of one and the other country. The Italian Commissariat of
                            Emigration has constantly given proof of its willingness in such
                            direction.</p>
                        <p>4) The Johnson bill contemplates the admittance, extra quota, of
                            children, wives and parents of American citizens, but the Reed bill only
                            grants them a preference in obtaining the visa certificates. There seems
                            to be every good reason to believe that the free admittance into the
                            United States should be a privilege accruing to the family of every
                            citizen through his constitutional right to cohabitate with his wife and
                            children and to be unhampered in the enjoyment of family life.</p>
                        <p>5) The provision of laying the burden of proof on the alien in case of
                            refusal of admittance or of deportation from the United States,
                            contained in both the Reed and the Johnson bills, is in contradiction to
                            the recognized procedure of law the world over; in the original Reed
                            bill N. 2576 it was applicable to all individuals but in the amended
                            bill the word “individual” has been substituted by the word “alien”
                            thereby refusing to aliens an equitable safeguard granted to any
                            citizen.</p>
                        <p>It should also be considered that in accordance to Section 2 (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Reed bill the visa certificate is to be
                            surrendered by the immigrant to the immigration officer at the port of
                            entry so that he finds himself deprived of the most important document
                            with which to prove that he has been lawfully admitted into the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>The Italian Government sincerely hopes that the preceding remarks may be
                            taken into serious consideration by the United States Government with
                            the aim of suggesting such forms in the drafting of the immigration law
                            and regulations as will harmonize the rightful interests and the
                            friendly feelings of their respective countries.<note n="84" xml:id="d147fn84">The Department appears to have made no
                                reply.</note></p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-04-05"><hi rend="italic">April 5, 1924</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>