<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-07-01T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-07-01T21:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">875.01/245: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Albania</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tirana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-07-02T03:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">July 2,
                                        1924—3 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received July 3—10:30
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>62. Department’s 39 of June 24. Greece is the only country which has
                            given unconditional recognition to Fan Noli’s government. The only
                            failure to reply to his direct telegram was by the British Prime
                            Minister. The Greek and Italian representatives have established formal
                            relations with the government, but in the latter case with the
                            reservations previously reported. The Servians will doubtless delay
                            recognition. They are much concerned over the Irredentist influence
                            which is apparent in the new regime, and Ahmed Zogu is at Belgrade. The
                            French express [omission]. The only remaining regent, whose term expires
                            next fall, has gone on indefinite leave, ostensibly for reasons of
                            health, and his functions have been professedly transferred to the Prime
                            Minister who states that there will be no elections before March 1925.
                            Under these circumstances there is no remaining head of the State and
                            the government proposes to start its program of much-needed agrarian and
                            social reform unhampered by a legislative body. There is no, longer any
                            pretension that the government has a legal status under the
                            constitution.</p>
                        <p>I shall not address any formal communications to the Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs. I propose to hand to him impersonal memoranda of important
                            conversations if such action is needed.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grant-Smith</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>