<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in China ( (Mayer) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1924v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-11-06T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-11-06T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-11-06T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-11-06T03:00:00-05:00" n="356"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5710: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-11-06T16:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 6, 1924—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 6—1:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>434. 1. Chinese Government troops yesterday compelled Manchu ex-Emperor and
                    entourage to vacate Forbidden City and they removed to Prince Chun’s palace,
                    where now residing. Today, by orders of the metropolitan police, as I am
                    informed, the streets are beflagged to celebrate the initiation of “a genuine
                    republic.”</p>
                <p>2. British, Netherlands and Japanese Ministers called on Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs yesterday afternoon in relation to subject of ex-Emperor’s safety, Sir
                    Ronald Macleay having called upon Netherlands Minister and expressed opinion
                    that King George would be solicitous for personal safety of the youth who was
                    formerly Emperor of China and with whose family the British Royal Family had
                    been on terms of friendship; Japanese Minister believes that his own sovereign
                    animated by similar sentiments. At this interview British Minister informed Dr.
                    Wang that if harm should befall ex-Emperor the credit reposed in the Chinese
                    Government by foreign powers would be seriously impaired and referred to “terms
                    of favorable treatment” to be given ex-Emperor and Imperial House as embodied in
                    agreement between Chinese Government and ex-Emperor in 1912. See Legation’s
                    despatch number 427, February 13, 1912.<note n="19" xml:id="d356fn19">
                        <ref target="frus1912#pg_65">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1912, p. 65</ref>; the
                        enclosure giving the terms agreed upon with respect to the treatment of the
                        Imperial Family is not printed.</note> Yoshizawa made substantially same
                    remarks, Netherlands Minister saying very little.</p>
                <p>3. Minister for Foreign Affairs replied that agreement had been already revised
                    by Yuan Shih-kai in 1916; that it was now intended to effect another revision in
                    consultation with the ex-Emperor. Dr. Wang stated most positively that the
                    Government would take precautions that no harm should befall ex-Emperor either
                    in respect of his own person or private property.</p>
                <p>4. Belief by credible persons that above action Bolshevik inspired, working
                    through Kuomintang for purpose finally eliminating monarchical restoration and
                    further inciting anti-imperialist feeling and <pb facs="0505" n="391"
                        xml:id="pg_391"/> so anti-foreign feeling. I am reliably informed that C. T.
                    Wang; has seen Karakhan<note n="20" xml:id="d356fn20">Soviet Ambassador in
                        China.</note> daily for past week or two. …</p>
                <p>5. Repeated to Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mayer</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
