<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-03-18T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-03-18T18:00:00-05:00" n="514" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d514">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.053 Sh/23: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-03-18T18:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">March 18,
                                        1924—6 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>56. Legation’s telegram 75 of March 11, 10 a.m. The actual conditions in
                            China seem to give confirmation to the position which was taken
                            generally by the diplomatic corps as indicated by the comments on
                            circular 69 forwarded with Legation’s despatch 1572 of May 30,
                                1923,<note n="45" xml:id="d514fn45">Not printed.</note> that the
                            Government at Peking does not have sufficient control in the vicinity of
                            Shanghai to make it possible for it to offer satisfactory guarantees
                            that it will fulfill any agreements which might result from negotiations
                            for the rendition of the Mixed Court and possibly other matters
                            affecting port of Shanghai. This opinion appears to be given support
                            especially by the passage of an act for a cigarette tax by the
                            Provincial Assembly of Kiangsu and its imposition, imminent if not
                            actual, in spite of your protests.<note n="46" xml:id="d514fn46">For
                                protests against internal taxes, see <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_579"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    579</ref>.</note> Moreover, the widespread disregard which
                            provincial authorities show for treaty rights and the lack of any
                            evidence of a real desire on their part to correct this situation causes
                            the Department to question the advisability of taking action which many
                            elements among the Chinese might interpret as resulting from weakness or
                            as indicating, or being preliminary to, a surrender of extraterritorial
                            rights in the near future. As the reasons given by your colleagues last
                            year for not entering into negotiations seem more cogent now than then,
                            the Department is at a loss to understand their present willingness to
                            do so.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, the Department is not ready to admit that the date for the
                            meeting of the Commission on Extraterritoriality is so indefinite as to
                            bar the hope that that body may make a survey of the status of the Mixed
                            Court.</p>
                        <p>The Department would like to receive your comments regarding the views
                            presented above before it authorizes you to concur in the <pb facs="0640" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/> proposed note of the dean of
                            the diplomatic corps. More complete information is desired with respect
                            to the considerations which seem to make it advisable to concur in the
                            proposed note.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>