<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-10-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="560" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d560">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">693.11171/66</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Report of the Annual Meeting of the Associated
                                American Chambers of Commerce of China, at Shanghai, October 16 and
                                17, 1923</hi><note n="13" xml:id="d560fn13">Transmitted by the
                                consul general at Shanghai with despatch no. 2026, Jan. 14, 1924.
                                The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China consisted of
                                representatives of American Chambers of Commerce at Shanghai,
                                Hankow, Tientsin, Peking, and Harbin.</note></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Shanghai</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" from="1923-10-16" to="1923-10-17" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">October 16 and 17, 1923</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">American Relations with China</hi></p>
                        <p>“America has a definite and well-established policy toward China, based
                            upon the open-door policy of John Hay and the principles of the
                            Nine-Power Treaty adopted at the Washington Conference,<note n="14" xml:id="d560fn14"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_271"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 271</ref>.</note> but the trouble with America’s
                            relations with China at the present time is due principally to the lack
                            of a definite program.” This statement by a prominent American observer
                            of conditions in China summarizes pretty well the general feeling of the
                            American residents <pb facs="0695" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/> of China,
                            whether they are interested in commercial enterprises or
                            missionary-educational work.</p>
                        <p>The resolutions adopted at the annual meeting of the Associated American
                            Chambers of Commerce in China held on October 16, and 17, 1923, in the
                            city of Shanghai do not attempt to outline an American program suitable
                            for coping with the serious situation which has developed in China in
                            recent years. The resolutions do, however, represent the feelings or
                            reactions of the American commercial communities in China in respect to
                            certain matters which we believe should receive the serious attention of
                            our people at home, both in government service and outside.</p>
                        <p>The lack of a definite program on the part of the American Government in
                            respect to China which has been very much in evidence since the close of
                            the Washington Conference, has been nothing short of disastrous to
                            American interests in this country. The uncertainty has prevented the
                            extension of business generally and in the case of firms with branches
                            in the interior of China it has caused withdrawals and losses or
                            depreciation of investment which has been most serious.</p>
                        <p>Practically the same thing applies to American missionary and educational
                            endeavor in the interior of the country. Obviously a country harassed by
                            unrestrained banditry and uncontrolled soldiery offers little
                            opportunity for the efficient conduct of missionary educational work.
                            The American people have probably invested in China an amount of money
                            in missionary-education work which far exceeds the amount which has been
                            invested in business and it obviously is the affair of the American
                            Government to adopt measures for protecting these enterprises as well as
                            the enterprises of business men.</p>
                        <p>It is our hope that these resolutions will be of service to American
                            Governmental officials, chambers of commerce and other bodies in the
                            United States which are interested in China and in a continuance of
                            American effort in this part of the world, as well as a further
                            cementing of the relations of the American and Chinese peoples.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as America took the lead in calling the Washington. Conference
                            and in directing its discussions, it is to be expected that this
                            leadership on the part of the United States is to be maintained,
                            otherwise the prestige which accrued to America as a result of the
                            Washington meeting is likely to be lost.</p>
                        <p rend="center">[<hi rend="smallcaps">Resolutions</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">illegal taxation</hi></p>
                        <p>Various treaties between China and the foreign powers have put a
                            limitation upon the taxation of imported goods, without regard to their
                            nature. Any taxation levied in excess of those provided for in <pb facs="0696" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/> these treaties is therefore a
                            violation of the said treaties. The first exception to this principle
                            appears in the Washington Agreement in the provision that has been made
                            for the levying of a tax on luxuries. It therefore applies that any
                            violation of treaties by the illegal taxation of any article of commerce
                            jeopardises the principle established by treaty and would further
                            establish a precedent which might be extended to all importations.</p>
                        <p>Under the treaties, when goods are imported into China they may be
                            shipped from treaty ports to the interior under transit pass, the
                            payment for which exempts goods from all other taxation. This however,
                            has been a point in dispute between the Chinese Government and foreign
                            powers, the Chinese claiming that when goods reach their destination
                            they are subject to additional taxes. This position has been strongly
                            contested by the various Legations and the maintenance of the spirit of
                            the treaties has been insisted upon although the Government in Peking
                            does not successfully exercise its authority over all the provinces.</p>
                        <p>Under the provisions of the treaties providing for the use of the transit
                            pass the shipper is given the option of either using the transit pass or
                            shipping his goods to the interior without a transit pass, paying
                            instead the local taxes. When the tax is paid by the use of the transit
                            pass the funds are put into the regular Customs revenues which are
                            hypothecated for certain purposes. Taxes paid in this form do not
                            directly reach the provincial Governments or any other branch of the
                            Central Government than the Customs. Certain provinces, however, have
                            fixed the local taxes at such rates as would induce shippers to forward
                            their goods without transit passes thus benefiting the particular
                            locality. The effect of the treaties has therefore been to make the cost
                            of the transit pass the limit of taxation on any article of commerce
                            shipped into the interior. The treaties also provide that trade in the
                            treaty ports be free from taxation so that the only taxes a merchant has
                            to consider are those levied upon his goods when they leave the treaty
                            port. But in spite of treaty obligations and special agreements arrived
                            at between the Chinese Government and several Legations, various
                            provinces have illegally imposed further taxes on certain commodities
                            not only in the interior districts but even in treaty ports. The action
                            of these provinces has been strongly protested by the British and
                            American Legations both to the Peking Government and thru the consulates
                            to the provincial authorities. The Peking authorities have admitted the
                            illegality of the action on the part of the provinces but declare
                            themselves helpless to enforce the rights and obligations created by the
                            treaties and agreements made thru the Legations. But as these violations
                            of the rights of foreign merchants established a precedent which may be
                            followed and extended by military leaders in all sections <pb facs="0697" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> of the country in order to
                            secure funds for the maintenance of their armies: therefore, in view of
                            the action taken at the Washington Conference wherein it is provided
                            that a Special Conference is to be held in China for the purpose of
                            revising China’s customs revenues by the addition of a 2½ percent surtax
                            on ordinary commercial goods and a 5 percent surtax on luxuries, the
                            Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that the
                            American Delegation to the Special Conference in association with the
                            other delegations from the various nations give serious consideration to
                            this matter of illegal taxation before agreeing to China’s request for
                            further increases in the customs tariff.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">disorder in china</hi></p>
                        <p>In view of the long series of outrages in China culminating in the
                            so-called Lincheng Incident of May 5, 1923, which constitute a menace to
                            the lives and property of American citizens and other foreign nationals
                            residing in the country, the Diplomatic Body consisting of official
                            representatives of sixteen nations on August 10, 1923, addressed a
                            formal note of protest to the Chinese Government.<note n="15" xml:id="d560fn15"><ref target="frus1923v01#pg_682"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 682</ref>.</note> This note demanded that the
                            foreign passengers be reimbursed for property losses, for loss of time
                            and injuries sustained and also demanded the punishment of Chinese
                            officials responsible and that proper means be taken at once by the
                            Chinese Government for the protection of travelers and transportation of
                            merchandise on the Chinese Government Railways.</p>
                        <p>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Chinese Government in reply to
                            this note stated among other things that <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The safety of foreigners has always been the subject of very
                                    deep solicitude on the part of the Chinese Government,” and said
                                    further “That through the series of measures recently adopted
                                    the lives, property and interests of foreigners in China will
                                    enjoy added security.”<note n="16" xml:id="d560fn16">For text of
                                        note of Minister of Foreign Affairs, see <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_696"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 696</ref>.</note></p></quote></p>
                        <p>Since this reply of the Chinese Government was written there have been
                            additional bandit and military outrages, one of which in Szechuan
                            province resulted in the murder of two missionaries, and others in Honan
                            and Hupeh provinces resulting in the murder of a Catholic priest, the
                            kidnapping of two women missionaries and the destruction of considerable
                            missionary property. In addition to these incidents there has been
                            frequent firing upon peaceful American cargo and passenger boats on the
                            Upper Yangtsze and in the case of a ship belonging to another foreign
                            nation interested in this trade the vessel was raided by soldiers,
                            several members of <pb facs="0698" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> the crew
                            killed, the chief officers carried into captivity and the cargo
                            destroyed. Lists of these outrages affecting the lives and property
                            interests of American and other foreigners and the Chinese people as
                            well have been compiled by the Associated American Chambers of Commerce
                            of China and are on file at the American Legation in Peking.</p>
                        <p>These outrages are a direct consequence of the condition of military
                            anarchy which has developed in China since the country became a republic
                            in 1911 which matter received the attention of the Washington Conference
                            on February 1, 1922, when a resolution was adopted<note n="17" xml:id="d560fn17">See Resolution <hi rend="smallcaps">x</hi>, <ref target="frus1922v01#pg_295"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    295</ref>.</note> expressing the earnest hope that immediate and
                            effective steps would be taken by China to reduce the military forces
                            and expenditures. This resolution received the signature of the Chinese
                            Delegates as well as those of the delegates representing other nations
                            at the Conference.</p>
                        <p>In spite of the foregoing action of the Washington Conference and the
                            continued protests of foreign governments, the recruiting of troops into
                            the various Chinese armies has steadily continued until the number of
                            soldiers under arms in the country at the present time, according to the
                            1923 edition of the <hi rend="italic">China Year Book</hi>, amounts to
                            1,335,835 [<hi rend="italic">1,332,835</hi>] men, the largest standing
                            army in the world.</p>
                        <p>The inability of the Chinese Government to keep this army paid and under
                            control is the chief cause of unsettled conditions existing in the
                            country. As the authority of the Central Government has broken down
                            through conspiracy and civil war, the army has broken up into provincial
                            units under the control of Military Governors or <hi rend="italic">Tuchuns</hi>. Sections of the army, unable to obtain pay,
                            constantly rebel and become bandits. The bandit gangs in turn terrorize
                            the country, pillaging villages, burning property or menacing the lives
                            of foreigners until they become strong enough to force their way back
                            into some provincial army.</p>
                        <p>This situation of military anarchy which has developed in China
                            constitutes a menace not only to the peace of the Far East, but to the
                            entire world. It is a matter of special and vital interest on the part
                            of the United States on account of our well known policies and trade
                            relations with this part of the world, and especially because of our
                            position of leadership in the calling and deliberations of the
                            Washington Conference.</p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China has always been of
                            the opinion that nothing short of a definite stand on the part of the
                            Powers would be sufficient to bring China’s military dictators to a
                            realization of the obligations of China as a sovereign and independent
                            country among the nations of the world. <pb facs="0699" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> Until such time as the nations which participated
                            in the Washington Conference are prepared to adopt a definite policy in
                            respect to China, it is vital that the United States take steps to
                            secure to American citizens their just treaty rights in China.</p>
                        <p>To this end we feel that at the present time the maximum of protection in
                            China for our interests can only be obtained by increasing our military
                            and naval forces to the strength we are entitled to under treaty rights.
                            This involves the bringing of our military and marine forces stationed
                            in Peking and Tientsin under the Boxer protocol of 1901<note n="18" xml:id="d560fn18"><ref target="frus1901China#pg_312"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901, Appendix
                                    (Affairs in China), p. 312</ref>.</note> up to their full
                            strength, and additions to the China section of the Pacific Fleet and
                            the Yangtsze Patrol Squadron.</p>
                        <p>Both the State and Navy Departments at Washington in correspondence with
                            the American Legation at Peking dated August 6 and 21, 1923, have
                            signified the necessity for immediately increasing our naval force on
                            the Yangtsze River and other navigable streams of China.<note n="19" xml:id="d560fn19">Department’s instruction of Aug. 21, 1923, to the
                                Minister in China, not printed; it transmitted a letter from the
                                Acting Secretary of the Navy dated Aug. 6, 1923, and the
                                Department’s reply dated Aug. 20, 1923, <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_746"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                                    746</ref>–<ref target="frus1923v01#pg_747">747</ref>.</note> It
                            is understood that the Navy Department has put in its estimates for the
                            Budget to be presented to the next session of Congress, a request for
                            the immediate construction of six river patrol boats of special
                            construction for service on the Upper Yangtsze. It has been recommended
                            that these boats be built on the Asiatic station in order to expedite
                            their being put into service and for economy in the cost of
                            construction. The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China
                            desire to go on record as being heartily in favor of these
                            recommendations and urges that Congress give immediate and serious
                            consideration to the proposals.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">need for american owned consular
                                property in china</hi></p>
                        <p>The United States Government maintains consular officials in nineteen
                            different treaty ports in China and with the exception of Shanghai and
                            Amoy has never acquired property for the housing of the consul or office
                            space for the transaction of the official business of the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>In the cases of Shanghai and Amoy where the consular property is owned,
                            the property consists of antiquated residence buildings in a dilapidated
                            condition which have been converted to office use. The condition of
                            these buildings is such that frequent repairs are necessary to keep them
                            in a habitable condition. In all of the other points in China, the
                            American Government follows the shortsighted policy of renting property
                            usually from native landlords and in very few cases is the property
                            suitable for the purpose desired. In Tientsin <pb facs="0700" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> a few years ago, the American Consul was forced to
                            vacate his premises at short notice because the property was desired for
                            other purposes by a Japanese landlord. In the city of Antung, the house
                            occupied by the American Consul in 1923 collapsed during a heavy rain
                            storm and had it not been for the hospitality offered by the
                            Commissioner of the Chinese Customs, the official representative of the
                            United States Government would have had no place to go At one station in
                            South China the house occupied by the American Consul is located on
                            ground so poorly located as to be frequently flooded at high tide. In
                            Hankow the foreign concession where the American Consulate is located
                            has become so congested that it is questionable whether the present
                            lease can be renewed on any terms.</p>
                        <p>The examples above, which are typical of the situation, point to the
                            necessity of the United States Government acquiring its own consular
                            property in China. The present rented property in use at most of the
                            ports is inadequate from the standpoint of efficient conduct of the
                            business of the United States which has grown proportionately with the
                            rapid increase of American interests in this part of the world.
                            America’s share in the direct foreign trade of China has increased from
                            6½ per cent in 1910 to 16.3 per cent in 1922. The amount of money
                            expended for rentals would pay for suitable consular property in a few
                            years and when the rapid increase in property values at all of the
                            Chinese ports is considered, there can be no question of the benefit of
                            property ownership from the standpoint of investment.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the foregoing obvious reasons for the ownership of its own
                            consular property on the part of the United States Government, there is
                            the additional element of prestige which would accrue to America through
                            the ownership of suitable structures for the residences and office
                            requirements of the American consuls. It is difficult for the average
                            Chinese, whose principal knowledge of the United States comes from his
                            acquaintance with the American consul and his surroundings, to
                            understand why America which plays such an important part in the affairs
                            of the Far East, should be so negligent in respect to the housing of its
                            official representatives.</p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that a
                            Government architect be sent to China to make a report and
                            recommendation on the possibility of obtaining suitable land and the
                            construction of buildings at the principal Chinese ports and cities
                            where American consular officials are maintained.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">improvement of diplomatic and consular
                                services</hi></p>
                        <p>There has been before Congress for several years a measure known as the
                            “Rogers Bill” which is intended to improve the consular and <pb facs="0701" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/> diplomatic services of the
                            United States through combining the two services into a unified foreign
                            service.</p>
                        <p>According to the terms of the Rogers Bill provision is made for increases
                            in salaries, travelling expenses, retirement and for promotions in
                            accordance with the abilities of the individual.</p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that the question of improvements in the United
                            States Consular and Diplomatic Services in China have been a frequent
                            source of consideration on the part of this body as well as other
                            American organizations in China the Associated American Chambers of
                            Commerce of China desire to go on record as being in favor of and fully
                            endorsing the Rogers Bill and expresses the hope it may be speedily
                            enacted into law by Congress.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">american policy toward china</hi></p>
                        <p>The Washington Conference which met in Washington on November 12, 1921,
                            while called principally for the purpose of discussing the limitation of
                            naval armament devoted most of its time to a consideration of the
                            problem of China. At the close of the Conference a number of treaties
                            and resolutions were adopted calculated to improve not only the
                            international status of China but also provide a basis for an
                            improvement of the internal situation.</p>
                        <p>In spite of the hopes of the leading statesmen of the world as expressed
                            in the treaties and resolutions of the Washington Conference in respect
                            to China, conditions in this country have deteriorated rather than
                            improved and up to the present the leaders of China have shown an
                            absolute disregard of the obligations of China as a sovereign power
                            among the nations of the world.</p>
                        <p>Owing to the failure of the unanimous ratification of the various
                            treaties and resolutions adopted at the Washington Conference the United
                            States has made no move toward bringing into effect the Washington
                            Conference decisions. In view of the serious situation which has
                            developed in China as a result of the continued serious internal
                            disorder the practical effect has been to damage the prestige of the
                            United States which nation took the lead in the call and deliberations
                            of the Washington Conference. Unless all Governments concerned ratify
                            the Washington Conference treaties without further delay the Associated
                            American Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that the United States
                            Government take up this question with the Governments prepared to adopt
                            a united policy in respect to the protection of their nationals and the
                            general improvement of conditions in this country.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as America took the lead in calling the Washington Conference
                            and in directing its discussions it is to be expected that this
                            leadership on the part of the United States is to be maintained, <pb facs="0702" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/> otherwise the prestige which
                            accrued to America as a result of the Washington Meeting is likely to be
                            lost.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">extraterritoriality</hi></p>
                        <p>In accordance with the terms of a resolution adopted at the Washington
                                Conference<note n="21" xml:id="d560fn21"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_290"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    290</ref>.</note> an international commission of jurists was to
                            visit China within six months after the adjournment of the Conference to
                            report upon the status of extraterritoriality and to make
                            recommendations for improvements.</p>
                        <p>On May 6, 1922,<note n="22" xml:id="d560fn22">According to Department
                                files, this request was made on Apr. 13, 1922; see <ref target="frus1922v01#pg_822"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                                    822</ref>.</note> the Chinese Minister to the United States
                            requested the State Department to postpone the visit of the Commission
                            for a year owing to the desperate political situation existing in China.
                            In view of the fact that the year’s postponement requested by the
                            Chinese Minister has now expired and conditions in China have
                            deteriorated rather than improved it is the opinion of the Associated
                            American Chambers of Commerce of China that any consideration of a
                            revision of the system of extraterritoriality now existing in China
                            should be indefinitely postponed.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">tonnage dues in chinese ports</hi></p>
                        <p>The tonnage dues which China is permitted to charge foreign vessels are
                            based upon treaties between China and other nations beginning with the
                            Tientsin treaty between China and Great Britain signed in 1858. These
                            dues amount to 4 mace (equivalent to 30 cents U. S. currency) per net
                            registered ton on vessels of over 150 tons and 1. mace (equivalent to 8
                            cents U. S. currency) per net registered ton on vessels of 150 tons and
                            under. The dues are levied in a lump sum upon any foreign ship that
                            touches at a Chinese port, and cover a period of four months. These dues
                            are higher than those charged by any other country and were adopted
                            originally more than a half century ago because of the fact that few
                            foreign ships touched Chinese ports and the high dues were necessary to
                            provide funds for the construction and maintenance of light houses, etc.
                            Since these high rates work a handicap upon American shipping not
                            engaged in the coastwise trade of China, the Associated American
                            Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that steps be taken by the
                            United States Government to revise these regulations which have been in
                            effect without change for 64 years.</p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that all
                            foreign vessels be granted the privilege of paying tonnage dues at the
                            rate of 4 mace (equivalent to 30 cents U. S. <pb facs="0703" n="589" xml:id="pg_589"/> currency) per net registered ton and good for a
                            period of 4 months or the privilege of paying tonnage dues at a fair
                            rate per net registered ton per call.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">special tariff conference</hi></p>
                        <p>In accordance with the terms of a treaty adopted at the Washington
                            Conference on February 6, 1922,<note n="23" xml:id="d560fn23"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_282"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    282</ref>.</note> a special conference of the powers is to be
                            held in China to prepare the way for the speedy abolition of likin with
                            a view to levying surtaxes provided for in the treaty, the surtax to be
                            levied at the uniform rate of 2½ per cent ad valorem provided that in
                            case of certain articles of luxury which in the opinion of the special
                            conference can bear a greater increase without unduly impeding trade the
                            total surtax may be increased to but may not exceed 5 percent ad
                            valorem.</p>
                        <p>Although two years have elapsed since the close of the Washington
                            Conference the special Tariff Conference has not been called owing to
                            the non-ratification of the various treaties and resolutions by all of
                            the Powers concerned. In case the various Governments finally ratify the
                            treaties and the special Conference is called, the Associated American
                            Chambers of Commerce of China desire to go on record that any increases
                            granted to China under the Washington Conference treaty be predicated
                            upon the condition that all defaulted foreign obligations be secured out
                            of the increased monies resulting from the revised tariff regulations;
                            it being understood that obligations incurred by the operating
                            departments of the Chinese Government for materials supplied take
                            precedence over all bonded indebtedness.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">exchange of news between united states
                                and china</hi></p>
                        <p>Among the resolutions adopted by this body at its last annual meeting was
                            one urging the importance of a fuller exchange and distribution of
                            American news in this part of the world. Since the passage of this
                            resolution the Federal Telegraph Corporation of San Francisco in
                            association with the Radio Corporation of America has made a contract
                            with the Chinese Government whereby a number of high powered American
                            radio stations are to be constructed in China, the chief one being at
                            Shanghai with feeder stations in the interior.</p>
                        <p>Owing to protests by other foreign interests the work of the American
                            companies in the construction of these radio stations has been seriously
                            retarded. The Chamber heartily approves of the policy of Secretary of
                            State Hughes in upholding American rights in connection with the Federal
                            Telegraph Company’s contract<note n="24" xml:id="d560fn24">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_570">pp. 570</ref>
                                ff.</note> and hopes that his vigorous policy in this connection
                            will be continued.</p>
                        <pb facs="0704" n="590" xml:id="pg_590"/>
                        <p>It is the belief of the Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China
                            that the erection here of a high powered radio station will be of
                            tremendous service in placing China in direct communication with the
                            United States for the exchange not only of news but of commercial
                            messages as well at reasonable rates.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">yangtze patrol force</hi></p>
                        <p>In view of the serious political situation existing along the Yangtze
                            River which constitutes a menace to the lives and property of American
                            citizens engaged in business and missionary activities, the Associated
                            American Chambers of Commerce of China desire to incorporate as a part
                            of this report a pamphlet entitled “For the Protection of American Lives
                            and Property in China,”<note n="25" xml:id="d560fn25">Not
                                printed.</note> which was published on October 1st, 1923 and
                            circulated to members of Congress and other officials of the United
                            States Government and to Chambers of Commerce in the United States.</p>
                        <p>For years the American Chambers of Commerce in China have protested
                            against the frequent changes in American officials assigned to posts in
                            China. The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China desire to
                            repeat this protest and especially emphasize the importance of retaining
                            experienced men in control of the Yangtze Patrol. In the past the policy
                            of the United States has been to send naval officers to this post and as
                            soon as they became familiar with conditions and have made connections
                            with Chinese officials transfer them to other posts. This has had an
                            unfortunate effect upon American prestige and has militated against the
                            development of a definite and continuing American policy on the Yangtze.
                            It is therefore recommended that experienced men be retained in this
                            work as well as in other lines of American Governmental activity in this
                            part of the world.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">representation at washington</hi></p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China realize that more
                            suitable action may be obtained on matters pertaining to China and the
                            Far East, affecting American business and interests generally, if the
                            Associated Chambers were directly represented at Washington. It is
                            therefore recommended that arrangements be made at once to appoint a
                            resident representative of the Associated American Chambers of Commerce
                            of China at Washington who shall be empowered to give publicity to all
                            matters which may be referred to him from time to time, to enlist the
                            aid of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States of America,
                            Government officials and departments <pb facs="0705" n="591" xml:id="pg_591"/> and commercial and other organizations interested
                            in the various subjects referred to him for attention.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">payment of claims against the chinese
                                government</hi></p>
                        <p>As a result of the disorder which has existed in China for many years
                            American interests have suffered greatly by the loss or destruction of
                            property resulting from bandit outrages, uncontrolled soldiery and
                            internal fighting.</p>
                        <p>Claims covering these losses have been on file at the various consulates
                            and the Legation in Peking for years with no settlement being made by
                            the Chinese Government.</p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China recommend that
                            these claims be brought forward by the American authorities at the
                            special conference and that the American Delegation, be instructed to
                            insist upon payment of these claims before agreement is given to the
                            revision of the Customs Tariff.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">publicity campaign in america</hi></p>
                        <p>Owing to the fact that foreign trade occupies such a small portion of the
                            interest or activities of the American people generally, it is always
                            difficult to induce the American Government to adopt constructive and
                            continuing policies in foreign affairs and especially in respect to
                            American interests in this part of the world. The lack of familiarity on
                            the part of many of the officials at Washington in respect to the
                            protection of the lives and property of its own citizens not to mention
                            the larger diplomatic and strategic interests of America in the Far East
                            has made it necessary for American citizens both individually and
                            through their organizations to frequently conduct publicity campaigns in
                            the United States. Such publicity campaigns in the past, although
                            largely unorganized, have nevertheless been of considerable benefit in
                            concentrating the attention of the American people and through them of
                            the government upon particular problems affecting the interests of
                            Americans in this part of the world.</p>
                        <p>In view of the serious situation now existing in China which
                            constitute[s] a menace to the lives and interests of American citizens
                            residing in the Chinese Republic, it is recommended that the Associated
                            American Chambers of Commerce of China give this subject special
                            attention and that a special committee be appointed to work out in
                            cooperation with other American organizations, a definite publicity
                            campaign calculated to bring to the attention of the American people,
                            members of Congress and other officials of our government the necessity
                            of a definite policy in respect to the present situation of China.</p>
                        <pb facs="0706" n="592" xml:id="pg_592"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">the boxer indemnity</hi></p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that Congress has not yet taken action in respect to
                            the disposition of the unexpended balance of the American share of the
                            Boxer Indemnity amounting to approximately fifteen million gold dollars,
                            it was decided that it would not be in accordance with traditional
                            American policy toward China for the United States Government to
                            withhold payment of this money on account of the present default on the
                            part of the Chinese Government of American loans or obligations for
                            materials purchased by the Chinese Government Railways and other
                            departments.</p>
                        <p>In view of the great number of proposals which have been placed before
                            this body covering possible uses for this money it was decided that the
                            Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China should take no action
                            on this subject at the present time.</p>
                        <p>The Associated American Chambers of Commerce of China are of the opinion
                            however that any expenditure for educational or other purposes in China
                            should be closely supervised by an American committee composed of
                            representatives of the United States diplomatic or consular services and
                            of the American business and missionary organizations in China.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">american income tax</hi></p>
                        <p>American Chambers of Commerce in London, Paris, Mexico City, Buenos
                            Aires, Manila and elsewhere representing American commercial interests
                            engaged in foreign trade have for many years agitated against the
                            injustice of the United States Government enforcing its domestic income
                            tax regulations upon Americans residing abroad who derive their income
                            from non-American sources.</p>
                        <p>The American Chamber of Commerce (Shanghai) after an agitation lasting
                            over several years was able to obtain the passage by Congress of a
                            measure known as the China Trade Act<note n="26" xml:id="d560fn26">Of
                                1922; 42 Stat. 849.</note> which exempts American companies
                            registered under the Act from the operation of the domestic income and
                            excess profits taxes but was unable to obtain an exemption of American
                            citizens generally from the domestic personal income taxes.</p>
                        <p>The provision in the Revenue Bill passed by Congress in 1921 intended to
                            exempt Americans residing in the Far East including the Philippine
                            Islands, and China was stricken from the bill when it went to conference
                            before final passage.</p>
                        <p>There are approximately 240,000 foreigners residing in China of which
                            number about 9,000 are Americans. Americans are the only foreigners who
                            are required by their home Government to pay income <pb facs="0707" n="593" xml:id="pg_593"/> taxes upon income derived from activities
                            in this part of the world and entirely outside of the United States.</p>
                        <p>The handicap which this places upon the American citizen in his
                            competition with the British, Japanese, French, Germans and other
                            foreigners interested in foreign trade in this part of the world is
                            self-evident. Governor-General Leonard Wood of the Philippine Islands
                            has well stated the case in letters and cables to the Secretary of War
                            and to the President of the United States dated September 7 and 8, 1923.
                            In these communications Governor-General Wood said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Filipinos and foreign residents of the Philippine Islands,
                                    business competitors of Americans, are exempt from Federal
                                    income tax paying only local taxes which are very much lower.
                                    Resulting discrimination against Americans on an outpost of our
                                    foreign commerce is grossly unjust.—British subjects abroad have
                                    never been subjected to British taxation on income derived from
                                    sources outside of Great Britain. By the Finance Act of 1920
                                    Great Britain has even gone to the extent of refunding to
                                    overseas British subjects taxes heretofore levied on income
                                    derived solely from British sources. Relief on the part of
                                    Congress would greatly facilitate the general efforts to build
                                    up our foreign trade now seriously interfered with by subjecting
                                    it here and elsewhere abroad to the handicap of heavier income
                                    taxes than those paid by foreign competitors. … I feel very
                                    strongly that the least the home Government can do is to give a
                                    considerate hearing to the American business men of this
                                    community in order that all the facts may be before you before
                                    definite action is taken.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>The situation affecting Americans interested in business and other
                            activities in China is exactly the same as the situation outlined by
                            Governor-General Wood in the Philippines. All foreigners residing in
                            China are subject to certain municipal and other taxes in the
                            communities wherein they live but it is only the Americans residing in
                            China who are subjected by their home Government to all of the domestic
                            taxes of the United States even though the incomes are derived from
                            sources entirely outside of the United States.</p>
                        <p>In view of the above factors the Associated American Chambers of Commerce
                            of China desire to approve of the action of other American Chambers of
                            Commerce in various parts of the world, and especially the action of the
                            American Chamber of Commerce of the Philippine Islands, as well as the
                            action of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States of America to the
                            effect that Congress in framing the next Revenue Bill may exempt
                            Americans residing overseas and deriving their income from non-American
                            sources from the operation of our domestic income tax law.</p>
                        <pb facs="0708" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">unpaid accounts for materials supplied
                                to the Chinese government railways and other services</hi></p>
                        <p>With regard to the obligations of the Chinese Government Railways the
                            United States Government has adopted the position that obligations for
                            materials supplied to the Chinese Government Railways “constitute a part
                            of the operating expenses of the railways, and as such should be met
                            before any charges on the surplus revenues are provided for, or before,
                            in fact, it can be said that any surplus exists” or in other words,
                            “that such obligations for equipment become a part of the operating
                            expenses of the railways and as such form a prior lien on the actual
                            earnings of the railways before any surplus can be said to exist,” which
                            position was transmitted to the Chinese Government by the American
                            Minister in his notes No. 168, May 18, 1922,<note n="27" xml:id="d560fn27">Not printed.</note> and No. 219, July 7 [<hi rend="italic">8</hi>], 1922.<note n="27" xml:id="d560fn28">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>On September 27, 1923, the American Minister, in his note No. 627,<note n="27" xml:id="d560fn29">Not printed.</note> addressed to the
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs, called attention to the fact that although
                            almost a year had elapsed no reply had been received, covering the
                            principle outlined above to the effect that “obligations for the payment
                            of equipment become a part of the operating expenses of the railways and
                            as such form a prior lien on the actual earnings of the railways before
                            any surplus can be said to exist for the payment of bonded
                            indebtedness.” To this note an answer has been received which entirely
                            ignores the point at issue.</p>
                        <p>In view of this continued disregard of the rights of American creditors
                            of the Chinese Government, the Associated American Chambers of Commerce
                            of China urge that the State Department instruct the American Minister
                            to bring more pressure on the Chinese Government and that he insist that
                            immediate arrangements be made to meet the obligations incurred by the
                            Chinese Government Railways for materials supplied.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>