<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-12-05T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-12-05T16:00:00-05:00" n="59" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">511.4 A 2/178: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Tuck</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-12-05T16:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">December 5,
                                        1924—4 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>Your December 4, 11 A.M. For Porter.</p>
                        <p>The Department has received an <hi rend="italic">Aide Mémoire</hi> from
                            the British Embassy at Washington dated December 3, reading as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The American Delegation to the Second Opium Conference which is
                                    now proceeding at Geneva have submitted a number of proposals
                                    including two which the British Delegate considers to be outside
                                    the scope of the Conference.</p>
                                <p>The object of the Conference is to consider measures to limit—(1)
                                    the manufacture of morphine, heroin, cocaine, etc., (2) the
                                    amounts of raw opium and coca leaf to be imported for
                                    manufacture and for other medicinal and scientific purposes and
                                    (3) the production of raw opium and coca leaf for export to the
                                    amount required for medicinal and scientific purposes.</p>
                                <p>The American proposals in question are—(1) that the contracting
                                    parties shall control the production and distribution of raw
                                    opium so that there will be no surplus available for purposes
                                    not strictly medical or scientific; and (2) that the contracting
                                    parties, in whose territories the use of prepared opium is
                                    temporarily permitted, shall agree to reduce the importation by
                                    10 per cent each year so as to bring the use of opium to an end
                                    within 10 years.</p>
                                <p>Of these proposals the first raises questions of domestic
                                    consumption in India and His Majesty’s Government fear that
                                    unless it is withdrawn a difficult situation will arise. The
                                    question will be raised whether the Conference is competent to
                                    discuss a matter not specified on the agenda and the decision
                                    taken on this point will have a bearing on the second American
                                    proposal above referred to.</p>
                                <p>If the American delegates bring forward their second proposal the
                                    course of the proceedings at the Conference will probably be as
                                    follows: The Netherlands Delegation will refuse to take part in
                                    the discussion and some of the other Powers with Far Eastern
                                    territories, if not all, will do the same. The British Delegate
                                    will take the line that the matter is outside the scope of the
                                    Conference and that it was considered by the first Conference
                                    (on the control of opium smoking in the Far East) which reached
                                    an agreement as to the further measures to be taken. The
                                    position in British territories was then fully set out and,
                                    apart from the question as to the competence <pb facs="0231" n="117" xml:id="pg_117"/> of the Conference, no useful
                                    purpose will be served by re-opening the matter.</p>
                                <p>The British Delegate will then propose that the Council of the
                                    League of Nations should be invited to appoint a small impartial
                                    Commission with an American Chairman to visit the territories
                                    concerned of all nationalities as well as any other countries,
                                    such as China, that may be necessary in order to investigate and
                                    report on all relevant facts as affecting further measures of
                                    repression. In the opinion of His Majesty’s Government this
                                    Commission should include no nationals of Powers possessing Far
                                    Eastern territories.</p>
                                <p>His Majesty’s Government feel that the adoption of this proposal
                                    would disarm criticism in the United States, where British
                                    administrative difficulties in the Far East are naturally not
                                    widely known, and would also convince public opinion generally
                                    that His Majesty’s Government neither shirk impartial
                                    investigation nor desire to take up an obstructive attitude.</p>
                                <p>In the circumstances His Majesty’s Government hope that the above
                                    proposal will be acceptable to the United States Government and
                                    that they will be disposed to instruct the American Delegation
                                    at Geneva to co-operate with the British Delegate when he puts
                                    it forward, with a view to its being carried into
                                effect.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>The Department proposes to reply to the British that in view of the
                            conditions set forth in the preamble of the House Joint Resolution
                            approved May 15, 1924, authorizing an appropriation for the
                            participation of this Government in the International Narcotics
                            Conference, and in view of the further fact that the representatives of
                            the United States are not authorized to sign any agreement which does
                            not fulfill the conditions Decessary for the suppression of the
                            habit-forming narcotic drug traffic, as set forth in the preamble of the
                            Joint Resolution in question, it finds itself unable to acquiesce in the
                            suggestions made by the British Government as set forth in the <hi rend="italic">Aide Mémoire</hi>. The Department may further suggest
                            to the British that since all the other participating Governments in the
                            Geneva Conference are likewise interested in the questions at issue, it
                            would perhaps be better to have the questions determined by the
                            Conference itself.</p>
                        <p>The Department is hopeful that no issues will arise at Geneva which will
                            jeopardize the success of the Conference and with that in mind it
                            suggests that you may find it advisable not to rigidly adhere to a fixed
                            term of 10 years within which the importation of raw opium for the
                            purpose of making prepared opium should be discontinued. The Department
                            feels that some flexibility in this period of time might afford an
                            avenue through which a compromise might be reached if the differences
                            foreseen by the British Government, as set forth in its <hi rend="italic">Aide Mémoire</hi>, should arise.</p>
                        <p>The Department desires your comment on the <hi rend="italic">Aide
                                Mémoire</hi> and the proposed reply.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>