<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Van Valkenburgh to to Mr. Seward.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1868p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="314"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d314">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Van Valkenburgh</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward.</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 14.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hiogo,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-03-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1, 1868.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I had the honor, in my No. 13, to inform you of a
                    rumor that the Tycoon had abdicated, and that the Prince of Kiusiu had been
                    named as his successor as the head of the Tokugawa family; that Mr. Roches, the
                    French minister, had returned to this port, but whether to resume his position
                    or <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to France, I was not then aware. On
                    yesterday, the 29th of February, the foreign representatives held a conference,
                    at which he was present. He announced his determination to resume his functions
                    and delay his departure, having received, by the last mail which reached
                    Yokohama during his recent stay there, instructions from his government to
                    remain until his successor arrived. He held conferences with the Tycoon while at
                    Yedo, on the 12th and 19th February. The Tycoon in the first interview declared
                    his intention of submitting to the will of the Mikado; but at the same time
                    denying his right to invade or deprive him of his possessions as the head of the
                    Tokugawa family, insisting upon protecting them to the utmost. At the same time
                    he repeated the history of this struggle as I have attempted to give it in my
                    previous dispatches, and alleged that the Mikado was in duress and not acting of
                    his own free will. On the second interview he informed Mr. Roches that he had
                    abdicated and that the Prince of Kiusiu, a boy of about seventeen years of age,
                    was his successor as head of his family; that he, the late Tycoon, would act for
                    the prince, and be the manager of his affairs; that it was intended only to
                    protect their patrimonial estates and no further than that, to carry on the war
                    against the Mikado.</p>
                <p>This abdication was promulgated at Yedo on the 19th February, but as yet we have
                    received no official notice of it. I trust this act, by which Japan is left
                    without a Tycoon, and with but a single government, that of the Mikado, will
                    result in peace; but it is difficult to say, there are so many discordant
                    elements and separate interests, that dissensions and strifes may yet
                    continue.</p>
                <p>I inclose, marked No. 1, copy of Mr. Roches’ letter, announcing his return, which
                    was received by me late last night.</p>
                <p>Yesterday, Date Iyo No Kami, one of the officers charged with the conduct of
                    foreign affairs, arrived from Kioto and paid me a visit of ceremony. He arranged
                    for a business conference for to-day, at one o’clock, with all the foreign
                    representatives, and it is just concluded. He said to us that the officer
                    ordering the fire upon foreigners on the 4th instant had been examined and found
                    guilty of a grievous offense, and been sentenced to death, and that to-morrow
                    had been assigned as the day of execution. That we should also receive to-morrow
                    the <pb facs="0728" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/> apology from the Mikado’s
                    government. We then arranged to go to Osaka on Thursday, the 5th instant, reopen
                    our legations for a short time, and return to Yokohama. The Costa Rica mail
                    closes in a few moments, and I have no further time to write.</p>
                <p>From Nagasaki I hear all is quiet. The new governor of that port, appointed by
                    the Mikado, sails to-morrow for that place. I inclose copies of two official
                    communications received by me yesterday from the United States consul there,
                    marked Nos. 2 and 3.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R. B. VAN VALKENBURGH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kobé,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-02-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 29, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir and Dear Colleague:</hi> I had the honor to inform
                        you, by my letter of the ninth February, for what motives I thought it
                        necessary, without separating the action of France from the collective
                        action of the foreign representatives, to leave Hiogo and return to
                        Yokohama.</p>
                    <p>During the few days that I have passed at Yokohama and at Yedo I have
                        convinced myself that it was more convenient and in the interests of my
                        government that I returned to you and communicated to you the information
                        and impressions I had collected. Acting like this, I had thought that even
                        my absence might be useful for the general interests we represent in Japan,
                        and that to the gratification of giving you this information would be added
                        the one of informing you personally of the state of things, and of one of
                        the phases of our present situation, as well as to recommence with you the
                        community of views and work which has been so happily maintained by the
                        Baron Brin.</p>
                    <p>I am happy to approve everything which Baron Brin has done in conjunction
                        with you, and to thank you for the help you have lent him during the
                        interview I had charged him with. I have, therefore, only to felicitate
                        myself for having left and having returned.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, and dear colleague, with assurances of my consideration,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>LEON ROCHES.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency General <hi rend="smallcaps">Van Valkenburgh</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Minister Resident of the United States of
                                America.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 22.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Nagasaki,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-02-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> By her Britanic Majesty’s ship Adventure,
                        which leaves here very shortly for Hiogo, I hasten to give you some
                        information concerning the situation of affairs at this port.</p>
                    <p>Considerable excitement has existed here during the last week, in consequence
                        of the news received from Osaka of the defeat of the forces of the Tycoon by
                        those of Satsuma and other princes.</p>
                    <p>The governor of the port, Kawaza Izu No Kami, finding he had not a sufficient
                        force at his command to hold the place in the event of an attack being made
                        by the men of Satsuma, Tosa, and other Daimios hostile to the Tycoon’s
                        government, considered it prudent to resign his authority here, and on the
                        eighth instant left for Yokohama in the steamer Courier, accompanied by all
                        the Yedo officials who had been connected with him in the management of
                        aifairs at this port. When on the point of leaving he addressed a letter to
                        each of the consuls of the treaty powers, stating that he had left the city
                        of Nagasaki under the protection of the Princes Hiziu and Chickuzen,
                        according to previous instructions from his government. His hurried
                        departure was doubtless owing to his having received information the night
                        before that his house would be attacked and burnt during the night by a
                        number of Rouins, about eighty, said to be in town. It was also reported
                        that the foreign settlement would probably be attacked and the custom-house
                        and bonded warehouse fired; consequently an armed force from the Shenandoah
                        and two English naval vessels in port was landed for their protection. No
                        attack, however, was made, though we learned on the following day that
                        Tosa’s <pb facs="0729" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"/> men took possession of the
                        governor’s house during the night, but found the governor had already left.
                        The agents here of different Daimois, fourteen in number, the most prominent
                        ones being Hiziu, Chickuzen, Satsuma, and Tosa, on the day of the governor’s
                        departure notified the foreign consuls that pending the appointment of a
                        governor for this port by the Mikado they had assumed control of affairs
                        here, and all business would be transacted by themselves in conjunction with
                        the local officers; and at an interview just had with them they assured us
                        that no action would be taken on their part to endanger the lives and
                        property of foreigners, but that their interests would be properly cared
                        for. I have therefore adopted the course pursued by my colleagues, with the
                        exception of the French consul, who refuses to recognize any one but the
                        Princes of Hiziu and Chickuzen, and recognized these agents as constituting
                        the government <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> at this port, and trust that
                        by doing so my action will meet with your approval.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. L. MOORE, <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Gen. <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Van Vankenburgh</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >United States Minister Resident in Japan, Hiogo.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 25.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Nagasaki,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-02-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 20, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt,
                        on the twelfth instant, of your dispatches, Nos. 20, 26, and 28, all
                        relating to the disturbances at Osaka, and instructing me how to act should
                        war occur at this port between the contending factions.</p>
                    <p>My dispatch No. 22, of the eleventh instant, will acquaint you with all that
                        has transpired here up to that date, since when the excitement has entirely
                        subsided; the business of the port, both native and foreign, is being
                        conducted as usual, and foreigners visit the native city without being
                        molested, though the number of two-sworded men in town has considerably
                        increased of late.</p>
                    <p>Although the princes’ agents, now in authority, have so far conducted matters
                        satisfactorily, yet it is very desirable that a governor be sent here as
                        soon as possible, as nearly all of them are largely indebted to foreigners,
                        and as long as they have control here it will be a difficult matter to
                        obtain a settlement with them. Claims to a considerable amount against
                        several of them were some time ago forwarded by me to the late governor, but
                        they still remain unsettled.</p>
                    <p>I have not yet been able to communicate with our consul at Hakodadi, as
                        requested by you, no opportunity having lately offered for that port.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. L. MOORE, <hi rend="italic">United States Vice-Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Gen. <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. Van Vankenburgh</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >United States Minister Resident in Japan, Hiogo.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
