<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to  to Mr.
                                Moran</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1868p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675" lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-06-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="84" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Moran</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 14.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-06-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 22, 1868,</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The correspondence recorded in your
                            legation is full of remonstrances and expostulations, which, by the
                            President’s direction, I have addressed to her Majesty’s government
                            against the imprisonment of Messrs. Warren and Costello.</p>
                <p>The reasons have been fully and frequently assigned why the judicial
                            severity maintained by the British government in these cases has tended
                            to embarrass the friendly relations between the two countries, and to
                            protract the political excitement which has so greatly disturbed the
                            peace of the British realm and of the British provinces adjacent to the
                            United States. On many occasions I have had the honor to urge upon <pb facs="0367" n="319" xml:id="pg_319"/> the British government the
                            necessity of a modification of the laws of the British realm in the case
                            of subjects of Great Britain who have become citizens of the United
                            States under our naturalization laws.</p>
                <p>By the President’s direction, also, I have with much urgency invited the
                            British government to enter into an equal treaty with the United States
                            on that subject, as a proceeding which is essential for the removal of
                            discontents which, if suffered to continue, might involve the two
                            nations in reprisal or war. Hitherto these proceedings have been
                            unfruitful, although we have many friendly assurances of a favorable
                            disposition on the part of the British government.</p>
                <p>In connection with this matter, the President now makes it my duty to
                            give you a copy of a resolution of the House of Representatives of the
                            United States, which was passed on the 15th of June, “requesting the
                            President to take such measures as shall appear proper to secure the
                            release from imprisonment of Messrs. Warren and Costello, convicted and
                            sentenced in Great Britain for words and acts spoken and done in this
                            country, by ignoring our naturalization laws, and to take such other
                            measures as will secure their return to our flag with such ceremonies as
                            are appropriate to the occasion.”</p>
                <p>I further call your attention to the fact that a bill which has passed
                            the House of Representatives is now engaging the attention of the
                            Senate, the effect of which bill, if it shall become a law, will be to
                            require the President to make reprisals in cases of judicial denial in
                            Great Britain to naturalized Americans of the rights which are conceded
                            thereto native American citizens.</p>
                <p>You will be expected to read the resolution referred to, together with
                            this instruction to her Majesty’s principal secretary of state for
                            foreign affairs, and to give him a copy of these papers if he shall
                            request it.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Benjamin Moran</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Fortieth Congress, Second Session–Congress of the United
                                States.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">In the House of
                                            Representatives,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-06-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 15, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>On motion of Mr. Robinson,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved,</hi> That the President of the United
                                States is hereby requested by this House to take such measures as
                                shall appear proper to secure the release from imprisonment of
                                Messrs. Warren and Costello, convicted and sentenced in Great
                                Britain for words and acts spoken and done in this country, by
                                ignoring our naturalization laws, and to take such other measures as
                                will secure their return to our flag, with such ceremonies as are
                                appropriate to the occasion.</p>
                    <p>Attest:</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>EWD. McPHERSON, <hi rend="italic">clerk.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
