<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>198. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in Saudi
                    Arabia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-12-13T18:57:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-12-13T18:57:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-12-13T18:57:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-12-13T18:57:00-05:00" n="198"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                <head>198. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Saudi Arabia</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 780.022/12–1355. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                            >Newsom</persName> and approved and signed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>. Repeated to London. According to
                            <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName>, in an audience with
                            <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1">Faisal</persName> on December 24, the
                        Prince asked the Ambassador about new developments in the Buraimi matter.
                            <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> replied by reading the
                        Secretary’s message to the King. (Telegram 280, December 24; <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 786A.11/12–2455)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-12-13T18:57:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 13, 1955—6:57 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>279. From Secretary. Please convey on my behalf in appropriate oral form
                    following message to King: <pb facs="0335" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have followed with concern problem of Buraimi oasis. As Under
                            Secretary informed Azzam Pasha and Ambassador Khayyal,<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d198fn2">See <ref target="#d194fn4">footnote 4, Document
                                    194</ref>.</note> we have agreed to assist informally as friends
                            of both parties in effort find acceptable solution. With this in view, I
                            have sent personal message to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHM1"
                                >Macmillan</persName>. I have stressed to him moderate attitude
                            which Your Majesty has pursued on matter. I hope it may be possible for
                            me to discuss matter with him at early date.</p>
                        <p>“I am also instructing Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WGE1"
                                >Wadsworth</persName> to keep in close touch with you on this issue
                            and on other matters of common interest between us.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>This and following telegram constitute message referred to in last sentence
                        <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 268.<note n="3" xml:id="d198fn3">
                        <ref target="#d195">Document 195</ref>. “Following telegram” presumably
                        refers to telegram 281 to Jidda, December 13. (Department of State, Central
                        Files, 780.022/12–1355) This telegram transmitted to the Embassy additional
                        points which it might wish to convey to the King. The Department, inter
                        alia, suggested that the Embassy repeat to <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1"
                            >Faisal</persName> the U.S. desire to discuss the Dhahran Airfield and
                        to assist Saudi Arabia in strengthening its defenses. The Department also
                        instructed the Embassy to express the hope that the King would not use his
                        resources to support opponents of the Baghdad Pact. On December 29 <persName
                            corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> transmitted the King’s written
                        reply to the Secretary’s message. In his message, <persName
                            corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> thanked the United States for its
                        efforts to help solve the Buraimi problem. According to <persName
                            corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName>, the “soundest means” to resolve the
                        problem was a return to arbitration, based on restoration of the status quo
                        ante and the establishment of a neutral international commission in the
                        disputed areas. According to <persName corresp="#p_WGE1"
                            >Wadsworth</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1">Faisal</persName>,
                        who had transmitted the King’s message, added that the King, in view of
                        domestic pressures, could not wait forever. (Telegram 282 from Jidda,
                        December 28; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 780.022/12–2855)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
