<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-05-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="233" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                        <head>233. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1" type="from">Rountree</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary
                                of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d233fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 786A.11/5–2156. Secret. Drafted
                                by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Newsom</persName> on May
                            18.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-05-21"><hi rend="italic">May 21,
                                1956</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Possible Visit of King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> to the United States</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi></p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> has previously indicated that, at an
                            appropriate time, during or following the renegotiation of the Dhahran
                            Airfield Agreement we might wish to invite King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> to visit the United States.
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> confirms
                            other reports we have received of the King’s keen interest in receiving
                            such an invitation.</p>
                        <p>We envision that such an invitation would come in the context of a
                            successful conclusion of the negotiations which are about to commence.
                            The dates of the actual visit could be arranged to fit the convenience
                            of the President and the King, probably in 1957.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> mentioned the
                            possibility of such a visit to the President when he saw him on May 9
                            and urged that favorable decision at this time might well assist him in
                            his negotiations, <pb facs="0407" n="375" xml:id="pg_375"/> particularly
                            if full accord could not be reached before June 18 when the present
                            agreement expires. The President’s reply, while in no sense a
                            commitment, was to the effect that the suggestion had “good points”.</p>
                        <p>We have, therefore, prepared the attached memorandum<note n="2" xml:id="d233fn2">The memorandum to the President recommended, among
                                other things, that upon successful conclusion of the Dhahran
                                Airfield agreement, the United States could further strengthen its
                                relations with Saudi Arabia by inviting King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> to this country in 1957. The
                                memorandum also pointed out that although <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> had visited the United
                                States in 1946 while Crown Prince, he would, if invited, be the
                                first reigning Saudi leader to pay a state visit.</note> to the
                            President, suggesting that, if the President concurs, Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> be authorized at an
                            appropriate stage in the negotiations of the Dhahran Airfield Agreement,
                            to tell the King that the United States Government would be pleased if,
                            upon the conclusion of the new agreement, Saudi and American ties could
                            be further strengthened by a state visit by His Majesty to the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi></p>
                        <p>That you approve the attached memorandum to the President.<note n="3" xml:id="d233fn3">A notation on the source text by <persName corresp="#p_MWB1">Macomber</persName> indicates that <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> disapproved the memorandum.
                                An additional marginal notation, presumably by <persName corresp="#p_MWB1">Macomber</persName>, reads as follows: “Will
                                play too early. Domestic implication Jewish [friends?]”.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>