<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>276. Telegram From the Embassy in Saudi Arabia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-04-11T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-04-11T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recrT0TBgNbKJyC3W" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recwXdagbfSBlXglR" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">International waters</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-11T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-11T02:00:00-05:00" n="276"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                <head>276. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Saudi Arabia</gloss> to
                    the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d276fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 120.1580/4–1157. Secret. Repeated to Tel Aviv, Cairo, Amman, and
                        Paris.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jidda</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-11T10:00:00+03:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 11, 1957—10 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>617. From <persName corresp="#p_RJP1">Richards</persName>. I have received
                    effusive show of welcome Saudi Arabia. First audience afternoon April 9 was in
                    King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName>’s residence palace, where he
                    said he had previously received no foreigners except Chiefs of State. As <gloss
                        target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> expressed it, he viewed Americans as his closest
                    friends and not as outsiders, and he wanted to show special deference to
                    personal representative of President <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>.</p>
                <p>I conveyed President’s respects and abiding friendship. <gloss target="#t_HM1"
                        >HM</gloss> reciprocated these with feeling and said he was working on means
                    of even further strengthening these friendly relations not only between two
                    Chiefs of State but also between two peoples.</p>
                <p>After dinner given by <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss>, had private audience his
                    office, where President’s gifts proudly displayed. <gloss target="#t_HM1"
                        >HM</gloss> began by emphasizing he was exerting “every possible effort
                    create understanding and friendship other countries for America, that we may
                    coordinate our efforts maintain world peace and tranquility”. <gloss
                        target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> later said “I shall fight every destructive
                    influence in this area of world”.</p>
                <p>I said my mission has been impressed by what <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss>
                    has done in area relations. <persName>Said</persName> however we were disturbed
                    by recent developments Jordan and Syria. I outlined basic elements mission goals
                    and said we had been met everywhere so far in tour by friendly people and
                    friendly governments. <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> responded “I pray for
                    continued success of mission”.</p>
                <p>In response my invitation for <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss>’s comments on
                    area developments <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> first observed that he and
                    his country were outspoken opponents of Communism, as was well-known. <gloss
                        target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> continued “your promise to come to aid of country
                    threatened by direct Communist aggression is clear. What is not clear is
                    definition which countries are under domination of forces international
                    Communism. This lack of clarity enables some elements make statements against
                        <pb facs="0522" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/> your interests this area. For
                    instance, while I do not deny there are extremist elements in Syria I do not
                    believe it is country dominated by international Communism. You should clarify
                    these points concerning that portion of American Doctrine which relates to
                    indirect aggression.”</p>
                <p>I said we had attempted make plain American Doctrine not designed settle
                    intra-area disputes. As to decision re specific countries being dominated by
                    international Communism, this must be left to good judgment of President. King
                    asked whether we would accuse Syria of being Communist dominated and therefore
                    come to aid of Israel in event trouble between them. I replied no governments
                    had asked us for help against Syria. Some governments in this area have asked us
                    for help in strengthening their internal situation so they can withstand
                    pressures of Communist or leftist elements from within or without.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> then presented at length problem of Aqaba. He
                    kept reasserting his eternal friendship for President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Eisenhower</persName>. <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss>
                    said Aqaba question would not affect our basic friendship but he wanted friendly
                    cooperation from <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> in fighting his enemy. He
                    was determined never to consent to Aqaba Straits being considered international
                    waterway. “We will never permit in any way Israel transit through our
                    territorial waters” he said he would stir up entire Moslem world to prevent
                    this. I told him I knew he could do this, but hoped his faith in US would make
                    him hesitate in doing such a thing, because he knew President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Eisenhower</persName> and His Majesty when they sat down
                    together could settle this great question in amicable way. I asked King
                        <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> to consider both sides of
                    American position on question. While we fully understood sincerity of his
                    position, I hoped he would concede sincerity of ours. Informed him that
                    principles involved in Aqaba question applied also to other waterways in world
                    and stand taken by US had to apply to all parts of world. We could not make
                    exception in Aqaba just because of Israeli situation. Called his attention to US
                    efforts build firm structure of international law through which disputes of all
                    nations could be settled. <persName>Said</persName> our experts state precedents
                    point to Aqaba as an international waterway. We had shown our respect for world
                    law and United Nations itself by condemning Israel aggression, and demanding
                    Israel forces retire from Egyptian territory. Pointed out we had in many
                    additional ways helped to formulate through <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    respect for world morals and world law. Since we believe that under world law
                    Aqaba waters are international waters, we would not be honest and consistent if
                    we did not say so. I granted it was possible that we were wrong and position
                    King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> took might be right. In that
                    light, I asked if <gloss target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> would agree to refer matter
                    to world court for determination and abide by its determination. I did not
                    venture <pb facs="0523" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/> to assert that US would be
                    bound by decision but I presume that he assumed that we would. He would have no
                    part of such procedure and asked that US have nothing to do with it. <gloss
                        target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> insisted whole Gulf was Arab <gloss
                        target="#t_SEA1">Sea</gloss> and belonged not to <gloss target="#t_SA1"
                        >SA</gloss> alone but to Islamic world, and that Israel had seized Aqaba as
                    avenue of expansion. He mentioned pilgrimages to Holy places and I replied
                    President <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Eisenhower</persName> had guaranteed
                    there would be no interference and that we reasserted that principle. King
                    remained adamant in his position and I promised him I would convey what he said
                    to President.</p>
                <p>I said where there is friendship and good will much can be done. <gloss
                        target="#t_HM1">HM</gloss> answered “I have no doubt whatsoever President
                    and his Government and people will always try to do what is right” ….</p>
                <p>In courtesy call on Crown Prince <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1">Faisal</persName>
                    later same evening, <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1">Faisal</persName> said “may
                    God help and speed you in accomplishment your mission”. Subject of Aqaba was
                    again brought up and briefly discussed. Arrangements were made for technical
                    discussions following morning with Prince Sultan, Minister of Communications and
                        <persName corresp="#p_SMS1">Mohammad Surur</persName>, Finance Minister.
                        <persName corresp="#p_FAARFS1">Faisal</persName>’s parting words were to
                    effect we would continue have trouble in this area so long as British and
                    “Zionism” were present.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Wadsworth</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
