<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-12T17:36:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="4" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                        <head>4. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On April 1, in a memorandum to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern,
                            South Asian, and African Affairs <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">George
                                Allen</persName> presented his views on the matter of Jordan’s or
                            other Arab States’ adherence to the Turko-Iraqi Pact. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> informed the Secretary that he
                            had discussed the question with the Counselor of the British Embassy and
                            expressed concern that Jordanian adherence to the Pact might encourage
                            Lebanese or even Syrian participation. Such events, <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> continued, might complicate U.S.
                            efforts to effect an Egyptian-Israeli settlement by isolating Egypt,
                            weakening <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>, and
                            intensifying “Israel’s agitation.” (Department of State, Central Files,
                            682.87/4–155)</p>
                        <p>That same day, the Embassy in London reported that in conversations with
                                <persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName>, the Assistant
                            Under-Secretary of State expressed the view that the United Kingdom was
                            not pressing Jordan or any other Arab State to join the Turko-Iraqi
                            pact. The British made it clear, <persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName> continued, that should Jordan decide to enter
                            the pact, the United Kingdom would consider revising the Anglo-Jordanian
                            treaty. According to the Embassy, <persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName> thought it “extremely dangerous” for either
                            the United States <pb facs="0038" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> or the United
                            Kingdom to discourage Jordanian adherence. (Telegram 4350 from London;
                                <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</p>
                        <p>On April 4, <persName corresp="#p_AWW1">Aldrich</persName> informed the
                            Department that in the course of a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName>, the British Prime Minister
                            stated that neither the United States nor the United Kingdom should
                            advise Jordan against joining the Turko-Iraqi pact. (Telegram 4365 from
                            London; <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 780.5/4–455)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>