<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-25T11:04:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-25T11:04:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                        <head>76. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Saudi Arabia</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d76fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 785.00/4–2557. Secret; Priority. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Newsom</persName> and approved and signed by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-25T11:04:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">April 25,
                                        1957—11:04 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>944. Department desires you seek audience as soon as possible with King
                            to review current situation in Jordan. Emphasize our deep concern over
                            events and our firm determination, which we believe King shares with us,
                            to preserve independence of Jordan. You may inform King: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We have irrefutable evidence Syrians and Egyptians are
                                    carrying out widespread covert operations against <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName> and Jordanian
                                    regime in obvious collaboration with Communists. We have
                                    knowledge Egyptian sponsored plot to assassinate <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName>. We would urge
                                        <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> exercise great
                                    care with respect his own personal security at this time.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>We attach importance at this juncture to open support of
                                        <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName> by
                                    friendly nations such as Saudi Arabia and Iraq and to public
                                    expression of willingness by such nations to provide forces for
                                    assistance of <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName>
                                    if he should request them. We would hope King might see way
                                    clear to make such expression. We know <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName> keenly appreciates
                                    King’s current support.</item>
                                <pb facs="0144" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We wish lend our support in every practicable way and have
                                    problem under constant consideration. (<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>: In this connection Department requests you
                                    also determine, if possible, extent of King’s current financial
                                    assistance to Jordan. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.)</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>We believe this to be most critical time and believe it is in
                                    interests freedom and independence of all Arab peoples to
                                    support <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d76fn2">On April 29, <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wadsworth</persName> informed the
                                        Department that he presented the substance of telegram 944
                                        to King <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> in an
                                        audience on April 27. According to the Ambassador, <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Saud</persName> noted, among other
                                        things, that he would continue to support <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName> and had already
                                        placed Saudi forces in Jordan under <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName>’s command. The
                                        King also noted that <persName corresp="#p_Hussein1">Hussein</persName> was short of funds and if the United
                                        States could furnish money, it would be best to do so
                                        through Iraq. (Telegram 659 from Jidda; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 785.00/4–2957)</note></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>