<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Paraguay ( (Thurston) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-08-07T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-08-07T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-08-07T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-08-07T10:00:00-05:00" n="118"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/94: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Paraguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thurston</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Asunción</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-08-07T11:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 7, 1935—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>54. My 53, August 1, 10 a.m. Having received from Ambassador Gibson a telegram
                    stating that the Argentine Minister for Foreign Affairs had heard that the
                    Presidents of Paraguay and Bolivia were to meet between August 8 and 11 to
                    discuss the territorial question but apparently had heard nothing of bringing
                    the military leaders into the negotiations, I called upon President Ayala last
                    evening and inquired concerning the results of the conversations between
                    Generals Estigarribia and Penaranda and the report (published in the morning
                    papers) that he would hold a meeting with President Tejada Sorzano.</p>
                <p>President Ayala replied that General Estigarribia had reported that his
                    conversation with General Penaranda had been most satisfactory. Although the
                    President did not explicitly so state, his subsequent remarks indicated that the
                    purpose of the conversations was to ascertain whether agreement exists as to the
                    necessity and feasibility of an immediate and definite settlement of the
                    boundary question and that agreement on this point does exist. In the meanwhile
                    the President has been urged by Argentina, ostensibly in the person of General
                    Martinez Pita,<note n="73" xml:id="d118fn73">Rodolfo Martinez Pita (Argentine),
                        Chairman of the Neutral Military Commission.</note> to meet with the
                    President of Bolivia and has indicated his readiness to do so. He is however, he
                        <pb facs="0207" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> said, apprehensive that the
                    Bolivian President will present a demand for a port on the Paraguay or some
                    other unacceptable claim and he is accordingly unwilling to hold the meeting
                    until he is assured that Sorzano is prepared to discuss with him the one
                    paramount question of the boundary. I inferred that negotiations designed to
                    bring about a meeting on this basis are under way probably between Estigarribia
                    and Penaranda.</p>
                <p>In the course of the conversation the President made the following remarks: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>All other features of the peace negotiations are secondary to the
                            boundary settlement and if that can be arrived at Paraguay will be
                            disposed to modify its stand on some points, notably the question of
                            responsibility—which it would drop:</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>If boundary agreement is not reached through direct efforts he
                            foresees failure of Buenos Aires Conference.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Paraguay will not cede territory it now occupies. Adjustments may
                            become possible in the future but are impossible now. Repeated to Buenos
                            Aires.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thurston</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
