<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-09T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-09T14:00:00-05:00" n="138" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/163: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gibson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de
                                            Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-09T16:00:00-03:00">September 9, 1935—4
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 5:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>218. Bolivian Chargé d’Affaires called this afternoon and asked my
                                support for a resolution which he proposes under the instructions of
                                his Government to have introduced by Colombian delegate at next
                                week’s meeting of Red Cross Conference. This resolution is in effect
                                an outline of the Bolivian thesis on prisoners of war and calls in
                                the name of humanity and on grounds of international law for the
                                immediate release of all prisoners now held by Paraguay and Bolivia.
                                The Chargé d’Affaires states that while his Government feels the
                                mediators are doing all they can, they are unable to overcome
                                Paraguayan resistance which can be met only through formal
                                condemnation by public opinion.</p>
                            <p>I told him that inasmuch as the question of prisoners of war was now
                                under negotiations by a group of powers whose mediation had been
                                accepted I feel it would be improper for either party to start
                                propaganda of this sort; that persistence by the Bolivian Government
                                in bringing a controversial political question into the Red Cross
                                Conference might readily create a situation where the Chaco
                                Conference could not get agreement on this or any other
                                question.</p>
                            <p>The Chargé d’Affaires said that nevertheless his Government felt this
                                pressure should be exerted and asked for the support of the American
                                delegation to the Red Cross Conference. I said I had no authority
                                over the American delegation but that it would be wise not to count
                                too much on their support as, if the resolution were introduced, I
                                should be obliged to explain its political implications to our
                                delegation and suggest that they might deem it wise at least to
                                abstain from voting while stating their reasons.</p>
                            <p>The Chargé d’Affaires said he quite appreciated the dangers of the
                                contemplated step but did not indicate that he would modify his
                                plans.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Dawson.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>