<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-09-21T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-09-21T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-21T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-21T17:00:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/185: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-21T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 21, 1935—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 10:42 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>215. From Dawson. Paragraph 3, my 212, September 20, 9 p.m. Bolivian and
                    Paraguayan delegations have agreed that the International Commission on War
                    Responsibility should be chosen as follows: the Bolivian and Paraguayan
                    Governments would each request a neutral American Government to designate a
                    judge and the third and presiding member would be a Justice of the Supreme Court
                    of the United States, “negotiations” for the designation of the latter being
                    entrusted to the chairman of the Conference. The Commission would have a
                    prolonged period probably 18 months in which to render an opinion on all aspects
                    of the war responsibility question. If either party failed to accept the
                    conclusions, the question would under the terms of the June 12 Protocol go to
                    the Permanent Court of International Justice for final decision.</p>
                <p>Saavedra Lamas tells me that he feels it is essential to know before the final
                    draft of the necessary resolution is approved whether any Justice of our Supreme
                    Court would be prepared to accept an invitation to sit on the Commission and
                    asks me to endeavor to ascertain this through the Department. His idea is
                    apparently that it would be useless to adopt a resolution making definite
                    provisions for an American Justice without reason to believe that one would
                    accept. I should appreciate instructions as to what reply I should make.</p>
                <p>Preliminary drafts so far considered have not specified a meeting place. I have
                    expressed the opinion to Saavedra Lamas and to members of the Drafting Committee
                    that it would probably be impossible for an American Justice to absent himself
                    from Washington for a period such as that contemplated.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Rio de Janeiro. [Dawson.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
