<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-12-30T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-12-30T14:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/327: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                            Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-12-30T16:00:00-03:00">December 30, 1935—4
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 5:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>305. From Braden. My 303, December 24, 4 p.m.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>December 22nd formula drafted by us with Ayala and accepted by
                                    him was forwarded to the Department by air mail December 27.
                                    Since our return we have run into difficulties with both the
                                    Paraguayans and the Bolivians and have been intently engaged in
                                    trying to overcome them.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Zubizarreta, in addition to several minor objections to text
                                    of December 22nd formula, expressed unwavering opposition to a
                                    provision included in it at Ayala’s suggestion whereby Bolivia
                                    and Paraguay would agree to abandon recourse to the
                                    Responsibilities Tribunal provided for in article 1, clause 7 of
                                    the June 12th Protocol. He tendered his resignation as chairman
                                    of the Paraguayan delegation to Ayala, stating that he could not
                                    sign the December 22nd formula and would oppose it in the
                                    Senate.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We submitted the December 22nd formula to the Bolivian
                                    delegation on December 24 and they transmitted it to their
                                    Government. The reply received December 27 was a complete
                                    rejection of the formula insisting on the December 2nd
                                    proposal.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>On December 28 we suggested to the Bolivian and Paraguayan
                                    delegations that they might agree on the December 2nd proposal
                                    with certain changes which were included in the December 22nd
                                    formula. <pb facs="0291" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> These are
                                    that (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) protocolized act would be
                                    subject to approval by the Bolivian and Paraguayan Congresses;
                                        (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) provisions extending
                                    effectiveness of security measures, including lines of
                                    separation, would be incorporated in the protocolized act
                                    instead of being an interpretation of the June 12th Protocol
                                    contained in a Conference resolution and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) these measures would be maintained “until the
                                    provisions of article 1, clause 3 of the June 12th Protocol are
                                    fulfilled” instead of “as long as the Peace Conference does not
                                    dissolve.”</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The Bolivian and Paraguayan delegations have expressed
                                    satisfaction with this suggestion. In an attempt to compose his
                                    differences with Ayala, Zubizarreta since December 28 has been
                                    endeavoring to get the former’s approval but so far has no
                                    definite answer. Should this be favorable the suggestion will be
                                    submitted to the Bolivian Government with which less difficulty
                                    is expected.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>If other questions can be worked out, net payment by Bolivia
                                    to Paraguay for maintenance of prisoners will probably be set at
                                    2,400,000 pesos. Ayala agreed confidentially to accept this
                                    amount which Elío has indicated Bolivia could pay.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Repeated to Rio de Janeiro by telegraph; Asunción and La Paz
                                    by mail. [Braden.]</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>