<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Colombia ( (Washington) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-02-01T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-01T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" n="219"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">721.23/2444: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-01T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 1, 1935—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 11 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>18. At the request of Dr. Olaya I called at his house this afternoon. He informed
                    me that he would probably accept the post of Minister for Foreign Affairs and
                    assume office tomorrow although before doing so he wishes to see his way clear
                    toward a solution of the problem of the Rio de Janeiro pact. He says that the
                    question of its ratification by the Colombian Senate depends upon two or three
                    very uncertain votes and he is not sure that approval will be given without some
                    qualifying statement or condition attached. His conversation with me dwelt
                    principally upon the possibility of obtaining Peru’s agreement to two or three
                    interpretative amendments or additions. He is not pleased with the intervention
                    of the League of Nations in the matter, being particularly distrustful of the
                    British attitude toward Colombia in the latter’s relations with Peru. He expects
                    to confer with Dr. Belaunde, Peruvian Minister to Colombia, but is not certain
                    as to the extent that the latter voices the opinion of the Peruvian Government
                    or is able to influence its decisions.</p>
                <p>Dr. Olaya stated that unless he felt that approval would certainly be given by
                    the Colombian Senate in a form which would be satisfactory to Peru he would
                    advise the President to close the Colombian Congress and resubmit the Pact to
                    the new Congress which he expects to be elected with a substantial Liberal
                    majority in the month of May.</p>
                <pb facs="0302" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                <p>Though Dr. Olaya has not yet made any requests of me, he clearly inferred that he
                    would be pleased if he could be informed confidentially through the United
                    States Government regarding the probable attitude of the Peruvian Government in
                    the event, (1) that the Colombian Senate should put the Colombian Government in
                    the position of having to request Peru’s agreement to certain interpretative
                    modifications of the pact or, (2) that the Colombian Government seeing the
                    impossibility of securing approval by the present Colombian Senate should
                    dissolve Congress immediately and propose an exchange of notes between Peru and
                    Colombia providing for ratification before the end of 1935.</p>
                <p>I explained to Dr. Olaya your interest in proceeding with the negotiations for
                    the commercial treaty.<note n="7" xml:id="d219fn7">See <ref target="#pg_430">pp.
                            430</ref> ff.</note> He said that he would speak to the President about
                    the matter and try to expedite the Colombian reply to the American proposals.
                    However, he added that the question of the Rio pact must be settled first and
                    that if it were decided to close the sessions of the present Colombian Congress
                    because of the apparent impossibility of obtaining favorable action on the
                    foregoing pact it would be necessary for reasons of internal politics to do so
                    immediately and this would prevent the consideration by that body of any
                    commercial treaty which might be signed with the United States until the new
                    Congress should meet in July next.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
