<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Brazilian Ambassador ( (Aranha))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="366"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Agreement Series No. 82</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3231/961</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Brazilian Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aranha</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-02">February 2,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                    receipt of Your Excellency’s note of this date.</p>
                <p>My Government welcomes the declaration of the Government of Brazil contained in
                    Your Excellency’s note under acknowledgment in connection with the arrangements
                    for the development of trade between the United States and Brazil embodied in
                    the new Commercial Agreement between the two countries and has taken note of the
                    determination of the Government of Brazil to resolve in so satisfactory and
                    orderly a manner matters involving foreign exchange between the two
                    countries.</p>
                <p>The security in exchange matters these assurances will give to trade between the
                    two countries should greatly assist in the development of that trade. They
                    appear to this Government to be both reasonable and moderate and in no way to
                    obstruct such plans or efforts as the Brazilian Government may wish to carry
                    forward in furthering a liberal exchange policy.</p>
                <p>Your Excellency will, of course, appreciate that the proffer by Your Excellency’s
                    Government of these assurances as contained in Your Excellency’s note above
                    referred to is not construed by this Government as modifying or affecting in any
                    way the rights of American holders of Brazilian bonds issued in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
