<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Brazil ( (Gordon) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-06-22T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-06-22T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-06-22T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-06-22T12:00:00-05:00" n="412"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.5151/661: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-06-22T14:00:00-03:00"
                            >June 22, 1935—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 5:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>165. Department’s 113, June 21, 5 p.m.<note n="70" xml:id="d412fn70">Not
                        printed.</note> arrived this morning in a badly garbled condition. However,
                    Department’s 114, June 21, 6 <pb facs="0473" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/> p.m.,
                    arrived in good shape and just in time for me to use it as the Foreign Minister
                    asked me to call upon him this morning although he had announced that he would
                    only commence receiving members of the Diplomatic Corps on Monday afternoon.</p>
                <p>I greatly appreciate this instruction which was exceedingly helpful and in reply
                    to the implied query in the last paragraph please let me say that the points
                    covered and the manner of presentation outlined seem to me to meet the situation
                    for the time being.</p>
                <p>When I communicated your views to the Minister for Foreign Affairs he said that
                    he understood that uneasiness should be created and that American interests
                    involved would be quick to bring pressure on our Government; but as to the loss
                    of orders for American interests he was inclined to argue that Brazilian exports
                    of cotton to Germany are the only thing that could cause loss of American
                    orders, and that as cotton is excluded from the latest ruling he did not see how
                    the question of loss of orders could arise.</p>
                <p>I then went into a full discussion with him and told him that prior to May 30th
                    (when compensation marks transactions were forbidden) specific cases of loss of
                    orders for American interests through the operation of compensation marks had
                    been brought to my attention and that there was every reason to believe that
                    similar cases would occur again—especially might this be so in the case of
                    American interests bidding against German firms on tenders for supplies of
                    service and imported material, for instance in railroad construction work where
                    the Germans would be willing to accept payment in compensation marks.</p>
                <p>Since sending my 161, June 19, 6 p.m. to the Department I have received definite
                    confirmation of the fact that as a result of the decision last Monday of the
                    Brazilian Federal Foreign Trade Council the Bank of Brazil had [announced?] that
                    the 35% in official exchange of Brazilian export bills to Germany would no
                    longer have to be supplied in currencies having international acceptance but
                    would be receivable in compensation marks. Referring to this further factor I
                    further pointed out to the Minister for Foreign Affairs that even in the absence
                    of numerous cases of specific loss of orders for American interests the almost
                    inevitable increase of German-Brazilian trade and the gradual shifting of trade
                    to Germany, which, in the absence of the Brazilian decision of last Monday,
                    would not have gone to the latter country, would, it seemed to me, eventually
                    constitute a definite displacement of American trade.</p>
                <p>At the end of our discussion the Minister called in the Secretary General, asked
                    me to repeat what I had said, and told him to make an <pb facs="0474" n="381"
                        xml:id="pg_381"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> thereof on the basis of which the Foreign
                    Minister would take the matter up with the Minister of Finance at once.</p>
                <p>I am to see the Foreign Minister again on Tuesday or Wednesday.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
