<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="441" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d441">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">625.116/31</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Scott</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 500</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-10-29">October 29, 1935</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                November 7.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to this
                            Embassy’s despatch No. 441 of August 16, 1935, and previous
                            communications regarding the difficulties of our commerce in Chile. In
                            this connection, having learned <pb facs="0515" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> of two new developments, it was felt desirable to discuss them in an
                            informal way with the Foreign Office. The first point was the fact that
                            a short time ago the British had been accorded authorization for the
                            transfer of sterling accounts. One consisted of certain collections in
                            the Magallanes and Valparaiso districts which were authorized some weeks
                            ago. The second transfer consisted of certain blocked credits in
                            Santiago. The second point which has arisen in connection with exchange
                            restrictions concerned the apparent extension of exchange restrictions
                            to include automobile tires and spare parts. It will be recalled that
                            originally authorizations were held up for American tires, but after
                            some conversation on this subject the Minister of Finance stated that it
                            was not desired to restrict the importation of these articles and
                            pending orders were released. Recently American tires importers have
                            complained to the Embassy that their <hi rend="italic">solicitudes</hi>
                            for the obtention of export drafts have been held up or not authorized
                            by the Exchange Control Commission and that it appeared, therefore, that
                            in effect the restrictions were being extended to include tires.</p>
                        <p>A conversation was held at the Foreign Office on October 26th concerning
                            these matters and a record of the same is enclosed.<note n="11" xml:id="d441fn11"><hi rend="smallcaps">Not printed</hi>.</note> With
                            regard to the transfer of frozen credits or blocked funds on deposit in
                            banks, it will be noted that the Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs
                            requested the Embassy to furnish a list of funds whose transfer was
                            desired. This list was furnished in conformity with this suggestion, a
                            copy of the Embassy’s Memorandum on this subject being enclosed.<note n="11" xml:id="d441fn1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Not
                                printed</hi>.</note></p>
                        <p>With regard to the extension of restrictions to tires and automobile
                            spare parts, there is enclosed a copy,<note n="11" xml:id="d441fn2"><hi rend="smallcaps">Not printed</hi>.</note> with translation, of a
                            letter just received from the Under Secretary on this point. The reply
                            is typical of the attitude now being adopted by Chile with regard to our
                            commerce and, as will be seen, on the one hand it states that there are
                            no restrictions on the importation of spare parts and tires, but it then
                            states that certain authorizations for the latter have been only
                            accorded for a future time when exchange availabilities are sufficient
                            to prevent a rise in the dollar. In other words, tires in reality are on
                            exactly the same basis as automobiles and radios since, according to the
                            Chilean Government’s statements, the restrictive measures are in all
                            cases only temporary and designed to place a check upon the use of
                            dollar exchange.</p>
                        <p>As the thoroughly unsatisfactory treatment we are receiving on the two
                            points mentioned above is only part of the present situation with regard
                            to American commerce in Chile, the entire question is being made the
                            subject of a more comprehensive report.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Winthrop R.
                            Scott</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>