<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Ecuador ( (Gonzalez) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-11-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-11-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="522"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d522">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2231/84</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gonzalez</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 177</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-11-08">November 8,
                            1935</date>.<lb/>[Received November 19.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my despatch No. 161 of October
                    28, 1935, concerning the preferential tariff at present enjoyed by France on its
                    imports into Ecuador, I have the honor to report that I left yesterday with the
                    Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs a copy of the provisions of the American law
                    authorizing the President, in the event of discrimination by foreign countries,
                    to establish new or additional duties on the products of those countries
                    entering the United States (The Code of the Laws of the United States of America
                    in force January 3, 1935, Title 19, Section 1338). The Under Secretary was not
                    aware of the existence of this authorization and remarked that it appeared to be
                    a violent measure. I pointed out that it was the policy of the United States
                    Government to avail itself of this provision only in case of a palpable
                    discrimination and an indisposition upon the part of the authorities to remove
                    it.</p>
                <p>In discussing the situation with the Under Secretary I recognized that trade with
                    France leaves a very favorable balance for Ecuador (exports to France during
                    1934, 21,117,112 sucres; imports from <pb facs="0604" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/>
                    France, 2,383,040 sucres). However, I pointed out that the fact must not escape
                    the attention of the Ecuadorean Government that the bulk of its exports during
                    that period was sold to the United States (exports, 48,716,381 sucres, imports,
                    21,153,826 sucres), and that the balance in favor of Ecuador had been in excess
                    of 27 million sucres. Therefore, it was incumbent upon his Government to take
                    immediate steps to remove the existing discrimination against American
                    products.</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary stated that his Government had already indicated its desire
                    to conclude a new Commercial Treaty with the United States and that provision
                    could be made therein to remove the discrimination. In compliance with the
                    Department’s instruction No. 52 of September 4, 1935, I expressed our
                    appreciation of this interest and explained our inability to initiate the
                    negotiation of a permanent treaty at this time. I added that his Government
                    should experience no great concern over a delay in concluding a commercial
                    treaty since such delay was not prejudicial to the interests of Ecuador. In this
                    connection I explained that the advantages conceded in our bilateral agreements
                    to other countries, particularly Colombia and Brazil, on exports identical to
                    those of this country, are extended under our most-favored-nation treatment to
                    articles of Ecuador exported to the United States. I cited that the two
                    principal articles in which Ecuador is interested, namely, coffee and cacao, and
                    also bananas and vegetable ivory, have already been the subject of treaty
                    negotiations with Brazil<note n="7" xml:id="d522fn7">See <ref target="#pg_300"
                            >pp. 300</ref> ff.</note> and/or Colombia,<note n="8" xml:id="d522fn8"
                        >See <ref target="#pg_430">pp. 430</ref> ff.</note> that the United States
                    has agreed with those countries to maintain these articles on the free list, and
                    that these concessions are extended to Ecuador as and when they become effective
                    for the countries immediately concerned.</p>
                <p>In view of the inability to initiate discussion of a definitive Commercial Treaty
                    at this time and in order to remove the discrimination referred to, I submitted
                    for the consideration of the Under Secretary a copy of the communications
                    exchanged between the American Embassy at Santiago, Chile, and the Chilean
                    Government on September 28, 1931, and I suggested that a <hi rend="italic">modus
                        vivendi</hi> to the same effect would appear to offer a solution of the
                    present problem pending the conclusion of a definitive commercial treaty. I
                    explained that the purpose of this exchange of notes had not been to obtain any
                    special concession for American exports to Chile, but simply to remove
                    discrimination similar to that which is now occurring in Ecuador. The Under
                    Secretary referred to the fact that the French-Ecuadorean <hi rend="italic"
                        >modus vivendi</hi> grants to all French imports a reduction of 30 percent.
                    Under these circumstances, were this same advantage extended to the United
                    States, it would mean that a reduction of 30 percent would be accorded <pb
                        facs="0605" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/> not only on the imports from the
                    United States identical to those imported from France, but also on all other
                    American imports. Therefore, an arrangement on this basis would go far beyond
                    that contemplated in the Chilean-American <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                    under reference. I admitted that this would be the result but that the
                    underlying cause was the very generous treatment which Ecuador had formally
                    accorded to France, and it was the desire of my Government now to remove the
                    existing discrimination by extending the same concessions to imports from the
                    United States. The Under Secretary stated that he would study the matter and
                    after consultation with the Minister, make a suggestion of an arrangement which
                    would correct the present situation. In this latter connection I feel that if a
                    proposal is not made within a week or ten days, I should be authorized to lodge
                    a formal complaint and insist upon the immediate removal of discrimination.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio C. Gonzalez</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
