<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-14T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-14T20:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/4864: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cox</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                            Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-14T21:00:00-04:00">May 14, 1935—9
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 11 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>41. Embassy’s 39, May 11, 10 p.m., confidential.</p>
                            <p>1. At Chaco meeting today the same representatives were present.
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs read telegram received from Paraguayan
                                Foreign Minister accepting invitation to come to Buenos Aires as
                                well as a telegram received from Bolivian Foreign Minister from
                                Bolivian general headquarters stating that Elio, upon his early
                                return to La Paz to consult President, would give a formal reply
                                immediately. He also read telegram just received from the Argentine
                                Minister in La Paz reporting that latter had been assured Bolivia’s
                                reply would be forthcoming today or tomorrow.</p>
                            <p>2. Minister for Foreign Affairs read a second telegram from Bolivian
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs stating that Foreign Ministers of
                                Argentina, Brazil, Chile, the United States and Peru had indicated
                                that they would view with pleasure Mexican inclusion in the
                                mediating group and suggesting to the group convenience of extending
                                such invitation officially to Mexico. I informed those present of
                                your views concerning this question contained in paragraph 2
                                Department’s telegram No. 41, May 10, 8 p.m.</p>
                            <p>There ensued a lengthy discussion, to which I listened, concerning
                                the possible consequences were the mediating group so augmented as
                                to become practically a pan-American conference. The question of
                                Mexican inclusion is being referred by the Ambassadors present to
                                their Governments.</p>
                            <p>3. Another meeting has been called for May 16, 6 p.m. by which time
                                it is hoped that the Bolivian reply to the invitation will have
                                arrived. Consideration was given to the advisability, if the
                                Bolivian Foreign Minister has not replied by Thursday evening, of
                                the mediating group sending him a further telegram expressing hope
                                for a prompt reply and stating that the question of Mexican
                                inclusion is under consideration.</p>
                            <p>Please instruct on this latter point.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Cox</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>