<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-06-18T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-06-18T19:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/4984: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-06-18T20:00:00-04:00">June 18, 1935—8
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>77. For Gibson. Your 84, June 16, 11 a.m. and 86, June 17, 5 p.m. I
                                have given very careful consideration to the views expressed to you
                                by the Foreign Ministers of Chile and Brazil. I cannot feel that
                                there is any serious basis for the first and second objections
                                listed in your No. 84. With regard to number (1), there is no more
                                logical justification for the present group than there would be for
                                any other artificially selected group of American nations. There
                                would, on the other hand, be complete logical justification for the
                                inclusion in the present peace conference of the nine states
                                composing the original commission of neutrals which dealt with the
                                Chaco dispute throughout the earlier period. Since Uruguay, which
                                was one of this group, and is not a neighboring state, has been
                                included, there is no justification for excluding Mexico, Colombia,
                                and Cuba, which were also members of the original commission of
                                neutrals.</p>
                            <p>With regard to objection (2), while certain of the Central American
                                Republics have periodically attempted during the past 5 years to
                                further a peaceful settlement of the Chaco controversy, their
                                present inclusion as a matter of policy is not comparable to that of
                                the other states above mentioned, and their alleged exasperation
                                because of their exclusion from the peace conference would not be a
                                determining factor in any future inter-American conference which
                                might be called to consider the creation of adequate peace machinery
                                for this Continent. It would, of course, be highly desirable that
                                the Central American and Caribbean Republics be invited to take
                                part, should the peace conference prove successful, in some formal
                                inter-American session terminating the work of the conference.</p>
                            <p>With regard to objection (3), if the peace protocol is ratified by
                                both Bolivia and Paraguay, discretion as to the invitations to the
                                peace conference would appear to be vested solely in the President
                                of <pb facs="0174" n="81" xml:id="pg_81"/> Argentina, and it is not
                                believed probable that since Paraguay urged and obtained the
                                inclusion of Uruguay among the mediating powers she would raise
                                serious objection to the inclusion of Ecuador.</p>
                            <p>It seems that in your conversations with Cruchaga and Macedo Soares
                                no specific reference has been made to the League recommendations,
                                which specifically provided for invitations to be extended by the
                                President of Argentina to the nations already represented as well as
                                to Mexico, Colombia, Cuba, Venezuela, and Ecuador.</p>
                            <p>From the point of view of this Government, the important fact to be
                                borne in mind is that throughout the duration of the Chaco conflict
                                repeated efforts have been made by the various American Republics
                                and various groups of American Republics to bring about a peaceful
                                solution, but at no time has there been any concerted effort on the
                                part of all of the American Republics to press for peace. This has
                                been due, in large part, in my judgment, to the lack of adequate
                                peace machinery on this Continent in which the American Republics
                                could properly have confidence. If any beneficial results are to be
                                derived from the experience of these past 6 years, they would seem
                                to lie solely in the possibility of seizing the opportune moment
                                presented by a successful termination of the coming peace conference
                                and for the United States to join with other powers of this
                                Continent in an initiative to suggest the need for the creation of
                                adequate peace machinery competent to deal with such inter-American
                                disputes should they arise in the future. If this opportunity is
                                lost, you will readily understand that an appropriate moment will
                                presumably not soon again arise. For this reason it would seem
                                especially desirable that certain influential governments, and in
                                particular Mexico and Colombia, should not be offended by their
                                exclusion from the present conference, since the offense thus
                                occasioned would inevitably make them far less willing to cooperate
                                with the nations already represented in the conference in any effort
                                such as that above indicated.</p>
                            <p>This Government appreciates the attitude taken by the Brazilian
                                Foreign Minister and I shall discuss the possibility in further
                                detail with Aranha after the return of the Foreign Minister to Rio
                                de Janeiro.</p>
                            <p>Because of the views you have expressed, and because of the fact that
                                it is clearly undesirable to raise any controversial issue at this
                                moment which might delay prompt ratification of the protocols by the
                                two belligerents, you may leave the question in abeyance until
                                further instructions are sent to you. I believe, however, that you
                                will share my view that while the first objective is to provide for
                                a satisfactory and speedy conclusion of permanent peace as envisaged
                                in the protocols, the larger objective from the point of view of our
                                    <pb facs="0175" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> continental policy is to
                                seize the occasion if it is presented to press for adequate
                                continental peace machinery and for that reason to do everything
                                possible to encourage and foster concerted continental public
                                opinion among the American Republics towards that end.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>