<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="822" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d822">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/8196</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lane</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 770</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-03-15">March 15, 1935</date>.<lb/>[Received March
                                21.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my strictly confidential
                            despatch No. 758 of March 8, 1935,<note n="40" xml:id="d822fn40">Not
                                printed.</note> on the general political situation and to my
                            telegram No. 12, <pb facs="0936" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> of
                                today,<note n="40a" xml:id="d822fn40a">Not printed.</note> I have
                            the honor to report that last evening the Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                            Doctor Leonardo Argüello (who it must be remembered has definite and
                            open aspirations to the Presidency), inquired of me as to what our
                            attitude would be should President Sacasa’s successor come into office
                            illegally. I replied that insofar as I knew, the Department’s policy
                            with regard to non-recognition of governments coming into power through
                            violence was the same as that expressed in the treaties of 1923<note n="41" xml:id="d822fn41">General Treaty of Peace and Amity signed at
                                Washington, February 7, 1923, <hi rend="italic">Conference on
                                    Central American Affairs, Washington, December 4, 1922–February
                                    7, 1923</hi> (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1923), p.
                                287. See also <ref target="frus1923v01#pg_320"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 320</ref> ff.; <ref target="frus1932v05#pg_566"><hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1932, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 566</ref> ff.; <ref target="frus1933v05#pg_882"><hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1933,
                                    vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 882</ref> ff.; <ref target="frus1934v05#pg_526"><hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1934,
                                    vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 526</ref> ff.</note> to
                            which Nicaragua, Guatemala and Honduras are still parties. The Minister
                            countered my remark by saying that he did not merely wish to refer to
                            governments coming into power through a <hi rend="italic">coup
                                d’etat</hi> but to governments which might come into power
                            “illegally”. When Dr. Argüello said to me that the attitude of the
                            United States was always of great importance on such matters, I made the
                            suggestion that our present policy is not to interfere in Nicaraguan
                            political matters and that the intervention is a thing of the past.</p>
                        <p>Making it evident that I was speaking for myself only and not necessarily
                            for my government, I stated that in my opinion the term “illegally”
                            might easily be susceptible to misinterpretation and that it would seem
                            the duty of the competent Nicaraguan authorities, and not for a foreign
                            power, to interpret the illegality of a matter affecting the
                            constitution of Nicaragua.</p>
                        <p>Should I have gone further than the Department desires, it will still be
                            possible for me to correct my statements to Doctor Argüello, I having
                            made it clear to him that I was not speaking on behalf of the
                            Department. I felt, however, that it was necessary to make some reply to
                            the Minister’s question and as I had already intended to make certain
                            recommendations to the Department on our policy in the case of a
                            contingency which probably will arise prior to the scheduled elections
                            in 1936, I felt it would not be inconsistent to speak to Doctor Argüello
                            as I did.</p>
                        <p>From many friends close to General Somoza<note n="42" xml:id="d822fn42">Anastasio Somoza, Jefe Director of the Guardia Nacional since
                                1932.</note> I am informed that he is definitely determined to be
                            the next President. The Government organ <hi rend="italic">La
                                Noticia</hi>, probably as a <hi rend="italic">ballon d’essai</hi>,
                            published a list of Senators and Deputies who, so the newspaper stated,
                            had been interviewed as to how they would vote on the calling of a
                            constitutional convention. According to the paper the Deputies voted 23
                            to 18, and the Senators, 17 to 6, against the calling of the convention.
                            While no mention is made in the article, a copy of which is enclosed,
                                herewith,<note n="43" xml:id="d822fn43">Not reprinted.</note>
                            <pb facs="0937" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/> as to the reasons for the
                            calling of a convention, it is general knowledge that it would be for
                            the purpose of amending Articles 105 and 141 of the constitution<note n="44" xml:id="d822fn44"><hi rend="italic">Constitución Politico, de
                                    la República de Nicaragua, 1911</hi> (Managua, Tip. de T.
                                Matamoros J., n. d.), pp. 32, 47.</note> to permit General Somoza to
                            be the next President. Indicative of the inaccuracy of the report
                            published in <hi rend="italic">La Noticia</hi> is the information which
                            comes to me from a reliable American source, that at least one of the
                            deputies (C. Lacayo Vivas), was not approached by anyone as to his vote
                            which, so it is reported, he would in any case give in favor of the
                            convocation of a constitutional convention.</p>
                        <p>Today I received an oral report from Mr. H. D. Scott, Manager of the
                            Bragman’s Bluff Lumber Company at Puerto Cabezas, a reliable American
                            citizen who has lived in Central America for many years, regarding a
                            conversation which he had this afternoon with General Somoza. According
                            to Mr. Scott, General Somoza gave him a verbal account of an
                            understanding which he had reached with President Sacasa,<note n="45" xml:id="d822fn45">Juan B. Saeasa, President of Nicaragua since
                                1933.</note> substantially as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>General Somoza definitely promises not to fire a shot against the
                                    Loma, except in the case of the resignation of President Sacasa.
                                    (I take this to mean that Somoza is willing to use force against
                                    anybody who tried to force the President to resign—ABL). The
                                    President would like to have Somoza succeed him. Somoza,
                                    however, does not wish the President to support his candidacy,
                                    merely remain neutral. The President wishes Somoza to submit to
                                    the people of the country through a plebiscite the question of
                                    changing the constitution (presumably articles 105 and 141—ABL),
                                    to permit him to be legally a candidate to the Presidency.
                                    Somoza claims that the <hi rend="italic">La Noticia</hi> article
                                    reflects only the editor’s wishes and is not accurate.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>My comment on the foregoing is that even though the President may have
                            such an understanding with Somoza, the President’s immediate advisers
                            are believed to be hostile towards Somoza.…The proposition to submit to
                            a plebiscite the question of constitutional amendments rather than to
                            have the matter brought up in Congress as provided for in the
                            constitution (article 160) would manifestly give the Government a patent
                            opportunity of preventing the passage of the amendments, through its
                            proven effective control of the electoral machinery. Somoza, on the
                            other hand, through a show of force, as was done in connection with the
                            López amnesty project,<note n="46" xml:id="d822fn46">José Antonio López
                                Barreda, a lieutenant in the Guardia Nacional and chief of police of
                                Managua, was tried by court martial on the charge of being the
                                principal instigator of a fire and explosion that occurred in the
                                Campo de Marte in Managua on September 12, 1934, and given the death
                                penalty. This sentence was confirmed by General Somoza, but
                                President Sacasa decided that the article of war which Lopez was
                                found guilty of violating did not specify the death penalty, and
                                sent the case back to General Somoza who substituted life
                                imprisonment at hard labor. The Chamber of Deputies, making
                                political issue of the matter, passed a bill on March 1, 1935,
                                granting amnesty to López. This action was rescinded, however, after
                                an announcement by Somoza that he would not release López
                                alive.</note> would probably be able to control the Congress.</p>
                        <pb facs="0938" n="845" xml:id="pg_845"/>
                        <p>On March 13, in the course of a dinner given by General and Mrs. Somoza
                            in honor of the retiring Mexican Minister and Mrs. Herrera de Huerta,
                            Mrs. Somoza asked me if I would give her husband “some good advice” in
                            connection with his future. She said that her husband did not know what
                            to do and that she would be grateful if I should talk to him. I said
                            that the only advice I could give was not to do anything rash and not to
                            resort to violence. Mrs. Somoza replied that there was no question of
                            resorting to violence but that it might be necessary to “make some
                            changes”. I did not pursue the matter further, nor do I expect to do so
                            unless the Department instructs me.</p>
                        <p>It is disheartening, after all the efforts we have made during the past
                            year to establish our intention of not interfering in Nicaraguan affairs
                            and to give Nicaragua a completely free hand in working out her own
                            destinies, to learn that the general feeling among Nicaraguans is that
                            Doctor Sacasa’s successor to the Presidency will be chosen by the United
                            States. I fear that the experience of the intervention is still too near
                            and the memory too intense to enable Nicaraguans to believe in our
                            sincerity of allowing them to hold a free Presidential election without
                            intimations or insinuations from us as to whom we desire to have
                            elected.</p>
                        <p>We are now faced with a problem of great difficulty. If, in answer to
                            questions such as Doctor Argüello’s which will undoubtedly be repeated
                            to me by other persons in the future, I should say that we will not
                            recognize the government of any candidate who comes into the Presidency
                            illegally, this would probably be interpreted as a desire on our part to
                            kill Somoza’s candidacy. While I do not think that Somoza has now any
                            intention of taking violent measures to attain his ambitions, a seeming
                            rejection of his candidacy by us might goad him to action. If, on the
                            other hand, we should give an affirmative answer, this would give the
                            impression that we favor Somoza for the Presidency and would strengthen
                            the general prevalent impression that we are still intervening in
                            Nicaraguan affairs and are choosing Doctor Sacasa’s successor.</p>
                        <p>My recommendation would be that I be authorized to say, in reply to
                            questions, that it is for the appropriate Nicaraguan authority
                            (presumably the Supreme Court), to determine the legality or illegality
                            of an election; that the Department can express no opinion in advance as
                            to whether it will or will not recognize a given government; and that it
                            is contrary to the Department’s general practice to answer hypothetical
                            questions.</p>
                        <pb facs="0939" n="846" xml:id="pg_846"/>
                        <p>According to the General Treaty of Peace and Amity of 1923, now in force
                            with respect to Nicaragua, El Salvador [<hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>] and Honduras, it would seem that General Somoza, if
                            elected, could not rightfully claim recognition from Honduras and
                            Guatemala unless he should resign from his present “high military
                            command” at least “six months preceeding…<note n="47" xml:id="d822fn47">Omission indicated in the original despatch.</note> the election”
                            (Article II, head 2, Treaty of 1923). According to the Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs, General Somoza’s advisers have pointed out to him that
                            should he resign from his present position, his authority will be gone,
                            and he will no longer have at his disposal the physical forces now
                            available. (Dr. Argüello said that this advice was given to Somoza by
                            General Moncada<note n="48" xml:id="d822fn48">José Maria Moncada,
                                President of Nicaragua 1929–32.</note> in the presence of Dr.
                            Cordero Reyes.)</p>
                        <p>Insofar as recognition is concerned, this possibility has presumably
                            already been considered by General Somoza. As my colleague in Guatemala
                            has already reported (Mr. Hanna’s despatch No. 504 of January 22,
                                1935),<note n="49" xml:id="d822fn49">Not printed.</note> it appears
                            that General Somoza has been desirous of obtaining the support of his
                            candidacy through the intermediary of Dr. Ramírez Brown. (In considering
                            the possibility as to whether Nicaragua, Honduras or Guatemala might
                            denounce the present treaty so as to render it nugatory for any and all
                            of the present adherents, I have noted that the language of Article
                            XVIII appears to be silent on one important point: Should one party of
                            the three remaining adherents to the treaty file its denunciation, when
                            does such denunciation take effect?)</p>
                        <p>I understand from Mr. Scott that General Somoza, in discussing today the
                            question of his possible recognition, remarked that General Martinez had
                            been able to remain in power in El Salvador for some time without the
                            recognition of the parties to the Treaty of 1923 and that consequently
                            this matter did not worry him. (I feel convinced, however, that Somoza
                            does not undervalue the importance of the recognition or lack of
                            recognition on the part of the Government of the United States).</p>
                        <p>As soon as the Department has had an opportunity to consider the matter
                            with which this despatch deals I should deeply appreciate an instruction
                            by air mail or telegraph in answer to the recommendation contained in
                            the first whole paragraph on page six.<note n="50" xml:id="d822fn50">Paragraph beginning “My recommendation would be…”, <ref target="#pg_845">p. 845</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Arthur Bliss
                            Lane</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>