<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-02-10T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-02-10T04:00:00-05:00" n="127" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/3294</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SPA1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stovall</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-02-10T10:00:00+01:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February 10, 1917, 10 a.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received February 11, 12.20
                                    p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>501. Referring to my telegram No. 488 of February 5, noon.<note n="1" xml:id="d127fn1">Not printed.</note> I have received from Dr.
                                    <persName>Hoffmann</persName>, Chief of the Swiss Political
                                Department, a supplementary and definitive reply to my note of
                                February 4. The following is a translation of this reply: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>Mr. Minister: By my note of February 5,<note n="1" xml:id="d127fn2">Not printed.</note> I had the honor to
                                        inform your excellency that before determining definitely in
                                        regard to the declarations of the German Government relative
                                        to the blockade, the Swiss Federal Council desired to enter
                                        into communication with the other neutral states of Europe
                                        which are in situation analogous to that of Switzerland. I
                                        added that the Federal Council desired first to draw the
                                        attention of President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> to Switzerland’s peculiar attitude
                                        prescribed by its principles as a state of complete and
                                        perpetual neutrality, principles founded on its
                                        constitution, on ancient traditions, and on the will of its
                                        people.</p>
                                    <p>The Federal Council today can only refer to Switzerland’s
                                        declaration of neutrality dated April [<hi rend="italic">August</hi>] 4, 1914, of which all foreign governments
                                        were informed at the time of its promulgation. On that date
                                        the Federal Assembly and the Federal Council announced their
                                        firm determination not to deviate in any manner whatsoever
                                        from the principles of neutrality, so highly cherished by
                                        the Swiss people and in such perfect conformity with their
                                        aspirations, with their institutions, with Switzerland’s
                                        situation in regard to other states, and which the
                                        guaranteeing powers expressly recognized in 1815. This is
                                        the reason the Federal Council and the Federal Assembly have
                                        expressly declared that, during the duration of the war, the
                                        Swiss confederation will maintain and will defend its
                                        neutrality and the inviolability of its territory by all the
                                        means in its power.</p>
                                    <p>The events of the present war have fortified the Federal
                                        Council in its conviction of the necessity for the
                                        maintenance of a strict and loyal neutrality and have
                                        furnished the proof that, today as in 1815, the true
                                        interests of European politics are furthered by the entity
                                        and independence of Switzerland. Switzerland will maintain
                                        this neutrality so long as the independence and integrity of
                                        its territory, its honor, and its vital interests are not
                                        attacked.</p>
                                    <p>The Federal Council must again draw the attention of
                                        President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> to
                                        the unusual geographical situation of Switzerland entirely
                                            <pb facs="0300" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/> surrounded by
                                        belligerents, and which would certainly become the moment
                                        that Switzerland ceased to be neutral, the theater of the
                                        general war.</p>
                                    <p>Regardless of how difficult Switzerland’s economic situation
                                        may become because of the threatened blockade and regardless
                                        of the degree in which the effective execution [of] the
                                        blockade may run counter to the principles of international
                                        law, the Federal Council can not however decide to follow
                                        President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> in
                                        his <hi rend="italic">demarches</hi> regarding the Imperial
                                        German Government which have been made necessary by a state
                                        of affairs entirely special. Consequently the Federal
                                        Council has confined itself to a protest and has reserved
                                        all its legal rights resulting from the execution of the
                                        blockade announced by the Imperial Government should this
                                        blockade prove to be contrary to neutral rights as
                                        recognized by the general principles of international law.
                                        In particular the Federal Council has reserved all its legal
                                        rights in the event that the effective execution of the
                                        blockade proving incomplete, should the means used by
                                        Germany and its allies result in the destruction of Swiss
                                        citizens or of Swiss property.</p>
                                    <p>In submitting the present communication to your excellency in
                                        reply to your note of February 4, 1917, I take this occasion
                                        to present to you assurances of my high consideration.
                                            <persName>Hoffman</persName>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SPA1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stovall</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>