<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-02-08T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-02-08T14:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/3262</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Panama</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Price</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Panama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-02-08T14:00:00-05:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February 8, 1917, 2 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 7.15 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Supplementing my February 4, 4 p.m. The following are the paragraphs
                                of a note received from Panaman Minister for Foreign Affairs
                                acknowledging my note pursuant to Department’s telegram February 3,
                                1 p.m.: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>The Government feels that the final conclusion reached by His
                                        Excellency the President of the United States of America,
                                        painful though it may be, is the only line of conduct
                                        compatible with the honor of the American nation and for the
                                        security of neutral commerce which can not be left to the
                                        mercy of a declaration of one of the belligerents.</p>
                                    <p>It is to be hoped that it will not be necessary for the
                                        United States of America to resort to force for the defense
                                        of its interests and for the defense of the universally
                                        accepted principles of international law, but if it should
                                        occur I can assure your excellency that Panama will
                                        faithfully carry out the engagements it has contracted with
                                        that nation and will cooperate in the most efficacious
                                        manner for the defense of the canal.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Detention of certain Germans in the Republic of Panama, against which
                                I advised, will not be carried out for the present.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Price</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>