<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Fletcher) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917Supp01v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d355</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">355</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-04-25T21:36:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-04-25T21:36:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-04-25T21:36:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-04-25T21:36:00-05:00" n="355"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d355">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 862.20212/273</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FHP1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fletcher</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico City</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-04-25T20:00:00-06:36">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 25, 1917, 8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received April 26, 2 a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>133. I have just had an hour’s conversation with President-elect <persName
                        corresp="#p_CGV1">Carranza</persName> in the course of which I read to him
                    paraphrases of your telegrams No. 123, April 21, 7 p.m., and 124, April 21, 8
                    p.m. He thinks it will be a good plan if the representatives of the Allied
                    powers now in Washington, along with the preparation of plans for the
                    prosecution of the war, could agree upon an outline of terms of peace; that
                    these terms might be communicated through their diplomatic representatives in
                    the United States to the Latin-American neutral powers who would act as
                    mediators in their presentation to the German Government. He intimated that it
                    might be possible, if these neutrals found the terms just and equitable, that in
                    presenting them to Germany they might state that unless accepted these neutral
                    nations would take sides with the Allies. He said that this was a thought which
                    has occurred to him but that he did not wish to make the suggestion in any
                    official way and asked me to telegraph it to you for such consideration as it
                    might merit.</p>
                <p>In the course of the conversation I explained to him fully the considerations
                    which had driven us into the war and pointed out to him the danger which Mexico
                    and other American nations would incur from an inconclusive peace, which would
                    leave the military <pb facs="0438" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> party in Germany as
                    a standing menace to all nations who wished to work out their destinies in
                    unarmed peace. I think he is coming to a juster appreciation of the great issues
                    involved in the war and of Mexico’s interest as affected thereby.</p>
                <p>The Mexican Government receives every day by telegraph a synopsis of what is said
                    in the leading papers of the United States relating to Mexico, and he complained
                    of the misstatements and decidedly distrustful and hostile attitude of our
                    leading papers with regard to Mexico in its relation to the war and asked me to
                    endeavor to put things in their true light before the Department which he hoped
                    might discourage the circulation of absurd and baseless stories about Mexico. He
                    said that he was very much pleased with the interview I had given out yesterday
                    and that it would have an excellent effect in reestablishing mutual
                    confidence.</p>
                <p>He stated that he would be very glad to receive any evidence or information we
                    might have showing German activities tending to compromise Mexican neutrality,
                    and that he would take immediate steps to frustrate them. He said that the
                    recent taking over of various British railways was not to be regarded in any way
                    as hostile to Great Britain or the enemies of Germany, but that such measures
                    became necessary in connection with the activity of the various insurrectionary
                    bands operating along those railways and for the safe movement of traffic.</p>
                <p>I feel sure that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Carranza</persName> fully
                    realizes the desirability and necessity of Mexico maintaining strictly its
                    neutrality.</p>
                <p>His attitude was frank, cordial, and rather encouraging.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FHP1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
