<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-08-14T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-08-14T10:00:00-05:00" n="455" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d455">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 832.85/11</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MEV1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morgan</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-08-14T12:00:00-03:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">August 14, 1917, 12 noon</hi></date>.
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 8 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>After Belgian and Italian Ministers had failed to do so, British and
                                French Ministers are attempting to secure some of the German
                                interned vessels now units of the Lloyd Brazilian mercantile fleet,
                                property of the Brazilian Government. The Government is not prepared
                                to part with any of these units, irrespective of whether or not they
                                were formerly German. Ten of them will soon be ready for employment
                                on Brazilian lines along American coast only, between <pb facs="0488" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> New York and Valparaiso.
                                Until the Brazilian Government has found by experience that it can
                                not repair and use all the units, as it ultimately must do, there is
                                little prospect of our obtaining any of them, either by purchase or
                                charter.</p>
                            <p>Administration leader stated Saturday in Chamber of Deputies that the
                                Brazilian Navy will only maintain a defensive coast patrol, which is
                                equivalent to a patrol against submarine bases and communication
                                between raiders and the shore. The Navy has no intention of
                                patrolling the high seas, which it is expected will be done by the
                                Allies. Brazil, not being a belligerent, has no right of visit and
                                search outside territorial waters and therefore can take no action
                                against raiders on the high seas. Should <persName corresp="#p_CRAWB1">Admiral Caperton</persName>’s squadron now
                                be withdrawn, Brazilian coast patrol would become useless and might
                                even be discontinued. The Brazilian Government would become
                                discouraged and Germany’s friends would represent, in the three
                                countries where the Admiral had been, that his visits were intended
                                to compel adhesion to United States plan rather than to express
                                appreciation of cooperation in the present or the future.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEV1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Morgan</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>