<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-10-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="498" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d498">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/7230</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Peruvian Minister</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FSMd1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Freyre</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-10-06">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 6, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>[A copy of the following translation of a telegram from the Peruvian
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs to the Peruvian Minister at Washington,
                                was handed by the Minister to the Secretary of State on October 8,
                                1917:]</p>
                            <p>After having vainly endeavored to procure that the German Government
                                settle our claim for the sinking of the Peruvian bark <hi rend="italic">Lorton</hi>, which occurred in February of this
                                year and constituted a violation of the fundamental principles of
                                international law, the Peruvian Government was compelled to exact of
                                the Imperial German Government a satisfactory solution of the
                                question, within a term of eight days. The German Government,
                                however, declared to the Peruvian Minister at Berlin that a solution
                                of the question within a peremptory term was absolutely impossible.
                                I, therefore, decided to inform Congress of the Government’s
                                resolution to break diplomatic relations with Germany, and Congress
                                approved this resolution by a <pb facs="0513" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> vote of 105 to 6. Instructions have been
                                forwarded immediately to the Peruvian Minister at Berlin that he
                                demand his passports, and passports have been handed to the German
                                Minister at Lima. We will address a direct communication on the
                                subject to the United States Government; in the meanwhile, you are
                                instructed to make it acquainted with the situation.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TDF1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tudela</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>