<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="624" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d624">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/3697</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RPS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Reinsch</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1407</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-01">
                                        <hi rend="italic">March 1, 1917</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received April 6.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my No. 1390 of
                                February 14 last,<note n="1" xml:id="d624fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_414">p.
                                    414</ref>.</note> and supplementing my telegrams of February 21,
                                6 p.m.,<note n="2" xml:id="d624fn2">Not printed.</note> and February
                                28, 7 p.m.,<note n="3" xml:id="d624fn3">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_412">p.
                                    412</ref>.</note> I have the honor further to report on the
                                Chinese protest against the German policy of submarine warfare.</p>
                            <p>Thus far the Chinese Government has not received a formal answer from
                                the Government of the German Empire. Dr. W. W. Yen, the Chinese
                                Minister at Berlin, telegraphed that he had been informed by the
                                German Foreign Office that instructions were being sent to the
                                German Minister at Peking. At the same time Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ZDA1">Zimmermann</persName> stated that Germany
                                found herself compelled by the action of her enemies to take radical
                                measures of defense, but that every care would be exercised to avoid
                                injury to. Chinese citizens. As stated, the German Legation has not
                                yet transmitted to the Foreign Office a formal reply to the Chinese
                                note.</p>
                            <p>Immediately after the announcement of the position taken by China,
                                the Japanese, who had up to that point discouraged Chinese
                                intervention, suddenly changed; they veered around so completely
                                that the officious Japanese press, following the lead of the Foreign
                                Office, stated that China had not gone far enough. Thenceforward,
                                increasingly strong pressure has been exerted by the Japanese
                                Foreign Office upon the Chinese Government, through the Chinese
                                Minister at Tokyo, with a view to inducing China to associate
                                herself with the Allies.</p>
                            <p>Among high Chinese officials, the alternative of joining the Allies
                                is at present considered as the course which will probably have to
                                be taken. The Vice President, whose connection with the Shanghai
                                opium purchase has injured his standing, appears to see in a war
                                policy an opportunity of rehabilitating himself. General <persName corresp="#p_TCj1">Tuan Chi-jui</persName> and a number of the
                                older officials are working with General <persName corresp="#p_FK1">Feng Kuo-chang</persName>, as they see a good chance of getting
                                the upper hand over Parliament and the President. Those leaders who
                                are specially under the influence of Japan are naturally in favor of
                                the suggested policy. There is considerable danger that the
                                movement, if carried through, would be entirely reactionary in
                                character, as far as Chinese political institutions and practices
                                are concerned. It is of course not known what arrangements have been
                                concluded between <pb facs="0597" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> General
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FK1">Feng</persName> and General <persName corresp="#p_TCj1">Tuan</persName>, both of whom are rivals for
                                the presidency. But it is suspected that should no arrangement
                                concerning the succession to the presidency prove possible, all
                                these forces may unite in an attempt to restore the Manchu Dynasty
                                and perpetuate the rule of the more reactionary elements.</p>
                            <p>If it had been possible for me to give any assurance of an active
                                interest on the part of the American Government in having China
                                continue to follow a concordant policy with the United States in
                                this matter, it would have been possible very decidedly to influence
                                the currents of opinion among the high Chinese officials. Under the
                                circumstances I had to confine myself to advising caution in taking
                                any further steps and to pointing out that China was entitled to
                                receive assurances as to essential points protective of her vital
                                rights before committing herself to any joint action.</p>
                            <p>In confidential conversation I asked the British Chargé d’Affaires
                                what effective assurances they could offer China were she to
                                cooperate with the Allies. He stated that he hoped that China could
                                be safeguarded. I am now informed that, in behalf of the Allies, the
                                French Minister called at the Foreign Office and expressed the
                                readiness of the Allies to give assurances with respect to financial
                                matters, such as the postponement of the instalments of the Boxer
                                indemnity and the upward revision of the Chinese customs tariff. The
                                Chinese themselves are more deeply concerned over the matter of the
                                exercise of their sovereign rights in connection with army control.
                                Should the Allies be able spontaneously to give joint assurances to
                                the effect that in the matter of military collaboration the Chinese
                                Government will be allowed to take its own action with only such
                                assistance as it may itself invite, I believe that the Chinese
                                Government would be very likely to associate itself with the
                                Allies.</p>
                            <p>There are herewith enclosed a copy of a despatch (No. 1174) of the
                                12th ultimo from the Consulate General at Shanghai, transmitting
                                certain newspaper reports concerning the subject matter of this
                                despatch, as well as clippings from the <hi rend="italic">Peking
                                    Gazette</hi> of February 28 and March 1, on the same
                                    subject.<note n="1" xml:id="d624fn4">Enclosures not
                                    printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RPS1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>