<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-01-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="762" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d762">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72111/4420</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5568</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-01-05">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 5, 1917</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 15.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your telegram No. 4216
                            December 27, 1916, 4 p.m. and my No. 5416 of the 4th instant<note n="1" xml:id="d762fn1">Telegram of Jan. 4 not printed.</note> in reply, I
                            have the honor to submit the following report. The difficulties in the
                            way of obtaining any reliable information on this subject have been
                            great, and I have not in fact suceeded in ascertaining anything worth
                            mentioning in regard to the reported activities in developing railroad
                            terminals and dock facilities at Halifax, North Sydney, and St. John’s,
                            nor on the point of the possible detail of disguised cruisers to protect
                            the lines of trade, but I have gathered privately from an Admiralty
                            source that though the British authorities do not appear to have taken
                            any very definite steps as yet they are undoubtedly considering steps
                            for the further protection of their merchant shipping to meet the
                            increased dangers they apprehend.</p>
                        <p>The British Government does not appear to know exactly where they stand
                            with our Government with regard to the arming of British merchantmen. In
                            spite of our general pronouncement to the effect that merchantmen may
                            properly be armed for defensive purposes they do not know how this would
                            work out in practice or whether our authorities have laid down specific
                            rules as to what constitutes defensive armament or what such rules might
                            be. They understand in a general way that there is to be a limitation in
                            number and in calibre of guns and that they should be mounted at the
                            stern, failing which that ships might be classed as warships.</p>
                        <p>The British authorities look for a recrudescence of submarine activity
                            off the American coast as soon as the Allies’ reply to the President’s
                            note is made public, and they feel it their duty to see to it that their
                            ships are adequately armed to meet this menace since from time
                            immemorial it has been the undisputed right of merchant <pb facs="0719" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/> men to arm for defense. In old times it
                            was not thought unusual for a merchantman to be armed not merely with
                            bow and stern chasers but with broadsides as well, and the necessity for
                            this sort of armament is greater to-day than ever before, for, whereas
                            in old times a hostile cruiser would be sighted on the horizon and the
                            merchantman would take to flight using her stern chasers for defense,
                            to-day a hostile submarine might suddenly appear on the surface a mile
                            ahead of the merchant ship and if the latter mounted guns only at the
                            stern she would be in no position to defend herself. So much for the
                            number and position of guns.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the calibre, the Admiralty has knowledge that the new
                            German submarines carry comparatively heavy guns with a range of
                            something like 8,000 yards. A merchantman with guns of less range might
                            just as well be totally unarmed.</p>
                        <p>A point which seems to me to be of some importance is that the British
                            Admiralty holds that there is nothing in the question as to whether
                            British merchantmen are armed for defense or offense. Whatever the
                            armament might be a merchantman to-day could be armed only for defense,
                            since there is nothing afloat against which she could take the
                            offensive. She can hot be armed for the purpose of seeking out and
                            destroying less heavily armed enemy merchant ships since none such is at
                            present on the high seas, and it is not reasonable to suppose that a
                            merchant ship, being without armor—no matter how numerous or how heavy
                            her guns, might be—could possibly be so rash as to attack an enemy
                            man-of-war, but a heavy and mobile armament obviously seems necessary
                            for merchantmen to meet the present submarine menace, and, if there is
                            any danger of British merchant ships being refused clearance papers in
                            American ports because of this, they may have to give up using American
                            ports whenever possible.</p>
                        <p>I do not know that any difficulties have lately arisen in American ports
                            with regard to this matter, but the British disposition appears to be
                            that they can not afford to take the risk of arming their ships properly
                            and then have three or four large ships libeled and interned at New
                            York. This would be too expensive a way of ascertaining the attitude of
                            our Government.</p>
                        <p>The foregoing should I think be considered in connection with the article
                            I enclose on arming merchantmen from yesterday’s <hi rend="italic">Morning Post</hi> and with the attached telegram in that newspaper
                            from its Washington correspondent which states that the question of
                            arming merchantmen is being reconsidered by the Neutrality Board, but
                            that the President is opposed to permitting merchant ships to be more
                            heavily armed than at present.<note n="1" xml:id="d762fn2">Not
                                printed.</note> This telegram also states that at <pb facs="0720" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/> present merchantmen are allowed two 6-inch
                            guns at the stern but no more.</p>
                        <p>Another danger in New York Harbor under present conditions is that the
                            municipal regulations appear to make it necessary for all ships entering
                            that port to take up a pilot, who is taken on board outside territorial
                            waters. This compels ships to come practically to a dead stop outside
                            the 3-mile limit and would give a lurking hostile submarine an enormous
                            advantage in attacking. The British Government, however, for obvious
                            reasons has no desire at this time to make any efforts toward inducing
                            neutrals to extend the limits of their territorial waters.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PWH1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter Hikes Page</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>