<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-04-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="830" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d830">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 701.6311/289a</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the British Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Spring Rice</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1541</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-04-19">
                                        <hi rend="italic">April 19, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to enclose
                                herewith a copy of a note from the Swedish Minister at this Capital,
                                representing Austro-Hungarian <pb facs="0769" n="597" xml:id="pg_597"/> interests in the United States,<note n="1" xml:id="d830fn1">Not printed.</note> in which, with reference to
                                the intended departure of <persName corresp="#p_TCA1">Count
                                    Tarnowski</persName> and the late Austro-Hungarian Chargé
                                d’Affaires at Washington, <persName corresp="#p_ZBE1">Baron
                                    Zwiedinek</persName>, and the persons of their suite, he
                                requests information on the following points: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Will there be any restrictions as to the personal goods
                                        and effects, particularly jewels and other valuables, they
                                        carry?</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Will there be any restrictions as to money, and, if so,
                                        how large an amount may each person carry?</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>May photographs and personal documents (certificates of
                                        birth, diplomas, etc.) be carried?</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>May official documents (in plain language) be
                                        carried?</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Referring to the statement orally made by you to the Assistant
                                Secretary of State that your Embassy had been authorized to grant to
                                the Austro-Hungarian diplomatic and consular officers a safe-conduct
                                so worded as to concede freedom to these officers to pass to their
                                destination, but containing no statement which would in any way
                                conflict with the rights of the British Government to search members
                                of the party and their effects, I beg to say that while this
                                Government, of course, is in thorough accord with the British
                                Government’s views in this respect, still, at the same time, in view
                                of the very great courtesy which has been extended by the
                                Austro-Hungarian Government to American diplomatic and consular
                                officers leaving Austria, I venture to express the hope that the
                                Austro-Hungarian party may be permitted to pass with the least
                                possible delay and will be shown every possible consideration.</p>
                            <p>I shall be very glad to be advised whether your Embassy will issue
                                such instructions as will enable the members of the party to carry a
                                reasonable amount of money and of the other articles mentioned in
                                the Minister’s inquiries.<note n="2" xml:id="d830fn2">No record of
                                    answer.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LR1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>