<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
        <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Third Four-Power
                                                Consultative Meeting on Charter Proposals, Held at
                                                San Francisco, May 3, 1945, 9:40 p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-05-03T23:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-03T23:40:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
                <body>
                        <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-03T23:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-03T23:40:00-05:00" n="205" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">RSC Lot 60–D 224, Box 99; UNCIO
                                        Cons. Four Min. 3</note>
                                <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Third Four-Power
                                                Consultative Meeting on Charter Proposals, Held at
                                                San Francisco, May 3, 1945, 9:40 p.m.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <dateline>
                                        <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-03T21:40:00-07:00">May 3, 1945, 9:40
                                                p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                                <opener>
                                        <seg rendition="#center">[Informal Notes—Extracts]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <p>[Here follows list of names of participants, including members of
                                        delegations of the United States (13); United Kingdom (4);
                                        Soviet Union (4); and China (4).]</p>
                                <p rend="center">1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Celebration of</hi> V–E <hi rend="smallcaps">Day</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                                <p rend="center">2. <hi rend="smallcaps">France’s Participation in
                                                Four Power Discussions</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said that M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> had called on him to express his
                                        regret at not participating in the conversations which he
                                        had heard were being held among the Four Delegations. Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>,
                                        in reply, had first expressed regret that France was not a
                                        sponsoring power and then proceeded to say that of course
                                        the heads of the four delegations had held discussions, as
                                        was only natural. M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> had then asked if he might join
                                        the meetings. When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> requested <pb facs="0644" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/> the views of the others,
                                        no objections were expressed to inviting the French to join
                                        the talks. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> remarked that in any case
                                        after May 4 there would not be many occasions on which
                                        meetings of the big powers would be necessary. When Dr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName> raised
                                        the question of France’s participation in the meetings of
                                        the Four Presidents of the Conference, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> said that
                                        this had not come up but he thought he could handle it;
                                        there was no comment.</p>
                                <p rend="center">3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Status of Consultation</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                                <p rend="center">4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Domestic Jurisdiction</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>At Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>’
                                        request <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        </hi> presented a report from the subcommittee on domestic
                                        jurisdiction. The subcommittee had agreed that the exception
                                        for domestic jurisdiction should cover not only the peaceful
                                        settlement of disputes, but should apply to the whole
                                        Charter except for threats to the peace, breaches of the
                                        peace and action with respect thereto. He submitted a report
                                        in this sense, pointing out that the only pointed issue was
                                        the inclusion of the words “by international law”. The
                                        United Kingdom and China were inclined to include them but
                                        the U.S.S.R and U.S. representatives on the subcommittee had
                                        preferred to exclude them due to the difficulty of
                                        establishing when a matter is by international law under
                                        domestic jurisdiction.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>
                                        </hi> expressed his approval of the Committee’s draft with
                                        the reference to international law included. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> preferred to keep paragraph 7 of VIII, A, intact. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi>, commenting that he preferred a “shade to a blank” and
                                        that international law is now only a shadow but may grow
                                        stronger, preferred to include reference to it. After
                                        Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName> had
                                        said that he agreed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> commented that the words “by international law” are in
                                        the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals and that he agreed with Dr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName> in
                                        desiring to keep them. After Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> had read
                                        the original paragraph 7 of VIII, A, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said that he was puzzled as he had understood that all
                                        had agreed on the new paragraph and that the only
                                        disagreement was over “by international law”. To this <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> had now reconsidered his
                                        position. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                                        </hi> indicated a preference for the old paragraph with the
                                        words “by international law” and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that if it was necessary to choose he
                                        preferred the new proposal without the reference to
                                        international law to the old one with it. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that the new draft will make the matter
                                        obscure.</p>
                                <p>Thereupon, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        </hi>, speaking at the request of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>, said that
                                        the exemption for domestic jurisdiction should cover the
                                        whole charter, as the matters to which it applies are not
                                        limited to <pb facs="0645" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> VIII,
                                        A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> then said that he would concur with the U.S. and
                                        U.S.S.R. position on a new paragraph without the words “by
                                        international law”, and, in reply to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s inquiry as to
                                        why there should be a departure from the good old Dumbarton
                                        Oaks language, said “because we have all agreed to.” <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> reiterated his preference for the old paragraph,
                                        indicating that he did not care one way or the other about
                                        the inclusion in that case of the phrase “by international
                                        law”. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> then said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> would explain the reason for the
                                        change and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        laughed.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MSW1">
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William Malkin</hi>
                                        </persName> undertook to answer Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s question by
                                        an illustration: The third paragraph of Chapter II provides
                                        for settlement of disputes by peaceful means and the U.K.
                                        desire to have the language about domestic jurisdiction
                                        cover this point. From the points of view of countries
                                        anxious on this point, the new text is better. When Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        inquired in what respect it was better, <persName corresp="#p_MSW1">
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William Malkin</hi>
                                        </persName> said that it was better because it covers this
                                        and other similar points. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                                        </hi> commented that under the new text, a state has a
                                        larger option to reserve domestic jurisdiction and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> added that in the new form and location it applied
                                        even to Assembly discussion. When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> put the
                                        question as to whether or not to accept the subcommittee
                                        recommendation, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName> inquired whether agreement had not
                                        been reached on the new text, and after <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said he had thought so, both of them indicated a
                                        preference for the new with the words “by international
                                        law”. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> repeated that he saw no reason to change but he
                                        thought the reference to international law in paragraph 7 of
                                        VIII, A, might be thrown out. Upon Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>’ request
                                        for his suggestion as to the way to settle the difference,
                                        he replied he would leave it as it is in the Dumbarton Oaks
                                        Proposals except for the words “by international law”. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> commented that this had been the original suggestion
                                        by the U.S.<note n="84" xml:id="d205fn1">See memorandum
                                                entitled “Changes in Dumbarton Oaks Proposals as
                                                Suggested by the United States Delegation,” May 2,
                                                1945, <hi rend="italic">Postwar Foreign Policy
                                                  Preparation</hi>, p. 679.</note>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        </hi>, after Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> had restated Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s position,
                                        said that he did not think this proposal was as good as the
                                        revision.</p>
                                <p>After further discussion and an inquiry by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> as to
                                        whether the four wished to refer the matter back to the
                                        subcommittee, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> clarified his understanding as follows: (1) under the
                                        old text domestic matters might be considered international
                                        issues except under one chapter (VIII–A); (2) under the new
                                        text domestic matters were generally protected. That is why
                                        he preferred the new paragraph.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> thought the amendment led in exactly the opposite
                                        direction, but Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> agreed with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>. After further <pb facs="0646" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> discussion in
                                        which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        remarked that he was afraid the new text might permit
                                        interference in the relations between the U.K. and India,
                                        and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had said
                                        that he wanted the new language to remove just such a
                                        possibility, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> summed the matter up by saying that there appeared to
                                        be agreement on what was wanted, to which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> nodded
                                        affirmatively. Before it was agreed to send the matter back
                                        to the subcommittee, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> restated the U.S. position
                                        and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> concurred
                                        in this.</p>
                                <p rend="center">5.<note n="*" xml:id="d205fn2">Minutes of the
                                                Subcommittee on Treaties annexed. [Footnote in the
                                                original; minutes not printed.]</note>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Revision of Treaties</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> reported that the subcommittee had not yet agreed and
                                        was going to meet again the next day. He suggested that this
                                        subject therefore not be discussed by the four for the
                                        moment and then inquired whether it was the understanding of
                                        the other three that if the four failed to reach agreement,
                                        they would act independently and separately in the
                                        committees. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>
                                        and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> said
                                        yes and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> said,
                                        “yes—reluctantly”.</p>
                                <p rend="center">6. <hi rend="smallcaps">Economic and Social
                                                Council</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>After Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> had
                                        introduced this subject by saying that there appeared to be
                                        a substantial measure of agreement, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName>
                                        </hi> reported from a subcommittee. He said that all were
                                        agreed on the inclusion in Chapter IX, Section A, paragraph
                                        1, and Section C, paragraph 1 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) of
                                        the word “cultural”. The U.S.S.R, and the U.K. with Chinese
                                        support wished to insert a new paragraph after C1 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) relating to respect for human
                                        rights and fundamental freedoms. As to Section D, paragraph
                                        1, the U.K., the U.S.S.R., and China were opposed to
                                        spelling out the reference to several commissions. He read
                                        the new text, showing the changes, including insertions
                                        pointing out the changes and stating that their effect was
                                        to give greater prominence to human rights and fundamental
                                        freedoms. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName>
                                        </hi> then said that the U.S. Delegation prefers to specify
                                        in Section D, paragraph 1, reference to economic, social and
                                        other activities and to the promotion of human rights. When
                                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName> said that
                                        he had not yet seen the latest U.S. proposal as read by Dr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName>, the
                                        latter explained that the U.S. Delegation had not agreed on
                                        it until 8:00 o’clock.<note n="85" xml:id="d205fn3">Minutes
                                                of meeting, May 3, 6:20 p.m., <ref target="#pg_574">p. 574</ref>.</note>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName>
                                        </hi> then said that he preferred this language; he did not
                                        want to mention commissions but this language was all right.
                                        All agreed on the <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName> report and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said that that ended the subcommittee report.</p>
                                <p rend="center">7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Basis of Selecting
                                                Non-Permanent Members of the Council</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said that the next question was that of inserting some
                                        qualifications with respect to the election of non-permanent
                                        members <pb facs="0647" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> of the
                                        Council in Section A of Chapter VI, and restated the earlier
                                        positions of the four delegations.<note n="86" xml:id="d205fn4">See minutes of Four-Power meeting,
                                                May 2, 9 p.m., <ref target="#pg_548">p.
                                                548</ref>.</note>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> stated that the U.K. Delegation had a new proposal
                                        which he proceeded to read. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> thought this a very good
                                        proposal and then when <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>
                                        </hi> said he preferred the words “equitable geographical
                                        distribution” both Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> approved
                                        the change.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> thought that contribution towards the maintenance of
                                        peace and security and geographical distribution should not
                                        be put on the same plane and therefore proposed insertion of
                                        the words “and also” between the two clauses and the
                                        omission of the symbols (A) and (B). When <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                                        </hi> inquired why the words “in the first instance” were
                                        inserted, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> explained that it was because the contribution to
                                        peace and security should come first. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                                        </hi> then said that he thought the U.S. should reserve its
                                        position, but <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said it was necessary to reach a decision and asked
                                        whether the two factors could not be put on the same plane.
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> commented that some nations are interested in one
                                        criterion, some in another, to which <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that everyone should be interested in the
                                        first criterion. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> withdrew his objection and
                                        Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName> his
                                        reservation, and all agreed to the U.K. Proposal as modified
                                        by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>’s and
                                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s
                                        amendments.</p>
                                <p rend="center">8. <hi rend="smallcaps">Eights of Non-Member
                                                States</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> stated that the U.S. withdrew its reservation to the
                                        proposed Chinese proposal for an addition to paragraph 2 of
                                        VIII, A, respecting the requirement that non-member states
                                        accept the obligations of peaceful settlement provided in
                                        the Charter. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> also withdrew his objections and
                                        this amendment was therefore agreed to.</p>
                                <p rend="center">9. <hi rend="smallcaps">Security Council
                                                Recommendations of Terms of Settlement</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>In introducing the discussion of the U.K. Proposal for an
                                        addition to paragraph 4 of VIII, A,<note n="87" xml:id="d205fn5">For text, see minutes of Four-Power
                                                meeting, May 4, 12:15 p.m., <ref target="#pg_598">p.
                                                  598</ref>.</note>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> expressed regret that U.S. still could not accept the
                                        change. To this <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> (or another U.K. spokesman) commented that this is a
                                        very important matter.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> then explained that this introduced a new element into
                                        the picture: to give the Council the power to recommend
                                        terms of settlement on its own alters the scheme laid down
                                        in Dumbarton Oaks, and extends the Council’s powers very
                                        considerably. He thought it would lead to great difficulty.
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> in reply said that what worried him was that the
                                        Council would not be able without this amendment to do as
                                        much as it should. He thought it ought to go just as far as
                                        possible in the realm of peaceful settlement. <pb facs="0648" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MSW1">
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William Malkin</hi>
                                        </persName> added that it is not true that this introduces
                                        something new. If under 4 as it stands, the Council does not
                                        have this power of recommending terms of settlement,
                                        paragraph 4 has no meaning, for all the Council can do is to
                                        recommend to the states that they use arbitration or other
                                        means of peaceful settlement, and the Council can already do
                                        this under paragraph 5.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that in writing paragraphs 4 and 5 at
                                        Dumbarton Oaks, they had introduced a progression. He
                                        explained his own understanding of this progression and
                                        added that they had stopped short of permitting the Security
                                        Council to recommend terms of settlement because they did
                                        not wish it to take the still further step of imposing a
                                        settlement. The U.S. Delegation was not prepared to go so
                                        far as to permit the imposition of settlement and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> said he took it that the U.K. was not, either. He
                                        thought it bad to permit the Council to recommend terms of
                                        settlement without giving it the powers to impose its terms;
                                        this would weaken the Council. As matters now stand the
                                        Council can in any case take enforcement action if the
                                        dispute is not settled.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> announced that he would accept whatever the U.K. and
                                        the USA Delegation could agree upon. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName> wanted to
                                        consider the matter further.</p>
                                <p>After Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had
                                        mentioned the Senate, indicating his great respect for it,
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said that this matter could not be settled now. When
                                        he added that he felt it was one on which the four powers
                                        would have to go their own ways, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said that he hoped this would not be the case.</p>
                                <p rend="center">10. <hi rend="smallcaps">Amendment to
                                                Paragraph</hi> 1 <hi rend="smallcaps">of Section B,
                                                Chapter</hi> VIII</p>
                                <p>After Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> had
                                        recapitulated the different positions with respect to the
                                        proposal for introducing a reference to paragraph 4 of
                                        Section A into paragraph 1 of VIII, B, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> stated that the U.S. feels this would be very broad
                                        and inquired whether the U.K. Delegation felt that this
                                        would permit the imposition of a settlement. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName>Jeeb</persName>
                                        </hi> (U.K.) replied that VII, B, limits the Council to
                                        enforcement action. When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName> inquired whether he was right
                                        in interpreting this as meaning the Council could not go
                                        beyond military action to impose a settlement, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said that he considered the imposition of a settlement
                                        as falling short of military action.</p>
                                <p>After further discussion it was agreed, on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>’ proposal,
                                        that this matter be carried over and be considered later in
                                        connection with the U.K. amendment to paragraph 4 of VIII,
                                        A.</p>
                                <p rend="center">11. <hi rend="smallcaps">Provisional Measures</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> stated that the U.S. Delegation now accepts the
                                        Chinese proposal to insert a new paragraph regarding
                                        provisional <pb facs="0649" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                                        measures between paragraphs 2 and 3 of Chapter VIII, Section
                                        B. This amendment is now therefore agreed upon by all four
                                        powers.</p>
                                <p rend="center">12. <hi rend="smallcaps">Subcommittees of the
                                                Military Staff Committee</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>In introducing the question of subcommittees to the Military
                                        Staff Committee, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> called upon <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi>, who said that the U.S. would accept the addition at
                                        the end of paragraph 9 of VIII, B, of a sentence reading
                                        “The Military Staff Committee, with the authorization of the
                                        Security Council, may establish its own regional
                                        subcommittees.” This was agreed upon by all four.</p>
                                <p>Upon Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s inquiry
                                        as to whether that finished the items relating to Chapter
                                        VIII, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                                        </hi> said it did except for the amendment to paragraph 2 of
                                        Section C, which was still in subcommittee.</p>
                                <p rend="center">13. <hi rend="smallcaps">Specific Reference to the
                                                International Labor Organization</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> stated that the U.S. views respecting the U.K.
                                        proposal to insert specific reference to the International
                                        Labor Organization remained the same, that is, the U.S. was
                                        opposed.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>
                                        </hi> said that this amendment was too sweeping. After Mr.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had said
                                        that each country could reserve its own position on this,
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> inquired whether the subcommittee had discussed it.
                                        When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        said it had, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> inquired of the other three whether it was true that
                                        none of them liked the U.K. proposal. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> indicated that in view of the subcommittee’s position
                                        there was no point in referring the matter again to a
                                        subcommittee and asked whether the others would like to
                                        discuss the question hi the big four at this time. He said
                                        that he agreed with the U.S. and Chinese delegations in
                                        opposing the amendment. Then <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> reiterated that the U.K. would reserve its position to
                                        bring the proposal up in the Conference committee. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> asked if it was true that there was no intention to
                                        reorganize the ILO, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that that was correct, but that there would be
                                        some improvement and then it would be transferred to the new
                                        organization. When <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> asked whether the present structure is sacrosanct, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said it was not but that the ILO would do its own
                                        reorganizing. He added that the U.K. hoped it would take its
                                        place in the new world organization. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName>
                                        </hi> emphasized that the ILO is an existing autonomous body
                                        with its own constitution.</p>
                                <p>In reply to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> pointed out that the ILO cannot be brought in
                                        completely sis the U.S.S.R. is not a member of that body.
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        </hi> said he realized that and that it was most
                                        unfortunate.</p>
                                <p>The discussion at this point was brought to a close by <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> saying that the consultation was now ended and that he
                                        understood the U.K. would go its own way on this matter.
                                        This was agreed on.</p>
                                <pb facs="0650" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/>
                                <p rend="center">14. <hi rend="smallcaps">Election of the Secretary
                                                General and Deputies</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> introduced the question of the Soviet amendment to
                                        Chapter X by reviewing its status and then announcing that
                                        the U.S. was ready to state its position but before doing so
                                        desired to call on the Chinese Delegation. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_STV1">Soong</persName>
                                        </hi> parried the question by asking the U.S. position and
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> eventually said the U.S. favored a three-year term for
                                        the election of a Secretary General as suggested by the
                                        U.S.S.R. After it had been pointed out that the U.S.S.R.
                                        proposal was for a two-year term, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> remarked that
                                        that was correct.</p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> went on to say that the U.S. would like the Secretary
                                        General to be eligible for reelection and suggested that the
                                        Soviet reconsider its position. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> replied that he did not wish to press on this point
                                        and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> said then that there would be no limit to the number
                                        of times the Secretary General could be reelected.</p>
                                <p>All agreed to the three-year term with eligibility for
                                        reelection.</p>
                                <p rend="center">15. <hi rend="smallcaps">Further Subcommittee
                                                Meetings</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                                <p rend="center">16. <hi rend="smallcaps">Amendments of Other
                                                Delegations</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> raised the question of the manner in which the four
                                        would deal with amendments proposed by other delegations.
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> in reply suggested we let others propose their
                                        amendments and then talk about them. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> inquired whether the four expected to discuss among
                                        themselves any questions raised by amendments from other
                                        countries. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                        and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        agreed that this was desirable and the latter thought that
                                        M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> should be
                                        brought in as well. To Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s inquiry as to why the French
                                        should be included, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                                        </hi> referred to his statement at the beginning of the
                                        meeting and said that the meetings beginning the following
                                        week should consist of the five foreign ministers. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                                        </hi> said he had no objection. Agreed.</p>
                                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                                <p>The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
                        </div>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
