<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Thirty-Fourth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 9, 1945, 5:30 p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d220</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">220</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-05-09T19:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-09T19:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-09T19:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-09T19:30:00-05:00" n="220" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">RSC Lot 60–D 224, Box 96: U.S. Cr. Min. 34</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Thirty-Fourth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Wednesday, May 9, 1945, 5:30 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-09T17:30:00-07:00">May 9, 1945, 5:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Informal Notes—Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of persons (30) present at meeting.]</p>
                <p>The Secretary of State opened the meeting at 5:32 p.m.</p>
                <pb facs="0717" n="655" xml:id="pg_655"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Announcements</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Appointment of Members of the Coordination Committee</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> stated that it was necessary to appoint
                    at once the members of the Coordination Committee, which was to meet at 6:00
                        o’clock.<note n="51" xml:id="d220fn1">Doc. 198, CO/2 May 10, UNCIO
                        Documents, vol. 15, p. 5.</note> This Committee was to comprise fourteen
                    members, namely, one deputy for each member of the Executive Committee. It had
                    also been agreed that each deputy would have an alternate. <hi rend="smallcaps">The secretary</hi> proposed that the deputy and alternate for the United
                    States be Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName> respectively. This proposal was approved
                    by the Delegation.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Attendance at Commission and Committee Meetings of the
                        World Trade Union and of Other Organizations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> remarked that he wished to submit to the
                    Delegation an emergency matter on which a decision must be taken without delay.
                    The problem arose out of a vote taken by the Economic and Social Committee to
                    invite the World Trade Union Conference to send a representative to the meetings
                    of the Committee.<note n="52" xml:id="d220fn2">See Doc. 189, II/3/7, May 10,
                        UNCIO Documents, vol. 10, p. 16; see also, Doc. 83, II/3, May 4, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. 8, p. 7. See Doc. 165, ST/4, May 9, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. 5, p. 187, meeting of the Steering
                        Committee on May 8, 3:35 p.m., for data on approval of recommendation of the
                        Secretary General to leave to the bodies concerned the matter of inviting
                        the representatives of the five intergovernmental organizations to attend
                        meetings.</note> He requested Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hiss</persName>
                    to explain the situation.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hiss</persName>
                    </hi> explained the parliamentary situation stating that the Steering Committee
                    was the only body of the Conference competent to pass upon the subject and that
                    it had made a positive but not a negative decision, i.e., it had approved an
                    invitation to the five official organizations but had not explicitly ruled out
                    invitations to the other organizations. He was of the opinion that if the
                    question of the invitation to the World Trade Union Conference were brought up
                    in the Steering Committee an acrimonious debate would ensue.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> requested that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hiss</persName> call a meeting of the Steering Committee
                    for 10:30 the next morning to consider the question.<note n="53" xml:id="d220fn3">Doc. 224, ST/7, May 11, UNCIO Documents, vol. 5, p.
                        207.</note> He likewise requested Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hiss</persName> to hold up sending the invitation of the Economic and
                    Social Committee pending a final disposition of the issue.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of schedule of Committee meetings, proposed Conference
                    procedure on drafting of the final Charter, background talks by the Delegates on
                    the amendments to the Dumbarton <pb facs="0718" n="656" xml:id="pg_656"/> Oaks
                    Proposals made by the Big Four, and procedure in the Committees.]</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Non-Permanent Membership on the Security Council</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> remarked that pressure for an increase in the membership of the Security
                    Council up to fifteen members was building up and asked for suggestions on how
                    this could be met. He thought that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName> might have something to contribute on this point
                    since a great deal of the pressure was emanating from the Latin American group.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> said that this was in part a reflection of the desire of Brazil for a
                    permanent seat and of the group as a whole for at least two nonpermanent
                    seats.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> expressed the opinion that the delegations pressing for an increase
                    in membership should be reminded that the five permanent members represented 65
                    percent of the peoples of the world. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> said in this connection that in the Assembly all states, regardless of
                    size and importance, would have an equal vote and that a majority would elect
                    six of the members of the Security Council. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> characterized the discussion developing on this subject as “academic”
                    since an increase in the permanent and non-permanent members was out of the
                    question. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> held that while this might be true it was desirable and wise to allow full
                    and free discussion since it would permit the middle and small states to “get
                    the thing off their chests”.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">Commander Stassen</persName>’s Progress Report
                        on Trusteeship</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> reported that the conversations with the other four powers had not
                    yet reached the stage where anything could be approved and indicated that the
                    following problems were being discussed: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the non-discriminatory language was opposed by the British and the
                            French and the possibility of a different approach was being
                            explored.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the British opposed the distinction between strategic and
                            non-strategic territories.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the handling of welfare problems of the inhabitants of the trusteeship
                            territories was causing difficulties and it had been suggested that
                            jurisdiction over these problems be delegated by the Security Council to
                            the trustee governments.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>we were opposing a British proposal that the trusteeship governments
                            have the right to conscript the forces and facilities of the trusteeship
                            territory.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>the British and French opposed the right to petition and investigate.
                            We were standing firm on the right to petition and would insist on some
                            right of inspection within the general trusteeship territories.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                        <item>France was opposed to the self-government phrase, apparently because
                            of the absence of an adequate equivalent in French. The <pb facs="0719" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/> British were prepared to accept this
                            terminology with proper qualifications.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FP1">Fraser</persName>, the Chairman of the Committee,
                    was anxious to proceed without delay and a comparative study of the proposals
                    was now being prepared.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The meeting was adjourned at 6:27 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
