<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Thirty-Sixth Meeting of the United States Delegation, Held at
                    San Francisco, Friday, May 11, 1945, 2:30 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-05-11T16:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-11T16:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec0IxeMNnec48ljR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional security</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-11T16:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-11T16:30:00-05:00" n="222"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">RSC Lot 60–D 224, Box 96: U.S. Cr. Min. 36</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Thirty-Sixth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, Held at San Francisco, Friday, May 11, 1945, 2:30 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1945-05-11T14:30:00-07:00">May 11, 1945, 2:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Informal Notes]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of persons (30) present at meeting.]</p>
                <pb facs="0726" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>, in the absence of the
                    Secretary, convened the meeting at 2:40 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Regional Arrangements</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> requested Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName> to report on the
                    new draft on regional arrangements.<note n="63" xml:id="d222fn1">See annex, <ref
                            target="#pg_674">p. 674</ref>.</note> …</p>
                <p>(At this point the Secretary entered the room.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> took the Chair and informed the meeting
                    that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> planned to leave Sunday
                    morning because of the situation in England. He will call on President
                        <persName>Truman</persName> on his way through Washington but will not
                    discuss the problems of the Conference. A public statement to this effect will
                    be made both by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and the Secretary
                    at an opportune moment. <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had expressed anxiety over the
                    regional problem at the morning meeting in the Penthouse<note n="64"
                        xml:id="d222fn2">In his <hi rend="italic">Diary</hi> of May 11, Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> noted: “<persName
                            corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> came to talk with me at 10:30 this
                        morning and I did not talk, but we have got to talk to him on this before he
                        goes.”</note> and indicated that he was favorably impressed by the French
                    amendment to Chapter VI, Section C.<note n="65" xml:id="d222fn3">Doc. 2, G/7
                            (<hi rend="italic">o</hi>), March 21, UNCIO Documents, vol. 3, pp.
                        384.</note> In this respect he appeared to share the opinion expressed
                    recently by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_PE1">Padilla</persName> of Mexico. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> added that he had tentatively called a
                    meeting of the Big Five for tonight<note n="66" xml:id="d222fn4">The meeting was
                        not held.</note> to discuss the matter. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> had talked by telephone with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> and the Secretary with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HC1"
                        >Hull</persName>. The former had indicated that he would discuss the formula
                    with the Secretary of War and report back his views. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                    </hi> said that he had discussed the problem in an informal way with the Chiefs
                    of Staff who had indicated that they did not want to take a position which would
                    interfere with the working out of a political formula.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> called on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1"
                        >Gates</persName> who reported on the reaction in Washington. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> confirmed that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> had
                    discussed the problem yesterday with the Chiefs of Staff but indicated that at
                    that time they did not have the new formula.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> reported on the conversation with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HC1"
                        >Hull</persName> who had indicated that he considered the draft might offer
                    a possible solution but wanted to mull over the formula. He had raised two
                    questions: (1) whether the formula might encourage states to take themselves out
                    of the Security Council, and (2) whether a political conflict might not ensue if
                    an American state attacked another, requiring a decision by the Security Council
                    and the adoption of a position by the United States. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> reported that he had indicated to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HC1"
                        >Hull</persName> that states would take action under the formula only if the
                    Security Council failed and a state was attacked; the Security Council would
                    have to <pb facs="0727" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/> decide to go to the aid of the
                    State attacked or to call a halt to the hostilities. This must be left to the
                    discretion of the Security Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> requested the opinion of the military
                    people and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he could not speak for them. <hi rend="smallcaps">The
                        Chair</hi> inquired if <persName corresp="#p_ELGSD1">General
                        Embick</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_WVAR1">Admiral Willson</persName>
                    could express their personal views. <persName corresp="#p_ELGSD1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">General Embick</hi>
                    </persName> reported that he had been in telephonic conversation with Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> who considered the formula
                    satisfactory. <persName corresp="#p_FMMS1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">General Fairchild</hi>
                    </persName> agreed with this and <persName corresp="#p_WVAR1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Willson</hi>
                    </persName> expressed the opinion that “in view of the history of the subject”
                    he thought the draft was adequate.</p>
                <p>(At this point <persName corresp="#p_HAAJ1">Admiral Hepburn</persName> entered
                    the room.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> said that the draft should not be discussed
                    with the President in Washington until after the Delegation had agreed. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> gave assurances that the military people in Washington would limit their
                    discussions of the proposal to their own group.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HAAJ1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Hepburn</hi>
                    </persName> reported that he had talked with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> who had said that his impression and that of others in
                    Washington was that the Draft in its present form might weaken the world
                    organization; that it was satisfactory in so far as it related to the protection
                    of the inter-American system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">MacLeish</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if the idea of attack in the draft was not too vague and recalled
                    that Germany had entered Poland at the beginning of the present war on the
                    pretext that Poland had attacked her. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> referred to the Act of Chapultepec. He said that it had two parts: first,
                    it incorporated the principle that an attack on one American republic is an
                    attack on all. The second part recommends the conclusion of a treaty consistent
                    with the principles and purposes of the new international organization. He
                    thought that it was hard to reconcile on paper the establishment of two police
                    groups, the regional and the world. However, he saw no real clash because it was
                    highly unlikely that a local police group would be established in the Western
                    Hemisphere. The proposed draft takes the first part of the Act and recognizes
                    that it establishes a valid principle. The use of the word “attack” is already
                    in the Act of Chapultepec. We thus take the operative part of the Act and say it
                    is acceptable, subject to the concurrent power of the Security Council. The
                    French proposed amendment to Chapter VI, Section C, is substantially similar in
                    concept—if the Security Council fails to act then states can take measures of
                    defense. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> thought that the French proposal was unduly restrictive, involving a
                    negative concept. The problem was to indicate definitely when there was a
                    failure on the part of the Security Council. However, the basic concept in the
                    two, that is, the French and the new draft, is the same, i.e., the inherent
                    right of self-defense cannot be immobilized.</p>
                <pb facs="0728" n="666" xml:id="pg_666"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> inquired whether the Security Council could take cognizance of a situation
                    in which there was an attack and a counterattack by other states acting in
                    self-defense. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1"
                            >Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> replied in the affirmative and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> added that however the states were not obliged to discontinue their
                    countermeasures taken in self-defense. In other words, that there was concurrent
                    power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> recalled that since the deadline had
                    passed for the submission of amendments, no new proposal could be offered and
                    that, therefore, we had to build on the French proposal. He also inquired
                    whether it was necessary to mention the Act of Chapultepec. He thought that it
                    would be hard to negotiate the new draft with the British and the Russians if
                    the Act was mentioned. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1"
                            >Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> agreed that perhaps it might not be necessary to mention the Act but that
                    we could start with it as a negotiating point. It could be dropped later if
                    necessary. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1"
                            >Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> agreed but emphasized that the mention of the Act had a sales value for
                    the Latin American group. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1"
                            >Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> thought, however, that the general language of the draft took care of the
                    idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> was very strongly of the opinion that the
                    time had arrived when, while recognizing the strategic importance of
                    inter-American solidarity, we should not allow ourselves to be compelled to
                    adopt a position contrary to our own view of national interest … The United
                    States must lead, not follow. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> said the Secretary had given the right kind of leadership and that the
                    attitude of some of the Latin American republics merely reflected the grave
                    concern they felt over developments which they believe tended to weaken the
                    inter-American system. This concern made them say things that they ordinarily
                    would not say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> said that some of the Latin American
                    representatives had come to the Penthouse and declared that they had lost
                    confidence in the Conference and that recent developments made them entertain
                    doubts that an effective international organization could be created here and
                    that it might be necessary to build a fence around the hemisphere. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> added that we had come to this Conference to
                    create an international organization and could not be deviated from that course.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> referred to the support given the American Delegation with respect to the
                    Trade Union conference, despite the fact that Mr. <persName>Toledano</persName>
                    <note n="67" xml:id="d222fn5">
                        <persName>Lombardo Toledano</persName>, Mexican labor leader.</note> had had
                    many of the Latin American delegations lined up in favor of admission. He did
                    not think that they were motivated by an isolationist spirit and recalled that
                    most of the Latin American republics had been members of the League while we had
                    stayed out of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NHA1">Notter</persName>
                    </hi> spoke against the mention of the Act of Chapultepec and said that under
                    the Act several states, not including the United <pb facs="0729" n="667"
                        xml:id="pg_667"/> States, could take action against another American state
                    and the United States would have to deal with the consequences of such a
                    situation in the Security Council. The right of self-defense is an inherent
                    right and is not restricted to the case of a direct attack. The concept is much
                    broader. He recalled that the concept of an indivisible peace had dominated the
                    thinking of Mr. <persName>Roosevelt</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HC1"
                        >Hull</persName>, President <persName>Truman</persName>, and Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>. This concept is that an
                    attack against one state in any part of the world is an act against all. This is
                    the concept of world security, not of regional security.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HGH1">Hackworth</persName>
                    </hi> said that the Act was mentioned merely by way of example. The Act is in
                    fact merely a first step toward the ambition of the United States to prevent and
                    stop aggression through the creation of a world security system. He did not
                    think that we were setting a precedent by referring to the Act since the
                    precedent was already in Article XXII [<hi rend="italic">XXI</hi>] of the
                        League.<note n="68" xml:id="d222fn6">Reference is apparently to article 21:
                        “Nothing in this Covenant shall be deemed to affect the validity of
                        international engagements, such as treaties of arbitration or regional
                        understandings like the Monroe Doctrine, for securing the maintenance of
                        peace”, <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_92">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris Peace Conference,
                            1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 92</ref>.</note> He
                    thought that it would be helpful in securing the support of the Latin American
                    bloc and to the world at large to have an example of the kind of regional
                    undertaking that we consider desirable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> inquired as to the distinction between “attack” in the first sentence and
                    “armed attack” in the second sentence. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> explained that the distinction was made deliberately in order to cover the
                    Monroe Doctrine which has two parts—the case of an overt attack and that of
                    political efforts from outside the continent to overthrow the political
                    institutions of the American Republics. Perhaps the word “attack” could be used
                    to cover both contingencies but the second has specific reference to collective
                    action under the Act of Chapultepec. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName
                            corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> understood from this that the first was broad enough to cover a propaganda
                    attack.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if it would not suffice to use the language of Article XXII [<hi
                        rend="italic">XXI</hi>] of the League Covenant. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> read Article XXII [<hi rend="italic">XXI</hi>] and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> recalled that he had drafted similar language which would cover both the
                    Monroe Doctrine and regional arrangements and indicated a personal preference
                    for such language. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> thought that this would open up regionalism; that the League Article XXII
                        [<hi rend="italic">XXI</hi>] was adequate for its time but not now. The new
                    draft doesn’t refer to regional arrangements. It avoids the idea of regionalism
                    in preference for the concept of self-defense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> reported that the discussions yesterday in Washington were based on the
                    previous idea developed by the Delegation, that is, <pb facs="0730" n="668"
                        xml:id="pg_668"/> that we proceed by way of an exception of the American
                    system to the provision of prior authorization for enforcement actions He
                    thought the present draft was broader and presumably covered regionalism in
                    other parts of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> said that the problem is broader and that if we proceeded by way of
                    exception in Section C, Chapter VIII, we would encourage the specific mention of
                    other regional arrangements, including the Arab League. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> inquired whether since we have a unique system in this hemisphere we would
                    not be justified in insisting on an exception. <hi rend="smallcaps">The
                        Chairman</hi> thought that we could not expect special consideration for the
                    inter-American system in the Charter. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> agreed with this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WVAR1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Willson</hi>
                    </persName> said that this was a compromise which gives all regional systems the
                    right of automatic action but retains in the general organization the exclusive
                    right to determine when there is a threat to the peace.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> expressed the opinion that the Advisers had done an able job and
                    that he would join in a recommendation to the President that the draft be
                    accepted, after the Secretaries of War and Navy had been heard from. He
                    considered that this was a high policy decision which must be passed upon by the
                    President. He thought the formula was a satisfactory compromise since it (1)
                    placed no restrictions on pacific settlement by regional means, (2) recognizes
                    the paramount authority of the world organization in enforcement but (3)
                    permitted freedom of action for all in the event of failure by the general
                    organization and of an attack. He thought the formula fits both world and
                    regional requirements. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1"
                            >Gates</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if this formula didn’t encourage regionalism which would shut us
                    out of other parts of the world in which we had a direct and vital interest.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> thought it did not since it applied only in case of an attack. We
                    cannot prevent an immediate response to a direct attack and moreover this
                    provision did not affect enforcement action. This was the same principle as in
                    private law in which defense must have relation to the nature of the attack. In
                    the case of propaganda we would respond with propaganda. In the case of an armed
                    attack we would respond with an armed attack, this however, without prejudice to
                    the continued authority of the Security Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> stressed that the principle operates if the Security Council is paralyzed
                    by unwarranted exercise of the veto power and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> agreed and stressed that the Act of Chapultepec has a symbolic value
                    similar to the Monroe Doctrine and that it would be helpful to have a specific
                    reference to it in the formula. <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> agreed with this opinion and said that if the principle is sound we
                    should have a specific mention. The Act is the modern Monroe Doctrine. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SDV1">Sandifer</persName>
                    </hi> expressed the opinion that it was <pb facs="0731" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"
                    /> not desirable to include the Act since it was a transient instrument. To this
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HGH1">Hackworth</persName>
                    </hi> said that the Act has two parts, one of which relates to the war period
                    and ends with it and the other to the postwar in which the implementation of the
                    Act is contemplated through the negotiation of a treaty. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> thought there was merit in the mention of the Act in so far as it might
                    constitute a warning to other states to keep out of this hemisphere and in so
                    far as it might give body and content to the vague concept of self-defense. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> inquired whether it might not be desirable
                    to mention the Monroe Doctrine and <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName
                            corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> thought that such a reference was outdated—that we had gone beyond the
                    point where we could speak exclusively of the Monroe Doctrine. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GOB1">Gerig</persName>
                    </hi> called attention to the fact that mention of the Monroe Doctrine in
                    Article XXII [<hi rend="italic">XXI</hi>] in the League Covenant had always
                    proved rather embarrassing at Geneva; that it was very difficult to explain to
                    non-American states precisely what was meant by the Monroe Doctrine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> at this point canvassed the opinion of the
                    meeting and it was agreed that the new draft should be discussed with the other
                    sponsoring governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName>
                    </hi> said that there appeared to be consensus that the draft represented our
                    maximum demands. He thought this should be made clear to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> so that he would have the assurance that
                    later on we would not ask for more. <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> again
                    said that in the discussions he would stress that we had built on the French
                    amendment and would discuss the draft in general terms, since the specific text
                    had not yet been cleared by the War and Navy Departments or approved by the
                    President. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> thought it desirable not to say that the new draft was a modification of
                    the French amendment but rather that it was based on the French position. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> thought that the Delegation must come to a definite conclusion and stand
                    by it in the discussions with the other powers. He said that it might be well to
                    emulate <persName>Stalin</persName>’s tactics at Yalta where he had told
                        <persName>Churchill</persName> and <persName>Roosevelt</persName> that he
                    could not vary from the position he had taken; that it was the <hi rend="italic"
                        >sine qua non</hi> of Russian approval of the Yalta conclusions. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> agreed that a firm position should be taken
                    but thought it should be with respect to the fundamental ideas contained in the
                    draft and not on the exact text.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Rockefeller</persName>
                    </hi> said that the draft under consideration represented our minimum demands,
                    not the maximum, as Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName> had
                    indicated. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BI1">Bowman</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he had reference solely to the fact that <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> is about to leave and the Secretary must
                    take a position and inform <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> that he
                    can leave with the assurance that his deputies will not be called upon to make
                    greater concessions later on. <persName corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> thought that the draft represented both the minimum and the
                    maximum.</p>
                <pb facs="0732" n="670" xml:id="pg_670"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">MacLeish</persName>
                    </hi> thought that we would regret the formula as long as the memory of the
                    Conference lasted. He referred specifically to the vague terminology,
                    specifically the term “attack”. He also considered that the state attacked and
                    the other states siding with it should be required specifically to submit to a
                    decision of the Security Council. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> thought that the third sentence of the draft amply satisfied the point
                    raised by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">MacLeish</persName>. He thought,
                    however, that the draft would require public explanation so as to avoid the
                    impression that the Security Council had lost out. The point should be driven
                    home that the formula covered only emergency situations and that the Security
                    Council had the power to stop the fighting at any stage.</p>
                <p>(At this point the Secretary, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>,
                    and <persName corresp="#p_ELGSD1">General Embick</persName> left the meeting to
                    talk by telephone with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> declared that states already have the right to take measures of
                    self-defense against attack and that the draft should be read in relation to the
                    responsibility given the Security Council and the right of the states to submit
                    the case to the council and their obligation to abide by its decision. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SCHE1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Commander Stassen</hi>
                    </persName> thought the formula would be attacked by extremists on both sides
                    and agreed that it was necessary to have a full explanation of the background
                    and meaning of the draft. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1"
                            >Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> stressed that the formula would of course work only if good faith was
                    present.</p>
                <p>(At this point Representative <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Bloom</persName> entered
                    the meeting.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> suggested certain drafting changes, particularly the insertion of the word
                    “inherent” before the phrase “right to take measures of self-defense” and also
                    that the words “be reported immediately to the Security Council and shall not in
                    any way” be added before the phrase “affect the authority and responsibility of
                    the Security Council.…” <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1"
                            >Connally</persName>
                    </hi> said that he agreed with the revisions and that it was clear that they did
                    not mean that the states attacked should stop fighting before the necessary
                    counter-measures were taken by the world organization; that the situation was
                    similar to that of the individual who could continue to protect himself until
                    adequate police measures had been taken. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_GOB1">Gerig</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that the draft not only didn’t affect the authority of the
                    Security Council but includes the right of the attacked state to appeal to the
                    Council. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>
                    </hi> added that as far as the Western Hemisphere is concerned we had additional
                    protection in our veto right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> inquired as to which of the Conference committees had jurisdiction. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> thought that perhaps a joint subcommittee should study the proposal in the
                    first instance and that ultimately the Coordination Committee would decide as to
                    location. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1"
                            >Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> recalled that Subcommittee III/4/A had been <pb facs="0733" n="671"
                        xml:id="pg_671"/> requested to consolidate or amalgamate the various
                    amendments offered to Section C of Chapter VIII<note n="70" xml:id="d222fn7"
                        >Doc. 196, III/4/, May 10, UNCIO Documents, vol. 12, p. 669.</note> and that
                    the draft, in his opinion, could be submitted direct to the Subcommittee.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Statement to the Press</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The United States Position on the Amendments Offered by
                        Other Delegations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> reported? that the Committee of Five had studied the ten questions before
                    it and had completed part of the work. Substantial agreement had been reached to
                    recommend acceptance of the first sentence of the Australian proposal on
                        membership.<note n="71" xml:id="d222fn8">Doc. 2, G/14(1), May 5, <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. 3, p. 543.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean <persName corresp="#p_GVC1">Gildersleeve</persName>
                    </hi> reported that the group of Advisers and Technical Experts assigned to
                    Committee I/1 had met all afternoon to study the amendments suggested by other
                    governments and to point up the issues which required decision by the United
                    States Delegation. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SDV1"
                            >Sandifer</persName>
                    </hi> informed the Delegation that a report on the work of the various
                    commissions and committees had been prepared and distributed. It was agreed that
                    there would be no committee meetings tomorrow and that the Delegation would meet
                    at 9:00 a.m. and stay in session all morning to determine the United States
                    position, on the various amendments.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Voting Procedure in the Committees</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Representative <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Bloom</persName>
                    </hi> inquired as to the voting procedure in the committees and <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> said that this question had come up in the Committee of Five but that a
                    final decision had not been taken.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the amendments proposed by other governments should be voted
                    upon in the first instance and rejected. If it appeared that the vote would be
                    against the United States position, appointment of a subcommittee should be
                    suggested and if this failed the United States representative should reserve the
                    position of the Delegation. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1"
                            >Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> stressed that pressure for an increase in the members of the Security
                    Council should be opposed by every means and if necessary carried back through
                    the Executive and Steering Committees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_CT1">Connally</persName>
                    </hi> thought the Steering or Executive Committee should rule on the number and
                    duration of speeches. He thought that something should be done immediately since
                    the tendency to make long speeches was delaying the work of the Conference.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jurisdictional Disputes Between Committees</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AHF1">Armstrong</persName>
                    </hi> inquired as to the procedure where there was a dispute between two
                    committees as to where a given subject should be <pb facs="0734" n="672"
                        xml:id="pg_672"/> discussed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> said that this problem had come up in the Coordination Committee and that
                    no agreement had been reached. He thought, perhaps, that the issue could be
                    settled by the Steering Committee. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_AHF1">Armstrong</persName>
                    </hi> said that in practice the Chairmen were deciding either individually or in
                    consultation and <hi rend="smallcaps">Representative <persName corresp="#p_BS1"
                            >Bloom</persName>
                    </hi> thought this was undesirable since it might foreclose the issue; he
                    considered the dispute should go direct to the body competent to decide such
                    questions. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1"
                            >Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> then suggested that perhaps it might be better that the matter be reported
                    to the President of the Conference through the Secretary General. It was agreed
                    that this should be done.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Regional Arrangements</hi> (Continued)</p>
                <p>(The Secretary, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>, and <persName
                        corresp="#p_ELGSD1">General Embick</persName> returned to the meeting.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> reported he had talked with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> who had just finished a conversation
                    with the War and Navy Secretaries who felt that the draft placed too much
                    emphasis on regionalism at the expense of the world system. They thought it
                    might be better to go back to the idea of a specific exception for this
                    hemisphere. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> was to talk again
                    with the Secretaries of War and Navy and report back. <hi rend="smallcaps">The
                        Chairman</hi> also said that <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                    </hi> thought the drafting changes agreed upon at the meeting would be
                    helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gates</persName>
                    </hi> added that the impression in Washington appeared to be that the draft
                    strengthened our position in the Western Hemisphere from the military point of
                    view but that the problem of world security was not adequately covered; that the
                    formula might be a wide open invitation to regionalism; and that the distinction
                    between “attack” and “armed attack” gave rise to certain doubts. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> thought that it would be very difficult to explain in the Committee and in
                    the Senate the distinction between the two concepts of “attack” and “armed
                    attack”. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HGH1"
                            >Hackworth</persName>
                    </hi> thought it might be better to speak of “armed attack” in both cases and
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chair</hi> thought it might be useful to use the
                    word “aggression” instead of “attack”. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that there be no tinkering with the text around the table since
                    every word had been carefully scrutinized by the group which had prepared it and
                    that if there were any suggestions for drafting changes they should be referred
                    to the small group for study and report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> inquired as to what should be done with
                    respect to the meeting with the other sponsoring governments and France
                    scheduled for tonight and specifically whether the other sponsoring delegations
                        <pb facs="0735" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> should be with him when he
                    discussed the draft with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>. He
                    thought perhaps it was better to confine the conversation to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> since his departure made it necessary to be
                    specific with him. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1"
                            >Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> was of the opinion that tonight’s meeting of Five should be called off and
                    that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> should be told that the
                    Delegation was moving in the direction set out in the draft. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> thought that the others could be seen later in the evening. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Pasvolsky</persName>
                    </hi> believed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> would accept the
                    proposal since he had been worried regarding the situation which would ensue if
                    the Security Council failed to take action as a consequence of the exercise of
                    the veto power by one of the permanent members.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the procedure from here on should be: (<hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi>) the Delegation would wait to hear the views of the Secretaries of
                    War and Navy; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) if these views were favorable, the
                    draft would be submitted to President <persName>Truman</persName> for his
                    approval; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the Secretary would cancel his meeting with
                    the representatives of the four sponsoring powers and M. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> and would explain in an informal manner
                    to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and his chief advisers the
                    general lines of the Delegation’s thinking; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) in
                    negotiating the draft the position would be taken that it was simply a United
                    States modification of the French proposal.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Representation of the Delegation at Committee Meetings</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Representative <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Bloom</persName>
                    </hi> stressed that it was important that a voting member of the Delegation be
                    at all committee and subcommittee meetings. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SDV1">Sandifer</persName>
                    </hi> referred to a directive issued recently by the Chairman with respect to
                    this matter. <hi rend="smallcaps">The Chairman</hi> stated that the Secretary
                    General of the Delegation had the responsibility to see that a voting
                    representative of the United States was at every committee meeting. In the
                    absence of the delegate, the adviser would vote and in his absence the principal
                    technical expert assigned to the committee.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Statement to the Press</hi> (Continued)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">MacLeish</persName>
                    </hi> reverted to his previous request for instructions regarding a statement to
                    the Press, particularly if he were asked whether the subject had been referred
                    to Washington.…</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hickerson</persName>’s suggestion was approved,
                    to the effect that the Press be informed that there were approximately seventeen
                    amendments on the various aspects of the problem and that the Delegation had
                    spent the afternoon considering the position it should take, that it had made
                    progress, but that it had not completed its studies.</p>
                <p>The meeting was adjourned by the Chairman at 5:00 p.m.</p>
                <pb facs="0736" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>(<hi rend="smallcaps">Regional Arrangements</hi>)</head>
                    <p>(This is a new paragraph to be added to Chapter VIII, Section B, as paragraph
                            12.)<note n="71a" xml:id="d222fn9">Marginal notation on the original:
                            “(Deletions made at the Delegation meeting of May 11, are indicated by
                            lines through the word and additions by underscoring.)”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>12. In the event of an attack by any state against any member state, such
                        member State <del rend="strikethrough">shall</del> possess<hi
                            rend="underline">es</hi> the <hi rend="underline">inherent</hi> right to
                        take measures of self-defense. The <hi rend="underline">inherent</hi> right
                        to take measures of self-defense against armed attack shall apply to
                        arrangements, like those embodied in the Act of Chapultepec, under which all
                        members of a group of states agree to consider an attack against any one of
                        them as an attack against all of them. The taking of such measures shall <hi
                            rend="underline">be reported immediately to the Security Council and
                            shall</hi> not <hi rend="underline">in any way</hi> affect the authority
                        and responsibility of the Security Council under this Charter to take at any
                        time such action as it may deem necessary in order to maintain or restore
                        international peace and security.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
