<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France (
                    (Caffery))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-02-20T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-20T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-20T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-20T20:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.CC/2–2045: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="36" xml:id="d28fn1">Text transmitted to Mexico City for
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName> and his
                        Assistant, <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Leo Pasvolsky</persName>, in telegram
                        337, February 20, 9 p.m., not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-20T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >February 20, 1945—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>686. News stories in today’s <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Herald Tribune</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Baltimore
                        Sun</hi> by <persName>Harold Callender</persName>, <persName>Sonia
                        Tomara</persName> and <persName>Philip Whitcomb</persName>, respectively,
                    and apparently arising from a report by <persName corresp="#p_BG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> to the Foreign Affairs Committee of the French
                    Consultative Assembly, together make it appear possible that the Provisional
                    Government of France will not take part in the San Francisco Conference unless
                    “it obtains satisfactory information about aims and the agenda”. These reports
                    also make it appear that a chief stumbling block in French acceptance to
                    participate is the interpretation of the “trusteeship system”. Moreover
                        <persName>Callender</persName>’s report has the relevant substance of our
                    cablegram to you (reDeptel 546, February 11) covering this and some of the other
                    subjects therein.</p>
                <p>Apart from the fact that these reports state the term “trusteeship” does not
                    readily translate into French, they also claim France is afraid that under the
                    proposed trusteeship system (1) French rights in Syria and Lebanon would be
                    affected, (2) any of their claims to the Rhineland might be prejudiced, and (3)
                    questions may arise of “strategic bases”, the latter of which particularly
                    “aroused deep suspicions on the part of the French”. In the event of a French
                    decision not to participate in the San Francisco Conference we are particularly
                    concerned that such an eventuality should not occur because of our failure to
                    furnish full information regarding proposals to be studied there.</p>
                <p>Therefore, should a convenient opportunity arise will you please again stress to
                        <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> and <persName>de
                        Gaulle</persName> that in connection with the proposed trusteeship system
                    neither the proposed preliminary consultations among the five powers nor the
                    discussions at the United Nations Conference would deal with specific
                    territories but would be restricted to the formulation of principles and
                    provisions for machinery. Any question of the specific territories which may be
                    placed under the trusteeship system would in each case be dealt with by
                    subsequent agreement.</p>
                <p>You should also recall to <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> and
                        <persName>de Gaulle</persName> that the five sponsoring nations are to
                    consult each other prior to the United Nations Conference with a view to
                    presenting agreed proposals as to machinery for dealing with trusteeships. As
                    soon as France has agreed to become one of the sponsoring nations, we would
                    expect to begin consultation among the five powers on this subject.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GJC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
