<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Twenty-Sixth Five-Power Informal Consultative
                        Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco, June 19, 1945, 5
                        p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d306</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">306</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-19T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-19T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-19T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-19T19:00:00-05:00" n="306" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d306">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">RSC Lot 60–D 224, Box 99: UNCIO Cons Five Min
                    26</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Twenty-Sixth Five-Power Informal Consultative
                        Meeting on Proposed Amendments, Held at San Francisco, June 19, 1945, 5
                        p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-19T17:00:00-07:00">June 19, 1945, 5 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Informal Notes]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of participants, including members of delegations of
                    the United States (15); United Kingdom (1); Soviet Union (3); China (2); France
                    (2); and the International Secretariat (1).]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> of the United States presided and called the meeting to order. He asked
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> to give the group a statement which he believed the Ambassador had
                    ready.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> announced that in connection with the question which had been raised by
                    him in the Executive Committee and in the Steering Committee, and which had been
                    discussed here yesterday, he wanted to submit a new text of a paragraph as a
                    substitute <pb facs="1440" n="1378" xml:id="pg_1378"/> both for Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>’s text and for the text prepared here
                        yesterday.<note n="48" xml:id="d306fn1">Doc. 1108, EX/28, June 20, UNCIO
                        Documents, vol. 5, p. 535; Doc. 1107, ST/18, June 20, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 272; minutes of the Five-Power meeting, June 18, 12
                        noon, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1348">p.
                        1348</ref>.</note> He then read the text as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The General Assembly has the right to discuss any questions or any
                            matters within the sphere of the functions or powers covered by this
                            Section, or relating to the powers and functions of any organs provided
                            for in the Charter, and, except as provided for in paragraph 2 (B) of
                            this section, to make recommendations to the members of the United
                            Nations or to the Security Council or both on any such questions or
                            matters.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> asked <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> if he would give the reasons for dropping the reference to the principles
                    and purposes of the Charter in this paragraph. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> replied that the phrase “powers and functions of any organs” would cover
                    this. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> thought it would be less vague to have a reference to the principles and
                    purposes of the Charter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> thought that we were very close on the text. He recalled that Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> had been frank in saying that
                    there was no objection to the General Assembly’s discussing anything in the
                    principles and purposes in the Charter. He thought this additional phrase would
                    be indispensable to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> and his
                    group; and that if this phrase were added that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> would accept this text. He suggested that there be
                    inserted after the phrase “within the sphere” the following language: “the
                    principles and purposes of the Charter”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> agreed with <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> that we were quite close on the draft. He thought we must get the thing
                    generally agreed upon quickly. He could not think that the Senator’s suggestion
                    would be unpalatable or difficult to the Ambassador, since we agreed yesterday
                    that there was no controversy in this respect. At the worst, the addition of the
                    phrase suggested by the Senator would be a repetition. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord
                            <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> observed that knowing Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>, he
                    thought that the nearer we kept to his words, the easier the task would be. He,
                    therefore, hoped that the Ambassador would agree to the inclusion of these
                    words.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> thought the reference to “organs” was adequate, noting that the organs of
                    the United Nations must operate according to the principles and purposes of the
                    Charter. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Dejean</hi>
                    </persName> thought it was only a question of words, and that the substance was
                    the same. He felt that on such an important matter the question of words ought
                    not to divide us. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> commented that we all mean the same thing.</p>
                <pb facs="1441" n="1379" xml:id="pg_1379"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> remarked that he did not understand the significance of the change
                    proposed in the Russian draft, providing for discussion by the General Assembly
                    of matters relating to the functions and powers of organs provided for by the
                    Charter. He noted that in the Chapter on the General Assembly, only Section B
                    mentions the powers and functions of that body. The same is true of the Chapter
                    on the Security Council where only one Section refers to its powers and
                    functions. He wanted to know if the Ambassador meant by this draft to limit the
                    General Assembly’s discussion to only those two Sections. For example, he
                    observed, the voting Section on the Security Council was outside the Section
                    relating to its powers and functions. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> wanted the following words inserted: “or otherwise covered by the purposes
                    and principles of the Charter”. He felt this language would make the text
                    clearer and that it should be added so as to make the text clear beyond any
                    misunderstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> said that he could not agree with this. He observed that under his draft,
                    the General Assembly could discuss any question relating to powers of any organ
                    of the United Nations, the Economic and Social Council, the Trusteeship Council,
                    judicial problems, etc. He thought this covered everything that is in the
                    Charter, and that all questions were covered by “organs of the Charter”. He
                    observed that there was no exception to this except for paragraph 2 (B). He
                    thought that the General Assembly could discuss the broadest possible scope of
                    questions under this draft.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> did not suppose that the Ambassador and the rest of the group had any
                    substantial difference of purpose. He felt it was important, however, to
                    consider the effect in the minds of the Technical Committee as they compared
                    this text with the draft which they already had. He thought the Committee would
                    ask immediately the question: do you mean that the words in this draft cover the
                    same things as the words “purposes and principles of the Charter”? If so, why
                    don’t you say it? If you do not mean this, you limit the General Assembly to
                    discussion of something less than the principles and purposes of the Charter,
                    and that is unacceptable. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that this change in the text carries the implication of
                    attempting to limit the Assembly’s discussion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> thought that his draft meant that the General Assembly could talk about
                    anything. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dejean</hi>
                    </persName> said he could not see any difference between the two texts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> thought that the General Assembly could discuss all matters relating to
                    the Charter. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> thought that if the language “principles and purposes of the Charter” were
                    used, it would mean that the General Assembly could discuss any <pb facs="1442" n="1380" xml:id="pg_1380"/> question in the sphere of international
                    relations. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> thought it was just a matter of wording. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord
                            <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> asked that the Section referred to in this draft be read aloud. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> then read aloud the text of Chapter V, Section B, as adopted by Committee
                    II/2 on May 29, 1945.<note n="49" xml:id="d306fn2">Doc. 686, II/2/34, May 30,
                        UNCIO Documents, vol. 9, p. 108.</note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> thought that from Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>’s
                    standpoint, his group would raise the same question that <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> had raised. That is, they would ask whether the phrase “powers and
                    functions of any organs” is a technical phrase designed merely to pick up by
                    reference three Sections of the Charter, i.e., Chapter V, Section B on the
                    General Assembly; Chapter VIII, Section B on the Security Council; and Chapter
                    X, Section 9 on the Economic and Social Council. He noted that the words
                    “functions and powers” were used in these three places as a technical phrase. He
                    asked the Ambassador, therefore, if this phrase were designed to refer only to
                    these three Sections or to refer broadly to all powers of the organs of the
                    United Nations. In other words, he wanted to know if the Ambassador intended
                    that the General Assembly should be excluded from broader discussion by these
                    words.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> thought this phrase was broad enough to include the whole scope of the
                    questions with which the organs will deal. He said he thought if we said
                    “purposes and principles” any member of the Organization could raise any
                    question and justify this on the ground that it relates to the principles and
                    purposes of the Organization. He said that they could always raise any question
                    without limitation because this language is so very vague.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, if we say that the General Assembly can discuss any question
                    within the sphere of the powers and functions of any organs provided for in the
                    Charter, this will not allow any member of the Organization to raise and discuss
                    questions which are not within the scope of the functions and powers of any
                    organ. This formula, he thought, was so broad that it offered practically
                    unlimited possibilities for the General Assembly to discuss international
                    questions relating to the maintenance of peace and security, economic
                    cooperation, trusteeship, judicial questions, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> thought that in order to save time, the proper procedure would be to talk
                    with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> promptly and put the
                    Soviet proposal to him. Speaking for the United States Delegation, he preferred
                    the phrase “principles and purposes of the Charter”. However, in order to get
                    ahead, he would accept the provision for discussion with respect to powers and
                    functions of the organs of the United Nations, on the basis of the
                    interpretation that it is all inclusive, provided that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> agreed to it. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> said that he would not vote against the proposition that the General
                    Assembly <pb facs="1443" n="1381" xml:id="pg_1381"/> could deal with anything in
                    the Charter. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the United States would vote in favor of the provision that
                    the General Assembly can discuss anything in the Charter at any time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> said that his position was the same, and that he would sooner see the
                    phrase “principles and purposes” included. He did not think, however, that there
                    was any division in substance, in view of the interpretation of the Russian text
                    that the General Assembly was not in fact debarred from discussing anything in
                    the Charter. He wondered if we could reach an agreement on this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Dejean</hi>
                    </persName> stated that he agreed. He noted that Chapter VI, Section B, Article
                    2 provided that the Security Council must act in accordance with the principles
                    and purposes of the Organization; and that if the General Assembly could discuss
                    any power or function of any organ, it should be able to discuss the purposes
                    and principles, of the Organization under this provision. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> observed that this was inherent. He asked <persName corresp="#p_DM1">M.
                        Dejean</persName> if he were willing to have him discuss this matter with
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">M.
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dejean</hi>
                    </persName> said he would accept the Soviet text if Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> said that he wanted to be clear as to what the phrase in the Russian text
                    meant, and whether it referred only to the three Sections or to all of the
                    Charter. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> said that the answer has ta be “yes” before the United States Delegation
                    would support the proposal. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> if this
                    phrase in the Russian text limited the General Assembly’s discussion to the
                    three Sections relating to the powers and functions of the General Assembly, the
                    Security Council, the Economic and Social Council, or whether the General
                    Assembly would have the right to discuss the Charter as, a whole. If this text
                    limited the General Assembly’s right of discussion to those three Sections, he
                    wanted to think it over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the phrase “powers and functions, of any organs” did not mean
                    just the technical side, but rather, had the broader meaning, and that the
                    General Assembly could deal with all matters with which all organs can deal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </hi> asked if we could use the words the Ambassador had just used and get away
                    from the technical phrase “powers and functions”. He stated that he personally
                    would accept the Ambassador’s, interpretation, but that it must be remembered
                    that we were dealing with forty suspicious nations. He thought that if we used
                    words, which were subject to a narrow technical interpretation, their suspicion
                    would be increased. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> asked what was the Ambassador’s language. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi> stated that his language was just an explanation and was not a substitute
                    for the draft.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> then informed <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName>
                    </hi> that <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    </hi>, had given assurance that the Russian text had a broad meaning. He <pb facs="1444" n="1382" xml:id="pg_1382"/> thought we had gone as far as we
                    could go, and proposed that Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    and he discuss this matter with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>. If Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> asked any
                    questions that they could not answer, they would telephone the Ambassador. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> noted that as a practical matter, it was important to get the agreement of
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName> and his group because it would
                    be impossible to get the votes of Committee II/2 otherwise. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName>
                    </hi> added that we would not get those votes if we told them that we were
                    limiting the powers of the General Assembly. <hi rend="smallcaps">Senator
                            <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>
                    </hi> observed that it was a very belligerent group in Committee II/2.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>
                    </hi> then adjourned the meeting and stated that he would notify the group later
                    that evening of the results of his conversation with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EHV1">Evatt</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
