<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-28T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-28T18:00:00-05:00" n="345" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d345">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">500.CC(PC)/11–2845: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Acting United States Representative on the Preparatory Commission</hi>
                            (<persName corresp="#p_SAE1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">at London</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-28T18:00:00-05:00">November 28,
                                1945—6 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>10333. Preco 324. We have had indications that the British are giving the
                        impression that this Government prefers not to have the permanent
                        headquarters of the organization located in the United <pb facs="1542" n="1480" xml:id="pg_1480"/> States. If these reports are accurate they
                        may be due to the fact that the British feel warranted in giving such an
                        impression as a result of remarks which I made to Lord <persName corresp="#p_H1">Halifax</persName> and <persName>Noel-Baker</persName>
                        on October 24, 1945. You are familiar with these remarks and you will
                        observe that I did not deviate from the official position which we have
                        consistently taken that this Government will not seek the location of the
                        headquarters of the organization in the United States but that if the United
                        Nations desire to place their headquarters here we will welcome it. I also
                        indicated that in view of the vote of the Executive Committee I considered
                        the question of location had already been decided. You are authorized to
                        deny that this Government does not wish the location to be in the United
                        States and to state that our position remains as stated in the third
                        sentence of this telegram.<note n="45" xml:id="d345fn1">
                            <p>In telegram 12562, Copre 445, December 1, 3 p.m., from London, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName> reported, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, “I informed
                                    <persName>Noel-Baker</persName> yesterday of the substance of
                                Preco 324. He replied: ‘I have never said anything to anyone that
                                was not textually in accord with what Mr.
                                    <persName>Byrnes</persName> said to me, and I hope you will
                                assure him that I have always understood and understand now the
                                absolutely loyal and generous attitude of the United States Govt.
                                But you have seen the message from Washington in the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> and I think a number of delegations
                                have independently had messages from their govts to the effect that
                                US opinion was by no means unanimous. I am more anxious than I can
                                say that this business should not become a question of being pro or
                                anti-American, and I hope that I shall be able to get everybody who
                                takes our view to do everything in their power to ensure that this
                                is the chief object they have in view. I will make clear to everyone
                                I can reach exactly what Mr. <persName>Byrnes</persName> said to me.
                                When the vote comes, it is, of course, very likely to uphold the
                                Executive Committee’s decision; and if it does, I am extremely
                                anxious that it should be accepted by everybody with the fullest
                                goodwill. As for myself, I only say that the happiest times of my
                                life have always been in the U.S. So my goodwill will be very keen
                                and personal.’</p>
                            <p>“This reply indicates to me that <persName>Noel-Baker</persName>
                                intends to continue to use his memorandum of conversation with the
                                Secretary of Oct. 24.” (500.CC (PC)/12–145)</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>