<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="357" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">713.1311/127</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_WF1">White</persName>)</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-11-23">November 23, 1932</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Minister of Guatemala<note n="12" xml:id="d357fn12">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RA1">Adrian Racinos</persName>.</note> called
                            and said that he had seen in the press that the Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs of Costa Rica left Salvador yesterday for Guatemala in
                            connection with the project for the abrogation of the Treaties of 1923.
                            He asked me my views regarding this matter.</p>
                        <p>I told him that this was a matter for the Central American Governments to
                            decide but pointed out to him the benefits of the Treaty of 1923 and
                            emphasized that since 1907, when the Treaties were signed out of which
                            grew the 1923 Treaty, there had been no international conflict in
                            Central America. I recalled the chaotic conditions in Central America
                            prior to that date, as contrasted with the tranquility since, and
                            pointed out even the diminution in revolutions. I spoke of the economic
                            conditions throughout the world at present which have resulted in
                            political upheavals in so many countries, and stressed the value and
                            benefits of peace, order, and stability. I said that this Government was
                            not a party to the 1923 Treaty but had desired to do anything it could
                            to help the Central American Governments in carrying out what they
                            themselves thought would be conducive to peace, order, and stability in
                            their countries. I said that I was glad to tell the Minister exactly the
                            way we look at the situation but that the Central American Governments
                            would have to judge the matter for themselves; the responsibility is
                            theirs. I said that there is a very grave responsibility resting on them
                            and that I trusted they would not enter into a decision light-heartedly
                            but would consider very carefully what the consequences are apt to be
                            and if they take the road of <pb facs="0443" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/>
                            abolishing the Treaties to inquire very carefully where it may lead
                            them. I thought that they would want to consider very carefully what the
                            results would be before they abolished or even modified the Treaties. I
                            said that of course the Treaties are perhaps not perfect but that any
                            change that might be made should be distinctly for the better, and that
                            I thought they would want to carefully consider any proposed change to
                            know whether it would better conditions or not before embarking on such
                            a course.</p>
                        <p>The Minister said that he felt sure that that would be our position and
                            that there would be no change from the position outlined by the
                            Secretary in a recent statement but he wanted to confirm it before
                            reporting the matter to his Government.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WF1">F[<hi rend="smallcaps">rancis</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">hite</hi>]</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>