<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Brazil ( (Morgan) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">469</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="469"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.00 Revolutions/415</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MEV1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morgan</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3958</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-10-07">October 7,
                            1932</date>.<lb/>[Received October 15.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Continuing the subject of Embassy’s despatch No.
                    3954 of September 28 last regarding the political situation, it will be obvious
                    from the said despatch that the end of the São Paulo revolt was in sight and
                    that it might be expected that the military leaders would recognize that it was
                    impossible to continue the struggle on account of insufficiency of ammunition
                    and other military supplies. The end, however, came more suddenly that [<hi
                        rend="italic">than?</hi>] it might and was brought about by the separate but
                    contemporaneous requests of <persName corresp="#p_KGB1">General
                        Klinger</persName>, Commander in Chief of the São Paulo Forces, and of
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCHd1">Colonel Herculano de Carvalho</persName>, the
                    Commander of the Força Publica of São Paulo, to <persName corresp="#p_GMGPA1"
                        >General Gões Monteiro</persName>, Commander of the Federal Forces, to
                    arrange an armistice. This was granted and on the First of October went into
                    effect, the Federal Government placing <persName corresp="#p_CCHd1">Colonel
                        Herculano de Carvalho</persName> temporarily in charge of the City of São
                    Paulo, where he was accepted by the people after some local disorder in the
                    streets which did not assume a serious character. He has since been relieved by
                        <persName corresp="#p_LGW1">General Waldomiro Lima</persName>, Commander of
                    the Second Military District in which São Paulo is situated, who temporarily
                    will administer the City and State. Meantime, <persName corresp="#p_KGB1"
                        >General Klinger</persName> has been brought to Rio de Janeiro, as well as
                    other Paulista military leaders, where he is confined upon an island in the Bay,
                    which also houses <persName>Borges de Medeiros</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAS1">Arthur Bernardes</persName>, the Rio Grande and Minas
                    political leaders, who were taken with arms in their hands after tentative
                    revolutionary activities. The capture and transportation to the Federal Capital
                    of these political leaders was a shrewd political move and convinced São Paulo
                    that she could no longer expect the assistance upon which from the first she had
                    counted from the States to which these leaders belonged, and was an attributable
                    cause of her surrender.</p>
                <p>The Federal Government has declared that it does not wish to humiliate the São
                    Paulo people and for that reason has refrained from occupying the city with a
                    Federal force. Those Federal troops which are normally stationed there are
                    returning, and will be in garrison in the City and State. This, however, creates
                    a different situation from that which would have arisen had São Paulo been
                    occupied from the first by a display of military power.</p>
                <p>It is believed that the Federal Government will also permit the paper currency
                    which São Paulo issued to continue in circulation, <pb facs="0530" n="426"
                        xml:id="pg_426"/> but will demand that eventually it is redeemed by a State
                    loan. This and other questions are still pending. Public holiday until the 13th
                    of the month has been declared throughout the State in order that the public
                    departments may be reorganized.</p>
                <p>The Port of Santos is open to such steamers as are willing to accept the risk of
                    passing through the channel which has been cleared of mines, and telegraphic and
                    postal communication has been reestablished with that City and with São Paulo.
                    No foreign mails are detained in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                <p>The Coffee Council is sending its President to Santos to examine the coffee
                    situation and shipments abroad will probably begin during the coming week,
                    although cargoes of coffee from Santos can scarcely reach the New York market
                    before November.</p>
                <p>Reviewing the principal events of the revolution, it is clear that the attitude
                    of <persName corresp="#p_dCF1">Flores da Cunha</persName>, Interventor in Rio
                    Grande, was decisive. Had he not refused to allow his State to join São Paulo,
                    the result might have been the opposite from what it has been. The valuable
                    training which the officers who were loyal to the Federal Government received
                    from the French Military Mission during past years must also be included among
                    the causes of Federal success. The influence of the American Naval Mission upon
                    the Brazilian Navy is also evident in the loyalty of the officer corps, in spite
                    of considerable sympathy with São Paulo, to take an active part in favor of that
                    State. Had it done so the Port of Santos would have remained open, communication
                    would have been established with the outer world and São Paulo would have been
                    able to obtain the military supplies, the want of which caused her
                    surrender.</p>
                <p>An interesting feature of the civil war has been the action of the Aviation Corps
                    which through its bombardments did much to break down São Paulo morale. The
                    amount of damage done to foreign corporations was remarkably insignificant
                    considering the number of bombs which it is alleged were dropped. I have
                    authentic information of one instance only in which a damage of $400.00 was
                    rendered. It is also of interest that the spirit of the Paulistas was kept alive
                    by the daily distribution by radio of incorrect and lying reports. Both sides
                    distributed false information which was accepted by the public as true, those
                    emanating from São Paulo being even less reliable than those distributed by the
                    Federal Government. What reaction this will have upon the Sáo Paulo public when
                    it recognizes this fact has yet to be ascertained.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MEV1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin V. Morgan</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
