<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-08-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="605" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d605">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3310</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Cuban Chargé</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BJT1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Barón</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-08-03">August 3,
                                1932</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Doctor <persName corresp="#p_BJT1">Barón</persName></hi>: In reply to your letter dated August 1,
                            I am pleased to inform you, as you have already been advised by
                            telephone, that the Department requested the Department of Justice to
                            take appropriate measures to observe the movements and activities of
                            General <persName corresp="#p_MMG1">Menocal</persName> during his stay
                            in the United States. The Department likewise suggested to the
                            Department of Justice the advisability of having an agent of that
                            Department meet General <persName corresp="#p_MMG1">Menocal</persName>
                            upon his arrival on the steamship <hi rend="italic">Lafayette</hi> and
                            warn him in confidence to abstain from any activities which may violate
                            our so-called neutrality laws, with the provisions of which I believe
                            you are familiar, under penalty of suffering legal consequences. I
                            understand that the <pb facs="0660" n="556" xml:id="pg_556"/> Department
                            of Justice telephoned appropriate instructions to its New York office on
                            the afternoon of August 2.</p>
                        <p>The Department likewise took occasion to remind the Department of Justice
                            of the obligations assumed by the United States under Article 5–c of the
                            Convention between the United States and Cuba to suppress smuggling,
                            signed at Habana on March 11, 1926.<note n="24" xml:id="d605fn24">
                                <ref target="frus1926v02#pg_23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1926, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 23</ref>.</note> I assure you
                            that any information reaching the Department indicating that General
                                <persName corresp="#p_MMG1">Menocal</persName> is engaged in
                            organizing any armed expedition in this country or in conspiracies
                            against the Cuban Government will be promptly communicated to you as
                            provided under the aforesaid treaty.</p>
                        <p>With kindest regards, I am, my dear Doctor <persName corresp="#p_BJT1">Barón</persName>,</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WF1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis White</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>