<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-08-20T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-08-20T14:00:00-05:00" n="61" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/2109: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Minister in Paraguay (<persName type="to">Wheeler</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-08-20T15:00:00-04:00">August
                                        20, 1932—3 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>35. Your 93, August 19, 8 p.m. received much garbled and not fully
                                worked out as yet. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Soler</persName>
                                called this morning with a cable from <persName corresp="#p_AE3">Ayala</persName> indicating that he might not be able longer to
                                hold back the army from trying to retake Boquerón. I told him that
                                it is obviously to Paraguay’s advantage to work with the Neutral
                                Commission and the other American nations rather than against them.
                                The Neutral Commission <pb facs="0179" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/> has
                                been holding long sessions considering all phases of the matter and
                                is doing everything possible to bring about a definite cessation of
                                hostilities. He was told that it would seem to be to Paraguay’s
                                advantage to work with the other American countries rather than to
                                start another military adventure now which might well prove
                                disastrous and would certainly overnight cause Paraguay to lose any
                                moral advantage she now has.</p>
                            <p>Bolivia has told the Neutral Commission that she has some time ago
                                stopped hostilities temporarily. These statements were transmitted
                                textually to Paraguayan Government on August 10. If Paraguay has any
                                information to the contrary, full details should be sent to the
                                Neutral Commission at once in order that the Neutral Commission can
                                take the matter up with Bolivia. It was Paraguay’s failure to work
                                through the Commission early in July that greatly aggravated the
                                situation. It is hoped that you can persuade the Paraguayan
                                Government that now is the time to exercise patience and calm,
                                attempt to quiet and not to inflame the war spirit, and to cooperate
                                with the Neutrals and through them with all the other nations of
                                America.</p>
                            <p>In this connection it is important to know just what solution
                                Paraguay would accept in order that the Neutrals may know better how
                                to handle the matter in discussions with Bolivia. Would Paraguay
                                agree not to reoccupy the three forts taken by Bolivia if Bolivia
                                should agree to evacuate them, thus establishing a neutral zone?
                                Would Paraguay agree to having observers sent up to see that the
                                neutral zone is respected? It is naturally hardly likely that
                                Bolivia will agree to Paraguay policing this zone alone. Is the
                                suggestion you make in your telegram under acknowledgment that the
                                Paraguayan police force be used in the neutral zone or only in the
                                Mennonite colony? If the neutral zone is policed by both countries
                                further conflicts will inevitably occur. As much information as you
                                can send regarding possible solutions acceptable to Paraguay will be
                                most helpful.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WF1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">White</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>