<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-02-09T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-02-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="630" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d630">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">816.01/84: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Guatemala</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WS1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Whitehouse</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-02-09T18:00:00-05:00">February
                                    9, 1932—6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>6. Your 14, February 8, 4 p.m.<note n="12" xml:id="d630fn12">Not
                                printed.</note> You may say to the Minister for Foreign Affairs that
                            the diplomatic representative of the United States in Salvador has
                            stated categorically on several occasions to <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> and to other officials of the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> regime that the position of the United States is
                            based on the 1923 Treaty and that in the Department’s view it is clear
                            that under that Treaty <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName>
                            cannot be recognized. You may add for his confidential information that
                            when the Department learned of <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName>’ intention to send <persName corresp="#p_AL2">Luis Anderson</persName> to Washington to attempt to obtain
                            recognition for his regime, the Department advised both <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AL2">Anderson</persName> that <pb facs="0679" n="575" xml:id="pg_575"/>
                            the latter would not be received by any official of the Department in
                            connection with this matter. Furthermore, the Department has in the past
                            24 hours been informed by the Legation at San Salvador that <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> desires to send a financial
                            representative to Washington to discuss with the Department the
                            financial situation in connection with the 1922 Salvador loan.<note n="13" xml:id="d630fn13">See <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_885">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 885</ref> ff.</note> The
                            Department has replied that it is not in a position to receive such a
                            representative.</p>
                        <p>In view of the foregoing, the Department feels its position has been made
                            amply clear to <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName>. The
                            situation, however, is of course a difficult one. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> appears to have strengthened
                            his position in Salvador as a result of having put down the recent
                            disorders and he apparently has a favorable majority in the recently
                            elected Salvadoran Congress. On the other hand, the 1923 Treaty appears
                            clearly to bar him from recognition, and the other Central American
                            states and the United States have announced their decision not to
                            recognize him because of the provisions of that Treaty. It is evident
                            that <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> has been trying by
                            every possible means to bring pressure to bear on the other states,
                            including the United States, to alter their decision. It would seem,
                            however, that <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> must before
                            long realize that these efforts have failed and that the only way which
                            appears to be open to escape from the present impasse is for Salvador to
                            put its Government on such a basis that it can be recognized by the
                            other Central American states and the United States consistently with
                            the obligations of the Treaty.</p>
                        <p>The Department would be interested to know just what “definite steps” the
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs feels should be taken in order, as
                            indicated in his conversation with you, to bring home to <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Martínez</persName> that the other states intend to
                            support the Treaty.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SHL1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>