<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Haiti ( (Munro) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d717</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">717</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recA365XAlFrgaB1r" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="717"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d717">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/2453</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MDG1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Munro</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 418</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-06">June 6,
                            1932</date>.<lb/>[Received June 9.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Since the delivery of the Department’s reply to
                    the Haitian Government’s proposal for a reorganization of the system of
                    financial control, the Minister of Foreign Affairs has repeatedly indicated a
                    desire to continue the negotiations on this subject and to receive a
                    counterproposal from this Legation. I have pointed out to him that the United
                    States Government, in the proposal for a new financial convention which I
                    outlined to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHP1">Sannon</persName> last spring, has
                    already indicated what it would consider desirable in the new agreement. M.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LAN1">Leger</persName> has replied, however, that this
                    agreement, involving as it would a continuation of practically all features of
                    the present control, would be absolutely unacceptable to the Haitian Government
                    and could never receive the approval of the Haitian Congress. He has insisted
                    that neither the Protocol nor the loan contracts give the Government of the
                    United States any right to demand such complete control as that envisaged in the
                    plan presented by the Legation and he has emphasized the unfairness of
                    continuing so far-reaching an intervention in the Haitian Government’s internal
                    affairs simply to assure the payment of the small amount of bonds which will
                    remain outstanding after 1936.</p>
                <p>Pending a reply to the Haitian Government’s proposal and in view of other
                    circumstances which made me feel that the time was not yet ripe to undertake
                    serious discussions on this subject, I have hitherto not considered it advisable
                    to lay a concrete plan before the Department or to attempt to inaugurate active
                    negotiations with the Haitian Government. I now feel that the time has come when
                    an effort should be made to adjust all of the remaining questions connected with
                    the Treaty of 1915 and that the present state of our relations with the Haitian
                    Government makes it probable that we can obtain as satisfactory a settlement of
                    these questions now as we could hope to obtain at any time in the future.</p>
                <p>With reference to the financial control, there are two principal questions
                    involved: (1) Should further changes in the existing financial control be made
                    before 1936, and (2) what arrangements should be made to safeguard the
                    bondholders after the expiration of the Treaty.</p>
                <p>With regard to the first question, the United States Government would clearly
                    have a right to insist upon the maintenance intact of the present system of
                    financial control if it saw fit to do so. It would <pb facs="0742" n="638"
                        xml:id="pg_638"/> perhaps be advisable to refuse to accept changes in the
                    present system if the service of the bonds until 1936 was the only question to
                    be considered; but it is obvious that the character of the arrangement governing
                    the period after 1936 will be of greater importance from the standpoint of the
                    bondholders than the precise nature of the system prevailing during the
                    remaining years of the Treaty. It may, therefore, prove to be in their best
                    interests to make some concessions with regard to the present system, if it
                    proves that such action will make it possible to obtain a better arrangement
                    after the termination of the Treaty. I do not think that we should propose such
                    concessions in the first instance, but I believe that we should be prepared to
                    make them during the course of the negotiations if necessary in order to obtain
                    a satisfactory agreement.</p>
                <p>In considering the second question, it is necessary to have in mind the exact
                    situation which will exist when the Treaty expires. At that time there will be
                    between nine and ten million dollars par value of bonds outstanding, the exact
                    amount depending upon the rate at which amortization purchases are made in the
                    meantime. Series B of the loan will be amortized in full before or just after
                    1936, so that the contractual requirements for interest and amortization will
                    amount to approximately $1,375,000.00 per annum or just under 20% of the
                    Republic’s average annual revenue for the past ten years. The service of the
                    loan will, therefore, still require large annual payments and the interests of
                    the bondholders will not be secure unless the Haitian Government continues to
                    follow a sufficiently sound financial policy to assure the payment not only of
                    the debt service but of the essential expenses of government. Before 1915 the
                    Haitian Government showed itself totally unable to maintain such a policy; and
                    despite the progress which has unquestionably been made in other respects, there
                    is nothing in our recent experience which affords any ground for hope that the
                    Haitian Government will be more competent to conduct its finances properly after
                    1936 than it was before 1915. A new financial agreement involving an adequate
                    measure of control by representatives of the United States Government will,
                    therefore, be necessary. The problem would be solved automatically if a general
                    refunding arrangement were effected in the meantime, but the possibility of
                    making a refunding loan between now and 1936 seems very small under current
                    financial conditions and in view of the difficulties created by the existing
                    loan contracts. Any new agreement which is made will remain in effect a
                    relatively short time, however, as the entire outstanding debt will be retired
                    by 1946, at the latest, and by 1942 or 1943 unless there is a much greater
                    increase in the prices of the bonds than now seems probable.</p>
                <pb facs="0743" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/>
                <p>As stated above, the present state of our relations with the Haitian Government
                    makes this a favorable time to begin negotiations. I believe that our own
                    position is stronger now than it will be later. If no general financial
                    agreement is reached, we shall unquestionably continue to have controversies on
                    such questions as the annual budget, the finance laws, and the powers of the
                    Financial Adviser; and the almost inevitable result of such controversies during
                    a period when we are rapidly relaxing our control in other respects will be a
                    loss of influence and prestige. In dealing with questions connected with the
                    financial control, we have discovered several points where our position from a
                    legal and a practical point of view is somewhat weak and where a controversy
                    almost inevitably involves some loss of authority unless we assume an extremely
                    arbitrary position. It is obviously desirable to have a clear understanding on
                    such points insofar as they are essential to continued financial control and to
                    reach such an understanding before they have become the subjects of
                    long-continued and bitter controversies.</p>
                <p>It must be realized, however, that no agreement can be reached by friendly
                    negotiation either now or later without making substantial concessions to the
                    point of view and to the political necessities of the Haitian Government. A plan
                    such as was proposed last year, involving practically the continuation of the
                    financial control established by the Treaty, might perhaps have been accepted as
                    a part of the Haitianization agreement by President <persName corresp="#p_VSJ1"
                        >Vincent</persName>’s first Cabinet, which had been very modest in its
                    demands, but it was summarily rejected by the following Cabinet and I do not
                    believe that it would be voluntarily accepted by any future Haitian Government.
                    The chief concrete advantage offered to the Haitian Government in this plan was
                    the removal of the Financial Adviser’s control over the distribution of funds as
                    between the different Haitian Departments and activities, but this control was
                    in fact abandoned during the budget negotiations last year because it proved
                    utterly impracticable and inadvisable to attempt to maintain it. Without
                    attempting to go into the history of last year’s budget negotiations, I may
                    point out that they offer an excellent example of the manner in which our actual
                    authority in financial questions will be imperilled by each controversy even
                    when we are prepared to take a very firm stand and to insist upon our point of
                    view at the risk of serious disturbances in Haiti.</p>
                <p>While emphasizing the fact that substantial concessions must be made if an
                    agreement is to be reached, I nevertheless believe that we can obtain a more
                    satisfactory agreement with less harmful concessions at the present time than if
                    the negotiations are postponed until the Treaty is about to expire. By 1936 our
                    control over the Haitian <pb facs="0744" n="640" xml:id="pg_640"/> Government’s
                    affairs in other respects will presumably have been reduced to a minimum and we
                    shall have withdrawn or be on the point of withdrawing the Marine Brigade. The
                    Haitian Government and people will be enthusiastically awaiting the end of the
                    Treaty as the beginning of their second independence and will be disinclined to
                    accept any agreement which would translate the rather general provisions of the
                    protocol and the loan contracts into an effective financial control, except
                    under such compulsion as the United States Government would find it exceedingly
                    embarrassing to exercise. Whatever demands were put forward as a basis for
                    negotiations, I believe that the Department would in the end find itself
                    accepting as the only way out of a troublesome and noisy controversy an
                    arrangement much less satisfactory than we can probably obtain now by friendly
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>I am enclosing herewith a draft convention embodying the suggestions which I have
                    made above. It will be noted that this draft departs in many respects from the
                    language of the present Treaty even with regard to matters where the powers
                    conferred by the Treaty are to be retained. I believe that it will be helpful to
                    the success of any negotiations that the new convention should resemble the
                    present Treaty as little as possible. It will also be noted that the draft does
                    not embody the maximum concessions above suggested. It is intended to serve as a
                    first proposal and a basis for negotiations. The question of possible changes to
                    be put into effect before 1936 has been left to be considered during the course
                    of the negotiations.</p>
                <p>The Financial Adviser-General Receiver has read the rough draft of this despatch
                    and has expressed his general accord with the views and recommendations
                    contained therein. He has made a number of helpful suggestions regarding the
                    draft agreement, practically all of which have been incorporated in the text as
                    herewith transmitted. A copy of a letter written by him in response to my
                    request for his views on the subject is transmitted herewith.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MDG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dana G. Munro</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Draft Convention Regarding Financial Control</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">I</p>
                    <p>After the expiration of the Treaty of September 16, 1915, and until the total
                        retirement of all bonds issued in accord with the Protocol of October 3,
                        1919, a Fiscal Representative and a Deputy Fiscal Representative appointed
                        by the President of Haiti upon the nomination <pb facs="0745" n="641"
                            xml:id="pg_641"/> of the President of the United States, shall control
                        the collection and allocation of the revenues hypothecated for the service
                        of these bonds as provided in Article VIII of the said Protocol.</p>
                    <p rend="center">II</p>
                    <p>The Fiscal Representative shall administer the tariff and shall collect all
                        duties on imports and exports accruing at the several customs houses and
                        ports of entry of the Republic of Haiti under the customs tariff now or
                        hereafter in force. He shall have for this purpose and for the necessary
                        audit and accounting services such assistants and employees as he deems
                        necessary. The expenses of the customs service, however, including the
                        amount upon which the two Governments may agree as the salary of the Fiscal
                        Representative, may not exceed five per centum of the receipts from the
                        customs duties, unless by agreement of the two Governments, and these
                        expenses will constitute a first charge upon the customs receipts.</p>
                    <p rend="center">III</p>
                    <p>The Service of Contributions shall be reorganized not later than May 3, 1936,
                        under a Haitian Director and with an exclusively Haitian personnel, unless
                        the Haitian Government should express its desire to retain the services of
                        one or more foreign technical employes. The Director of Contributions shall
                        have full administrative authority over the Service, under the high
                        direction of the Minister of Finance, but the Fiscal Representative, in
                        pursuance of the requirements of the Protocol of October 3, 1919, shall have
                        the power and the duty to inspect all activities of the Internal Revenue
                        Service and to make any appropriate recommendations regarding the conduct of
                        the service or the efficiency of individual employes.</p>
                    <p>The Fiscal Representative, for this inspection service, shall employ such
                        American and Haitian inspectors and assistants as he may deem to be
                        necessary, providing, however, that the total amount allocated for this
                        service shall not exceed $84,000 annually, except by previous agreement
                        between the two governments. This allocation shall be made by means of funds
                        established, as set forth in Article V.</p>
                    <p>If the Fiscal Representative should notify the Minister of Finance that there
                        is reason to suppose that the conduct of any officer or employe is incorrect
                        or inefficient, such employe will be suspended and will not be reinstated
                        until the charges against him have been disproved to the satisfaction of the
                        Minister of Finance and of the Fiscal Representative.</p>
                    <p>The Fiscal Representative shall present to the Minister of Finance <pb
                            facs="0746" n="642" xml:id="pg_642"/> such suggestions as may appear
                        helpful regarding the perfection of existing internal revenue legislation
                        and the enactment of new laws.</p>
                    <p>A law to be drafted by the Minister of Finance in accord with the Financial
                        Adviser and to be enacted before the reorganization of the Service of
                        Contributions will govern the appointment, promotion, and retirement of the
                        personnel of this Service.</p>
                    <p rend="center">IV</p>
                    <p>If for any reason the internal revenues should decline so that the amount
                        collected falls below 3,000,000 gourdes during the six months from October
                        to March inclusive, or below 2,000,000 gourdes during the six months from
                        April to September inclusive, the Fiscal Representative shall call the
                        situation to the attention of the Minister of Finance and shall make such
                        recommendations as he may deem appropriate for restoring collections to
                        their proper level. If the decline should continue, so that the total
                        collections for any consecutive twelve months are less than 5,000,000
                        gourdes, the Fiscal Representative, if so instructed by the Government of
                        the United States, may assume temporarily full control of the administration
                        of the Service of Contributions for the purpose of reorganizing it and
                        restoring collections to their proper level. This temporary control shall
                        not continue for a period longer than two years, except by agreement between
                        the two Governments.</p>
                    <p rend="center">V</p>
                    <p>The expenses of the Service of Contributions shall be paid by the Fiscal
                        Representative out of the amounts collected, in accord with a schedule of
                        payments agreed upon between that official and the Minister of Finance.
                        These expenses shall not exceed 15% of the total amount of internal revenue
                        collections, except by agreement between the Minister of Finance and the
                        Fiscal Representative, but an additional amount of not exceeding 84,000
                        Dollars per annum, as provided in Article III above, shall be included in
                        the same schedule to cover the salaries and expenses of the inspectors who
                        shall be attached to the office of the Fiscal Representative for the
                        supervision of the Service of Contributions.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VI</p>
                    <p>The expenses of the Service of Contributions including the expenses of the
                        inspectors attached to the office of the Fiscal Representative, shall
                        constitute a second charge upon the internal revenues, next in order after
                        the payment of interest and sinking fund upon the bonds issued in accord
                        with the Protocol of October 3, 1919.</p>
                    <pb facs="0747" n="643" xml:id="pg_643"/>
                    <p rend="center">VII</p>
                    <p>The Haitian Government agrees that it will not reduce the customs duties nor
                        modify the internal revenue laws in a manner to reduce the internal revenues
                        without the accord of the Fiscal Representative.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VIII</p>
                    <p>All authorities of the Haitian Government will extend full protection and all
                        proper assistance to the Customs Service and to the Internal Revenue Service
                        in order to assure their proper operation and the enforcement of the tax
                        laws.</p>
                    <p>Neither the Fiscal Representative nor those of his assistants who are not of
                        Haitian nationality shall be subject to arrest or to any judicial
                        proceedings without the consent of the Government of the United States.</p>
                    <p rend="center">IX</p>
                    <p>All monies received by the Haitian Government from all sources shall be
                        deposited in the first instance in the National Bank to the credit of the
                        Fiscal Representative, in order that he may make the payments for debt
                        service required by the loan contracts. The balance remaining on the first
                        day of each month, after making such payments and deducting for the payment
                        of the expenses of collection, 5% of the customs revenues and 15% of the
                        internal revenues, shall then be deposited in the National Bank to the order
                        of the Minister of Finance, to be used by him to meet the other expenses of
                        the Government, as hereinafter provided.</p>
                    <p>Unexpended and non-obligated balances in the customs 5% fund and the internal
                        revenue 15% fund shall revert to the general treasury account at the end of
                        each fiscal year.</p>
                    <p rend="center">X</p>
                    <p>The Haitian Government agrees that it will balance its budget each year and
                        that no supplemental or extraordinary appropriations will be made unless
                        unobligated funds are available to cover them after setting up such reserves
                        as may be necessary to assure the payment of the debt service and other
                        budgetary expenses during those months of the fiscal year when receipts are
                        normally reduced.</p>
                    <p>The Haitian Government further agrees to include in the budget the amounts
                        necessary for the interest and sinking fund of the foreign debt and for the
                        payment of other contractual obligations.</p>
                    <pb facs="0748" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/>
                    <p rend="center">XI</p>
                    <p>In view of the requirement of Article VIII of the Protocol of October 3,
                        1919, that an officer nominated by the President of the United States shall
                        control the allocation of the revenues hypothecated for the service of the
                        bonds issued thereunder, the Haitian Government will proceed in agreement
                        with the Fiscal Representative; <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>In determining the amount of the estimate of ways and means to be
                                used in preparing the annual budget.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>In estimating the ways and means available to meet extraordinary
                                or supplemental credits.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>In permitting any department of the Government under the
                                conditions set forth in the Law of Finance, to exceed its monthly
                                allocation (<hi rend="italic">douzième</hi>).</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In compliance with the same requirement of the Protocol of 1919, each check
                        drawn by the Minister of Finance against a budgetary item or against a
                        supplemental or extraordinary appropriation will be countersigned by the
                        Fiscal Representative to show that he has determined the regularity of the
                        payment under the law and the sufficiency of the justifying documents. The
                        National Bank will be irrevocably instructed not to honor checks against
                        government funds without such countersignature.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XII</p>
                    <p>If it should appear during the course of a fiscal year that the revenues will
                        be substantially less than the estimates used in preparing the budget, the
                        Haitian Government, acting in accord with the Fiscal Representative, will
                        adopt adequate means to meet the deficit, either by reducing expenditures or
                        by providing new sources of revenue.</p>
                    <p>The Government will not sell the securities held in the investment account,
                        or other public property, except with the prior accord of the Fiscal
                        Representative.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XIII</p>
                    <p>In order to establish on a more satisfactory basis the Republic’s system of
                        financial administration, a permanent law of finance, a copy of which is
                        annexed to this agreement, will be enacted by the Haitian Congress, and the
                        Haitian Government agrees that it will not make any changes in this law
                        which may affect the work of the Fiscal Representative without obtaining the
                        agreement of that official.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XIV</p>
                    <p>The Republic of Haiti shall not issue further series of the loan authorized
                        June 26, 1922, nor otherwise increase its public debt, except by previous
                        agreement with the President of the United States, and <pb facs="0749"
                            n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/> shall not contract any debt or assume any
                        financial obligation unless the ordinary revenues of the Republic available
                        for that purpose, after defraying the expenses of the Government, shall be
                        adequate to pay the interest and provide a sinking fund for the final
                        discharge of such debt. No subsidy shall be granted for a period of more
                        than one year except with the accord of the Fiscal Representative.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XV</p>
                    <p>In order to assure the maintenance of public order, the Minister of Finance
                        will give instructions to the National Bank to set aside preferentially each
                        month from the sums deposited by the Fiscal Representative to the credit of
                        the Minister of Finance the monthly budgetary allocation for the Garde
                        d’Haïti, and the sums thus set aside shall not be subject to withdrawal for
                        any other purpose than the necessary expenses of the Garde. Any unexpended
                        balance at the end of the fiscal year shall revert to the general fund of
                        the Treasury.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XVI</p>
                    <p>The Fiscal Representative shall maintain adequate records of all receipts and
                        disbursements, which records shall be open to inspection and verification by
                        the appropriate authorities.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XVII</p>
                    <p>The Haitian Government reserves the right to retire the bonds issued under
                        the Protocol of October 3, 1919, in advance of their due date; and the
                        Government of the United States will not invoke the provisions of Article VI
                        of the Protocol as an obstacle to such retirement before the expiration of
                        the period of fifteen years fixed therein, provided that the Haitian
                        Government is able to make an arrangement for this purpose satisfactory to
                        the holders of the outstanding bonds.</p>
                    <p rend="center">XVIII</p>
                    <p>The convention shall automatically become null and void and of no effect upon
                        the payment or retirement of all bonds issued or to be issued under the
                        provisions of the Protocol of October 3, 1919.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
