<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 3.Mr. Baker to Mr. Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894Nicaragua</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1894-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1894-02-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="diplomatic-recognition" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="diplomatic-recognition">Diplomatic Recognition</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97000533"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Enrichment</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-02-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="3"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <head>No. 3.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Baker</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Managua, Nicaragua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-02-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 9, 1894</hi>
                        </date>. (Received March 5.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have just received from United States Consul
                    Braida a report from B. B. Seat, United States consular agent at Bluefields, a
                    communication of which I inclose herewith a copy.</p>
                <p>It relates to the unsatisfactory condition of political affairs in the Mosquito
                    Reservation.</p>
                <p>There seems to be trouble brewing in that quarter.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lewis Baker.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 3.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Seat</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Braida</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consular Agency</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bluefields, Nicaragua</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-01-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 22, 1894</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with your request made some
                        time ago, I transmit herewith a brief report relating to the condition of
                        public affairs in the Mosquito Reservation.</p>
                    <p>We have recently had considerable local excitement, caused by rumors of a
                        threatened invasion of the Mosquito Reservation by bodies of armed men from
                        Honduras.</p>
                    <p>About the 5th of the present month about two hundred Nicaraguan soldiers were
                        landed at Bluefields, and were quartered for several days on the steamboat
                            <hi rend="italic">Mabel Comeaux</hi>, which lies in the harbor in front
                        of the town.</p>
                    <p>They were awaiting transportation to Honduras, and were finally sent forward
                        to their destination on board the schooner <hi rend="italic">Ensmo
                            White</hi>, which was towed as far as Cape Gracias by the steamer <hi
                            rend="italic">Yeslie</hi>. Their presence at Bluefields did not fail to
                        produce a stir and commotion among the natives and residents of the
                        town.</p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/>
                    <p>The chief, or more properly his advisers, construed the mobilization of
                        Nicaraguan troops within the reservation as an infraction of their rights
                        under the treaty of Managua.</p>
                    <p>One of the Mosquito officials, by the name of Usher Hodgoon, called on
                        Commissioner Lacayo, and demanded the withdrawal of the soldiers or the
                        surrender of their arms to the municipal authorities of the town. Of course
                        the commissioner refused to comply with the demand.</p>
                    <p>On the 13th instant a written communication, signed by Robert Henry Clarence,
                        chief, was received by the commissioner, protesting against the presence of
                        armed soldiers of Nicaragua, and serving notice on the commissioner that
                        protest would be made to Her Britannic Majesty’s Government.</p>
                    <p>The commissioner answered the chiefs communication, notifying him that the
                        Republic of Nicaragua was then at war with Honduras, and that the necessity
                        had arisen for placing the coasts and frontier of the sovereign in a state
                        of defense, and that only the sovereign could determine the measures for
                        such defense; that no treaty obligations could bind the sovereignty to
                        jeopardize its own existence; that he, the chief, had no diplomatic
                        recognition; that he had no foreign relations or representation and no
                        international responsibility, and that, therefore, he did not recognize his
                        right to interpret for himself the treaty obligations of the sovereign, nor
                        did he (Lacayo) admit the right of England to interfere in any way
                        whatever.</p>
                    <p>On the 15th instant the soldiers were sent forward, as above stated, to the
                        Honduras border.</p>
                    <p>Since the departure of the soldiers two meetings have been held in the town
                        for the alleged purpose of devising ways and means for the local protection
                        of life and property, in which some foreign residents as well as natives
                        were participants.</p>
                    <p>A question arose as to the right of the people to organize military forces
                        without the consent and approval of the sovereign power.</p>
                    <p>The commissioner was willing that a local guard should be organized, but to
                        be under the control of the sovereign power and to be replaced by the
                        Nicaraguan troops when they returned.</p>
                    <p>I do not know if any agreement was arrived at, but on yesterday morning a
                        body of twenty-five natives, armed with Remington rifles, commanded by one
                        officer, marched up and down the principal street and afterwards assembled
                        at the old government building, where they seemed to have established
                        temporary quarters.</p>
                    <p>The commissioner is certainly charged with a very delicate mission, and I
                        fear will have an exceedingly difficult task to establish here a due
                        recognition of the sovereign authority without some local trouble.</p>
                    <p>The political authority of the reservation has been in the hands of the same
                        set of men for many years past, each one of whom has not hesitated to assume
                        the functions of one, two, and three offices, and that without
                        accountability to any source but themselves.</p>
                    <p>Two natives of the Island of Jamaica, one J. W. Cuthbert and one John D.
                        Thomas, both of whom claim their British nationality, are the acknowledged
                        leaders of this ring of rulers; and under their control the others have
                        become thoroughly inoculated with the idea of their local independence of
                        the sovereign, and that their political status, as such, is fully
                        recognized, and that they are under the special protection of Great Britain.
                        Hence they are exceedingly tenacious of the power so long wielded by
                        themselves in the reservation, and which they have come to look upon as
                        legitimate and proper.</p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                    <p>As a matter of feet the Mosquito Indians proper know but little of the
                        Government as it exists 5 and according to well authenticated reports have
                        become dissatisfied and have recently developed considerable opposition to
                        this local régime.</p>
                    <p>They claim that they are not the beneficiaries of anything that is done; that
                        their country is being alienated and its wealth squandered for the
                        enrichment of their rulers, while they as a people are left destitute and
                        poor.</p>
                    <p>The administration of justice in the reservation has long been a practical
                        failure, to such an extent that scarcely anyone thinks now of appealing to
                        the local courts for the assertion of any legal right.</p>
                    <p>Their courts will render a judgment, but they will not issue an execution
                        upon such judgment, and consequently the debtor class in the reservation has
                        a free bill, while the creditor class is left without a remedy.</p>
                    <p>It seems to be the purpose of the commissioner to remedy existing abuses by
                        the reincorporation of the reservation into the Republic, but I fear this
                        can not be effected without opposition from the people who at present
                        control the reservation.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">B. B. Seat</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Consular Agent</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Received January 24, 1894, forwarded to the United States legation, at
                            Managua, January 28, per dispatch No. 19.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. C. Braida</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
