<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="632" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d632">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 63 D 351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 156 Series</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Note by the Executive Secretary (<persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1" type="from">Lay</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">National Security Council</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 156</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-23">June 23, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Strengthening the Korean
                            Economy</hi></p>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>References:</head>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action Nos. 711 and 741<note n="1" xml:id="d632fn1">For <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                    Action No. 711, see the memorandum of discussion at the 131st
                                    meeting of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, Feb. 11,
                                        <ref target="frus1952-54v15p1#pg_769">p. 769</ref>; in
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 741, the
                                    Council noted an oral summary of a memorandum by <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName>, dated Mar. 20, 1953,
                                    which reported on the activities of the committee established
                                    pursuant to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 711.
                                    A record copy of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No.
                                    741 can be found in <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) files, lot 66 D
                                    95. For the memorandum by <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName>, Mar. 10, see <ref target="frus1952-54v15p1#pg_813">p. 813</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 154,<note n="2" xml:id="d632fn2">Dated June 15, <ref target="#pg_1170">p.
                                        1170</ref>.</note> paragraph 14</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Memos for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive
                                Secretary, subject “Settlement of Republic of Korea Advances of
                                Korean Currency (<persName corresp="#p_WYDG1">Won</persName>) to the
                                United States Forces”, dated February 9, and March 10, 1953<note n="3" xml:id="d632fn3">Neither printed, but see footnotes 1,
                                        <ref target="frus1952-54v15p1#pg_747">pp. 747</ref> and <ref target="frus1952-54v15p1#pg_813">813</ref>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At the direction of the President the enclosed report to the President on
                            the subject by the mission headed by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Henry J. Tasca</persName>, Special Representative of the President
                            by Korean Economic Affairs, is referred herewith for the consideration
                            of the National Security Council.</p>
                        <p>The enclosure consists of the following parts of the complete <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Tasca</persName> Mission report: <pb facs="0127" n="1245" xml:id="pg_1245"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Letter of Transmittal to the President</p>
                                <p>Glossary of Abbreviations</p>
                                <p>Foreword</p>
                                <p>A Synopsis of the Report <list>
                                        <label>A.</label>
                                        <item>Achievement of U.S. Security Interests</item>
                                        <label>B.</label>
                                        <item>Ways and Means of Strengthening the Korean
                                            Economy</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>Mission Recommendations <list>
                                        <label>A.</label>
                                        <item>Amounts and Types of U.S. Assistance</item>
                                        <label>B.</label>
                                        <item>Efficient Utilization of U.S. Assistance</item>
                                        <label>C.</label>
                                        <item>Coordination of Economic Programs</item>
                                    </list></p></quote></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">The complete report<note n="4" xml:id="d632fn4">A copy
                                of the complete report can be found in <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> files, lot 60 D 330.</note> has been furnished
                            directly to interested agencies by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Tasca</persName>. A copy of the complete report is also available
                            for reference in this office.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> will report on the
                            proposed procedure for handling the enclosed report at the Council
                            meeting on June 25.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1"><hi rend="smallcaps">James S.
                                        Lay, Jr.</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure 1]</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Special Representative for Korean Economic
                                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_THJ1" type="from">Tasca</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-15">June 15,
                                    1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: In accordance with your
                                letter of April 9<note n="5" xml:id="d632fn5">Not printed. (<gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> files, lot 60 D 330, <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Tasca</persName> Report)</note> asking me
                                to investigate ways and means of strengthening the Korean economy in
                                the light of the security objectives of the United States and the
                                United Nations, I have the honor to transmit to you the attached
                                report of my findings. The preparation of this report was only
                                possible because of the fine cooperation of the interested agencies
                                of the U.S. Government. <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General Mark W.
                                    Clark</persName> and the United Nations Command rendered
                                invaluable assistance at every stage during my visit to the
                                theater.</p>
                            <p>The report deals with military requirements, production, investment
                                and consumption in relation to defense posture, imports, and
                                external aid, the prevention of inflation, and ways and means of
                                making U.S. aid effective at lowest cost to the U.S. The following
                                are highlights which may be of special interest to you.</p>
                            <p>The Republic of Korea has been making a magnificent contribution to
                                the military effort of the free world in Korea. As of the first of
                                April the Government of the Republic of Korea had the equivalent of
                                14 divisions in combat status. Since then two more divisions have
                                been activated and four more are scheduled to be activated before
                                the end of December. As of April, <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces held two-thirds of the front line. <pb facs="0128" n="1246" xml:id="pg_1246"/> Over the past year the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s generally have suffered
                                over 50 percent of the casualties each month and in several months
                                over 70 percent.</p>
                            <p>This superb military contribution of the Republic of Korea must be
                                viewed against the economic background and the devastation and
                                hardship which has struck that country. There are an estimated
                                2,500,000 refugees, 5,000,000 more destitute, and approximately
                                600,000 houses have been destroyed. War damages are calculated to be
                                $1 billion, and about 1,000,000 human lives have been lost since the
                                invasion in June 1950. Production of rice, a basic crop in Korea,
                                last year was only two-thirds of the 1945/50 average. Per capita
                                daily food consumption is below 1500 calories. Income per capita in
                                the last year was about $60 compared to about $75 in 1948/49 and $90
                                in 1949/50. The entire visible export trade of Korea during the past
                                year was little more than twice the value of the used clothing and
                                similar items given to Korea by private American charities during
                                the same period of time. There has been continuous inflation in
                                Korea, wholesale prices having increased 20 times from June 1950 to
                                June 1953.</p>
                            <p>It is my considered view that unless the total volume of resources
                                available to the Republic of Korea increases substantially, it
                                cannot maintain the present level of forces without further
                                inflation and increased hardship. However, our present plans provide
                                for the increase of the presently activated 16 divisions to 20
                                divisions during the course of the next year. Further inflation and
                                economic hardship could undermine the morale of the civilian
                                population. Deterioration of morale and the consequent damage to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> military effort could
                                seriously affect the U.S. position in Asia.</p>
                            <p>In the light of the foregoing, I strongly recommend a new three-year
                                integrated economic program of military support, relief and
                                reconstruction. The amount of additional U.S. aid required for the
                                Fiscal Year 1954 would be $300 million in addition to that already
                                contained in the <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> (proposed $71
                                million for <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>) and Department
                                of Defense budget ($75 million for civil relief) or a total slightly
                                under $450 million. For the following years the comparable total is
                                estimated at about $348 and $275 million respectively. Such an aid
                                program would provide the necessary economic support for Korea’s
                                military effort as well as enable that country to regain its
                                pre-invasion standard of living. Reconstruction and recovery cannot
                                be achieved by a series of stopgap measures.</p>
                            <p>Such a program would achieve the following objectives: <list>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Support the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed
                                        forces both logistically and in terms of morale.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Release U.S. armed forces from present assignments in
                                        Korea by substitution with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Strengthen the morale of the Korean people and increase
                                        their support of U.S. objectives.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0129" n="1247" xml:id="pg_1247"/>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Provide an example to the rest of free Asia and the free
                                        world generally that resistance to aggression will bring
                                        forth effective moral and material assistance from other
                                        nations of the free world.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Provide strong collateral support to the Japanese economy
                                        and Japanese economic orientation toward the free world by
                                        developing increased trade between Japan and Korea at a time
                                        when potential reduction in U.S. military procurement in
                                        Japan and continued loss of a large export market in China
                                        may tempt Japan to seek additional markets in Communist
                                        areas.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>It has been a great privilege and pleasure to undertake this mission
                                to Korea. The truly heroic quality of the Korean people in their
                                struggle against Communist aggression will remain ever a source of
                                inspiration to me.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_THJ1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry
                                            J. Tasca</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>[Here follows a glossary of abbreviations.]</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure 2]</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Excerpt of <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Tasca</persName> Mission Report on Strengthening the Korean
                                    Economy</hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-15">June 15, 1953</date>.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreword</hi></p>
                            <p>Pursuant to a recommendation of the National Security Council,
                                President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> on 9
                                April 1953 appointed Dr. <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Henry J.
                                    Tasca</persName> as Special Representative of the President for
                                Korean Economic Affairs and requested that he head a Mission to
                                investigate ways and means of strengthening the Korean economy in
                                light of the security objectives of the United States and the United
                                Nations. The President directed that the Mission’s recommendations
                                include the amounts and types of United States assistance desirable
                                in support of the Korean economy; proposals as to the manner in
                                which the United States can best be assured that any resources it
                                may contribute are utilized in the most efficient manner possible;
                                and the formulation of measures to be adopted to ensure the
                                coordination of all economic programs in Korea. The results of the
                                Mission’s investigation are embodied in this report.</p>
                            <p>The Mission arrived in Korea on 17 April 1953 and headquarters were
                                established in Pusan in the offices of the United Nations Civil
                                Assistance Command, Korea. A series of meetings was held with United
                                Nations Command agencies in Korea, with the United Nations Korean
                                Reconstruction Agency, with each of the Ministries of the Republic
                                of Korea, with the Chairmen of National Assembly Committees, and
                                with the Korean Chamber of Commerce. Each of the above prepared
                                extensive material on the Korean economy for consideration by the
                                Mission. In addition, the Special Representative visited most of the
                                important industrial <pb facs="0130" n="1248" xml:id="pg_1248"/>
                                plants and agricultural and mining areas in South Korea including
                                Seoul, the capital.</p>
                            <p>The Mission is deeply indebted to <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General Mark W. Clark</persName>, Commander-in-Chief, United
                                Nations Command and his staff for their cooperation and invaluable
                                assistance. Assistance furnished by all commands including Eighth
                                Army, Korean Communications Zone, Korean Military Advisory Group,
                                Army Forces Far East, and especially the United Nations Civil
                                Assistance Command is appreciatively acknowledged. The support and
                                cooperation of the United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency was
                                also invaluable.</p>
                            <p>United States Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Ellis O.
                                    Briggs</persName> and his staff were especially helpful in
                                supplying political guidance at all stages in the preparation of the
                                report.</p>
                            <p>The Mission wishes to thank all Republic of Korea Government agencies
                                with which it came into contact for their excellent cooperation. The
                                Mission is especially grateful for the cooperation rendered by Prime
                                Minister <persName corresp="#p_PTC1">Paik Too Chin</persName>.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Strengthening the Korean
                                    Economy</hi></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">A Synopisis of the Report</hi></p>
                            <p rend="center">(Sections A and B)</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">Achievement of U.S. Security
                                    Interests</hi></p>
                            <p>The security interests of the United States require the strengthening
                                of the economy of the Republic of Korea. An economic policy for
                                Korea must (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) strengthen the Korean economy
                                to provide maximum support to the military effort of Korean and
                                United Nations forces in Korea; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) ensure
                                living standards for the Korean population which will make Korea
                                safe against starvation, disease, unrest and subversion; and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) develop the Republic of Korea into a
                                self-defending and self-supporting nation as early as possible and
                                to the maximum degree feasible.</p>
                            <p>The achievement of United States military plans in Korea requires the
                                immediate expansion of the Korean armed forces by increasing the
                                number of Army divisions from the present 16 divisions, of which two
                                were only recently activated, to 20; and the development by the end
                                of US <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56 of an economic base in
                                Korea which will provide maximum support to armed forces of the
                                above magnitude, in addition to making possible restoration of the
                                pre-invasion standard of living.</p>
                            <p>The above goals cannot be achieved with Korea’s own resources. The
                                proposed number of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> combat
                                divisions, for example, approximates the number of combat divisions
                                in the U.S. Army at the present time. To support armed forces of
                                this magnitude the Republic of Korea has a population of only 21.5
                                million, of whom nearly a quarter are presently receiving some form
                                of government relief and of whom approximately <pb facs="0131" n="1249" xml:id="pg_1249"/> three million are in a refugee
                                status. The reconstruction problem is staggering; war damage to
                                property has exceeded $1 billion and nearly one out of every six
                                homes has been destroyed. Further, the armed forces and the civilian
                                population must be rebuilt on the basis of an economy of dwarf-like
                                proportions. The total national income of Korea, for example, is
                                smaller than the income of the population of San Francisco. The
                                power generation capacity of all South Korea is less than that of
                                the battleship <hi rend="italic">Missouri</hi> alone. The entire
                                visible export trade of the Republic of Korea during the past year
                                was little more than twice the value of the used clothing and
                                similar articles given to Korea by private charities during the same
                                period of time. Per capita gross national product during the current
                                year is only $60, compared with $200 in Japan, and over $2,000 in
                                the United States. Food consumption amounts to less than 1,500
                                calories per person per day.</p>
                            <p>The six-fold expansion of the Korean forces since June 1950 has been
                                largely financed by inflation, which has raised retail prices today
                                more than twenty times their level of three years ago. In view of
                                the enormous gap between resources available and resources required,
                                it will patently be impossible, unless the total volume of available
                                resources is increased substantially, to maintain even the present
                                level of forces without further inflation and mounting hardship.
                                Continued build-up to 20 divisions would be catastrophic from an
                                economic point of view unless additional resources were quickly made
                                available.</p>
                            <p>The root of this difficulty is the extreme, acute, and widespread
                                shortage of food stuffs, raw materials, equipment, and technical
                                skills, in relation to the war demands of the Republic of Korea
                                armed forces and the minimum subsistence needs of the civilian
                                population. Unbalanced budgets, inflationary gaps, perverse prices,
                                miscontrols, black and barter markets, premiums on speculation to
                                the detriment of productive effort, pervasive graft and corruption
                                in government, shortages in transport, industry, agriculture,
                                housing, and consumption, as well as large scale unemployment and
                                nonutilization of natural wealth, have already derived from the
                                fundamental shortage of material resources in general. The major
                                deficiency of assistance programs to Korea since 1950 is the fact
                                that all such programs combined were and are of inadequate size and
                                scope to close the resources gap. It is imperative to narrow—rather
                                than to widen—this basic gap between the sum of prescribed military
                                and essential civilian requirements on the one hand and of resources
                                made available from Korean production and external assistance on the
                                other. Unless this gap is narrowed, the economy will be entirely
                                incapable of sustaining both the civilian population and the
                                proposed defense forces. The budget proposed by the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government as immediately necessary
                                to support the augmented forces, for example, would require annual
                                expenditures of nearly two and a half times annual revenues. Further
                                inflation of the currency and eventual economic chaos would <pb facs="0132" n="1250" xml:id="pg_1250"/> be inevitable. The
                                result would be to undermine the ability of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> to maintain a defense posture and
                                would pave the way for subversion of the civilian population through
                                exploitation of the inevitable disease, starvation, unrest, and lack
                                of economic opportunity.</p>
                            <p>Such collapse of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> war effort
                                and morale, with its attendant threat to the survival of the state
                                itself, in addition to posing problems of the gravest magnitude in
                                regard to the conduct of military operations in Korea, would
                                seriously prejudice the U.S. position of international leadership as
                                well. It could effectively create the belief that support of U.S.
                                security objectives could be disastrous to countries still free to
                                choose sides. Protracted resistance to Communist aggression is
                                imposing acute and visible hardship on the Korean population. If the
                                people of the free world, particularly of the Far East, were led to
                                believe that comparable resistance to aggression might mean only
                                similar future hardships for them, the present defense of the U.S.
                                could be gravely affected in other parts of the world by a
                                deterioration of the will to resist and the desire to remain
                                free.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Ways and Means of Strengthening
                                    the Korean Economy</hi></p>
                            <p>The Mission’s principal terms of instruction require recommendations
                                as to ways and means of strengthening the Korean economy in the
                                light of the security interests of the United States. In simplest
                                terms, the requirement is for an economic base which will provide
                                maximum feasible support for the build-up and maintenance of a 20
                                division army and modest air and naval forces for an indefinite
                                period subsequent to February 1954; which will eventually provide
                                maximum feasible support for a 10 division army and small air and
                                naval forces for an indefinite period subsequent to the program
                                period; and which will provide a standard of living high enough to
                                ensure resistance to the blandishments of Communist subversion.</p>
                            <p>Despite Korea’s present appalling lack of visible resources, and the
                                omnipresent possibility of an accelerated inflationary spiral, it is
                                the judgment of the Mission that with necessary external assistance
                                the above objectives can be met in three years.</p>
                            <p>To meet the objectives, it will be necessary to restore Korean
                                consumption levels to those prevailing in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 50 and to increase Korean production sufficiently to
                                make this increase in consumption and the greater defense effort
                                economically feasible. This means specifically that per capita
                                consumption should increase from $50 in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 53 to $70 in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56.
                                This increase is feasible. Analysis of production possibilities
                                indicates that during the program period food production could
                                increase by 60 percent, mineral output by 140 percent, industrial
                                output by 160 percent, and that the shortages of fertilizer, fuel,
                                power and transport could be eliminated.</p>
                            <pb facs="0133" n="1251" xml:id="pg_1251"/>
                            <p>In order to make the Korean economy closer to viability, it will be
                                necessary to decrease imports and to increase exports. Military
                                imports will decline as the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                economy begins to produce more of the requirements of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Armed Forces. Civilian imports
                                follow a downward trend as food production and fertilizer production
                                increase. Dollar earnings from services and supplies to the UN
                                forces will gradually decline but the increase in commercial exports
                                will overbalance this decline.</p>
                            <p>The economic expansion implied in these goals must go together with
                                the achievement and maintenance of internal financial stability.
                                Although the annual defense expenditure by the Republic of Korea in
                                dollar equivalents should rise from $90 million in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 53 to $280 million in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56, the rising level of gross
                                national product, together with improvements in tax administration,
                                should progressively narrow the deficit in Government accounts.</p>
                            <p>The basic concept underlying the above plan is that an integrated
                                Korean relief, reconstruction and defense program of adequate size,
                                composition and timing, carried out with skill and vigor, and
                                appropriately blending external assistance with internal performance
                                by the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> government, can lead the
                                Korean economy out of its present state of dangerous weakness and to
                                a position of strength great enough to enable the Republic of Korea
                                to carry a substantial share of the necessary defense burden as well
                                as to support its population at pre-war standards of living.</p>
                            <p>Economic progress in Korea will also permit the elimination of the
                                refugee camps and the relief dole for the millions dislocated and
                                made destitute by the war. These millions will be needed and will
                                find gainful and useful employment in new and expanded production
                                activities. The morale benefits alone of such an accomplishment will
                                be of incalculable value.</p>
                            <p>The proposed plan also recognizes that the aggregate cost of
                                supporting the defense effort by outside assistance will be less if
                                part of the assistance is devoted to economic reconstruction and to
                                investments increasing Korea’s productive resources.</p>
                            <p>In developing its plan the Mission has examined in detail the
                                consumption requirements of the Republic of Korea and production and
                                investment possibilities and programs in all sectors. The
                                recommendations are grounded in large measure on a <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> five year program, which, however,
                                has been revised to assure principal concentration on key production
                                areas essential to a reconstruction and recovery program. The report
                                assumes, in this connection, that an armistice will be negotiated at
                                the beginning of the three year period, that the guerrilla threat
                                will become negligible by the middle of the first year, and that
                                there will be no substantial change in the current geographical area
                                of the Republic of Korea.</p>
                            <pb facs="0134" n="1252" xml:id="pg_1252"/>
                            <p>The Mission’s optimism that the Korean economy can expand to the
                                degree indicated in the program, while at the same time achieving
                                and maintaining internal financial stability, rests on certain
                                dominant features of the economy which may be summarized as follows: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>A substantial number of economic problems in Korea are
                                        simple, visible, and tangible. A mine is not connected with
                                        the national railroad network. Build a short connecting link
                                        and this problem is solved. Coal is piling up at pit heads
                                        for lack of freight cars. Import freight cars and the coal
                                        can be moved. Output of minerals is low, because there are
                                        no pneumatic drills. Import these and output will increase
                                        tenfold. Priorities in any low level economy are brutal: eat
                                        more, heat less, or vice versa; have one pair of shoes a
                                        year or repair the roof, but not both. But brutal priorities
                                        have the one redeeming feature that they are simple and
                                        certain and easy and speedy to administer. And this, of
                                        course, holds true for all phases of economic life with a
                                        low degree of diversification.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In a war-damaged economy completing investments of the
                                        simple repair and replacement type abound. There are
                                        innumerable instances where “for the lack of a nail the
                                        horse was lost.” Relatively small repairs and replacements
                                        will bring whole industrial aggregates back into production.
                                        A little dollar and local currency capital, together with
                                        arrangements giving individual initiative the right of way,
                                        will rapidly clear up these waste pockets in the industrial
                                        structure.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>In the recent past, large amounts of potential production
                                        have been lost due to the interruption of, or the stretch
                                        out of, industrial production resulting from actual or
                                        anticipated lack of raw materials. Potentially substantial
                                        quantities of foodstuffs have been lost as a result of
                                        delayed arrival and insufficient quantity of fertilizer. In
                                        the early part of the program period large increases in
                                        production will result from importing fertilizer and raw
                                        materials to capacity levels and by building up stocks that
                                        enable an optimum timing and flow of production.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Bringing modern equipment into an undeveloped economy
                                        provokes production increases far above those normally
                                        expected in developed countries. The shift from hand methods
                                        and human power to machine methods and mechanical power goes
                                        beyond the realm of marginal increments and results in a
                                        discontinuous upsurge.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>In the second part of the program period, the fixed
                                        installations, the construction of which was begun in the
                                        early program period, will be ready for production. Since in
                                        many important production fields, it is a matter of breaking
                                        virgin ground, production returns on investment will be
                                        high.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>With returning monetary stability, all the innumerable
                                        sources of sloth, waste, and misapplication of human energy,
                                        labor, goods, and materials which are now prevalent as a
                                        natural consequence of the long drawn out inflation, will
                                        come to an end. The vicious spiral of universal speculation,
                                        diversion, and corruption will be arrested and a cumulative
                                        healing process will set in.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>Manpower will be brought nearer full utilization but will
                                        not become a bottleneck during the period. In <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56 an estimated available
                                        labor force of 9.5 million will meet a calculated manpower
                                        requirement of 9.2 million. As regards technical talent,
                                        liberal foreign exchange allowances will be made in order to
                                        acquire technical personnel from <pb facs="0135" n="1253" xml:id="pg_1253"/> abroad and vocational training in
                                        Korea will proceed at maximum speed.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>The known deposits of tungsten, columbite, manganese,
                                        beryl, gold, anthracite, and graphite in Korea are very
                                        valuable and a proper geological survey would probably
                                        disclose many more. Even small investments in these
                                        opportunities will show very quick and very large returns.
                                        As a matter of actual experience, for example, tungsten
                                        production in Korea expanded from 1,154 tons in 1951 to
                                        3,789 tons in 1952 and to an annual rate of 5,050 tons in
                                        early 1953.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>In all countries which enter into the early phases of the
                                        modernization, industrialization, and commercialization of
                                        their national life, large intangible human productivity
                                        reserves exist at the outset. These can be mobilized by
                                        experts who generate a cumulative process of imitation. No
                                        development of new technical or managerial research is
                                        needed in Korea. The vast reservoir of knowledge available
                                        in Western civilization need only be tapped. And the
                                        Koreans, like the Japanese a hundred years ago, have the
                                        will and the ability to do so, and are not inhibited by
                                        irrational traditions and institutions.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">mission recommendations</hi></p>
                            <p rend="center">Chapter VIII (Sections A, B and C)</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">Amounts and Types of United
                                    States Assistance</hi></p>
                            <p>If the United States is to achieve the stated objective of
                                augmentation of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces
                                around an army of 20 divisions, and if the necessary economic base
                                in support of such forces is to be developed in Korea, Korea must
                                have additional aid and must have it immediately. It is the
                                recommendation of the Mission that the United States institute
                                without delay a new three year program of military support, relief,
                                and reconstruction in Korea. The total amount of such aid represents
                                a blending and a balancing of requirements for economic support of
                                the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces, for
                                consumption, for investment in productive facilities, and for the
                                generation of counterpart funds to meet unavoidable budgetary
                                deficits and the local currency costs of investment projects. In
                                consideration of all of these factors the total requirement for
                                external economic assistance to the Republic of Korea for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 54 is estimated at $533 million, of
                                which $75 million would be supplied by <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss>, $118 million by <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> ($71 million U.S.), $300 million based on the
                                present survey, and the balance accounted for by other voluntary and
                                UN contributions. <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss>, the new aid
                                program, and the U.S. share of <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> would amount to $446 million in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 54. It is the estimate of the Mission
                                that total <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> requirements for
                                economic assistance from the U.S. in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 55 will be $348 million out of a total proposed aid,
                                including <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>, of $368 million,
                                and in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56 $275 million out of a
                                total of $280 million. The Mission believes that the assistance
                                should be made available over a three year period as the minimum
                                time required to achieve the investment and production goals.</p>
                            <pb facs="0136" n="1254" xml:id="pg_1254"/>
                            <p>The proposed assistance program is a basic supporting element in an
                                integrated plan designed to lead to balanced development of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> economy. The Mission’s three
                                year plan is based on a <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> five
                                year plan but concentrates on the key production areas essential to
                                a reconstruction and recovery program. The Mission’s plan emphasizes
                                investment in agriculture, mining, industry, transportation, and
                                power, and assumes that mining, agriculture and possibly the cottage
                                industries are those with the greatest export potential. Stress is
                                placed on projects which can achieve the following results: Provide
                                for reconstruction and development of basic services and utilities;
                                rapidly produce increased supplies and essential goods and services;
                                contribute to the attainment of self-sufficiency in food stuffs,
                                fuel, and consumer goods; improve and maintain public health and
                                safety; restore minimum levels of housing and education; and make a
                                beginning on flood control, land reclamation and reforestation. The
                                Mission also recognizes that the long range interests of Korea will
                                be served by establishing technical and vocational schools and using
                                foreign advisors to train Koreans to assume the managerial and
                                technical responsibilities formerly exercised by Japanese.</p>
                            <p>The Mission has been deeply impressed by the mineral potential of
                                Korea and by the fact that mineral exports are and may well continue
                                to be the greatest dollar earner in commercial trade. In addition to
                                substantial investment in developmental and rehabilitation project,
                                the Mission recommends initiation of a geological survey.</p>
                            <p>With respect to agriculture, the Mission supports the general
                                recommendations of a <gloss target="#t_FAO1">FAO</gloss> team which
                                recently completed a study of Korean agriculture. Principal
                                recommendations included a sharp increase in the application of
                                fertilizer and pesticides; acceleration of the repair and extension
                                of the irrigation systems; a shift in land use so as to increase the
                                production of potatoes and sweet potatoes with a reduction of rice
                                acreage on land not suited to rice; and increased emphasis on land
                                reclamation. In the administration of the economic assistance
                                program, the Mission recommends that domestic grain collections and
                                grain imports be pooled so that cross hauling and local shortages
                                can be avoided.</p>
                            <p>Imports of consumption goods, added to domestic production, will
                                provide consumption levels by <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56
                                approximately equal to those of 1949–50. Grain imports will remain
                                at a fairly high level during <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 54
                                to enable the Government to meet its grain obligations and replenish
                                stock levels. Grain imports will drop sharply in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 55 and cease entirely in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56, at which time the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> should have achieved a precarious
                                self-sufficiency in staple foods. There will remain, however,
                                continuing requirements for certain types of food to supplement the
                                Korean diet, deficient in fats and proteins. Certain U.S. surplus
                                commodities, notably butter, dried skim milk, cotton seed oil, and
                                peas and beans, are admirably suited to fill this deficiency. The
                                recommended <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 54 assistance <pb facs="0137" n="1255" xml:id="pg_1255"/> program, therefore,
                                includes U.S. surplus butter, cheese, dried skim milk, cotton seed
                                oil, and peas and beans, valued at $29,000,000, for utilization by
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces, by
                                institutions and for relief distribution.</p>
                            <p>Against the cost of the proposed economic assistance program must be
                                measured the substantial reduction in U.S. support of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces which would be
                                effectuated during the same period of time estimated as a reduction
                                in U.S. military assistance from $1,655 million in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 53 to $660 million in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 56. Additional savings to the U.S.
                                will accrue from the replacement of U.S. divisions in Korea by
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions. On the basis of
                                present combat support arrangements, the annual saving to the U.S.
                                for each U.S. division replaced by a <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> division is in the magnitude of $100 million. U.S.
                                plans call for withdrawal of a substantial number of U.S. troops in
                                the near future and their replacement with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> personnel. Pay, allowance, and personnel costs for
                                each increment of 100,000 U.S. troops are in the magnitude of $375
                                million annually and in a ratio of approximately 8–1 to comparable
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> costs under the new <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces pay bill approved in
                                April.</p>
                            <p>With respect to types of U.S. assistance, the Mission recommends
                                continuation of present U.S. appropriations for <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>, as well as initiation of a new appropriation to
                                accelerate recovery and reconstruction and to provide additional
                                economic support to Korea’s defense effort.</p>
                            <p>The requirement of a Theater Commander for funds for emergency
                                civilian relief in support of his military mission is a recognized
                                aspect of modern military operations, and it is the judgment of the
                                Mission that the <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> concept
                                should be continued until termination of hostilities permits the
                                elimination of such a peculiarly emergency funding requirement.</p>
                            <p>Although the military situation in Korea has not eventuated as
                                anticipated at the time of <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>’s
                                establishment, the Mission does not recommend that <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> be phased out of the Korean
                                picture at the present time. The war is based on collective UN
                                action and the concept of rehabilitation has been grounded on the
                                assumption of a UN effort; a move to make the economic assistance
                                program a unilateral U.S. program would undermine the whole concept
                                of collective action. In the long run it would also require the U.S.
                                to assume one hundred percent of the expenditures now borne by
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> as opposed to the
                                sixty-five percent to which the U.S. is pledged at present.
                                Furthermore, if there is to be assumed a continuance of the cold war
                                in the future, there must be recognized the serious disadvantage of
                                creating a precedent in Korea which might then require unilateral
                                action by the U.S. in similar situations in the future. Overall,
                                however, it should be noted that although the <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>, and new economic defense support programs are
                                considered separately, in view of their diverse funding sources, in
                                economic <pb facs="0138" n="1256" xml:id="pg_1256"/> terms they
                                should be considered to represent a single integrated program of
                                economic assistance to Korea.</p>
                            <p>The Mission has given serious consideration to the question of
                                assimilation of the military assistance program with the economic
                                aid program, as for example, is done in <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> countries. It has concluded, however, that while
                                such accommodation is undoubtedly desirable, and should be initiated
                                when feasible, substantial additional examination of the matter
                                would be necessary before it could be deemed practicable during the
                                current period of military operations, since potential combat
                                exigencies require the fullest possible flexibility with regard to
                                the extent of direct logistic support furnished the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> armed forces, including the right
                                to commit from military stocks whatever support is deemed necessary
                                by the combat commander.</p>
                            <p>It is the opinion of the Mission, in view of the comparability of the
                                proposed new aid program to defense support programs elsewhere, that
                                appropriations for the new program should be sought through <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> and that funds for the <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> should be requested through
                                    <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> as a part of the same
                                appropriation. It is further the view of the Mission that as long as
                                the military situation continues to require that the Theater
                                Commander have immediate access to funds for emergency civilian
                                relief, funds for <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> should
                                continue to be requested, as at present, from the military
                                budget.</p>
                            <p>With regard to requisite appropriation language, it is believed that
                                the <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> language should remain
                                substantially as at present. Language for the proposed economic
                                defense support program should be designed to provide the greatest
                                possible flexibility in the use of funds, language such as that
                                authorizing European aid programs being considered appropriate. It
                                is believed that the U.S. contribution to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> should be appropriated as part of the economic
                                defense support appropriation, with the legislative language
                                providing for transfer of funds to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> to meet the U.S. pledge to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>. It would also be desirable for
                                the language to permit transfer of funds to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> additional to those actually
                                pledged to date by the U.S. This would serve not only to avoid
                                duplications of personnel and effort in the reconstruction field but
                                could also serve to solicit further contributions to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> from other nations on the basis
                                of the existing 65/35 sharing of <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> costs between the U.S. and other nations.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Efficient Utilization of United
                                    States Assistance</hi></p>
                            <p>The Government of Korea necessarily has sovereign authority over all
                                economic matters in Korea. However, it does not have command over
                                sufficient resources to meet the minimum requirements of the
                                civilian population, let alone the needs for larger military forces
                                or for reconstruction. United Nations agencies have no sovereign or
                                occupational authority in Korea, but they do possess, or can be
                                provided with, <pb facs="0139" n="1257" xml:id="pg_1257"/>
                                sufficient resources to meet the above requirements. Solution of
                                Korea’s economic problems, therefore, demands not only proper
                                coordination between United Nations agencies and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> but binding assurances by the
                                Government of Korea that it will take such steps as are necessary to
                                guarantee the most effective use of resources made available under
                                external assistance programs.</p>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> economic coordination with the
                                Republic of Korea is presently achieved through the Combined
                                Economic Board. Although the provisions of the <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                Economic Coordination Agreement provide that the Board will consider
                                all pertinent aspects of the economy of Korea, in practice the
                                Board’s actions during the past year have been limited to matters
                                specifically involving United Nations Command economic relationships
                                with the Republic of Korea, e.g., pricing of <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> aid goods, repayment for United
                                Nations hwan drawings, determination of a new military conversion
                                rate, etc. It is the considered judgment of the Mission that the
                                Combined Economic Board should devote a far more substantial
                                proportion of its time than at present to the development of
                                internal financial and economic policies in Korea which will
                                strengthen the economic structure of the Republic of Korea and its
                                capacity for self-support and self-defense. A new aid agreement
                                between the United States and the Republic of Korea, or basic
                                amendments to the existing Agreement on Economic Coordination, will
                                be required as a means of assuring positive <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> action on necessary economic and financial
                                measures. The initiation of a defense support program which will
                                sharply change the emphasis from furnishing aid to prevent disease
                                and unrest to furnishing aid to stabilize, rehabilitate and develop
                                the economy requires significant modifications in the Agreement.
                                Furthermore, the existing agreement, as do <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> Agreements,
                                describes in general terms the economic policies to be followed.
                                Experience has shown that such agreed generalities are not effective
                                in obtaining the decisive economic action required in Korea.
                                Specific policies of the following nature to be added to the more
                                general policies now in the Agreement are therefore recommended: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>These establishment of a single valid exchange rate as
                                        soon as practicable which would be applicable to all
                                        transactions between hwan and foreign currencies.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The pricing of imported goods into the economy at the
                                        single valid exchange rate, except as may be agreed by the
                                        Board in special circumstances and for a temporary
                                        period.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The development of a comprehensive plan for promoting the
                                        sale or long-term leasing of state-owned industries and
                                        other productive enterprises to private buyers and the
                                        encouragement of private enterprise. The transfer of foreign
                                        trade from governmental to private channels having due
                                        regard to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> constitutional
                                        requirements.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The adjustment of the price structure, i.e., the rate of
                                        exchange, prices and wages, to monetize income and make
                                        unnecessary hidden subsidies.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0140" n="1258" xml:id="pg_1258"/>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The coordination of economic and financial policies in the
                                        Combined Economic Board including particularly those
                                        concerning budgetary, tax, investment and credit
                                        policies.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>It would be possible to achieve all the necessary modifications
                                described above by an amendment to the Agreement on Economic
                                Coordination. This would have the advantage of avoiding possible
                                difficulties in renegotiating an agreement already in force. The
                                amendments, however, would be so numerous that the Mission
                                recommends the recasting of the existing agreement plus
                                modifications in a new aid agreement. In this connection, however,
                                it should be noted that in <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> eyes
                                the development of a 20 division army is the Korean <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the proposed assistance
                                program. Since the Republic of Korea even prior to receiving any
                                formal assurance of additional U.S. aid has already begun the
                                augmentation of its armed forces in accordance with U.S. desires,
                                the Government may well take the position that the U.S. assistance
                                is being granted only with unwarranted conditions, whereas the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> share of the compact is
                                being carried out freely and unconditionally.</p>
                            <p>In addition, it would be highly useful to provide that the new
                                agreement will become effective upon ratification by the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Assembly. The Agreement on Economic
                                Coordination was not ratified by the Assembly and the Government has
                                been hampered, especially in the pricing field, by actions taken by
                                the Assembly which prevent full compliance with the agreement.</p>
                            <p>Later implementation of the agreement will require that the Republic
                                of Korea take a number of politically unpalatable but nevertheless
                                imperative steps to normalize the country’s financial structure.
                                These include but are not limited to: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Strenuous efforts to balance the Government’s budget
                                        notwithstanding the military build-up, including reduction
                                        in proposed <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 53/54
                                        government expenditures to the extent noted in this report.
                                        Development of a phased schedule of government expenditures
                                        consistent with revenue income.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Stringent credit policies, particularly with respect to
                                        loans to governments and government-sponsored
                                        enterprises.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Use of counterpart funds to promote monetary stability and
                                        recommended investment programs, within the framework of the
                                        general efforts of the Republic of Korea to avoid
                                        inflation.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Initiation of a study of the existing system of controlled
                                        prices with a view to moving as rapidly as possible to a
                                        free market price basis.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The Mission finds that the financial weakness of the Republic of
                                Korea represents a most serious threat to the accomplishment of U.S.
                                objectives in Korea. Without additional external assistance the
                                outlook is for more inflation in Korea. Even additional external
                                assistance will not be fully effective unless the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government modifies current
                                financial <pb facs="0141" n="1259" xml:id="pg_1259"/> policies and
                                operations. Some changes may require legislative action but much of
                                the work can be accomplished through the machinery of the Combined
                                Economic Board where the joint nature of the decisions will provide
                                desirable support to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> actions.
                                The United States member should also be enabled to lend the
                                necessary technical experts available in the United States—tax
                                experts, administrative specialists, accountants, etc.</p>
                            <p>In connection with Government spending, the Mission finds that
                                proposed <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1953/54 budgetary
                                expenditures can be safely reduced without damage to the objectives
                                of military strength and economic recovery. The Mission recommends
                                that the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government adopt as a
                                working figure the suggested amount in this report and further that
                                an exhaustive reexamination of the budget be undertaken as soon as
                                possible with a view toward achieving more economies in
                                expenditures. The Mission is convinced that vigorous efforts in the
                                tax collections field will yield substantial increases in government
                                receipts and recommends a tax investigation under <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> auspices. Where U.S. and UN
                                military and civilian establishments can assist tax efforts, as by
                                income tax deduction from salaries, such arrangements should be
                                instituted without delay. Although it regards adequate government
                                pay scales as indispensable for efficient government operation the
                                Mission urges postponement of pay increases and other deferrable
                                expenditures until significant improvement in the government’s
                                financial position is achieved. Finally, the Mission recommends that
                                the closest coordination be achieved between government
                                disbursements and aid arrivals.</p>
                            <p>The Mission finds that in principle existing credit controls provide
                                adequate machinery for limiting expansion of the money supply
                                through bank lending but that the controls are ineffective in
                                practice because of the Monetary Board’s inability to limit
                                borrowing by Government and Government-sponsored enterprises. The
                                Board must be strengthened and given greater authority in making and
                                controlling implementation of monetary and credit policy. The
                                Mission believes that great progress can be made in this direction
                                by arranging for Board members to participate in <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> deliberations as representatives of
                                the monetary policy authority of the Republic of Korea, since credit
                                policy is of strategic importance on questions affecting the control
                                of the money supply. The mission further recommends that the
                                Monetary Board engage an experienced banking and monetary advisor to
                                be made available by the U.S. Government to render policy and
                                technical assistance to the Board in decisions affecting loans and
                                credit policy.</p>
                            <p>The Mission finds that the existing extensive government ownership
                                and control of industry has acted as an obstacle to developing a
                                healthy economy. Government enterprises are financially weak, poorly
                                managed and suffer from government restrictions, red tape and
                                arbitrary price policies. The Mission recommends the development of
                                a comprehensive <pb facs="0142" n="1260" xml:id="pg_1260"/> plan to
                                promote the sale or long-term leasing of vested properties to
                                private buyers.</p>
                            <p>The operating losses of the large Government enterprises constitute a
                                continuing pressure for bank loans to cover the losses. The Mission
                                recommends that <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> direct an
                                investigation into the financial position of these enterprises. The
                                Mission further recommends that such an examination include study of
                                Government monopoly operations and transportation with the view
                                toward increasing revenue derived by the government from these
                                activities.</p>
                            <p>The Mission believes that the United States Government should assist
                                Korea in determining the feasibility of establishing banking
                                facilities to mobilize domestic capital for long term investment
                                purposes and should use a portion of counterpart derived from the
                                aid program to support this purpose. The Mission further recommends
                                that the Republic of Korea Government be urged to implement the
                                General Banking Act to give the Monetary Board greater supervisory
                                authority over the bank institutions of the country.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the use of foreign exchange resources of the Republic
                                of Korea, the Mission finds that present regulations and procedures
                                governing exchange transactions prevent the most effective use of
                                available exchange. The Mission feels that full control in
                                determining foreign exchange policy should be shifted from the
                                Ministry of Finance to the Monetary Board to permit the Board better
                                to integrate the use of available exchange with fiscal and credit
                                policies. The Mission recommends that the <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> request the Monetary Board and Bank of Korea to
                                develop recommendations designed to simplify existing foreign trade
                                and foreign exchange procedures including steps to permit authorized
                                commercial banks to deal in foreign exchange. The Mission further
                                recommends a foreign exchange budget be developed in consultation
                                with the <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> to coordinate foreign
                                exchange policy with external assistance.</p>
                            <p>The Mission has found that the existing system of controlled prices
                                has proved to be ineffective in treating the economic problems of
                                the country and regards the system as an obstacle to economic
                                recovery. The Mission recommends that the <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> direct a study of the existing system and recommend
                                changes in the direction of moving as rapidly as possible to a free
                                market price basis. The Mission urges that adjustment of prices and
                                wages be made not later than six months after the aid program. The
                                Mission also feels that the Government should accept as an objective
                                the monetization of incomes and the elimination of payments in kind
                                as rapidly as possible.</p>
                            <p>The Mission recommends a devaluation of the official rate of exchange
                                to a level established in consultation with the <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss>. The Mission feels that agreement
                                by the Republic of Korea to the military conversion rate of 180–1
                                provides a basis for consultation leading to the establishment of a
                                single rate of exchange. The exchange rate adjustment <pb facs="0143" n="1261" xml:id="pg_1261"/> and the price wage
                                adjustment referred to above must be made together and the Republic
                                of Korea Government should accept as an objective the establishment
                                of a new rate not later than six months after the initiation of the
                                recommended aid program. In the interim period the Mission
                                recommends that <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> agreement be
                                sought on a policy of pricing aid goods at free market prices.</p>
                            <p>Korean membership in both the International Monetary Fund and the
                                International Bank for Reconstruction and Development should be
                                supported by the United States Government. The Mission further
                                recommends that the United States Government encourage the Republic
                                of Korea to consult with and seek technical assistance on its
                                financial problems from the Fund and the Bank.</p>
                            <p>Rationalization of the price structure and development of a valid
                                exchange rate will be of extreme importance in opening the way to
                                Korean participation in the U.S. offshore procurement program.
                                Offshore procurement in Korea of small arms, ammunition, vehicle
                                maintenance, etc. will serve to stimulate defense industries and
                                provide a source of dollar earnings. Further, permitting Korean
                                bidding for items now normally purchased in Japan would have a
                                stimulating and rehabilitating effect on Korea out of all proportion
                                to the amount involved. It would have the further healthy effect of
                                exposing segments of Korean industry to international
                                competition.</p>
                            <p>An important aspect of the proposed new assistance program would be
                                greater Korean participation at all levels than is true with respect
                                to present programs. It is recognized that possibly the most serious
                                factor limiting <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> economic
                                development may well turn out to be a shortage of professional and
                                technical skills, which can only be overcome step by step. As
                                rapidly as possible, however, it is proposed to increase Korean
                                participation in programming and procurement for all aid programs,
                                supporting such participation as necessary, with foreign advisors
                                employed and paid by the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                Governments and industry.</p>
                            <p>The political importance of such measures can hardly be
                                overestimated. Considerable resentment exists in the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government regarding the <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> method of procurement which
                                excludes the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> from operational
                                participation. Desire to be treated as an equal partner is one of
                                the strongest factors in Korean morale, fully understandable in view
                                of the political subjugation of Korea in recent times. Furthermore,
                                as a practical matter, it is desirable that the U.S. pursue a policy
                                of permitting the Koreans to stand on their own feet in such matters
                                as these as soon as possible. Finally, in view of the Government’s
                                greater familiarity with Korean needs and conditions, a primary
                                Korean role in procurement is deemed essential to assure the most
                                effective use of U.S. aid in meeting basic Korean requirements.</p>
                            <p>The development in the <gloss target="#t_CEB1">CEB</gloss> of the
                                annual investment program will naturally involve judicious
                                consideration of dollar and hwan costs and <pb facs="0144" n="1262" xml:id="pg_1262"/> availability for investment programs and will
                                probably require some revision of the current concepts under which
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> funds are considered to
                                be available only for <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>
                                sponsored projects and <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> only
                                for U.S. sponsored projects.</p>
                            <p>The Mission further recommends that as soon as practicable
                                discussions leading to a comprehensive civil affairs agreement be
                                initiated. The stability of the military situation no longer
                                justifies the continuation of the emergency arrangements under which
                                U.S. Forces now obtain the use of facilities and services. An
                                agreement independent of the aid agreement is preferable because of
                                the nature of the subject matter and of the time element; the civil
                                affairs agreement negotiation will be lengthy, and it is necessary
                                to initiate an expanded aid program with as little loss of time as
                                is possible.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">Coordination of Economic
                                    Programs</hi></p>
                            <p>The absence of central authority for economic assistance to Korea
                                cannot be corrected absolutely, because of the division of
                                responsibility which must inevitably persist between the Republic of
                                Korea and the US/UN. There must, however, be complete coordination
                                on the US/UN side and it is imperative that all external economic
                                assistance to the Republic of Korea, including relief,
                                rehabilitation, and assistance for defense support be coordinated,
                                integrated, and implemented under one head now and in the
                                post-hostilities period for all economic activities in Korea, as has
                                been done in the military field, including positive operational
                                control over <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>. Such
                                delegation of over-all economic responsibility to the <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> would only recognize facts based on the needs of
                                the situation, for there can be only one effective and authoritative
                                voice for all United Nations economic activities in Korea.</p>
                            <p>It would further be anticipated that subject only to overriding
                                military consideration <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                                operational responsibilities in the economic field would in effect
                                be concentrated in a special U.S. representative with headquarters
                                in Korea, who would represent both the President and <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>, who would serve as the
                                    <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> Representative on
                                the Combined Economic Board, and who would direct and coordinate the
                                over-all economic assistance program. This would not only provide
                                the necessary program integration but would also ensure Korean
                                support of the <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> program in a
                                measure that has been and is conspicuously lacking. In addition it
                                would provide a bridge to the post-hostilities period in
                                anticipation of the eventual phasing out of the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>It is anticipated that the internal organization of the <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> Mission in Korea could be
                                maintained substantially as at present except that certain general
                                functions common to all aid programs would be transferred to the
                                Office of the Special Representative. <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> responsibilities would be essentially those of
                                project development and implementation <pb facs="0145" n="1263" xml:id="pg_1263"/> in the rehabilitation and reconstruction
                                fields with funds available to that agency, or with such other funds
                                as might be made available. It is also anticipated that <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> would be assigned such other
                                responsibilities as appropriate and that <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> personnel would be freely seconded to <gloss target="#t_KCAC1">KCAC</gloss>, as is true at the present time,
                                and to the Office of the Special Representative. By and large it is
                                considered that <gloss target="#t_KCAC1">KCAC</gloss> will continue
                                most of its present responsibilities with regard to the operational
                                aspects of civilian relief programs and will also assume such
                                operational responsibilities with regard to other aid programs as
                                experience may indicate to be desirable.</p>
                            <p>To assure appropriate consideration in the Combined Economic Board of
                                all aspects of the over-all assistance program, it is recommended
                                that both the Commanding General of <gloss target="#t_KCAC1">KCAC</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss>
                                Mission Chief in Korea be appointed Deputy <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> representatives on the
                                Combined Economic Board.</p>
                            <p>A program of the nature herein proposed is also of concern to several
                                of the departments and agencies of the United States Government,
                                including the Departments of Defense, State, and Treasury, the
                                Mutual Security Agency, and the Bureau of the Budget.</p>
                            <p>Over-all responsibility for economic assistance to Korea should be
                                assigned to the Director of Mutual Security or his successor, who
                                would finalize annual programs, justify them to Congress, and direct
                                the expenditure of funds. This would not necessarily preclude the
                                administration of <gloss target="#t_CRIK1">CRIK</gloss> funds by the
                                Department of the Army or of funds appropriated to <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> by appropriate <gloss target="#t_UNKRA1">UNKRA</gloss> officials, but would assure
                                that all available funds were expended as part of a single over-all
                                program.</p>
                            <p>In view of the diversity of interests involved during the continuance
                                of hostilities, it is also believed that it will be necessary to
                                continue to maintain a forum for inter-departmental cooperation at a
                                senior and policy-making level. To assure this, it is recommended
                                that the present National Security Council Subcommittee on Korea be
                                continued in existence. In the event that this is not feasible, it
                                is considered essential that there be established a committee of
                                senior departmental and agency representatives outside of the
                                National Security Council framework to provide the necessary
                                forum.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>