<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Republic of Korea Draft of Mutual Defense Treaty Between the United States
                    and the Republic of Korea</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d682</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">682</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec0IxeMNnec48ljR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional security</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="682"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d682">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/7–953</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Republic of Korea Draft of Mutual Defense Treaty Between the
                        United States and the Republic of Korea</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d682fn1">This draft treaty was transmitted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> to the Department of State in
                        Army message 091320Z from Seoul, July 9, 1953.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-09">July 9,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and USA, the parties to this Treaty,
                    reaffirming their faith in purposes and principles of Charter of UN and their
                    desire to live in peace with all peoples and all governments, desiring to
                    strengthen fabric of peace in Pacific area,</p>
                <p>Remembering with deep satisfaction that earliest formal relations between our two
                    nations commenced with Amity Treaty of 1882,</p>
                <p>Recalling with mutual pride the close relationship which brought two nations
                    together in a common bond of sympathy and mutual ideals to fight side by side
                    against Communist aggression in Korea,</p>
                <p>Desiring to declare publicly and formally their sense of unity and their common
                    determination again to defend themselves against external armed attack so that
                    no potential aggressor could be under illusion that either of them stands alone
                    in Pacific area,</p>
                <p>Desiring further to strengthen their present efforts for collective defense for
                    preservation of peace and security pending development of a more comprehensive
                    and effective system of regional security in Pacific area,</p>
                <p>Agreeing that nothing in this present instrument shall be considered or
                    interpreted as in any sense or in any way altering or diminishing any existing
                    agreements or understandings between USA and <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                    >ROK</gloss>,</p>
                <pb facs="0242" n="1360" xml:id="pg_1360"/>
                <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article I</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The parties undertake, as set forth in Charter of UN, to settle any international
                    disputes in which they may be involved by peaceful means in such a manner that
                    international peace and security and justice are not endangered and to refrain
                    in their international relations from threat or use of force in any manner
                    inconsistent with purpose of UN.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article II</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The parties reaffirm their recognition of fact that lawful jurisdiction of <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> extends throughout traditional area of Korea
                    and specifically northward to Yalu and Tumen Rivers.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article III</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In order more effectively to achieve objective of this treaty, the parties
                    separately and jointly by self-help and mutual aid will maintain and develop
                    their individual and collective capacity to resist armed attack. If the US
                    should find it desirable to station its land, sea, or air forces in or about
                    Korea, arrangements for this purpose can be readily effected.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article IV</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The parties, through their Foreign Ministers or their deputies will consult
                    together from time to time regarding implementation of this treaty and whenever
                    in opinion of either of them the territorial integrity, political independence
                    or security of either of the parties is threatened by external armed attack in
                    the Pacific.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article V</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The parties agree that an armed attack against one shall be considered an attack
                    against the other; and consequently the parties agree that, if such an armed
                    attack occurs, each of them, in the exercise of the right of individual or
                    collective self-defense recognized by Article 51 of Charter of UN, will assist
                    the party so attacked by taking forthwith and immediately such action as it
                    deems necessary, including the use of armed force, to resist armed attack. Any
                    such armed attack and all measures taken as a result thereof shall be
                    immediately reported to the Security Council of the UN. Such measures shall be
                    terminated when the Security Council has taken the measures necessary to restore
                    and maintain international peace and security.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VI</hi>
                </p>
                <p>For purpose of Article IV, an armed attack on either of the parties is deemed to
                    include an armed attack on metropolitan territory of either of the parties, or
                    on the island territories under its jurisdiction in the Pacific or on its armed
                    forces, public vessels or aircraft in Pacific.</p>
                <pb facs="0243" n="1361" xml:id="pg_1361"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VII</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This treaty does not affect and shall not be interpreted as affecting in any way
                    the rights and obligations of the parties under Charter of UN or the
                    responsibility of UN for maintenance of international peace and security.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VIII</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This treaty shall be ratified by <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and USA in
                    accordance with their respective constitutional processes and will come into
                    force when instruments of ratification thereof have been exchanged by them.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article IX</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This treaty shall expire whenever in the opinion of the Government of <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and USA there shall have come into force such
                    UN arrangements or such alternative individual or collective security
                    dispositions as will satisfactorily provide for the maintenance by UN or
                    otherwise of international peace and security in the Korean area.</p>
                <p>In witness whereof the undersigned plenipotentiaries have signed this treaty,
                    etc.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
