<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d742</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">742</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="742"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d742">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/8–1053</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Denver</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1953-08-10">10 August 1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>[Subject:</head>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’trip to the Far
                        East]</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> and I met with the President for
                    about an hour, from 8:00 to 9:00 a.m. We showed both the communiqué signed by
                        <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Syngman Rhee</persName> and the Draft Security
                    Treaty initialed by Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_PYT1">Pyun</persName>
                    and myself.</p>
                <p>I pointed out that the Draft Security Treaty conformed in every essential respect
                    with the Draft which had been exhibited to and discussed with the Senate leaders
                    and that we had successfully resisted the efforts which President <persName
                        corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> had made to incorporate features which
                    might be objectionable and enlarge US responsibility.</p>
                <p>The President said he had a little concern about the initialing of the Treaty in
                    the absence of the Senators but as long as the Draft conformed to what they had
                    previously seen he thought it was OK.</p>
                <p>We went over the Joint Communiqué, explaining briefly the essential features. The
                    President expressed particular gratification at the last paragraph whereby it
                    was asserted on authority of President <persName corresp="#p_RS1"
                        >Rhee</persName> and myself that there were no secret understandings. The
                    President suggested that this point should be emphasized to the press.</p>
                <p>The President asked as to the attitude of <persName corresp="#p_TLGMD1">General
                        Taylor</persName> toward use of the Armed Forces for at least technical work
                    of reconstruction. I said that this had not been specifically discussed, but
                    that <persName corresp="#p_TLGMD1">General Taylor</persName>, in his briefing,
                    had emphasized that the Army would be engaged for several months in
                    reconstructing defense positions to replace those which had been abandoned by
                    the two kilometer withdrawal under the armistice agreement. The President
                    re-emphasized his conviction that the Army could make a large contribution to
                    “winning the peace.”</p>
                <p>There was some discussion of the future American to head the <gloss
                        target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> in view of <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General
                        Clark</persName>’s prospective retirement. The President requested me, as
                    promptly as possible, to ascertain through Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        >Wilson</persName> whether <persName corresp="#p_TLGMD1">General
                        Taylor</persName> felt that the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> could
                    operate from Korea as against Japan. The President also stated that he had told
                    the Defense Department to clear with me the question of any successor.</p>
                <p>I reported on the unsatisfactory condition in Japan as regards their own security
                    efforts and their economic extravagance in terms of imports. I said that I very
                    strongly emphasized this in the same talk with Prime Minister Yoshida when I had
                    advised him of the prospective return of the Amami Island group.</p>
                <pb facs="0374" n="1492" xml:id="pg_1492"/>
                <p>The President expressed very strongly the view that we should encourage a
                    liberalization of trade between Japan and China in terms of non-strategic goods.
                    He felt that trade could be a weapon on our side and that such trade was
                    indispensable to the livelihood of Japan.</p>
                <p>There then ensued a discussion of general character with reference to US trade
                    policies.</p>
                <p>The President expressed his satisfaction at the results which had been
                    obtained.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> brought up the question
                    of the set-up from our side of the proposed political conference and outlined
                    his plans for holding the membership to those who had combat forces in Korea. He
                    pointed out that this would exclude India, which has deliberately played the
                    role of neutral, notably as chairman of the neutral commission. He pointed out
                    that this position to exclude India would, from the standpoint of overall
                    relations, be offset by our support of Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PSVLMP1"
                        >Pandit</persName> for President of the Assembly. The President expressed
                    his concurrence in this approach.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">JFD</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
