<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India (Allen) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d750</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">750</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-08-26T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-08-26T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-26T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-26T02:30:00-05:00" n="750"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d750">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AD/8–2653: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India (<persName corresp="#p_AGV1"
                            type="from">Allen</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-26T13:00:00+05:30"
                            >August 26, 1953—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>389. Repeated <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> London 55. Re <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 216 August 24<note n="1" xml:id="d750fn1"
                        >In this telegram, <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> received
                        instructions to see <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> and urge
                        India’s voluntary withdrawal from the proposed Korean Political Conference.
                        (357.AD/8–1553)</note> and <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 388
                    August 25.<note n="2" xml:id="d750fn2">In this telegram, <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> reported that he was unable to see
                            <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>, who was tied up in a party
                        meeting; meanwhile he conveyed the substance of telegram 216 to New Delhi to
                            <persName corresp="#p_PNR1">Pillai</persName> for relaying to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> that night so that the Indian Prime
                        Minister could think it over before his meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> on Aug. 26. (357.AD/8–2553)</note>
                </p>
                <p>I saw <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> at 9:15 this morning to urge
                    India’s voluntary withdrawal from Korean political conference in accordance with
                    Department’s instructions. Conversation was most friendly, in sharp contrast to
                    yesterday’s outburst, and results were considerably better than I expected.</p>
                <p>I emphasized that US had no objection to India as such, we appreciated India’s
                    valuable and possibly decisive role in achieving armistice due to fact that
                    India was not active participant in Panmunjom negotiations, possibility that
                    India might play similar role outside political conference, and that our genuine
                    objective, as that of India, was to achieve success of conference, whether our
                    views as to how this might best be achieved were similar or not. I then pointed
                    out that if Korean conference was successful and wider discussions on Far East
                    eventuate, US would expect India as well as other countries to formally
                    participate in discussions of matters of direct interest to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> said he was confident US Government
                    was not trying to “do <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> down”. He would be
                    equally frank to say that in his personal opinion US had allowed itself to be
                    tied down closely to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>. He expressed
                    appreciation for US Government’s views (I read from telegram in order to
                    emphasize their official nature) and said these views would be given full
                    consideration. He remarked that vote was expected to be taken in <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> committee today,<note n="3" xml:id="d750fn3">On
                        Aug. 27 at the 625th meeting of the First Committee, the draft resolution to
                        invite India to attend the political conference was adopted. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Yearbook of the United Nations 1953</hi>, p. 126)</note>
                    but that some time would elapse between committee vote and consideration of
                    subject in plenary <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session. <pb facs="0383"
                        n="1501" xml:id="pg_1501"/> He said India was naturally in consultation with
                    “other powers” on subject and he did not wish to be accused of going back on his
                    word to them or acting behind their back. He would have to consult them again.
                    He added that it was difficult in rapidly-developing situations of this kind to
                    send categorical instructions to his delegation in NY and that certain amount of
                    latitude was necessary.</p>
                <p>I then said, on my own, that one reason for serious US concern in this matter was
                    due, in all frankness, to fact that we had large number of troops in Korea whom
                    we did not wish to see placed in jeopardy (Usito 10, August 24<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d750fn4">Not printed.</note> report was carried in today’s press).
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> asked whether our concern was
                    over possibility of further aggression by any one. I said if political
                    conference failed, situation would be highly unsatisfactory and tension mount,
                    in which case any spark might set off conflagration without premeditated
                    aggression by anyone.</p>
                <p>I expressed confidence that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> participated in
                    our view that while show of hands in UN might be necessary, we would much prefer
                    to avoid this contingency, with attendant animosities, if at all possible.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> said he agreed fully.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> did not refer to his statement to
                    Congress Party caucus last night, reported prominently in today’s press, that
                    India would not voluntarily withdraw under <persName corresp="#p_RS1"
                        >Rhee</persName>’s threats and I carefully avoided subject or any reference
                    to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s attitude since such reference by
                    me would have destroyed atmosphere of talk and merely brought forth further
                    tirade of abuse against <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> and against
                    our allowing him to decide our policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> did not explain “other powers” he
                    would consult, but it is obvious he had Commonwealth principally in mind,
                    although some consultation with Peking should also not be excluded. Australian
                    High Commissioner has asked to see me this morning and I am seeing acting UK
                    High Commissioner later.</p>
                <p>I think it quite possible India will release Commonwealth from obligation to vote
                    for Indian participation, Moreover, I do not believe India will participate in
                    any case if we continue firm in our disapproval.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
