<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="819" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d819">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/12–1253: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Representative for the Korean Political
                                Conference (<persName corresp="#p_DAH1" type="from">Dean</persName>)
                                to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d819fn1">This telegram was repeated to Paris for <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> who was attending the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial
                            meetings.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss></hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Munsan-Ni</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-12">December 12, 1953</date>.<note n="2" xml:id="d819fn2">There was no time of transmission indicated on
                                    this telegram, which was received at the Department of State at
                                    12:43 p.m., Dec. 12.</note></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>168. Repeated information Seoul, Tokyo, <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>, New Delhi, Department of Defense unnumbered.</p>
                        <p>At end uninterrupted 5-hour and 45 minutes meeting today from 1100 hours
                            to 1645 hours, I finally walked out after <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Huang</persName>, Chinese delegate, refused withdraw repeated
                            charges of perfidy against United <pb facs="0538" n="1656" xml:id="pg_1656"/> States after my repeated requests to do so or I
                            would consider it notification to us they were proposing indefinite
                            recess.</p>
                        <p>Last interchange between us went as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName>: “I have a
                                    statement to make.</p>
                                <p>“Your remarks today were so calculatedly rude, arrogant and
                                    insulting and you accused my government of perfidy which you
                                    know to be untrue and your remarks were made with such a
                                    complete lack of responsibility for the truth and the facts that
                                    I can only interpret your remarks as notifying us that you wish
                                    these talks to recess indefinitely. I can place no other
                                    interpretation on your actions. You have charged my government
                                    with perfidy. You know the charge to be untrue. Unless the
                                    charge is withdrawn, I shall treat it as a notice to me that you
                                    wish these talks to recess indefinitely.”</p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Huang Hua</persName>: “The
                                    position of our side is very clear. Since your side has violated
                                    the terms of reference signed by your side, it is a perfidy. Can
                                    you deny this? Do you want to break up the discussions? If you
                                    dare to bear the responsibility of breaking off the talks
                                    between the two sides, I propose to recess until Monday.”<note n="3" xml:id="d819fn3">Dec. 14.</note></p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName>: “Your charges
                                    are untrue. I therefore treat it as a notification that you wish
                                    these talks recessed indefinitely.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>During previous 2 hours and 45 minutes we listened to increasing tempo of
                            rude, arrogant intemperance and increasingly insulting abuse not against
                            me which doesn’t bother me in the slightest but against the Government
                            of the United States for “plot”, “treacherous designs” and “perfidious
                            actions”. He was reading from typewritten papers so it was calculated
                            browbeating and intentional insult which could not be ignored.
                            Specifically accused Government of USA conniving with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> to release 27,000 prisoners after
                                <persName corresp="#p_HMGWKJ1">General Harrison</persName> had
                            signed terms of reference in June. If we had merely accepted recess felt
                            our negotiating position would have become intolerable, if, indeed, not
                            impossible and with considerable reluctance finally made the move I did.
                            Am very sorry not to continue meetings but tempo of build-up has been
                            increasing to crescendo and am sure was planned insult. <persName corresp="#p_KSP1">Ki</persName> opened meeting on this note of
                            questioning my authority but not with much tone. After I finished
                            carefully reasoned statements on agenda and secretariat and stating my
                            authority to represent <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> if they could
                            represent USSR, <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Huang</persName> began tirade
                            against me for not representing all 17 and for possibility we would
                            carry out perfidious acts at Political Conference and in effect
                            challenged my authority. After I replied by denying his allegations and
                            refuting his rudeness and replying very reasonably, I proposed a recess
                            until Monday.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HH1">Huang</persName> rudely refused the recess and
                            went through long vicious harangue with increasing tempo of questions
                            regarding my authority. I answered most of his questions on voting
                            procedures in calm reasoned <pb facs="0539" n="1657" xml:id="pg_1657"/>
                            way for 2 hours and 45 minutes and calmly ignored his vilification. He
                            increasingly jeered at my answers and then he became more and more
                            insulting, arrogant and rude in tone and manner. He finally said I had
                            not answered satisfactorily, ridiculed our voting procedures as designed
                            to permit <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s to wreck conference as
                            they did armistice and finally said he would continue such questions
                            later since my answers were not correct and proposed recess until
                            Monday. I countered by saying his statements were untrue and did he want
                            indefinite recess. He replied and each time he again accused us of
                            violating armistice and perfidy and conniving with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> intentionally to release prisoners
                            in violation our agreement. After much consideration and some reflecting
                            finally concluded boded ill for our negotiations for a representative of
                            USA and of 17 free nations to take such bullying, intentionally rude
                            statements and charges of perfidy from a Chinese Communist which were
                            very carefully prepared. Honestly did not see how we could continue
                            negotiations Monday unless he withdrew his assertions. <persName corresp="#p_KSP1">Ki</persName> took no part in this at all.</p>
                        <p>Would have to recess and to make over-all statement Monday before leaving
                            but believe it would have been impossible for our future relations in
                            light of his exceptionally rude tone and obviously arrogant manner
                            today. Talks therefore are recessed indefinitely unless his charges are
                            withdrawn. Regret not carrying out instructions and took action only
                            after most careful reflection on ultimate results.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DAH1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dean</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>