<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="821" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d821">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, <persName>Whitman</persName>
                            file</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 175th Meeting of the
                                National Security Council, Tuesday, December 15, 1953</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d821fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Gleason</persName> on Dec. 16.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes
                                    only</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-12-15">December 15, 1953</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Present at this meeting were the President of the United States,
                            presiding; the Vice President of the United States; the Acting Secretary
                            of State; the Acting Secretary of Defense; the Acting Director, Foreign
                            Operations Administration; the Director, Office of Defense Mobilization.
                            Also present were the Acting Secretary of the Treasury; the Attorney <pb facs="0541" n="1659" xml:id="pg_1659"/> General; <persName>Walter
                                Williams</persName> for the Secretary of Commerce (for Item 3); the
                            Director, Bureau of the Budget; the Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission;
                            the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Director of Central
                            Intelligence; <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Robert R. Bowie</persName>,
                            Department of State; General <persName>Porter</persName>, Foreign
                            Operations Administration; the Assistant to the President; <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Robert Cutler</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                            President; <persName corresp="#p_JCD1">C. D. Jackson</persName>, Special
                            Assistant to the President; the Deputy Assistant to the President; the
                            Acting White House Staff Secretary; the Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; and the Deputy Executive Secretary,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>There follows a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the main
                            points taken.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion on items 1. “Significant World Developments
                            Affecting U.S. Security,” 2. “Continental Defense,” and 3. “Development
                            of Nuclear Power.”]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Report by the Vice
                            President</hi></p>
                        <p>In anticipation of the Vice President’s arrival, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> reviewed briefly the relevant
                            courses of action in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 170/1 and Annex
                            A thereto.<note n="2" xml:id="d821fn2">Dated Nov. 20, <ref target="#pg_1620">p. 1620</ref>.</note> He also read a telegram
                            from <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName>, dated
                            December 10, which was also germane to this subject.<note n="3" xml:id="d821fn3">Reference was to telegram C 66454, <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss> to the Department of the
                                Army, Dec. 10, not printed. (<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                records, CCS 383.2 Korea (3–19–45))</note> In view of the situation,
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> said that it seemed to
                            him sensible to press forward now with our courses of action designed to
                            deter President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> from
                            reinitiating hostilities. He asked Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> to speak to this point.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> stated that while
                                <persName corresp="#p_WCT1">Tyler Wood</persName> had finally
                            arrived at a satisfactory understanding with President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d821fn4">For
                                the text of the agreement signed at Seoul on Dec. 14 on a program
                                for strengthening the Korean economy, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, Jan. 11, 1954, pp. 65–67.</note>
                            the discussions had been extremely acrimonious. Furthermore, the other
                            serious problem, namely, the conflict between <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> and the Japanese, remained unresolved. President
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> was behaving quite
                            outrageously, and there was no solution in sight. Moreover, continued
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>, we are of course
                            now faced with the possibility of further difficulties as a result of
                            the breaking off of the Panmunjom negotiations, which he felt were not
                            likely to be renewed on any satisfactory basis. While the prisoners
                            would undoubtedly be released, we may have difficulties with India on
                            this point. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna Menon</persName> has
                            stated that the prisoners could not be released in the absence of a
                            political conference. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> again pointed out that <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> seemed to be talking a great deal of late about a
                            unilateral renewal of hostilities. While Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> apparently believes that
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> is bluffing, one could
                            never tell, since <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> is such an
                            incalculable quantity.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> thought there was
                            very good reason at this point to review the courses of action set forth
                            in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 170/1, with particular <pb facs="0542" n="1660" xml:id="pg_1660"/> respect to ways and means of
                            preventing <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> from initiating
                            hostilities. He noted that <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General
                                Hull</persName>, among other things, had been directed to consult
                            with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> army leaders in order to
                            prevent <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> from acting
                            unilaterally. There was danger that <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General
                                Hull</persName> would, in following this directive, talk to so many
                            leaders that it would be as good as publishing to the world an effort to
                            undermine the loyalty of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> army to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> thought we should go
                            very slowly in implementing such a course of action, and the President
                            expressed emphatic agreement with this view. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> also commented on the danger of
                            giving <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 170/1 as a directive to the
                            people in the field. It should, he thought, have been confined to the
                            people around this table. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> further suggested that when <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> went to Korea in the
                            near future he should sit down and explain to <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName> the objectives we sought
                            in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 170/1 and devise the best ways
                            and means of reaching these objectives.</p>
                        <p>The President said that it had certainly never been his intention to take
                            action which would undermine the <hi rend="italic">esprit de corps</hi>
                            of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> army or destroy its
                            loyalties. He not only agreed with the proposal that <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> discuss this subject
                            with <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName>, but
                            recommended that Generals <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">Hull</persName>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_TLGMD1">Taylor</persName> be brought back
                            every few months for consultation.</p>
                        <p>After a brief discussion of the situation in Iceland and the status of
                            our bases in Morocco, the Vice President arrived from the State
                            Department and was asked by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> to report to the Council briefly on the results
                            of his conversations with President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President stated that the best way to summarize his talks with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> was first to
                            analyze what we are seeking to accomplish in Korea. President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> was a very complex character, as we
                            all knew. The Vice President had had two conversations with <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>, one lasting two hours and the
                            other an hour and a half, and these conversations had heightened the
                            Vice President’s impression of <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s complexity. On the other hand, it was important
                            to distinguish between what <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            says and what he will actually do—his public actions from his private
                            thoughts. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> had what might be
                            described as a conspiratorial mind, not unlike that of a Communist.
                            Accordingly, it was possible to draw erroneous conclusions from his
                            statements.</p>
                        <p>My assignment, continued the Vice President, was to deliver to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> the letter from President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d821fn5">For text, see the enclosure to the letter from <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, Nov. 4, <ref target="#pg_1591">p. 1591</ref>.</note> This letter was
                            unequivocal in content, and I delivered it. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s reaction was one of considerable emotional shock,
                            and he began at once his sparring tactics to avoid the commitment which
                            President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s letter had
                            asked for. At last, however, we did get down to the commitment, and when
                            we had reached this point <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            finally said, after protestations of his desire to <pb facs="0543" n="1661" xml:id="pg_1661"/> follow President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s wishes and to respect U.S.
                            interests, that he would not do anything unless and until he had
                            informed the President of the United States.</p>
                        <p>In subsequent conversations with our Ambassador and other officials, they
                            all stated their feeling that <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            had gone further than he had ever gone before. Actually, however, said
                            the Vice President, at his final meeting with President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> he went even further. He had
                            prepared in advance two typed pages of what he was going to say, and he
                            gave these two pages to the Vice President after he had read them
                            aloud.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> believes that in the battle
                            with Communism you must always make an effort to retain a good
                            bargaining position, just as the Communists always sought such a
                            position. It was necessary for them continually to fear what you might
                            do. Hence any public announcement by <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> of a denial of intent to resume hostilities without
                            U.S. approval would actually weaken the position of the United States at
                            the conference table. Indeed, such an announcement would assure the
                            Communists of much greater freedom of action. Why, inquired <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>, could not President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> make the same use of me and
                            the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> as the Communists use their
                            satellites—to take positions which subsequently the USSR itself might or
                            might not stand by, depending on the circumstances?</p>
                        <p>The Vice President also commented that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName> was inclined to agree that this
                            argument of President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> had
                            some merit and that it was indeed unwise to pull all of <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s teeth.</p>
                        <p>So, to sum up: I do not believe that <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> will take any action of the sort we fear without
                            prior notification to the President. Nor will he take any action unless
                            he is assured that the U.S. will go along. He will, however, continue to
                            utter threats for reasons which are not, even now, wholly clear to me,
                            since he knows in his heart that as a practical matter he can never get
                            away with any course of action which would forfeit U.S. support.</p>
                        <p>Another complicating factor is that <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> hears from time to time from friends in the United
                            States that he will actually have American support if he “goes it
                            alone”. The Vice President stated that he had done his best to disabuse
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> of this belief, speaking
                            to him as a friend. All in all, therefore, the Vice President felt that
                            we have finally got across to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            the realization that we will not back him up if he moves along the
                            course that he has threatened. This realization, said the Vice
                            President, would almost certainly control <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s action. He will nevertheless continue violently
                            to oppose the presence of the Soviet Union at the political conference
                            except as a belligerent. Moreover he will continue to be violently
                            opposed to India’s presence, since he regards that nation as no more
                            than a Communist satellite.</p>
                        <pb facs="0544" n="1662" xml:id="pg_1662"/>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> observed that if
                            this report proved to be accurate, we could certainly make great use of
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> as a threat to the
                            Communists.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President answered that that was precisely why <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> was so anxious that his pledge to
                            the President should not be made public.</p>
                        <p>The President inquired whether it would not be a good idea to place in
                            the files of the Council a single copy of the original memorandum which
                            the Vice President had sent from Korea describing his conferences with
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>.<note n="6" xml:id="d821fn6">This memorandum is printed in its original form as
                                a draft telegram from <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>,
                                Nov. 13, <ref target="#pg_1609">p. 1609</ref>.</note> No other
                            copies were to be made.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> pointed out that
                            the Vice President was presumably unaware of the recent decision to
                            withdraw two divisions of our troops from Korea. We have been discussing
                            the best means of making a public announcement of this move. Should
                                <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> be told privately of this
                            proposal before the public announcement was made? Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> answered that President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> should by all means be told in
                            advance.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President said that he had one final point to make. We very
                            frequently hear, particularly from diplomatic personnel who are
                            irritated by <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s maneuvers,
                            that <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> did not have the genuine
                            support of the people of South Korea. If I am convinced of anything as a
                            result of my visit, continued the Vice President, it is the very
                            complete support which the President enjoys in Korea and also the strong
                            popular desire to achieve the unification of Korea. Accordingly, we must
                            be very cautious in judging the temper of the Korean people. This had
                            proved very different from what the Vice President had anticipated
                            before he got to Korea.</p>
                        <p>The National Security Council:<note n="7" xml:id="d821fn7">The following
                                paragraph constituted <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No.
                                986, a record copy of which can be found in <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous)
                                files, lot 66 D 95.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Discussed a preliminary oral report by the Vice President on his
                                    recent world trip, with specific reference to his conversations
                                    with President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>.</p></quote></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GSE1">S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett
                                        Gleason</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>