<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in India</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d832</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">832</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-01-04T19:21:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-01-04T19:21:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3XEGKKPtP3pRdp" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners">Prisoner release</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-04T19:21:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-04T19:21:00-05:00" n="832"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d832">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/1–454: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d832fn1">Also repeated for action to <persName
                            corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> at Munsan-ni and to Tokyo with
                        instructions to pass it to <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1"
                        >CINCUNC</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-01-04T19:21:00-05:00"
                            >January 4, 1954—7:21 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>770. 1. Briefing meeting with group of sixteen today produced general agreement
                    desirable resume Panmunjom conversations preferably before January 22. Re last
                    para New Delhi’s 1032<note n="2" xml:id="d832fn2">Not printed, but see <ref
                            target="#d831fn7">footnote 7</ref>, <hi rend="italic">
                            <ref target="#d832">supra</ref>
                        </hi>.</note> we feel on balance beneficial effect of move to resume on
                    Indian Government and others outweighs possible though slight risk of
                    complicating prisoner release question. Resumption will also help avoid
                    premature convocation of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. Therefore we would
                    hope if talks could not be resumed by January 22 we could at least work out
                    arrangements for resumption prior to that date.</p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> should therefore make high-level
                    approach to Indians asking if they would not wish sound out Chinese Communists
                    on possibility resumption Panmunjom talks. This would not be a formal request
                    for Indians to take any specific action, and in anything they did we would
                    expect them to approach Chinese Communists as if they were themselves initiating
                    proposition in interests reaching political settlement in Korea. Resumption
                    might be on basis of Chinese Communist agreement expunge statements they made re
                    “perfidy” at last Panmunjom meeting, simply as technical matter of rectifying
                    record and as not germane, and not as prejudicing any position or claims on
                    substance. Alternatively, if Communists react negatively to this idea, perhaps
                    Indians could explore <pb facs="0574" n="1692" xml:id="pg_1692"/> possibility
                    expunging Panmunjom record so as also to remove our charge Chinese Communists
                    are Soviet agents, under same qualification.</p>
                <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> in his discretion should raise
                    matter with Indians in same terms. In both cases, important it be made
                    completely clear we are not moving with undue haste or attempting exercise any
                    pressure; that this is not formal request for resumption and that we would
                    welcome Indian assistance in making soundings on their own initiative to
                    ascertain Chinese Communist response.<note n="3" xml:id="d832fn3">
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> sent the
                            following response in telegram 1050, Jan. 5, from New Delhi: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In absence of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1"
                                        >Nehru</persName> I discussed question of resuming Panmunjom
                                    conversations with Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_NRK1"
                                        >R. K. Nehru</persName> today, stating that Department
                                    wished to find out whether <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                                    might be willing to sound out Chinese Communists on this
                                    question. I emphasized that any action <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                                        >GOI</gloss> might take should be at <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                                        >GOI</gloss> initiative and without reference to our
                                    approach.</p>
                                <p>“R. K. said he would take matter up promptly with Prime Minister
                                    when latter returns to Delhi tomorrow at noon. R. K.’s personal
                                    reaction was sympathetic. I think he was pleased at this
                                    indication of our belief that <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                                        >GOI</gloss> might play useful role.</p>
                                <p>“R. K. asked how we thought demands by both sides that charges be
                                    withdrawn might be overcome. I said we thought conference record
                                    might be edited and perfidy charge omitted. If Communists
                                    insisted we also edit out charge that Chinese Communists were
                                    Soviet agents, I thought we would be agreeable.</p>
                                <p>“He asked whether we had any specific date in mind for resumption
                                    of talks. I said I thought we were ready at any time agreement
                                    could be reached.” (795.00/1–554)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
