<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Deputy Representative for the Korean Political Conference (Young) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d854</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">854</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-01-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="854"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d854">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/1–1554: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Deputy Representative for the Korean Political Conference
                            (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="from">Young</persName>) to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Munsan-ni</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-01-15">January 15,
                            1954</date>.<note n="1" xml:id="d854fn1">No time of transmission was
                            indicated on this telegram, which was received at the Department of
                            State at 5:54 a.m., Jan. 15.</note>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>221. Repeated information Seoul, Tokyo, <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1"
                        >CINCUNC</gloss> unnumbered. Regarding possibility of retraction Communists
                    charges, there now seem to be enough indications Communists may resist and then
                    refuse make any change whatsoever in the record of previous meetings.</p>
                <p>Soundings made by the Indians in Peiping and Kaesong last week indicate
                    Communists take position there are no obstructions to resumption of the talks.
                    The insistence in their letters of liaison meetings only to agree on the date
                    and their statements in first two liaison meetings follow out their basic
                    positions that there are no impediments to talks.<note n="2" xml:id="d854fn2">A
                        report of these inconclusive liaison meetings can be be found in telegram
                        22, Jan. 15, 1954, not printed. (795.00/1–1554)</note> We thus start the
                    liaison meetings with a basic divergence. Yet Communists have not, so far, gone
                    completely out on limb against making any changes in the record. There may still
                    be some slight flexibility left.</p>
                <p>This may be a difficult period to negotiate with the Chinese Communists any
                    backtracking in public on their charges, no matter how we seek to ease them into
                    it. It is probably a question of face and prestige for them as well as a
                    disinclination to make any concessions to our side at a time when they are
                    wrought up over the “release” of the prisoners which is a major issue of
                    “prestige” for them. The neutrals at Panmunjom consider the release, following
                    the results of explanation, a substantial “psychological defeat” for the Chinese
                    Communists particularly in view of the fact that, as things now stand, the
                    Indians are thwarting Peiping by carrying out an action which <persName
                        corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> has protested to <pb facs="0609"
                        n="1727" xml:id="pg_1727"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> in the strongest possible terms and
                    which directly counters the Communist position on the <gloss target="#t_PW1"
                        >PW</gloss> question.</p>
                <p>Am certainly not suggesting that we should not stick to our guns at Panmunjom. We
                    must. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Martin</persName> and I will do our best
                    tactfully to negotiate the question of retraction or expunging the record in
                    such a way the Communists are not confronted with an unacceptable public
                    challenge. We are aware their sensibilities and question on face as well as need
                    keep some flexibility between their position and ours on expunging record.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Young</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
