<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    (Drumright) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d921</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">921</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="921"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d921">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/7–1254</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                        Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="from"
                            >Drumright</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d921fn1">According to an attached memorandum by <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_OCRL1"
                            >O’Connor</persName>, July 16, this memorandum for the Secretary did not
                        reach the Executive Secretariat until <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName> had left for consultations with Congress; therefore,
                        it was sent to <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> who approved it.
                        However, according to a marginal note by <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1"
                            >McClurkin</persName>, who drafted both memoranda, <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> did see it on July 19, 1954.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-16">July 16,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Redeployment from Korea.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Your telegram of June 26 to Seoul, Tokyo, Taipei and Saigon<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d921fn2">The reference was to telegram 1043 to Seoul, <ref
                            target="#pg_1815">p. 1815</ref>.</note> concerning redeployment from
                    Korea brought forth considerable comment from, and difference of opinion among,
                    the posts mentioned, <persName corresp="#p_VFLGJA1">General Van Fleet</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName>. The chief points made
                    are summarized below: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Redeployment to the United States would be interpreted as a sign of
                            weakness, but deployment from Korea to other places in the Far East
                            could be publicly treated as increasing strategic flexibility of United
                            States forces.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Publicity should be minimized except as the increased strategic
                            flexibility can be stressed.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and other Governments
                            concerned should be informed in advance. Discussions with the <gloss
                                target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> should not take place until we are
                            prepared to tell them what we will do to strengthen or increase their
                            defense forces.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Any plans for redeployment should be considered in the context of our
                            whole Far East policy.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_VFLGJA1">General Van Fleet</persName> recommends
                            redeployment from Japan first, simultaneous announcement of 10
                            additional native combat divisions each for Japan, Korea and Formosa
                            (these would be reduced-strength or reserve divisions except for two in
                            the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>), and later movement of two
                            divisions from Korea—one to go to Okinawa and the Philippines and one to
                            Hawaii.</item>
                        <pb facs="0720" n="1838" xml:id="pg_1838"/>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName> recommends
                            redeployment of two divisions from Korea first, with one division going
                            to Okinawa and one to Hawaii, no further withdrawals from Korea or from
                            Japan until United States policy for the whole Far East is determined,
                            and no announcement of, or policy for, 10 additional native combat
                            divisions each for the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, Japan and
                            Formosa. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>
                            agrees. <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName> recommends
                            development of additional reduced-strength Korea divisions which he says
                            can be done within presently authorized personnel strength and with
                            available equipment. Additional military support funds of at least $100
                            million will be required.</item>
                        <label>(8)</label>
                        <item>[<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General
                                Hull</persName> has announced the plan to withdraw the First Cavalry
                            Division from Hokkaido to Northern Honshu, thus turning the defense of
                            Hokkaido over to the Japanese forces. He will soon submit a plan for the
                            scheduled withdrawal of United States forces from Japan.</item>
                        <label>(9)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName> reports that since
                            last spring 8 out of 19 Chinese Communist armies have been moved out of
                            North Korea. North Korean forces have been increased from six corps to
                            seven and have gained in effectiveness. The UN forces are stronger than
                            Communist forces and are relatively stronger than they were at the time
                            of the Armistice since <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces have
                            been increased by five divisions and “improved tremendously” while
                            United States forces have been reduced by only two divisions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I suggest that decisions on deployment from Korea should be made in the course of
                    preparations for President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s visit
                    and that these decisions should be discussed with him along with United States
                    plans for the increase or strengthening of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss> forces.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
