<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Commander in Chief, Far East (Hull) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d940</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">940</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">United States Army</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="940"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d940">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/9–1054</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Commander in Chief, Far East (<persName
                            corresp="#p_HGJE1" type="from">Hull</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-10">September 10,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Matters of Concern to the Far East Command with Respect to Korea</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Neutral Nations Supervisory Commission</hi>. I have
                        noted with appreciation your efforts to persuade the Swiss and the Swedes to
                        declare publicly that Communist obstructionist tactics have rendered the
                            <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> completely ineffective as a
                        neutral organization under the Armistice Agreement and to announce their
                        withdrawal from that body.<note n="1" xml:id="d940fn1">In telegram 316 to
                            Bern and 166 to Stockholm, Sept. 3, the Department of State instructed
                            the respective Embassies to approach the Swiss and Swedish Foreign
                            Ministries and state that the United States was strongly in favor of
                            their withdrawal from the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> before
                            the opening of the UN General Assembly. (795.00/8–2545)</note> I share
                        your concern that if the present situation is permitted to persist too long,
                        the US may be confronted with the adverse effects which would inevitably
                        follow unilateral <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> action against the
                            <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> or which would result if the
                        Communists were successful in obtaining a resolution during the 9th General
                        Assembly of the UN to the effect that the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1"
                            >NNSC</gloss> is functioning satisfactorily. We should not wait too long
                        for <pb facs="0756" n="1874" xml:id="pg_1874"/> evidences of cooperation in
                        this matter on the part of the Swiss and Swedes, who may be motivated by an
                        over-anxiety to preserve neutral appearances. The most positive solution,
                        and thus perhaps the best one available to us, may be the unilateral action
                        on the part of the United Nations Command which I have proposed on several
                        occasions. I would have my representative in the Military Armistice
                        Commission announce to the Communist side that they have by their actions is
                        the north confronted the UN side with a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                        abrogation of this portion of the Armistice Agreement and, while reluctant
                        to do so, we have no alternative but to consider those provisions of the
                        Armistice Agreement which pertain to the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1"
                            >NNSC</gloss> as null and void.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Prevention of Unilateral Action by Korea</hi> As you know,
                        there have been reports of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> preparations
                        for unilateral military action intended to embroil US forces with the
                        Communists. If such an action is attempted it is most likely to be attempted
                        within the next month, before the departure of major US forces from Korea.
                        As US forces depart, or prepare for departure, more and more control over
                        their own logistic support must be given to the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                            >ROK</gloss> forces. They then become more capable of offensive action.
                        When President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> was considering a
                            <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> offensive some time ago, the senior
                            <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> generals convinced him that the
                        offensive could end only in failure and <persName corresp="#p_RS1"
                            >Rhee</persName> gave it up. That plan was for an all out offensive. We
                        believe that the plan now most likely to be attempted would only create an
                        incident or start hostilities in an effort to get us involved. In the hope
                        that the senior <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> generals can again
                        influence <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLGMD1">General Taylor</persName> and I have both made it
                        clear to them that the reopening of hostilities by the <gloss
                            target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> will not be supported by the US nor will we
                        be deceived by any faked incident designed to cast blame on the
                        Communists.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Signature on Memorandum of Understanding</hi>. I was
                        delighted with the strong position which you took in insisting on signature
                        on the part of President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> of the
                        Memorandum of Understanding developed as a result of the Washington
                        conference. Indications being received by me and by <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLGMD1">General Taylor</persName> in Korea point to the
                        probability that President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> will
                        display a reluctance to sign the Memorandum or will attempt to force the
                        United States to agree to major modification of that instrument. It is my
                        hope that you will adhere to the position you have taken. Over the past
                        months, cooperation and conciliation have only produced opposition or even
                        outright antagonism. Firmness on our part not only gives promise of success,
                        because it has long been effective with Orientals, but it may well serve to
                        stiffen the resolution of those who are in opposition to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> on matters vitally affecting the United
                        States interest.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. E. Hull</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">General, United States Army</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
