<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                    <head>No. 96.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Reinberg</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Hunter</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guayaquil,
                                    Ecuador</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-03-02"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2, 1885</date>.
                            (Received March 26.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 105.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose you herewith copy
                        of Consular Agent Goddard’s dispatch No. 23, dated February 20, 1885, having
                        reference to his interview with Mr. Santos; also, copy of declaration of Mr.
                        Gumercindo Villacis, former political chief (<hi rend="italic">jefe
                            politico</hi>) of the district where Mr. Santos resided, referring
                        likewise to the case of Mr. Santos.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>MARTIN REINBERG,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                Vice-Consul-General.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 105.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goddard</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Reinberg</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consular Agency</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bahia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-20"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 20,
                                    1885</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 23.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I have the honor to advise you that
                            U. S. S. Wachusett arrived here on 14th instant, and that, in
                            conformance with your instructions, proceeded in her to Manta, from
                            which place I went, in company with Commander Mahan, of Wachusett, <pb facs="0322" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> to Monte-Cristi for the
                            purpose of interviewing Mr. J. R. Santos, the prisoner in the hands of
                            the Ecuadorian Government charged with complicity in the late
                            revolutionary movement in this province.</p>
                        <p>The answers of Mr. Santos to the questions put to him by Commander Mahan
                            and myself were all written down and delivered by me to Commander Mahan,
                            to be forwarded to you. I also succeeded in obtaining an amount of
                            corroborative evidence bearing directly on the subject of the intention
                            of Mr. Santos to return to the country of his adoption, all of which I
                            handed to Commander Mahan, retaining at the consulate copies.</p>
                        <p>I have also the pleasure to inclose you a copy of an official dispatch
                            which I received this morning from the minister of foregn affairs, with
                            date January 4, 1885, which surprises me, as Mr. Beach’s letter of
                            January 21 is now before me, in which Mr. Beach advises me that on the
                            date mentioned he called upon the secretary of foreign relations and
                            that the secretary promised to have the charges investigated which had
                            been adduced against me.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>E. T. GODDARD,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consular
                                    Agent.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Since writing above I have obtained another declaration bearing on
                                the Santos case from the former political chief, which I now
                                inclose.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 105.]</seg></opener>
                        <p>At Bahia de Caráquez, on the 21st day of the month of February, 1885, Mr.
                            Gumercindo Villacis, being present at this consulate, took oath as a
                            Catholic, and under that oath declared that he knew that Don Julio R.
                            Santos went to North America, while still a minor, for the purpose of
                            receiving his education, and that he resided there for many years; that
                            the said Mr. Santos had repeatedly told him, in private conversations,
                            that it was his intention to leave Ecuador and to settle permanently in
                            North America with his whole family; that his brother, Mr. Santos Elias
                            Santos, left here and went to that city (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>)
                            with the same intention, proposing to establish a mercantile house which
                            was to begin operations on the 1st day of January, 1885; that he knew
                            that Mr. Santos had accepted no public office involving the exercise of
                            jurisdiction; that while he (deponent) had held the office of political
                            chief of this canton he had frequently requested the said gentleman to
                            accept some office in this locality, which he had always refused to do
                            on the ground that he was an American citizen.</p>
                        <p>He declared the foregoing statement to be true, according to the oath
                            which he had taken, and signed, G. Villacis.</p>
                        <p>I, the undersigned consular officer, certify that the foregoing was
                            declared under oath in my presence.</p>
                        <closer><signed>E. J. GODDARD,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consular
                                    Agent</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>