<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="154" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                    <head>No. 150.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pendleton</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-16"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1885</date>.
                            (Received November 30.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 114.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith an article, with
                        translation, from the Staatsburger Zeitung, of this city, of the 15th
                        instant.</p>
                    <p>It has no special significance except as showing the views taken by very many
                        Germans of the power of expulsion, and its reasonable exercise in the given
                        cases.</p>
                    <p>It is hardly necessary to say that the correspondent speaks for himself
                        alone, and that I am responsible for nothing except the statement of the
                        number of cases in the neighborhood of Föhr, in which my intervention was at
                        that time sought.</p>
                    <p>Inclosed herewith I also transmit an article, with translation, from the
                        Berlin Preussische Zeitung of the 13th instant.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>GEO. H. PENDLETON.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                114.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Extract from the Staatsburger Zeitung of Sunday,
                                November</hi> 15.</head>
                        <p>In relation to the expulsion of German-American citizens, the Berlin
                            correspondent of the Breslau Morning Zeitung, who has spent some years
                            in the United States, writes the following:</p>
                        <p>According to information from the island Föhr, fifteen German-Americans
                            have suddenly received the order to leave. This news was all the more
                            calculated to excite great uneasiness among the ten thousand
                            German-Americans who again live in Germany, because they see the
                            numerous expulsions of the subjects of other nationalities. In order to
                            come to the truth of the matter I visited the American minister, Mr.
                            Pendleton, and asked for information. Whilst the minister declared that
                            he did not know the number of notices of expulsion, he said also that
                            his intervention had been sought in four cases only; that is, in other
                            words, that notices have in fact been given in four cases only, for
                            never has a notice of expulsion been given to an American without his
                            claiming the intervention of the minister, and that coincides with my
                            information from other sources. With this statement vanishes also the
                            exaggeration of the report, for these four cases are announced not from
                            Föhr alone, but from the neighborhood of Föhr. From the islands and the
                            coasts young men can easily emigrate to America. It is very possible
                            that these four men have returned at the same time and attract some
                            attention. In any case these events in the north of Germany have been
                            repeated nowhere else. And it can be said in the most certain manner
                            that here is no question of a new system; but that a fact which has
                            happened occasionally for years has attracted special attention because
                            of the time at which it happened, and has been immoderately exaggerated.
                            The new American minister, even <pb facs="0395" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/> in the short time he has been in Berlin, has experienced, as his
                            predecessors, Bancroft, Kasson, Taylor, Sargent, &amp;c., were
                            accustomed to say, that the German Government shows no disposition to he
                            especially hard on German-Americans. Questions usually arise in relation
                            to those who have not performed their military duty. Political suspects
                            must expect to be treated more sharply.</p>
                        <p>Young German-Americans are usually given the choice, either to return to
                            America or to perform the duties here of a German subject, if they draw
                            special attention to themselves. The so-called Bancroft treaty, which
                            regulates this subject, provides that the German who has become an
                            American citizen and then returns to Germany, shall be considered an
                            American citizen for two years, but afterwards shall be held to be a
                            German subject again. This provision, clear as it seems to be, is
                            subject to question, and has given rise to differences of opinion as to
                            its meaning. Whilst Germany claims that the native German who acquires
                            American naturalization becomes again a German after two years, America
                            asserts that even after the lapse of two years there is needed some
                            especial indication of his surrender of his American citizenship, and
                            out of this spring up many differences. But they have always been in
                            some way reconciled. That a young German, who shortly before he is
                            required to enter the army, leaves Germany, and returns immediately
                            after the lapse of five years, which are necessary for American
                            naturalization, to snap his fingers in the face of the Government,
                            should be held either to perform his military duty here or to return to
                            America, even the American papers find entirely right. They are not mild
                            in their judgment over those who wish to enjoy the rights of citizenship
                            in two nations and to perform the duties of citizenship in neither. They
                            have no sympathy with those of whom they with right declare that they
                            would be just as ready to claim German protection if it would avail to
                            screen them from the perfarmance of a duty to the United States. The
                            four cases on the island Föhr are not distinguishable from those
                            described above. Up to this time nothing has been determined as to
                            them.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                114.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Extract from the Berlin Preussische Zeitung of
                                November</hi> 13, 1885.</head>
                        <dateline>[<date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-13">November 13,
                                1885</date>]</dateline>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">the settlement of foreigners.</hi></p>
                        <p>In North Schleswig, an old ordinance against the settlement of foreigners
                            has been again enforced. The landrath of the district Hardesleben has
                            given notice that the decree of the 5th November, 1841, is still in
                            force, according to which no foreigner can settle in any circuit of the
                            district without official sanction, or even take up a temporary
                            residence in any circuit without permission.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>