<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="240" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                        <head>No. 236.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">L.
                                    West</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-12-07"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 7,
                                1886</date>. (Received December 9.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your note of the 30th of
                            July last, I am instructed by the Earl of Iddesleigh to communicate to
                            you the inclosed copy of a dispatch, with its inclosures, from the
                            officer administering the Government of Canada, respecting the action of
                            the customs officer at Magdalen Islands, in the case of the United
                            States fishing vessel Mascotte.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>L. S. SACKVILLE WEST.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in note of December 7,
                                    1886.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Acting Governor Lord <persName type="from">A. G.
                                        Russell</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Stanhope</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Halifax, Nova Scotia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-10-30"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 30, 1886</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your telegraphic
                                message of the 22d August, and to your dispatch of the 25th of
                                August, marked Secret, transmitting copy of a dispatch from Her
                                Majesty’s chargé d’affaires at Washington, with a note from Mr.
                                Bayard, complaining of the action of the customs officer at Magdalen
                                Islands with reference to the American fishery schooner Mascotte. I
                                have the honor to forward herewith a copy of an approved minute of
                                the privy council of Canada, embodying a report of the minister of
                                marine and fisheries on the subject.</p>
                            <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer><signed>A. G. RUSSELL,<lb/><hi rend="italic">General.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0570" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2 in note of December 7,
                                    1886.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Report of a committee of the honorable the privy
                                    council, approved by his excellency th administrator of the
                                    Government in council for Canada on the 30th day of
                                October</hi>, 1886.</head>
                            <p>The committee of the privy council have had under consideration a
                                telegram of the 22d August and a dispatch of the 25th August last,
                                from the right honorable the secretary of state for the colonies,
                                transmitting copy of a letter from Her Majesty’s minister at
                                Washington, inclosing a note from Mr. Secretary Bayard, complaining
                                of the action of the customs officer at Magdalen Islands, with
                                reference to the American fishing schooner Mascotte.</p>
                            <p>The minister of marine and fisheries, to whom the correspondence was
                                referred, observes that Mr. Bayard, in his note to the British
                                minister at Washington, says:</p>
                            <p>“I am also in possession of the affidavit of Alex. T. Vachem,<note n="*" xml:id="d240fn1">So to the British copy, The master’s name
                                    is Alex. McEachern, (See Doc. No. 66, page 147.)</note> master
                                of the American fishing schooner Mascotte, who entered Port Amherst,
                                Magdalen Islands, and was there threatened by the customs official
                                with seizure of his vessel if he attempted to obtain bait for
                                fishing or take a pilot.”</p>
                            <p>And from a report of the customs officer at Magdalen Islands, a copy
                                of which, so far as it relates to the case in point, is hereto
                                annexed, it appears that no grounds exist for the complaint made by
                                the master of the Mascotte.</p>
                            <p>The minister states that Captain Vachem [McEachern] was served with a
                                printed copy of the “warning,” and was, in addition, informed by the
                                collector that under the treaty of 1818 he had no right to buy bait
                                or to ship men. He was not forbidden to take fish, but, on the
                                contrary, the collector pointed out to him on the chart the places
                                in which, by the convention of 1818, he, as a United States
                                fisherman, had the right to inshore fishing, and one of the places
                                so pointed out to him was the Magdalen Islands.</p>
                            <p>Notwithstanding the “warning” and the personal explanation of the
                                collector, it appears that Captain Vachem [McEachern] did go up the
                                country and attempt to hire men, and upon his return informed the
                                collector that he could not get any. For this, clearly an illegal
                                act, he was not interfered with by the collector.</p>
                            <p>The minister further observes that the convention of 1818, while it
                                grants to United States fishermen the right of fishing in common
                                with British subjects on the shores of the Magdalen Islands, does
                                not confer upon them privileges of trading or of shipping men, and
                                it was against possible acts of the latter kind, and not against
                                fishing inshore, or seeking the rights of hospitality guaranteed
                                under the treaty, that Captain Vachem [McEachern] was warned by the
                                collector.</p>
                            <p>With reference to the remarks of the colonial secretary that “Her
                                Majesty’s Government would recommend that special instructions
                                should be issued to the authorities at the places where the inshore
                                fisheries has been granted by the convention of 1818 to the United
                                States fishermen, calling their attention to the provisions of that
                                convention, and warning them that no action contrary thereto may be
                                taken in regard to United States fishing vessels,” the minister
                                states that the circular instructions issued to collectors of
                                customs recite the articles of the convention of 1818, which grant
                                to United States fishermen the right to take fish upon the shore of
                                the Magdalen Islands, and of certain parts of the coasts of Labrador
                                and Newfoundland, which instructions the collector in question had
                                received, and the import of which his report shows him to be
                                familiar with.</p>
                            <p>In addition to this, the commander of the fishery protection steamer
                                La Canadienne was ordered to visit Magdalen Islands, and explain
                                fully to collectors there the extent of their powers.</p>
                            <p>The minister, in view of these instructions, printed and oral, does
                                not deem it necessary to send further special orders.</p>
                            <p>The committee, concurring in the foregoing report, advise that your
                                excellency be moved to transmit a copy hereof, if approved, to the
                                right honorable the secretary of state for the colonies.</p>
                            <p>All which is respectfully submitted for your excellency’s
                                approval.</p>
                            <closer><signed>JOHN J. McGEE,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Clerk, Privy
                                        Council.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in note of December 7,
                                    1886.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Poinchaud</persName>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Minister of Marine and
                                    Fisheries</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Custom-House, Magdalen
                                        Islands</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-08-28"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 28,
                                        1886</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge the receipt of
                                your telegram respecting captain of the schooner Mascotte’s report
                                in reference to my having threatened him with seizure.</p>
                            <p>I replied, on receipt: “Mascotte information incorrect. Particulars
                                per mail Tuesday.”</p>
                            <pb facs="0571" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                            <p>Particulars: On arrival of the captain I served him a “warning”
                                personally; informed him he could not buy [(?) bait] or ship
                                men.</p>
                            <p>I say this to all American fishermen. He tried, however, to hire;
                                went up the country to hire, but could not hire a man.</p>
                            <p>I saw him and men go up, and on his return he told me he could not
                                hire. I did not oppose him. He attended halibutting at Seven
                                Islands, Dominion. I found this out since. I deny having said I
                                would seize him if he obtained bait, himself or crew. I did not use
                                the term, but it suits the captain or owners to use it, as it serves
                                their meaning to make the report good.</p>
                            <p>I particularly showed him where, on the chart, he had the right to
                                fish inshore, to wit, at the Magdalen Islands, Cape Ray, &amp;c., as
                                per treaty in my hands then.</p>
                            <p>I think I was very lenient with him and all American fishermen
                                calling here, knowing their privileges.</p>
                            <p>I treated them so gentlemanly that I am surprised to hear he made the
                                above inaccurate report to you.</p>
                            <p>Yours, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer><signed>J. B. F. POINCHAUD,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Collector of
                                        Customs.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>