<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 288.Mr. Stallo to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1886-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1886-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recuDOya1d5mZZhX2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85080659"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Manufactured product</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="292"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                <head>No. 288.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Stallo</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rome, Italy</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-06-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 19, 1886</date>. (Received July
                        3.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 69.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that, in obedience to
                    your telegraphic instruction of the 9th April, 1886, I have attended the
                    International Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property, held in
                    Borne from the 30th of April to the 11th of May, 1886. I have withheld ray
                    report up to the present time because I have just come into possession of the
                    minutes of the conference, which had to be submitted to its several members
                    before it was finally printed.</p>
                <p>The conference was attended by representatives of Belgium, Brazil, Spain, France,
                    Great Britain, Italy, Norway and Sweden, the Netherlands, Portugal, Servia,
                    Switzerland, and Tunis.</p>
                <p>These countries, with the exception of Great Britain, had become members of an
                    International Union for the Protection of Industrial Property by virtue of
                    articles of Union agreed upon in Paris on March 20, 1883, Great Britain having
                    acceded to this Union in 1884. The conference was also attended by
                    representatives of the German Empire, Luxembourg, Mexico, Paraguay, Roumania,
                    and Uruguay, and the United States of America, all of whom, like myself,
                    appeared solely for the purpose of taking note of the proceedings of the
                    conference and reporting to their respective Governments.</p>
                <p>The articles of the Union adopted on the 20th of March, 1883, at Paris, are set
                    forth in the pamphlet which I herewith transmit. The objects of the Union are
                    stated in the second of these articles, which provides that “the subjects or
                    citizens of each of the contracting states shall enjoy, in all the other states
                    of the Union, in respect of patents, industrial models or designs, trade-marks,
                    and commercial names, all the advantages which are actually conferred, or may be
                    conferred hereafter, upon the subjects or citizens of any of these states by
                    their respective laws, so that they shall have the same protection and the same
                    legal recourse against all infringements of their rights (enjoyed by the
                    subjects or citizens of any state) on condition of their compliance with the
                    formalities imposed upon such subjects or citizens by the internal legislation
                    of each state”; and in the third article, which provides that the same rights
                    and privileges shall be extended to the subjects or citizens of states not
                    members of the Union who have a domicile or industrial or commercial
                    establishment on the territory of ne of the states of the Union.</p>
                <p>Among the other noteworthy articles is Article 5, providing “that as a condition
                    precedent to the enjoyment of patent rights in any of the states of the Union,
                    the owner of the patent must avail himself of it (<hi rend="italic"
                        >l’exploiter</hi>) in conformity with the laws of the country into which the
                    patented articles are introduced.”</p>
                <p>And also Article 9, relating to the seizure of manufactured articles or articles
                    of commerce bearing fraudulent trade-marks.</p>
                <p>The present conference at Borne was held in compliance with Article 14, which
                    provided that the convention formed at Paris in 1883 should be subject to
                    periodical revision, and that the next conference should be held in Borne.</p>
                <p>Before the meeting of the conference a number of amendments to the original
                    articles were submitted to the members by the representative of Belgium, France,
                    Great Britain, and Switzerland.</p>
                <pb facs="0632" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                <p>Several of these amendments were adopted by the conference, but only two of them
                    appear to me to be worthy of note.</p>
                <p>The first of them (an amendment to Article 5) is in these words: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Each country is to determine for itself the sense of the term
                            “exploiter.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>During the course of the discussion it became evident that the object of the
                    French representatives, by whom the amendment was proposed, was to limit the
                    enjoyment of patent and trade-mark rights to those objects or articles actually
                    manufactured in France, in conformity with the construction of the legal phrase
                    “exploiter,” as repeatedly given by the French tribunals. It is not without
                    significance that England voted with France for the adoption of this
                    amendment.</p>
                <p>Another noteworthy amendment is that to Article 10, relating to the seizure of
                    articles bearing fraudulent trade-marks, and especially the latter part of this
                    amendment, which is to the effect that trade-marks shall not be considered
                    fraudulent when it appears that they have been adopted with the consent of the
                    manufacturer whoso name is affixed to the manufactured product.</p>
                <p>It is hardly necessary to say that both of these amendments were adopted in the
                    interest of “home industries,” so called, and, as was justly observed by Mr.
                    Monzilli, who strongly protested against these amendments in the name of the
                    Italian Government, were in derogation of the objects for which the Union was
                    formed.</p>
                <p>I do not deem it necessary or proper to make any further comments upon the
                    proceedings of the conference, but content myself with the observation that any
                    State or country not yet a member of the Union has the right to join it by
                    simply notifying the Swiss Government, and through it the Governments of all the
                    other states, of its intention to do so, and that any of the States forming part
                    of the Union may withdraw from it upon a year’s notice.</p>
                <p>I announced to the conference at its first regular session, on April 30, 1886,
                    that I attended it solely <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi>, and that I
                    signed the minutes upon the express declaration of the President that this
                    signature imported nothing more than a certificate of their accuracy.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. B. STALLO.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 69.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Convention for the protection of industrial property, made
                            at Paris, March</hi> 20, 1883, <hi rend="italic">between Belgium,
                            Brazil, Spain, France, Guatemala, Italy, The Netherlands, Portugal,
                            Salvador, Servia, and Switzerland.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>His Majesty the Xing of the Belgians; His Majesty the Emperor of Brazil; His
                        Majesty the King of Spain; The President of the French Republic; The
                        President of the Republic of Guatemala; His Majesty the King of Italy; His
                        Majesty the King of the Netherlands; His Majesty the King of Portugal and
                        the Algarves; the President of the Republic of Salvador; His Majesty the
                        King of Servia; the Federal Council of the Swiss Confedaration;</p>
                    <p>Equally animated by the desire to assure, by common accord, a complete and
                        efficacious protection to the industry and commerce of the subjects of their
                        respective states, and to contribute to the safeguard of the rights of
                        inventors, and to the loyalty of commercial transactions, have resolved to
                        conclude a convention to, that effect, and have named as their
                        Plenipotentiaries the following: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of the Belgians:</hi> Baron
                                Beyens, Grand Officer of His Royal Order of Leopold, Grand Officer
                                of the Legion of Honor, etc., His Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                                Plenipotentiary at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the Emperior of Brazil:</hi> M. Jules
                                Constant, Count de Villeneuve, Member of the Council of His Majesty,
                                His Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipo <pb facs="0633" n="549"
                                    xml:id="pg_549"/> tentiary near His Majesty the King of the
                                Belgians; Commander of the Order of Christ, Officer of His Order of
                                the Rose, Knight of the’Legion of Honor, etc.;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of Spain;</hi> His Excellency
                                the Duke of Fernan-Nuñez, de Montellano, and del Arco, Count de
                                Cervellon, Marquis of Almonacir, Grandee of Spain of the 1st Class,
                                Knight of the distinguished Order of the Golden Fleece, Grand Cross
                                of the Order of Charles III, Knight of Calatrava, Grand Cross of the
                                Legion of Honor, etc. Senator of the Kingdom, His Ambassador
                                Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">The President of the French Republic:</hi> Mr.
                                Paul Challemel-Lacour, Senator, Minister of Foreign Affairs; Mr.
                                Hérison, Deputy, Minister of Commerce; Mr. Charles Jagerschmidt,
                                Minister Plenipotentiary of 1st Class, Officer of the National Order
                                of the Legion of Honor.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">The President of the Republic of Guatemala:</hi>
                                Mr. Crisanto Medina, Officer of the Legion of Honor, etc., His Envoy
                                Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of Italy:</hi> Mr. Constantin
                                Ressman, Commander of His Orders of St. Maurice and St. Lazarus, and
                                of the Crown of Italy, Commander of the Legion of Honor, etc.,
                                Counsellor of the Embassy of Italy at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of the Netherlands:</hi>
                                Baron de Zuylen de Nyevelt, Commander of His Order of the Lion of
                                Netherlands, Grand Cross of His Grand Ducal Order of the Oaken Crown
                                and the Golden Lion of Nassau, Grand Officer of the Legion of Honor,
                                etc., His Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at
                                Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of Portugal and the
                                    Algarves:</hi> M. José da Silva Mendes Leal, Counsellor of
                                State, Peer of the Kingdom, Minister and Honorary Secretary of
                                State, Grand Cross of the Order of St. James, Knight of the Order of
                                the Tower and of the Sword of Portugal, Grand Officer of the Legion
                                of Honor, etc., His Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary
                                at Paris; Mr. Fern and de Azevedo, Officer of the Legion of Honor,
                                etc., First Secretary of the Legation of Portugal at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">The President of the Republic of Salvador:</hi>
                                Mr. Torres-Caïcedo, Corresponding Member of the Institute of France,
                                Grand Officer of the Legion of Honor, etc., His Envoy Extraordinary
                                and Minister Plenipotentiary at Paris;</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">His Majesty the King of Servia:</hi> Mr. Sima M.
                                Marinovitch, Chargé d’Affaires ad interim of Servia, Knight of the
                                Royal Order of Takovo, etc.;</item>
                            <item>And the <hi rend="italic">Federal Council of the Swiss
                                    Confederation:</hi> Mr. Charles Edward Lardy, its Envoy
                                Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary at Paris; Mr. J. Weibel,
                                Engineer at Geneva, President of the Swiss Section of the permanent
                                Commission for the protection of Industrial Property.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their respective full powers,
                        found to be in good and due form, have agreed upon the following
                        Articles:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                    <p>The Governments of Belgium, of Brazil, of Spain, of France, of Guatemala, of
                        Italy, of the Netherlands, of Portugal, of Salvador, of Servia and of
                        Switzerland, have constituted themselves into a state of Union for the
                        protection of Industrial Property.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                    <p>The subjects or citizens of each of the contracting States shall enjoy, in
                        all the other States of the Union, so far as concerns patents for
                        inventions, trade or commercial marks, and the commercial name, the
                        advantages that the respective laws thereof at present accord, or shall
                        afterwards accord to subjects or citizens. In consequence they shall have
                        the same protection as these latter, and the same legal recourse against all
                        infringements of their rights, under reserve of complying with the
                        formalities and conditions imposed upon subjects or citizens by the domestic
                        legislation of each State.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                    <p>Are assimilated to the subjects or citizens of the contracting States, the
                        subjects or citizens of States, not forming part of the Union, who are
                        domiciled or have industrial or commercial establishments upon the territory
                        of one of the States of the Union.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                    <p>Any one who shall have regularly deposited an application for a patent of
                        invention, of an industrial model, or design, of a trade or commercial mark,
                        in one of the contracting States, shall enjoy for the purpose of making the
                        deposit in the other States, and under reserve of the rights of third
                        parties, a right of priority during the periods hereinafter determined.</p>
                    <pb facs="0634" n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/>
                    <p>In consequence, the deposit subsequently made in one of the other States of
                        the Union, before the expiration of these periods cannot be invalidated by
                        acts performed in the interval, especially by another deposit, by the
                        publication of the invention or its working by a third party, by the sale of
                        copies of the design or model, by the employment of the mark.</p>
                    <p>The periods of priority above mentioned shall be six months for patents of
                        invention and three months for designs or industrial models, as well as for
                        trade or commercial marks. They shall be augmented by one month for
                        countries beyond the seas.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                    <p>The introduction by the patentee into countries where the patent has been
                        granted, of articles manufactured in any other of the States of the Union,
                        shall not entail forfeiture.</p>
                    <p>The patentee, however, shall be subject to the obligation of working his
                        patent conformably to the laws of the country into which he has introduced
                        the patented articles.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                    <p>Every trade or commercial mark regularly deposited in the country of origin
                        shall be admitted to deposit and so protected in all the other countries of
                        the Union.</p>
                    <p>Shall be considered as country of origin, the country where the depositor has
                        his principal establishment.</p>
                    <p>If this principal establishment is not situated in one of the countries of
                        the Union, shall be considered as country of origin that to winch the
                        depositor belongs.</p>
                    <p>The deposit may be refused, if the object, for which it is asked, is
                        considered country to morals and to public order.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                    <p>The nature of the production upon which the trade or commercial mark is to be
                        affixed cannot in any case, be an obstacle to the deposit of the mark.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                    <p>The commercial name shall be protected in all the countries of the Union
                        without obligation of deposit, whether it forms part or not, of a trade or
                        commercial mark.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                    <p>Every production bearing, unlawfully, a trade or commercial mark, or a
                        commercial name, may be seized upon importation into those of the States of
                        the Union in which such mark or such commercial name has a right to legal
                        protection.</p>
                    <p>The seizure shall take place either at the instance of the public prosecutor
                        or of the interested party, conformably to the domestic legislation of each
                        State.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                    <p>The provisions of the preceding article shall be applicable to every
                        production bearing falsely as indication of origin, the name of a stated
                        locality when this indication shall be joined to a fictitious commercial
                        name or a name borrowed with fraudulent intention.</p>
                    <p>Is reputed interested party every manufacturer or trader engaged in the
                        manufacture or sale of this production, when established in the locality
                        falsely indicated as the place of export.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 11.</p>
                    <p>The High Contracting parties engage between themselves to accord a temporary
                        protection to patentable inventions, to industrial designs or models as well
                        as to trade or commercial marks for the productions, which may figure at
                        official or officially recognized International Exhibitions.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 12.</p>
                    <p>Each one of the High Contracting parties engages to establish a special
                        service of Industrial Property and a Central Depôt, for giving information
                        to the public, concerning patents of invention, industrial designs or models
                        and trade or commercial marks.</p>
                    <pb facs="0635" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 13.</p>
                    <p>An International Office shall be organized under the title of “International
                        Bureau of the Union for the Protection of Industrial Property.”</p>
                    <p>This Bureau, the cost of which shall be supported by the Governments of all
                        the contracting States, shall be placed under the high authority of the
                        Superior Administration of the Swiss Confederation, and shall work under its
                        supervision. Its powers shall be determined by common accord between the
                        States of the Union.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 14.</p>
                    <p>The present convention shall be submitted to periodical revisions for the
                        purpose of introducing improvements calculated to perfect the system of the
                        Union.</p>
                    <p>With this object, Conferences shall take place successively in one of the
                        contracting States between the delegates of said States.</p>
                    <p>The next meeting shall take place in 1885 at Rome.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 15.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that the High Contracting parties respectively reserve the
                        right to make, separately, between themselves, special arrangements for the
                        protection of industrial property so far as these arrangements shall not
                        interfere with the provisions of the present convention.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 16.</p>
                    <p>The States that have not taken part in the present convention shall be
                        admitted to adhere the same upon their application.</p>
                    <p>This adhesion shall be notified through the diplomatic channel to the
                        Government of the Swiss Confederation and by the latter to all the
                        others.</p>
                    <p>It shall convey, of full right, accession to all the clauses and admission to
                        all the advantages stipulated by the present convention.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 17.</p>
                    <p>The execution of the reciprocal engagements contained in the present
                        convention is subordinated in so far as needful, to the accomplishment of
                        the formalities and rules established by the Constitutional laws of such of
                        the High Contracting parties as are bound to ask the application thereof,
                        which they agree to do within the shortest delay possible.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 18.</p>
                    <p>The present convention shall be put into execution within a month after
                        exchange of ratifications, and shall remain in force during a period of time
                        not determined, until the expiration of one year from the day upon which the
                        denunciation shall be made.</p>
                    <p>This denunciation shall be addressed to the Government empowered to receive
                        adhesions. It shall only produce its effect as regards the State making it,
                        the convention remaining executory for the other contracting parties.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 19.</p>
                    <p>The present Convention shall be ratified and the ratifications shall be
                        exchanged at Paris, within the period of one year at the latest.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed it and
                        affixed to it their seals.</p>
                    <p>Done at Paris the 20th of March, 1883.</p>
                    <table cols="3" rows="15">
                        <row>
                            <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>.]</cell>
                            <cell>(Signed)</cell>
                            <cell>BEYENS.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>VILLENEUVE</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>DUC DE FERNAN-NUÑEZ.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>P. CHALLEMEL-LACOUR.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>CH. HÉRISSON.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>CH. JAGERSCHMIDT.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>CRISANTO MEDINA.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>RESSMAN.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>BARON DE ZUYLEN DE NYEVELT.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>JOSÉ DA SILVA MENDES LEAL.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>F. D’AZEVEDO.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>J. M. TORRES-CAÏCEDO.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>SIMA M. MARINOVITCH.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>LARDY.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>“</cell>
                            <cell>J. WEIBEL.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <pb facs="0636" n="552" xml:id="pg_552"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">final protocol.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On proceeding to the signature of the convention concluded this day between
                        the Governments of Belgium, Brazil, Spain, France, Guatemala, Italy, the
                        Netherlands, Portugal, Salvador, Servia, and Switzerland, for the protection
                        of industrial property, the undersigned plenipotentiaries have agreed on the
                        following:</p>
                    <p>(1) The words <hi rend="italic">industrial property</hi> are to be understood
                        in their widest acceptation, in the sense that they apply not only to the
                        productions of industry properly so called, but equally to the productions
                        of agriculture (wines, grains, fruits, cattle, &amp;c.) and to mineral
                        productions used in commerce (mineral waters, &amp;c.).</p>
                    <p>(2) Under the name <hi rend="italic">patents of invention</hi> are included
                        the various classes of industrial patents granted by the laws of the
                        contracting states, such as patents of importation, patents of improvement,
                        &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>(3) It is understood that the final provision of Article 2 of the convention
                        shall in no respect infringe upon the laws of each of the contracting
                        states, so far as concerns the procedure before the courts and the
                        competence of the said courts.</p>
                    <p>(4) Paragraph 1 of Article 6 is to be understood in the sense that no trade
                        or commercial mark shall be excluded from protection, in one of the states
                        of the Union, by the mere fact that it may not satisfy, in respect to the
                        signs composing it, the conditions of the laws of this state, provided that
                        it does satisfy, in this regard, the laws of the country of origin, and that
                        it has been in this latter country, duly deposited. Saving this exception
                        which concerns only the form of the mark, and under reservation of the
                        provisions of the other articles of the convention, the domestic legislation
                        of each of the states shall receive its due application.</p>
                    <p>In order to avoid all misinterpretation, it is understood that the use of
                        public armorial bearings and decorations may be considered contrary to
                        public order in the sense of the final paragraph of Article 6.</p>
                    <p>(5) The organization of a special service of industrial property mentioned in
                        Article 12 shall include, as far as is possible, the publication in each
                        state of an official periodical.</p>
                    <p>(6) The common expenses of the International Bureau, created by Article 13,
                        shall in no case exceed yearly a sum-total representing a mean of 2,000
                        francs for each contracting state.</p>
                    <p>In order to determine the contributory share of each of the states in this
                        sum-total of expenses, the contracting states, and those who may hereafter
                        adhere to the Union, shall be divided into six classes, each contributing in
                        proportion of a certain number of units, namely: First class, 25 units;
                        second class, 20 units; third class, 15 units; fourth class, 10 units; fifth
                        class, 5 units; sixth class, 3 units.</p>
                    <p>These coefficients shall be multiplied by the number of the states of each
                        class, and the sum of the products thus obtained shall furnish the number of
                        units by which the total expense is to be divided. The quotient will give
                        the amount of the unit of expense.</p>
                    <p>The contracting states are classified as follows in respect to the division
                        of the expenses: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">First class.</hi>—France, Italy.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second class.</hi>—Spain.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Third class.</hi>—Belgium, Brazil, Portugal,
                                Switzerland.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fourth class.</hi>—Netherlands.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fifth class.</hi>—Servia.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sixth class.</hi>—Guatemala, Salvador.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Swiss Government shall supervise the expenditure of the International
                        Bureau, make the necessary advances, and state the annual account, which
                        shall be communicated to all the other Governments.</p>
                    <p>The International Bureau shall collect information of every kind relating to
                        the protection of industrial property, and shall compile from it general
                        statistics, which shall be transmitted to all the Governments. It shall
                        occupy itself with examinations of general utility which may be of interest
                        to the Union, and shall publish, with the assistance of the documents put at
                        its disposal by the various Governments, a periodical in the French language
                        on questions which concern the object of the Union.</p>
                    <p>The numbers of this periodical and all the documents published by the
                        International Bureau shall be partitioned among the Governments of the
                        states of the Union in the proportion of the number of contributory units
                        above mentioned.</p>
                    <p>The copies and supplementary documents which may be requested either by the
                        said Governments, or by corporations or private persons, shall be paid for
                        separately.</p>
                    <p>The International Bureau must always hold itself at the disposal of the
                        members of the Union, in order to furnish them, on questions relating to the
                        international service of industrial property, with such special information
                        as they may need.</p>
                    <p>The Government of the country where the next conference is to be held shall
                        prepare, with the assistance of the International Bureau, the work of the
                        said conference.</p>
                    <p>The director of the International Bureau shall be present at the sessions of
                        the conferences, and shall take part in the discussions without voting.</p>
                    <pb facs="0637" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                    <p>He shall make an annual report on its management, which shall ho communicated
                        to all the members of the Union.</p>
                    <p>The official language of the International Bureau shall be the French
                        language.</p>
                    <p>(7) The present final protocol, which shall be ratified at the same time as
                        the convention concluded this day, shall be considered as forming an
                        integral part of that convention, and shall have the same force, value, and
                        duration.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the undersigned plenipotentiaries have drawn up the present
                        protocol.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>BEYENS.</item>
                                <item>VILLENEUVE.</item>
                                <item>Due <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> FERNAN-NUÑEZ.</item>
                                <item>P. CHALLEMEL-LACOUR.</item>
                                <item>CH. HÉRISSON.</item>
                                <item>CH. JAGERSCHMIDT.</item>
                                <item>CRISANTO MEDINA.</item>
                                <item>RESSMAN.</item>
                                <item>BARON <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> ZUYLEN <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >de</hi> NYEVELT.</item>
                                <item>JOSÉ <hi rend="smallcaps">da</hi> SILVA MENDES LEAL.</item>
                                <item>F. D’AZEVEDO.</item>
                                <item>J. M. TORRES-CAÏCEDO.</item>
                                <item>SIMA M. MARINOVITCH.</item>
                                <item>J. LARDY.</item>
                                <item>J. WEIBEL.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">protocol.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The International Conference of the Union for the Protection of Industrial
                        Property, convened at Rome April 29, 1886, having concluded its labors,
                        submits to the Governments of the states, represented the articles
                        additional to the convention concluded at Paris March 20, 1883, and the
                        regulation for the execution of the said convention of the following
                        tenor:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Additional articles to the convention concluded at Paris
                            March</hi> 20, 1883.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(To Article 5.)</p>
                    <p>Each country is authorized to define the sense in which the term “<hi
                            rend="italic">exploiter”</hi> is to be interpreted within its
                        jurisdiction.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(To Article 10.)</p>
                    <p>1. Every production bearing illegally a false mark of origin may be seized on
                        importation in all the contracting states.</p>
                    <p>The seizure may likewise be made in the country in which the false mark has
                        been affixed as well as in the country in to which the production has been
                        imported.</p>
                    <p>The seizure is to be made on the complaint of the public prosecutor, or of an
                        interested party, person, or corporation, in conformity with the domestic
                        legislation of each state.</p>
                    <p>The courts of each country are empowered to decide what are the cases which,
                        by virtue of their generic character, are not included in the present
                        provisions.</p>
                    <p>The authorities are not required to make the seizure <hi rend="italic">in
                            transitu.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>2. No fraudulent intention exists in the case provided for by paragraph 1 of
                        Article 10 of the convention, when it is proved that it is by the consent of
                        the manufacturer, whose name is stamped on the productions imported, that
                        the said stamp has been affixed.</p>
                    <p>The present additional articles shall be ratified, and the ratifications
                        shall be exchanged at Rome within the period of one year, or sooner if
                        possible.</p>
                    <p>They shall take effect one month after the exchange of the ratification, and
                        shall have the same duration as the convention.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Regulation for the execution of the convention concluded
                            at Paris March</hi> 20, 1883.</p>
                    <p rend="center">I.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Explanatory provisions.)</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>In order to obtain the same treatment as subjects or citizens of the
                            contracting states, in accordance with the terms of Article III of the
                            convention, subjects or citizens of states not included within the
                            Union, who, without being domiciled in its <pb facs="0638" n="554"
                                xml:id="pg_554"/> own industrial or commercial establishments in the
                            territory of one of the states of the Union, must be exclusive
                            proprietors of the said establishments, be represented there by a
                            general agent, and prove, in case of denial, that they carry on there
                            actually and continuously their industry or commerce.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>As regards the states of the Union lying in Europe, the extra European
                            countries which do not border on the Mediterranean Sea are considered
                            countries beyond the seas (Article 4).</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">II.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Accession of additional states to the International
                        Union.)</p>
                    <p>When another state adheres to the convention, the date of the note by which
                        its accession is announced to the Swiss federal council shall be considered
                        the date of entrance of the said state into the Union, unless its Government
                        shall assign a subsequent date of accession.</p>
                    <p rend="center">III.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Jurisdiction of the Union.)</p>
                    <p>Are considered as belonging to the International Union for the Protection of
                        Industrial Property.</p>
                    <p>(The various Governments shall furnish to the International Bureau the names
                        of those of their territories, colonies, or possessions included in the
                        Union by the mere fact of the accession of the parent state.)</p>
                    <p rend="center">IV.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Certifications of legal protection.)</p>
                    <p>(1) In order to insure the protection of the trade or commercial marks of
                        their subjects or citizens in all the territory of the Union the Governments
                        of the country of origin shall grant them a certificate declaring that the
                        said marks have been deposited in the country of origin.</p>
                    <p>(2) No authentication of the above-mentioned certificate is necessary.</p>
                    <p>(3) Every petition for the extension of a patent to other countries of the
                        Union must be accompanied by a copy, in manuscript or print, of the
                        description of the invention, and of the drawings (if any exist) which may
                        have been deposited in the country in which the first petition was made.</p>
                    <p>This copy must be authenticated by the special service of industrial property
                        of this latter country.</p>
                    <p rend="center">V.</p>
                    <p>(Information to be furnished by the International Bureau).</p>
                    <p>(1) The International Bureau is required to furnish gratuitously the various
                        Governments with such information as may be asked of it by them concerning
                        patents and trade or commercial marks.</p>
                    <p>(2) The same information shall be furnished private persons domiciled within
                        the territory of the Union at the rate of 1 franc for the information
                        requested.</p>
                    <p>This fee may be paid in postage-stamps of the various contracting states on
                        the following basis for those states which do not have the franc as their
                        monetary unit, namely: Brazil, 1 franc=400 reis; Dominican Republic, 1
                        franc=20 centavos de peso; Spain, 1 franc=l peseta; Great Britain, 1
                        franc=10 pence; Guatemala, 1 franc=20 centavos de peso; Norway, 1 franc=80
                        oere; Netherlands, 1 franc=50 cents; Portugal, 1 franc=200 reis; Sweden, 1
                        franc=80 oere; Salvador, 1 franc=20 centavos de peso.</p>
                    <p>(3) The Governments of the various states above mentioned shall receive at
                        the rate stated in the preceding paragraph, the stamps of their country
                        which the International Bureau may have taken as fees for information.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VI.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Temporary protection for inventions, drawings, models, and
                        marks exhibited at international expositions.)</p>
                    <p>(1) The temporary protection provided for by Article 11 of the convention
                        consists of a term of priority of at least six months counting from the date
                        of admission of the production to the exposition, during which the
                        exhibition, publication, or employment, without the authority of the person
                        entitled, of the invention, drawing, model, or mark thus protected, shall
                        not prevent the person who has obtained the said temporary protection from
                        making with due effect, within the said period, his demand for a patent or
                        the deposit necessary to insure definitive protection throughout all the
                        territory of the Union.</p>
                    <p>Each state is empowered to extend the said period.</p>
                    <p>(2) The above-mentioned temporary protection shall have no effect, unless,
                        during its continuance, a petition for a patent is filed or a deposit made
                        for the purpose of <pb facs="0639" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> insuring to the
                        object td Which it applies definitive protection in one of the contracting
                        states.</p>
                    <p>(3) The terms of priority mentioned in Article 4 of the convention are
                        distinct from those treated of in the first paragraph of the present
                        article.</p>
                    <p>(4) The patentable inventions to which provisional protection has been
                        accorded by virtue of the present article shall be made known to the
                        International Bureau, and shall form the subject of publication in the
                        official organ of the said Bureau.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VII.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Statistics.)</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Before the end of the first half of each year the Governments of the
                            Union shall transmit to the International Bureau the following
                            statistics concerning the preceding year, namely: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Patents of invention.</hi>—(1) Number of
                                    patents demanded; (2) number of patents granted; (3) amount of
                                    fees collected under this head.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Drawings or industrial models.</hi>—(1) Number
                                    of drawings or models deposited; (2) number of drawings or
                                    models registered; (3) amount of fees collected under this
                                    head.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Trade or commercial marks.</hi>—(1) Number of
                                    marks deposited; (2) number of marks registered; (3) amount of
                                    fees collected under this head.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The International Bureau shall be empowered to adopt the
                            classification it may consider best as regards the statistics of patents
                            of invention, trade or commercial marks, and drawings or industrial
                            models.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">VIII.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Enforcement of the present regulations.)</p>
                    <p>The present regulation shall be put in force as soon as possible.</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Desire expressed by the conference.)</p>
                    <p>The conference, moreover, expressed the following desire with reference to
                        Article 2 of the convention of 20th March, 1883.</p>
                    <p>The states included in the Union which do not possess laws in regard to all
                        the classes of industrial property are to perfect, as soon as possible,
                        their codes of legislation on this point.</p>
                    <p>The same is to be done by the states which may hereafter enter the Union.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the undersigned delegates of their respective Governments at
                        the International Conference of Rome have drawn up the present report and
                        have affixed their signatures thereto.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1886-05-11">May 11,
                            1886</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>For Germany: <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr</hi>. STÜVE.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Belgium: <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr</hi>. JEUX</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Brazil: <list>
                                        <item>LOPEZ NETTO.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Spain: <list>
                                        <item>COUNT <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> RASCON.</item>
                                        <item>LUIS M. <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> LARRA.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bmé</hi> SPOTTORNO.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For the United States of America: <list>
                                        <item>J. B. STALLO.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For France: <list>
                                        <item>COUNT <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> TOUR.</item>
                                        <item>C. NICOLAS.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Great Britain: <list>
                                        <item>H. READER LACKE.</item>
                                        <item>J. H. G. BERGNE.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Italy: <list>
                                        <item>UBALDINO PERUZZI.</item>
                                        <item>ANTOINE MONZILLI.</item>
                                        <item>ORESTE LATTES.</item>
                                        <item>REMY TRINCHERI.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Luxemberg: <list>
                                        <item>SPEDENER.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Mexico: <list>
                                        <item>SANCHEZ ASCONA.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Norway: <list>
                                        <item>COUNT HAMILTON.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Paraguay: <list>
                                        <item>E. RENAZZI.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For the Netherlands: <list>
                                        <item>WESTENBERG.</item>
                                        <item>GEORGE SNYDER, <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>. W.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Portugal: <list>
                                        <item>E. <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> SOUZA PREGO.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Roumania: <list>
                                        <item>A. C. PLAGINO.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Servia: <list>
                                        <item>M. CHRISTITCH.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Sweden: <list>
                                        <item>COUNT HAMILTON.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Switzerland: <list>
                                        <item>BAVIER.</item>
                                        <item>DR. WILLI.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Tunis: <list>
                                        <item>MICHEL PELLETIER.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>For Uruguay: <list>
                                        <item>P. ANTONINI DIEZ.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
