<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-08-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="338" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                    <head>No. 334.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Porter</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Jackson</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-08-23"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 23,
                            1886</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 240.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 291, of the 10th instant,
                        communicating Mr. Mariscal’s reply of that date to the inquiries you were
                        instructed to make touching the murder of Francisco Resures (heretofore
                        erroneously called Arresures) has been received.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bayard’s instruction No. 233, of the 14th instant, has anticipated a
                        reply to Mr. Mariscal’s three points that Resures was not a citizen of the
                        United States; that he was surrendered upon a regular demand of extradition,
                        and that he was attempting escape from his guard when shot.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Mariscal, quoting from the telegram addressed to him by the authorities
                        of the State of Coahuila, says: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>The chief of the Coahuila Guards of Public Safety officially
                                requested him (Resures) from the American authorities (<hi rend="italic">lo pidió oficialmente á autoridades
                                    Americanas</hi>).</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>No information has yet reached this Department to show that Mondragon, or any
                        other officer of the State of Coahuila, made the formal application for
                        extradition contemplated by the treaty, with the indispensable evidence to
                        “establish,” as Article I provides, the “feet of the commission of the
                        crime” charged against the alleged fugitive. If Señor Mariscal can obtain
                        satisfactory proof of the official demand which he asserts was made, it is
                        in the interest of justice, both municipal and international, that it should
                        be produced. The execution of a compact between nations for the mutual
                        extradition of fugitives from justice is too important a matter to be left
                        in doubt or fall into discredit through proceedings in contravention of its
                        letter and spirit. It is alleged by the Texan extraditing magistrate that
                        the application was orally made without production of evidence to sustain
                        the charge. If this be so, a clear case of kidnapping is made out against
                        all concerned in the forcible deportation of Resures, and the treaty of
                        extradition cannot be invoked to cloak the act whereby the unfortunate man
                        was delivered into the hands of Mondragon.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JAS. D. PORTER,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting
                            Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>