<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 348.Mr. Bell
                            to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="protocol" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663" lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="352" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                <head>No. 348.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bell</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">The
                                Hague</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 1, 1885</date>. (Received
                            December 14.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 76.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to ray No. 60 of the 26th October
                        last, I now have the honor to inform you that the minister of foreign
                        affairs, Mr. Van Karnebeek, has replied to the observation comprised in the
                        report of the commission of the Second Chamber respecting the budget of the
                        department of foreign affairs for the year 1886.</p>
                <p>The minister, after referring to the protocol of the conference upon the Suez
                        Canal, published by the English Government, admits that the conference did
                        not reach the desired result.</p>
                <p>It is claimed, however, that there is ground for the belief that a practical
                        solution of the pending questions will be arrived at through diplomatic
                        negotiations.</p>
                <pb facs="0818" n="734" xml:id="pg_734"/>
                <p>The minister says that the new treaty of commerce and navigation with Spain
                        has encountered great difficulties owing to the conclusion of pretended
                        treaties of reciprocity which the United States have concluded with some
                        American states and with Spain, by virtue of which treaties there is
                        assured, on one side and on the other, certain favors on the condition that
                        they will not be granted to third powers in virtue of the “most favored
                        nation clause.”</p>
                <p>The treaty with Spain, the minister further says, concerns especially the
                        islands of Cuba and Porto Rico, and from the intimation from the Government
                        of Spain this treaty will make it difficult to admit the Netherland vessels
                        and merchandise in those two colonies upon the footing of the most favored
                        nation; that is, upon the footing of the United States.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, the Netherlands Government does not consent to the new
                        theory adopted by the United States and Spain as to the signification of the
                        “most-favored nation clause,” a clause upon which are based all the treaties
                        of commerce concluded by the Netherlands.</p>
                <p>Consequently the Netherlands Government have decided to suspend temporarily
                        the negotiation with Spain, and especially has this course been determined
                        upon as it has been shown that the treaty of reciprocity between the United
                        States and Spain has produced a very unfavorable impression among the other
                        powers, and as it has also encountered very serious opposition in the United
                        States, it is not improbable that in the end it will not be ratified.</p>
                <p>The question of the importation of Netherlands sugar into the United States
                        has by right attached itself to the question of the treaty of reciprocity,
                        and must depend, therefore, for its fate upon this treaty. * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ISAAC BELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
