<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 368.Mr. Buck
                            to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131" lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recDxa7szVhIjbJXw" type="compound-subject" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general">Where we were</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-12-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="372" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                <head>No. 368.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lima,
                                Peru</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 4, 1885</date>. (Received
                            December 26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 57.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my No. 56, of last Saturday, 28th ultimo,
                        you were advised that the situation here seemed very serious.</p>
                <p>On Saturday evening, after dark, the several diplomatic representatives here
                        received a manifesto from Colonel Solar, General Cáceres’ general minister,
                        dated at Vitarte (about 4 miles from Lima), November 27, of which I inclose
                        a copy and translation.</p>
                <p>At once, by concert with the French minister, Count Piná, the English,
                        Italian, and Spanish ministers and myself met at his legation to consider
                        the situation. We had not time, owiug to the urgency of the case, to get
                        together all the members of the diplomatic corps in a formal meeting.</p>
                <p>We agreed that the manifesto from General Cáceres, in view of his near
                        position, should be accepted, not as grounds for making any representations
                        to the Government, but as a notice from an invading force of imminent
                        danger, in conjunction with the visible preparations being made by General
                        Iglesias in the very heart of the city for a combat, justifying the
                        liveliest feelings for the safety of our several colonies.</p>
                <p>We therefore unanimously resolved to address to the minister of foreign
                        affairs the note of which I inclose a copy and translation.</p>
                <p>This action was taken between 10 and 11 o’clock at night, after due
                        interchange of views; and the note was placed in the hands of the chancellor
                        of the French legation to be delivered at once.</p>
                <p>He, however, did not succeed in finding the minister of foreign affairs, and
                        was informed at the palace that orders had been issued to receive no
                        dispatches whatever during the night, and the note was not delivered until 8
                        o’clock Sunday morning.</p>
                <p>The reply of the minister of foreign affairs was not made until the afternoon
                        of same day, and was evasive, simply acknowledging receipt of the note and
                        stating that the subject-matter would have to be considered by the cabinet
                        and, as soon as that had been done, he would advise us. Meanwhile, at ten
                        o’clock on Sunday morning, the whole diplomatic corps convened at the house
                        of the dean (the Chilian minister), and it was resolved unanimously, in view
                        of the imminent peril, in the interest of humanity, to tender the good
                        offices of the corps to ascertain if they could be of any service in
                        avoiding a combat in the streets of the capital.</p>
                <p>A memorandum was formulated, of which I inclose copy and translation, and the
                        Italian, Argentine, and Bolivian ministers were appointed as commissioners
                        to communicate the same. This they did, and the result is announced in a
                        note of which only the inclosed translation has been furnished me.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>As will be observed from the note of General Cáceres, he had established
                        himself within about 4 miles of Lima, at Vitarte, on November 27.</p>
                <p>Combats followed on Saturday and Sunday; and on Monday, November 30, there
                        was active fighting all day, between the advancing skirmish <pb facs="0847" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/> line of General Cáceres and outposts and
                        skirmishers of the Government.</p>
                <p>The two lines occupied positions with their right resting on the river Rimac,
                        south of the stream, and extending across a level stretch to the foot of the
                        hills and thence along the crest of parallel ranges in the segment of a
                        circle to the southeast, some three miles. The sharpest fighting occurred
                        when the Cáeristas captured the peak, some 1,400 feet high, called San
                        Bartolomé, when two pieces of Government artillery were taken between 9 and
                        10 a.m., and at the Government’s right, where its forces had artillery
                        stationed, which was captured by the Cáceristas late in the evening.</p>
                <p>Through the whole two days of fighting without the city, the Cáceristas made
                        constant advances, taking position after position, and finally driving the
                        Government forces into the city late Monday evening.</p>
                <p>Early in the day the noted negro cavalry leader, Colonel Pachas (chief of the
                        squadron of Polica), was killed, and his death seems to have had a
                        demoralizing effect on the Government troops.</p>
                <p>The general line of fighting along the hills could be seen from the
                        house-tops of Lima, and was watched by thousands of people in towers and on
                        the roofs.</p>
                <p>The Government occupied the mountain of San Cristobal, more than 1,100 feet
                        high, just to the north of the city, on Monday evening. It is almost an
                        inaccessible peak and overlooks the city and country for miles, until in one
                        direction the view is cut off by the higher peaks of the Cordilleras, and in
                        the other it is limited by the far-away horizon line of the Pacific. This
                        was the extreme limit of their occupation to the north.</p>
                <p>In connection with the city, north of the Rimac the Iglesias forces occupied
                        the old bridge Desamparados, stretching their line behind its stone
                        battlements and thence, under cover of the buildings to the American
                        railroad station of Desamparados, just opposite the northeast corner of the
                        palace fronting on the main plaza, the palace itself having been converted
                        into a formidable citadel. They also occupied the house-tops to the north of
                        the palace, the cathedral towers to the north of the plaza, and commanded
                        with artillery and gatling guns the streets running east and west along the
                        front and rear of the palace and the next parallel street south of the
                        plaza, and also the two streets running north and south along the other two
                        sides of the palace and the plaza. They also occupied the artillery barracks
                        in the southeast part of the city, and the principal church towers; notably
                        those of San Francisco, San Pedro, San Domingo, Mercedes, and San Augustin,
                        all of which are formidable fortresses in themselves; and from their
                        superior elevations overlook the palace and the plaza within easy
                        rifle-shot.</p>
                <p>The Cáceristas entered the city during Monday night to the east, through the
                        old “Portada de Maravillas” into the “Calle de Anchas,” and through the
                        “Portada de Barbines” into the “Calle de Juuin.” Along these streets they
                        could approach by oblique lines under cover to the center of the city, and
                        from them distribute themselves into position without being raked by fire
                        from the palace and plaza, except as they crossed the streets commanded at
                        right angles from the strongholds of the Government. Thus they occupied with
                        their right the “Puente de Viterbo”—more commonly known as “Battas Bridge”—a
                        splendid iron structure, and approached the church of San Francisco, which
                        they stormed and captured, thus gaining a splendid position within one
                        square of the palace, with an open plaza in front, and threw up a barricade
                        of large stone slabs, taken from the sidewalks, across the entrance to San
                            <pb facs="0848" n="764" xml:id="pg_764"/> Francisco plaza, looking
                        towards the palace. With that small plaza thus covered, they could handle
                        their men and artillery from the church and behind their protections. Thence
                        they extended their lines along the Calle de Abancay, throwing up barricades
                        at the intersection of the three streets Junin, Muallaga, aud Ucayali, which
                        were commanded by the fire of the Government troops from the palace, plaza,
                        and at the corner of the streets Ucayali and Carabaya.</p>
                <p>The legation where we were stationed during the fight is in the street
                        Carabaya, between the plaza and the corner of Ucayali. Behind each of their
                        barricades the Cáceristas had cannon, and for the first time in the history
                        of street fighting in this country artillery was used by the attacking
                        force, and the explosion of shells added to the general horrors of a battle
                        in the heart of a great city.</p>
                <p>Early in the day, Tuesday, the Cáceristas captured the towers of San Pedro,
                        and from that point on their left to San Francisco on their right, and from
                        the towers of those two churches, there was the heaviest firing during the
                        day.</p>
                <p>An attack was made on the artillery barracks at one time, but it was soon
                        abandoned, and at another a force of Cáceristas climbed the peak of San
                        Cristobal and drove down the steep sides toward the city the Government
                        troops who were from their lofty cover keeping up a harassing fire on that
                        part of their force stationed at “Battas Bridge,” but after a most wonderful
                        feat in scaling steeps so precipitous that a man can with difficulty climb
                        them unincumbered, they found the place was not worth sparing men to occupy,
                        and they gave it up in order to concentrate their force along the main line
                        of fight, as indicated, in the designated streets.</p>
                <p>The firing began before 6 o’clock a.m. and lasted until 6.30 p.m., when the
                        Government asked for a truce. Thus was ended one of the most brilliant and
                        remarkable military achievements of which I know any record; indeed, so
                        remarkable that only success, which overrides all rules, could make its
                        conception appear other than the promptings of despair or the rashness of
                        reckless adventure.</p>
                <p>The obscureness of the field of action and the smallness of the forces
                        involved alone can keep it from centering upon General Cáceres the eyes of
                        the world.</p>
                <p>After the battle of Jauja, and what must have been a serious loss, he marched
                        his army of over 2,000 men about 200 miles from Huaripampa, in the Tambo, to
                        Lima, across the rugged Cordilleras, almost without roads, over the ice and
                        snows of the mightiest mountains, stopping only two days <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> for rest, encountering almost intolerable hardships, yet
                        sometimes making 30 miles a day with his soldiers on foot leading their
                        horses, which were loaded with arms, provisions, and cannon, the latter
                        being taken to pieces and strapped on pack-saddles. Of this distance only
                        about 85 miles was aided by railroad.</p>
                <p>At Chicla, the terminus of the Oroya road, he captured one locomotive and ten
                        cars, and, although the Government had destroyed bridges on the line, * * *
                        he had these put in place and with such scant railroad facilities had
                        transferred his army down the gorges of the Rimac to Lima in twelve days
                        after the battle of Jauja, and in four days more he had driven the
                        Government forces, larger than his own, superbly equipped and armed, from
                        every position on the outskirts of the capital, corraled them in the walls
                        of their inner defenses within the heart of the city, and forced the
                        Government, with all its superior resources, and behind its central
                        fortress, to sue for a peace which conceded virtually just the terms he had
                        always consistently demanded.</p>
                <pb facs="0849" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/>
                <p>The Government claimed before the combat to have 3,700 men, but I doubt if
                        they really had more than 2,500. Perhaps Cáceres did not have under his
                        command more, than 2,300 men when he entered the city.</p>
                <p>The wounded in the hospitals are stated as follows: Government forces, 14
                        officers and 79 soldiers; Cáceristas lost 20 officers and 112 soldiers;
                        citizens, 30. The number of dead is not given.</p>
                <p>Tuesday evening, after thirteen hours of fighting, the minister of foreign
                        affairs, communicated with the Brazilian minister, whose residence was most
                        accessible, the firing being too heavy to reach other legations, and stated
                        that the Government desired to suggest terms for peace, and wished to accept
                        the good offices of the diplomatic corps.</p>
                <p>These terms were stated verbally, but were as recorded in the act, written in
                        General Cáceres’s headquarters, of which I inclose copy and translation.</p>
                <p>Of course great haste was needed, as General Cáceres had announced when the
                        truce was asked, unless an arrangement was effected by noon of Tuesday he
                        would reopen fire, so a pen copy had to be obtained afterwards.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile General Cáceres, upon the truce being asked, had communicated to
                        the French minister by note his desire that an arrangement should terminate
                        bloodshed, and indicated his inclination to abide by the same terms which he
                        had repeatedly suggested before.</p>
                <p>The diplomatic corps convened at the Chilian minister’s at 10 o’clock
                        Wednesday morning, and concluded to proceed in a body with the terms
                        suggested by General Iglesias to General Cáceres’ headquarters, and on
                        behalf of the Government lay them before him.</p>
                <p>Upon presenting the matter General Cáceres stated the terms were virtually
                        those he had repeatedly himself proposed and were in accordance with his
                        views, so they were, for purpose of definite record, put into writing, and
                        signed in duplicate by General Cáceres, and each member of the diplomatic
                        body. One copy was left with General Cáceres; the dean took the other, and
                        the whole corps proceeded at once to the palace, presented the document to
                        President Iglesias and his foreign minister, and it was signed by him, and a
                        copy made and left with the minister of foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>I have only to add that these preliminaries being accomplished, General
                        Iglesias named as commissioners on the part of the Government Monseñor
                        Tovar, Dr. José Nicolas Rebaza, and Dr. Manuel A. Barinaga, and General
                        Cárceres on his part Messrs. Cárlos M. Elias, José Gregorio Garcia, and Dr.
                        José Eusebio Sanchez.</p>
                <p>These six commissioners met in the Spanish legation, and formulated the
                        conditions for the formation of a new provisional Government, and named the
                        several members of the new cabinet as follows: President of the council and
                        minister of foreign affairs, Dr. Antonio Arenas; minister of Government,
                        police and public works, Dr José Eusebio Sanchez; minister of justice,
                        public instruction, and beneficence, Monseñor Dr. Manuel Tovar; minister of
                        war and navy, Colonel Manuel Velarde; and minister of the treasury and
                        commerce, Pedro Correa y Santiago</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES W. BUCK</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0850" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">manifesto.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vitarte</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 27,
                                    1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Most Excellent Sir</hi>: The gravity and most high
                            importance of the events about to occur in search of a solution which
                            may put an end to the fatal struggle in which the forces of General
                            Iglesias are engaged against the opinion of the country, oblige me to
                            address myself in the name of his Excellency, the provisional President
                            of the Republic, to your excellency as a worthy member of the diplomatic
                            body resident at Lima.</p>
                    <p>General Iglesias, against all precepts of right and human laws, is
                            engaged in maintaining his personal authority at the cost of Peruvian
                            blood already profusely shed, and intent upon the pursuit of this end
                            has converted the capitol of the Republic and the Government palace into
                            a military fortification, compelling even neutrals to sacrifice
                            themselves at the altar of his foolish ambition.</p>
                    <p>Hard as may be so cruelly bloody a sacrifice, unavoidable duties prevent
                            my Government from refusing to take sides in this, it being the only
                            bulwark behind which General Iglesias sustains his unpatriotic
                            Government. Only he and those who being able and perhaps in duty bound
                            to do so, fail to prevent the sad consequences, will be responsible for
                            the same.</p>
                    <p>I am, then, under the necessity of informing your excellency of the
                            determination of my Government to seek General Iglesias within the
                            formidable intrenchments of the palace as the only means existing of
                            accomplishing the task imposed upon it by the nation. Not the least
                            responsibility will rest upon us on account of the blood that will be
                            shed there, nor the horrors accompanying such an event.</p>
                    <p>It is hereby certified, notwithstanding, that General Cáceres is still
                            disposed to desist from the employment of force and to resign the
                            authority with which he is invested immediately General Iglesias does
                            the same, thus leaving the people free to exercise their will without
                            violence or coercion.</p>
                    <p>It is my honorable duty to inform your excellency of the intentions and
                            sentiments that animate my Government in the present question. Hoping
                            your excellency will take such steps as may appear just and proper in
                            view of the common calamity with which all are threatened,</p>
                    <p>I subscribe myself, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>PEDRO A. DEL SOLAR,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">General Minister
                                    of General Cáceres.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Note of portion of the <gloss type="from">diplomatic
                                    corps</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Urrutia</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 28,
                                    1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr.<hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: Consequent upon accounts received
                            from good sources and in view of the visible military preparations which
                            have been going on for some days at the Government palace, the
                            undersigned unfortunately feel themselves justified in fearing an
                            imminent attack upon the city of Lima.</p>
                    <p>Being intrusted with the protection of the interests of their respective
                            countrymen, the painful impression made upon them by the prospect of a
                            battle threatened to be I fought in the streets of the city and the
                            well-founded alarm caused to them, in consequence, cannot escape the
                            foresight of the Government. It being, under the circumstances,
                            incumbent upon them in so far as they may be able to do so before it be
                            too late to take efficient measures for the protection of their charges,
                            the undersigned earnestly beg your excellency to be so good as to inform
                            them without delay whether the Government has really determined to offer
                            battle in the capital itself to the forces that actually threaten
                            her.</p>
                    <p>Awaiting a prompt and explicit reply and formulating from this moment the
                            most ample reservations as to the responsibility regarding the damages
                            that may accrue to their respective colonies, the undersigned avail
                            themselves of this opportunity to renew to your excellency the
                            assurances of their high consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>BUCK.</item>
                                <item>PINÁ.</item>
                                <item>EMILIO DE OJEDA.</item>
                                <item>E. DE GUBERNATIS.</item>
                                <item>C. MANSFIELD.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0851" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Note from <gloss type="from">diplomatic
                                    corps</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Urrutia</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>In Lima, on the 29th day of November, 1885, met together the Envoys
                            Extraordinary and Ministers Plenipotentiary, Mr. Jovino Novoa for the
                            Republic of Chili, Mr. Jacinto Villegas for the Argentine, Mr. Charles
                            W. Buck for the United States of America, Mr. José Manuel Braun for
                            Bolivia, and the Condé a de Piná for the Republic of France; the
                            resident ministers, Mr. Hermann A. Schumacher for the Empire of Germany,
                            Mr. Emilio de Ojeda for His Christian Majesty, Mr. Enrique de Gubernatis
                            for His Majesty the King of Italy, Mr. Charles Mansfield for Her
                            Britannic Majesty, and the Chargé d’Affaires, Mr. Enrique de B.
                            Cavalcanti de Lacerda, for the Empire of Brazil, and Mr. Shu Cheon Pon
                            for the Empire of China, and agreed upon the following:</p>
                    <p>“The diplomatic corps, in view of the present state of affairs and of the
                            possibility of a combat taking place in the city of Lima, think it a
                            duty to humanity to offer to the Government of Peru their good offices
                            in so far as these can serve to avoid the calamities and disasters of
                            this combat.”</p>
                    <p>It was also agreed to name Messrs. Villegas, Braun, and Gubernatis to
                            present a copy of this act to the minister of foreign affairs of
                            Peru.</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>Jovino Novoa, Jacinto Villegas, Charles W. Buck,
                                José Manuel Braun, Piná, Emilio de Ojeda, C. Mansfield, E. de
                                Gubernatis, Hermann A. Shumacher, Shu Cheon Pon, H. B. Cavalcanti de
                                Lacerda</signed>.</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>True copy of the original act.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item>JOVINO NOVOA,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Minister
                                                Plenipotentiary of Chili.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>MANUEL J. NOVOA,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of
                                                the Legation of Chili.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Note from the <gloss type="from">Italian minister to
                                    Peru</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">diplomatic
                                corps</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi>
                                29</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Colleagues</hi>: After considerable search
                            we found Urrutia, who had been informed of our mission by Novoa, and was
                            prepared with his answer. His answer was as follows: “The Government
                            appreciate the generous sentiments which determined the action of the
                            diplomatic body, and are extremely grateful for your good offices.”</p>
                    <p>At one moment he appeared to say, “Are grateful for and accept;” but
                            having desired him to repeat his sentence, he confined himself to
                            expressing their gratitude. All attempts to extract another word proved
                            fruitless, more especially as Mr. Villegas put a stop to this interview
                            by remarking that our object reduced itself to receiving his answer and
                            transmitting the same. Mr. Urrutia nevertheless closed by adding that in
                            the event of a conflict taking place the responsibility rested with
                            Cáceres, not with Iglesias. Upon this he asked me whether, in
                            consequence of the declaration made by the diplomatic body, it remained
                            his duty to answer yesterday’s note. I replied that I was not intrusted
                            with the mission of expressing the opinion of my colleagues on that
                            score, but that I could give him my personal views. “In my opinion,” I
                            continued, “all depends on the reply which the Government may return to
                            our offer of good offices. Should our good offices be accepted and
                            enable us to avert the disasters we anticipate, then our note has no
                            farther reason to exist; but if, on the other band, the Government,
                            while expressing their acknowledgments, reject our offer, I should
                            desire to learn at an early date the intentions of the Government, in
                            order to take measures in consequence.” Mr. Urrutia took note of my
                            views, and reserved to himself to ask you for your opinion.</p>
                    <p>I am,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GUBERNATIS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Buck</hi>, Count <hi rend="smallcaps">Piná</hi>, and Colonel <hi rend="smallcaps">Mansfield.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">agreement.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Chili in Peru</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Lima</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The diplomatic corps being assembled in the building of Congress in the
                            presence of General Cáceres with the object of seeking a means of
                            solution of the existing internal contest, the minister of Chili, Mr.
                            Novoa, for himself and his honorable colleagues, <pb facs="0852" n="768" xml:id="pg_768"/> set forth that the diplomatic corps, in their
                            desire to contribute to the pacification of Peru, had tendered their
                            good offices to General Iglesias, and that he, accepting them, had
                            stated that he was animated by the same sentiments and was ready to
                            enter into arrangements with General Cáceres on the basis of both
                            resigning the power exercised by them, and determining by means of
                            special commissioners a third authority (<hi rend="italic">entidad</hi>), that should convoke an election of President,
                            vice-president, senators, and deputies of the nation.</p>
                    <p>To this statement of Mr. Novoa, ratified by each and all of his honorable
                            colleagues, General Cáceres answered, showing that the basis just now
                            proposed by General Iglesias preserved perfect conformity with that
                            which had before and on repeated occasions been presented by himself, in
                            his desire to insure internal peace,: Mr. Novoa then stated that once in
                            accord, as they were, <hi rend="italic">on the essence of the
                                question</hi>, it was in his opinion indispensable that General
                            Iglesias be immediately informed of this result, in order that he might
                            name special commissioners.</p>
                    <p>After this conclusion Mr. Ojeda pointed out the advisability of making
                            record of the present conference in order to give relief and
                            tranquillity to the alarmed inhabitants of the city.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Novoa added that General Iglesias had expressed his desire that after
                            settlement had been made there should reign in all political parties
                            complete oblivion of past differences, leaving neither conqueros nor
                            conquered, hut Peruvians bound by the indissoluble tie of love of
                            country.</p>
                    <p>General Cáceres having manifested that he was moved by the same
                            sentiments, the act was pronounced terminated.</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>Cáceres, Jovino Novoa, Jacinto Villegas, Carlos W.
                                Buck, José M. Piná, Braun, Hermann A. Schumaker, Emilio de Ojeda, E.
                                de Gubernatis, C. E. Mansfield, A. B. Cavalcanti de Lacerda, Shu
                                Cheon Pon, Pedro A. del Solar, A. Morales Toledo</signed>.</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>A correct copy of the original.</p>
                        <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>JOVINO NOVOA,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Minister Plenipotentiary of
                                    Chili.</hi>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]
                                    <signed>MAN’L J. NOVOA,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the
                                        Legation of Chili.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No.
                            57.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">agreement of the peace commissioners.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Met together in the house of the Resident Minister of Spain, Messrs. Dr.
                            José Eusebio Sanchez, Carlos M. Elias, José Gregorio Garcia, Monseñor
                            Dr. Manuel Tovar, Dr. Manuel A, Barinaga, and Dr. José Nicolas Rébaza,
                            being the commissioners named, respectively, by General Andres A.
                            Cáceres and General Miguel Iglesias, with the object of arriving at an
                            agreement to put an end to the actual state of affairs and to secure
                            internal peace, they proceeded to exchange the corresponding full
                            powers, which were found ample and in order.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Ermel J. Rospigliosi having been named secretary of the
                            commissioners, Dr. Tovar proposed that the act drawn up at the meeting
                            of the honorable diplomatic corps on this day should be read; and
                            starting with the agreement arrived at and accepted in the said meeting,
                            and agreed to by General Iglesias and by General Cáceres, and in view of
                            the full powers given to the commissioners, the following was agreed to: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. To put in force at once
                                    the constitution of 1860.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. That the resignation to
                                    which the said act refers, made by Generals Cáceres and
                                    Iglesias, will be made evident in an explicit manner by the
                                    respective decrees which will be issued to the effect.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. That the authority which
                                    shall assume the government to which said act refers will be a
                                    council of ministers named by the commission, giving to each
                                    member a portfolio, and naming the one to which the presidency
                                    of the council corresponds.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 4. The council of ministers
                                    will call popular elections for President of the Republic,
                                    vice-president, senators and deputies within the third day of
                                    their installation, which elections will be made according to
                                    the constitution of 1860.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 5. Both the forces of General
                                    Cáceres, as well as those of General Iglesias, will, remain
                                    under the command of their respective commanders-in-chief, who
                                    will hold them at the disposal of the council of ministers, they
                                    taking up their quarters in the following places: The forces of
                                    General Cáceres will encamp in the zone of the plantation of
                                    Santa Clara; those of General Iglesias in the zone of Chorillos;
                                    those that should arrive from the north of the Republic in
                                    Callao; and those under the command of Colonel Gregorio Relaize
                                    in the zone which the new Government shall appoint. <pb facs="0853" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> The evacuation of this
                                    capital should commence to-morrow, Thursday, 3d instant, at 1
                                    p.m., the city remaining in charge of the police forces, under
                                    the command of the actual prefect of the department.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 6. The council of ministers
                                    having charge of the executive power remains formed as
                                    follows:</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>President of the council and minister of foreign affairs, Dr. Antonio
                            Arenas; minister of government Police and public works, Dr. José Eusebio
                            Sanchez; minister of justice, public instruction, and beneficence,
                            Monseñor Dr. Manuel Tovar; minister of war and marine, Colonel Manuel
                            Velarde; Minister of finance and commerce, M. Pedro Correa y Santiago,
                            having agreed that the portfolios are obligatory.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Sanchez and Monseñor Dr. Tovar strongly opposed being named for
                            government and justice, respectively, but they were overruled by the
                            other members of the commission. It was lastly agreed to make three
                            copies of the present memorandum of agreement, with the end that one
                            should be given to General Cáceres, another to General Iglesias, and the
                            third to the president of the council of ministers, and they signed José
                            Eusebio Sanchez, Manuel Tovar, José Nicolas Rébaza, Carlos M. Elias,
                            Manuel A. Barinaga, José Gregorio Garcia.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">note communicating result to president
                                of council and ministers.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Ermel J. Rospigliosi, secretary, having communicated the preceding
                            agreement the following note was sent:</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2, 1885.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. President of the Council of
                                Ministers and Minister of Foreign Affairs,<lb/>Dr. Antonio
                                Arenas:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">President</hi>: The undersigned, named in
                            commission by Generals Miguel Iglesias and Andres A. Cáceres, with the
                            object of arriving at an arrangement which would put an end to the
                            actual state of affairs and secure internal peace, have proceeded to
                            elect a council of ministers to exercise the supreme command in the
                            terms which appear in the act which we have the honor to forward to your
                            honor, who has been named to preside over the same.</p>
                    <p>Which we have the honor to communicate to your honor for the after
                            effects.</p>
                    <p>God guard your honor.</p>
                    <closer>Signed: <signed>Manuel Tovar, José Eusebio Sanchez, José Nicholas
                                Rebaza, Carlo M. Elias Manuel A. Barinaga, J. Gregorio
                                Garcia</signed>.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
