<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 37.Mr. Pringle to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="38"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d38">
                <head>No. 37.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pringle</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation in Central America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 6, 1885</date>. (Received January 4,
                        1886.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 454.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to report that the elections passed off
                    quietly, and General Manuel Barillas has been elected constitutional President,
                    and Vicente Castaneda Vice-President of the Republic of Guatemala.</p>
                <p>The official announcement does not take place until Congress meets next
                    August.</p>
                <p>I also inclose a decree of General Menendez, President of Salvador, relative to
                    the dissolution of the Assembly, and also the decree in which he declares the
                    country under martial law.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>D. LYNCH PRINGLE,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 454.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Decree of General Menendez, President of Salvador.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Francisco Menendez, general of division and provisional President of the
                        Republic of Salvador, considering: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>That ever since the first session of the constitutional Congress
                                there has been noticed a spirit of division amongst the members
                                composing it, a departing each day further and further from that
                                patriotism with which it should be inspired, so as to establish the
                                institutions which must consolidate that real liberty, peace, and
                                public order to which all Salvadorians legitimately aspire.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>That notwithstanding the notorious designs of leaving an
                                inadequate constitution, and not only a palpable but aggressive
                                resistance to the reforms indicated by the executive power, the
                                latter has reached the extreme of its prudence and tolerating
                                spirit, abstaining from having recourse to those violent measures
                                demanded by the public sentiment, from the desire to evade for the
                                Republic a scandal and the evils attendant upon an abnormal
                                situation of the country, as well as from the hope that it would
                                have succeeded in causing the opposition circle to relax in their
                                mournful endeavors to provoke difficulties and disturbances.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>That the moderation of this conduct is almost interpreted as
                                weakness on the part of the Government, and that, far from diverging
                                from their intentions, which are hostile towards it and which are
                                tending to denaturalize the glorious programme of the revolution, it
                                appears better to have given them more strength of mind and greater
                                audacity to bring into play their machinations, an overestimating
                                and abasing of the unlimited liberty and the guarantees which this
                                same Government has vouchsafed them.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>That from this cause the dissenters, against the actual dictates
                                and against a good and liberal constitution, have engendered in the
                                Republic an anomalous, unsustainable situation, the uneasiness
                                sequential to a public lack of confidence and the intranquillity
                                among the citizens, which is the unavoidable result of the endless
                                expectation of a revolutionized state of politics.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>That of late the spirit of discord has manifested itself by events
                                which have taken place in the excited session of to-day, in which a
                                considerable number of members of the assembly, not wishing to
                                become the plaything nor the ridicule of the opposition party,
                                violently abandoned their seats, with protests that they would never
                                return to occupy them, this action causing Congress to be
                                spontaneously dissolved.</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>That the first and principal duty of the Government is to maintain
                                sacredly the principles of authority and of public order, and it
                                would not be compatible to the fulfillment of this duty were it to
                                forsake the great social and political interests which are intrusted
                                to it by going so far as to countenance with criminal indifference,
                                thereby compromising its own dignity, the disorder caused in the
                                very body of Congress itself, which threatens the public peace and
                                the free and republican practices of the people of Salvador, whose
                                guardian and defender it is.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">decree.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">First and only article</hi>. It is hereby declared that
                        in consequence of the spontaneous dissolution of the constitutive Congress
                        without fulfilling its high mission, <pb facs="0135" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/>
                        notwithstanding that it had been organized for two months, the dictatorship
                        in which the provisory government is invested by the will of the people
                        shall remain in vigor until such time as the passions shall have become
                        calmed and the Republic shall be at peace, when appropriate measures will be
                        taken.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Given in <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>,
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-26">26th of November,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>FRANCISCO MENENDEZ.</item>
                                <item>CRUZ ULLOA.</item>
                                <item>RAFAEL MEZA.</item>
                                <item>ESTANISLAO PEREZ.</item>
                                <item>Z. GALDIAMEZ.</item>
                                <item>HIGINIO VALDIVIESO.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 454—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">decree of general menendez, president of salvador.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Francisco Menendez, general of division and provisional President of the
                        Republic of Salvador, considering— <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>That the scandalous dissolution of the constitutional Assembly
                                might give rise to new disorders, which the Government must avoid in
                                time and repress in a prompt and energetic manner;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>That however painful, and even repugnant, it maybe to appeal to
                                measures of a grave character, it is necessary to do so in extreme
                                cases, in order to preserve public order and when the tenacity and
                                obstinacy of those who try to destroy the principles of authority,
                                without whose shelter liberty is an empty word;</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>By virtue of all the authority with which I am invested,</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">decree.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> I declares to be re-established in
                            full force the state of siege under which the Republic has been
                            maintained already a situation which the same national Congress
                            dissolved to-day of its own accord brought about and determined to
                            maintain.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. This decree shall take effect from
                            this date.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Given in <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-27">27th of November,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>FRANCISCO MENENDEZ.</item>
                                <item>CRUZ ULLOA.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
