<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 380.Mr. Bayard to Mr. Curry.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1886-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1886-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recHhqoArQDK36RN7" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="hiv-aids"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007002196"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">ELISA</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="384"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                <head>No. 380.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Curry</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-02-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 40.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of the representations which this
                    Government has to make on the practices of the Cuban customs authorities,
                    adverse to the established agreement between the two Governments, I inclose a
                    report of the consul-general at Havana.</p>
                <p>This report shows, first, that Spanish vessels arriving at Cuban ports from
                    Spain, not exceeding twenty days out, and sailing from Cuba with cargo to the
                    ports of the United States are exempt in clearing from all tonnage duties in
                    Cuban ports, while American steamers sailing from Cuba with cargo to the ports
                    of the United States are required to pay, on clearing from Cuban ports, 62½
                    cents per ton on their cargoes if mail steamers, or $1.35 if not such, and,
                    second, that Spanish sailing vessels arriving from Spain at Cuban ports and
                    clearing from Cuba with cargo to the ports of the United States, pay in Cuban
                    ports 25 cents per ton on their cargoes destined for the United States, while
                    American sailing vessels clearing from Cuba with cargo to the ports of the
                    United States pay in Cuban ports $1.35 per ton on their cargoes. Thus it is
                    manifest that in the language of section 4231, Revised Statutes, “discriminating
                    or countervailing duties on tonnage are levied upon vessels of the United
                    States,” in Cuban ports.</p>
                <p>The fact that exemption of Spanish steamers and the lower duties fixed for
                    Spanish sailing vessels are made dependent upon certain conditions as to the
                    domestic trade between the Spanish Peninsula and the Spanish Antilles does not
                    affect the question as contemplated by the act of Congress cited.</p>
                <p>It is understood that the Spanish Government has not, up to the present time,
                    admitted the Antillean possessions to the benefits of the coastwise trade; but
                    even if that should be done, it could not alter the situation as to the trade
                    between the Antilles and the United States.</p>
                <p>The object of Congress was to secure for American vessels engaged in the trade
                    between this country and the Spanish possessions the same treatment in Spanish
                    ports as was accorded in those ports to Spanish <pb facs="0866" n="782"
                        xml:id="pg_782"/> vessels engaged in the same trade. Section 4228, Revised
                    Statutes, says that— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Upon satisfactory proof being given to the President by the Government of
                            any foreign nation that no discriminating duties of tonnage or imposts
                            are imposed or levied in the ports of such nation upon vessels wholly
                            belonging to citizens of the United States, or upon the produce,
                            manufactures, or merchandise imported in the same from the United States
                            or from any foreign country, the President may issue his proclamation
                            declaring that the foreign discriminating duties of tonnage and impost
                            within the United States are suspended and discontinued, &amp;c.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It will be seen from the correspondence had with the Spanish legation in this
                    city in 1877 (<ref target="frus1878#pg_804">F. R., 1878, pp. 804</ref>–<ref
                        target="frus1878#pg_808">8</ref>), that Sr. Mantilla appealed to the
                    provisions of this law in order to secure the exemption of Spanish vessels from
                    the discriminating tonnage duties levied on Spanish vessels in the United
                    States, and declared that Spain “has not levied on American tonnage any greater
                    or other charges than she levied on Spanish tonnage,” and he supported this
                    declaration by a certificate from the auditor of customs at Havana. Upon this
                    declaration being confirmed by the ministry at Madrid, the Secretary of the
                    Treasury directed the suspension of the discriminating: tonnage tax of which
                    complaint had been made. The late tonnage regulations at Havana, based upon the
                    Spanish law of July 20, 1882, referred to by Consul-General Williams, are in
                    plain opposition to the declaration of Sr. Mantilla and the Madrid ministry, and
                    they constitute such a discrimination against American vessels as calls for the
                    enforcement of the corresponding measures indicated by Congress, unless at once
                    revoked.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 40.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Porter</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-01-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 28, 1886</date>. (Received February
                            4.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with your instruction No. 124,
                        dated the 4th of November last, encharging me to investigate carefully the
                        discrimination in tonnage dues practiced against American vessels in the
                        ports of Cuba, as alleged by Messrs. James E. Ward &amp; Co., of New York,
                        in their letter addressed to the Department under date of 21st October last,
                        I have now the honor to present you the following report, together with its
                        accompanying correspondence, and upon which it is mainly based.</p>
                    <p>As the Department will perceive, both the report and correspondence will show
                        that the allegation of Messrs James E. Ward &amp; Co. is, because of the
                        existence of the facts they mention, correctly founded.</p>
                    <p>The inclosed copies of this correspondence are numbered respectively from 1
                        to 13.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 1 is a copy of my letter of December 9 last, addressed
                            to Messrs. Hidalgo &amp; Co., agents in this city for both the Alexandre
                            and Ward lines of American steamers, the first plying between New York
                            and Vera Cruz, and touching each way at this port for passengers and
                            freight, and the second running exclusively between New York and Cuban
                            ports.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 2 is copy of their answer thereto, dated the 11th of
                            December.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 3 is a copy of the letter addressed by me to Messrs.
                            Lawton Brothers, agents of the Morgan line of American steamers, plying
                            between New Orleans, via the West Florida ports, and Havana; and who
                            are, as well, agents of the steamers of the Plant Steamship Line,
                            running between Tampa Bay and Havana via Key West.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 4 is copy of their answer thereto, dated 10th
                            December.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 5 is copy of my letter, dated December 12, 1885,
                            addressed to Mr. George Marsden, an American ship-broker, who has been
                            for many years established in this port, having, therefore, a wide
                            experience in the matter under investigation.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 6 is copy of his answer, under date of December
                            17.</item>
                        <item>Inclosure No. 7 is copy of the letter dated the 19th of December last,
                            which I directed to Mr. Louis Placé, a ship-broker of this city,
                            intimately acquainted with the facts mentioned in the letter of Messrs.
                            James E. Ward &amp; Co., as will be seen in his answer thereto, marked
                            No. 8.</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0867" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/>
                    <p>Also, and as confirmatory of the allegation presented by Messrs. James E.
                        Ward &amp; Co., will be found, under inclosure No. 10, the copy of the
                        letter dated the 12th instant, received from Don Joaquin Fernandez, the
                        collector of customs of the port of Havana, in answer to my letter of
                        inquiry addressed to him the day previous, copy of which is accompanied
                        herewith as inclosure No. 9.</p>
                    <p>You will be pleased to observe that, according to this letter of the
                        collector, the several discriminations herein set forth are practiced
                        pursuant to the law of commercial relations, dated at San Ildefonso the 20th
                        of July, 1882, to be found on page 113 of the accompanying printed copy of
                        the Cuban customs tariff.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">First discrimination.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It will be seen from the accompanying letters of Mr. George Marsden and Mr.
                        Louis Placé that Spanish steamers arriving from Spain in periodical trips of
                        less than twenty days, and almost any steamer nowadays can do it within the
                        limit, and leave again loaded with cargo for the United States, pay neither
                        inward nor outward tonnage.</p>
                    <p>But, in contrast to this, all regular trading American steamers running
                        between the United States and the island pay 62½ cents per ton on both
                        inward and outward cargo.</p>
                    <p>To illustrate the effects of this law against American steamers I will cite,
                        singly, the following actual occurrence as a sample of its workings:</p>
                    <p>The Spanish steamer Herman Cortes, which arrived here in the early part of
                        last August in less than twenty days from Barcelona, Spain, as will be seen
                        by this correspondence, brought of inward cargo equal in tons to 1,460, and
                        after discharging loaded up with an outward cargo of sugar for New York,
                        equal in tons to 2,100, making, jointly, of inward and outward cargo a bulk
                        equal in tons to 3,560, but upon which the Herman Cortes <hi rend="italic"
                            >paid no tonnage dues whatever.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Now, in opposition to this, under the same customs law, had a regular trading
                        American steamer brought to and carried away from Cuba the same amount of
                        cargo, then her tonnage dues at the rate of 62£ cents per ton would have
                        amounted in Spanish gold to $2,225.</p>
                    <p>The extent of favor enjoyed in this case by Spanish steamers over their
                        American rivals trading between the United States and Cuba is so great that
                        it is evident, under the operation of the handicapping discrimination, it
                        will be quite impossible for American steamers to compete with Spanish
                        steamers in carrying sugars to the United States from this island the day
                        the supply of the latter’s tonnage becomes sufficient to meet the freight
                        demand of this market, and as Spanish steamers are all built in the
                        ship-yards of Great Britain there is no doubt, to this end, as to the
                        prolificness of the source from which they are to draw.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Second discrimination.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In comparing the tonnage dues paid here by Spanish and American sailing
                        vessels bringing inward and loading outward cargoes the following contrast
                        offers itself: An American sailing vessel arriving here from the United
                        States or any other part of the world with inward cargo, and clearing with
                        outward cargo, pays $1.35 Spanish gold per ton of net register. But, as the
                        opposite of this, a Spanish vessel coming from Spain with inward cargo pays
                        37½ cents per ton, and on her departure for the United States with outward
                        cargo pays 25 cents per ton of net register. Now, assuming in this case a
                        sailing vessel of the medium size of 500 tons net register as a standard of
                        calculation and comparison, we arrive at the following results: <table
                            cols="2" rows="3">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Tonnage dues on an American sailing vessel of 500 tons, net
                                    register, inward</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap" role="num">$675 00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Tonnage dues on a Spanish sailing vessel of 500 tons, net
                                    register, at 37½ cents inward, $187.50, and 25 cents outwards.
                                    $125</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap #bottom #border-bottom" role="num">312
                                    50</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">362 50</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>This difference, as the Department will observe, in view of the low rates of
                        ocean freights that have ruled for years past, is quite an advantage in
                        favor of the Spanish vessel over the American vessel, the amount, indeed,
                        being more than sufficient to pay all the ordinary stevedores’ bills of the
                        Spanish vessel.”</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Third discrimination.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In this case, the contrast or difference lies between Spanish and American
                        vessels arriving in ballast and departing with outward cargo for the United
                        States. Accordingly, American sailing vessels which arrive here in ballast
                        and leave with <hi rend="italic">outward</hi>
                        <pb facs="0868" n="784" xml:id="pg_784"/> cargo for a home port pay $1 per
                        ton net register for tonnage dues, while the Spanish vessel arriving from
                        Spain and loading for the United States in same manner only pays 25 cents
                        per ton of net register. Assuming, again, for the purpose of illustration, a
                        sailing vessel of 500 tons net register as standard, we will reach the
                        following result, viz: <table cols="2" rows="4">
                            <row>
                                <cell>500 tons net American register, at $1 per ton on outward
                                    cargo</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$500</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>500 tons net Spanish register, at 25 cents per ton on
                                    outward</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom" role="num">125</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">375</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Difference in favor of the Spanish vessel over the American
                                    vessel carrying cargo to the United States</cell>
                                <cell role="num">375</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fourth discrimination.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In regard to the other discriminations to which Messrs. James E. Ward &amp;
                        Co. call the attention of the Department—such as the charging of higher
                        import duties on products taken out of bond in the United States, not the
                        growth or production of the United States, when loaded there by American
                        vessels, over what is paid upon the same goods when loaded in ports of the
                        United States and brought here by Spanish vessels, namely: Coffee in bond,
                        Newfoundland codfish, East India rice, South American jerked beef, or
                        Chinese groceries—I beg respectfully to annex, in answer, and to incorporate
                        as a part of this report, copies of my official communication of November
                        17, 1884, and January 9, 1885, addressed to the governor-general of the
                        island, as also copy of his excellency’s reply through the political
                        secretary, Mr. Cassá, dated the 12th of January, 1885, and of which the
                        Department was duly informed, in reference to the 286 bags of La Guayra
                        coffee, shipped in New York on board the American steamer Saratoga, and upon
                        which, regardless of the convention of February 13, 1884, between the United
                        States and Spain, import duties were collected on this coffee under the
                        fourth column of the customs tariff of Cuba, instead of under the third
                        column, as the convention provides.</p>
                    <p>The excess of duties collected in this case over what the same coffee would
                        have paid if it had been brought from New York in a Spanish vessel, was, as
                        I then stated, $67.56 Spanish bank bills, and $608.11 Spanish gold.</p>
                    <p>I understand that this discrimination still exists, and as a matter of
                        course, as long as it lasts, American ships, in this respect, cannot compete
                        either, even in our own ports, with Spanish shipping.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Messrs.
                                <gloss type="to">Hidalgo &amp; Co.</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States of
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 9, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sirs</hi>: For the information of this office, I
                        have to ask of you the kindness to tell me what are the rates of tonnage
                        dues paid by you in this port on the Alexandre and Ward lines of steamers,
                        for which you are the agents—namely: <list>
                            <item>First. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly,
                                exceed in tons their register tonnage; and</item>
                            <item>Second. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly, are
                                less than their register tonnage.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Hidalgo &amp; Co.</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                                >Williams</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 11, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In answer to your letter of the 9th
                        instant we beg first to refer you as regards the payment of tonnage dues on
                        steamers of the Alexandre and Ward lines, to paragraphs 112 and 113 of the
                        latest edition of the customs tariff, where you will find a <pb facs="0869"
                            n="785" xml:id="pg_785"/> copy of a royal decree dated Madrid, 25th
                        August, 1867, which deals with the matter. Secondly we have to answer your
                        questions as follows: <list>
                            <item>To the first. We pay duties according to net registered tonnage,
                                less 6 tons.</item>
                            <item>To the second. Sixty-two and one-half cents per 1,000 kilograms of
                                cargo imported and exported.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>We have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>HIDALGO &amp; CO.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Messrs.
                                <gloss type="to">Lawton Brothers</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 9, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sirs</hi>: For the information of this office, I
                        have to ask of you the kindness to tell me what are the rates of tonnage
                        dues paid by you in this port on the steamers for which you are the agents,
                        namely: <list>
                            <item>First. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly,
                                exceed in tons their registered tonnage; and</item>
                            <item>Second. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly, are
                                less than their register tonnage.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Lawton Brothers</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                                >Williams</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana, Cuba</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 10, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In reply to your valued favor of
                        yesterday’s date, we beg to inform you that the rate of tonnage dues paid in
                        this port on the steamers for which we are the agents, is: <list>
                            <item>First. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly,
                                exceed in tons their register tonnage, 62½ cents per ton; and</item>
                            <item>Second. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly, are
                                less than their register tonnage, 62½ cents per ton, provided they
                                carry, jointly, over 6 tons.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The tonnage dues are, in all cases, paid in Spanish gold.</p>
                    <p>We have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>LAWTON BROTHERS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Marsden</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 12, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: For the information of this office, I
                        have to ask of you the kindness to tell me what are the rates of tonnage
                        dues paid by vessels in this port, particularly steamers, namely: <list>
                            <item>First. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly,
                                exceed in tons their register tonnage; and</item>
                            <item>Second. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly, are
                                less than their register tonnage.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS.<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0870" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Marsden</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 17, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In reply to your request, that I should
                        make a statement of the tonnage dues which steamers and vessels have to pay
                        in Cuba, I submit the following list of rates, and how charged: <table
                            cols="4" rows="18">
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="3">American steamers:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Making periodical voyages, on cargo—</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Inward, per 2,000 pounds per ton</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$0 62½</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Outward, per 2,000 pounds per ton</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">62½</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">If cargo in and out exceed the net register tonnage,
                                    they pay per net register tons, less 6 tons</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">1 35</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="3">American steamers:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Not making periodical voyages, with cargo—</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Inward, clearing in ballast, on net register ton</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">1 30</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Outward cargo additional, per ton</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">05</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="3">American sailing vessels the same per ton</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$1 30 or 1 35</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell cols="3">Spanish steamers:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Making periodical voyages, passing in less than
                                    twenty days from Spain or Spanish port, inward</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">Free.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Loading outward for any port, including ports of the
                                    United States—</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">Free.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">From foreign port, via Spanish ports—</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Cargo from Spanish ports</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">Free.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Tonnage dues on cargo from foreign port</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$0 62½</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Outward for Spanish port</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">25</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">Outward for foreign port</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">62½</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>You will notice that it appears Spanish steamers coming from Spain have an
                        advantage over American steamers when they can take cargo from this island
                        for the United States and be exempt of tonnage dues, while American steamers
                        belonging to lines that run regularly, leaving here two or three steamers
                        weekly, are subject to the payment of 62½ cents per ton on their outward
                        cargo from Cuba.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GEORGE MARSDEN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 7 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Placé</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 19, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: For the information of this office I
                        have to ask of you the kindness to cell me what are the rates of tonnage
                        dues paid by vessels in this port, particularly steamers, namely: <list>
                            <item>First. When they come and return with cargoes which jointly exceed
                                in tons their register tonnage, and</item>
                            <item>Second. When they come and return with cargoes which, jointly, are
                                less than their register tonnage.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In addition, please state if Spanish steamers arriving here from Spain in
                        less than twenty days, and leaving with outward cargo for the United States,
                        pay or do not pay tonnage dues in this port.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 8 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Placé</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-12-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 22, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with the desire you expressed
                        in your favor of the 19th instant, I have the honor to inform you—</p>
                    <p>First. A foreign or Spanish mail steamer arriving with foreign goods only and
                        clearing for any part of the world pays tonnage at the rate of 62½ cents for
                        every ton <pb facs="0871" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/> imported and exported,
                        if these do not exceed her net register tonnage, and if they should exceed
                        her net register tonnage, pays according to the net register at the same
                        rate of 62½ cents per ton, deducting 6 tons.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>—The steamer Newport, from New York to Havana
                        and hack to New York, which arrived at this port on the 4th of November
                        ultimo, paid her tonnage dues as follows: 718 tons inward and 899 tons
                        outward; in all, 1,617 tons, at 62½ cents each. Her register tonnage being
                        1,806 tons.</p>
                    <p>The steamer Niagara, from New York to Havana and back to New York, which
                        arrived at this port the 12th of November ultimo, settled her tonnage dues
                        as follows: 949 tons inward and 1,024 tons outward; in all, 1,973 tons, and
                        as her net register tonnage is 1,661.60, paid tonnage on the net register at
                        the same rate of 62½ cents per ton.</p>
                    <p>Second. Spanish steamers arriving with Spanish and foreign goods and clearing
                        with cargo, pay tonnage dues as follows: On the goods from and for foreign
                        countries 62½ cents per ton, imported and exported, provided same do not
                        exceed her register tonnage. And the cargo from Spain to the Spanish
                        Antilles is free of tonnage dues, provided the steamer has performed her
                        voyage in less than twenty days from Spain; if the voyage exceeds twenty
                        days the steamer has to pay the following tonnage dues: 37½ cents per ton of
                        cargo landed, and 25 cents per ton of cargo loaded.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>—The Spanish steamer Cadiz, from Liverpool
                        and Santander, which arrived in this port on the 17th of October ultimo,
                        discharged 127 tons of cargo from Liverpool (balance of her cargo was for
                        other Cuban ports), for which she paid 62½ cents each, and 290 tons from
                        Santander, and as the voyage from Santander was accomplished in less than
                        twenty days, the above 290 tons were free from tonnage dues.</p>
                    <p>Third. Spanish steamers from Spain arriving with cargo and clearing with
                        cargo to a port or ports in the United States, provided the voyage from
                        Spain is made in less than twenty days, are free from tonnage dues on the
                        inward and outward cargo.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>—The Spanish steamer Hernan Cortes, from
                        Barcelona, arrived at this port the 16th of August ultimo; discharged 1,464
                        tons of cargo and loaded 2,176 tons of sugar for New York; both inward and
                        outward cargo was free of tonnage dues.</p>
                    <p>Fourth. An American sailing vessel from any part of the world with general
                        cargo and clearing with cargo to the United States pays $1.35 per ton net
                        register, while a Spanish sailing vessel from Spain with cargo and loading
                        full or part cargo, to the United States only pays 37½ cents per ton of
                        inward cargo and 25 cents per ton on the outward cargo.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>—The American schooner John. R. Bergen, from
                        New York, with general cargo, which arrived at this port the 3d of November
                        ultimo, and loaded at Havana for Philadelphia, paid $1.35 per ton on her
                        register of 615.28 tons.</p>
                    <p>The Spanish brig Elisa, from Spain, arrived on the 27th of August ultimo,
                        discharged 451 tons of cargo, paying 37½ cents per ton, took here 474 tons
                        of sugar to New York, and only paid 25 cents per ton outward.</p>
                    <p>You will please notice the disadvantage of the American marine in these
                        waters. While an American steamer has to pay 62½ cents per ton, the Spanish
                        steamer from Spain bound to the United States does not pay <hi rend="italic"
                            >one single cent</hi> of tonnage dues, and while an American sailing
                        vessel has to pay $1.35 per ton with full or part cargo only the Spanish
                        sailing vessel from Spain, loading for the United States only, has to pay 25
                        cents per ton.</p>
                    <p>Foreign steamers that are not mail boats, arriving and clearing with cargo
                        other than coal, pay for every ton, net measurement, $1.35 per ton; arriving
                        with cargo other than coal and clearing in ballast, $1.30 per ton; arriving
                        in ballast and clearing with cargo, $1 per ton. Foreign steamers and sailing
                        vessels bringing coals only, but in less quantity than their register
                        tonnage, pay nothing per every ton occupied by coals, and for every ton not
                        so occupied, 62½ cents per ton.</p>
                    <p>Please excuse my calling your attention to the fact that the difference
                        between the measurement of the tonnage of American and Spanish steamers help
                        the Spanish steamers considerably.</p>
                    <p>While the steamship Newport, measuring 1,806 tons net, carries about 2,000
                        hogsheads of sugar, the Spanish steamer Leonora, measuring 1,853 tons,
                        cleared from Cardenas the 2d day of May ultimo, with 3,440 hogsheads and
                        2,000 bags, and the Spanish steamer Guido, measuring 2,065 tons, cleared
                        from Sagua on the 5th”day of May ultimo, with 3,736 hogsheads of sugar.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Boletin Comercial</hi> of the 29th August last
                        says:</p>
                    <p>“The immense number of the Spanish steamers (over forty steamers now
                        running); their capacity, as most of them carry twice the cargo of an
                        American steamer; the circumstance of paying the tonnage dues in the United
                        States only once a year, they get full cargoes in Cuba to the United States
                        and leaving from the United States to their European port also with full
                        cargoes,—allows them to accept freight in Cuba at rates much more equitable
                        than formerly paid.”</p>
                    <p>This immense quantity of British steamers running under Spanish flag (to save
                        the difference of duties) between Liverpool, Havana and other Cuban ports;
                        the immense quantity of cargo that comes to this island from Liverpool,
                        owing to the advantages <pb facs="0872" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/> that the
                        Liverpool steamers enjoy, by bringing cargoes not only from Liverpool but
                        from “all parts of the world,” France, Germany, Belgium, Austria, Italy,
                        Holland, Sweden, Norway, that goes to Liverpool in transit for Cuba to meet
                        the British steamer that tinder Spanish flag gives to all the goods from
                        Europe the advantage of the “third column.” Advantages that the American
                        steamers from New York ought to have if the agreement signed by the
                        Government of the United States on the 14th of February, 1884, in which
                        stipulating “American produce under American flag,” are the only articles
                        that can be entered at our custom-house under the third column, and
                        therefore driving away from New York considerable cargo that in transit’
                        from many ports in Europe could have been imported via New York.</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, this argreement, which prohibited American vessels from bringing
                        cargo in transit via New York, allows the same to be done by Spanish
                        vessels, owing to our custom-house regulations. Foreign goods under Spanish
                        flag “third column” therefore Spanish vessels from New York can bring
                        American goods and also foreign goods, all under the “third column.”</p>
                    <p>This advantage, given to the Spanish flag to the prejudice of the American
                        flag by the American Government, is something incomprehensible.</p>
                    <p>Why are not American vessels allowed to carry cargo in transit “via New York”
                        from France, Belgium, Holland, Germany, Sweden, and Norway, when our
                        customhouse is not prejudiced thereby? As said goods as above stated are
                        forwarded to Liverpool to meet British steamers that under the Spanish flag
                        bring them from Liverpool to this island, and this advantage is considerable
                        in many respects, and one of them is that the Spanish steamers from
                        Liverpool bring generally a full cargo to Cuban ports and their net register
                        is fully covered by the inward cargo, this allows them to accept cargoes
                        from Cuba to the United States to greater advantage than American
                        steamers.</p>
                    <p>And referring to the argreement signed at Washington the 14th of February,
                        1884, please take due notice of the following observations published in the
                            <hi rend="italic">Boletin Comercial</hi> of the 5th of September ultimo,
                        under the heading of “<hi rend="italic">La linea de Circumvalacion:”</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>“Regarding the first article, published on the 28th of August, we said that
                        in the agreement of navigation with which we have been occupying ourselves,
                        the Americans renounced their monopoly, not having on the other hand any
                        compensation whatever, as we proved in another article.</p>
                    <p>“Articles 2, 3, and 5 having been withdrawn from the agreement concluded at
                        Madrid on the 2d of January, 1884, between Mr. Ruiz Gomez y Albacete for
                        Spain, and Mr. Foster for the United States, Mr. Canovas del Castillo
                        suggested that the particulars referred to were exclusively attributes of
                        the Cortes, and that the Government was not authorized to make any agreement
                        leaving only to the benefit of the United States the only advantage of their
                        goods being entered at the custom-house under the ‘third column,’ which is
                        the same that ‘all the goods that are imported under the Spanish flag pay
                        from all the parts of the world.’</p>
                    <p>“Placed on same footing as European goods, what advantage did the Americans
                        dream of obtaining over this resigning for this equality of duties the only
                        monopoly of navigation trade that they really possessed?”</p>
                    <p>The Articles 2, 3, and 5 of the primitive agreement suppressed refer to: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>The free importation of live fish from Key West.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The suppression of consular fees on manifest of cargoes.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>The suppression of tonnage dues.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>“Leaving to Americans the advantage of <hi rend="italic">only small</hi>
                        reduction of duties on their goods, which reduction has in fact only
                        benefited Spain.</p>
                    <p>“Since this reduction has in no way increased the importation of the American
                        goods, on the contrary it has diminished, especially as regards corn,
                        potatoes, hay, corn-starch, and many other goods. According to this it is is
                        evidently proved that all the advantages of the ‘ agreement’ are for the
                        exclusive benefit of Spain obtained from the Americans by the ability,
                        intelligence, and wonderful sagacity of the eminent political economists and
                        statesmen, Messrs. Canovas del Castillo and Ruiz Gomez de Albacete, an
                        ‘agreement’ which we must be permitted to style as a master work of
                        diplomacy (<hi rend="italic">obra maestra en diplomacia</hi>).”</p>
                    <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>LOUIS PLACE</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 9 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">collector of customs of the port of
                            Havana</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States of
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-01-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 11, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: To the end that I maybe enabled to
                        comply with an instruction received from my Government, I beg that you will
                        please inform me if the Spanish steamers coming from Spain to the Island of
                        Cuba in less than twenty days are exempt <pb facs="0873" n="789"
                            xml:id="pg_789"/> from the payment of outward and inward tonnage dues to
                        the custom-houses of this island on exporting cargo either for Spain or for
                        the United States. Should this be true, I beg that you will be pleased to
                        inform me if the concession is granted under the authorization contained in
                        article 11 of appendix 16, printed on page 111 of the official pamphlet
                        entitled “Tariff of Customs of the Island of Cuba,” which reads as follows:
                        “Spanish mail steamers will pay in accordance with the special contracts
                        they may have with the Government,” or whether such concession is founded on
                        some other authorization.</p>
                    <p>Also, with regard to Spanish sailing vessels coming from Spain, I have
                        likewise to inquire of you whether the tonnage dues which they pay in the
                        custom-houses of the island are, respectively, at the rates of 37½ cents
                        inward and 25 cents outward, when exporting cargo either for Spain or for
                        the United States, beseeching you at the same time to indicate to me the law
                        upon which these rates are based.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 10 in No. 340.—Unofficial.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fernandez</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-01-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 12, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi> In reply to your attentive letter of the 11th
                        instant, I have to inform you that it is true that Spanish steamers arriving
                        from Spain to this island making periodic trips of less than twenty days are
                        exempt from the payment of tonnage dues, both inward and outward, it
                        mattering not for what port they may afterwards leave. This concession is
                        effected under the authorization granted by the law of commercial relations
                        of July, 1882, inserted in the New Tariff, published by this office on the
                        24th of June of last year, and, in consequence has nothing to do with the
                        eleventh article cited by you.</p>
                    <p>With respect to sailing vessels and steamers not performing periodic trips
                        from ports of Spain, they pay tonnage dues at the rate of 37½ cents per ton
                        of 1,000 kilograms, <hi rend="italic">discharged</hi> in ports of the
                        island, and 25 cents for the cargo taken <hi rend="italic">on board</hi>,
                        without regard to the port of destination; this grant being also included in
                        the law of commercial relations.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOAQUIN FERNANDEZ.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 11 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Cassá</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States of
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-11-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 17, 1884</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to present for your
                        excellency’s consideration and decision the following case, which has been
                        reported to this consulate-general by Mr. Manuel Lopez, now here, and
                        partner of the firm of Messrs. Calixto Lopez &amp; Co., of New York City,
                        the facts of which are as follows, viz:</p>
                    <p>Those gentlemen, under the impression that the commercial agreement entered
                        into between the United States and Spain, at Madrid, on the 13th of February
                        last past, had for its object the abolition of the differential duties on
                        the part of Spain and the countervailing or retaliatory duties on the part
                        of the United States hitherto mutually imposed on the trade between the
                        United States, Cuba, and Porto Rico, and conversely between those islands
                        and the United States, did, on the 16th of last month, ship in New York, on
                        board the American steamship Saratoga, bound for Havana, 286 bags of coffee,
                        the product of the Republic of Venezuela, which had been carried from the
                        port of La Guayra, in Venezuela, to the port of New York, in the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>But, regardless of the conditions of said agreement of the 13th of February,
                        and on the landing of this coffee in the port of Havana, the customs
                        authorities here have pretended to collect the import duties thereon
                        according to the fourth column, instead of according to the third column, of
                        the tariff ruling in the island.</p>
                    <p>In consequence, an excess of import duties has been assessed on said coffee
                        of $67.56 Spanish bank bills, and $608.11 Spanish gold, over and above what
                        it would have had to pay had it been brought from New York to Havana in a
                        Spanish vessel.</p>
                    <pb facs="0874" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/>
                    <p>I am therefore compelled to remonstrate before your excellency against the
                        action of the customs authorities in the case, as being contrary to the
                        intent and meaning of the said agreement of the 13th of February last,
                        promulgated in the Official Gazette of this city, in its issue-of the 23d of
                        April of the present year, and according to which, as your excellency will
                        observe on reference thereto, it is explicitly stated that the object of the
                        agreement was the mutual concession of tariff advantages between the islands
                        of Cuba and Porto Rico and the United States.</p>
                    <p>The same decree, article 1, also declares that, “in virtue of the authority
                        granted to the Spanish Government by Article 3 of the law of the 20th July,
                        1882, that the duties of the third column of the Cuban and Porto tariffs
                        shall be applied, which implies the suppression of the differential or flag
                        duties to the products and <hi rend="italic">merchandise proceeding</hi>
                        from the United States.”</p>
                    <p>The fact of this collection of an excess of import duties in the case cited
                        constitutes, beyond all doubt, the imposition of a discriminating duty
                        against the American flag in Cuban ports, which was suppressed by the
                        agreement of 13th of February, 1884.</p>
                    <p>It is also in contravention to the law of the Congress of the United States,
                        by which the President was authorized to accept the agreement of Februaty
                        13, 1884, for it is opposed to the perfect reciprocity upon which said
                        Congressional authority is based.</p>
                    <p>Again, had this coffee been brought first from La Guayra to Havana, and from
                        thence shipped in a Spanish bottom to the United States, no more duties
                        would have been collected there than had it been shipped in an American
                        bottom; that is, the shipping of both nations would have been placed on a
                        perfect equality in the ports of the United States.</p>
                    <p>Neither is it reasonable to suppose that the Government of the United States
                        would ever have entered into an arrangement by which the vessels of foreign
                        nations should be favored in the loading of cargo in American ports over
                        American vessels, yet such is what is implied by the interpretation of the
                        agreement of the 13th February ultimo by the Havana customs authorities.</p>
                    <p>Therefore, relying upon your excellency’s clear judgment and good desires for
                        the promotion of commercial relations between the United States and Cuba, I
                        have to ask that it be ordered through your excellency’s superior authority,
                        in view of the foregoing, that no more duties be collected on the said 286
                        bags of coffee of Messrs. Calixto Lopez &amp; Co., of New York, than if they
                        had been brought to Havana in a Spanish vessel.</p>
                    <p>Trusting in an early reply from your excellency for transmission to the
                        honorable the Secretary of State at Washington,</p>
                    <p>I remain, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 12 in No. 340.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Cassá</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States of
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-01-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 9, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: On the 17th of November last I had the
                        honor to address your excellency an official communication upon the subject
                        of a discriminating import duty collected by the customs authorities of this
                        city upon 286 bags of La Guayra coffee, transshipped in the port of New York
                        on board the American steamer Saratoga for this port, to which communication
                        I have not as yet received an answer.</p>
                    <p>In consequence, and in obedience to special instructions, dated Washington
                        the 30th ultimo, from the honorable the Secretary of State of the United
                        States, I have now most respectfully to ask your excellency to be pleased,
                        to inform this office at your earliest convenience of the decision that the
                        island government may have reached upon the subject, to the end that I may
                        accordingly communicate the same to the honorable the Secretary of State,
                        adding, by instruction, that the Government of the United States certainly
                        expects that an engagement like that of February, 1884, which proposes to
                        abolish all differential duties, should be interpreted so as not to
                        discriminate against any cargo carried in an American vessel.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RAMON O. WILLIAMS,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0875" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 13 in No. 340.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cassá</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Williams</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Havana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-01-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 12, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[General government of the Island of Cuba, secretary’s office,
                        political bureau, general business.]</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In answer to your communication of the 17th
                        of November last and 9th instant, referring to the collection of customs
                        duties on 286 bags of coffee, the product of the Republic of Venezuela,
                        proceeding (procedentes) from the United States in the American steamer
                        Saratoga, his excellency the governor-general, after a hearing with the
                        department of the treasury, has been pleased to decide that you be informed,
                        as I now have the honor to manifest, that the 286 bags of coffee have been
                        appraised under the fourth column of the tariff, in accordance with the
                        decision given by this general government on the 30th of May last, which
                        ordered that the benefit of the third column could only be enjoyed by the
                        products of the United States imported under the American flag, a
                        circumstance foreseen in the treaty between the United States and Spain, the
                        said benefit corresponding only to the products of that nation proceeding
                        from the same, but not to the products of other countries, though they come
                        from ports of the United States.</p>
                    <p>God guard you many years.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FRANCO. CASSÁ.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
