<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 39.Mr. Bayard to Mr. Hall.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">40</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1886-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1886-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="40"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d40">
                <head>No. 39.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hall</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-02-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 20, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 329.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose, for your information, a copy of a
                    letter from Mr. Fernando O. Valentine, consul-general of Guatemala at New York,
                    dated the 13th instant, touching the alleged violations of the United States
                    neutrality statutes by the enemies of Honduras and Salvador, and asking the
                    assurances of this Government, conjointly with those of Guatemala, to insure the
                    peace of the Central American Republics. I add also my letter, in reply, of the
                    19th instant, declining to give such assurances, but saying, at the same time,
                    that no effort would be spared in case of proper application by any one of those
                    states to prevent and punish any violation of our neutrality acts.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 329.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Valentine</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of Guatemala</hi>, 345 <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">Produce Exchange,</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-02-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 13, 1886</date>. (Received February
                            15.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to translate the following
                        letter I have just received from Guatemala, which I believe to be of
                        sufficient international interest to warrant my calling your attention to
                        it, demonstrating as it does the marked amity that exists <pb facs="0141"
                            n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/> between the Central American Republics, and
                        clearly evincing that such North American interests as are vested in the
                        Republics of Central America are by no means menaced by such filibustering
                        projects as have recently been discussed by the press of the United States,
                        and further showing that if ever a project of any noteworthy dimensions
                        should be put on foot to overthrow either of the Governments mentioned, they
                        would be staunchly met by the combined forces of the interested Governments,
                        who are determining to preserve peace at all hazards. I communicate the
                        subjoined letter to you with a view that you may, if you deem proper, make
                        public my assurance that those who have interests of any kind in Central
                        America need cherish no fears as to their safety; and, further, I would
                        remind all that the dissemination of rumors of war, which I assure you are
                        but rumors, will by no means act as a remedy for the fact that still
                        six-sevenths of the trade of Central America is done with Europe, whose
                        merchants are not at all alarmed by what might prove an impediment to the
                        increase of the trade of the United States, if such assurances did not exist
                        as are portrayed by the following letter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="center">[Translation.]</p>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Guatemala, January</hi> 18, 1886.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Doctor <hi rend="smallcaps">Fernando C.
                                    Valentine</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Consul-General of Guatemala in New York:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It has come to the knowledge of this Government that some persons
                                residing in New York City are endeavoring to send filibustering
                                expeditions intended to disturb the peace and order of the Republics
                                of Honduras and Salvador.</p>
                            <p>Inasmuch as the perpetuation of peace in Central America particularly
                                interests Guatemala, and actuated by a desire to preserve the sister
                                Republics from any disturbance, the President commissions me to
                                charge you to employ all of your zeal and activity in the discovery
                                of such steps as are taken in the United States to the above ends,
                                and that you do all in your power to impede the said expeditions,
                                and that you will take the same interest in these matters <hi
                                    rend="italic">as if they concerned this Republic</hi> (<hi
                                    rend="italic">of Guatemala</hi>) <hi rend="italic"
                                    >exclusively.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>You will inform me by cable of any matter that you may deem important
                                in this connection.</p>
                            <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                            <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <p rend="right">ANTONIO LOZO ARRIAGA.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>In view of the foregoing facts that are borne out by the above letter, and in
                        evidence of the friendship of the United States of North America towards the
                        Republic of Guatemala, do you authorize me to cable my Government as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>“Secretary State this Government assures me that its assistance is at our
                        command to prevent expeditions against Central America, should any
                        arise.”</p>
                    <p>While Guatemala has no fear of such expeditions as have recently been
                        mentioned, and while the letter I have transmitted expresses only a desire
                        for positive information, the cablegram above suggested will counteract the
                        unfavorable impression that cannot fail to be created in Central America by
                        some of the matter that has recently been published in papers that will
                        shortly reach our countries, and the context of that matter may, I fear,
                        produce in the minds of many a misapprehension of the feelings of the
                        Government of the United States towards Central America, inasmuch as several
                        of the reports make it appear that your Government allows filibustering
                        expeditions to be equipped and armed undisturbedly against friendly nations.
                        The cablegram I suggest will at once annul any such erroneous
                        conceptions.</p>
                    <p>Assuring you, sir, that the Government of Guatemala, under the Presidency of
                        General Manuel Lisandro Barillas, cherishes the most profound respect for
                        its great sister, the United States of America,</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FERNANDO C. VALENTINE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General of Guatemala.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 329.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Valentine</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-02-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your letter of the 13th
                        instant transcribing a note addressed to yourself by the minister for
                        foreign affairs of Guatemala, wherein he apprehends that filibustering
                        expeditions are about to be dispatched from New York against the peace <pb
                            facs="0142" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> of Honduras and Salvador. You
                        thereupon ask to be authorized to cable your Government that you have
                        received the assurances of the United States that its assistance is at the
                        command of Guatemala to prevent expeditions against Central America should
                        any arise.</p>
                    <p>Although the Government of the United States has given heretofore abundant
                        proor of its determination to uphold its neutrality statutes in respect to
                        the Governments of Central America, as well as in respect to all other
                        Governments which may be involved in wars, domestic or foreign, I am unable
                        to comply with your wishes as expressed. Violation of our neutrality
                        statutes is an offense against the domestic sovereignty of the United States
                        and is to be punished on competent proof that the wrong complained of was
                        done contrary to our laws and within their jurisdiction.</p>
                    <p>This Government is disposed to take every possible means within the power of
                        the United States to prevent hostile attempts being set on foot within their
                        jurisdiction against the peace of the Republic of Guatemala, should occasion
                        arise. The same is also true as regards either of the other Central American
                        states. But to give assurance that the power of this Government will be
                        allied with that of Guatemala to prevent alleged violations of our
                        neutrality against the peace of the other Central American Republics is a
                        step which this Government cannot take. In the event, however, of evidence
                        of such violation being presented in the proper way as respects any one of
                        those States, no effort would be spared to prevent and punish to the fullest
                        extent of the law any persons charged with the violation of the neutrality
                        statutes of the United States.</p>
                    <p>In this connection I take occasion also to acknowledge the receipt of your
                        telegram of the 19th instant upon this subject.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
