<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 78.Mr. Foulk
                            to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1886-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1886-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692" lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495" lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307" lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257" lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862" lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-03-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                <head>No. 78.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foulk</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Seoul,
                                Corea</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-03-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 20, 1886</date>. (Received May
                            27.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 286.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward herewith inclosed
                        a report of notes on mineral products of Corea prepared by myself.
                        Considerable interest is manifested in various ways in the East in regard to
                        the mineral resources of Corea, and that of Western capitalists is likely to
                        be drawn to the subject at some future day.</p>
                <p>These considerations have prompted my submitting the inclosed report, which,
                        though deficient in accurate statistics and but a general statement,
                        contains, I feel assured, the bulk of such information as is yet obtainable
                        in Corea.</p>
                <p>Several localities are about to be examined for gold and silver by a German
                        chemist in the service of the Corean mint, now being established. His
                        examination will probably give more accurate results than have been
                        heretofore obtained.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEORGE C. FOULK,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Ensign U. S. Navy, Chargé
                                d’Affaires ad interim</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 286.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report on mineral products of Corea.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The only practical effort to work mines in Corea that has been made as
                            yet by Western foreigners was that of Messrs, Jardine, Matheson &amp;
                            Co., a wealthy commercial firm of China, in 1883–’84. This firm, after
                            negotiations with Mr. P. G. von Mölendorff, who then served as general
                            adviser to the Corean Government, sent a <pb facs="0300" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/> well-equipped party of foreigners and Chinese into
                            the country from Seôul in the winter of 1883 to make an examination,
                            with the view of securing mining concessions in case minerals were found
                            in paying quantities. The party established a camp or two and remained
                            in the country, its members making frequent individual visits to Seoul
                            and Chemulpho, until about August of 1884.</p>
                    <p>Early in the spring of 1884 the firm established a head office at
                            Chemulpho, moored a large hulk in the harbor there, and started a
                            steamer to ply between the port and Shanghai. From this it is to be
                            inferred that the company expected great results.</p>
                    <p>The party at work in Corea began their examination near Seôul, and
                            continued it thence in a northerly direction until it came to the main
                            chain of the coast mountains to the south of Wonsan (Gensan). It may be
                            said the examination was entirely confined to a narrow belt of territory
                            lying to the north of Seôul, between the northern tributaries of the
                            Seôul River and about 100 miles long.</p>
                    <p>From first to last the work of examination was attended with great
                            difficulties. The poor accommodations for living in the interior of
                            Corea, the severity of the winter, the wretched roads, and wild,
                            mountainous character of the district, ignorance of the language and
                            customs of the people, distrust of the natives, most of whom had never
                            seen or heard of Western foreigners—such were natural enough
                            obstructions. But in addition to these it is quite evident that the
                            company did not have the support and assistance of the Government in its
                            work, and that Mr. von Mölendorff alone conducted the examination for
                            Corea, without the Government’s having much, if any, voice or interest
                            favorable to the success of the examination. The geographical, social,
                            and political conditions of Corea are such, that without earnest
                            governmental encouragement and direct assistance success cannot attend
                            any great venture in the country.</p>
                    <p>It is significant to note that the district examined by Messrs. Jardine,
                            Matheson &amp; Co. is one of the very few <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                            generally described by Coreans as rich in minerals.</p>
                    <p>In March, 1884, it was made known that galena had been discovered by the
                            party in Yong Phyöng prefecture, but the silver was so small in amount
                            that work would only pay by using extensive reducing machinery. But no
                            traces of coal were discovered. Full reports of the work were not
                            published, yet it is generally believed the results of the examination
                            are known. The following notes are taken from an English Blue Book,
                            containing a translation of an article written by a Chinese who was with
                            the party.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">location of deposit.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Gold is reported to be found at Hakwa-U and San-Kwa-U, two places about 3
                            miles apart, the first 1½ miles from Yang-tök prefecture, and gold was
                            obtained from these places in 1833.</p>
                    <p>Silver was found in Yöng Phyöng prefecture, about 40 milea from Seôul, in
                            small quantities (in galena). Lead was plentiful. Absence of coal,
                            remoteness from the coast, and bad transportation, &amp;c, preclude
                            working these mines at present.</p>
                    <p>Copper mines which have been worked by Coreans were found at
                            Ni-shil-tong, in Yang-tok valley, and also at a place about 8 miles
                            eastward of Kinewha prefecture. Copper is mined also at Chong-no, near
                            the boundary of Kum Soüg prefecture, and the yield is reported as
                            fair.</p>
                    <p>At Sokok, some 20 miles beyond Kum Soüg, a copper mine in a deep gorge is
                            reported.</p>
                    <p>Lead was being mined by Coreans in two mines 800 and 500 feet deep, near
                            Sokok, some 50 to 60 pounds only per day being produced; the yield is
                            sold at Sokok.</p>
                    <p>Silver is found in the lead ore of Tang Hyong. It is reported that there
                            are iron and copper mines at Chilhimto, Yong Phyöng, Kim-wha, and Kum
                            Soüg which will bear working for thirty or forty years and produce
                            paying quantities. No traces of coal were found.</p>
                    <p>In June, 1884, Messrs. Jardine, Matheson &amp; Co. sent an expert mining
                            engineer to join the party in Corea. He made several visits of
                            inspection along the line from Seôul to Wonsan and visited some
                            districts outside of the belt in which the party had been working.</p>
                    <p>His examinations were very superficial, and he returned to Seôul unable
                            to show any very satisfactory results. During the summer of 1884 gold
                            dust and nuggets were very plentiful in Seôul, and I am certain that
                            this engineer endeavored to buy specimens of Corean gold in Seôul, that
                            he might take them to the head office of his employers in lieu of those
                            he had not been able to find himself.</p>
                    <p>At about this time the company sent to its camp in the neighborhood of
                            Yang-tök an American named James Graham, a seaman by profession, who had
                            mined in California. This man kindly treated the natives, and set his
                            few coolies to work at pan-washing in some rice-fields. He at once
                            produced gold in considerable specimen quantities in dust and large
                            rounded nuggets. He returned to Seôul very soon and made his report.
                            Graham, who had once served with me on board the United States <pb facs="0301" n="217" xml:id="pg_217"/> steamer Monocacy, exhibited
                            his find to me—a packet of dust and nuggets worth about $400. He
                            described to me the locality in which he had been working as very rich
                            in gold, and stated that pumps only would be needed to make the yield of
                            washing in the Yang-tök valleys very valuable.</p>
                    <p>While he was at work in the rice-fields an officer came to complain that
                            he was drawing water from the fields and otherwise injuring them. Upon
                            this he stopped work at once.</p>
                    <p>Promptly upon the receipt of Graham’s report Messrs. Jardine, Matheson
                            &amp; Co. began negotiations with Mr. von Mölendorff to get a franchise
                            of mining rights. He failed, however, to produce it, and the Government
                            now began to show much interest, perhaps surprise, in Messrs. Jardine,
                            Matheson &amp; Co.’s venture. The firm endeavored to secure rights by
                            other means, but failed in every instance. It finally abandoned its
                            intentions to work mines in Corea, and removed its office, the cargo,
                            hulk, and mining party from Corea towards the close of 1884. In, the
                            following spring Graham endeavored to secure a position under the Corean
                            Government to enable hi in to work gold washings for it.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">mining privileges.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is no doubt whatever that in China and Japan it is believed that
                            Corea is rich in minerals, and more particularly gold. Yet it has been
                            the rule heretofore for the natives of those countries to present the
                            most disparaging reports of Corea. At the same time it will be observed
                            that Japanese and Chinese are crowding into Corea with all dispatch, and
                            forming colonies where permitted. Their trade is always increasing, and
                            inasmuch as the exports of Corea are few and poor, while Chinese and and
                            Japanese imports are considerable, and that Corea has no coinage or
                            currency acceptable abroad, it follows that there must be a constant and
                            considerable flow of the crude precious metals of Corea into Japan and
                            China.</p>
                    <p>In the autumn of 1885 the Chinese commissioner in Seôul and his assistant
                            made application for mining rights in Corea to the King.</p>
                    <p>They proposed sending to the gold districts of the country gangs of
                            thirty to forty Cantonese Chinamen who had mined in the United States.
                            Twenty per centum of the net profits in gold was to be the share of the
                            Corean Government.</p>
                    <p>The application failed abruptly, and was regarded as being very
                            extraordinary in the terms. At about the same time certain Germans made
                            application for mining rights, but were asked to wait until “next year”
                            for its consideration. It has been several times stated by the Corean
                            Government that it is not prepared to consider propositions in regard to
                            mining, but will do so when it shall have secured competent foreign
                            advisers for its service. The disposition of the Government is to guard
                            its mines jealously, and to be the actual proprietor of them in case
                            they are to be developed after the” Western methods of working.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">position of mines.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>All Coreans proclaim here that there is much gold and other mineral
                            wealth in the country. From very ancient times gold and other mines have
                            been worked in Corea, and their localities are widely known. It is a
                            great mistake to suppose that Coreans are ignorant of the localities of
                            mineral products of their country. There is probably no country in the
                            world where the mass of the people are better acquainted with the
                            geography of their own land than Coreans.</p>
                    <p>The excellence and great number of maps to be found is very remarkable.
                            There are, in even the smallest village, maps on large scales and
                            showing minute details of their localities. The localities of all the
                            principal products, natural or manufactured, are well known to even the
                            children of ordinary intelligence.</p>
                    <p>Phyöng-an province is generally spoken of as richest in gold, the chief
                            locality being Yong-won, a remote inland town, where gold has been
                            produced from very ancient times.</p>
                    <p>In Ham-Kyöng province (N. E.) at Yöng-hung there are from twelve to
                            twenty washings, which are now the most productive in the country. This
                            place, Yong-hung, is but a few miles north of the treaty port of Wonsan
                            (Gensan), whence the largest part of Corean exported gold is carried in
                            Japanese steamers. The Japanese evince a very hearty interest in these
                            mines.</p>
                    <p>The following nine places are noted from ancient times as gold mines:
                                <table cols="4" rows="6">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Province.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Prefecture.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Province.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top">Prefecture.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Kyöng-sung
                                        (southeast)</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Kynng-chü.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Whanghai (west)</cell>
                                <cell>Chang-yöun.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Söng-clü.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell>Söng-wha.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Wi-söng.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Phyöng-an
                                        (northwest)</cell>
                                <cell>Yöng-won.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Ham-Kyöng
                                        (northeast).</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Yöng-hung.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #nowrap">Chöula
                                        (southwest)</cell>
                                <cell>Kumku.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom">Imshil.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0302" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/>
                    <p>During the fall of 1885 the Government sold permits to private
                            individuals to work at these places for a period of five months, a small
                            percentage of the gold to he presented to the Government. It would
                            appear that the Government has never worked for itself continuously any
                            gold mines. Referring to the mines at Yong-hung, which are often visited
                            by Japanese, the director of the engineering association of Japan, Mr.
                            Ito Yajiro, writes as follows:<note n="*" xml:id="d82fn1">Taken from a
                                published collection of notes in a report.</note> “Yong-hung, in
                            Ham-Kyöng Do, has 12 gold mines (one of which, however, is closed, owing
                            to its proximity to a royal tomb), and in these 5,600 laborers are (now)
                            employed.</p>
                    <p>“The exact amount of the output of these mines cannot be ascertained
                            owing to the defectiveness of official regulations. It is Known for
                            certain that the miners present to the Government, and to some of the
                            public officials, gold obtained, at the rate of 60 per cent, for the
                            former and 30 per cent, for the latter, amounting to 50,400 pounds a
                            year, but any quantity obtained beyond that weight is sold secretly by
                            the laborers.” It has been stated to me that at present (March, 1886)
                            the Government receives about 30 <hi rend="italic">nyang</hi>
                        <note n="†" xml:id="d82fn2">A <hi rend="italic">nyang</hi> is a weight equal to
                                1.2 ounces. One <hi rend="italic">nyang</hi> of crude gold dust of
                                average quality is now worth about $21 Mex.</note> of gold per month
                            from the Yöng-hung mines.</p>
                    <p>The winter has been very severe, and the work could not be carried on at
                            the eight other places stated above to have been farmed out by the
                            Government in the autumn of 1885.</p>
                    <p>
                        <note n="‡" xml:id="d82fn3">From here to end of table of mines is culled
                                from Mr. Ito Yajiro’s report.</note> At Unsan, in Phyöng-an
                            Province, there is said to be large deposits of gold dust some five or
                            ten feet under the surface of the ground, but the quantity of metal to
                            be obtained is too small to make the work of the Coreans profitable.</p>
                    <p>“Silver is found in Kyöng kui, Chhung-Chhöng, Chöula, and other
                            divisions, but is not commonly worked. Whenever officials travel to
                            Peking a quantity of silver is dug from the mines, one-half of which is
                            worked into bars and the remainder retained as treasury reserve, and
                            2,000 pounds are given to each ambassador to the Chinese capital.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">other minerals.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>“Copper mines, though found here and there in Kyöng kui and Kyöng-sung
                            provinces, are only occasionally worked, when there is a demand for
                            copper coins or when the ore is in demand for commerce. The annual
                            output is estimated at five or six thousand pounds.</p>
                    <p>Two or three good veins were discovered in Phyöng-an Province many years
                            ago. Iron of a superior quality is obtained in all but the two northern
                            provinces.</p>
                    <p>Coal is found in large quantities between Hamhung and On-Söung in
                            Ham-Kyöng Province, and one or two veins are exposed in Kyöng-sung
                            Province. Nothing is yet known as to the continuity of these veins, but
                            the outcrop bears a slight resemblance to those of Chikuzen (Japan). The
                            total amount of gold and silver exported from 1881 to 1884 from the
                            treaty ports is as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="center">[One yen is about $1 silver.]</p>
                    <table cols="5" rows="6">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right" rows="2">Port.</cell>
                            <cell cols="2" rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Gold.</cell>
                            <cell cols="2" rendition="#border-bottom #border-top">Silver.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Weight.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Value.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Weight.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top">Value.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">
                                <hi rend="italic">Pounds.</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">
                                <hi rend="italic">Yen.</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">
                                <hi rend="italic">Pounds.</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Yen.</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Pusan</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">979.7273</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">245,019.203</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">2,953.7605</cell>
                            <cell role="num">50,914.703</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Wonsan.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4,468.7737</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1,355,258.218</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1,702.8550</cell>
                            <cell role="num">39,898.889</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom">Chemulpho</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">1,091.1610</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">284,755.770</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">14,023.6280</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom" role="num">296,955.852</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The number of mines is as follows: <table cols="8" rows="9">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Province.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Gold.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Silver.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Copper.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Iron.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Coal.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Lead.</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top">Precious
                                        stones.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Kyöng Kui</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">3</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">2</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Chhung-Chhöng</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">6</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Ham-Kyöng</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">10</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">2</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">7</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Whanghai</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">9</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">5</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Kangwön</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">14</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">3</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">6</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Chöula</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">9</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">4</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right">Kyöng-sung</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">17</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">7</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">10</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">2</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right" role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">3</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom">Phyöng-an</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">19</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">3</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">3</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                                <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom" role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom" role="num">1</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0303" n="219" xml:id="pg_219"/>
                    <p>From Mr. Ito’s report it would appear that the exports of crude gold arid
                            silver from Corea are as follows from 1881 to 1884: Gold, 3,785,033.191
                            yen; silver, 387,769.444 yen; making an average in round numbers of
                            $1,200,000 worth of each metal per year.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">mining method.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Corean methods of working goldmines are very primitive. The tools
                            employed are of the simplest kind, and ate only those for washing out
                            the gold from the soft earth of the valleys. Quarts has probably never
                            been worked.</p>
                    <p>Quicksilver is somewhat used in collecting gold after washing. It maybe,
                            however, that gold will for many years be best obtained by washing in
                            the valley.</p>
                    <p>The country presents the evidences of very great geological age, and the
                            hills are very generally in great areas, made up of decomposed granite
                            and other rocks washed down into long, low foot-hills.</p>
                    <p>Tunnel mines are known to be in existence, more particularly in the
                            northern provinces. Some are said to be very deep, and their ventilation
                            so bad that miners cannot remain in them any length of time.</p>
                    <p>Mining laborers are said to number 60,000.</p>
                    <p>Iron is said to be very abundant at Chai-ryöng, in Whanghai Province.</p>
                    <p>Coal has been found recently in large quantities and in fair quality in
                            Phyöng-an Province, near the capital city, Peng-yang, and on the banks
                            of the Tatong River. This locality, which may be described as that of
                            the mouth of the Tatong River, would seem to present some valuable
                            features as a field for western enterprise.</p>
                    <p>The river is navigable for quite a distance. Near it are the two
                            celebrated gold districts of Whanghun Province, and on it not far from
                            these mines is the large coal deposit above referred to. The
                            neighborhood is well populated, and is reported to be thrifty in many
                            ways.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">future prospects.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As yet no competent mining engineer, geologist, or mineralogist has made
                            examinations in Corea, either privately, or under the patronage of the
                            Corean Government, from whom statistics as to mineral riches may be
                            obtained. While the question is an open one, as measured by the absense
                            of statistics, the evidences we have, such as they are, go to show that
                            Corea as a field for mining enterprises will attract much attention in
                            the future, and may prove to be much richer in mineral products than she
                            has been represented by her neighbors.</p>
                    <p>It is very possible that belief in Corea’s great mineral riches is a
                            factor in the cause of the embarrassing political situation the
                            peninsula is placed in between China and Japan, and this embarrassment
                            may be very greatly augmented should such a belief take root in the
                            European nations whose interests have already been drawn politically
                            towards Corea.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GEORGE C. FOULK,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ensign, U. S. Navy,
                                    Charge d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                    Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Seôul,
                                        Corea</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-03-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 20</hi>,
                                1886</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
