<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 79.Mr. Bayard to Mr. Parker.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1886</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1886-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1886-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <head>No. 79.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Parker</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-04-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 28, 1886</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 8.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received Mr. Foulk’s No. 274, of the 29th
                    of January last, in relation to the difficulties that have been encountered in
                    the organization and establishment of the general foreign settlement at
                    Chemulpho.</p>
                <p>The attempt to organize a foreign settlement there has been made, as you will
                    find, under an agreement with the Corean Government, which has been signed by
                    the representatives of the United States, Great Britain, and Germany, in Corea,
                    and of which a copy was transmitted to this Department with Mr. Footers No. 95,
                    of the 21st of July, 1884.</p>
                <pb facs="0304" n="220" xml:id="pg_220"/>
                <p>Under that agreement the Corean Government undertook to cause all Corean houses
                    within the limits of the settlement to be removed within a specified time, and
                    to prepare the land for sale to the citizens or subjects of the signatories. The
                    upset prices of lots were fixed, and it was agreed that they might be sold at
                    public auction.</p>
                <p>It was further agreed that a yearly rental of a certain sum per 100 square meters
                    should be charged on each lot, according to the class to which it belonged; that
                    of this sum 30 cents per 100 square meters should be retained by the Corean
                    Government, and that the remainder, together with any balance left from the
                    proceeds of land sales, after deducting therefrom the cost to the Government of
                    the preparation of the lots for sale, should belong to the municipal fund.</p>
                <p>This fund was to be under the control of a council, to which the police power of
                    the municipality was committed, and the council was to consist of a Corean
                    official, the consuls of the signatory powers, and three registered land-holders
                    who, were “to be selected by the other registered land-holders.”</p>
                <p>The settlement was marked out by the Corean Government more than a year ago, and
                    about fourteen lots have been taken up by German subjects, but as yet no title
                    deeds have been issued. And as there are thus no registered land-holders, no
                    council has been elected.</p>
                <p>This delay in the organization of the settlement seems to be due, in part, to the
                    failure of the Corean Government to keep any account of the expenditures made in
                    the preparation of the land for sale and occupation. It was proposed to the
                    Corean Government by the representative of Germany to divide the whole cost of
                    preparation by the number of lots, and to treat the result as the amount to be
                    paid to the Government by the purchaser on each lot. But, as no account of the
                    expenditures had been kept, no such arrangement could be effected, and it was
                    then agreed that the German purchasers should pay to the Corean authorities
                    one-third of the full price of the lands, receiving therefor a receipt for the
                    whole amount and their title deeds.</p>
                <p>This arrangement the Corean Government now desires to undo, claiming the right,
                    under the original agreement, to receive and retain all the proceeds of the sale
                    of land until the aggregate shall equal the amount expended in preparing the
                    whole site of the settlement.</p>
                <p>To this contention there are two objections: the first being the fact already
                    adverted to, that the Government is unable to tell how much it has spent on the
                    settlement, and the second that such a course would leave nothing immediately
                    available from the proceeds of the sale of lots for the use of the
                    municipality.</p>
                <p>These complications seem to make it expedient to endeavor to effect some revision
                    or amendments of the agreement on terms as favorable to the purchasers as can be
                    obtained, at the same time taking care to protect the interests of the
                    municipality as a whole. A fair basis for such an arrangement would seem to be a
                    division or apportionment of the price of each lot purchased between the
                    Government and the municipality, allowing to the former the average cost of
                    preparation, or a sum agreed upon as equivalent thereto, and turning over the
                    balance of the purchase money to the latter.</p>
                <p>Until some definite arrangement shall have been made, the course recommended by
                    Mr. Foulk in his No. 274, in case an American citizen should desire to purchase
                    a lot, may be adopted with the concurrence of the Corean Government.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
