<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the American Delegation ( (Davis) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-06-01T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-06-01T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-06-01T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-06-01T20:00:00-05:00" n="194"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/75: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-06-02T02:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 2, 1934—2 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received June 2—12:44 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>863. My 862, June 2, 1 a.m.<note n="57" xml:id="d194fn57">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_94">p. 94</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In a second talk with Simon this afternoon he said that he hoped I could
                        come to London soon to start the naval conversations and wanted to know when
                        I would be there. I told him we could not well begin before the middle of
                        the month because our naval experts could not sail until June 6th.</item>
                    <pb facs="0345" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>As this seemed an opportune moment I asked if he had any particular ideas
                        in his mind with regard to the proposed conversations. He replied that while
                        he had little to do with the matter himself it was his understanding that
                        since the Japanese experts would not arrive very soon the British and
                        Americans would first clear up all questions between themselves which should
                        not be difficult. They would then be prepared to take the matter up with the
                        Japanese.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I then remarked that aside from discussing technical naval questions as
                        between ourselves there remained the question of determining what our
                        attitude should be with regard to an increase in the Japanese ratio. As to
                        this he said that he had recently told Matsudaira frankly that he had been
                        somewhat disturbed about what he had read in the press with regard to
                        Japanese pretensions and claims for an increase in ratio but that he had had
                        no intimations from the Japanese Government that it was making any claims
                        and that he would like to know if the Japanese were making such claims
                        officially as that would be a serious matter. Matsudaira had then cabled
                        home and subsequently reported to him that the Japanese Government had not
                        made any such claims. I told Simon I was glad to know that and that I judged
                        by this that the British Government was still opposed to any increase in the
                        Japanese ratio; which was reassuring because it had been somewhat disturbing
                        to read speeches like that of Admiral Keyes and to learn of statements by
                        certain of the British naval officers advocating a close community of
                        interest between England and Japan in naval matters or the granting of
                        parity to Japan. Simon then said that Admiral Keyes was retired and a member
                        of Parliament; that neither the Government nor the Admiralty had any control
                        over him but that he could not believe that any naval officer on the active
                        list could take such a position because it was positively not the attitude
                        of either the Government or the Admiralty; that Great Britain has more seas
                        to cover than Japan and that parity with Japan would be absurd.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
