<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-07-05T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-07-05T09:00:00-05:00" n="237" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/133: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-07-05T15:00:00+01:00">July
                                        5, 1934—3 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received July 5—2:52 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>385. My 378, July 3, 3 p.m. From Norman Davis. When I called to see
                                Baldwin yesterday afternoon, Simon was also present, which was a
                                surprise to me but which had perhaps been arranged in order that
                                Simon might inform me of what the Japanese Ambassador had just told
                                him to the effect that the Japanese representatives would not arrive
                                until October, at which time they would be prepared to discuss the
                                naval question in all its aspects.</p>
                            <pb facs="0388" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/>
                            <p>Baldwin began by saying that in view of the Japanese delay, which
                                caused him some concern as he felt we were going to have trouble
                                with Japan, he did not feel that there was any hurry in attempting
                                to reach any definite conclusions as between ourselves except as to
                                broad general principles, and that in any event he would like first
                                to find out what arrangements if any the British can arrive at with
                                France next Monday and Tuesday, not only with regard to the navy,
                                but with regard to Germany and the whole European situation, as this
                                would have a definite bearing on Great Britain’s ability to conform
                                more closely to the point of view of the United States. He felt,
                                however, that our conversations to date had been most beneficial in
                                that while they have brought out a difference of view with regard to
                                technical questions, they have helped to bring about a more friendly
                                and frank understanding as to the necessity for us to work in
                                harmony, and that if we can only avoid the mistake of 1927<note n="16" xml:id="d237fn16">For correspondence on the Three-Power
                                    Conference for the Limitation of Naval Armament, Geneva, June
                                    20–August 4, 1927, see <ref target="frus1921v01#pg_1">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1921, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> of
                                allowing our technical differences to be aired in the press instead
                                of between ourselves, there will be no difficulties which we will
                                not be able to overcome.</p>
                            <p>I then reviewed what had happened with regard to publicity and our
                                justifiable complaints on this score. Simon showed real concern over
                                this, insisting that the Foreign Office was in no way to blame and
                                trying also to exculpate the Admiralty, which I am now satisfied has
                                been the cause of the trouble. I believe Baldwin is determined to
                                prevent a recurrence of such incidents in the future. Baldwin said
                                he considered it of the utmost importance that there should be no
                                statements given out by either Government, but that after they have
                                talked with the French he would like for us to have some further
                                conversations. I stated that in view of the postponed arrival of the
                                Japanese I felt it was not necessary or quite right for me to remain
                                here much longer after the departure of the French. He agreed that
                                we should probably then discontinue for the present the
                                conversations but that we should consider giving out a joint
                                statement. Under the circumstances I thought it inopportune to
                                discuss with him the draft statement cabled you in the telegram
                                under reference. Baldwin said that in the meantime and in order to
                                avoid any publicity it would be very easy for us to meet informally
                                at dinner any time.</p>
                            <p>Simon said that if we could only produce our figures as they had
                                done, we could proceed with the technical discussions. I repeated
                                that if we were to attempt such discussions before we have agreed
                                upon a common objective, we would be floundering in the dark. At
                                this point I placed categorically before Baldwin the two questions
                                outlined in the second paragraph of my cable under reference, but he
                                evaded a definite answer, saying he would like to think that over
                                    <pb facs="0389" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/> although Simon said
                                that they were of course in favor of a renewal of the treaty, but
                                that they would like to discuss certain technical modifications
                                which would make it more acceptable to themselves. I emphasized that
                                if it should prove impossible to renew the London Treaty it was most
                                important in my opinion that neither England nor the United States
                                should be the cause of the failure, and that we at least ought to be
                                wise enough to let some other power assume that onerous role.
                                Baldwin said that he was impressed by that argument and would like
                                to think it over but that he considered Anglo-American cooperation
                                as more important now than anything else and that in spite of all
                                the perplexing problems that are facing Great Britain now, he was
                                satisfied that with the spirit that now animates us both we would
                                reach a mutually satisfactory meeting of minds.</p>
                            <p>Throughout the talk Baldwin was exceedingly friendly and impressed me
                                as not being so converted to the Admiralty point of view as
                                MacDonald. [Davis.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bingham</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>