<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the American Delegation ( (Davis) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d285</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">285</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-11-16T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-11-16T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-11-16T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-11-16T16:00:00-05:00" n="285"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d285">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/266: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-11-16T21:00:00+00:00"
                            >November 16, 1934—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 16—7:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>41. After reflection and discussions among ourselves and with some of the British
                    with regard to the questions raised in the last meeting with the British
                    (reported in my 37, November 15, 8 a.m.<note n="93" xml:id="d285fn93">Not
                        printed; it summarized minutes of meeting between British and American
                        delegations on November 14; for text of minutes, see <ref target="#pg_334"
                            >p. 334</ref>.</note>) I wish to submit the following observations and
                    conclusions.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>The British now agree with us that since Japan has repeatedly informed us
                        of her unalterable decision to denounce the Washington Treaty, it would be
                        unrealistic from now on to continue the negotiations without accepting at
                        face value the Japanese decision and proceeding on the basis of such
                        denunciation.</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>That group within the British Cabinet who are particularly fearful of the
                        European situation, from which Great Britain cannot detach herself, and who
                        feel that it is of vital importance in some form to bind and limit Japan by
                        agreement, are at present largely controlling the course of negotiations.
                        The predominant opinion even in that group, however, is that in any such
                        agreement with Japan it is vitally important that the United States should
                        be a party. The British are thus anxious that we should go along with them
                        in the discussion of such a program but, if not, that we should at least
                        agree for them to explore all possibilities, keeping us informed of every
                        move. It is for that reason that they frankly outlined the so called “middle
                        course”.</item>
                </list>
                <p>We have thus reached a situation where I feel that we need your instructions on
                    certain definite questions.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>Can we agree to go along with the British in discussing with the Japanese
                        some such “middle course” proposal as was outlined to us at our last
                        meeting?</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>If the answer is in the affirmative what are the conditions we must insist
                        upon, particularly with respect to qualitative limitation, without any
                        quantitative limitation?</item>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>If we cannot cooperate along the lines of a “middle course”, how shall we
                        proceed, bearing in mind that denunciation will otherwise make it difficult
                        to avoid a new conference, under article XXIII of the Washington
                        Treaty?</item>
                </list>
                <p>I personally think that the wisest course would be for us to go along with the
                    British as under (1) above, with proper precautions and safeguards. Thus, the
                    British take the primary responsibility and we safeguard our position by
                    preventing them from acting as mediator and later proposing something that would
                    be embarrassing to us. <pb facs="0452" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/> In keeping this
                    on the British doorstep we may avoid a possible responsibility that might
                    otherwise devolve upon us under article XXIII of the Washington Treaty. We
                    should furthermore bear in mind that, in the event of a conference to be called
                    as a result of a denunciation of the Washington Treaty, presumably preliminary
                    conversations would be necessary, in which case we could not well avoid such
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>If you decide that we shall acquiesce in the middle course proposed by the
                    British as a basis of further discussion, I suggest for your consideration the
                    following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>If there is to be included in the “middle course” a statement of the
                            respective building programs either to be embodied in a treaty or by
                            unilateral undertaking, these programs should maintain the present
                            ratios and failing that, any statement of building programs should be
                            eliminated altogether, and it should be understood that we are free as
                            to quantitative construction within such qualitative limitations as may
                            be agreed upon.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>If it should be deemed advisable to maintain the present provisions
                            for non-fortification of bases in the Far East, we might, in agreement
                            with the British (as Simon has suggested to me) make it a condition that
                            there be an additional provision granting the right of full and free
                            inspection.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Since the present naval treaties are based on political agreements as to certain
                    principles and policies, we might reserve the right in connection with any new
                    naval treaty to reexamine any question, political or otherwise, which would be
                    involved in or affected by such a treaty.</p>
                <p>The impending Japanese denunciation of the Washington Treaty of course adds
                    considerably to the complications of the situation. It is difficult to accept it
                    as a <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi>, and difficult to ignore it. It would
                    in a way simplify the problem if the Japanese should go ahead and give
                    notification of denunciation but, if we are to continue to negotiate before they
                    denounce it is important to have a clear understanding as to the bases of the
                    negotiations and that we are not negotiating a modification of that treaty.</p>
                <p>I had been inclined to favor an early adjournment if it could be done without our
                    taking the responsibility for it, thinking perhaps that we could meet under
                    better auspices after denunciation. However, I am now more inclined to think it
                    wiser to permit the negotiations to continue under British initiative and
                    responsibility (particularly since the British favor it and the Japanese are
                    apparently willing to go ahead) in the hope that we may be able to clear up the
                    matter one way or another.</p>
                <p>If we are to participate even indirectly in negotiations for an entirely new
                    agreement it would seem important, for political reasons, <pb facs="0453"
                        n="353" xml:id="pg_353"/> to avoid the impression that we are considering
                    modifications in the present agreement and thus making concessions to Japan. It
                    should be made publicly known that the Japanese have announced to the British
                    Government and ourselves their definite intention to denounce the Washington
                    Treaty and their determination not to continue bound by the ratios and
                    principles embodied in both the Washington and London Treaties, and that this
                    decision is reluctantly accepted as final. Also that the Japanese have presented
                    certain proposals predicated upon the abandonment of the principles embodied in
                    the present system of naval limitation and intended to form the basis of a new
                    treaty of limitation; that these proposals the British and ourselves have been
                    unable to accept and that we have accordingly decided to explore the
                    possibilities of an entirely new agreement.</p>
                <p>It might be well to consider whether it would be advisable for the British and
                    ourselves, and perhaps the Japanese, to agree upon a public statement setting
                    forth these facts.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
