<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the American Delegation ( (Davis) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-12-13T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-12-13T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-12-13T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-12-13T14:00:00-05:00" n="314"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d314">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A5/330: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-12-13T19:00:00+00:00"
                            >December 13, 1934—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 13—3:49 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>72. Your 50, December 12, 1 p.m. I think my 70, December 12, 10 p.m. will have
                    answered paragraphs 1 and 2.</p>
                <p>As regards paragraph 3 I pointed out to Craigie that the formula they were
                    discussing was not consistent with our previous understanding that any building
                    programs to be acceptable should be contractual. He said that was partially true
                    but insisted that they were achieving the same results in practice through a
                    contractual undertaking for previous consultation and for 12 months’ notice, a
                    provision which would constitute a satisfactory substitute for the present
                    escalator clause. At any rate he said we were not being asked to agree to this
                    now, that it would be a question for future consideration, although so far as
                    the British were concerned, they felt there were certain advantages in such a
                    proposal quite aside from attempting to find a face saving formula.</p>
                <p>As regards your fourth paragraph I told Craigie I did not know whether we would
                    feel justified in discussing our 1937–1942 naval <pb facs="0499" n="399"
                        xml:id="pg_399"/> program and that we would certainly not be willing to
                    present it even tentatively until we knew the character of the Japanese program.
                    He replied that he would not expect us to do so.</p>
                <p>As to your paragraph 5 I fully agree with you as to the inadvisability of
                    introducing any new element into the conversations at the present time such as
                    entering upon a discussion of the technical differences of opinion between the
                    British and ourselves.</p>
                <p>This morning’s <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> in an obviously inspired article on
                    the future of the naval talks contains the following passage.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The American delegation consider that the Washington Treaty gave all its
                        signatories equality of security. Great Britain agrees with this view but
                        would like if possible to meet in some way the Japanese objection to being
                        classified in a lower category…”<note n="40" xml:id="d314fn40">Omission
                            indicated in the original.</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
