<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Legal Adviser ( (Hackworth))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d441</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">441</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign currency</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec6cb1b0c545b7fae" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaties, conventions, etc.</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="441"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d441">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51 Johnson Act/76</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Legal Adviser</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Hackworth</hi>)<note n="16" xml:id="d441fn16">Copy of this memorandum was
                        enclosed with letter of May 17, 1934, from Assistant Secretary of State
                        Moore to the Attorney General (not printed). In his reply dated May 18, the
                        Attorney General stated: “It follows from these considerations that the
                        acceptance by American bondholders of scrip or funding bonds, under the
                        circumstances hereinbefore set forth, is not forbidden by the Act of April
                        13, 1934.” (37 Op. Atty. Gen. 526.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-05-14">May 14,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Issue by Germany of Scrip or Bonds in Payment of Interest
                        on Outstanding Obligations of German States, Municipalities, and
                        Corporations Held by American Nationals</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The following is submitted in response to the request in the Attorney General’s
                    letter of May 9, 1934,<note n="17" xml:id="d441fn17">Not printed.</note>
                    regarding the question presented by Mr. George Rublee, Counsel for the Foreign
                    Bondholders Protective Council, transmitted to the Attorney General by Mr.
                    Moore’s letter of May 8, 1934.<note n="17" xml:id="d441fn1">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The situation as I understand it is substantially as follows:</p>
                <p>The bonds, the interest coupons of which are to be liquidated, are those of
                    German States, Municipalities, and Corporations. The German <pb facs="0637"
                        n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> Government controls all foreign exchange in
                    Germany. Sufficient exchange to enable the obligors to meet the interest
                    payments on their bonds is said not to be available. The plan, therefore,
                    contemplates payment of the interest by the obligors to the German Government
                    and the issue in turn by the Government of its obligations, scrip or bonds, in
                    satisfaction, in part at least, of the coupons.</p>
                <p>The Act approved April 13, 1934, makes it unlawful for any person to purchase or
                    sell “the bonds, securities, or other obligations of, any foreign government or
                    political subdivision thereof or any organization or association acting for or
                    on behalf of a foreign government or political subdivision thereof, issued after
                    the passage of this Act, or to make any loan to such foreign government,…<note
                        n="18" xml:id="d441fn18">Omission indicated in the original
                        memorandum.</note> except a renewal or adjustment of existing indebtedness
                    while such government, political subdivision,” etc. is in default in the payment
                    of its obligations to the Government of the United States.</p>
                <p>If the bonds, the coupons of which are thus to be liquidated, were the bonds of
                    the German Government, there would seem to be no doubt that the transaction
                    would come within the stated exception, and within the Attorney General’s
                    opinion of May 5, 1934. The Attorney General stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“… In other words, such ‘scrip’ or ‘funding bonds’ are authorized if
                            issued in the bona fide ‘renewal or adjustment of existing
                            indebtedness.’</p>
                        <p>“… Thus an adjustment of an existing indebtedness within the meaning of
                            the Act is any lawful arrangement entered into in good faith between the
                            debtor and the creditor which compromises or determines the amount to be
                            paid by the debtor to the creditor and it may include other details of
                            composition or settlement.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The question then is whether the fact that the interest payments to be adjusted
                    are not payments on obligations of the German Government precludes our regarding
                    the transaction as a renewal or adjustment of “existing indebtedness”. It would
                    appear not unreasonable to conclude that by the term “existing indebtedness” as
                    used in the Act was meant indebtedness of the government making the
                    adjustment,—not the indebtedness of a third party. On this hypothesis it would
                    be at least arguable that acceptance by American bondholders of the obligations
                    of the German Government would be illegal under the Act.</p>
                <p>This, however, would probably be a narrow and illiberal interpretation. A broader
                    interpretation which would admit the legality of the transaction would be based
                    on the theory (1) that the purpose of the law is to prevent governments in
                    default on their obligations to the United States from floating additional loans
                    or establishing additional <pb facs="0638" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> credits in
                    the United States; and (2) that by “adjustment of existing indebtedness” is
                    meant any indebtedness for which the foreign government is liable.</p>
                <p>In elaboration of this theory it might be said that the German Government by
                    establishing a control of foreign exchange and undertaking to accept from the
                    German obligors the interest payments in marks, which it has already done, and
                    to settle with the foreign bondholders, has become obligated to pay this
                    indebtedness, and that, therefore, the present proposal to exchange scrip or
                    other obligations for the coupons on the bonds held by American nationals is an
                    adjustment of existing indebtedness within the meaning of the Act.</p>
                <p>There would seem to be little doubt that Germany is liable on these obligations
                    under both German law and international law. The German law of June 9, 1933,
                    effective July 1, 1933, provides in Section (1) that— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“[§ 1.] (1) Interest, dividends and regular amortizations, as well as
                            real estate rents, payments under leases and similar regularly recurring
                            payments on accounts, credits, loans, mortgages, land charges,
                            participations and other capital investments of foreigners or
                            Saarlanders must be paid by the debtor at the contractual due date in
                            Reichsmarks, to the credit of the foreign or Saarland creditor, to the
                            Conversion Office for German Foreign Debts (§ 2). The permits necessary
                            under the legal provisions concerning foreign exchange are to be granted
                            when the conditions of sentence 1 are at hand. In case the debtor is
                            required to pay in foreign currency, the amount is to be converted into
                            Reichsmarks at the official Berlin middle rate of the currency in
                            question on the weekday preceding the date of payment. In case the
                            currency is not officially quoted on the Berlin Stock Exchange, the
                            conversion shall be made at the rate determined upon as the middle rate
                            by a Committee of the Berlin ‘Association for Fixing Conditions for the
                            Trade in Securities’ (<hi rend="italic">Bedingungsgemeinschaft für den
                                Wertpapierverkehr</hi>) and published in the press. If, in the case
                            of a currency, neither an official quotation on the Berlin Stock
                            Exchange nor a determination of rates by the Berlin Committee on
                            Conditions has been made, the rate of conversion is to be determined on
                            the basis, on the one hand, of the last known rate on a foreign Stock
                            Exchange of the foreign currency in question and on the other hand, of
                            the last known official middle rate of said foreign Stock Exchange
                            quoted on the Berlin Stock Exchange or determined by the Berlin
                            Committee on Conditions; as rates determined in accordance with this
                            provision, the rates determined by the Reichsbank to be such shall
                            govern.</p>
                        <p>“(2) To the extent to which the debtor makes payment to the Conversion
                            Office for German Foreign Debts, he is freed from his obligation. The
                            Obligation of the Conversion Office for German Foreign Debts toward the
                            creditor is governed by the provisions of § 3.<note n="19"
                                xml:id="d441fn19">The following omission indicated in the original
                                memorandum.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <pb facs="0639" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                        <p>“§ 2. (1) A Conversion Office for German Foreign Debts is hereby created.
                            The Conversion Office is a public law corporation; it stands under the
                            supervision of the Reichsbank-Direktorium and carries its account with
                            the Reichsbank. The Reichsbank-Direktorium will elect the Conversion
                            Office’s responsible agencies.</p>
                        <p>“(2) The other legal relations of the Conversion Office are governed by
                            its statutes which will be fixed by the Reichswirtschaftsminister in
                            agreement with the Reichsbank-Direktorium.</p>
                        <p>“(3) The Conversion Office is free of the taxes which the Reich, the
                            states and the municipalities (associations of municipalities) levy on
                            income, on property and on business establishments.</p>
                        <p>“§ 3. The amounts paid in (§ 1 paragraph 1) will be credited to the
                            foreign or Saarland creditors. The claims of the creditors arising from
                            the credit will be determined according to principles which will be laid
                            down in the statutes of the Conversion Office. At what point of time
                            payments may be made out of the accounts, the Reichsbank will
                            determine.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It will be seen from the foregoing that the German Government has by law
                    prohibited the German obligors on these bonds from making payment to the
                    bondholders; has required those obligors to pay the money over to an agency of
                    the German Government, and has discharged the debtors from further obligation
                    toward the creditors. There is, in effect, a sequestration by the German
                    Government of property or property rights of the foreign creditors for which the
                    German Government is liable under international law.</p>
                <p>A situation somewhat analogous to this was presented when certain states during
                    the revolutionary period provided by law for payment to official agencies of
                    those states obligations due British merchants. The British creditors not being
                    able by the “ordinary course of judicial proceedings” to obtain compensation for
                    their debts, the action of those states was made the subject of treaty
                    stipulations between the United States and Great Britain which provided for
                    arbitration of the question (Article VI of the Jay Treaty of 1794), and this
                    having failed, the Government of the United States was required, by the Treaty
                    of January 8, 1802, to pay the British Government £600,000, amounting to
                    $2,664,000, in satisfaction of the obligations due British merchants. (1 Malloy,
                        <hi rend="italic">Treaties, Conventions, etc.</hi>, (1910) 590, 594, 610,
                    611; I Moore, <hi rend="italic">International Arbitrations</hi> (1898) 271; III
                    Moore, <hi rend="italic">International Adjudications</hi> (modern series, 1931)
                    entire volume).</p>
                <p>Since American nationals, unless they accept the proposed arrangement, will
                    presumably be unable to collect on their coupons and apparently will be without
                    an adequate remedy, and since the precise meaning of the Act in this respect is
                    not entirely clear, the more liberal interpretation would seem to be warranted.
                    Having in mind these latter considerations, I am inclined to the view that such
                    an interpretation <pb facs="0640" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/> would not do
                    violence to the Act, and might, with reason, be adopted.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Green H. Hackworth</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
