<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-04-28T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-04-28T14:00:00-05:00" n="531" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d531">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">856D.6176/229: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-04-28T14:00:00-05:00">April 28,
                                    1934—2 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>166. Your 204, April 26, 4 p.m.<note n="37" xml:id="d531fn37">See
                                footnote 32, <ref target="#pg_652">p. 652</ref>.</note> The British
                            reply does not substantially lessen the Department’s doubts regarding
                            the rubber restriction plan as outlined. Therefore please in your
                            inquiry Monday put forward again the points conveyed to you in previous
                            instructions, emphasizing particularly the extreme desirability of
                            getting the assurance that would be conveyed by some specific price
                            protection in some form or other (you may make it clear again that this
                            Government is not seeking to bring about any particular arrangement for
                            price protection by merely seeking the assurance of having some definite
                            know-in-advance price protection arrangements), in the absence of which
                            this Department fears speculative price movements and injurious price
                            situations. If the American consumer of rubber has no explicit
                            protection, how can he be expected to feel assured in the face of
                            restrictive arrangements the operation of which is completely <pb facs="0757" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/> at the discretion of a small
                            committee drawn from the producing countries. Emphasize also the fact
                            that the arrangement merely for a panel of consuming interests to tender
                            advice to the committee from time to time seems inadequate both for the
                            purpose of assuring consumers a full knowledge of the plan’s operation
                            and also to carry out the obligations assumed by His Majesty’s
                            Government under section (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>). This Government
                            regrets that it must continue this exchange of contentions. If the plan
                            is put through as it stands at present, the British Government must not
                            be surprised if critical opinion forms in this country. This Government
                            would regret such an eventuality and is anxious to avoid it. It appears
                            that the two Governments are in substantial agreement as to the
                            desirable objectives of the rubber plan and this Government hopes some
                            way can be found to reach agreement on those details of the plan which
                            would be of importance in obtaining the objectives.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>