<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Gilbert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d592</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">592</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-07-12T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-07-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-07-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-07-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="592"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d592">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.C115/347: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-07-12T17:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 12, 1934—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 12—2:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>196. Department’s 77, July 11, noon. A financial arrangement peculiar to the
                    Geneva organizations is that their budgets are not determined by funds available
                    from arbitrary national contributions but that these contributions are fixed as
                    shares of a total predetermined budget.</p>
                <p>The contributions of League states are based upon the total budget requirements
                    of the League, the International Labor Organization and the Permanent Court, By
                    a precedent set in the case of Brazil states members of the organization and not
                    members of the League pay into the Labor Organization direct, the amount thus
                    received being subtracted from the labor office share of the total budget of the
                    three organizations mentioned.</p>
                <p>The plan followed with Brazil and the one envisaged for the United States is that
                    the contribution to the organization, is determined by negotiations between the
                    governing body and state concerned and may be either some determined proportion
                    of the total organization budget or a fixed sum. In the case of Brazil both
                    arrangements have been followed.</p>
                <p>The governing body meets in January, April, May and October. Labor office
                    officials view it as impracticable for procedural reasons as well as perhaps
                    presenting an equivocal aspect for the United States to negotiate its
                    contribution before becoming a member. This however could undoubtedly be
                    arranged were the United States to regard it as essential. While in theory the
                    governing body could take any position it desired respecting what it regarded as
                    an adequate American contribution it is felt that no difficulties would be found
                    in the United States agreeing to pay the British contribution which is
                    approximately 10 percent of the total budget estimated with reasonable
                    confidence for 1935 at $310,000 at the current exchange between the Swiss franc
                    and the dollar or a fixed sum in about that amount.</p>
                <p>Certain details in Consulate’s despatch 951, political, dated July 2<note n="16"
                        xml:id="d592fn16">Not printed.</note> and further details in despatch being
                    prepared.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
