<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-05-24T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-05-24T07:00:00-05:00" n="65" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d65">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4 General Committee/912:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The American Delegate</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-05-24T13:00:00+01:00">May
                                        24, 1934—1 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received May 24—10 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>840. Your 414 May 23, 5 p.m.</p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) No further developments.</p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Subject to a general reservation by Italy
                                a maximum attainable program appears possible which provides for a
                                national licensing system for manufacture of arms together with full
                                publicity of licenses issued coupled with a control of export in
                                arms along the lines provided in 1925 convention.<note n="35" xml:id="d65fn35">
                                    <p>Convention for the Supervision of the International Trade in
                                        Arms and Ammunition and in Implements of War, signed at
                                        Geneva, June 17, 1925, <ref target="frus1925v01#pg_61">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 61</ref>.</p>
                                    <p>For correspondence concerning efforts to secure ratification
                                        of this convention by the United States, see <ref target="#pg_449">pp. 449</ref> ff.</p>
                                </note> It is contemplated that publicity shall be concentrated in
                                the hands of some central international body. In any negotiations in
                                this respect it must be anticipated that France, the Little Entente
                                and Spain will press for the inclusion of some sort of quota
                                restriction as envisaged by the French amendment<note n="36" xml:id="d65fn36">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the General Commission</hi>, vol.
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 591.</note> to the British
                                draft. Even this program, however, will be jeopardized by the
                                absence of Germany and this political factor must be given due
                                consideration.</p>
                            <p>However, the foregoing is based upon views which have been expressed
                                in consideration of the control of manufacture of and traffic in
                                arms being a portion of a general disarmament convention and I
                                cannot predict with certainty whether the same positions would be
                                taken in default of a general convention.</p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Before submitting recommendations it would
                                be essential to understand whether the Government of the United
                                States has in mind favoring or proposing a separate convention on
                                regulation of manufacture and trade in arms if no general convention
                                is realizable. The recommendations which I would care to submit
                                would be predicated on knowledge of this fact. It is obvious that if
                                there is a general convention embodying a substantial reduction we
                                could go further in the <pb facs="0169" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/>
                                control of manufacture of and trade in arms than in the event of a
                                treaty limited to this particular aspect of armament. Further, it
                                would be useful to know the pertinent portions of Mr. Davis’
                                contemplated speech in order to recommend helpfully.</p>
                            <p>Copy to Paris.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>