<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-04-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="701" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d701">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4215 Air Pollution/492</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Minister in Canada</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Robbins</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 303</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-04-18">April 18,
                                    1934</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I acknowledge the receipt of the
                                Legation’s despatch No. 517 of April 11, 1934, transmitting a note
                                dated April 10, 1934, which the Department of External Affairs of
                                Canada addressed to the Legation, relating to the Trail Smelter
                                matter.</p>
                            <p>It is stated in the second paragraph of the Canadian note that a new
                                aspect of the problem had arisen which suggests the necessity of
                                further consideration before a draft of a convention dealing with
                                the Trail Smelter matter can be submitted to the two Governments. It
                                is understood that the Canadian Government refers to the conditions
                                which that Government found to exist at Detroit, Buffalo and other
                                places along the international boundary as a new aspect of the Trail
                                Smelter problem.</p>
                            <p>I do not feel that conditions at Detroit, Buffalo and other places
                                can be regarded as an aspect of the Trail Smelter case.
                                Correspondence between the two Governments in regard to the Trail
                                Smelter matter began in 1927, and it has throughout been considered
                                as a problem in itself, separate and distinct from questions arising
                                elsewhere on the international boundary. No mention has at any time
                                been made, prior to April 10, 1934, in the correspondence between
                                the two Governments relating to the Trail Smelter matter of
                                conditions at Detroit, Buffalo or elsewhere on the international
                                boundary.</p>
                            <p>The Trail Smelter matter was investigated by the International Joint
                                Commission, and the Commission rendered its Report in February,
                                1931. The questions now raised by the Canadian Government <pb facs="1032" n="932" xml:id="pg_932"/> have not been so
                                investigated. Correspondence with the Canadian Government following
                                the Report of the Commission on the Trail Smelter Reference was
                                opened by the note of the Legation to the Department of External
                                Affairs dated February 17, 1933. Since that time there have been a
                                number of exchanges of communications without mention therein of
                                conditions at Detroit, Buffalo and elsewhere.</p>
                            <p>I do not feel that conditions at Detroit, Buffalo and other places
                                along the international boundary can be regarded as an aspect of the
                                Trail Smelter problem or that those conditions can properly be
                                injected at this time into the discussion pertaining to the Trail
                                Smelter matter.</p>
                            <p>In the third paragraph of the note of April 10, 1934, reference is
                                made to a statement contained in the Canadian Government’s note of
                                February 17, 1934, to the effect that a principle should not be
                                established in the Trail Smelter case which would potentially
                                involve a shutting down of existing industries of various types in
                                industrial communities in the Dominion of Canada and the United
                                States along the international boundary.</p>
                            <p>It is not deemed necessary or desirable to establish any principles
                                in the solution of the Trail Smelter matter. Proposals made by the
                                Government of the United States looking to a solution of the Trail
                                Smelter problems have not contemplated the establishment of any
                                principles. It is the view of the Government of the United States
                                that the Trail Smelter case should be determined according to
                                established and recognized principles. The formula proposed in
                                Article 4 of the draft convention referred to in the Canadian note
                                would admit of the application of established principles. I agree
                                that it is not desirable, and feel that it is not necessary, to
                                establish any principles in adjusting the Trail Smelter case. I feel
                                that the questions presented by the operation of the Smelter at
                                Trail, in so far as interests in the United States are affected, can
                                and should be determined by the application of existing recognized
                                principles.</p>
                            <p>It is stated in the last sentence of the third paragraph of the
                                Canadian note that it was assumed that the maximum frequency,
                                duration and concentration of sulphur dioxide visitations which it
                                was proposed should be determined by a tribunal for the State of
                                Washington would be applicable to other cases in which sulphur
                                dioxide was crossing the international boundary.</p>
                            <p>There was no suggestion in any of the correspondence exchanged
                                between the two Governments prior to the Canadian note of April 10,
                                that decisions to be made with respect to the Trail Smelter case
                                should have application to any other case or cases which might arise
                                along the international boundary. The Trail Smelter case should be
                                adjudicated according to established principles applicable to that
                                particular case. <pb facs="1033" n="933" xml:id="pg_933"/> Any other
                                case which might arise should be determined according to established
                                principles applicable to that particular case. The Trail Smelter
                                case has been the subject of extensive investigation by both
                                Governments. No showing has been made which would necessitate a
                                conclusion that the questions raised by conditions at Detroit,
                                Buffalo or at Canadian industrial centers along the international
                                boundary would be susceptible of determination by the application of
                                the same principles as would control in determining the questions
                                raised by the Trail Smelter case. There is no occasion at this time
                                to conclude that decisions which might be made with respect to the
                                Trail Smelter case would have application to questions which might
                                arise at other places.</p>
                            <p>It is not understood that the Canadian Government suggests any
                                definite procedure to be followed with respect to conditions at
                                Detroit, Buffalo and other places along the international boundary.
                                The Canadian note of April 10, seems to contemplate that
                                consideration of the Trail case should be deferred until
                                investigations are completed at Detroit, Buffalo and other places
                                along the boundary and that the provisions in the proposed
                                convention relating to the Trail case be extended to apply to other
                                cases.</p>
                            <p>I cannot acquiesce in any suggestion that contemplates delay in
                                settling the Trail case. As emphasized above, the Trail case is
                                entirely separate and distinct from questions which are now raised
                                with respect to Detroit, Buffalo and other places on the
                                international boundary. The questions which are now raised by the
                                Canadian Government have not attained the same status that the Trail
                                case has attained. I do not consider that there is any justification
                                for mingling the Trail case with any new questions. The adoption of
                                any suggestion which would have the effect of delaying
                                considerations of the Trail case could not fail to operate to the
                                advantage of the trespassers and to the disadvantage and further
                                injury of the victims of the wrongs. If the Canadian Government will
                                submit concrete proposals as to the procedure which it considers
                                should be followed with respect to the industrial centers to which
                                reference is made in the Canadian note of April 10, 1934, separate
                                from the Trail Smelter case, I shall be glad to consider those
                                proposals. I exceedingly regret that the Canadian Government
                                considers that new cases should be associated with the Trail case. I
                                earnestly hope that the Canadian Government can see its way to
                                proceed expeditiously to the conclusion of an agreement calculated
                                to settle the Trail case.</p>
                            <p>It is suggested, in conclusion, that conditions at Detroit, Buffalo
                                and other places along the international boundary about which the
                                Canadian Government now expresses concern would more appropriately
                                be referred to the International Joint Commission for investigation
                                and report, as was done with respect to the pollution of boundary
                                waters <pb facs="1034" n="934" xml:id="pg_934"/> under date of
                                August 1, 1912, than to a tribunal such as it has been proposed to
                                establish to adjudicate the Trail Smelter case. To conduct such
                                investigations is one of the purposes for which the International
                                Joint Commission was established and is maintained.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Walton Moore</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>