<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-10-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="711" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d711">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4215 Air Pollution/565a</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName> to the Prime Minister of Canada</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bennett</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-10-25">October 25,
                                        1934</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Prime Minister</hi>: There are one
                                or two matters which I should like to have talked over with you
                                personally, but I realize, to my regret, that this is for the moment
                                impracticable. I have accordingly asked Mr. William Phillips, our
                                Under Secretary of State, to proceed to Ottawa to place my views
                                respecting these matters before you in a spirit of full frankness.
                                Will you not talk to Mr. Phillips respecting these matters in the
                                same way in which I feel that you would talk to me?</p>
                            <p>The most pressing of these questions is that of the Trail Smelter
                                case which, as you know, has been pending between our countries for
                                a number of years and remains unsettled. I am receiving in
                                increasing numbers protests from residents and officials in the
                                State of Washington. These communications disturb me greatly and
                                cause me to fear that, unless a way is found as soon as possible to
                                reach a settlement of this case, real harm may be done to the
                                relations of Canada and the United States in the Far West. The
                                continued drifting of sulphur dioxide into the State of Washington,
                                with its consequent injury to the interests of a large number of
                                American citizens, is a matter to which I cannot remain
                                indifferent.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Phillips will, as I have stated above, express fully my views to
                                you.</p>
                            <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Franklin D. Roosevelt</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>