<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="154" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                        <head>154. Memorandum of a Conversation, Paris, April 29, 1955<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d154fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_FESEA1">FE/SEA</gloss> Files: Lot 58 D 207, Paris
                                Talks—May, 1955. Top Secret. Drafted by <persName>Dillon</persName>
                                and D.M. Bane of the political section of the Embassy.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-04-29">April 29, 1955</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Edgar
                                Faure</persName></item>
                            <item>Secretary of State Laforest</item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_MRL1">M. Massigli</persName></item>
                            <item>M. Bérard</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName></item>
                            <item>D.M. Bane</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Political Situation in South Vietnam</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REFERENCE</head>
                            <item>Embassy’s telegram 4740 (Saigon 687) April 29<note n="2" xml:id="d154fn2">In this telegram, <persName>Dillon</persName>
                                    described the manner in which he had carried out the
                                    instructions set forth in <ref target="#d149">Document
                                    149</ref>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Central Files,
                                    751G.00/4–2955)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Ambassador opened the meeting by outlining in detail those points on
                            which the United States Government would like clarification from the
                            French Government prior to proceeding with the consideration of
                            questions of procedure and personalities posed in the French
                            Aide-Mémoire of April 17, as well as those assurances of wholehearted
                            support for the future Vietnamese Government which the United States
                            Government feels must be received from the French Government and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> in order to justify
                            the continued support of the United States Government in South Vietnam.
                            A detailed account of the Ambassador’s exposition, which was read and
                            approved by the French, was contained in the reference telegram as <pb facs="0353" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/> well as the Ambassador’s
                            comments to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Edgar
                                Faure</persName> regarding United States concern over the
                            continuation of <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Jean Sainteny</persName> in
                            the role of French Delegate General to North Vietnam. The following
                            summary of the French reaction was read and approved by the French and
                            is set forth here since it is in greater detail than the account given
                            in the reference telegram.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Edgar Faure</persName> began by
                            saying that he must tell us in all seriousness that the French
                            Government felt constrained to review its policy vis-à-vis Vietnam in
                            the light of recent developments, and to confirm that the French
                            Government had no intention of intervening unilaterally with <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> at this juncture.</p>
                        <p>He reminded us that for the past six months the French Government had
                            made clear its conviction to the United States Government that the
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government did not
                            possess the capability of effecting a stabilization of the political
                            situation in South Vietnam, and that for the past month the French
                            Government had endeavored to persuade the United States Government to
                            enter into a joint review of the political situation at Saigon and to
                            reach mutual agreement on a course of action to follow that might avert
                            the outbreak of civil war. He added the personal comment that while
                            holding the posts successively of Minister of Finance, Foreign Affairs,
                            and now Prime Minister, he had not met a single person who believed that
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> could succeed in
                            stabilizing the situation at Saigon.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister emphasized, however, that while neither he nor anyone
                            in the French Government shared the American point of view as regards
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, he wished to make clear
                            that neither he nor the French Government had any intention or desire to
                            enter into conflict with the United States on this score. The fact that
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> is anti-French, he said,
                            is and has always been a secondary consideration as far as the French
                            were concerned. The Prime Minister reiterated once again that the French
                            Government is not wedded to any particular formula for the solution of
                            the crisis at Saigon and that it continued to hold the hope that it
                            might be possible to reach, in consultation with us, a mutually
                            satisfactory position.</p>
                        <p>In referring to the steps taken by <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                                Dai</persName> yesterday to convoke <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> as well as certain Vietnamese personalities to
                            Cannes, the Prime Minister expressed his very real fear that these steps
                            had perhaps been taken too late to save South Vietnam from full-scale
                            civil war. If <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s action had
                            been taken several weeks ago, he said, the chances of success would have
                            been infinitely greater than those presented to us today. Although it
                            may be too late to prevent the occurrence of full-scale civil war in
                            South Vietnam, the Prime Minister said that France remains ready to do
                            its utmost in conjunction with the United States to retrieve the
                            situation. In this connection, the Prime Minister expressed the view
                            that with the sole exception <pb facs="0354" n="322" xml:id="pg_322"/>
                            of the problem posed by our feeling that <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">M.
                                Sainteny</persName> not return to Hanoi, he foresaw no difficulty in
                            the French Government’s accepting the views of the United States
                            Government as outlined by the Ambassador. He said, however, that he
                            would like Minister Laforest and other officials concerned to go over
                            the points as outlined by the Ambassador and that he would confirm the
                            French position shortly.</p>
                        <p>As regards United States concern over French policy towards North
                            Vietnam, the Prime Minister said that he wished to underline in
                            strongest terms that the French Government was not following an
                            equivocal policy or playing “a double game” in Vietnam and that it had
                            no intention of “playing the Vietminh card” to the detriment of the
                            legally constituted Government of South Vietnam. He emphasized that the
                            French Government had no illusions regarding <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName>. However, he said, France needed a
                            representative at Hanoi not with a view to cooperating with the Vietminh
                            but solely for the purpose of protecting such French interests and
                            influence as remain and to keep abreast of developments in that region.
                            The Prime Minister made abundantly clear that for domestic political
                            considerations it was out of the question for him to relieve <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> of his functions. However, he
                            wished to assure the United States Government that the French Government
                            had, as in the past, every intention of taking fully into account United
                            States views in this regard. Minister Laforest at this juncture stated
                            that the failure of the French Government to conclude the mixed company
                            agreement with the Vietminh could be attributed in large measure to the
                            unfavorable attitude taken by the United States Government toward the
                            conclusion of such an agreement. The sale of the Charbonnages du Tonkin
                            constituted, he said, a clear-cut illustration of the intention of the
                            French Government to give maximum consideration to United States views.
                            The person of <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName>, however,
                            Minister Laforest reiterated, posed a domestic political problem. The
                            latter’s role, he said, was limited to that of an observer, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> had been selected for
                            this post solely because he was considered to be the best qualified man
                            for the job. The <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> mission
                            as constituted today, the Prime Minister emphasized, represented a far
                            more preferable approach than that of being placed in the position of
                            having to accredit a consul to the Vietminh Government, a situation
                            which the French Government has tried to avoid from the beginning. In
                            conclusion, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName> stressed
                            that with the sole exception of the recall of <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName>, he could foresee no impediment to French
                            acceptance of the points as outlined by the Ambassador pursuant to the
                            Department’s instructions.</p>
                        <p>In response to the Ambassador’s inquiry concerning <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s delegation of full military
                            power to General <persName corresp="#p_NVV1">Vy</persName>, Minister
                            Laforest stated that <persName corresp="#p_NVV1">Vy</persName> was the
                            oldest Vietnamese General, that he was generally respected, and stressed
                            the importance of the fact that General <pb facs="0355" n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NVV1">Vy</persName> had made clear that he did not
                            wish to participate in a fratricidal civil war. He noted that <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> presently has perhaps
                            approximately 10 battalions of Tonkinese troops, including elite
                            parachute elements, presently engaged in supporting him in the present
                            conflict at Saigon. Minister Laforest likened the situation to the Swiss
                            support of <persName corresp="#p_GGLCF1">Louis</persName> XVI. However,
                            he said, while <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> might succeed
                            in gaining control of the situation in Saigon–Cholon, unquestionably
                            civil war would flare up and continue indecisively in the provinces.
                            Many terrible things could occur in the next several weeks, he added,
                            and irremediable damage inflicted. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName> intervened to point out that the
                            Vietminh are deliberately keeping clear of the present conflict,
                            “rubbing their hands in delight”, with full knowledge that civil war
                            will ultimately deliver South Vietnam into their hands.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister at this juncture referred to his statement at his
                            morning press conference to the effect that France would keep its
                            engagements under the Geneva Accords as regards elections, and he
                            expressed the fear that the scheduled elections had been passed over
                            (depasse) by events which very likely would deliver South Vietnam in
                            fact into the hands of the Vietminh before July 1956.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister stressed, however, that it was perhaps not impossible
                            to retrieve the situation and ultimately succeed in the test with the
                            Vietminh if joint Franco-American action taken quickly. He underlined
                            that the basic objective of France and the United States was the same,
                            namely to maintain and safeguard a non-Communist Vietnam within the free
                            world orbit. <persName corresp="#p_FE1">M. Faure</persName> made clear,
                            however, that the next move was primarily up to the United States and,
                            specifically, he expressed the hope that the United States would exert
                            its influence on <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to see that
                            he returned to Cannes in accordance with <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                                Dai</persName>’s request in an effort to salvage the situation and
                            find a salutary solution.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>