<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-05-09T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-05-09T16:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                        <head>182. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d182fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 751G.00/5–955. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution. The
                                source text is the copy repeated for information priority to the
                                Department of State.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-05-09T22:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">May 9,
                                        1955—10 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 28. For <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>. This morning <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> and Gibson met with Laforest,
                                <persName>Berard</persName> and Risterucci at French request.
                            Friendly but forthright discussion laid out frankly differing attitudes
                            of French and Americans on various aspects Vietnamese crisis, except, of
                            course, basic desire work together if possible for common objective of
                            preventing Communist take-over.</p>
                        <p>Much of meeting spent by French in complaining about specific unfavorable
                            U.S. press articles and in alleging U.S. subordinate officials <pb facs="0419" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> in Saigon can be proved to
                            have aided and abetted <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>‘s
                            attack on Binh Xuyen and government’s anti-French propaganda campaign.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> refuted these
                            charges and enumerated some complaints about French behavior. Both
                            agreed mutual recriminations would not be helpful and turned to
                            immediate problems.</p>
                        <p>Following seemed to be main points of Laforest’s exposition: <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>If U.S. insists on <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, primary requirement is to reinforce <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government and make it
                                    really government of national union according to one of
                                    principles of original <persName corresp="#p_EGPHR1">Ely</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName> seven-point program. French Government
                                    remains prepared to carry out its terms.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item><p>French Government had tried to support <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, but present hostility
                                        to <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> grows out of
                                        increasingly violent press attacks against the French.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> himself has
                                        provoked this hostile attitude in France.</p>
                                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> While claiming <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> himself is using
                                        anti-French themes to build up his own strength, French
                                        officials, when pressed, admitted some of the anti-French
                                        activities are probably done without <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s knowledge. French
                                        officials seem to be most upset over sound trucks moving
                                        around Saigon.)</p></item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>He took up question of <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>
                                    withdrawal by referring to <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName>’s proposition of last Saturday for
                                    “progressive reduction of <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>”
                                    which would allow <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to
                                    say Vietnam is independent. If <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> should leave Indochina it would be in response
                                    to requests from various Vietnamese elements surrounding the
                                    government. If the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> should
                                    leave and the requests of the Vietnamese be met in this respect,
                                    would the U.S. give assurances that it would take over
                                    responsibility for protecting European lives and property?
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> reminded
                                    Laforest of Secretary’s reply in trilateral meeting. Matter
                                    dropped.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> informed Laforest of
                            conclusions in Saigon’s 5074,<note n="2" xml:id="d182fn2"><ref target="#d173">Document 173</ref>.</note> paragraph 8(1)(a) to
                            (g), para 8(2), and final paragraph of <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>. Laforest and Risterucci, in particular, reacted
                            against suggestion French should make all-out declaration for <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> government. They also thought
                            broadening of government should be carried out before other
                            recommendations considered.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> also told
                                <persName>Laforest</persName> that <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> had told <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName> ammunition and other shortages which French had
                            refused to supply had prevented National Army from pursuing Binh Xuyen.
                            French knew nothing about this and discounted <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s statement entirely.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>