<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-05-12T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-05-12T12:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <head>185. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d185fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Conference Files: Lot 60 D 627, CF 447. Top Secret; <gloss target="#t_niact1">Niact</gloss>; No Distribution. On a copy of
                                this telegram in the <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman File, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Series, there is a marginal notation by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GCAJ1">Goodpaster</persName> indicating
                                that the President saw this cable on May 13.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-05-12T18:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">May 12,
                                        1955—6 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 32. Eyes only Acting Secretary
                            from Secretary for President.</p>
                        <pb facs="0432" n="400" xml:id="pg_400"/>
                        <p>“Dear Mr. President:</p>
                        <p>I have not had time to write you since day before yesterday. Tuesday
                                night<note n="2" xml:id="d185fn2">May 10.</note> we had another long
                            session with the French on Indochina and again last night, both sessions
                            lasting until 1 a.m.<note n="3" xml:id="d185fn3">See <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 36, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="#d185">supra</ref></hi>, and <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 42, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="#d186">infra</ref></hi>.</note> I am trying to do
                            the hard thing which is actually to persuade them that <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> is the best hope and that that
                            hope is a possibility only if we treat him as the head of an independent
                            government and not as a puppet to whom we can dictate. The French seemed
                            to think that all we need to do is to crack the whip. I keep emphasizing
                            that if that is the case, then the situation would be hopeless because
                            he could never gain the confidence of his own people. I really think I
                            have made progress. <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName>
                            professes to have been genuinely converted.</p>
                        <p>Last night matters came to a head. <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Faure</persName> wanted us to make an agreement with the French as
                            to our future policies including efforts to influence <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. I said we would not make any
                            agreement because the subject matter did not lend itself to precision
                            and any agreement would almost surely lead to charges and
                            countercharges. I said I would draft our instructions to our Ambassador
                            following the lines of our policy as previously expounded, and that we
                            would show our instructions to the French for their information, and
                            that I hoped the French would send corresponding instructions to
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGPHR1">Ely</persName> which we could see, but
                            that it must be clear that we were following what I hoped would be
                            paralleled courses because this was in the common interest, but that
                            neither of us had any formal engagements to the other. This they
                            accepted, and the work is going forward on this basis.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> has been sitting in on
                            some of our meetings and the information which he has from <persName corresp="#p_MDM1">Malcolm MacDonald</persName> conforms closely to
                            our own thinking so that the British have been helpful.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows a report on discussions at Paris unrelated to
                            Indochina.]</p>
                        <p>Faithfully yours, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Foster</persName>.”</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>