<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-11-18T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-11-18T22:00:00-05:00" n="352" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                        <head>352. Telegram From the Ambassador in Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_RGF1" type="from">Reinhardt</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d352fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                033.90B51G/11-1956. Confidential. Repeated for information to
                                Rangoon, New Delhi, Phnom Penh, Vientiane, and
                            Bangkok.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-11-19T10:00:00+07:00"><hi rend="italic">November 19,
                                        1956—10 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1674. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> summoned me evening
                            November 16 to discuss U Nu visit.<note n="2" xml:id="d352fn2">U Nu,
                                former Prime Minister of Burma and chairman of the dominant
                                political party in Burma, the Anti-Fascist People’s Freedom League,
                                visited Saigon in mid-November.</note> Apparent from outset
                            President both pleased at way visit went off and impressed with
                            personality of guest whom he repeatedly described as simple, kind and
                            deeply religious with high moral sense of justice. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> recounted details of visit
                            outlined Embassy telegram 1643<note n="3" xml:id="d352fn3">Not printed.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 033.90B51G/11–1456)</note> and
                            asserted he had from outset decided it would be preferable to avoid
                            raising controversial questions with Nu and simply to show him country
                            and people in most informal fashion possible. This he had done and he
                            felt sure it had been correct tactic.</p>
                        <p>Nu had asked about unification of Vietnam and was told this was an
                            internal question for which time would be ripe when South had built up
                            its economic and military strength sufficiently to meet North on equal
                            terms. At such juncture <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> said
                            he would be happy to meet <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi
                                Minh</persName> face to face. Concerning relations with Soviet
                            Russia <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> had said that Vietnam
                            was too small and delicate a garden to have such a massive elephant
                            rooting around with its trunk amid the straw huts and pagodas. It was
                            true American elephant was present but it was friendly creature and
                            brought Vietnamese presents of bananas. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> was convinced that U Nu’s impromptu conversations
                            with Vietnamese and Thai refugees had brought home to him some of plain
                            truths of Communist barbarity. He had given Nu comprehensive briefing
                            history <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> and Viet
                                <persName>Minh</persName> movement. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> thought their drive together along miles of
                            unpatrolled jungle roads had impressed him with measure of internal
                            security already attained here. Although Nu had not raised the subject
                            Myint Thein<note n="4" xml:id="d352fn4">Myint Thein, former Burmese
                                Ambassador to China, was a Justice of the Burmese Supreme
                                Court.</note> had said that Burmese were much more concerned with
                            indirect Communist aggression and subversion than with the possibility
                            of overt aggression. (If one is to believe <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s account there was less topical political content
                            in his conversations with Nu than in latter’s Saigon press
                            conference.)</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> said his guest had invited
                            him to visit Burma, suggested a visit by Vietnamese military officers
                            and expressed himself in favor <pb facs="0783" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/>
                            of establishment of relations between the two countries but that nothing
                            specific had been decided on any of these points. (British Embassy on
                            contrary was told by senior official of Burmese delegation that
                            agreement had been reached to exchange Consuls General.)</p>
                        <p>It is general consensus here that visit was indeed highly successful. It
                            marks, I believe, stage in this government’s process of growing up and
                            revealed new level of sophistication on part of <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> himself.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RGF1"><hi rend="strong">Reinhardt</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>