<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>357. Letter From the Ambassador in Vietnam (Reinhardt) to the Director of the
                    Office of Southeast Asian Affairs () to the Director of the Office of Southeast
                    Asian Affairs (Young))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-12-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-12-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="357"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                <head>357. Letter From the Ambassador in Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_RGF1"
                        type="from">Reinhardt</persName>) to the Director of the Office of Southeast
                    Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="to">Young</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d357fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.51J/12–2056. Secret; Official–Informal.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-12-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 20, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Ken</persName>
                    </hi>: The question of Vietnamese-American relations, raised in your letter of
                    October 29,<note n="2" xml:id="d357fn2">
                        <p>This letter is attached to a copy of the letter from <persName
                                corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName> to <persName
                                corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> of December 20, <hi rend="italic"
                                >ibid.</hi>, Saigon Embassy Files: Lot 62 F 52, 320 International
                            Relations, A–Z, 1956–1958. <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName>
                            observed that “several of us in the Department and the other agency have
                            noticed recent indications of increasing difficulties in dealing with
                            the President.” <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> asked for
                                <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName>’s reaction to the
                            following questions:</p>
                        <p>“(a) The reaction of <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Ngo Dinh Diem</persName>
                            and those close around him to American official and unofficial
                            advice.</p>
                        <p>“(b) The prospects of such concentration of decision and power over such
                            a wide and seemingly unnecessary range of matters.</p>
                        <p>“(c) The theory of ‘mandarinism’.”</p>
                    </note> has been one to which we have devoted increasing attention in recent
                    months. Although I do not believe that any fundamental change in the <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s attitude has occurred, I think there is no
                    question that a gradual trend toward greater assertiveness vis-à-vis Americans
                    has been developing for some time and can be expected to continue. Although
                    American assistance is eagerly sought, American advice, as you well know, has
                    never been accepted with any alacrity, particularly on political issues. The few
                    occasions, moreover, in which our “political” advice has materially affected
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> policies have been essentially limited
                    to international issues. Our influence in shaping internal developments, partly
                    because we have voluntarily refrained from asserting maximum effort, has been
                    extremely circumscribed.</p>
                <p>There has been some evidence that President <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                        >Diem</persName>, as he grows more sure of himself through the success he
                    has achieved, is becoming less receptive to unofficial advice given to him by
                    special advisors and close friends. There is probably little that we could do
                    about this situation, and although it is regrettable, I do not consider it
                    alarming. The major effect of this attitude will, I believe, be felt in our
                    economic aid program. It may eventually be necessary, if serious differences of
                    views develop in this field, to make clear to <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                        >Diem</persName> that our continued ability to support the Vietnamese
                    Government will <pb facs="0792" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/> depend on the adoption
                    by the latter of certain basic economic policies which will permit us to justify
                    such aid to the American Congress.</p>
                <p>With regard to the problem created by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                    >Diem</persName>’s concentration of decision and power over such a seemingly
                    wide range of matters, there is again little that can be done beyond recognizing
                    that this unfortunate state of affairs has existed since the beginning of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> regime and will likely be with
                    us for some time. Continuous efforts are being made by <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> to point out the
                    necessity of proper delegation of responsibilities and some improvement is made
                    from time to time along these lines. With the passage of time and the
                    development of really functioning governmental institutions and procedures it
                    can be hoped that these efforts will increasingly bear fruit, although it must
                    be recognized that the source of the difficulty lies principally in the
                    personality of the President, which is not likely to change radically.</p>
                <p>You also asked about the theory of “mandarinism.” This much used and misused word
                    had been made to cover a multitude of sins. Essentially, as I understand it, it
                    is mostly used to describe a form of bureaucratic aristocracy in which decisions
                    of government are largely made by a small group of government officials steeped
                    in the traditions of their office and distrustful of the masses, from which,
                    ironically enough, most of them sprang. In the context of present day realities
                    mandarinism essentially describes an attitude of paternalism approaching
                    benevolent despotism. Certainly one can find elements of the mandarin tradition,
                    in its better sense, in <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s philosophy
                    of government. Yet I think it would be erroneous not to recognize that <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> is far too intelligent and forward-looking
                    to be the prisoner of his own early training and experience as a member of the
                    mandarinate.</p>
                <p>With best wishes,</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="italic">Fred</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">G. Frederick Reinhardt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
