<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>370. Letter From the Assistant Secretary of Defense for International
                    Security Affairs (Sprague) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs () to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    (Robertson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-04-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-04-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="370"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d370">
                <head>370. Letter From the Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SMD1" type="from">Sprague</persName>) to the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_RWS1" type="to">Robertson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d370fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                        751G.5–MSP/4–1557. Secret. Printed also in <hi rend="italic">United
                            States–Vietnam Relations, 1945–1967</hi>, Book 10, pp. 1098–1099.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-04-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 15, 1957</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>
                    </hi>: Recent developments have brought about a new urgency in resolving the
                    problem of the ceiling on U.S. military personnel in Viet-Nam. You will remember
                    that by interdepartmental <pb facs="0813" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> agreement
                    early in 1956 there was established a ceiling of 692, which includes 342 for the
                        <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> and 350 for <gloss target="#t_TERM1"
                        >TERM</gloss>, the Temporary Equipment Recovery Mission.</p>
                <p>Two facets of the problem now point to the necessity of doing away with the
                        <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> ceiling and permitting the Departments
                    of the Army, Navy, and Air Force to augment <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> Viet-Nam with the additional personnel necessary to accomplish
                    the mission there.</p>
                <p>The first aspect is that raised in the telegram from the Embassy in Saigon to the
                    Department of State, 2772, of 12 March 1957, which points out that the
                    International Control Commission is becoming increasingly more restive in
                    respect to <gloss target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss> and recommends consideration of
                    several courses of action.<note n="2" xml:id="d370fn2">The four recommendations
                        of possible courses of action in this telegram were: 1) continuation of
                        exchange-of-letters exercise conceding nothing, making no commitments, and
                        hedging on details and assurances; 2) gradual withdrawal of <gloss
                            target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss>; 3) general compliance with <gloss
                            target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> demands and controls on <gloss
                            target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss>; and 4) abolishment of <gloss
                            target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss> and corresponding increase in <gloss
                            target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Vietnam or creation of new permanent
                        mission to perform <gloss target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss>’s functions. The
                        Embassy recommended the third of these courses for the “immediate future,
                        with serious consideration” of the second and fourth options “as eventual
                        alternatives. It increasingly difficult and embarassing to maintain
                        indefinitely a mission, mainly engaged in training, under guise of a
                        temporary mission solely concerned with recovery and out-shipment
                        equipment.” (Department of State, Central Files, 751.5–MSP/3–1257)</note>
                    The Department of Defense concurred in the April 9 Department of State telegram
                    to Saigon<note n="3" xml:id="d370fn3">The reference is to telegram 2630 to
                        Saigon, April 9, not printed. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.)</note> which
                    stated that a solution of the problem along the lines of incorporating <gloss
                        target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss> into an increased <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> was under study and that the Department of State would discuss
                    the problem with the Canadians, British, French, and Indians. This telegram was
                    the result of a conference on March 20 of staff representatives of the two
                    departments in which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DE1">Durbrow</persName>
                    participated.</p>
                <p>The second aspect of the problem is the necessity for taking over the training of
                    the Vietnamese Navy and Air Force. It will be remembered that <gloss
                        target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss> was created for a dual purpose, to provide a
                    logistical organization to resolve the problems of excess property in Indochina
                    and logistical training in Viet-Nam, and to free the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> from other duties so that its personnel could concentrate on
                    the training of the Vietnamese Army. The withdrawal of the French Army training
                    personnel required this increased emphasis on training. In the telegram from
                    Chief, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Viet-Nam 5607 of 4 April,<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d370fn4">Not printed. (Center of Military History, <persName
                            corresp="#p_WLGST1">Williams</persName> Papers, <gloss target="#t_TWXS1"
                            >TWX</gloss>s 1957 (14))</note> we have been informed that President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Ngo Dinh Diem</persName> told the Chief, <gloss
                        target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> that agreement had been reached with the
                    French Ambassador for the withdrawal of the French Air Force and Navy training
                    missions upon the completion of the present courses of instruction. The first
                    completion is scheduled for this month, and additional U.S. military personnel
                    will be required to pick up the training <pb facs="0814" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"
                    /> from the French. <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> has requested in
                    his 062352Z of 6 April<note n="5" xml:id="d370fn5">Not printed. (<hi
                            rend="italic">ibid</hi>.)</note> that additional personnel over and
                    above the present ceiling reach Viet-Nam in June of this year.</p>
                <p>Other aspects of the problem of the ceiling include a request from President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> for additional Army instructors
                    at the Viet-Nam military academy, a proposal by <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                        >CINCPAC</gloss> to transfer underway training of the Vietnamese Navy from
                    Subie Bay to Viet-Nam, and the current difficulty in operating <gloss
                        target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss>
                    efficiently within their present ceilings.</p>
                <p>An increase in <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> strength to achieve a rapid
                    improvement in the effectiveness of Vietnamese forces to compensate for the
                    withdrawal of French forces is considered a matter of urgency. While the French
                    have withdrawn approximately 190,000 regular troops from Viet-Nam since the
                    Geneva Agreement was signed the Viet <persName>Minh</persName> have continuously
                    reorganized and re-equipped their forces during the same period so as to
                    increase their regular combat strength from six to eighteen divisions. These
                    forces have a capability of conducting combat operations at Corps level. The
                    Vietnamese Army consists of ten divisions which are in the early stages of
                    training at regimental and division level. The current military situation
                    requires that the Vietnamese armed forces expeditiously attain a satisfactory
                    level of combat effectiveness.</p>
                <p>In view of the forthcoming visit of President <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                        >Diem</persName> to Washington on May 8th, 9th, and 10th and of the
                    impending training crises for the Vietnamese Navy and Air Force I recommend that
                    steps be taken as a matter of urgency to secure the necessary international
                    concurrences in the abolition of the ceiling on <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> Viet-Nam. I feel it might be desirable to have this problem
                    resolved, if possible, prior to the arrival of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> in Washington so that he could be informed
                    at that time of our plans to assist him in the training of his Navy and Air
                    Force.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SMD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Mansfield D. Sprague</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
