<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-02-16T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-02-16T13:00:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <head>43. Telegram From the Chargé in France (<persName corresp="#p_ATC1" type="from">Achilles</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department
                                of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 751G.00/2–1655. Secret. Repeated
                                for information to Saigon and Hanoi.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-02-16T19:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">February 16,
                                        1955—7 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>3452. Reference Department telegram 2863.<note n="2" xml:id="d43fn2">In
                                this telegram, February 14, the Department instructed the Embassy to
                                make known to the French its preliminary views (as set forth in
                                telegram 2846, February 11, cited in <ref target="#d43fn3">footnote
                                    3</ref> below) on proposed French Government participation with
                                the North Vietnamese in mixed companies (such as coalmining,
                                shipping, shipbuilding) in which the Vietnamese would hold the
                                majority share and the former French interests a minority one while
                                providing managerial and technical functions. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 751G.00/2–1455)</note> US preliminary views
                            Department telegram 2846<note n="3" xml:id="d43fn3">In this telegram,
                                February 11, the Department set forth its preliminary view on mixed
                                companies as follows: such a plan contradicted professed French
                                support for South Vietnam and joint U.S.-French policies there; it
                                represented wishful thinking as expropriation would come after the
                                1956 elections; it would adversely affect French interests in the
                                rest of Indochina, among other allies, and with the U.S. public and
                                Congress; and finally, it would hinder South Vietnam’s chances in
                                the 1956 elections. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                451G.519/2–755)</note> outlined to <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> (who leaving 19th for Bangkok) at Foreign Office as
                            instructed reference telegram. Minister Economic going over views
                            Department telegram 2846 with Wormser this afternoon.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> said they did not feel
                            Department sufficiently informed concerning French proposal and that as
                            consequence detailed exposition being sent <persName corresp="#p_CMMJ1">Couve</persName> today with instructions go over with Department.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> expressed hope Department
                            would reserve judgement until receipt fuller expression French views
                            this regard. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> underlined
                            tentative nature French proposal and said government had no idea as yet
                            whether Viet <persName>Minh</persName> prepared accept this or other
                            proposal. In hour-long conversation, <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> made abundantly clear that maintenance French
                            economic and cultural presence North Vietnam not just <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> idea but clearly established
                            French Government position. General line reasoning advanced by <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> in support French position
                            paralleled our analysis set forth <gloss target="#t_Embtels1">Embtel</gloss> 3394.<note n="4" xml:id="d43fn4">Not found in
                                Department of State files.</note> French Government, <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> said, intends protect and maintain
                            to extent possible French interests in north. In their view, he said,
                            nothing would be gained if French withdrew, since Chinese or other
                            Communist technicians would be brought in to replace French and carry on
                            operation French industrial installations. On contrary, he said, it in
                            interest free world French remain, thereby lessening <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho</persName>’s dependence on Communist orbit.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> emphasized that Viet
                                <persName>Minh</persName> has made clear it desires French carry on
                            in north in contrast attitude <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government towards French in south and that French
                            believe Viet <persName>Minh</persName> prepared <pb facs="0122" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/> accept French technical guidance. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> said French Government did not see
                            contradiction we see in French approach toward North Vietnam on one hand
                            and south on other. He emphasized maintenance French economic and
                            cultural presence north had no political objective such as French
                            assistance given South Vietnamese Government which designed support
                            latter government and help it win elections. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> pointed out French position towards two zones
                            Vietnam not inconsistent with Geneva settlement.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> insisted that basis for
                            compromise could be found once US gained full appreciation French
                            position. In specific reference points contained paragraph 4<note n="5" xml:id="d43fn5">In this paragraph, the Embassy was instructed to
                                inform the French that the Department did not believe that these
                                mixed companies would qualify as “western installations” and thus be
                                exempt from restrictions of the Paris Consultative Group (of which
                                France was a member) set up to control trade of strategic materials
                                with Communist countries.</note> Department telegram 2846, <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> expressed hope we would not
                            consider such measures until matter fully explored. With respect
                            reference <persName corresp="#p_EGPHR1">Ely</persName> in paragraph 1
                            Department telegram 2846, <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName>
                            made clear in polite way that French approach North Vietnam fell outside
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGPHR1">General Ely</persName>’s
                            jurisdiction.</p>
                        <p>We underlined at length to <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName>
                            that we considered maintenance French economic interests and cultural
                            influences in north in fundamental contradiction free world effort
                            support South Vietnam, and that problem facing us extended beyond scope
                            terms any formula that might be worked out with Viet
                                <persName>Minh</persName> to continue French participation
                            industrial establishments in north.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> We feel conversation with <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName> confirmed lines our 3394 and
                            particularly our conclusions contained paragraph 4 that telegram. We
                            more than ever convinced French determined maintain French interests in
                            north and that we must approach immediate problem French proposal as
                            only one aspect fundamental problem whether we prepared accept basic
                            lines French approach North Vietnam. We continue believe, therefore,
                            that problem involved might be raised most effectively with French at
                            next ministerial level meeting <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss>. Re
                            final paragraph Department telegram 2846, we have concluded on basis our
                            contacts with French officials and parliamentarians that French policy
                            maintain French economic and cultural position North Vietnam has broad
                            support extending beyond <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>,
                            his entourage, his government, and that <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> only implementing, not making this policy.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_ATC1"><hi rend="strong">Achilles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>