<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile ( (Biddle) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-04-27T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-04-27T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-27T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-27T12:00:00-05:00" n="128"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d128">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.6111/9: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Biddle</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-27T19:00:00+02:00"
                            >April 27, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received April 27—6:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Polish Series 41. Reference my 34, April 24, 6 p.m. Raczynski states in
                    confidence that on April 21, 1942 he replied to note of April 17 from Foreign
                    Secretary Eden. Raczynski has not given me the text but states its main points
                    are: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Polish Government maintains that proposed Anglo-Russian Agreement if
                            concluded will prove detrimental to war effort of the United Nations.
                            Polish Government’s reservations are based on fundamental premises of a
                            moral nature which, it holds, are of utmost importance to United Nations
                            and which have recently been confirmed to representatives of Polish
                            Government by responsible leaders of American policy. Moreover, Polish
                            Government feels principles of Atlantic Charter can not be reconciled
                            with sacrifice of smaller states to interests of a powerful neighbor;
                            the British Government intended to safeguard these assurances in any
                            agreement which might be concluded with Russia;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>No territorial provisions detrimental to interests of Germany are
                            included in contemplated agreement. On the contrary agreement follows
                            along the line of German-Soviet Agreement of 1939 and might thus
                            possibly become a basis for German-Russian coalescence in the future.
                            Agreement would not commit Russian Government in relation to Germany in
                            that expansion of Russian possessions is to be brought about not at
                            expense of Germany but of third parties. The Russian Government would
                            thus retain a valuable trump card in relation to any German Government,
                            even the present one;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Regarding question of vital Polish interests, Polish Government
                            re-emphasizes importance it attaches to maintenance of Lithuania’s
                            independence and to retention of Bukovina within the central European
                            area where it belongs. These two conditions are essential to insure
                            independent existence and development of a confederative system in this
                            area;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Polish Government considers Britain has an inherent right to take an
                            active part in a future general European settlement and does not
                            particularly need Russia’s approval;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>There follows an analysis of the existing legal situation between
                            Britain and Poland in regard to Lithuania wherein is set forth the
                            Polish interpretation. As regards Bukovina, the point is emphasized that
                            Russian sovereignty over Bukovina would render vastly more difficult the
                            formation of a central European federation with the participation of
                            Rumania and Hungary;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Polish Government takes note of renewed confirmation of British
                            Government’s guarantee that in any case it does not propose to conclude
                            any agreement affecting or compromising the territorial status of
                            Poland;</item>
                        <pb facs="0151" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Polish Government’s attitude regarding the purport of the proposed
                            Anglo-Russian Agreement, as far as it is known to Polish Government, is
                            one of principle. Since the agreement is of fundamental importance to
                            Polish interests its conclusion would find the strongest echo among the
                            Poles in Poland and abroad. Polish opinion would expect an authoritative
                            interpretation both of the contents and significance of the agreement
                            and it would be impossible for Polish Government to refuse to satisfy
                            this expectation of the nation.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Commenting on the foregoing and in his yesterday’s conference with Mr. Churchill,
                    Sir Stafford Cripps and other British authorities, Raczynski said the following:
                    (1) that while Mr. Churchill stated his desire for an early agreement, Raczynski
                    gained the impression that he was being pushed by Cripps and others who shared
                    Cripps’ insistence for the agreement; that he spoke like a man forced by
                    circumstances and by pressure of his associates, to act contrary to his
                    principles; that he was loath to deviate therefrom; (2) the Polish Government
                    was now carefully weighing, in light of its potential consequences, the question
                    of lodging a vigorous protest, in addition to declaring to the Polish people an
                    interpretation of the contents and significance of the agreement (as mentioned
                    paragraph <hi rend="italic">g</hi> above) in event the contemplated agreement
                    were concluded. This action, he said would probably serve to rally the Poles to
                    Sikorski. At the same time however it would undoubtedly antagonize the Russians
                    and risk placing a severe strain on Anglo-Polish relations. He was well aware of
                    the delicacy of the situation and realized that this question called for the
                    most thoughtful consideration.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Biddle</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
