<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile ( (Biddle) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-11-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/25996</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Biddle</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">Polish Series No. 231</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-09">November 9,
                            1942</date>.<lb/>[Received November 24.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">For the President, the Secretary and the Under-Secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that in a very recent
                    talk with General Sikorski, he informed me he had just received two notes from
                    the Soviet Embassy.</p>
                <p>The first Note had stated in effect that the Soviet Government considered the
                    further recruiting of Polish soldiers in Russia out of the question, on the
                    grounds that the Polish troops in Russia had <pb facs="0204" n="198"
                        xml:id="pg_198"/> demonstrated not only their unwillingness to fight
                    alongside the Russians, but also their desire to leave the country.</p>
                <p>In imparting the foregoing, the General said that these grounds, as stated in the
                    Soviet Government’s Note, were erroneous, in that previous to the period refered
                    to the Polish Government had already requested equipment for the Polish troops
                    in Russia, in order that they might continue the struggle at the side of the
                    Russian forces. It had been only later that the Polish Government had decided to
                    ask the Soviet Government to permit the evacuation of the Polish forces.</p>
                <p>The second Note, the General continued, had stated that the 16 welfare delegates
                    of the Polish Embassy in Russia, who were still under arrest, were now awaiting
                    trial on the grounds of spying in behalf both of Britain and of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Immediately following the receipt of these two Notes, the General said, he had
                    been invited to attend a showing of a moving picture at the Soviet Embassy.
                    Feeling it would be undignified under the circumstances to attend, he had
                    invented a pretext to absent himself. However, several of his Ministers had
                    attended the showing of the picture. They had subsequently imparted to him their
                    surprise at finding that, in depicting several scenes in Lwow, the picture had
                    reflected marked credit on the Polish citizens.</p>
                <p>In taking into consideration the inconsistency of this friendly gesture with the
                    numerous unfriendly acts which Poland had been suffering at the hands of Russia,
                    the General was inclined at the moment to feel that Poland might expect Russia
                    to pursue two policies: one a “small policy” entailing annoyances; the other, a
                    “big policy” entailing an effort to show Poland and the rest of the world that
                    Russia was Poland’s friend. Contributing towards his feeling on this score was
                    his own appraisal as to Russia’s position after her struggle with the Germans:
                    he expected Russia to become so weakened by this struggle that it would be more
                    likely to give way to Western influence than the West to yield to Russian
                    penetration.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Drexel Biddle, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
