<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-25T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-25T13:00:00-05:00" n="295" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/19753:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-25T19:00:00+01:00">February
                                    25, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 11:21 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>355. My 330, February 21, 7 p.m.<note n="9" xml:id="d295fn9">Not
                                printed.</note> I had a talk yesterday afternoon with Mr. Boheman,
                            Secretary General of Foreign Office.</p>
                        <p>1. Referring to rumored German plan to attack Sweden Mr. Boheman said
                            there was nothing new of significance to point in this direction nor had
                            there been any specific German demands or threats in last few days. He
                            said however that Swedish Government continues to receive warnings from
                            many sources that something from Germany is in air against Sweden.
                            Majority of these warnings come from friends of Sweden in Germany.
                            Boheman is inclined to discount <pb facs="0336" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/> possibility of an Allied attack on Norway this year which would
                            perhaps offer most outstanding provocation to Germany for attacking
                            Sweden but he said pessimists in Swedish circles argue that whether
                            Germany takes seriously possibility of such an Allied attack or not, it
                            would have little effect on her decision to attack Sweden as in any case
                            she would desire for strategic reasons to forestall any Allied attack on
                            peninsula and have herself entrenched in Sweden before it came.
                            Referring to warnings received and to more pessimistic views Boheman
                            said that he personally did not “believe a word of it,” although obliged
                            to admit anything was possible from Germany.</p>
                        <p>Sweden of course is in as great a state of preparedness as she can put
                            herself. Military units on active service Boheman pointed out were
                            greatly reduced on account of difficulty of maintaining morale of large
                            numbers of troops under winter conditions when physical activities are
                            necessarily restricted. Large numbers of men are now being called into
                            service. Boheman said that numbers were no greater than intensified
                            spring and summer activities would justify although he said they are
                            being called up somewhat earlier than would ordinarily be case.
                            (Military Attaché is reporting on these figures to War Department.)</p>
                        <p>I mentioned to Boheman general trend of Swedish press comment on
                            possibility of Sweden being involved in war which has been comment for
                            past few days (my 341, February 24<note n="11" xml:id="d295fn11">Not
                                printed.</note> gives typical examples of this comment; see also my
                            340, February 24<note n="11" xml:id="d295fn15">Not printed.</note>).
                            Boheman said that line taken by press yesterday in particular was
                            directly inspired by Government and accurately stated Government’s
                            policy. In my view it also reflects accurately the will of the
                            overwhelming majority of the Swedes. He remarked that Sweden was made
                            neutral by sheer force of circumstances, that it would be quite
                            impossible to induce Swedish people to fight either Norway or Finland;
                            that to fight Norway would mean being first joined with Allies and that
                            to fight Finland would mean being first joined with Germany; that Sweden
                            could be made to fight either Norway or Finland only by being attacked
                            herself.</p>
                        <p>Although our conversation was on a most informal and friendly basis
                            Boheman emphatically stated that it was determination of Swedes to
                            resist by force any attack on their territory from whatever quarter it
                            came. He remarked incidentally that according to estimates of Germans
                            themselves, which were known in Sweden, 35 to 40 divisions are
                            considered least number which would be necessary for successful invasion
                            and occupation of this country.</p>
                        <p>Knowing that Schnurre<note n="12" xml:id="d295fn12">Karl Schnurre of the
                                Office of Trade Policy in the German Ministry for Foreign
                                Affairs.</note> had been in Sweden for past week without <pb facs="0337" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> publicity I asked Mr. Boheman
                            if there was anything he could tell me regarding purpose of his visit.
                            He replied that Schnurre had stopped in Sweden en route to Germany from
                            Finland where he had been negotiating a trade agreement; that he had
                            spent past week here with friends without seeing any officials; that on
                                Monday<note n="13" xml:id="d295fn13">February 23.</note> he made a
                            formal call at Foreign Office prior to his departure for Germany; that
                            he had not brought up anything new but had merely again asked question
                            which either he or German Legation asks every week or two—that is
                            whether Sweden is not ready to change her mind about various
                            controversial matters.</p>
                        <p>2. Toward end of our talk Boheman referred briefly to conditions in
                            Norway and to immense sympathies which Swedish people feel for
                            Norwegians under their present trials.</p>
                        <p>He was most critical of the “commando” raids by British at different
                            points on Norwegian coast; said that in his opinion they accomplished
                            nothing of value to Allies and that their only result was that on each
                            occasion Germans or their satellites found an excuse to kill all of good
                            Norwegians.</p>
                        <p>He also spoke in very disparaging terms of Sir Stafford Cripps<note n="14" xml:id="d295fn14">British Ambassador in the Soviet Union,
                                June 12, 1940–January 22, 1942; became Lord Privy Seal and Leader of
                                the House of Commons February 19, 1942; made speech at Bristol
                                February 9 on Soviet policy.</note> whose unfortunate speech of 2
                            weeks ago made a very bad impression here. Boheman met Cripps sometime
                            ago when he came through here and talked with him. He said that Cripps
                            was undoubtedly “intellectual” but in his view by no means “an
                            intelligent man”. Boheman also interpreted Stalin’s speech of 2 or 3
                            days ago as a direct reply to Cripps’ speech and directed to the world
                            as well as to his own people. He pointed out that Stalin had stated
                            Russia was fighting this war alone while Germany was helped by Allies,
                            and made no reference to Great Britain or United States or to material
                            aid these countries were giving Russia, that he expressly stated he had
                            no quarrel with German people and that Russia had no intention of
                            occupying German territory. Boheman was of opinion that Cripps’ speech
                            had not served purpose either of Great Britain or of Russia in any
                            direction.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>