<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="39" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/15907⅔</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-21">October 21,
                                1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: At the time of your
                            meeting with Mr. Churchill in August,<note n="9" xml:id="d39fn9">For
                                correspondence regarding the Atlantic Conference, see <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_341">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 341</ref> ff.</note> with your
                            approval I inquired of Sir Alexander Cadogan, for the information of
                            this Government, whether the British Government had entered into any
                            commitments or secret understandings covering territorial readjustments
                            after the close of the war. You will remember that some six weeks
                            previously you had sent a personal message to Mr. Churchill<note n="10" xml:id="d39fn10">See telegram No. 2600, July 14, 1941, 6 p.m., to
                                the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_342">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 342</ref>.</note> expressing the
                            opinion that <pb facs="0040" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/> the British
                            Government should make no secret commitments to any of its allies
                            without the knowledge of the United States or without the agreement of
                            the United States.</p>
                        <p>Sir Alexander Cadogan gave me the most specific and positive assurances
                            that the British Government had entered into no agreements and had made
                            no commitments which had to do with frontier or territorial
                            readjustments, with one possible exception. He stated that this one
                            exception was an oral statement made to the Government of Yugoslavia
                            prior to the Yugoslav <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> that the
                            British Government believed that at the conclusion of the war the
                            subject of the jurisdiction of Istria was a matter which might well come
                            up for reconsideration. He went on to say that this did not constitute
                            any firm commitment and added that no mention whatever had been made by
                            the British Government of either Gorizia or Trieste.</p>
                        <p>Sir Alexander Cadogan further stated that, should the British Government
                            at any future time intend to make any commitments of this character, the
                            Government of the United States would be advised prior to the making of
                            such commitments.</p>
                        <p>I received yesterday a letter from Lord Halifax under date of October 18
                            which contains a message to me from Sir Alexander Cadogan. I am
                            enclosing a copy thereof for your information.<note n="11" xml:id="d39fn11">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Unless you see some objection I propose in reply merely to state that
                            this Government has taken due note of the contents of this message and
                            that we have no comment to offer and no suggestions to make.</p>
                        <p>As you know, the treatment by the Italians of the Senussis has been
                            shocking and, from the standpoint of humanity alone, a statement of the
                            kind proposed by the British Government would seem to me to be one which
                            would be welcomed by public opinion everywhere.</p>
                        <p>I shall appreciate it if you will let me have your views.<note n="12" xml:id="d39fn12">Notation on original: “SW OK FDR”.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Believe me [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>