<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-10T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-10T09:00:00-05:00" n="395" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d395">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/24791:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Kuibyshev</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>)</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-10T17:00:00+03:00">October 10, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received October; 12—4:10 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>874. Embassy’s 1369, July 17, 6 p.m., 1941;<note n="35" xml:id="d395fn35">
                                <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_630">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 630</ref>; this telegram
                                reported the latest re-institution of military, or political,
                                commissars. See also telegram No. 1011, August. 13, 1940, from
                                Moscow, <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_211">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 211</ref>; and <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_377">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, The Soviet Union, 1933–1939, p.
                                    377</ref>, footnote 22, <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_519">p.
                                    519</ref>, footnote 13, and <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_746">p.
                                    746</ref>, footnote 27.</note> and <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_729">729</ref>, September 1, 11 a.m.
                                1942.<note n="36" xml:id="d395fn36">Not printed.</note> The local
                            paper of today publishes a ukase<note n="37" xml:id="d395fn37">The ukase
                                was dated October 9, 1942.</note> of the <pb facs="0468" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the U. S. S. R.
                            abolishing the Institution of Military Commissars and Political Workers
                            “in all regiments and divisions, staff units, military academies and
                            institutions of the Red Army at both the front and the rear.”</p>
                        <p>The preamble to the ukase states that during the period of the civil war
                            which followed the revolution it had been considered necessary to
                            inaugurate the system of military commissars in the Red Army because of
                            lack of confidence in old officers “who at that time did not believe in
                            the firmness of Soviet power or were even alien to it”. It is pointed
                            out that during this period the military commissars played a decisive
                            role in the strengthening of the Red Army in the selection of officers
                            in the political education of the army and in instilling of military
                            discipline.</p>
                        <p>The preamble goes on to say that in the years following the civil war the
                            position of officers in the Red Army changed fundamentally as a result
                            of their “further growth and education and also under the influence of
                            the successes and victories of the Soviet system in all spheres of
                            life”. It states that the present struggle has hardened the officers of
                            the Red Army and has developed a very large group of new and talented
                            officers who are experienced in battle and fully faithful to their
                            military duty and the honor of their rank. The officers of the Red Army
                            have proved in battle their devotion to the fatherland and have grown in
                            military and political stature.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, it continues, the military commissars and political
                            workers have improved their military knowledge so that already some of
                            them have become military officers in actual command of troops. Many
                            others can also be used. The preamble concludes by stating that these
                            circumstances indicate that the basis for the existence of the system of
                            military commissars has completely disappeared and that furthermore the
                            continued existence of this system can operate as a brake on the
                            improvement of troop administration and may also place the commissars in
                            a false position. Accordingly the system is abolished.</p>
                        <p>The ukase establishes complete unity of command and vests it in the
                            military officers who are given full responsibility for the military and
                            political life of each unit, does away with the system of military
                            commissars and political workers in the Red Army and provides that they
                            shall be made “assistant officers” to the military officers at present
                            in command of given units. It also provides for the systematic transfer
                            of additional political officers to the status of military officers.</p>
                        <p>An order of the Commissariat for Defense is likewise published <pb facs="0469" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> implementing the foregoing
                            ukase and setting up courses of military training for political
                            officers.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>