<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-11-08T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-11-08T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec1b9eda462a0d1d1" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="axis-powers">Axis powers</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-08T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-08T15:00:00-05:00" n="410"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/11963: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-08T23:00:00+03:00"
                            >November 8, 1942—11 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 9—11:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>438. 1. The outstanding feature of the celebration of the 25th anniversary of the
                    revolution was Stalin’s speech of November 6, a brief summary of which has been
                    telegraphed to the Department from Kuibyshev. It is assumed that the full text
                    is available to the Department. The Embassy’s own translation will be sent by
                    mail.</p>
                <p>2. It is apparent that in his speech Stalin endeavored to give his Soviet
                    listeners the impression that Soviet agriculture and industry are functioning
                    satisfactorily; that the Red Army has been conducting defensive and offensive
                    operations against the German coalition in a manner which the army of no other
                    state could equal; and that the sole reason for the successes of the German
                    armies during the past summer has been the absence of a second front in Europe.
                    The concensus of foreign observers here is that those sections of the speech
                    which touched on the second front were worded in such a mariner as, without
                    giving undue offence to Russia’s allies, to cause the Russian’ people to blame
                    Soviet military reverses on the absence of such a front rather than upon errors
                    or miscalculations on the part of the Soviet leaders.</p>
                <p>Both Lozovsky<note n="57" xml:id="d410fn57">Solomon Abramovich Lozovsky,
                        Assistant People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs.</note> and Zarubin<note
                        n="58" xml:id="d410fn58">Georgy Nikolayevich Zarubin, Chief of the American
                        Section of the Commissariat for Foreign Affairs.</note> pressed me yesterday
                    for my opinion as to the manner in which Stalin’s reference to the second front
                    might be received in the United States. I told Lozovsky that I was confident
                    that the American Government and American people would understand Stalin’s
                    position and would certainly not take offense at his intimation that Russian
                    reverses were due to the absence of a second front. I said that Americans
                    appreciate plain speaking and do not object to criticism of a frank nature,
                    provided such criticism is not made in sarcastic vein or in such a manner as to
                    question the good intentions or the integrity of the American Government or
                    people.</p>
                <p>3. Stalin’s insistence in the latter part of his speech that close cooperation is
                    possible among the United States, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union, and that
                    there has been a progressive improvement in the relations of these three
                    countries did much, it is believed, to soften the criticism for the failure of
                    an establishment of a second front. His comparison of the aims and resources of
                    the Allies with those of the Axis Powers as well as his delineation of the tasks
                    of the Soviet Union should be extremely useful in connection with the conducting
                        <pb facs="0482" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> of Allied propaganda not only in
                    the Allied and neutral countries but also in Germany and Italy.</p>
                <p>4. Among the omissions in his speech the following are of particular interest:
                        (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) No reference to the Far East or to the fact that
                    there is a war in the Pacific. (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) No mention of
                    countries other than Great Britain and the United States as Soviet allies and
                    reference to the United Nations as such. Some of the United Nations of the
                    European continent were mentioned but merely as occupied countries. (<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) No acknowledgment of material or other aid to the
                    Soviet Union from the United States or Great Britain, (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)
                    No accusation that Great Britain and the United States had failed to live up to
                    their obligations. (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) No reference to the international
                    revolutionary movement or to religious questions. (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) No
                    mention of the military contribution of the United States and Great Britain
                    other than a comment on the small number of German and Italian troops in
                    Egypt.</p>
                <p>5. Although Stalin could have given more credit to other United Nations for their
                    contribution to the war effort without detracting from the accomplishments of
                    the Soviet Union, it is nevertheless felt, here in diplomatic circles and by
                    those Soviet officials with whom members of the Embassy have discussed the
                    speech, that it represents another step forward in the direction of closer
                    cooperation between the Soviet Union and its allies.<note n="59"
                        xml:id="d410fn59">The Chargé further reported in telegram No. 440 of
                        November 9, 1942, that in Kuibyshev “during the whole celebration we sensed
                        a feeling of restored confidence. The general attitude seemed to be that the
                        worst strain was over; the Germans had finally been halted; winter was
                        coming to the rescue; and at least by spring help would be forthcoming from
                        the western Allies.” (861.00/11964)</note> I believe and already have
                    received indications that Soviet officials are interpreting the speech as a
                    directive for the display of greater friendliness toward the United States and
                    Great Britain.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
