<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Standley) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-05-07T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-05-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-05-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-05-07T09:00:00-05:00" n="459"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d459">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/21469: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Standley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kuibyshev</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Moscow</hi>)</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1942-05-07T17:00:00+03:00">May 7, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 8—8:01 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>370. I have received a telegram dated May 4 from the Moscow Embassy reading as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>107, May 4, 2 p.m. For the Ambassador from Faymonville. If you approve
                            please transmit the following message.</p>
                        <p>“For Hopkins from Faymonville. President’s broadcast April 30<note n="6"
                                xml:id="d459fn6">An address to the nation was broadcast by President
                                Roosevelt on April 28, 1942. A partial text is in the Department of
                                State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May 2, 1942, p. 381, and the
                                full text is in the <hi rend="italic">Congressional Record</hi>,
                                vol. 88, pt. 9, p. A1583.</note> was well translated by Soviet
                            press. Effect was immediate and highly favorable. President’s
                            description of heroic bomber flight appealed powerfully to Soviet public
                            and brought congratulations and enthusiastic praise from Government
                            officials, soldiers and civilians. Accounts of American exploits which
                            may be filling all <pb facs="0561" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> American
                            press seldom reach the Soviet public unless they are restated with
                            approval by American [<hi rend="italic">Soviet</hi>] leaders. Similarly,
                            American appreciation of Soviet exploits is made known to Soviet
                            citizens almost exclusively through Soviet reprints of remarks by
                            distinguished Americans. Comments by Admiral Standley and Bill Batt<note
                                n="7" xml:id="d459fn7">William L. Batt, Director, Materials
                                Division, War Production Board; later, Vice Chairman of the
                                Board.</note> on Soviet achievements were widely quoted here.
                            Continued references by our leaders to heroic-American and Soviet
                            exploits will do much to build up and sustain confidence here and will
                            help to counteract the disappointment felt over failure to establish a
                            second front. Such reports will receive wide and very desirable
                            publicity especially if we can at the same time give to Soviet
                            Government officials solid and encouraging facts on American production
                            and Lend-Lease shipments”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The subject matter of this telegram is purely political and has little bearing on
                    Lend-Lease or supply questions and I feel that it would have been more
                    appropriate for Faymonville to have addressed to me for such unspecified use as
                    I might see fit, the comments on American-Soviet political relations contained
                    therein. I believe, however, that it would be inexpedient for me to withhold or
                    alter the message and I am therefore forwarding it to the Department for
                    transmission to Mr. Hopkins if the Department so desires. At the same time, I am
                    addressing the following telegram to Faymonville: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I appreciate receiving your views on American-Soviet political
                            relations, to which in general I subscribe, and am forwarding your
                            message to the Secretary of State with the suggestion that he may desire
                            to transmit; it to Mr. Hopkins. I am inclined to feel, however, that it
                            might be preferable in the future for you to address any information
                            which might come to your attention concerning the political relations
                            between the United States and the Soviet Union, or any views which you
                            may have on this subject, to me alone for such unspecified use as I may
                            deem appropriate. This is in accordance with my interpretation of the
                            understanding reached with McCabe<note n="8" xml:id="d459fn8">Thomas B.
                                McCabe, Deputy Lend-Lease Administrator.</note> as reported to you
                            in his message of March 23. I value your judgment and experience in such
                            matters and shall always be glad to receive from you any information or
                            comments you may desire to furnish me on this important subject.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I may state that in general I concur in the views expressed by Faymonville and
                    feel sure that he has accurately portrayed the views expressed to him by his
                    limited Soviet contacts but has possibly misconstrued these views as
                    representing the views of the public in general. The Soviet press did give
                    prominence to the President’s speech: referred to, but the press in this country
                    usually gives wide coverage to statements of friendly foreign statesmen,
                    especially when such statements contain favorable references to the Soviet
                    Union. There <pb facs="0562" n="556" xml:id="pg_556"/> has been no perceptible
                    change in this general policy in the present instance.</p>
                <p>I should appreciate receiving the Department’s comments on this telegram.<note
                        n="9" xml:id="d459fn9">
                        <p>A memorandum to the Secretary of State dated May 11, 1942, written by Loy
                            W. Henderson, Assistant Chief of the Division of European Affairs, and
                            signed by Ray Atherton, Acting Chief of this Division, read as
                            follows:</p>
                        <p>“We believe that the Ambassador should have our full support in his
                            efforts to centralize through him political reporting from the Soviet
                            Union and the carrying on of conversations of political import in the
                            Soviet Union between American and Soviet officials.</p>
                        <p>“We feel that if we should fail to give the Ambassador full support in
                            this instance his prestige would suffer to such an extent that his
                            usefulness in the Soviet Union would be materially affected.”</p>
                        <p>By telegram No. 219, May 11, Secretary Hull answered the Ambassador’s
                            request: “I fully approve of the action taken by you. The message
                            addressed to Hopkins was sent on to him.”</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Standley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
