<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Standley) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-22T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-22T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-22T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-22T11:00:00-05:00" n="505"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/23048: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Standley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kuibyshev</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Moscow</hi>)</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1942-07-22T19:00:00+03:00">July 22, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 23—6:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>629. Personal for the Secretary. Your 351, July 17, 6 p.m.<note n="98"
                        xml:id="d505fn98">Not printed, but see footnote 95, <ref target="#pg_609">p.
                            609</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Molotov made no such remarks to me as he is reported to have made to Clark
                        Kerr in the latter’s report to Eden. While it is, of course, quite possible
                        that Molotov may have expressed himself “subjectively” to Clark Kerr at the
                        luncheon on June 26 in the manner reported, I did not hear any such
                        remarks.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In my telegram No. 201, June 22, 7 p.m., from Moscow, I endeavored to make
                        clear the attitude with respect to a second front in Europe in 1942 which
                        has been assumed by Molotov in our conversations. As was pointed out in that
                        telegram and also in others (see in this connection Nos. 529, June 15, 2
                            p.m.,<note n="99" xml:id="d505fn99">Not printed.</note> 548, June 19, 5
                        p.m., and 551, June 20, noon),<note n="1" xml:id="d505fn1">For telegram No.
                            551, see <ref target="#pg_445">p. 445</ref>.</note> the confidence of
                        the Soviet people in the early establishment of a second front, as well as
                        their growing impatience at its failure to materialize, has been strongly
                        reflected in the Soviet press, [and] has been a principal feature in such
                        conversations as members of my staff have had with Soviet citizens in recent
                        weeks.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I am prepared to believe, however, that both Molotov and Stalin are fully
                        cognizant of the difficulties attendant upon the opening of a second front
                        and of the specific reservations which the summary of Eden’s letter to
                        Winant indicates were attached to the forecast of future possibilities. You
                        will recall that as I reported at the time Stalin remarked in my
                        conversation with him on July 2nd that wanting a second front and having one
                        were two different things. The possibility <pb facs="0619" n="613"
                            xml:id="pg_613"/> should also not be excluded that although the
                        limitations in regard to the establishment of a second front were clearly
                        understood by the Soviet Government it nonetheless decided that it would be
                        sound strategy to endeavor to create the impression at home and abroad that
                        such a front would actually materialize in Europe in 1942. It may have
                        reasoned further that should the second front not materialize it would thus
                        find itself in a better bargaining position vis-à-vis England and the United
                        States in any future political negotiations having to do with post-war
                        problems and frontiers. Although Molotov has never given me any indications
                        that this was the case I think it must be borne in mind.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I have been handicapped in my conversations with Stalin and Molotov and in
                        my interpretation of their attitudes and policies by the fact that I have
                        never been fully informed of what took place or of what commitments may have
                        been made to Molotov while he was in London and Washington; There is no
                        doubt, however, that popular, belief in the establishment of a second front
                        in Europe in 1942 has been fostered by the joint communiqués then issued and
                        by other public statements, irrespective of the intent behind them.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The British Ambassador called on me day before yesterday and informed me
                        in general terms of his conversation with Molotov on July 4. What he said
                        was in close agreement with the summary contained in the Department’s
                        reference telegram. In response to my inquiry he stated that insofar as he
                        was aware no steps had been taken by Molotov to correct any misunderstanding
                        that may exist in regard to this matter.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I feel that I should recall to the notice of the Department at this time
                        the fact that all the negotiations leading up to Molotov’s visit to London
                        (in this respect see my telegram No. 374, May 8, 5 p.m.,<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d505fn2">Not printed.</note> and other related messages) were
                        based on the firmly expressed intention of the Soviet Government to obtain
                        recognition by Great Britain of the Soviet frontiers of 1941. The fact that
                        Molotov returned from London with a treaty which ostensibly disregarded this
                        formerly believed vital and almost sole demand of the Soviet Government
                        obviously lends itself to the interpretation that in return for its
                        reliquishment some other equally desirable objective was obtained. In the
                        light of the communiqués issued and in the absence of information to the
                        contrary the assumption was logical that this objective was the
                        establishment of a second front in 1942.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>If there is little possibility of the opening of the second front this
                        year I believe that any public disavowal in that sense would be extremely
                        unwise, having in mind the inevitable and potentially far-reaching
                        repercussions of such a course now, not only in the Soviet <pb facs="0620"
                            n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/> Union but also elsewhere. Should it be desired
                        to correct any false impression which may have been created I consider that
                        this should only be done directly and privately to Molotov or Stalin.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Standley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
