<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-09-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="533" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d533">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.33/8</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                State</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-09-09">September 9, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Soviet Ambassador called at his request. He said that his Government
                            desired to transfer six submarines from Vladivostok to Russian ports in
                            the Archangel–Murmansk area, and that they would have to come through
                            the Panama Canal, stopping at given places within the United States
                            jurisdiction in order to replenish supplies, et cetera, et cetera. He
                            said he desired to inquire if it would be agreeable with this Government
                            to cooperate in getting these submarines through the Canal and also in
                            furnishing supplies wherever it might be deemed necessary for the
                            submarines to put into port.</p>
                        <p>I replied without hesitation that I was sure that everyone in this
                            Government would be delighted to cooperate in every feasible respect and
                            that I would see that this request of his Government was given prompt
                                attention.<note n="53" xml:id="d533fn53">The Navy Department
                                expressed its agreement in a letter of September 14, 1942, from
                                Secretary of the Navy Frank Knox, and the War Department did
                                likewise in a letter of September 15 from Secretary of War Henry L.
                                Stimson (861.3311/46, 45).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Some reference was made to the Japanese-Siberian situation and the
                            Ambassador promptly spoke with confidence and said that he did not think
                            there was any probability of an attack on Siberia.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ull</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>