<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-13T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-13T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-13T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-13T07:00:00-05:00" n="540"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">196.6/1438: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kuibyshev</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Moscow</hi>)</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1942-10-13T15:00:00+03:00">October 13, 1942—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 14—7:29 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>881. Reference Department’s 384, August 4, 4 p.m. Zarubin informed me that steps
                    have been taken to abolish the practice of giving bonuses or gratuities to
                    American sailors entering Soviet Arctic ports. <pb facs="0661" n="655"
                        xml:id="pg_655"/> He said that the Soviet Government in view of existing
                    currency legislation could not, however, furnish rubles to American sailors at
                    diplomatic rates of exchange or at any other than the official rates.</p>
                <p>Since the Soviet authorities were genuinely anxious to alleviate conditions they
                    were considering the advisability of furnishing gratis rubles to American
                    merchant officers and seamen arriving in northern ports, rubles in limited fixed
                    amounts which could be used as spending money. For instance, they might give
                    each officer a thousand rubles and each seaman three or four hundred rubles. Any
                    rubles which might be needed in addition should be purchased at official rates.
                    Zarubin said that he felt that this arrangement would not be subjected to the
                    objections which applied to the bonus which was in American dollars—since the
                    rubles would represent merely spending money and would have little or no value
                    outside the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>At his request I promised to inquire whether arrangements of the kind tentatively
                    proposed by him would be objected to by the American Government.<note n="92"
                        xml:id="d540fn92">Rear Adm. Emory S. Land, War Shipping Administrator, was
                        informed of this proposal by Assistant Secretary of State Breckinridge Long
                        in a letter of October 27, 1942, and his opinion of this arrangement
                        requested. The letter had been shown to Ambassador Standley, who was in
                        Washington, and who concurred.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[Ambassador Standley made his report on the problems and difficulties
                        encountered in the Soviet Union to President Roosevelt, in the presence of
                        Harry Hopkins, on October 22, 1942. No record of this meeting has been found
                        in Department files, or at the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N.
                        Y. The Ambassador’s own description of this conversation is printed in his
                        book, <hi rend="italic">Admiral Ambassador to Russia</hi>, pages
                        306–310.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
