<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d700</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">700</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="700"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d700">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.00/1408</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-08-05">August 5,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Minister of Yugoslavia called to see me this afternoon at his request. The
                    Minister gave me a series of telegrams, which are attached herewith, sent by
                    General Mihajlović to the Prime Minister <pb facs="0813" n="807" xml:id="pg_807"
                    /> of Yugoslavia.<note n="13" xml:id="d700fn13">Slobodan Jovanovich.</note> The
                    Minister said he believed that these telegrams would be of interest to this
                    Government and even to the President. I said I would be very glad to transmit a
                    copy of these messages to the President for his information.</p>
                <p>The Minister spoke briefly with regard to the difficulties which he was
                    constantly encountering in the United States from Communist sympathizers among
                    the Slovene and Croatian elements in the United States. He called my attention
                    specifically to the fact that the <hi rend="italic">Daily Worker</hi>
                    <note n="14" xml:id="d700fn14">Communist newspaper.</note> in New York a few
                    days ago had published an article asserting that the Yugoslav free radio station
                    (which the Minister stated did not exist) had proclaimed that the Yugoslavs
                    desired to identify themselves with the Soviet Union and that General Mihajlović
                    was a Fascist and a traitor. The Minister said this article had immediately been
                    republished in the Communist inclined portions of the Croatian press in the
                    United States. The Minister stated that these facts were all the more remarkable
                    inasmuch as up to ten days ago the <hi rend="italic">Daily Worker</hi> had
                    almost daily published a photograph of General Mihajlovic under headlines
                    proclaiming him as the great leader of the southern Slav forces of resistance
                    against Hitler. The Minister said the telegrams he had handed me would give
                    further indications of the campaign being conducted within Serbia by Communist
                    elements against General Mihajlović.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-05-26">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">May</hi> 26</date>, No. 209.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The President of the Yugoslav Government</hi>:</p>
                    <p>Last fall I received the communication from the British Government that we
                        have to fight for Yugoslavia and not to allow a Communist uprising for
                        Soviet Russia. I repeat the Communists are hated by the people on account of
                        the terror placed on their people. The people are against them and soon we
                        will see their end. Serbia, Sandjak and Eastern Bosnia have been liberated
                        from them and now in Montenegro there is a general uprising against them. I
                        repeat the people themselves have taken care to liquidate the Communists and
                        now Montenegro does the same. Last fall Captain Hudson<note n="15"
                            xml:id="d700fn15">Presumably Capt. Austin U. M. Hudson, British Civil
                            Lord of Admiralty, 1939–42.</note> has prevented the sending of supplies
                        which brought us to a very difficult crisis and I am afraid that this will
                        be repeated on account of the incomprehension of my situation. I cannot give
                        a serious blow to the enemy unless I receive arms and munitions. You may be
                        sure that all the people here stand with me and the Yugoslav Army.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mihajlović</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0814" n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-06">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 6</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The President of the Yugoslav Government</hi>:</p>
                    <p>The people in Montenegro and Sandjak in their general uprising against the
                        Communists have entirely cleaned two regions. The people have been provoked
                        by the incredible terror of the Communists who have killed thousands of
                        Nationalists. I have received photographs and documents of their atrocities.
                        I am proceeding now to the reorganization of those regions.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mihajlović</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-06">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 6</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Serbia has been completely organized. All the commanders are at their
                        respective posts. Have developed radio network for communication. From the
                        region of Leskovac and Vranje our organizations are pushing towards South
                        Serbia where young recruits are fleeing the Bulgarian army and joining my
                        detachments.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mihajlović</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-06">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 6</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In Bosnia, mountain of Majovica, my detachments have beaten the ustashis and
                        captured four guns. The ustashis have fled towards Serbia but they have been
                        supported by the Germans. In the region of Bosnia the action of chetniks is
                        going on. Hercegovina is now, unfortunately, subjected to a Communistic
                        terror. It seems that all our provinces have to go through this terror which
                        brings the revolt and finally the liberation. You may be sure that we will
                        be united for the final hour but we need arms and munition.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mihajlović</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>[Other telegrams, not printed, related to matters other than Communist
                            activities.]</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
