<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d718</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">718</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="718"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d718">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.00/1421<hi rend="superscript">4/8</hi>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-14">December 14,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Ambassador of Yugoslavia called to see me this morning and left with me the
                    documents attached herewith,<note n="46" xml:id="d718fn46">Not printed.</note>
                    which are self-explanatory. They all have to do with the present status of
                    General Mihailovich and the increasing evidences of Soviet-inspired propaganda
                    for the purpose of diminishing the prestige of General Mihailovich and in order
                    to make it appear that the real resistance now going on in Yugoslavia is due to
                    the “Partisans” and not to the forces under the command of General
                    Mihailovich.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador alleges that the immediate purpose of this propaganda is to try to
                    force the Allied Governments, when the time comes to undertake an invasion of
                    Yugoslavia, to deal with the commanding forces of the Partisans rather than with
                    the legitimate authorities under the control of General Mihailovich.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador stated that the British Eighth Army, under the command of General
                        Alexander,<note n="47" xml:id="d718fn47">Gen. Sir Harold R. L. Alexander,
                        Commander in Chief of the British Forces In the Middle East.</note> has five
                    liaison officers directly in daily contact with General Mihailovich who are
                    reporting every day to the British high command the resistance movements
                    undertaken by General Mihailovich. He also stated that the British are in
                    continuous contact with these forces by submarine and that the supplies in the
                    possession of General Mihailovich’s forces come in part from North Africa by
                    means of submarine. He insists that this Government must be in full possession
                    of these facts and that it would, therefore, be in the highest degree useful,
                    from the standpoint of the Government of Yugoslavia, if the President or the
                    Secretary of State, at a press conference, could make some statement with regard
                    to the effective military resistance kept up for so long a time and under such
                    desperately difficult circumstances by General Mihailovich—a statement along the
                    lines of those recently made by Mr. Eden in London and by General Alexander
                    through a message which he sent to General Mihailovich.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador we would give the most friendly consideration to the points
                    which he had raised.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
