<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1088</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1088</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="1088" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1088">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5123/9–847</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 980</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-08">September 8,
                            1947</date>.<lb/>[Received September 18.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Ambassador has the honor to forward a copy of a self-explanatory third person
                    note dated August 21, 1947 from the Embassy to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                    concerning certain provisions of the Income Tax Law—and the Regulations for the
                    Enforcement of the Income Tax Law—which the Embassy considers discriminatory
                    against foreign business having head offices abroad with branches in China and
                    subject to the income tax. There is also enclosed a copy of a similar note on
                    the same subject dated August 18, 1947, despatched to the Ministry of Foreign
                    Affairs by the British Embassy, Nanking.<note n="1" xml:id="d1088fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> Notes on this subject have recently also been sent to the
                    Ministry by the Netherlands Embassy and the Swiss Legation.</p>
                <p>For a number of months the Embassy has received strong objections on the part of
                    American business groups in Shanghai and elsewhere to the discriminatory nature
                    of the tax law. The American Chamber of Commerce made representations on this
                    subject to the Consulate General in Shanghai, as reported in the Consulate
                    General’s despatch no. 210 dated May 9, 1947 to the Embassy, a copy of which was
                    sent the Department.<note n="1" xml:id="d1088fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In discussing the discriminatory and conflicting provisions of the Income Tax Law
                    and Regulations with officials of the Direct Tax Bureau of the Ministry of
                    Finance, the officials have pointed out the difficulties of fairly and equitably
                    determining for tax purposes the capital of branches of foreign companies doing
                    business in China. They have stated their inability to see any discrimination in
                    the law. While, however, there may be a few Chinese firms with head offices
                    abroad and branches in China, making them subject to the same treatment as
                    foreign firms, their number is considered proportionately so small as to make
                    the administration of the law, in effect, discriminatory.</p>
                <pb facs="1373" n="1363" xml:id="pg_1363"/>
                <p>In the most recent conversation on this subject with tax officials, an officer of
                    the Embassy was informed that in January 1948 a revised Income Tax Law would be
                    promulgated and that this law would combine the two categories—1A and 1B—to
                    which objection is presently raised. It was stated that this new law, by
                    effecting such a merger, would eliminate the problem at issue. It is to be hoped
                    that this adjustment will be forthcoming, and the Embassy will attempt to remind
                    tax officials from time to time of its expectations in the matter.</p>
                <p>Despite these reported forthcoming adjustments, the Embassy considered it
                    advisable to despatch the enclosed note to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. As
                    soon as a response from the Ministry is received the Department will be
                    informed. It would be appreciated if copies of this despatch and of its
                    enclosures might be made available to the Commerce and Treasury Departments.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Embassy</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Chinese Ministry for Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1095</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Embassy of the United States of America presents its compliments to the
                        Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of China and has the honor to
                        refer to the Revised Income Tax Law of China, promulgated and enforced as of
                        April 16, 1946, and to the Regulations for the enforcement of that law
                        promulgated and enforced July 3, 1946. It has been brought to the attention
                        of the Embassy that the provisions of this Law and its Regulations may lead,
                        in their application, to inequality or discrimination as between companies
                        having their head offices abroad and doing business in China through
                        branches, and companies having their head offices in and doing business in
                        China.</p>
                    <p>Under Article 4 of the above mentioned Regulations, a limited liability
                        company with its head office outside the territory of the Republic of China
                        and carrying on business in China through branches is liable to income tax
                        on its profits earned in China according to the rates laid down in Article 6
                        of the Income Tax Law. On the other hand, a limited liability company with
                        its head office inside the territory of the Republic of China is taxed
                        according to the rates laid down in Article 5 of the Income Tax Law. The
                        result of such provisions is that companies having head offices in China are
                        taxed at a rate determined by the ratio of their income in a particular year
                        to their capital, while branches in China of companies having head offices
                        abroad are taxed simply on their net income, without reference to the
                        capital investment involved.</p>
                    <p>Such a split in the application of the income tax to companies <pb facs="1374" n="1364" xml:id="pg_1364"/> which in some cases may differ
                        only in the location of their head offices appears to the Embassy to be in
                        itself discriminatory. Also, while a Chinese company and a branch in China
                        of a foreign company might have identical organizational structures as
                        defined in Article 2, Category I (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and be otherwise
                        the same, and have identical income, they would not pay the same tax; under
                        the Income Tax Law itself two such companies would fall into the same tax
                        category, but because of the Regulations the foreign company would be taxed
                        as if it were a Category I (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) company. Furthermore,
                        it would appear that in a highly inflationary situation such as exists in
                        China today companies taxed according to the ratio of profits to capital
                        could reduce the burden of their income tax by an upward adjustment of
                        declared capital, while those taxed according to their net income can make
                        no adjustment to reduce the burden, which makes the law appear also
                        discriminatory in effect.</p>
                    <p>The Sino-American Treaty of 1943 for the Relinquishment of Extraterritorial
                        Rights in China and the Regulation of Related Matters<note n="2" xml:id="d1088fn3">Signed at Washington, January 11, 1943; Department of
                            State Treaty Series No. 984, or 57 Stat. (pt. 2) 767.</note> provides
                        that foreign nationals will be accorded national treatment in matters
                        relating to the levying of taxes or requirements in connection therewith—i.
                        e. foreign nationals taxable by the Government of China will be taxed on the
                        same basis as Chinese. This provision is contained in the second sentence of
                        Article V of the Treaty which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“…<note n="3" xml:id="d1088fn4">Omission indicated in the original
                                    note.</note> Each of the two Governments will endeavor to have
                                accorded in territory under its jurisdiction to nationals of the
                                other country, in regard to all legal proceedings, and to matters
                                relating to the administration of justice, and to the levying of
                                taxes or requirements in connection therewith, treatment not less
                                favorable than that accorded to its own nationals.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">It would appear that the collection of income tax in
                        accordance with present regulations is in contravention of assurances given
                        in the Treaty regarding taxation.</p>
                    <p>The Embassy understands that according to Chinese law, administrative
                        by-laws, rules, detailed rules, or measures cannot alter, modify, amend or
                        conflict with statutes. Article 4 of the Regulations for the Enforcement of
                        the Income Tax Law appears to conflict with the provisions of the Law itself
                        in that the Regulations provide for a different basis of taxation for
                        foreign as compared with Chinese corporations, a distinction apparently not
                        contemplated in the Income Tax Law.</p>
                    <p>This matter has for some time caused concern among American <pb facs="1375" n="1365" xml:id="pg_1365"/> and other foreign companies doing business
                        in China which are affected by the provisions of the Income Tax Law and has
                        been brought to the attention of the Embassy a number of times by them and
                        by the American Consulate General in Shanghai. The Embassy is thus now
                        obliged to seek from the Chinese Government, on behalf of American
                        businesses operating in China and on behalf of the Government of the United
                        States, either a clarifying and explanatory statement which will serve to
                        meet the seemingly valid objections of numerous concerned groups to the
                        current provisions of Income Tax Regulations, or assurances that steps will
                        be taken to revise the provisions of the Law and its Regulations to which
                        objections have been raised.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>, August 21, 1947.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
