<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-27T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-27T04:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6–2747: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-27T18:00:00+09:00">June 27,
                                    1947—6 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received June 27—12:33 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1412. Following is Shanghai’s 1144 of June 26, 5 p.m. just received:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mayor K. C. Wu, during dinner conversation 25th with visiting
                                    American publishers of <hi rend="italic">Round World
                                    Flight</hi>, stated that China now has conclusive proof that
                                    Chinese Communists using several divisions of Korean troops
                                    trained in North Korea and six divisions of Communist forces
                                    trained by Russians in Russia. Mayor stated Chinese had
                                    confessions of captured soldiers to prove these facts and that
                                    there was no doubt China was fighting third world war on behalf
                                    of US. He asked if it would take second Pearl Harbor to arouse
                                    Americans to their danger.</p>
                                <p>All publishers at table—Mrs. Ogden Reid, Mrs. Oveta Hobby,
                                    Gardner Cowles, Marshall Field and Roy Howard—disagreed Mayor’s
                                    last statement. Cowles asked Mayor why American correspondents
                                    knew nothing of the Russian and Korean-trained forces fighting
                                    with the Communists. Mayor only reiterated that Chinese had
                                    proof and <pb facs="0215" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/> suggested
                                    publishers talk to Colonel Yeaton<note n="83" xml:id="d172fn1">Ivan D. Yeaton, U. S. A.</note> (former Assistant MA,
                                    Shanghai, and former Commander, Yenan observer group) who Mayor
                                    said, also had proof of Russian connection with Chinese
                                    Communists.</p>
                                <p>Mayor stated only US could bring this to attention of world but
                                    Cowles, Field and Mrs. Reid said it was matter for UN” to act
                                    on. Mayor then said UN should send Investigating Commission
                                    immediately to China but declared China, remembering her
                                    experience with League of Nations would not take matter to UN
                                    unless assured US willing to back Chinese request for
                                    Investigating Commission. Mayor suggested to publishers that
                                    Secretary Marshall take up this subject with Chinese through
                                    diplomatic channels.</p>
                                <p>Mayor insisted repeatedly that Russia was beginning third world
                                    war in China. Mayor said only way for Chinese to bring this fact
                                    to attention of world would be by dramatic withdrawal to line
                                    along Yellow River, letting iron curtain fall over Peiping,
                                    Tientsin and Manchuria, shutting out exports and business as
                                    well as all contract [<hi rend="italic">contact</hi>] with
                                    points north of the line.</p>
                                <p>Publishers disagreed with Mayor’s proposal and Howard asked why
                                    Mayor favored this withdrawal rather than withdrawal to
                                    traditional line of the Great Wall. Conversation turned to other
                                    points without Mayor answering.</p>
                                <p>Mayor Wu stated there were 2,000 Chinese Communist agents in
                                    Shanghai but all were known and under surveillance, but since
                                    China was democratic country, sufficient evidence had to be
                                    secured before these agents could be arrested even though state
                                    of war existed. Mayor said if he was war lord, he would just
                                    issue orders to shoot down 50 of them on the streets—and I know
                                    which 50—and then there would be no further trouble in this
                                    city.</p>
                                <p>Turning to the Marshall Mission, Mayor stated that General
                                    Marshall came to China after success and when he met defeat in
                                    the Kuomintang-Chinese Communist negotiations he left Chinese
                                    very bitter toward the Government. Mayor said his statement
                                    showed he blamed the Chinese Communists for the defeat but felt
                                    the Government also was to blame. “But, as you well know, it is
                                    impossible to get Communists and Democrats together. Look at the
                                    US and Russia.” Mayor said he knew Marshall could only meet with
                                    failure because he represented Generalissimo during Hurley<note n="84" xml:id="d172fn2">Maj. Gen. Patrick J. Hurley, Special
                                        Representative of President Roosevelt in China in 1944 and
                                        subsequently Ambassador in China until November 1945.</note>
                                    attempt to get the two groups together. At this point, Howard
                                    chimed in to say that the Marshall Mission was a duplicate of
                                    the Hurley Mission and foredoomed to failure from the start, and
                                    that the only difference was that Marshall was a more able and
                                    balanced negotiator than Hurley. Others disagreed and said
                                    Marshall clearly put blame where it belonged in his
                                        statement.<note n="85" xml:id="d172fn3">January 7; for text,
                                        see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                        January 19, 1947, p. 83; <hi rend="italic">United States
                                            Relations With China</hi> (Washington, Government
                                        Printing Office, 1949), p. 686.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>In discussion of United Nations, Mayor felt UN was merely
                                    sounding-board and would not be able to do much toward cause of
                                    peace. <pb facs="0216" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> Howard agreed
                                    with Mayor, but Mrs. Reid and others defended UN and said it was
                                    up to members to get behind it and make it work, not just sit
                                    back hopefully wishing it would work, for world peace.</p>
                                <p>On 24th publishers made brief visit to Nanking where
                                    Generalissimo and Madame Chiang received them. Generalissimo
                                    expressed Chinese faith in United Nations in answer to question.
                                    Generalissimo said Manchuria was critical spot in world and
                                    world’s future peace would be determined by course of events
                                    there. Publishers had expected to have long off-record
                                    conference with Generalissimo and appeared disappointed over
                                    outcome.</p>
                                <p>Party departed for Tokyo 26th. Embassy repeat to Department in
                                    its discretion. Davis.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Following are Embassy’s comments: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Inasmuch as Pan Am plane was delayed in reaching Shanghai and
                                    editors had to change planes and return for afternoon reception
                                    Shanghai, their stay here was limited to short and unnoteworthy
                                    call upon Generalissimo and Madame Chiang.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Reference is made to Embtel 1409, June 27, 2 p.m. In this
                                    connection, Minister-Counselor informally called Vice-Minister
                                    George Yeh’s attention to categoric statements now being made by
                                    highly-placed Chinese officials, including Mayor Wu, and asked
                                    whether it was Foreign Office’s intention to make public the
                                    cited evidence of direct Soviet assistance to Chinese
                                    Communists. Yeh indicated that he was now in process of sifting
                                    such evidence as had been given Foreign Office by Minister
                                    National Defense and he hoped to be able to produce something in
                                    a few days. Speaking personally and confidentially, he expressed
                                    opinion that such statements should never have been made in the
                                    way they were made and indicated that he was having a very
                                    difficult time selecting the real from the bogus and that he was
                                    concerned lest the Chinese Govt make a public statement which,
                                    upon inspection, would prove to be insufficient.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Shanghai, repeated Department.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>