<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Davis
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d191</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">191</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-11T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-11T05:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-11T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-11T05:00:00-05:00" n="191" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d191">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/7–1147: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-11T19:00:00+09:00">July 11, 1947—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 10:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1681. Wang Yun-sheng, editor-in-chief <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi>, in
                    course of general conversation with Chase<note n="26" xml:id="d191fn1">Augustus
                        S. Chase, Consul at Shanghai.</note> yesterday which touched on Manchuria,
                    said that his paper’s Mukden representative recently visited Ssupingkai and made
                    special efforts to check basis for allegation of Russian and
                    Russian-organized-Korean aid to Communist armies in northeast. After careful
                    investigations and interviewing of captured Communists the representative could
                    find no evidence that Russians had participated in Communist operations (in
                    technical capacities) or otherwise assisted them, “though he did find abundant
                    proof that Communists had captured from Nationalists and effectively employed
                    much American equipment”. He found Koreans and Japs among prisoners, but only
                    few and found no grounds for concluding that they were organized, trained or
                    equipped by Russians.</p>
                <p>Wang said that paper’s representative did establish one positive fact, namely
                    that firepower used by Communists in attacking Ssupingkai was greater than ever
                    employed by them elsewhere in China. Wang felt, however, that this could not be
                    taken as proof of [overt] Soviet aid and may well merely mean that Communists
                    were using large supplies accumulated from other sources (abandoned by Japs and
                    captured from Nationalists).</p>
                <p>Sent Nanking as 1229, repeated Dept as 1681, Mukden as 102, Dairen as 27,
                    Changchun as 53, and Moscow as 7.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
