<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Douglas
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-04T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="inflation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112" lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9–447</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2016</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-04">September 4,
                            1947</date>.<lb/>[Received September 15.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: 1. I have the honor to enclose, as of possible
                    interest to the Department, copy of a memorandum of a conversation held by an
                    Embassy officer on September 3, 1947, with General Chu Shih-ming, a high-ranking
                    Chinese military officer who has just arrived in London from China.</p>
                <p>2. The enclosed memorandum sets forth certain views expressed by General Chu on
                    the situation in China.</p>
                <p>3. General Chu is well known to Departmental officers as a Chinese of rare
                    integrity and objectivity of thought. It is clear that General Chu has many
                    reservations with regard to the competence of the Chinese Government under which
                    he serves, but it is equally clear that he considers that Government—with all
                    its admitted weaknesses—to [be] the only present alternative: i. e., a Chinese
                    Communist Government subservient to the desires of the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Drumright</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">First Secretary of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the First Secretary of
                            Embassy in the United Kingdom</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Drumright</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-03">September 3,
                                1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">General Chu Shih-ming, former Chinese
                                Military Attaché, Washington, former Chinese Member, Allied Control
                                Council, Japan, et cetera</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. Tuan Mao-lan, Chinese Minister,
                                London</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Drumright</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Dr. Tuan Mao-lan telephoned Mr. Drumright to say that General Chu
                            Shih-ming had arrived in London and wished to discuss the China
                            situation with Mr. Drumright. General Chu, Dr. Tuan and Mr. Drumright
                            accordingly met the evening of September 3, 1947, and had a conversation
                            lasting more than two hours. The highlights of the conversation were as
                            follows:</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Dr. Chiang Mon-lin, General Chu and other members of the Chinese
                            delegation to the Institute of Pacific Relations Conference at
                            Stratford-on-Avon had left Shanghai by air on August 24, 1947, <pb facs="0285" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/> flying via Hong Kong and
                            India. General Chu proposed to travel from England to the United States
                            after the conference. He tentatively proposed to remain in the United
                            States about three months. General Chu omitted to reveal the purpose of
                            his mission to the United States.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Situation in China</hi>. General Chu said
                            that, generally speaking, the Government had made little progress in its
                            campaign against the Communists. The Government’s campaign against the
                            Communists had taken a favorable turn in Shantung just before his
                            departure from China. But even in Shantung the Government forces had
                            suffered several reverses and there had been four changes of commanders
                            in recent months. Hsueh Yueh and Tang En-po were among the commanders
                            who had been withdrawn from that front. The Generalissimo was pursuing a
                            strategy of extended operations against the Communists in the hope of
                            speedy victory. This strategy had not proved fruitful. The Generalissimo
                            had not followed the blockading tactics employed in his Kiangsi campaign
                            of 1934 because this method of operations was too slow and costly.
                            General Chu had counseled against the Government’s plan to occupy
                            Manchuria, but had been overruled. He considered the Government position
                            there untenable and he, for his part, would urge withdrawal of
                            Government forces to China Proper. But he thought that this would be a
                            bitter pill for the Generalissimo and the Government to swallow and,
                            moreover, withdrawal might severely impair confidence in the Government.
                            He thought that the Government might compromise on the problem by
                            withdrawing from extended positions at Kirin and Changchun. He said that
                            he doubted whether the Generalissimo would waver in his determination to
                            hold Mukden and the railway corridor to the south. General Chu said that
                            he personally regarded Manchuria as a “shell” and reiterated his belief
                            that the Government would be well advised to withdraw its forces
                            completely therefrom. General Chu said that it was obvious that the
                            Soviets had in various ways aided the Chinese Communists in Manchuria,
                            and that he was astonished to find that there were western observers who
                            went around saying there was “no evidence” of Soviet aid to the Chinese
                            Communists. General Chu said that when he left China the Government was
                            busy formulating a plan for the training of Chinese troops to be carried
                            out at three centers, one of which would probably be in Taiwan. General
                            Chu remarked that the American Military Advisory Group in China had
                            contributed little to the training of Chinese forces, adding that the
                            group was concentrated in Nanking and that General Lucas had virtually
                            no access to the Generalissimo and that he rarely saw General Chen
                            Cheng.</item>
                        <pb facs="0286" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Position of Chinese Government</hi>. General Chu said
                            that, contrary to reports commonly prevalent among western observers,
                            there was no possibility of an imminent collapse of the Chinese
                            Government. He said that, in his view, the Government could, even
                            without external assistance, remain in power for another year. In
                            expressing this view, General Chu said that he did not wish to minimize
                            the seriousness of China’s plight. The economic situation was extremely
                            critical. Inflation was an ever-growing canker which naturally produced
                            corruption and inefficiency. The Government was still deriving 60 per
                            cent of its revenue from the printing press, and the very great bulk of
                            China’s expenditures went to the military machine. The fact was, General
                            Chu observed, that China was far more exhausted by the war than Britain,
                            France or even Italy, but it seemed that, as during the war, the United
                            States was concentrating on the rehabilitation of Europe and leaving
                            China to shift for herself.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Generalissimo</hi>. General Chu said that the
                            Generalissimo was as determined as ever to surmount the crisis
                            enveloping China. He had been struggling with crisis after crisis since
                            his rise to power, and he would not be daunted by the present one. The
                            Generalissimo likened the present situation to the one which obtained in
                            the earlier stages of the Sino-Japanese war, with the Soviets replacing
                            Japan as the chief threat to China’s independence and integrity. The
                            Generalissimo had carried on the struggle against the Japanese alone and
                            at great odds, always counting on the fact that the United States would
                            in the end come to China’s aid in her own interests. While the
                            Generalissimo was now hurt and at a loss to understand the attitude of
                            the United States, he was confident that in due course the United States
                            would see the true significance of his struggle against Soviet
                            aggression and again come to his assistance. Meantime, the Generalissimo
                            would hang on grimly, shoring up the weaknesses of his Government as
                            best he could.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Wedemeyer Mission</hi>. General Chu was plainly
                            reserved in his remarks about the Wedemeyer mission. He said that he had
                            seen General Wedemeyer only once and had exchanged only a few remarks
                            with him. He remarked that although General Wedemeyer had made some
                            caustic remarks about China, he felt personally that General Wedemeyer
                            would in the end recommend some sort of support to the National
                            Government. In support of this observation, he said that he did not see,
                            in the present posture of world affairs, just how General Wedemeyer
                            could safely make any other recommendation. For any other course on the
                            part of the United States would be the equivalent of an open invitation
                            to the Soviets to march in (in the guise of their Chinese Communist
                            comrades) and take over China. <pb facs="0287" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/>
                            And however much the United States abhorred the weakness, inefficiency
                            and corruption of the Chinese Government, he could not see the United
                            States choosing the alternative course which would plainly be disastrous
                            to its own interests and security.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Situation in the Southern Provinces</hi>. General Chu
                            said that he was aware of reports of an imminent breakaway of Kwangtung
                            and perhaps Kwangsi from the National Government. He went on to say
                            that, based on his knowledge of the situation, there was no possibility
                            of Kwangtung and Kwangsi seceding from the National Government. In this
                            connection, General Chu explained that Li Chi-sen and those surrounding
                            him were malcontents of long standing, and that they had no influence or
                            power. As for General Chang Fa-kuei, the most powerful personality in
                            the southern provinces, he was an intimate of General Chen Cheng’s and
                            so long as that relationship existed there was no possibility of his
                            abandoning Nanking.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chinese Communists</hi>. General Chu said that he
                            felt there were now few observers of the Chinese situation who would
                            deny the direct relationship existing between the Kremlin and the
                            Chinese Communists. That relationship, he said, had become all too clear
                            in the past two years to warrant any extended comment. General Chu then
                            went on to make the interesting observation that the tie-up between
                            Moscow and the Chinese Communists was the major factor militating
                            against Communist domination of China. Had the Communists been a purely
                            indigenous political grouping, they would by now have toppled the
                            Chinese Government from power. But the bulk of the Chinese people sense
                            the fatal link between the Kremlin and the Chinese Communists. While the
                            Chinese people detest their present Government and long for another,
                            they like even less the prospect of a Soviet-dominated Communist regime
                            and are accordingly unwilling to support it. In discussing the Chinese
                            Communists, General Chu also made the noteworthy observation that,
                            contrary to most Communist fifth-column organizations, the Chinese
                            Communists lack uniformity in the application of their policy to the
                            areas controlled by them. In north Kiangsu, for example, their rule was
                            most despotic and they accordingly alienated the sympathy and support of
                            all classes of the populace. In Shantung, on the contrary, they have
                            pursued a mild and beneficent administration and in consequence receive
                            a good deal of support from the inhabitants. General Chu said he
                            considered that however hard Mao Tse-tung tried to impose uniformity,
                            China was too large and the Chinese (including the Communists) too
                            individualistic to hew to an identic line of conduct.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Institute of Pacific Relations Conference</hi>.
                            General Chu said that the Chinese delegation recognized that in the
                            discussions on China <pb facs="0288" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/> at the
                            impending conference there would be many harsh things said about the
                            Chinese Government, particularly by the fellow-travelling American
                            delegation headed by Edward Carter and Owen Lattimore. While the Chinese
                            delegates in discussions among themselves freely criticized the conduct
                            of the Chinese Government, they would rise to a man to defend that
                            Government against the attacks of outsiders. They were prepared for the
                            worst and would in the conference reply item by item to the strictures
                            of China’s detractors.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Drumright</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
