<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Stuart) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-01-29T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-01-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-01-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-01-29T19:00:00-05:00" n="24"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/1–3047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-01-30T08:00:00+08:00"
                            >January 30, 1947—8 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 30—5:45 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>162. Embassy is forwarding by despatch full text<note n="46" xml:id="d24fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 710; despatch No. 824, June 20, not
                        printed.</note> of lengthy statement by Lu Ting-yi, head of Department of
                    Information, Chinese Communist Party and member Party’s Central Executive
                    Committee, published <hi rend="italic">Emancipation Daily</hi>, Yenan, January 4
                    and 5.</p>
                <p>Lu sees world situation today as struggle between democratic and anti-democratic,
                    or Fascist, forces; the defeat of Germany and Japan did not finally destroy
                    Fascism and the struggle against it must now continue until the inevitable
                    victory of democratic forces throughout the world. Democracy, in Lu’s
                    definition, is synonomous with the Soviet Union and with those masses of people
                    to be found in every country who find themselves in sympathy with the selfless
                    desire of a Socialist Soviet Union to free all men from oppression and
                    imperialism. It is simply because these democratic forces include the
                    overwhelming majority of men that their victory is inevitable and what appears
                    to be the impressive present strength of reactionary forces is merely a
                    superficial delusion.</p>
                <p>Lu then proceeds to state that American imperialists have taken the place of
                    Germany and Japan in the world. Their objective is to enslave the American
                    people and by “peaceful means” to ensure American domination of the other
                    capitalist countries and all colonial <pb facs="0040" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/>
                    areas. American imperialism, therefore, has become the great enemy of
                    mankind.</p>
                <p>Embassy considers statement to be the strongest and most orthodox yet issued by
                    the Chinese Communists and the most important manifesto since Mao Tse-tung’s
                    report “on coalition govt” to the Seventh Party Congress in April 1945.<note
                        n="47" xml:id="d24fn2">May 1, 1945, <ref target="frus1945v07#pg_362">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p. 362</ref>.</note> The statement
                    follows so closely traditional Marxist analysis of social development and the
                    inevitable course and fate of monopoly capitalism that it might well have been
                    written in the Kremlin and it is of particular interest in view of current
                    Communist policy of avoiding any semblance of compromise or of taking any
                    position vis-à-vis the internal Chinese situation other than one of
                    intransigence and willingness to fight for their own terms.</p>
                <p>It is difficult, if not impossible, to estimate whether this revised line was
                    reached from independent theoretical studies or was suggested by outside
                    sources; or whether it is part of a long preconceived strategy which is now
                    merely announced at what seems a propitious moment. Certainly it changes the
                    emphasis of “on coalition govt” that socialism and communism for China are
                    merely an eventual ideal. Lu’s statement, in terms stronger than any ever used
                    before, closely identifies the Chinese Communist Party with the Kremlin’s
                    self-appointed propaganda line of championship of oppressed peoples throughout
                    the world.</p>
                <p>There is another thing. The Chinese Communist Party is the only Communist group
                    in the world which can compare in size and influence with the CPSU (B).<note
                        n="48" xml:id="d24fn3">Communist Party of the Soviet Union
                        (Bolshevik).</note> The Kremlin must be well aware that it is the only
                    important Communist Party in the world of which no one has yet been able to
                    prove that it has direct ties with the Soviet Party and that it is not primarily
                    an indigenous movement arising from Chinese conditions whose principal and
                    perhaps only direct link with the Soviets is ideological affinity. This factor
                    makes it, therefore, a useful vehicle for spreading the Communist line.</p>
                <p>Sent Dept 162. Repeat to Moscow.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
