<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/2–747: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-07">February 7,
                                1947</date>.<lb/>[Received February 7—4:16 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>220. Following is February 1st statement of Central Committee of
                            Communist Party:</p>
                        <pb facs="0043" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/>
                        <p>“The Political Consultative Conference comprising all major political
                            parties, groups and prominent social figures, convened on January 10,
                            1946 in accordance with stipulations of the summary of
                            Kuomintang–Communist talks in Chungking on October 10, 1945,<note n="56" xml:id="d26fn1">See <hi rend="italic">United States Relations With
                                    China</hi>, p. 577.</note> is universally recognized by the
                            people of the entire country and world powers as the highest political
                            body in China. Until China has a really democratic national parliament,
                            all important internal and diplomatic affairs which would be passed by a
                            parliament in democratic countries should pass through this Conference
                            or obtain agreement of major political parties and groups before they
                            can be regarded as effective.</p>
                        <p>Since January 10, 1946, however, Chinese Kuomintang Government has not
                            only enacted many arbitrary domestic measures but has also many times
                            singly conducted diplomatic negotiations of a serious nature with
                            certain foreign governments, in the course of understandings both oral
                            and written, secret and open, without these agreements and
                            understandings having been passed by the Political Consultative
                            Conference or consulting opinion of this party and other parties and
                            groups participating in Political Consultative Conference. These
                            diplomatic negotiations included loans from foreign governments,
                            continuation of Lend-Lease, buying and accepting of munitions and
                            surplus war materials, forming of treaties regarding special rights in
                            commerce, navigation, aviation and other economic and legal special
                            rights.</p>
                        <p>These negotiations and agreements request or permit foreign land, sea and
                            naval forces to be stationed in or operate on the seas, waterways,
                            territories, and in the air of the country, and to enter or occupy and
                            jointly construct or make use of military bases and points strategic to
                            the national defense. They furthermore request or permit foreign
                            military and other personnel to participate in organization, training,
                            transportation and military operations of land, air and naval forces of
                            the country, and to become conversant with military and other state
                            secrets of the country. They also permit such serious matters as foreign
                            intervention in internal affairs.</p>
                        <p>Those measures of the Chinese Kuomintang Government are completely
                            contrary to the will of the Chinese people and they have plunged and
                            will continue to plunge China into civil war, reaction, national
                            disgrace, loss of national rights, colonization and crises of chaos and
                            collapse. In order to rescue the motherland from this calamity, to
                            protect national rights and interests and the dignity of the Political
                            Consultative Conference, the Chinese Communist Party solemnly states:
                            This party will not now nor in the future <pb facs="0044" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/> recognize any foreign loans, any treaties which
                            disgrace the country and strip away its rights, and any of the
                            above-mentioned agreements and understandings established by the
                            Kuomintang Government after January 10, 1946, nor will it recognize any
                            future diplomatic negotiation of the same character which have not been
                            passed by Political Consultative Conference or which have not obtained
                            agreement of this party and other parties and groups participating in
                            the Political Consultative Conference. This party furthermore will
                            absolutely not bear any obligations for the above-mentioned.”</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>