<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Philip D. Sprouse
                    This memorandum and the one printed infra were submitted by Mr. Sprouse on September 19
                        to the Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs (Butterworth).</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d558</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">558</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="civil-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec1c8936cc6bb154a" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="yalta-agreement">Yalta Agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="558" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d558">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">121.893/9–1947</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Philip D. Sprouse</hi>
                    <note n="48" xml:id="d558fn1">This memorandum and the one printed <hi rend="italic">infra</hi> were submitted by Mr. Sprouse on September 19
                        to the Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs (Butterworth).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-29">29 July
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Summarized below are remarks made to me by Dr. Lew<note n="49" xml:id="d558fn2">Daniel Lew, member of the Secretariat of the Chinese Executive Yuan and
                        son-in-law of Gen. Chang Chun, President of the Executive Yuan.</note>
                    during the course of my call on him today.</p>
                <p>The only bright spot in the present situation in China is the free and
                    intelligent discussion which takes place during Executive Yuan meetings. The
                    present administration, as represented by the Executive Yuan, is the most able
                    that China has had in many years. They are faced, however, with a seriously
                    deteriorating economic and financial situation and an equally serious military
                    situation. There is no real solution as long as there is civil war, which
                    results in the expenditure of approximately 80% of the budget for military
                    purposes. The U. S. should give the present administration economic and
                    financial aid in order to provide support for an effective executive organ. The
                    present Government has made many mistakes and has been subjected to much
                    criticism, much of it justified, although there have been many exaggerations.
                    General Chang Chun is aware of this and deplores many of the excesses of the
                    military and the secret police, but he has no control over them. The military
                    are responsible solely to the Generalissimo. For this reason General Chang Chun
                    can take no steps to reduce military expenditures. Although all important
                    matters are referred to the Executive Yuan, no one opposes any measure
                    introduced or supported by the Generalissimo, who may be said to exercise a veto
                    power over the Executive Yuan. If the U. S. were to give China financial and
                    economic assistance, this would strengthen the position of the moderate
                    progressive group in the present administration. Militarily, the Government
                    should try only to contain the Communists in their present positions and build
                    up a strong and healthy economy in the areas south of the Yellow River <pb facs="0686" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/> with U. S. financial and economic aid.
                    The Government says that it can destroy the Communists by force, but this
                    provides no solution for the problem. (Dr. Lew, by indirection, expressed
                    disagreement with the Government’s view of its ability to destroy the
                    Communists.) Asked what action the Government might take to strengthen its
                    position and prestige among the Chinese people, Dr. Lew said that this was a
                    question which could be answered only by the Generalissimo. Dr. Lew referred
                    pointedly to U. S. responsibility for China’s present predicament in Manchuria
                    as a result of the Yalta agreement.<note n="50" xml:id="d558fn3">Signed February
                        11, 1945; <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_984">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta and
                            Yalta, 1945, p. 984</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While Dr. Lew was somewhat guarded in his statements and explained to me that his
                    position as the son-in-law of General Chang Chun made it difficult for him to
                    talk as freely as he might otherwise, he expressed his views sufficiently—which
                    may in a sense reflect something of General Chang Chun’s attitude—to indicate a
                    pessimistic picture of the situation. I have known Dr. Lew for about two years
                    and have always found him a fairly frank person with a definite pro-US
                    orientation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sprouse</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
