<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Mukden (
                        Ward
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d587</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">587</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-08-19T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-19T20:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-19T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-19T20:00:00-05:00" n="587" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d587">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">121.893/8–2047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Mukden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ward</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mukden</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-20T10:00:00+09:00">August 20, 1947—10 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 21—4:23 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>217. Local reactions toward Wedemeyer mission. Military and political clique led
                    by Hsiung<note n="4" xml:id="d587fn1">Gen. Hsiung Shih-hui, Director of
                        Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek’s Headquarters in the Northeast.</note>
                    obviously disappointed inability monopolize mission and to control its contacts.
                    Inasmuch as Hsiung had taken great pains to have persons selected by him coached
                    in presentation information according his light, his inability control contacts
                    available Wedemeyer, and the patently inaccurate information which he himself
                    advanced to Wedemeyer in presence Chinese officials and influential banker has
                    redounded to his discredit in local circles.</p>
                <p>Chinese industrialists impressed by desire of mission obtain facts good or bad,
                    and at lack of interest in “Hsiung inspired” propaganda they first attempted to
                    pass on particularly so far as Russian aid to <pb facs="0745" n="735" xml:id="pg_735"/> Communists concerned. All were impressed with background
                    knowledge of mission.</p>
                <p>Visit pleased native northeasterners more than others. Their representative given
                    hour Wedemeyer’s time where he was allowed to present northeasterns’ views
                    without interference. Mission definitely bolstered their morale in that for
                    first time they feel their grievances, solutions to problems and ideas will get
                    through Generalissimo.</p>
                <p>Ordinary persons impressed with lack of ostentation displayed by mission. Felt
                    that mission here to accomplish something. Were impressed by inability Hsiung
                    clique control mission’s activities despite elaborate preparations made toward
                    that end.</p>
                <p>Foreign community, particularly American, most favorably impressed with
                    background knowledge, desire for facts, and that Chinese were not afforded
                    opportunity to sway mission through elaborate entertainment and pressure
                    tactics. Deepest impression made by mission in short time grasping ideas of
                    local residents and officials. Openmindedness and desires for facts
                    appreciated.</p>
                <p>Common foreign and Chinese criticism not enough time spent to obtain and verify
                    information submitted to it, in fact in this regard some Chinese have voiced
                    opinion that mission has made its decision before coming Mukden and was
                    therefore not interested in making other than token visit Manchuria.</p>
                <p>Sent Embassy as 343; repeated Dept as 217.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ward</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
