<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d70</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">70</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-03-23T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-23T05:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-23T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-23T05:00:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/3–2347: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-23T18:00:00+08:00">March 23, 1947—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 24—1:32 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>636. Capture of Yenan by Government forces is a significant political event and
                    to a substantial extent meets the Government need mentioned in previous Embassy
                    telegrams for a striking victory to bolster its position.</p>
                <p>It is noteworthy that Government’s decision to take Yenan was apparently reached
                    during this month. In this connection it should <pb facs="0092" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> be recalled that Generalissimo in his statement of February
                        16,<note n="36" xml:id="d70fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Relations With China</hi>, p. 704.</note>
                    indicating Government’s intention of consolidating its current positions and
                    concentrating on opening lines of communication, spoke in the following words:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“On its part the Government will confine its military efforts to the
                            protection and restoration of communication systems so necessary for the
                            economic life of the nation and we shall spare no efforts to continue to
                            seek for a political solution of the Communist problem.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">At that time T. V. Soong categorically stated to Embassy that
                    both he and Generalissimo were of same mind that Yenan should not be attacked.
                    Subsequently, MA<note n="37" xml:id="d70fn2">Military Attaché.</note> was
                    similarly advised by G–2 Section<note n="38" xml:id="d70fn3">Military
                        intelligence.</note> of Ministry of National Defense. It is, therefore, fair
                    assumption that taking of Yenan was later required by the Government in general
                    and Chen Cheng in particular for prestige purposes. There are also indications
                    that the timing of the Russian <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> regarding Chinese
                    occupation of Dairen and Port Arthur area<note n="39" xml:id="d70fn4">For
                        correspondence on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_481">pp. 481</ref>
                        ff.</note> and Molotov’s proposal at Moscow conference so increased
                    apprehension that Russia might be planning another move that it was even feared
                    that it might accord some form of recognition to Chinese Communists which
                    capture of Yenan would frustrate.</p>
                <p>It is a fact that capture of Yenan does represent a significant psychological and
                    political victory for the Government which it is now attempting to exploit to
                    the full propagandawise. To the Chinese people no less than to the rest of the
                    world, Yenan was the capital of the Chinese Communist government and the effect
                    of its capture will be interpreted by many as the beginning of the end.
                    Actually, Yenan was the headquarters of the CCP and the capital of only one of
                    several regional governments.</p>
                <p>Although the Government claims it routed over 100,000 Communist troops, this
                    appears to be a gross exaggeration since American observers during the return of
                    Communist mediation personnel reported the virtual evacuation of Yenan. It has
                    long been apparent that the Communists had prepared well for this eventuality
                    and that they never had any real intention of defending Yenan should such action
                    appear to be costly. Rather it is more in keeping with their long developed
                    tactics to evacuate any given point in the face of enemy pressure, draw him into
                    a pocket, and thereafter gradually sap his strength with guerilla tactics.
                    Furthermore, Government lines are seriously extended into territory which can be
                    counted upon to be hostile in all respects. US officer in charge of Executive
                    Headquarters <pb facs="0093" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/> Liaison group, on his
                    return from Yenan, reported that General Chu Teh had told him that holding Yenan
                    and surrounding areas and maintaining order would immobilize 17 Government
                    brigades.</p>
                <p>MA reports that G–2 Section of Ministry of National Defense informed him that air
                    reconnaissance indicated Communists had withdrawn in two groups to the hills
                    around Yenan. It remains to be seen now whether they will employ their customary
                    guerilla tactics or in due course make an all-out attempt to retake Yenan.</p>
                <p>Department please repeat to Moscow as 3.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
