<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="936" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d936">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.24/7–147</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the Chinese Supply Commission</hi>
                            (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wang</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of Financial and Development
                            Policy</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Ness</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. S–2405</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-01">July 1,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Ness</hi>: We enclose the check of the Chinese
                        Supply Commission No. 1447, dated July 1, 1947, drawn on and certified by
                        the Bank of China, New York Agency, in the amount of $2,820,020.32. This is
                        the amount of the first payment of principal and interest due from the
                        Republic of China under the terms of the “Agreement between the Governments
                        of the United States and the Republic of China on the Disposition of
                        Lend-Lease Supplies in Inventory or Procurement in the United States”, dated
                        June 14, 1946, known as the <pb facs="1164" n="1154" xml:id="pg_1154"/>
                        “Pipeline” Agreement. Because of the unavailability of the supporting
                        documents on the part of the U. S. Treasury, it has not been possible to
                        determine precisely the exact amount due at this time. However, this amount
                        has been agreed upon between representatives of the United States Treasury
                        Department and members of our staff as being approximately correct, subject
                        to later adjustment when precise figures are available.</p>
                    <p>As I pointed out in my letter to you of May 29, 1947, it is provided in the
                        Pipeline Agreement that the terms of payment, including rate of interest,
                        may be altered by mutual agreement at the time of final settlement for
                        lend-lease aid received by China. Negotiations looking to such settlement
                        are now going forward. It is our view that during these negotiations many of
                        the considerations and developments which entered into the making of the
                        Pipeline Agreement or came up thereafter will need reexamination. Because of
                        the spirit of the Agreement, as evidenced in part by the provision referred
                        to, and because of the friendly attitude shown by the United States toward
                        China, we suggest that this check be held by you as evidence of our good
                        faith and not be turned in to the United States Treasury until the
                        conclusion of the final lend-lease settlement. In this way no subsequent
                        decision will be affected by this action. We would welcome any alternative
                        suggestion you may make for handling the matter which would likewise avoid
                        committing the above as a firm payment or setting a precedent for future
                        payments.</p>
                    <p>In any event we wish to place these funds in your hands without delay.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shott-Chin Wang</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>