<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="947" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d947">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/7–1847</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Vincent</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-18">July 18,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General Marshall</hi>: The real purpose and body
                        of the attached memorandum is to be found in the 5th and final Section,
                        Currency Reform; and the specific problem raised is that of a reintroduction
                        of silver into China as a medium of exchange. This Section of the memorandum
                        adds nothing to what we already know. As a matter of fact, we have much more
                        precise information from Sol Adler in Nanking. The Treasury experts continue
                        to take a dim view of the project. They do not consider it feasible. As a
                        layman I am still for it and wish that some way could be worked out to put
                        it into effect. I find also that most of the old China business hands with
                        whom I have talked favor the proposal. Some form of American supervision
                        would be necessary if we gave China a large silver credit to assure that it
                        did not fall into the hands of large speculators and hoarders in Shanghai
                        but actually went into the interior to loosen up the flow of goods to the
                        seaports. Jenkins of Treasury, who is accompanying Wedemeyer,<note n="12" xml:id="d947fn1">Lt. Gen. Albert C. Wedemeyer; for correspondence on his
                            mission to China, see <ref target="#pg_635">pp. 635</ref> ff.</note>
                        will no doubt report on the matter.</p>
                    <p>I am of course in hearty disagreement with the statement in Section 1 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) that “one and a half year’s time was lost to these
                        futile efforts to prevent civil war in this country”. I am quite sure that
                        conditions in China would have been much worse had there not been during
                        1946 a relative lull in military activity. Although little has been done,
                        the Chinese Government is more alive now than it was then to the need for
                        putting its house in order. Had there been active civil war in the early
                        part of 1946, I seriously doubt that the 250,000 Russian soldiers in
                        Manchuria would have withdrawn. And, unless we were prepared for total
                        involvement in the civil war on the side of Chiang, I do not believe he was
                        any more capable then than he is now of eradicating the Chinese Communist
                        army from north China.</p>
                    <p>With regard to Section 2, I would comment that Chiang’s popularity <pb facs="1178" n="1168" xml:id="pg_1168"/> is decreasing. Butterworth
                        supports this view. But it does not follow that he should be replaced.
                        Disintegrative forces in China are always stronger than integrative. Chiang
                        has been fighting a losing battle primarily because he has been, it seems to
                        me, playing the wrong game with the wrong cards. I do not believe he
                        realizes the extent to which the relative unity achieved by him before and
                        during the war was due to two factors: (1) the pressure exerted by Japan and
                        (2) the healthy financial and economic situation which made it possible to
                        attract provincial loyalty. The financial strength of the Nanking
                        Government, which it used to bring unity, has always been in the Yangtze
                        River area. Outlying areas have been, generally speaking, liabilities. If
                        Chiang goes, the disintegrative trend will be speeded up because there is no
                        strong man or group to succeed him. If he stays he may be able, with our
                        assistance, to improve his position in the Yangtze River area from a
                        financial and economic standpoint and cut some of his liabilities in
                        outlying areas. There is a somewhat oblique approach to a solution of this
                        kind in Section 4 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the memorandum which
                        suggests that in the area south of the Yangtze “greater power should be
                        vested in provincial governments so that governors may have a freer hand to
                        improve their fiscal administration, to balance their budgets, to make
                        necessary agrarian reforms, etc.”</p>
                    <p>I agree with the main thesis in Section 3 that “the prospect of peace with
                        the Communists is not very hopeful” and I might add one more reason to those
                        given; namely, the inability of the National Government to visualize the
                        problem in terms of a social as well as a military contest.</p>
                    <p>With regard to general policy on the question of economic aid to China I tend
                        more and more to the belief that, while continuing efforts to contain the
                        spread of Communism in China without becoming directly involved in the civil
                        war, the grass roots and strength of our relations with China over the past
                        100 years derive from American commercial and cultural activities in the
                        country. With this thought in mind, I believe we should do all that we
                        reasonably can to strengthen American business and cultural enterprise in
                        the country. Specific projects should be considered in the light of their
                        relation to strengthening American business in places where we may
                        reasonably expect operations not to be completely at the mercy of the
                        vicissitudes of civil war or of the vagaries of the present National
                        administration. If we can build up enclaves of increasing American influence
                        in such places as Shanghai and Tsingtao, the effect might gradually spread
                        and be beneficial to wider areas and perhaps lead the way to more extensive
                        economic assistance which we would then be able to justify in the eyes of
                        the American people as sound American policy. This will <pb facs="1179" n="1169" xml:id="pg_1169"/> take time; and the question is whether time
                        is on our side; whether we have time. I am inclined to think we have because
                        the Russians do not seem anxious to move aggressively and precipitately into
                        the morass of China. They may realize the difficulties of playing hockey in
                        a marsh.</p>
                    <p>Manchuria, of course, is a more urgent problem. There is no need crying over
                        the mistakes of the past. But I believe that if Chiang would modify his
                        desire to achieve unity based upon the complete authority of the National
                        Government and would make a practical and sincere attempt to gain the
                        support of the old Manchurian leaders and the Manchurian population, he
                        could at least move in the direction of improving the situation in
                        Manchuria. After all, Chang Tso-lin<note n="13" xml:id="d947fn2">Ruler of
                            Manchuria until his death in June 1928.</note> may have been a thorn in
                        the side of intramural Chinese Governments for 20 years because of a
                        semi-autonomous position; but he was also able to operate in a manner which
                        modified the aggressive tendencies of the Japanese and the Russians and
                        which maintained him in control.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohn</hi>] C[<hi rend="smallcaps">arter</hi>]
                                V[<hi rend="smallcaps">incent</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Memorandum]<note n="14" xml:id="d947fn3">Sent by the Secretary of State to Mr. Vincent
                                    on July 3 with a note asking for his comment on this memorandum
                                    which had come “from a very high Chinese source”.</note></seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Factors leading to the present
                                chaos:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Privation as the result of eight years of war against the
                                Japanese.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Development of the Red influence in North China in the course of
                                the war.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Too much optimism after the war. Peace negotiations during
                                Marshall’s mission, the preparations for the National Assembly and
                                the Coalition Government, etc. held many things in abeyance and
                                prevented the Government from paying necessary attention to such
                                important problems as the improvement of Government administration,
                                finance and monetary policy. About one and a half year’s time was
                                lost to these futile efforts to prevent civil war in this
                                country.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Factors essential to stability in
                                China:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Political unity, maintenance of the social economy and of regular
                            economic relations with countries abroad are the three most important
                            requirements for a peaceful and stable China.</p>
                        <p>Towards the objective of political unity, which is most important not
                            only to China herself but also to the Far East as a whole, the Chiang
                            regime has made an important contribution. There has been <pb facs="1180" n="1170" xml:id="pg_1170"/> two versions with respect to
                            the present regime. Although some think that the absence of the
                            Generalissimo from the Government may improve conditions in China, the
                            majority of the Chinese people believe that, before the completion of
                            the constitutional machinery, Chiang’s absence will bring greater chaos
                            to China, with peace to be regained only after a long period of
                            turbulence. Without the Generalissimo, there will likely be a united
                            Communist regime in North China vis-à-vis a disunited non-Communist
                            government in the South.</p>
                        <p>Thanks to the agrarian system in China, the economic system of the
                            country has never been impaired despite the repeated changes of
                            dynasties. But the situation is somewhat different under the present
                            conditions where a system of managed curency is used.</p>
                        <p>When the people loses confidence in the currency, their confidence in the
                            Government will also be lost. The loss of confidence among the rural
                            populace will mean interruption of trade between cities and rural areas.
                            There will be no agricultural supplies for the metropolitan areas and
                            little trade with countries abroad.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Peace with Communists:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The prospect of peace with the Communists is not very hopeful because of
                            (1) the different ideology of communism, (2) the deep-rooted hatred
                            between the Communists and the Kuomintang Party, and (3) the dominance
                            of the Soviet influence over the Reds in China.</p>
                        <p>A temporary truce with the Communists might be attained if, and only if, <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>China can meet the demands of Soviet Russia, particularly an
                                    exclusive interest in Sinkiang and Manchuria, or</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the Central Government can win a few strategic victories so as
                                    to ensure a definite superiority over the Reds, or</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the Central Government can yield unconditionally to the terms
                                    of the Communists.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Will the Chiang Government be able
                                to prevent the expansion of the Communists in China?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The bulk of the people in China is in favor of the Central Government
                            because (1) they are afraid of a radical revolution and (2) the
                            experience of those who have been in the Communist areas have not been
                            pleasant.</p>
                        <p>In order to consolidate its position among the people, there will also be
                            several important conditions which the Central Government must fulfill: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>On the political and military side, the Government must adopt
                                    a bold and determined policy. This will include the following
                                    points: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The area south of the Yangtze River will be designated
                                            as an <pb facs="1181" n="1171" xml:id="pg_1171"/> area
                                            for economic reconstruction and industrial development
                                            under the following conditions: <list>
                                                <label>(i)</label>
                                                <item>Civil personnel will take charge of the
                                                  provincial governments to replace the military men
                                                  who are now holding a great number of these
                                                  posts.</item>
                                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                                <item>Greater power should be vested in the
                                                  provincial governments so that governors may have
                                                  a freer hand to improve their fiscal
                                                  administration, to balance their budgets, to make
                                                  necessary agrarian reforms, etc.</item>
                                                <label>(iv)</label>
                                                <item>[(<hi rend="italic">iii?</hi>)] Peace and
                                                  order in this area will be maintained by militia
                                                  and police forces rather than regular combat
                                                  units.</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The area north of the Yangtze will be designated as a
                                            pacification area, in which more power should be given
                                            to the military personnel before the Communists are
                                            cleared up. In the meantime, it will also be imperative
                                            to make these areas adequately provided with food and
                                            clothing so that the allegiance of the northern
                                            provinces to the Central Government may be ensured,
                                            despite the continuance of the civil war in these
                                            provinces.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>On the economic side, currency reform and measures to reduce
                                    the budgetary deficit are imperative: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The currency reform must be undertaken in the next few
                                            months, before a total collapse in the present economic
                                            system becomes a reality.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The budgetary deficit must gradually be reduced by
                                            improving the tax system as well as curtailing
                                            government expenditure. To reduce military expenditure,
                                            it will be helpful to divide the nation’s military
                                            forces into two sections: the combat units and the local
                                            militia. The former units must be well trained and fully
                                            equipped for their duty, but their number may be reduced
                                            since the areas south of the Yangtze will mainly be
                                            guarded by the militia and police forces.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">The Currency Reform</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>In order to ensure the flow of indigenous agricultural supplies
                                from the rural districts and in view of the waning confidence in the
                                paper notes among the rural populace, the use of metallic coins will
                                probably be imperative if the currency reform is to be successful. A
                                limited amount of gold coins and a sizeable amount of silver money
                                will be put into circulation in the course of monetary reform. Gold
                                and silver certificates duly backed by metallic reserve may also be
                                used, if the technical difficulties involved in coinage prevent the
                                use of metallic coins at the early stage of the reform or when
                                conditions prevent the circulation of a new paper money. The size of
                                the gold circulation will be predicated on the supply of the metal
                                that China will be able to obtain. The coins will not be used to
                                meet the Government <pb facs="1182" n="1172" xml:id="pg_1172"/>
                                deficit, but to pay wages of industrial workers and to buy
                                agricultural supplies from the rural areas.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The conversion ratio between the old <hi rend="italic">fapi</hi>
                                notes and the new money will be fixed in accordance with the market
                                conditions at the time of the monetary reform.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>A currency reserve board consisting of representatives of the
                                Ministry of Finance, the Central Bank of China, the Ministry of
                                Audit of the Control Yuan, the Bankers’ Association, the Chamber of
                                Commerce and other relevant associations or institutions will be
                                established to supervise the issuance and the reserve of the new
                                currency. Foreign advisors may also be invited to participate in the
                                supervision.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>At present, the volume of the note circulation in China is about
                                nine trillion yuan. Assume that the circulation needed after the
                                monetary reform will double the present volume of circulation, the
                                conversion ratio between the old notes and the new money is about
                                25000:1, and 50% of the new circulation is composed of hard coins
                                and the rest of the money notes backed by a metallic reserve of 50%,
                                the amount of silver needed will be approximately 302,400,000
                                ounces. At US$1.29 per ounce, the official price for silver in the
                                United States, about US$390,096,000 will be required; and at the
                                market rate of US$.70 about US$211,680,000 will be required.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To undertake the monetary reform it will be necessary to have a
                                loan of 302,400,000 ounces of silver from the United States. The
                                loan may be repayable in silver in the course of a thirty-year
                                period beginning five years after the loan is granted. To ensure the
                                servicing of the loan, China will specify a few commodities to be
                                exported to the United States and the proceeds derived therefrom
                                will be used to purchase the silver for the payment of the interest
                                and amortization of the loan.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To replenish China’s depleting exchange reserve, short-term
                                commodity loans amounting at least to US$200,000,000 will also be
                                imperative besides the silver loan previously mentioned. In the past
                                year, commodities valued at about US$300,000,000 totaling about
                                three-fourths of China’s entire imports, were from the United
                                States. They included fuel, cotton, wheat, flour, dyestuff,
                                fertilizers, metals, pharmaceuticals, machinery and machine parts.
                                In order to continue such imports, it is necessary to arrange
                                commodity credits with either the Export-Import Bank or other
                                financial institutions of the United States. These credits will have
                                a term of not more than five years and will be strictly on a
                                business basis and repayable, like some of the previous loans from
                                the proceeds of specified exports from China. It is hoped that these
                                commodity credits will be repaid before the servicing of the silver
                                loan is started.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="1183" n="1173" xml:id="pg_1173"/>
                        <p>The above scheme of monetary reform is designed so as to: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Minimize the drain of gold, which is precious in the United
                                    States or the dollar fund, which is scarce in the world
                                    market.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Increase the demand for silver, which is relatively abundant
                                    in the United States.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Prevent the collapse of the social economy of China.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Guard through the Currency Reserve Board the credit granted by
                                    the United States from being mis-used.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is hoped that through this monetary reform, the confidence of the
                            people in the currency as well as political unity of the country may be
                            restored.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>