<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chinese Ambassador (
                        Koo
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d961</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">961</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="debt" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="961" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d961">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/9–2647</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chinese Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Koo</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>The Chinese Ambassador presents his compliments to the Secretary of State and has
                    the honor to present for the consideration of the United States Government the
                    claim of the Chinese Government against the assets in the United States of the
                    Russo-Asiatic Bank, a pre-Soviet joint stock bank which continued to function
                    outside of Russia after 1917 until its failure in 1926.</p>
                <p>The greater part of the claim of the Chinese Government, amounting to
                    £641,794.13.3 is for funds paid to the Shanghai branch of the Russo-Asiatic Bank
                    and transmitted to the London branch of the said bank during the period from
                    1917 to 1926, pursuant to the Chinese Reorganization Loan Agreement of
                        1913.<note n="42" xml:id="d961fn1">For correspondence on this subject, see
                            <ref target="frus1913#pg_143">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1913, pp. 143</ref>–<ref target="frus1913#pg_192">192</ref>.</note> It consisted of the
                    difference between the amounts deposited by the Chinese Government in, and
                    transmitted by the Shanghai branch of the Russo-Asiatic Bank to its London
                    branch during that period, and the amounts disbursed by the London branch in
                    payment of interest coupons and bond retirements in accordance with the
                    Agreement under which the Chinese Government was obliged to provide duplicate
                    payment of the difference.</p>
                <p>The United States Government, as assignee of the Soviet Government under the
                    so-called Litvinov Assignment of 1933,<note n="43" xml:id="d961fn2">See note
                        from the Soviet Commissar for Foreign Affairs to President Roosevelt,
                        November 16, 1933, <ref target="frus1933v02#pg_812">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1933, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            p. 812</ref>.</note> is taking steps to enforce against the New York
                    assets of the Russo-Asiatic Bank a 1917 decree of the Soviet Government
                    confiscating properties of that Bank. While the claim of the United States is
                    still in litigation, it has been upheld to the exclusion of all other claims by
                    the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, and petitions for
                    review are now pending in the United States Supreme Court.</p>
                <p>The Chinese Government, however, has had an interest in these assets antedating
                    the Litvinov Assignment, which it asserted by initiating legal action in the
                    United States prior to the Assignment. The grounds of the Chinese Government for
                    the belief that its claim is entitled to special consideration are among others
                    as follows: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The claim of the Chinese Government is based largely upon the payments
                            made by it, pursuant to the Chinese Reorganization Loan <pb facs="1201" n="1191" xml:id="pg_1191"/> Agreement of 1913, to the Shanghai
                            branch of the Russo-Asiatic Bank during the period of 1917 to
                            1926.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Such payments were made by the Chinese Government in a period of time
                            during which (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the United States Government
                            formally advised the Chinese Government that it would not approve the
                            Soviet confiscation of any pre-existing interests in the Chinese Eastern
                            Railway—all the stock of which was owned by the Russo-Asiatic Bank; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the courts of the United States held, in a
                            number of cases involving the Russo-Asiatic Bank, that the Soviet
                            confiscatory decrees would not be enforced against its New York assets;
                            and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) in at least one case (<hi rend="italic">de Guwoens</hi> v. <hi rend="italic">Equitable Trust Company</hi>),
                            deposits made in New York by the Shanghai branch of the Russo-Asiatic
                            Bank, after the bank was nationalized in Russia, were held properly
                            applied in satisfaction of a pre-nationalization debt of the
                            Russo-Asiatic Bank at Petrograd.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Prior to the Litvinov Assignment and the assertion of any claim of the
                            United States, the claim of the Chinese Government had not only been
                            placed in litigation, but had acquired the protection of a writ of
                            attachment granted by the Supreme Court of the State of New York and
                            levied upon the deposits of the Russo-Asiatic Bank with New York
                            banks.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>In connection with its efforts to enforce its claim in the courts, the
                            Chinese Government had incurred substantial expense which will have
                            inured in large part to the benefit of the United States Government if
                            the latter should ultimately recover the property in a suit.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>There is enclosed a memorandum<note n="44" xml:id="d961fn3">Not printed.</note>
                    containing a more detailed statement of the relevant facts of the case.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as the award to the United States Government of the assets in New York
                    of the Russo-Asiatic Bank would deprive the Chinese Government of the remedy
                    that otherwise might have been available to it, and in view of the special
                    circumstances briefly set forth above, the Ambassador, pursuant to instructions,
                    requests that the claim of the Chinese Government against these assets be given
                    due consideration in the event that the United States Government should
                    ultimately be successful in its efforts to collect these assets or through a
                    compromise settlement to be negotiated.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-26">September 26,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
