<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T20:34:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                        <head>354. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>During the 395th meeting of the National Security Council on January 29,
                            1959, <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> reported on
                            significant world developments affecting U.S. security in part as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Turning to Morocco and Tunisia, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> pointed out that the friction in the
                                    Istiqlal Party had come to a head in Morocco and the position of
                                    the present government was very shaky.</p>
                                <p>“Secretary Quarles reported that in the course of his recent
                                    visit to Europe he had observed among French, Spanish, and
                                    Portuguese officials very great concern about current
                                    developments in North Africa and especially in Morocco.
                                    Secretary Quarles explained that these officials feared the
                                    total collapse of the Moroccan Government [<hi rend="italic">1½
                                        lines of source text not declassified</hi>]. They also felt
                                    that the leadership of the Leftists in Morocco was taking its
                                    advice from the Soviet Embassy.</p>
                                <p>“The President commented that Morocco seemed to have been a most
                                    critical geographical corner ever since he became involved in
                                    the area in 1942. Our policy in Morocco might be a policy which
                                    we should look at carefully as often as every three months. Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gray</persName> assured the
                                    President that this would be done.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2043, the Council noted
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’ presentation, as well
                            as Quarles’ report on the serious concern of the Governments of France,
                            Spain, and Portugal over developments in North Africa, especially
                            Morocco, and agreed that existing policy on Morocco should be reviewed
                            frequently. (Memorandum of discussion, January 29; Eisenhower Library,
                            Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>