<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-08-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="357" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                        <head>357. Memorandum of Discussion at the 417th Meeting of the National
                            Security Council, Washington, August 18, 1959<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d357fn1">Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">Johnson</persName> on August
                                26.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-08-18"><hi rend="italic">August 18,
                                1959</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>[Here follow a paragraph listing the participants at the meeting and item
                            1.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. Significant World Developments
                                Affecting U.S. Security</hi></p>
                        <p>[Here follows discussion of the Soviet ballistic missiles program, Laos,
                            and Communist China.]</p>
                        <p>Turning to Morocco, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                            stated that the King’s abrupt return to Morocco from Paris on August 4
                            was probably dictated by the crisis in Morocco. It is also possible that
                            the King was advised by the Moroccan Government not to see <persName corresp="#p_deGGC1">De Gaulle</persName> so shortly before the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> General Assembly debate on
                            Algeria. Morocco was facing a financial crisis. The French had put the
                            squeeze on Moroccan operating accounts in French banks, and were
                            pressing Morocco to devalue the Moroccan franc. Morocco would like to
                            leave the franc zone and was consulting with Tunisia, which was having
                            trouble with France on the same issue. There was a reliable report that
                            the Soviets had offered Morocco a non-interest-bearing loan of perhaps
                            as much as $100 million. <pb facs="0820" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/> Some
                            negotiations certainly were going on. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> pointed out that there had been
                            a newspaper account yesterday of a possible Soviet loan offer of $37.5
                            million. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said,
                            however, that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> had had a good report
                            that the first offer was probably $100 million. He went on to note the
                            difficulties created by the violation of Moroccan territory by French
                            forces and the kidnapping by the Algerian rebels of the group
                            investigating this violation. He thought it likely that the King would
                            reshuffle or replace the present <persName corresp="#p_IMA1">Ibrahim</persName> government. The King continues to want a
                            broadly-based non-political government. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that there has been no progress in the base
                            negotiations, and pointed out that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YC1">Yost</persName> believes we should try for a 4-year agreement.
                            Morocco has made a request for U.S. military equipment, and has accepted
                            a U.S. military survey team.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:<note n="2" xml:id="d357fn2">The paragraph that follows constitutes
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2119.
                                    (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D
                                    95, Records of Action by the National Security
                                Council)</note></hi></p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Noted and discussed an oral briefing by the Director of Central
                                Intelligence on the subject, with specific reference to recent
                                developments in the Soviet ballistic missiles program; the
                                situations in Laos and Morocco; and recent developments in Communist
                                China.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>[Here follow items 3 and 4.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">5. Tunisia, Morocco, Algeria [here
                                follows a list of references]</hi></p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gray</persName> began his briefing by
                            saying he would concentrate on the question of Moroccan bases. He noted
                            the proposal, in the formal <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> views,
                            for revision of paragraph 21 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                5911;<note n="3" xml:id="d357fn3">The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> views were distributed under cover of an August 13
                                memorandum from the Acting Executive Secretary to the National
                                Security Council. (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records) Regarding NSC 5911, see
                                    <ref target="#d268fn1">footnote 1, Document 268</ref>.</note> he
                            referred to the split on the bases in the objectives (paragraph 24); and
                            then directed the Council’s attention to the split in paragraph 31.
                            Following Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gray</persName>’s presentation,
                            the President expressed surprise that public acknowledgement of the
                            principle of evacuation had not yet been made.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> pointed out that
                            we have discussed this matter with the Moroccans, but that the French
                            had requested that we put off any announcement until after <persName corresp="#p_deGGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s meeting with the King.
                            That meeting had of course never come off. The Secretary referred to
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YC1">Yost</persName>’s recent
                                message<note n="4" xml:id="d357fn4">Telegram 274 from Rabat, August
                                17. (Department of State, Central Files, 711.56371/8–1759)</note> on
                            the bases which had been previously mentioned by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>. He suggested that the
                            difference of opinion here was less a difference of policy than a
                            difference of evaluation of the situation in Morocco. Our alternatives
                            were not, in his <pb facs="0821" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/> view, to stay
                            four years or longer. One real alternative was agreement within the next
                            few months on a maximum term of four years with, perhaps, some months
                            after that for actual evacuation. If we do that, we might get agreement
                            from the Moroccans for a longer stay in the communications facilities
                            which are quite important to us. If, alternatively, we did not reach
                            agreement on this basis, Morocco would attempt to rally public opinion
                            to force us out and take action at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            against our “illegal” occupation. Morocco would probably also harass
                            deliveries of supplies and would perhaps engage in a mass blockade of
                            the bases. In such a situation our alternatives would be to stay through
                            the use of force, which was unthinkable, or to get thrown out in 18
                            months or so.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEN1">McElroy</persName> said that he
                            realized we couldn’t stay in these bases longer than feasible, but he
                            had feared that what was feasible could be interpreted as being as
                            little as one year. The President suggested that the language “as long
                            as required” and “as feasible” be combined.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gray</persName> suggested that Defense,
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_OCDM1">OCDM</gloss> were not blinded to the facts of life in this
                            matter.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEN1">McElroy</persName> reiterated that
                            if we start out on the basis of “feasibility”, the term might be
                            interpreted more weakly than was indicated by this discussion.</p>
                        <p>The President stated that we should, as a matter of urgency, try to reach
                            an agreement. He also felt that we should publicly announce our
                            acceptance of the principle of evacuation; to do so, he felt, would let
                            a lot of the steam out of the kettle.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MEN1">McElroy</persName> concluded the
                            discussion by stating that if the United States gets a 4-year deal, we
                            should determine after two and a half or three years whether we still
                            required the bases and then possibly re-open the question.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:<note n="5" xml:id="d357fn5">Paragraphs a–d and the Note that follows
                                    constitute <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2122.
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                    <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D 95, Records of
                                    Action by the National Security Council)</note></hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Discussed the draft statement of policy on the subject contained
                                in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5911; in the light of the
                                views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff thereon, transmitted by the
                                reference memorandum of August 13, 1959.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Tentatively adopted the following amendments in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5911: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Pages 16–17, paragraph 22:</hi> Include
                                        the Majority version and delete the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_OCDM1">OCDM</gloss>
                                        version.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Page 22, paragraph 35:</hi> Delete the
                                        bracketed language and the footnote thereto.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0822" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Page 22, paragraph 35–a, –b and –c:</hi>
                                        Include the Majority version and delete the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_OCDM1">OCDM</gloss> version.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Adopted paragraphs 24 and 31 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5911, subject to the following amendments: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Page 18, paragraph 24:</hi> Delete
                                            the paragraph and the footnotes thereto, and substitute
                                            therefor the following:</p>
                                        <p>“24. Within the limits of feasibility, maintenance of
                                            U.S. bases in Morocco for as long as they are
                                            required.”</p></item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Page 20, paragraph 31:</hi> Delete
                                            both versions of the paragraph, and substitute therefor
                                            the following:</p>
                                        <p>“31. Endeavor, within the limits of feasibility, to
                                            maintain access to U.S. bases in Morocco for as long as
                                            they are required, being prepared to this end to offer
                                            reasonable quid pro quos, to reach satisfactory
                                            agreement regarding tenure, and to conclude such other
                                            arrangements with Morocco as may be deemed appropriate
                                            and essential to the retention of the bases, including
                                            public acknowledgement of the principle of eventual
                                            evacuation and the relinquishment of non-essential
                                            facilities.”</p></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Referred <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5911 to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Planning Board for review and
                                revision in the light of the discussion at the meeting and of the
                                President’s forthcoming meeting with President <persName corresp="#p_deGGC1">De Gaulle</persName>.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> Paragraphs 24 and 31 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5911, as amended by the action in c
                            above, subsequently approved by the President; circulated for
                            implementation by all appropriate Executive departments and agencies of
                            the U.S. Government; and referred to the Operations Coordinating Board
                            as the coordinating agency designated by the President.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows item 6.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JRH1"><hi rend="strong">Robert H.
                                        Johnson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>