<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>374. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d374</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">374</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-12-31T20:34:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T20:34:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="374" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d374">
                <head>374. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>During a 10 a.m., February 10, meeting at the White House, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> briefed President
                        <persName>Eisenhower</persName> on his conversation the previous evening
                    with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The President spoke of the Tunisian incident. I reported on the talk I
                            had had with <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>. The
                            President asked whether I had referred to the impact this might have on
                            our French financial assistance operation. I said I had alluded to this.
                            The President expressed himself as very discouraged over the French
                            attitude. [<hi rend="italic">5½ lines of source text not
                                declassified</hi>] (Memorandum of conversation with the President;
                            Eisenhower Library, Dulles Papers, Meetings With the President)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Regarding the French raid on Sakiet Sidi Youssef, see <ref target="#d373fn2"
                        >footnote 2, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                    </ref>. Regarding <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’ conversation
                    with <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>, see <ref target="#d373fn5"
                        >footnote 5, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                    </ref>. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> also discussed the
                    incident at his press conference the following day. For text of his comments,
                    see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1958</hi>,
                    pages 1086–1088.</p>
                <p>At the February 13 National Security Council meeting, Director of Central
                    Intelligence <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> reported:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Events in Tunisia have been pretty largely reported in the press. At
                            present the Tunisians had clamped a virtual siege on all French troops
                            and naval vessels. <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>, hard
                            pushed by public opinion, had decided to take the case to the United
                            Nations. <persName corresp="#p_GF1">Gaillard</persName> had admitted
                            that the bombing had been done without the authority of the Government
                            in Paris, which, however, felt compelled to assume the responsibility.
                            Both sides were now attempting to avoid incidents, and had been
                            successful so far. Tunisia hopes the United States will intervene.”
                            (Memorandum of discussion at the 355th meeting of the National Security
                            Council, February 14; Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>That afternoon, Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                    informed Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, who was
                    vacationing in Atlantic City, New Jersey, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“A number of conferences on the Tunisian question had been held with the
                            Tunisian and French ambassadors. He said he felt that the boarding up of
                            the French garrisons might lead to an incident at any time. It is
                            possible that the French consulates may be closed. The French are taking
                            a very strong position and would like the US to support this position,
                            which CAH will not agree to. CAH believed there were no legal grounds to
                            have French troops in Tunisia, but <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                                >Alphand</persName> took the opposite stand. CAH felt the French
                            should make some sort of gesture, such as withdrawing French troops from
                            the south. No request had yet been made for an <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                                >SC</gloss> meeting but this will probably be done today or
                            tomorrow. CAH felt that Tunisia’s demand for withdrawal of troops would
                            be favorably received by other nations, particularly in South America.
                            The Secretary said he felt we should be very careful about tying
                            ourselves up with the French. CAH said all <pb facs="0858" n="824"
                                xml:id="pg_824"/> conversations were being reported to Amb.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HA2">Houghton</persName>. At a press
                            conference this morning Line White had been asked what we planned to do
                            about the situation. He replied that our good offices were always
                            available, if requested. A <persName corresp="#p_BH2"
                                >Bourguiba</persName> statement had just come over the ticker to the
                            effect that the US would be asked to mediate. <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                                >Alphand</persName> is shying away from this. The Secretary said he
                            did not think the French would accept us in this role. CAH said it was a
                            very difficult situation since one thing was being said in private and
                            another in public.” (Memorandum of a telephone conversation; Eisenhower
                            Library, <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Papers, Telephone
                            Conversations; neither the press conference nor <persName
                                corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s statement has been further
                            identified)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Documentation on the conversations with <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> and Tunisian Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SM2"
                        >Slim</persName> is in Department of State, Central File 651.72. Numerous
                    discussions were also held with British Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CSH1"
                        >Caccia</persName>; documentation on these conversations is <hi
                        rend="italic">ibid.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
