<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-08-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="396" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d396">
                        <head>396. Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BJL1" type="from">Berry</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Acting
                                Secretary of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d396fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 772.56/8–1558. Secret.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SWN1">Stokes</persName> on August
                                14 and concurred in by <persName corresp="#p_JFW1">Jandrey</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PSEJ1">Palmer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BRG1">Barnes</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VDSH1">Van
                                    Dyke</persName>, and <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/ISA.
                                Sent to <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> through <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>, initialed by <persName corresp="#p_PSEJ1">Palmer</persName> for <persName corresp="#p_BJL1">Berry</persName>, and initialed by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>. A note attached to the
                                source text reads: <quote><p>“<gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss>
                                            (<persName corresp="#p_VDSH1">Van Dyke</persName>)
                                        clearance granted if following note brought to Acting
                                        Secretary’s attention:</p>
                                    <p>“‘<gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> feels that if Tunisia
                                        is to acquire arms in the U.S., it should be in the form of
                                        military assistance rather than purchase, in view of
                                        Tunisia’s weak economic position. Any purchase of arms would
                                        add to Tunisia’s budget deficit, which is already acute, and
                                        thus increase Tunisian requests for economic assistance from
                                        the U.S.’”</p></quote></note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-08-15"><hi rend="italic">August 15,
                                1958</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Equipment for the Tunisian Army</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi></p>
                        <p>As you know, the French Government has replied to the presentation
                            envisaged in Tab B,<note n="2" xml:id="d396fn2">Memorandum from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, July 25. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 772.5/7–2558)</note> on the subject of Tunisia’s
                            urgent arms requirements, by stating that it has no desire to exercise
                            an arms monopoly in Tunisia, though it does wish to maximize
                            standardization. The reply also stated that France desires shipments
                            from Western sources other than France be held to “quasi-symbolic”
                            levels and wishes to be consulted in all cases (Tab C).<note n="3" xml:id="d396fn3">Telegram 106 to Tunis; see <ref target="#d395fn4">footnote 4, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note> We
                            thereupon instructed our Ambassador at Tunis to inform the Tunisian
                            Government that the United States arms market is now open for reasonable
                            purchases on terms similar to those offered last November, including
                            guarantees against transfer and aggressive use. (We expect to remain
                            within the $3.5 million program envisaged at that time.)</p>
                        <p>In response to our offer, the Tunisian Government specified its most
                            urgent need from the United States as arms to equip two battalions
                            (1,200 men) of the Tunisian Army which, though presently in uniform and
                            partially trained, are without weapons. An itemized list of requirements
                            is attached (Tab D).<note n="4" xml:id="d396fn4">Attached to another
                                copy of the memorandum in Department of State, <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>/AFN Files: Lot 63 D 304, Request for
                                Arms, 10/31/58.</note> Tunisia has also asked the United Kingdom to
                            arm another two battalions in similar circumstances.</p>
                        <p>Tunisia adamantly refuses to accept arms from France before it has
                            demonstrated its access to other sources of supply because of concern
                            that such an arrangement with France would be interpreted <pb facs="0889" n="855" xml:id="pg_855"/> by the North African public as
                            involving secret conditions disloyal to Maghrebian unity, and that the
                                <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> would be thereby impelled to
                            align its policy with that of Cairo. Meanwhile, the dispute between
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> over Tunisian agreement with France for
                            construction of a pipeline from Algeria across Tunisia has become more
                            acute. An <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> representative has told us
                            that the <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> is determined to prevent
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> from “drifting
                            further toward a pro-French policy.” <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s pro-Western attitude also has recently been
                            criticized openly by Moroccan political leaders.</p>
                        <p>In these circumstances <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> is
                            in serious danger of becoming politically isolated in North Africa.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> of course is almost
                            unique as a popular Arab government leader outspokenly friendly to
                            United States policy, and his importance to us in the United Nations and
                            other global contexts is very great indeed, as indicated by President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s recent message (Tab E)<note n="5" xml:id="d396fn5"><persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s August 2 message
                                to <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>; see <ref target="#d393">Document 393</ref>.</note> of appreciation to
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> for the latter’s
                            pro-Western speech of July 25. Moreover, <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s influence with the <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> and his support for moderate leaders in Morocco is a
                            vital political asset for the West in blocking efforts by the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> or the USSR to capture North African
                            nationalism and eliminate Western interests there. If he is to retain
                            these vital positions, and to speak with persuasion in our behalf,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> clearly needs
                            concrete assistance from the West in a number of fields, and most
                            urgently in assuring the physical security of himself and his
                            government.</p>
                        <p>The British share with us this sense of urgency, and appear prepared to
                            supply at least some arms to Tunisia promptly.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That you authorize me to make a presentation to the French along
                                the following lines: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>We are gravely concerned at the evident deterioration of
                                        internal security in Tunisia since our last conversation on
                                        this subject, particularly in view of the grave lack of arms
                                        available to the Tunisian security forces. If Tunisia were
                                        to be subverted by <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Nasser</persName>, we do not believe the government in
                                        Libya (where the United States and the United Kingdom have
                                        vital interests) could long survive. Similarly, we are
                                        convinced that control by <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Nasser</persName> of Libya and Tunisia would deal a
                                        mortal blow to French interests in Algeria. The example of
                                        Iraq is fresh in our minds, [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines of
                                            source text not declassified</hi>].</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>In this situation, the Western powers must act decisively.
                                        As the French Government is aware, we are engaged in a
                                        program of equipping and modernizing the police and the
                                        gendarme forces, but have delayed the difficult aspect of
                                        lethal items until we could be sure <pb facs="0890" n="856" xml:id="pg_856"/> of their minimum requirements. The
                                        police arms which we intend to begin shipping by August 25
                                        are listed in Tab A.<note n="6" xml:id="d396fn6">Attached to
                                            another copy of the memorandum; see <ref target="#d396fn4">footnote 4</ref> above.</note> No
                                        allowance in this list is made for the gendarmérie.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>Meanwhile, we and the British each have been asked by
                                        Tunisia to equip two battalions (1,200 men) of the Tunisian
                                        Army which are as yet wholly without arms. The Tunisians
                                        have made plain to us that they cannot accept French arms
                                        until some arms have been obtained from other sources, in
                                        order to obviate charges of disloyalty to Maghreb unity and
                                        to prevent the political isolation of <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> in North Africa.
                                        We continue to be most reluctant to enter the military
                                        equipment field, and agree with French views about the value
                                        of standardization, but realize that something must be done
                                        to catalyze Franco-Tunisian military cooperation.
                                        Accordingly, we have in mind to inform <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> that we will
                                        fulfill his request to us for light arms for 1,200 men on
                                        the understanding that: <list>
                                            <label>a.</label>
                                            <item>These arms would be transferred to the
                                                gendarmérie, under the U.S. police equipment
                                                program, when deliveries for the Army from France
                                                have been effected, so as to maintain a homogeneous
                                                arms pattern on the French model in the Tunisian
                                                military establishment;</item>
                                            <label>b.</label>
                                            <item>Such outworn weapons as may be displaced in the
                                                gendarmérie by this eventual transfer would be
                                                subject to the same guarantees against transfer or
                                                diversion that apply to the United States arms
                                                delivered under this program.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>We hope and expect that these deliveries would smooth the
                                        way for Tunisian acceptance of French arms. If the idea
                                        commended itself to France and Tunisia, we would be prepared
                                        to consider helping finance such military purchases in
                                        France through an Off-Shore Procurement program.<note n="7" xml:id="d396fn7"><persName corresp="#p_PSEJ1">Palmer</persName> spoke with <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName> on August 18.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Lucet</persName> asked
                                            that the United States issue a communiqué announcing the
                                            quantity of arms shipped to Tunisia, noting that France
                                            would issue the statement if the United States did not.
                                                <persName corresp="#p_PSEJ1">Palmer</persName>
                                            requested that the French Government reconsider this
                                            decision and examine the proposals outlined. (Memorandum
                                            of conversation; Department of State, Central Files,
                                            772.56/8–1858)</note></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>That you authorize me to concert our action in this matter with
                                the British.<note n="8" xml:id="d396fn8"><persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> initialed his approval on August 15.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BJAJ1">Bovey</persName> discussed the
                                    proposed U.S. approach to the French with Roger Jackling of the
                                    British Embassy on August 16. (Memorandum of conversation; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 772.56/8–1658) Jackling reported
                                    on August 18 that the British Government found the approach
                                    generally correct. (Memorandum of conversation; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 772.56/8–1858)</note></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>