<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T20:34:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="397" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                        <head>397. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On August 25, Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MS1">Mokaddem</persName> gave Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGL1">Jones</persName> a response to President
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s July 22 and August 2 letters to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>, noting that
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> had drafted the
                            message personally. (Despatch 173 from Tunis, August 29; Department of
                            State, Central Files, 711.11–EI/8–2958) Regarding
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s letters, see <ref target="#d393">Document 393</ref>.</p>
                        <p>Stating he wrote as one who embraced Western values and wished to see
                            them endure, <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> addressed
                            Soviet influence in the Near East, attributing its increase to vestiges
                            of Franco-Anglo colonialism in the region. The United States had too
                            often appeared to share these imperialist views, had responded too
                            slowly to the Soviet challenge, and had scattered efforts to combat it
                            among too many countries. The West could still defeat Soviet domination,
                            but a purely military response was no longer sufficient. <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> suggested Western leaders meet
                            periodically to consider a unified response to the psychological and
                            political situations they faced. He ended his letter by requesting
                            Western support for Algerian independence. (Despatch 173 from Tunis)</p>
                        <p>An informal translation of <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s letter was sent to the White House on
                            September 3. (Memorandum from Howe to <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName>; Eisenhower Library, Whitman File,
                            International File) On September 13, <persName corresp="#p_SJC1">Satterthwaite</persName> sent <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> a suggested reply to the letter, stating it had
                            “been drafted with a view to being as friendly and responsive as
                            possible” but “without conceding the validity of his arguments on the
                            first two points. With regard to Algeria, it is hoped that the comments
                            made will enable President <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> to reinforce his counsels of moderation to the
                            Algerian National Liberation Front.” (Department of State, Central
                            Files, 611.72/9–1358) <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> sent
                            the suggested response and a formal translation of <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s letter to
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName> on September 18. (Eisenhower
                            Library, Whitman File, International File)</p>
                        <p><persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s September 22 letter to <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> agreed that “one of the most
                            important tasks facing us all is to make clear the moral values and
                            principles on which our free institutions are based.” Concentrating U.S.
                            aid in a few countries would have required neglecting “other countries
                            whose needs were equally great.” Although “most interesting,” <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName>’s suggestion for regular
                            meetings to discuss political and psychological strategies might
                            “undermine important existing means of international cooperation.” The
                            United States would continue to do everything it could to contribute to
                            the solution of the Algerian problem, but would be less able to
                            influence further developments if it took “a partisan position” on the
                            issue. <persName>Eisenhower</persName> thanked <pb facs="0892" n="858" xml:id="pg_858"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> for his letter, praising
                            “the moderate, constructive and helpful role you and your country are
                            playing in these troubled times.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JGL1">Jones</persName> delivered the
                            letter on October 3. After reading its French translation, <persName corresp="#p_BH2">Bourguiba</persName> said, “I am pleased and proud
                            to receive this letter. You will note he had studied my letter and that
                            he answered all my main points. I greatly value this correspondence.”
                            (Telegram 478 from Tunis, October 3; <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> Staff
                            Secretary Records, International Series)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>