<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>58. Memorandum of a Conversation Between the Ambassador to Israel (Lawson)
                    and the Israeli Ambassador () and the Israeli Ambassador (Eban), Ambassador ),
                    Ambassador Eban’s Residence, Washington, December 14, 1958’s Residence,
                    Washington, December 14, 1958</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLI8eVbPHjBYKWy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="middle-east-and-north-african-relations">U.S.-Israeli
                        relations</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recZPVvCSdB8G01JR" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>58. Memorandum of a Conversation Between the Ambassador to Israel (<persName
                        corresp="#p_LEB1">Lawson</persName>) and the Israeli Ambassador (<persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName>), Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eban</persName>’s Residence, Washington, December 14, 1958<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d58fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D 59, Egypt, Israel, 1958.
                        Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LEB1">Lawson</persName>, who
                        had returned to the United States in November for consultations.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1958-12-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 14, 1958</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Israel’s Appeal to the Security Council on Syrian Attack December
                        3—Failure of U.S. to Date to Take Position Thereon</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> reviewed the whole
                    situation along lines already well known to the Department. He exhibited a copy
                    of his letter of December 12 to Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">
                        <ref target="#d57">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> in which he had pointed up in rather strong terms the Israeli
                    conviction that the U.S. should make a strong statement against Syrian
                    action.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> started his conversation by
                    referring to what he considered a “crisis in U.S.-Israeli relations.” (I doubt
                    that he meant to use such a strong descriptive term, but wished to emphasize the
                    seriousness of the problem.) In any event, he thought that perhaps the U.S.
                    Government was not fully aware of the importance of Israel of taking a firm
                    position with regard to Syria. He recalled with some emphasis the fact that (a)
                    the U.S. basic policy requires that all nations utilize the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as an agency to prevent conflict and not to rely
                    on military operations; (b) that the U.S. had frequently and strongly urged <pb
                        facs="0168" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/> the <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> to take up potentially dangerous problems with the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in advance of the point of explosion. This is
                    exactly what Israel is doing in the instance and for that reason feels that it
                    is justified in expecting firm U.S. action in this situation; (c) that the
                    failure of the U.S. to recognize in principle that the Syrians should be
                    condemned for their extensive military operation against civilian villages in
                    Israel would encourage not only Syrian but Arab countries in the area to act in
                    an undisciplined manner with regard to Israel; (d) that the failure of the U.S.
                    to act at this time, when Syrian action was so completely indefensible would
                    have some influences on Israel’s future dependence on appeals to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>; (e) he implied that failure of Israel to receive
                    U.S. support of its present appeal to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    Security Council must, perforce, require a <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                    reappraisal of U.S. urgings in behalf of the use of <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> facilities in specific area disputes and might well reduce the
                    influence of direct appeals by President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> and
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> to Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben Gurion</persName> in the future.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that Israel had reason
                    to believe that it was being fully supported by the French, British, and various
                    Latins who were willing to state their firm position against Syrian action, but
                    so far he had been unable to obtain a statement of position by the U.S.
                    Government. He said that the British had expressed surprise to him that the U.S.
                    “has held back.” It was clear to <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> that
                    no resolution or even an effective summing up by the President of the Security
                    Council would suggest condemnation of the Syrians for their indefensible action
                    unless the U.S. were to take a firm position.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that while the U.S. had not
                    refused to take a position, it had not yet done so. He repeated that this may be
                    the result of the Department’s not realizing the seriousness of such a failure
                    to act or possibly the opinion of some in the United States Government who feel
                    that the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> should not have gone to the
                    Security Council despite past urging by the U.S. Government and despite the most
                    recent message from the U.S. Government delivered by Embassy Tel Aviv stating
                    its approval of the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> employment of <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> facilities instead of military action.</p>
                <p>He read extracts from <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Golda Meir</persName>’s report
                    on Chargé <persName>Baxter</persName>’s visit to her<note n="3" xml:id="d58fn3"
                        >See <ref target="#d56">Document 56</ref>.</note> and delivery of the
                    Department’s message. This message from Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG1"
                        >Meir</persName> followed much the line reported by Embassy Tel Aviv with
                    regard to <persName corresp="#p_BWO1">Baxter</persName>’s visit to the Foreign
                    Office. It mentioned several times the Department’s earlier statement to Israel
                    Embassy, Washington, that the Department’s decision as to policy would be held
                    up until information had been received from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1"
                        >Rountree</persName> who was in the area. This seemed to confuse Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> as it apparently did Mrs.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName>.</p>
                <pb facs="0169" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/>
                <p>He made it clear that Israel would withdraw its complaint to the Security Council
                    if the United States “failed to speak up.” He said Israel would avoid further
                    embarrassment by the Security Council.</p>
                <p>Although the Security Council meeting is scheduled for the afternoon of Monday,
                    December 15, <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that Israel would
                    be willing to delay the meeting another day if the U.S. Government so
                    desired.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> informed me that he was
                    expecting to see Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WFO1"
                        >Wilcox</persName> at the Department Monday, December 15, at 10:30 a.m. He
                    said he also expected to see Deputy Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                        >Murphy</persName> at his home Sunday night, December 14.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d58fn4">
                        <p>Memoranda of <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName>’s conversation
                            with <persName>Murphy</persName> on the border incident and on Israeli
                            relations with Turkey, Iran, and Iraq are in Department of State, <gloss
                                target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 60 D 580, Israel–Syria,
                            1958, and Central Files, 683.84A/12–1558.</p>
                        <p>No record of the meeting with <persName corresp="#p_WFO1"
                                >Wilcox</persName> has been found, but in a telephone conversation
                            at 10:25 a.m., December 15, <persName corresp="#p_WFO1"
                                >Wilcox</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                                >Herter</persName> that <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName>
                            was due at any minute and that he was going to be noncommittal in
                            response to the Ambassador’s request for support. (Eisenhower Library,
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Papers)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>In response to my direct questions, he made the following replies: (1) the
                    incident of December 3 is now considered over. There is no thought of
                    retaliation. A failure of Israel to obtain condemnation of Syria by the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or the failure of the U.S. to take firm action at
                    this time would not bring military retaliatory action against Syria by the
                        <gloss target="#t_IDF1">IDF</gloss>. This is a finished episode. But a
                    repetition of the action “would be different—the situation would have to be
                    reviewed in line of Israel’s present experience with the Security Council.” He
                    reiterated that there was no retaliation planned now. Retaliatory action had
                    been fully considered by the Cabinet in a special meeting at the time of the
                    incident but had been rejected. The fact that there were no casualties, despite
                    the falling of 800 shells on defenseless kibbutzim house where women and
                    children normally resided, was a factor in the decision. (2) Any retaliatory
                    military action would, on account of the terrain and size of Syrian forces,
                    require a large size military operation, which in itself would be very serious.
                    (3) Any sizable military action would lead to incalculably serious area
                    conditions, and now with Berlin, Iraq, and other situations at a sensitive
                    point, the addition of a Near Eastern explosion should be avoided. These were
                    considerations influencing the Cabinet’s decision.</p>
                <p>When I raised the question of who was first to use artillery, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> admitted that Israel used mortars first but
                    (a) for a short time only and (b) they were directed only at military positions
                    and in no instance against strictly civilian areas. The use of mortars was
                    required to relieve the Israelis pinned down by Syrian fire, which had earlier
                    started the trouble by killing an Israeli shepherd on Israeli soil. He made the
                    point that the present complaint and the extensive front of actual <pb
                        facs="0170" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> military action did not involve the
                    demilitarized zones. Therefore, the <gloss target="#t_DMZDZDZ1">DZ</gloss>
                    problems were not involved in the one at hand. In particular, he said, all the
                    villages shelled were outside the <gloss target="#t_DMZDZDZ1">DZ</gloss>.</p>
                <p>In conclusion he made it quite clear, I thought, that in the absence of a U.S.
                    statement, Israel would be less influenced by U.S. exhortations in the future to
                    use <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> agencies to head off trouble or to settle
                    problems in the area; that Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben
                        Gurion</persName> would find such urgings in letters from the President and
                    the Secretary and approaches from U.S. Embassy in Tel Aviv somewhat less than
                    convincing; that Israel hopes for a U.S. statement in the Security Council
                    denouncing the Syrian action. This hope is based on their conviction that such
                    action by the U.S. Government would involve the clear question of principle of
                    whether the U.S. condoned or condemned an indefensible action under any
                    conditions and certainly indefensible under the present undisputed conditions;
                    he held that there were no basic conflicts over the facts of the incident.<note
                        n="4" target="d58fn4">
                        <p>At 3:10 p.m., December 15, <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                            called <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> who said that “a
                            few changes had been made” in the instructions to <persName
                                corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> “to be more responsive to
                            Israelis”. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.) No copy of these instructions
                            has been found.</p>
                        <p>The Security Council discussed the Israeli complaint beginning at 3 p.m.,
                            December 15. For the verbatim record of that discussion, including
                                <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>’s statement on the
                            question, see <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Doc. S/PV.844. The
                            U.S. Delegation to the United Nations, in summarizing the Security
                            Council consideration, said that it went smoothly, but that Israel had
                            given no assurance that it would not retaliate in future similar cases.
                            (Telegram 468 from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, December 16;
                            Department of State, Central Files, 330/12–1658) The Council did not
                            consider the matter further.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
