<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="25" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">888.2553/5–3151</note>
                        <head>No. 25<lb/><hi rend="italic">President <persName corresp="#p_THS1" type="from">Truman</persName> to Prime Minister <persName type="to">Attlee</persName></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d25fn1">On
                                May 30 Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MG1">McGhee</persName> transmitted to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName>, under a covering
                                memorandum, a draft message from President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> to Prime Minister Attlee and
                                a memorandum for the President reviewing the Iranian situation.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MG1">McGhee</persName> explained that a
                                personal message to Attlee along the lines of the draft would “be of
                                great value in persuading the British to pursue a course of action
                                which we feel has a good chance for success.” In the covering
                                memorandum, drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MG1">McGhee</persName> noted that the draft message was cleared by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss> and advanced arguments similar to those in the
                                memorandum for the President concerning the efficacy of sending the
                                message to Attlee. According to <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName>’s handwritten notation on another copy of the
                                covering memorandum, the “memo and enclosure telegraphed to Pres on
                                Wed evening. Reply (with changes in the message) sent to us
                                following morning [May 31].” The revised message to Attlee, printed
                                here, which is the same as the May 30 draft except for minor
                                changes, was transmitted to London in telegram 5565 (signed by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> and repeated to
                                Tehran) at 10 a.m., May 31, and delivered to 10 Downing Street on
                                the evening of May 31. (Telegram 6296 from London, May 31; 888.2553
                                    <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>/5–1351) Copies of the
                                covering memorandum with the attached draft telegram and memorandum
                                for the President and with <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName>’s handwritten notation are in files 888.2553
                                    <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>/5–3051 and 788.00/5–3051,
                                respectively.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-31">May 31, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I express to you the serious concern of the Government of the United
                            States, which I am sure you share, at the present situation <pb facs="0086" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/> in Iran. I realize the great
                            importance to Great Britain of a satisfactory solution to the
                            controversy with the Iranian Government concerning operations of the
                            Anglo-Iranian Oil Company.</p>
                        <p>I am also acutely aware that it is essential to maintain the independence
                            of Iran and the flow of Iranian oil into the economy of the free
                            world.</p>
                        <p>Recent information which has reached me has led me to believe that the
                            Iranian Government is willing and even anxious to work out an
                            arrangement with His Majesty’s Government which would safeguard basic
                            British interests and which could satisfy the desires of the Iranian
                            people for nationalization of their petroleum resources.</p>
                        <p>The United States Government has expressed to His Majesty’s Government in
                            recent days its firm conviction that an opportunity is now presented by
                            the Iranian Government for negotiations which should be entered into at
                            once. We earnestly hope that His Majesty’s Government can despatch to
                            Tehran without delay qualified negotiators possessed of full powers to
                            reach a settlement with the Government of Iran, and who are prepared to
                            put forward in an appropriate way a specific proposal consistent with
                            the principle of nationalization, acceptance of which was indicated by
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHS1">Morrison</persName> in his remarks on
                            May 29 before the House of Commons.<note n="2" xml:id="d25fn2">For text
                                of <persName corresp="#p_MHS1">Morrison</persName>’s statement, see
                                    <hi rend="italic">Parliamentary Debates</hi>, House of Commons,
                                5th series, vol. 488, cols. 40–42.</note> I understand that, while
                            the Iranian Government’s invitation for representatives to
                                negotiate<note n="3" xml:id="d25fn3">On May 20 and 24, <persName>Ali
                                    Varasteh</persName>, Iranian Minister of Finance, addressed
                                letters to Seddon asking that the <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> nominate representatives for discussions on the
                                implementation of the oil nationalization law. On May 27, Seddon
                                transmitted a reply from <persName corresp="#p_FSW1">Fraser</persName> to <persName>Varasteh</persName>, stating
                                that the company could not accept the Iranian view of the oil
                                dispute, that it was asking the International Court of Justice to
                                appoint an arbitrator, and that Seddon would meet with Iranian
                                officials but only to listen to what they had to say and report it
                                to the <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> in London. For the
                                texts of these three messages, see British Cmd. 8425, pp.
                                36–38.</note> was addressed to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, the
                            Iranian Government has indicated that it would have no objections if
                            such company negotiators were also officials of His Majesty’s
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>I know that you are fully aware of the serious implications of this
                            explosive situation. I am sure you can understand my deep <pb facs="0087" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> concern that no action should be
                            taken in connection with this dispute which would result in disagreement
                            between Iran and the free world. I am confident that a solution
                            acceptable both to Great Britain and Iran can be found. I sincerely hope
                            that every effort will be made to accomplish this objective.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>