<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-01-17T13:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-01-17T13:30:00-05:00" n="285" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d285">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">888.2553/1–1753: Telegram</note>
                    <head>No. 285<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1" type="from">Henderson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d285fn1">Transmitted in two sections; repeated to London eyes
                            only for the Ambassador.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss></hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-01-17T22:00:00+03:30">January 17, 1953—10
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2761. Eyes only Secretary and <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName>.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I have just returned from relatively short visit (90 minutes) with
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName> who handed me his
                            reply to package proposals. This telegram being drafted as reply is
                            being translated. <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Saleh</persName>, Prime
                            Minister’s assistant, translated it aloud to me in <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName>’s presence and I tentatively
                            discussed certain passages with Prime Minister. Since latter told me it
                            had been approved by his parliamentary advisers and he would like for it
                            to go to Washington and London as approved, I did not try persuade him
                            make any changes.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>After we had exchanged amenities <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName> handed me envelope stating “here is reply which
                            I have promised you.”<note n="2" xml:id="d285fn2">See telegram 2762,
                                    <ref target="#d286"><hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>.</note> I
                            said that <pb facs="0654" n="628" xml:id="pg_628"/> before looking at
                            reply I would like to refer to his comments during our last conversation
                            re prices and rate of interest in <gloss target="#t_DMPA1">DMPA</gloss>
                            contract. United States Government was anxious oil settlement should be
                            achieved in way which would restore Iran’s credit in eyes of business
                            world. Oil settlement should therefore be on a completely businesslike
                            basis. There should not be even a hint that Iran was being given any
                            grants or any special consideration. United States desired to help Iran
                            and I was confident that if oil settlement was effected United States
                            would be contributing much more for Iran’s welfare during coming year
                            than it would receive in interest; nevertheless it seemed to US
                            preferable that there should be no connection between oil settlement and
                            any assistance which it might render Iran.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Prime Minister said he had spoken rather strongly re rate of interest.
                            He and intelligent Iranians could understand why proposed contract was
                            on businesslike basis. Iranian people in general, however, would never
                            be able understand why United States should give billion dollars to help
                            Turkey and yet charge 4 and ½ percent interest on loan this kind to
                            Iran. He did not wish urge United States not to charge interest.
                            Therefore in his reply to our proposals he had suggested that sale of
                            oil by Iran be reduced from $133 to $65 million, of which $50 million
                            would be advanced at once in cash and 25 percent of net proceeds from
                            sale would be placed in escrow for possible use in payment of
                            compensation. There would be no interest involved because there would be
                            no loan. Refined and crude oil to value $65 million would be delivered
                            immediately to US.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Prime Minister said there was another problem created by name of US
                            purchasing organization. It might be extremely embarrassing for Iranian
                            Government to enter into transaction this kind with Defense Materials
                            Procurement Agency. It would be charged in certain circles in Iran that
                            Government was entering into some kind defense pact with US. Therefore
                            he hoped that US Government either would buy direct from <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> or that <gloss target="#t_DMPA1">DMPA</gloss> would make purchase and extend loan through some
                            American company.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Referring to <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName>’s
                            suggestion that amount of purchase be reduced to $65 million I said that
                            he had been insisting that Iran have at least $100 million in cash.
                            Prime Minister said Iran sorely needed that amount but he preferred to
                            receive only 50 rather than for US to lose Iranian good will by charging
                            interest in advance. Iran could not deliver $133 million worth of oil
                            immediately; it could, however, deliver oil to value of $65 million. I
                            said I convinced that it would be more than 6 months before Iran could
                            have $65 million worth of crude and refined oil ready for delivery.
                            Furthermore in my opinion it would be probably 12 months before <pb facs="0655" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/> tankers could be found to move
                            so much oil from Iran. If he wanted $50 million immediately there would
                            undoubtedly be interest charges for a period of at least one year.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName> said he hoped some
                            device could be found so that there would be no reference to interest
                            charges in contract. I suggested that perhaps something might be
                            arranged by paying lower prices. He made no comment but I could see this
                            suggestion was not pleasing.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>I said that in my opinion Iran Government was leaning rather far
                            backward in hesitating to deal with <gloss target="#t_DMPA1">DMPA</gloss> because of its name. <gloss target="#t_DMPA1">DMPA</gloss> was not a part of US Department Defense. It
                            independent executive agency charged with buying many kinds of raw
                            materials. Any charges that contract between <gloss target="#t_DMPA1">DMPA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> was of
                            political character could be easily disproved. Prime Minister however
                            seemed to be somewhat stubborn on this point. He asked if it would not
                            be possible for purchase to be made through some private American
                            company if not through US Government direct. I suggested purchase might
                            be made through international company mentioned in original draft. He
                            replied that company not as yet organized. Contract should be signed
                            immediately because he needed money. I said I suppose he understood that
                            international company would probably furnish tankers to carry oil
                            because <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> had more tankers available
                            than any other company. He said that immaterial.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Prime Minister pointed out that in his counterproposals he had
                            suggested that price refined oil be set at discount of 35 percent from
                            average or middle US Gulf price rather than from low as stipulated in US
                            proposals. I told him I unable add to comments in this regard to those
                            which I had made in our previous conversation. I would submit his
                            proposals intact. He said that he willing accept our original proposals
                            re price of crude, that is 35 percent discount from Persian Gulf
                            price.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>I asked <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName> re status
                            arbitration agreement. He said his advisers disapproved entirely
                            structure which draft provided for arbitration panel. They were
                            convinced from careful examination of document as it stood that it meant
                            that in end panel would consist of five eminent jurists selected by
                            vice-president of <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>. Iran did not want
                            anybody other than <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> to adjudicate
                            dispute. I said only recourse in that case would be for Iran to agree
                            that other party would be UK rather than <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>. Prime Minister said that was precisely what he and
                            advisers had agreed. They decided they did not want this dispute settled
                            by arbitration before some panel of arbitrators. They wanted case to be
                            adjudicated by <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> in accordance with
                            its statute. Therefore, they would agree to admit UK Government as other
                            party. I asked him re terms of reference. <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Saleh</persName> translated them aloud. They were similar to those
                            drafted by <pb facs="0656" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> Prime Minister
                            during our session of January 15. I again said in my opinion they too
                            inflexible. He said his legal advisers insisted they were sufficiently
                            flexible to permit court to determine compensation due <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> in accordance with any British law
                            passed prior to Iran national law acceptable to <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>. I said I did not recall date of coal national law and
                            asked if this new stipulation would bar use of that law. He said such
                            was not intent. He would not object if draft was altered to read “any
                            British law passed prior to January 1, 1953”. He reiterated he had no
                            objection to use by British of coal national law.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>As <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Saleh</persName> translated various
                            passages of <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName>’s suggestions
                            re arbitration agreement I observed that according to those suggestions
                            25 percent of net proceeds of sales of oil rather than of gross
                            proceeds, were to be put in escrow for compensation. I said this a
                            recession from previous statements made to me. <persName corresp="#p_MM1">Mosadeq</persName> said he had previously been in
                            error, he had forgotten provisions of national law. Iran could not pay
                            larger percentage for compensation than that law provided.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Referring to proposed exchange of notes between British Government and
                            Iranian Government on subject of foreign ships entering Iranian ports
                            and of lifting by <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> of its ban on
                            exports of Iranian oil Prime Minister said he considered such exchange
                            unnecessary. I asked him if he meant by that that he thought
                            developments suggested in note would take place without such exchange.
                            He replied in affirmative. He said naturally as soon as agreement had
                            been reached for referring matter compensation to <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> Iran would not object to entry British
                            or <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> vessels into Iranian ports and
                            he was sure <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> would not continue to
                            prevent export Iranian oil.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>My comments in subsequent telegram.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HLW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>