<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 459The Ambassador in Iran (Henderson) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-08T07:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-08T07:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-08T07:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-08T07:30:00-05:00" n="459"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d459">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">888.2553/5–854: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 459<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1"
                            type="from">Henderson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d459fn1">Repeated to London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-08T16:00:00+03:30"
                            >May 8, 1954—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2288. From <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>. <gloss
                        target="#t_noforn1">Noforn</gloss>. Limited distribution.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Following analysis and recommendations are confined primarily to
                        management problem and related factors which are believed to be major items
                        to resolve in reaching successful oil agreement. More general appraisal of
                        present status negotiations included in Embassy telegram 2287 to Department
                        this date by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Henderson</persName>
                        London 709.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Iranian hesitancy to grant adequate management authority to consortium
                        during the present negotiations appears due to variety of reasons some more
                        apparent than others.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Most obvious is whether consortium should have right to operate for own
                        account which Iranians feel would be hopelessly in conflict with
                        nationalization laws. Although discussions have now switched to hypothetical
                        consideration of agency type agreement whereby consortium would operate for
                        account of Iranian Government, Iranians still appear hesitant.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>While inability of Iranians to make distasteful decisions has always been
                        problem it appears there may be at least three additional points upon which
                        they will require adequate assurances before they commit themselves on
                        management question, namely, nationality of operating companies, nationality
                        of management and location of consortium headquarters.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="1021" n="995" xml:id="pg_995"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">a. Nationality of operating companies.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>Incorporation of operating companies in UK is not acceptable to Iranians.
                        They would prefer Iran but will settle for a “neutral” country such as
                        Holland or Switzerland.</item>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> still officially insistent on UK. They
                        urge that matter be left until very end of negotiations with expressed hope
                        of either forcing it through or using it as a bargaining weapon in obtaining
                        one or both of other major points enumerated below.</item>
                    <label>III.</label>
                    <item>Consortium at present under obligation to UK Treasury to support UK
                        incorporation in return for receiving certain sterling operating privileges.
                        Companies however including <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> will not
                        accept Iranian incorporation. With exception of <gloss target="#t_AIOC1"
                            >AIOC</gloss> others would probably be glad settle for “neutral”
                        country. <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> would undoubtedly balk
                        severely at Holland due to rivalry with Shell although UK Treasury could
                        probably exert more control over sterling operations through Dutch domicile
                        than through Swiss. US companies and Shell privately express deep concern re
                        effect which UK incorporation would have on Iranians.</item>
                    <label>IV.</label>
                    <item>US Government not committed in this matter. We convinced however, that
                        incorporation of operating companies in UK would seriously jeopardize
                        durability of any agreement in Iran even assuming it could be pushed through
                        under pressure which seems unlikely. So far we have reserved our position
                        giving British full opportunity to urge their own point of view. It seems
                        advisable we assume more positive approach in near future and specific
                        recommendations outlined paragraph 8.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">b. Nationality of management.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>Nationality or company affiliation of managing director (and by inference
                        also that of top management staff) was not resolved or discussed at London
                        meetings or consortium. In private talks <persName corresp="#p_FSW1"
                            >Fraser</persName> expressed keen desire that Pattinson, former manager
                        for many years <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> in Iran and now one of
                        four co-managing directors of parent company should become managing director
                        of consortium. <persName corresp="#p_FSW1">Fraser</persName> named Pattinson
                        as <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> member of negotiating group and he
                        now in Iran.</item>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>Iranians have not yet raised matter of nationality or company affiliation
                        of top management in Iran. It seems quite certain from confidential
                        information available to us that Iranians will react even more violently
                        against return of <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> or British
                        management than they are now reacting against the proposed British
                        incorporation of operating companies.</item>
                    <label>III.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> will probably do utmost to maneuver
                        Britisher preferably <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> man into position
                        of managing director although matter has not yet been raised by them.</item>
                    <pb facs="1022" n="996" xml:id="pg_996"/>
                    <label>IV.</label>
                    <item>Shell and American companies privately express selves as firmly against
                            <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> management for both technical and
                        political reasons. They favor Shell individual of Dutch nationality as
                        managing director with as many additional Dutchmen in top management as
                        possible.</item>
                    <label>V.</label>
                    <item>French will probably line up with <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> if
                        they pressed into taking position.</item>
                    <label>VI.</label>
                    <item>US Government not committed to nationality of managing director or of his
                        company affiliation. We feel return of British personnel in top management
                        positions and particularly <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> would
                        jeopardize permanence of any agreement more seriously than any other single
                        factor. Our recommendations on this phase of negotiations when they arise
                        set forth paragraph 8.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">c. Location of Consortium Headquarters.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>There no discussion at company level in London of location of consortium
                        headquarters. <persName corresp="#p_FSW1">Fraser</persName> however
                        privately expressed opinion that headquarters should be located in <gloss
                            target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> offices at Britannic House in London and
                        that managing director would make his principal headquarters at that
                        place.</item>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>It certain that Iranians would object strenuously to having headquarters
                        of consortium located in London, particularly if it identified with <gloss
                            target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>. While this matter has not come up in
                        discussions with consortium it certain it would become major sticking point
                        if serious proposal were put forward to such effect.</item>
                    <label>III.</label>
                    <item>It assumed that <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> will support position
                        of <persName corresp="#p_FSW1">Fraser</persName> although <persName
                            corresp="#p_WDAH1">Denis Wright</persName> made strong statement in
                        favor establishing headquarters in Tehran during Foreign Office meetings in
                        London last March. It perhaps significant however, that after he had been in
                        London several days he would no longer express opinion on this point.</item>
                    <label>IV.</label>
                    <item>Shell and American companies feel strongly that headquarters of consortium
                        should be in Iran, and that managing director and entire staff should reside
                        permanently within country. It understood that these companies have taken
                        similar position with respect to headquarters of Iraq Petroleum Company, but
                        they have had no success in having offices removed from Britannic House in
                        London.</item>
                    <label>V.</label>
                    <item>It probable that French would line up with <gloss target="#t_AIOC1"
                            >AIOC</gloss> if they forced into taking position.</item>
                    <label>VI.</label>
                    <item>US Government under no commitment with regard to location of headquarters
                        for consortium. It is our opinion as in cases of nationality of companies
                        and of managing director that durability of agreement would be severely
                        affected if headquarters were located in UK. Specific recommendations set
                        forth paragraph 8.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="1023" n="997" xml:id="pg_997"/>
                <list>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Consortium representatives plan to hold series of meetings with principals
                        of their companies in approximately 2 to 3 weeks. They will then determine
                        feasibility of operating under agency type agreement and review other
                        details of proposals. Upon returning to Iran they would supposedly be ready
                        negotiate on final terms. Notwithstanding desire expressed by British
                        Ambassador to leave matter of nationality of companies until very last
                        moment (presumably after the consortium representatives return to Iran), we
                        believe this question as well as two others outlined above should be
                        discussed with Iranians before consortium leaves Iran. If possible decision
                        should be arrived at simultaneously with projected meeting of
                        principals.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>It my opinion that US companies and Shell will finally accept reasonable
                        type of agency agreement. In order maintain strong bargaining position at
                        present stage of negotiations, they apparently do not feel opportune time
                        has yet arrived for making such concession, nor could they do so without
                        authority from their principals.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>While there no present indication that negotiations are reaching an
                        impasse or breakdown, it certain that if such situation develops British
                        will do utmost to shift blame on to US companies or US Government wherever
                        possible. We should be constantly on guard against this type maneuver.
                            <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Harden</persName> aware of this
                        situation.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>We recommend that US position should be to urge strongly: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Against (i) incorporation in UK, (ii) British top management, and
                                (iii) headquarters in London.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>In favor of (i) incorporation in “neutral” country, (ii) top
                                management by non-UK–US personnel, and (iii) headquarters in
                                Iran.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>That these matters should be resolved at earliest possible moment,
                                and certainly not later than at same time as meeting of principals
                                scheduled within next 2 to 3 weeks.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>We further recommend that we maintain our position so that: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>If suitable occasion arises, we can advise <gloss target="#t_HMG1"
                                    >HMG</gloss> we will use our best efforts to convince US
                                companies (and Shell) to accept agency-type agreement, in interest
                                of effecting an overall settlement, on condition that <gloss
                                    target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> supports “neutral” nationality for
                                incorporation and top management.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>In event we fail in getting British to modify their demands,
                                including possible stalemate in UK–Iran compensation negotiations,
                                then we should be in position to announce that US companies will
                                accept agency-type agreement, and thus avoid any onus on US
                                Government of US companies for failure negotiations.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Situation here still sufficiently fluid that unforeseen developments may
                        require revision above analysis and recommendations in some details, but
                        believe broad outlines will remain regardless. <pb facs="1024" n="998"
                            xml:id="pg_998"/> It most unfortunate that attitude British Ambassador,
                        Treasury representatives and British Embassy Staff make certain of above
                        conclusions and recommendations necessary.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Ambassador fully concurs.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Views and comments of Department and London appreciated soonest.<note
                            n="2" xml:id="d459fn2">On May 12 the Embassy in London responded that it
                            believed it would be undesirable to approach the British with a view of
                            changing the British Government position on particular points of
                            disagreement until the points of difference between the consortium and
                            Iran had crystallized. In the Embassy’s judgment, the British would
                            remain insistent on obtaining compensation, though they would doubtless
                            be willing to reduce somewhat the figure of 100 million pounds in the
                            course of negotiation. The Embassy also believed that the British would
                            be almost as insistent on the issue of the nationality of the operating
                            companies. If, however, the British were to abandon the point of British
                            nationality, the Embassy thought the British would prefer Iranian
                            nationality rather than neutral nationality in order to be able to make
                            direct representations and, if necessary, be able to appeal to the
                            International Court and the United Nations rather than having to deal
                            with the Swiss or some other neutral government. (Telegram 5060;
                            888.2553/5–1254)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>End of message.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
