<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-21T09:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-21T09:30:00-05:00" n="496" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d496">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">888.2553/9–1254: Telegram</note>
                    <head>No. 496<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1" type="from">Henderson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-21T18:00:00+03:30">September 21, 1954—6
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>711. 1. Impression gained from conversations with various deputies and other
                        Iranians some of whom not friendly to government is that <persName corresp="#p_ADA1">Amini</persName> speech morning September 21
                        presenting oil agreement to Majlis great success.<note n="1" xml:id="d496fn1"><p>The Embassy in Tehran telegraphed the text of the
                                single article bill which Finance Minister <persName corresp="#p_ADA1">Amini</persName> had introduced to the Majlis
                                on Sept. 21 in telegram 733, Sept. 25. It reads as follows:</p>
                            <p>“Single article: The National Consultative Assembly ratifies and
                                authorizes the Government to enforce and exchange the attached
                                agreement, the first part of which includes 51 articles and two
                                supplements re the sale and purchase of oil and gas and re the
                                manner in which the operations specified in the agreement are to be
                                managed, and which is signed by Iran and the National Iranian Oil
                                Company on the one hand [and] by the Gulf Oil Corporation, Socony
                                Vacuum Company, Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, Standard Oil
                                Company of California, the Texas Oil Company, the Anglo-Iranian Oil
                                Company, Limited, N. V. Bataafsche Petroleum Maatschappij and the
                                Compagnie Francaise des Petroles on the other hand (and according to
                                article three of the agreement also signed by the operating
                                companies): and the second part of which includes five articles re
                                compensation and which is signed by Iran and the <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> on the one hand and the
                                Anglo-Iranian Oil Company on the other hand.</p>
                            <p>“All laws and provisions which are in contradiction with this law are
                                cancelled.” (888.2553/9–2554)</p></note> With Iranian subtlety he
                        answered in advance main arguments which opposition was certain present. He
                        did not pretend agreement all Iran would like to have but indicated it was
                        best obtainable. His speech was masterpiece of personal humility mingled
                        with lofty patriotism and was designed win support extreme nationalists as
                        well as partisans of West. He did not appear in role of suppliant but in
                        most polite terms indicated that government not prepared renegotiate in case
                        Majlis should find agreement not satisfactory.</p>
                    <pb facs="1080" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/>
                    <p>2. Newspaper accounts so conflicting we shall not endeavor send full summary
                        until we can obtain official text which we hope will be tomorrow. If
                        Department has received satisfactory summary through other sources please
                        telegraph.</p>
                    <p>3. Foreign Minister this morning told me government extremely pleased at
                        reception speech and with members elected by Majlis to joint oil committee.
                        He said he personally would have been happier if more opponents to agreement
                        would have been elected since he would prefer give them opportunity vent
                        their views in committee meeting rather than on floor Majlis. Foreign
                        Minister also stated that Senate today was electing its members to joint oil
                        committee so that joint committee would probably be given until September 25
                        to study agreements; and that it would meet on that date with Finance
                        Ministry and oil experts who would be prepared answer questions and give
                        explanations. Plan was joint committee would make its report to two houses
                        Parliament October 2. It was hoped ratification could be achieved by October
                        9.</p>
                    <p>4. Embassy obtained this afternoon list members elected by Senate to oil
                        committee which it is analyzing. Our first impression is that only member
                        likely make real trouble is Lesani. Details later.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HLW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>