<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-19T01:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-19T01:30:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">888.2553/8–1951: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 72<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Special Assistant to the President
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_HWA1" type="from">Harriman</persName>) to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d72fn1">Repeated to London eyes only for the
                                Ambassador.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-19T10:00:00+03:30">August 19, 1951—10
                                a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>705. From <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> for President
                            and Secretary. No distribution except as directed by Secretary’s office.
                            British met with Iran negotiating committee this afternoon
                                (Saturday<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">Aug. 18.</note>) for an
                            informal exchange of views regarding British proposal. I was asked to
                            participate. Iran group had been released by Prime Minister to express
                            their opinions. However, these generally conformed to position taken by
                            Prime Minister. They maintained that proposal did not conform to formula
                            submitted through me principally on point that British control of both
                            purchasing organization and operating agency means return to <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> with thin disguise. Other objections
                            were raised that as that purchasing organization would have <pb facs="0167" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> substantial monopoly of Iran
                            exports, and that principle of 50–50 division of profit was inequitable,
                            particularly if combined with payment for assets taken over. Such
                            arrangements it was contended would not be acceptable to Iran public
                            opinion. <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName> gave obvious
                            replies explaining the commercial aspects of world oil business and
                            necessity of creating arrangements which would induce British staff to
                            remain in Iran. He was rather general in his comments on the control of
                            operation by <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> and also suggested
                            that it was Iran politician problem to deal with their public opinion.
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName> stated he believed
                            Irans would obtain under his proposal three times as much as they did in
                            1950. This would be about 50 million pounds on 1950 basis. He said he
                            could not remain indefinitely and it was therefore agreed they would
                            hold two meetings a day, the next one to be 10 a.m. tomorrow
                            (Sunday).</p>
                        <p>At close of mtg I expressed my satisfaction that the two groups were at
                            last talking informally and hoped that through this type of discussion
                            an understanding could be reached. I stated I believed that the
                            proposals put forward by British for discussion provided good basis for
                            negotiation and that arrangements could be worked out under these
                            proposals which would be within formula under which Brit mission had
                            been asked to come to negotiate. In specific reply to some of Iran’s
                            comments I stated that I did not consider these proposals as disguise.
                            British were negotiating in good faith and in my opinion proper
                            safeguards could be agreed to which would protect Iran interests and
                            establish appropriate control by <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss>.
                            I said that <persName corresp="#p_LWJ1">Levy</persName> and I would be
                            glad to discuss details of this with Iran group should they wish to do
                            so and I had had similar informal talks with <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName>. In this manner Irans could get <persName corresp="#p_LWJ1">Levy</persName>’s advice as to manner in which
                            proper arrangements could be made in conformance to practical aspects of
                            oil business.</p>
                        <p>Since Irans had talked of oil installations as Iran Govt property and had
                            referred rather generally to compensation, I stated that I could not
                            become involved in details of compensation but that I felt I shld state
                            my govt’s position on nationalization. We recognized right of any govt
                            to nationalize fon-owned property providing either mutually satisfactory
                            arrangements were worked out with previous owners or prompt and adequate
                            compensation was made. We recognized right of nationalization but not
                            right of confiscation. I said I felt sure that these principles were
                            accepted by Iran group and that as there were not funds available to
                            make adequate prompt compensation they would work out mutually
                            satisfactory arrangements with British interests. After I finished
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName> sent me a note saying
                            it was vital that I state Brit proposals had my full support and came
                            within the formula. As I felt my position stated above was clear and as
                            far as I should go at this time I made <pb facs="0168" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> no further comment on this aspect. In my opinion
                            arrangements under British proposal can be worked out to result in
                            either camouflage for complete return of British control or adequate
                            recognition of <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss>’s right to
                            appropriate control, safeguarding against practices which Irans objected
                            to in past.</p>
                        <p>At close of meeting Irans handed <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName> written reply to his proposals. This was in
                            Iranian language and I will not get translation until tomorrow morning.
                            It was agreed that this reply wld be released at 9 p.m. Tehran time
                            Sunday. After considering contents of Iran reply I will decide whether I
                            should make statement to press and the form of such statement. My
                            problem is that if I do not make a statement my silence will be
                            interpreted by Irans that I do not consider Brit proposal conforms with
                            formula. I am afraid that this will mean that they will make no genuine
                            attempt to come to agreement and expect us to bail them out after break
                            with British. On the other hand it is difficult to find language which
                            will reasonably satisfy Brit and not give Irans impression that I have
                            “sold out” to British.<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3">The Iranian reply
                                rejected <persName corresp="#p_SRR1">Stokes</persName>’ proposal
                                because it did not conform with the law nationalizing the Iranian
                                oil industry, stating in particular that the points concerning the
                                purchasing organization, the price of oil and the division of
                                profits, the operating organization, and compensation were not
                                satisfactory. <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>
                                transmitted a translation of the reply at noon on Aug. 19 in
                                telegram 706. (888.2553/8–1951) For the complete text, see British
                                Cmd. 8425, pp. 55–57 or <hi rend="italic">Documents</hi> (R.I.I.A.)
                                for 1951, pp. 504–506.</note></p>
                        <closer>[<signed><persName corresp="#p_HWA1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi></persName></signed>]</closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>