<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Herrick) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1924v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-05-13T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-05-13T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-05-13T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-05-13T09:00:00-05:00" n="100"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00 R 294/365: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Herrick</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-05-13T15:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 13, 1924—3 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7:15 p.m.<note n="45" xml:id="d100fn45">Telegram in three
                            sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>255. L–161, from Logan. The Belgian representative on the Reparation Commission
                    has approached me on the following matter: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The sum of approximately 100,000,000 gold marks is on deposit at
                            Coblenz as the net product of the Ruhr occupation obtained jointly by
                            Belgium and France. France is agreeable to handing this sum over to
                            Belgium directly for application on Belgian priority, deeming it to be
                            reparation money.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>To avoid at this important juncture raising difficult questions of the
                            legality of the Ruhr occupation and Belgian accounting for Ruhr army
                            costs, etc., both Belgium and France prefer not to put this money
                            through the Reparation Commission in the regular course. Bradbury<note
                                n="46" xml:id="d100fn46">Sir John Bradbury, British representative
                                on the Reparation Commission.</note> thinks it highly desirable to
                            avoid raising issues such as these at present and does not object to the
                            proposed disposition of funds.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Belgian representative states it is feeling of Prime Minister Theunis
                            that in fact and in equity even if not technically the payment does
                            constitute a cash reparation payment and thereby falls within intent of
                            language of Army Costs Agreement.<note n="47" xml:id="d100fn47">
                                <ref target="frus1923v02#pg_180">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 180</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>In spite of fact that Army Costs Agreement has not been ratified,
                            Belgian representative says that his Government, following broad policy
                            outlined in Bemelmans’ letter of November 22, 1923,<note n="48"
                                xml:id="d100fn48">Not printed.</note> which I forwarded to
                            Department in December, 1923, feels bound morally to put aside 25
                            percent of amount it receives in a blocked or special account which will
                            be available to Government of the United States in part payment of
                            American Army costs if and when Army Costs Agreement is ratified.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>I do not see any objection, under the circumstances, to our
                            Government’s accepting special agreement, and I feel that the possible
                            chance of our getting several million dollars should not be lost. We
                            shall not be entangled indirectly in Ruhr controversy because funds
                            would not be specifically set aside for us as Ruhr proceeds, but <pb
                                facs="0235" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> instead would be merely a cash
                            reparation settlement received from Germany by Belgium without regard to
                            the immediate source.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>I suggest that the Department authorize me to communicate with the
                            Belgian representative in terms substantially as follows (if place of
                            deposit or method of withdrawal is unsatisfactory, a change in either
                            instance would readily be made):<note n="49" xml:id="d100fn49">Proposed
                                communication not paraphrased.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I have not failed to communicate to my Government the generous
                                    proposal which you have made that 25 percent of a cash sum of
                                    approximately 100 million gold marks which the Belgian
                                    Government expects shortly to receive upon the reparation
                                    account of Germany should be set aside in some special or
                                    blocked account for the ultimate benefit of the United States in
                                    view of the fact that by the terms of the pending agreement
                                    relative to the reimbursement of the costs of the American Army
                                    of Occupation to which Belgium is a signatory, the United States
                                    would be entitled to 25 percent of the cash reparation receipts
                                    subject to certain modifications which are not material for the
                                    present purposes. It is understood that although the agreement
                                    is not yet effective, the Belgian Government is ready to set
                                    aside 25 percent of the sum in question for payment to the
                                    United States as soon as the agreement shall have been
                                    ratified.</p>
                                <p>I have the honor to advise last [<hi rend="italic">you?</hi>]
                                    that the Government of the United States accepts the proposal
                                    which you have made and appreciates the liberal attitude of the
                                    Belgian Government in spontaneously suggesting this action. My
                                    Government will be pleased should the Belgian Government see fit
                                    to carry its suggestion into effect by causing the Banque
                                    Nationale de Belgique to open a special account in the Federal
                                    Reserve Bank of New York to be known as the ‘American Army costs
                                    account’ into which shall be deposited in dollars the proper
                                    proportion of the cash reparation payments now under
                                    consideration and withdrawals from which shall be made upon the
                                    order of the Treasurer of the United States if and when the
                                    agreement relative to the reimbursement of the costs of the
                                    American Army of Occupation is ratified and pending such
                                    ratification shall be effected only by a specific decision of
                                    the Reparations Commission in each case.</p>
                                <p>Accept, etc., etc.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>(7)</label>
                        <item>The method set forth above of creating deposits follows line taken
                            with respect to relinquishment of all cash payments subject to
                            requirements of Reparation Commission in regular course. To introduce
                            Reparation Commission as protective medium against the withdrawal of
                            money for purposes besides payment of American Army costs does not
                            involve commission in decision of any question about the Ruhr, for by
                            that time money will have lost entirely its identity as a Ruhr product
                            and will be merely the property of the Belgian Government in dollars
                            which is put aside for the benefit of the Government of the United
                            States upon ratification of the Army <pb facs="0236" n="142"
                                xml:id="pg_142"/> Costs Agreement. The Separation Commission, having
                            in view the fiduciary nature of its prerogative, would not in practice
                            permit withdrawals from account unless it were clear that the Army Costs
                            Agreement was to fail of ratification, and I could always keep an eye
                            upon any proposed decision secured by this account to be made by the
                            commission.</item>
                        <label>(8)</label>
                        <item>I believe that the creation of deposit will be effective moral force
                            in bringing about ratification of the agreement. Logan. Copies sent to
                            Great Britain, Italy, and Belgium.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Herrick</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
