<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-09-02T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-09-02T15:00:00-05:00" n="165" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">667n.113/1: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kellogg</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-09-02T16:00:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">September 2,
                                        1924—4 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>315. The American Consul at Jerusalem, under date of August 19, 1924,
                            telegraphed the Department “New customs duties amendment ordinance
                            increasing considerably rate on imported articles published August 15th,
                            and duty collected under new schedule from August 18th”.</p>
                        <p>As you are aware, this Government has consistently taken the position
                            that pending the final determination of the status of the territories
                            detached from the Ottoman Empire, and in the absence of the assent of
                            the interested Powers to the suspension or modification of the rights
                            derived from the capitulations, the authorities administering
                            territories detached from the Ottoman Empire are bound by the
                            obligations incident to the existence of the capitulatory regime. By
                            virtue of the capitulations American citizens in Palestine are entitled
                            to exemption from all taxes except such as are approved by this
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>You should call the foregoing to the attention of the British Government
                            and say that this Government would be pleased to receive an expression
                            of the views of the British Government with respect to the situation in
                            Palestine which has arisen as a result of the reported attempt to
                            collect from American citizens an increased customs duty to which the
                            assent of this Government had not been previously requested.</p>
                        <p>You may likewise inform the British Government that the Department has
                            forwarded to you by mail a note to be communicated <pb facs="0295" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> to the British Government assenting,
                            except as regards certain minor points, to the proposals made by the
                            British Government in its note of July 17, 1924 enclosed with your
                            despatch No. 606 of July 24, 1924.<note n="21" xml:id="d165fn21"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_207">p.
                                207</ref>.</note> You may add that this Government confidently
                            expects that it will be possible to sign the proposed Palestine Mandate
                            convention at an early date. Repeat to American Consul Jerusalem for his
                            information only.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>