<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Kellogg) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1924v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="189"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.62 m 31/27</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kellogg</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-07-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 2, 1924</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received July 11.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 537</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In connection with my despatch No. 503, of June
                    17, 1924,<note n="66" xml:id="d189fn66">Not printed.</note> I have the honor to
                    enclose a copy, in triplicate, of a note from the Foreign Office dated June 30,
                    1924, together with its enclosures, concerning the subject in hand, namely the
                    question of the discriminatory tariff imposed by New Zealand on American goods
                    in the British mandate territory of Samoa. It appears that the Government of New
                    Zealand would be willing to accede to the request of the United States
                    Government for national treatment for its commerce and commercial vessels in
                    Western Samoa, provided that the United States Government on its part is willing
                    to give a specific assurance of its understanding that Article 3 of the
                    Convention of 1899 ensures to British commerce and commercial vessels national
                    treatment in that part of Samoa under United States administration.</p>
                <p>An examination of the full text of the note will show that this raises the
                    question of whether under our Coastwise Trading Act British ships bound for the
                    United States may call at Tutuila and carry goods and passengers between that
                    port and the United States under the same condition as our coastwise ships. I
                    have not had time to examine this question but am sending the note on for your
                    inspection.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">G. R. Warner</persName> of the
                            American and African Department of the British Foreign Office to the
                            American Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kellogg</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-06-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1924</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. A3920/2287/45</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: With reference to our
                        conversation on the 10th April last,<note n="67" xml:id="d189fn67">See
                            telegram no. 123, April 10, from the Ambassador in Great Britain, <ref
                                target="#pg_242">p. 242</ref>.</note> I have the honour to inform
                        Your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government have discussed with the
                        Government of New Zealand the question dealt with in previous correspondence
                        ending with Mr. Harvey’s note No. 1071 of the 20th [<hi rend="italic"
                            >25th</hi>] October, 1923,<note n="66" xml:id="d189fn65">Not
                            printed.</note> with regard to the rights claimed by the United States
                        in Western Samoa under article 3 of the Convention concluded at Washington
                        on the 2nd December, 1899, between the United Kingdom, Germany and the
                        United States.</p>
                    <pb facs="0338" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>You will observe that it is provided in the same article of that
                            convention that each of the three signatory powers shall continue to
                            enjoy in respect of their commerce and commercial vessels in all the
                            islands of the Samoan group privileges and conditions equal to those
                            enjoyed by the sovereign power in all ports which may be open to the
                            commerce of either of them. It will be remembered that in 1911 the
                            United States authorities had exercised some discrimination against
                            British ships trading between Pago Pago and Leone in Tutuila. On that
                            occasion inquiries were made of your government, who stated that Leone
                            was not a port of entry; but in the course of the correspondence which
                            ensued the United States Government admitted that British ships were
                            entitled to the same treatment as United States and German ships in this
                            respect (in this connection I would refer you to the note from the State
                            Department to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Washington of the 5th
                            February, 1912, et cetera<note n="69" xml:id="d189fn68">Not
                                printed.</note>). In the same year also a complaint was made by a
                            British firm that bills of health were being issued gratis by the United
                            States Consul at Apia to United States vessels trading between Apia and
                            Pago Pago, while a charge was made for similar bills of health issued to
                            British vessels trading on the same route. This complaint being brought
                            to the notice of the United States Government, it was decided by the
                            State Department in 1913 that the exaction of fees from British vessels
                            while United States vessels were exempt was contrary to article 3 of the
                            Convention of 1899, and instructions were accordingly given for the
                            collection of such fees to be discontinued (see note from the State
                            Department to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Washington, 15th October,
                                1913<note n="69" xml:id="d189fn69">Not printed.</note>). The United
                            States Government were thus, in 1913, of opinion that the convention
                            prevented preference in this respect being given to United States ships
                            trading with American Samoa.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Government of New Zealand have also called my attention to the
                            fact that, owing to the operation of the United States coast-wise laws,
                            British ships trading from New Zealand to San Francisco are no longer
                            able to call at Honolulu and to carry goods and passengers between that
                            port and San Francisco. Consequently, British ships can no longer call
                            at Honolulu except those on the Vancouver mail service. It is,
                            therefore, a matter of considerable importance to the Government of New
                            Zealand that British ships trading between New Zealand and the United
                            States should be able to call at Tutuila and, if necessary, to carry
                            goods and passengers between that port and the United States under the
                            same conditions as United States ships.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In the circumstances the Government of New Zealand would be willing to
                            consider the request of the United States Government for <pb facs="0339"
                                n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> national treatment for their commerce and
                            commercial vessels in Western Samoa, provided the United States
                            Government on their part are willing to give a specific assurance of
                            their understanding that article 3 of the Convention of 1899 ensures to
                            British commerce and commercial vessels national treatment in that part
                            of Samoa under United States administration.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>At the request of the Government of New Zealand, I have the honour to
                            append a communication received from them by His Majesty’s Government
                            stating their position in this matter.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>I beg leave further to refer you to your personal letter to me of
                            April 10th, giving the only case which you have been able to trace of
                            any case of discrimination against British vessels in ports of Samoa
                            under United States administration. In this connection I have the honour
                            to point out that the discrimination of which complaint is made by His
                            Majesty’s Government is rather that involved by the extension to
                            American Samoa of the coast-wise laws restricting trade between United
                            States ports to vessels of United States registry, which was provided
                            for by section 21 of the United States Merchant Marine Act of June 5th,
                                1920.<note n="70" xml:id="d189fn70">41 Stat 988.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>With regard to the statement contained in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >aide-memoire</hi> which you were so good as to leave with me on
                            April 10th last, to the effect that an Order in Council of September
                            25th, 1923, admits the entry free of duty into Western Samoa of German
                            and Austrian goods, I have the honour to enclose herein a copy of the
                            Order in Council in question, and of that of the 3rd September, 1923,
                            which it amended.<note n="71" xml:id="d189fn71">Neither printed.</note>
                            You will observe that the Order in Council of the 25th September only
                            dispensed with the necessity for a licence in respect of German and
                            Austrian goods imported into Western Samoa after April 1st, 1924, and
                            did not provide for their entry free of duty.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. R. Warner</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure—Telegram]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Governor General of New
                                Zealand</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British Secretary of
                                State</gloss> for the Colonies</hi>
                    </head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The New Zealand Government acting by His Majesty’s delegation as
                            mandatory authority of Western Samoa regrets any apparent delay in reply
                            to the representation of the United States Government on the subject of
                            British preferential duties in Western Samoa.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>This Government had, however, believed that the United States
                            Government understood the points of difference and this Government were
                            awaiting an intimation from the United States Government <pb facs="0340"
                                n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/> that the Tripartite Treaty of 1899
                            prevented the United States from restrictions upon British shipping in
                            American Samoa.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The New Zealand Government has recognised that the question whether
                            obligations of Tripartite Treaty are still imposed on Western Samoa,
                            notwithstanding its transition from German Sovereignty to mandatory
                            authority, is one to be determined by the Law Officers of the Crown in
                            England and in deference to their advice has not contended that it is
                            free from those obligations.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>But this government has maintained that Tripartite Treaty is equally
                            binding upon the Government of American Samoa and therefore that
                            restrictions upon British shipping in American Samoa are at least as
                            inconsistent with Tripartite Treaty as are the British preferential
                            duties in Western Samoa.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>If the Government of the United States definitely concede that New
                            Zealand ships and all British ships are entitled to carry goods and
                            passengers between American ports and ports of American Samoa, and that
                            British shipping will receive exactly the same treatment in all other
                            respects in such trade as American ships, both in American Samoa and in
                            United States ports, then the New Zealand Government will reciprocally
                            legislate to place American imports in the same position as the British
                            imports in Western Samoa.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
