<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-03-27T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-03-27T17:00:00-05:00" n="194" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">125.655/122: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kellogg</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-03-27T17:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">March 27,
                                        1924—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>74. Your 102, March 26, noon.</p>
                        <p>The Department is gratified to learn that there is good prospect of
                            settling the Newcastle case along lines previously agreed on.</p>
                        <pb facs="0344" n="250" xml:id="pg_250"/>
                        <p>I wrote you letter March 25, in answer to your letter February 27,
                            regarding the case.<note n="77" xml:id="d194fn77">Neither
                                printed.</note> My letter was sent by pouch yesterday and reiterates
                            Department’s position in the matter.</p>
                        <p>In discussing the case you should reiterate understanding already reached
                            which has been fully covered in previous telegrams and instructions.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Publication of the notes shall immediately follow the exchange. It
                                is the opinion of the Department that this exchange should occur in
                                London, but that publication should be simultaneous in London and in
                                Washington.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>That at the time of publication the Department will also announce
                                that the British Government has agreed that Slater and Brooks may be
                                assigned to posts within the British Empire and will shortly be sent
                                to such posts.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>That the British Government agrees to issue the necessary
                                exequatur and recognition to Slater and Brooks when they are sent to
                                Fort William and Port Arthur and to Belfast, respectively.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I have today had a conversation with the British Ambassador on this
                            subject and have read to him the text of this instruction.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>