<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-12-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.6831/60</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Laughlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-12-09"><hi rend="italic">December 9,
                                1924</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received January 5, 1925.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 197</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: My telegram No. 111, December 8th, 9
                                P.M.,<note n="21" xml:id="d226fn21">Not printed.</note> will have
                            informed you that I had found reason to believe that Mr. Roussos had not
                            carried out the promise I reported in my No. 110, December 5th, 5
                                P.M.,<note n="21" xml:id="d226fn22">Not printed.</note> to instruct
                            the Greek Legation in Washington to effect the exchange of notes you
                            desired for establishing a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> to cover
                            the period between the lapse on the 10th instant of the commercial
                            treaty with Greece and the conclusion of another treaty to replace
                            it.</p>
                        <p>I confirmed this by questioning the Chief of the Treaty Section of the
                            Foreign Office, as I was unable to have immediate access to the Foreign
                            Minister, and after making clear to him my feelings and intentions he
                            consented to accompany me forthwith to the Minister whom I found
                            assisting at the sitting of the National Assembly then in progress.</p>
                        <p>I succeeded without much difficulty in convincing Mr. Roussos of your
                            fixed desire to arrange the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                            according to the draft note you had communicated to him through the
                            Greek Legation in Washington and through this Legation, and expressed my
                            surprise at his failure to fulfil the promise I had had the honor to
                            report to you. In these circumstances I felt it necessary to insist that
                            he rectify the omission forthwith, but as the telegram he wrote in my
                            presence and read to me seemed to me not altogether certain to bring
                            about the result you desired, since it was susceptible of the
                            construction that the instructions to make the exchange of notes in
                            Washington might be dependent upon future action by the Greek National
                            Assembly, I expressed my dissatisfaction so forcibly that he himself
                            proposed to reassure me by making the exchange in Athens to-day after
                            the action he affirmed the Assembly was on the point of taking to
                            postpone the operation of the new customs tariff for some weeks.</p>
                        <p>Being convinced of your anxiety to arrange definitely a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> before December 10th apart from any
                            problematical Greek legislative action, I felt that this was the only
                            way to make sure of such a result and I therefore took it upon myself to
                            make the exchange with him to-day, not contingent upon any action of the
                            Greek Assembly, but as a positive engagement, subject however to your
                            subsequent confirmation since I had to take account of the <pb facs="0372" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/> arrangement you expected to
                            carry out of exchanging the notes in Washington. I felt that in view of
                            this intention you perhaps had omitted to inform me as fully as you
                            might have done had your original desire been for me to conclude the
                            business here, so I took the precaution of stating that I would make the
                            exchange subject to your later approval.</p>
                        <p>The exchange of notes was accordingly effected this morning as reported
                            in my No. 112, December 9th, 4 P.M.,<note n="23" xml:id="d226fn23">Not
                                printed.</note> and I have the honor to enclose herewith the two
                            notes establishing the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> of which the
                            Greek note is the original and mine the copy, and the copy of the note
                            by which I provided for your explicit assent to it.</p>
                        <p>I also enclose the copy of a Greek note<note n="23" xml:id="d226fn25">Not
                                printed.</note> presented to me at the time of the exchange which
                            tells of the passage last night by the National Assembly of a bill
                            giving the Government power to negotiate with other countries commercial
                            agreements to have a maximum duration of six months. During the
                            discussion of this bill the Finance Minister stated that he had no
                            objection to the postponement of the new tariff until the 1st of March,
                            the Assembly thereafter deciding to follow that course. The Department
                            will form its own conclusion as to the bearing, if any there be, that
                            this note may have upon the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> just
                            concluded. My telegram No. 113, December 9th, 5 P.M.,<note n="23" xml:id="d226fn26">Not printed.</note> reported this tariff
                            postponement.</p>
                        <p>In view of the many objections to the new duties raised during the
                            discussion in the Assembly yesterday evening the Government as well as
                            the party leaders agreed to the appointment of a Parliamentary Committee
                            to study the matter and to make any changes they might consider
                            necessary. One of the reasons for the delay in the application of the
                            tariff is the necessity of giving this Commission a reasonable time for
                            the completion of its work.</p>
                        <p>I take the liberty, in concluding, to express the hope that in examining
                            my action in this case you will consider the fact that it was determined
                            by your anxiously expressed desire to establish a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> without fail on or before December 10th and that
                            in making the exchange of notes here without your instructions, and in
                            fact with the knowledge that it should have been done in Washington, I
                            knew that unless I assumed this responsibility your wishes could not be
                            carried through.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Irwin Laughlin</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0373" n="279" xml:id="pg_279"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Laughlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Greek Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Roussos</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-12-09"><hi rend="italic">December 9,
                                        1924</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 73</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: As your Excellency is
                                aware the Secretary of State has communicated to the Hellenic Chargé
                                d’Affaires in Washington the desire of the Government of the United
                                States to conclude in the near future with the Hellenic Government a
                                comprehensive treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Consular Rights
                                which may serve as a lasting basis for economic and other
                                intercourse between the two countries and their nationals.</p>
                            <p>Your Excellency has also been apprised that pending the conclusion of
                                such a treaty the Government of the United States desires to effect
                                with the Hellenic Government a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                                by means of an exchange of notes.</p>
                            <p>I have therefore the honor to make to your Excellency the
                                communication embodied in my note No. 74 of to-day’s date which is
                                identical with the text I have received from my Government of the
                                draft note proposed to the Hellenic Legation in Washington, and to
                                add that I propose that this exchange of notes be effected in Athens
                                to-day in default of the exchange of notes that might have taken,
                                place in Washington before the 10th day of December 1924, or in
                                addition to such exchange there, should it occur, with the
                                understanding that in the former case the exchange is effected
                                subject to the confirmation of the Secretary of State in Washington
                                and that in the latter case the exchange of notes in Washington is
                                to be regarded as superseding that of to-day in Athens.</p>
                            <p>I embrace this opportunity to renew to your Excellency the assurances
                                of my highest consideration.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Irwin
                                Laughlin</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Laughlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Greek Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Roussos</hi></persName>)<note n="24" xml:id="d226fn24">The
                                    Greek Minister for Foreign Affairs replied in note no. 44543,
                                    Dec. 9, 1924, which differed only on very minor points from the
                                    note presented by the American Minister. The French text of the
                                    Greek note is printed in Treaty Series No. 706.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-12-09"><hi rend="italic">December 9,
                                        1924</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 74</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to make
                                the following statement of my understanding of the agreement reached
                                through recent conversations held at Washington on behalf of the
                                Government of the United States and the Government of Greece with
                                reference to the treatment which the United States shall accord to
                                the commerce <pb facs="0374" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> of Greece and
                                which Greece shall accord to the commerce of the United States:</p>
                            <p>These conversations have disclosed a mutual understanding between the
                                two governments which is that in respect to import, export and other
                                duties and charges affecting commerce as well as in respect to
                                transit, warehousing and other facilities and the treatment of
                                commercial travelers samples, the United States will accord to
                                Greece and Greece will accord to the United States, its territories
                                and possessions, unconditional most favored nation treatment, and
                                that in the matter of licensing or prohibitions of imports and
                                exports, each country, so far as it at any time maintains such a
                                system, shall accord to the commerce of the other treatment as
                                favorable, with respect to commodities, valuations and quantities,
                                as may be accorded to the commerce of any other country. It is
                                understood that no higher or other duties shall be imposed on the
                                importation into or disposition in the United States, its
                                territories or possessions, of any articles, the produce or
                                manufacture of Greece, than are or shall be payable on like
                                articles, the produce or manufacture of any foreign country; no
                                higher or other duties shall be imposed on the importation into or
                                disposition in Greece of articles, the produce or manufacture of the
                                United States, its territories or possessions than are or shall be
                                payable on like articles, the produce or manufacture of any foreign
                                country; similarly, no higher or other duties shall be imposed in
                                the United States, its territories or possessions, or in Greece on
                                the exportation of any articles to the other or to any territory or
                                possession of the other than are payable on the exportation of like
                                articles to any foreign country; every concession with respect to
                                any duty, charge or regulation affecting commerce now accorded or
                                that may hereafter be accorded by the United States or by Greece, by
                                law, proclamation, decree or commercial treaty or agreement, to any
                                third country will become immediately applicable without request and
                                without compensation to the commerce of Greece and of the United
                                States and its territories and possessions respectively;</p>
                            <p>Provided that this understanding does not relate to <list>
                                    <label>1)</label>
                                    <item>The treatment which the United States accords or may
                                        hereafter accord to the commerce of Cuba, or any of the
                                        territories or possessions of the United States, or the
                                        Panama Canal Zone, or to the treatment which is or may
                                        hereafter be accorded to the commerce of the United States
                                        with any of its territories or possessions, or to the
                                        commerce of its territories or possessions with one
                                        another;</item>
                                    <label>2)</label>
                                    <item>Prohibitions or restrictions of a sanitary character or
                                        designed to protect human, animal or plant life or
                                        regulations for the enforcement of police or revenue
                                        laws.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The present arrangement shall become operative on the day of
                                signature, and, unless sooner terminated by mutual agreement, shall
                                    <pb facs="0375" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/> continue in force
                                until thirty days after notice of its termination shall have been
                                given by either party, but should either party be prevented by
                                future action of its legislature from carrying out the terms of this
                                arrangement, the obligations thereof shall thereupon lapse.</p>
                            <p>I shall be glad to have your confirmation of the accord thus
                                reached.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Irwin
                                Laughin</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>