<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-07-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="311" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.945/1189</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-07-08"><hi rend="italic">July 8,
                                1924</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received July 25.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 571–E</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Embassy’s telegram No.
                            174, of July 2, 1924,<note n="68" xml:id="d311fn68">Not printed.</note>
                            I have the honor to transmit herewith the full text of the speech
                            delivered by Baron Shidehara at the opening of the Diet on July 1,
                            1924.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Jefferson
                            Caffery</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extract]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Speech by the Japanese Minister for Foreign
                                    Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shidehara</hi>) <hi rend="italic">at the Opening of the Japanese Diet, July 1,
                                    1924</hi><note n="69" xml:id="d311fn69">Translation as printed
                                    in <hi rend="italic">The Japan Advertiser</hi>, Tokyo, July 2,
                                    1924.</note></head>
                            <p>As you are aware, a new Immigration Act recently passed the United
                                States Congress, and having been approved by the President, it has
                                been finally written into the statute-books of the country. As to
                                the genesis of this Act, you will recall that of late years in the
                                United States, immigration from foreign countries, especially from
                                Southern and Eastern Europe, has been showing a marked increase. It
                                has come to be generally believed that it will <pb facs="0503" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> be a matter of practical difficulty to
                                merge these foreign elements in the homogeneous community of
                                original Americans. It has accordingly been felt necessary to impose
                                a more rigorous restriction upon foreign immigration. As for the
                                emigration of Japanese laborers to the United States, an arrangement
                                popularly called the Gentlemen’s Agreement has long been in force.
                                Under that arrangement the Japanese Government has been exercising a
                                prohibitory control over the departure to the United States of all
                                classes of laborers except certain relatives of those living in the
                                United States and persons who are returning to that country after a
                                temporary visit to Japan. Consequently, the increase of new Japanese
                                immigrants in the United States has not been, in fact, of any
                                appreciable number. It is believed that the new Immigration Act was
                                originally intended to institute a rigorous restriction of
                                immigration in general, and that there was no reason for embodying
                                in the Act a provision designed specifically to exclude Japanese
                                immigrants. It is sincerely to be regretted that while the Bill was
                                under discussion in Congress, certain leaders of anti-Japanese
                                persuasions should have succeeded in putting through a clause to the
                                effect that aliens ineligible to citizenship should, as a rule, be
                                denied admission into the United States.</p>
                            <p>In reviewing the development of this question, there are three points
                                which engage our attention.</p>
                            <list>
                                <item>First, no intimation has lately been made, even by the
                                    exclusionists, of any inferiority of the Japanese race. Their
                                    contention is in effect that the Japanese are to the Americans
                                    what oil is to water. Neither oil nor water can be said to be
                                    superior or inferior to the other, but the fact is that in no
                                    case can oil dissolve and merge in water. In other words, they
                                    say, Japanese are unassimilable to American life, and the
                                    introduction of such alien elements will prove a source of
                                    danger to the United States. Such an argument formed one of the
                                    essential phases for the exclusion of Japanese; it was not on
                                    the ground of the inferiority of the Japanese race that the
                                    exclusion clause was adopted. It should, however, be pointed out
                                    that the plea of Japanese unassimilability is no more than an
                                    arbitrary presumption unsupported by any evidence of facts. Our
                                    views on this point have been already roughly set forth in the
                                    Note of May 31 last addressed by the Japanese Government to the
                                    Government of the United States.</item>
                                <item>Secondly, it has always been consistently maintained by the
                                    United States, that the liberty to limit and control immigration
                                    is one of the essential attributes of the inherent sovereign
                                    rights of each nation. The same argument was repeatedly invoked
                                    with special emphasis in the discussion of the exclusion clause.
                                    “We understand that the importance placed on this point by the
                                    United States is due to the <pb facs="0504" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> special conditions of that country. But we
                                    have no intention of calling this doctrine in question. The
                                    recognition, however, of such principle does not lead to any
                                    conclusion that the exclusion clause is in no respect repugnant
                                    to the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation between Japan and the
                                    United States.</item>
                                <item>Thirdly, it should be appreciated that the President and the
                                    Secretary of State of the United States have from the outset
                                    shown their opposition to the exclusion clause, and have made
                                    all possible efforts to have it eliminated from the Act. Public
                                    opinion in the United States, as reflected by a great section of
                                    the American press, also appears to be sympathetically disposed
                                    to Japan’s position in the matter. It is a significant fact that
                                    the legislation in question has met with uniform disapproval by
                                    many influential newspapers of the United States.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Our protest against the exclusion clause is based upon the conviction
                                that a discriminatory treatment, as laid down in that clause, is
                                contrary to the dictates of justice and fairness, and is imposed
                                upon us in disregard of the ordinary rules of international comity.
                                The legislation is now an accomplished fact in the United States,
                                but we can by no means concede that the question is closed. Until
                                our just contentions shall have been given satisfaction, we shall
                                maintain our protest, and shall use our best possible endeavors to
                                seek an amicable adjustment of the question and to ensure forever
                                the traditional friendship between the two nations.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>