<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Rumania ( (Jay) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1924v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d541</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">541</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-08-05T14:16:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-08-05T14:16:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-08-05T14:16:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-08-05T14:16:00-05:00" n="541"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d541">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">871.6363/204: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jay</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-08-05T21:00:00+01:44">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 5, 1924—9 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received August 7—1:11 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>54. Department’s telegram 34, July 30, 5 p.m., only received on August 2, 7 p.m.
                    Your paragraph 2. There appears no immediate prospect of further action in
                    Baldwin case pending arrival from America of company’s representative. I firmly
                    believe however present intention of Roumanian Government is to effect as far as
                    possible mutual settlements, as they realize importance attached by us to this
                    question. Regarding negotiations with Equitable and Chase banks see my telegram
                    53, August 4, 9 p.m.<note n="36" xml:id="d541fn36">Not printed.</note> I called
                    by appointment yesterday afternoon on Minister for Foreign Affairs who is
                    incidentally also acting Minister of Finance in the absence of Vintila Bratiano
                    and had long and personally friendly interview.</p>
                <p>Your paragraph 3. I have informed Minister for Foreign Affairs that I propose to
                    leave on Sunday next and have given him your intentions regarding publicity
                    adding that Legation will refuse press interviews and that I will merely let it
                    be known [that I am going?] home on leave during which I will visit Washington.
                    I added that I believe my presence at Washington would be helpful in reaching a
                    solution of many vexatious questions provided the Roumanian Government continued
                    to show the same good will manifested in recent negotiations. Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs has asked me to see him day before my departure for final
                    conference. …</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Minister for Foreign Affairs informed me Minister of Finance has returned to
                    Paris but we did not discuss his visit to London which <pb facs="0723" n="629"
                        xml:id="pg_629"/> [omission?] local press however quotes London <hi
                        rend="italic">Financial Times</hi> as stating he refused loan from an oil
                    group owing to unfavorable terms.</p>
                <p>I gave the substance of paragraphs 5, 6, 7, 8 to Minister for Foreign Affairs.
                    During my conversation he read me part of a telegram dated August 1st from
                    Roumanian Minister at Washington reporting his latest interview with Department
                    and confirming above information your paragraph 7. Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    asked me to designate member of Legation to meet Secretary General of the
                    Minister of Finance tomorrow to receive suggestions and propositions of
                    Roumanian Government for settlement of private debts. I am sending commercial
                    attaché who has been in correspondence with various American creditors and
                    Secretary Dennis who is leaving Bucharest Friday. Their report will be duly
                    communicated to you.</p>
                <p>[Paraphrase.] It is my impression that the present Liberal Government will not
                    continue in power beyond this fall, due to the attitude of our Government and
                    that of Great Britain and to the hitherto unsuccessful visit abroad of the
                    Minister of Finance. [End paraphrase.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jay</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
