<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-01-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="566" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d566">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">164.12/954</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dennis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-01-21"><hi rend="italic">January 21,
                                1924</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received February 13.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 525</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>:</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>The Commercial Attaché of the Legation, Dr. Van Norman, has just
                            communicated to the Legation a translation made by his Office <pb facs="0751" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/> of an agreement concluded on
                            December 20, 1923, between representatives of Rumanian debtors and the
                            French Consul and Commercial Attaché, respectively, acting as principals
                            for French creditors, who had authorized the last named so to act for
                            them. The most important features of the agreement are the following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>It applies to commercial and private debts contracted between
                                    November 11, 1918 and January 1, 1922 by the Rumanian
                                    parties;</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>It allows a maximum moratorium period of twenty-six
                                    years;</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Debtors admitted to the benefits of the agreement must deposit
                                    a guarantee equivalent in value to four lei for each French
                                    franc owed, in acceptable securities,—at the prevailing rate of
                                    exchange this means about 40% of the debt;</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Liquidation of the debt at the rate of 7.33% annually, of
                                    which 5% will be applied as interest, and the remaining 2.33%
                                    for the amortization.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>This agreement will be ratified by the Council of Ministers
                                    and appropriate legislation passed to protect French creditors
                                    from executions against their debtors at the demand of other
                                    creditors with whom a collective agreement may not have been
                                    reached.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In reporting this agreement to the Department of Commerce, the Commercial
                            Attaché states, in a letter dated January 9, of which a copy is herewith
                            enclosed for the Department’s convenience,<note n="62" xml:id="d566fn62">Not printed.</note> that he considers it is now time for some
                            action of a similar nature to be taken in respect of American creditors
                            having debts of this character against private individuals or companies
                            in Rumania. He refers to the cases of the International Harvester
                            Company, which has a claim of about $400,000. against Staadecker and
                            Company now before the courts, also the case of Bencoe Export Company
                                <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> Kosca and Banca Agricola for a sum of
                            about $40,000.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>There appears to be no reason to believe that the present Rumanian
                            Government, nor any one likely to succeed it, will permit, in the near
                            future, the courts of this country to give legal relief and apply legal
                            remedies in accordance with the commercial code and the customary laws
                            of the country against any debtors in Rumania on the petition of any
                            foreign creditors, where the debt belongs to the category covered by the
                            agreement herein reported. This conviction is shared by all the foreign
                            representatives in this capital, as shown by the fact that the two
                            largest creditor nations, England and France, have already concluded
                            special agreements, while Italy, Switzerland, and Czechoslovakia are at
                            present negotiating towards this end.</p>
                        <p>It seems, therefore, that American creditors have the choice of
                            concluding an arrangement along the lines already laid down in the two
                            agreements just mentioned, or submitting to an indefinite
                            moratorium.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lawrence Dennis</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>