<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="590" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d590">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.3361/24</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Denby</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-02-06"><hi rend="italic">February 6,
                                1924</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose for your
                            confidential information a copy of a communication received directly
                            from Moscow under date of January 31, signed Litvinoff,<note n="13" xml:id="d590fn13"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> relating to
                            the visit of American warships to ports under control of the Soviet
                            authorities. The Department does not contemplate making any reply to
                            this telegram.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the call of destroyers at the port of Batum, the
                            Department considers that it is desirable that such calls should be
                            discontinued and the High Commissioner at Constantinople is being
                            informed of this view. The Department has added that in case a serious
                            situation should arise affecting the work of the Near East Relief in the
                            Caucasus or the safety of American citizens in that area, which, in the
                            opinion of the High Commissioner, would justify any modification of this
                            policy, he should report to the Department.</p>
                        <p>The Department would appreciate it if the Navy Department should see fit
                            to send instructions to Admiral Bristol with regard to the discontinuing
                            of further calls of destroyers under his command at the port of
                            Batum.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles E.
                            Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>