<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-22T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-01-22T05:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/3691: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DJW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-22T10:00:00+00:00"><hi rend="italic">January 22,
                                        1919, 10 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 4:36
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>469. From Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">Francis</persName>.<note n="24" xml:id="d19fn24"><persName corresp="#p_FDR1">David R.
                                    Francis</persName>, Ambassador in Russia, temporarily in
                                London.</note></p>
                        <p>“19, January 21, 7 p.m. Your 4157, January 20, 4 p.m.,<note n="25" xml:id="d19fn25">Not printed.</note> through American Embassy,
                            London, just received. <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName>
                                message<note n="26" xml:id="d19fn26">Transmitted by the Danish
                                Chargé in Russia, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_8">p. 8</ref>.</note> from Government never recognized by us or
                            any Allied Government nor any neutral except possibly Persia, is based
                            on fallacy that it represented Russian people, which it never did. I
                            refused recommending recognition notwithstanding importunities of
                                <persName>Robins</persName><note n="27" xml:id="d19fn27">Lt. Col.
                                    <persName>Raymond Robins</persName>, in charge of the American
                                Red Cross Commission to Russia, December 1917 to May 1918.</note>
                            and some other Americans. As records show, I always maintain that Soviet
                            Government’s object was world-wide social revolution and all their
                            efforts directed to that end as subsequent developments confirm. That
                                <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName> accepted German money
                            which used as German agent to corrupt Russia was clearly established but
                            he would likewise have taken American, British, or French money to
                            accomplish the same end. <persName corresp="#p_LNVU1">Lenin</persName>
                            is fanatic, openly avowing was trying experiment in government on
                            Russia. <persName corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName> is an
                            adventurer, saturated with personal ambition and wholly without
                            conviction. I encouraged Soviet opposition to Central Empires until
                            Brest peace when issued address endeavoring to arouse Russian spirit and
                            saying America would not recognize such peace but still considered
                            herself ally of the Russian people.<note n="28" xml:id="d19fn28"><ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_440"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1918, Russia, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 440</ref>–<ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_441">441</ref>.</note> For this,
                            also for address to Russians July 4,<note n="29" xml:id="d19fn29"><ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_569"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                    pp. 569</ref>–<ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_571">571</ref>.</note> German Government demanded of Central Soviet
                            Government that I be sent out of Russia. In the meantime had left St.
                            Petersburg February 27 on account of threatened German approach, stopped
                            at Vologda where remained five months being subsequently joined [by]
                            French, Italian, Belgian, Serbian Missions. My requests that American
                            officers be sent to aid <persName corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName>
                            in organizing army and that railroad engineers be sent from Vladivostok
                            to me at <pb facs="0140" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/> Vologda had ulterior
                            objects as records show.<note n="30" xml:id="d19fn30"><ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_487"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1918, Russia, vol <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 487</ref>–<ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_488">488</ref>, <ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_493">493</ref>, and <ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_519">519</ref>–<ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_521">521</ref>.</note> Copy sent to
                            American Mission.</p>
                        <p>Answering <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName> message, while
                            first reason dissipated, it unquestionably existed when Allied troops
                            sent into North Russia.</p>
                        <p>Second reason, while Soviet Government negotiating for retention supplies
                            at Archangel it was removing such supplies at rate hundred cars daily
                            and British and French assured me was breaking faith by doing so in
                            addition to having repudiated obligations given for purchase of such
                            supplies.</p>
                        <p>I refrained from participation in such negotiations as America had little
                            if any supplies there. Undoubtedly Soviet Government would not negotiate
                            for retention such supplies at Archangel or make any other promises for
                            recognition.</p>
                        <p>Third reason, a few days after <persName>Mirbach</persName>’s
                                assassination<note n="31" xml:id="d19fn31">Wilhelm, <persName>Count
                                    von Mirbach</persName>, German Ambassador to the Soviet
                                Republic, was assassinated at Moscow July 6, 1918.</note> the Soviet
                            Government wired Allied diplomats, Vologda, inviting or ordering them to
                            Moscow and saying Radek sent Vologda to “execute” removal.<note n="32" xml:id="d19fn32">Correspondence between Soviet officials and
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_FDR1">Francis</persName> relative
                                to the removal of the embassies from Vologda to Archangel is printed
                                in <ref target="frus1918Russiav01#pg_618"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1918, Russia, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 618</ref> ff.</note> Allied chiefs unanimously
                            declined invitation or order saying if order was meant considered it
                            offensive; furthermore, German press was charging
                                <persName>Mirbach</persName> death to Allied instigation and
                            demanding of Soviet Government that German and Austrian troops be
                            permitted to come to Moscow for protection of their Embassies and
                            Consulates. Ten days later, after midnight, July 23rd, I received, as
                            dean of diplomatic corps, telegram from <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName> urging Allied diplomats quit Vologda and
                            saying another day might be too late. To this we replied had concluded
                            to accept advice and leave Vologda requesting locomotive to convey
                            special train on track Vologda to Archangel. When <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName> heard we contemplated going
                            Archangel, he wired going there meant leaving Russia. I replied
                            repeating request stating would not leave Russia unless compelled by
                            force and then absence would be temporary. Locomotive furnished after
                            twenty-four hours’ delay and diplomatic corps arrived Archangel July
                            26th. When told by local Soviet and representative Central Soviet that
                            it was waiting to convey us where we elected we replied refusing to
                            embark before communicating with our Governments with which
                            communication had been severed for three weeks or more. After some
                            colloquy our decision was wired Soviet Government, Moscow, who replied
                            communication impossible. We decided to go Kandalaksha, which occupied
                            by Allied troops, if furnished additional steamer because one
                            inadequate, additional steamer provided July 28th but many useless
                            obstacles prevented <pb facs="0141" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/> clearing
                            until 4 a.m., July 29th. Meantime we heard from credible sources that
                            while Central and local Soviet professed willingness for our departure
                            that Central Soviet was secretly urging local Soviet to detain us as
                            possible hostages to prevent landing of Allied troops, which have heard
                            since was their object in insisting on our removing to Moscow rather
                            than regard for our safety. Local Soviet, however, was afraid to detain
                            us as local anti-Bolshevik revolution was impending. This was not first
                            evidence we had of <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName>
                            hypocrisy. Anti-Bolshevik revolution occurred August 2nd, Allied troops
                            landed four hours later and Allied Missions returned to Archangel August
                            9th.</p>
                        <p>Fourth reason, while Czecho-Slovak detention no longer obtains, it was
                            burning issue when Allied troops landed Archangel. Permitting
                            Czecho-Slovaks to depart now no reason why Soviet Government be
                            recognized and it should be remembered that when Czecho-Slovaks started
                            leaving Russia they were promised safe-conduct with their arms and all
                            Czechs’ trouble caused by treachery of <persName corresp="#p_TLDB1">Trotsky</persName> who issued secret order that they should not be
                            permitted to leave without giving up their arms and when given up they
                            should be detained notwithstanding.</p>
                        <p>Answering last reason, Allied missions had positive evidence that
                            German-Austrian war prisoners were being armed and German officers were
                            instructing Bolshevik forces. While German-Austrian prisoners may now be
                            free to return home, fact remains that Bolsheviks are propagandizing
                            among prisoners and offering every inducement to join Red Army. Probably
                            Soviet Government did send communication written and verbal to us
                            through Norwegian representatives that if American troops were withdrawn
                            they would establish diplomatic relations, but that involved recognition
                            of Bolshevik Government which neither we nor any other well-ordered
                            Government could afford, as Bolshevik orators not only charged our
                            Government with being capitalistic but openly advocated opposition to
                            all organized government everywhere. I was compelled to leave Archangel
                            for surgical operation November 6th but Soviet Government had already
                            instituted reign of terror to maintain themselves in power. They were
                            pillaging and murdering inoffensive civilians without trial and when
                            could not find men were arresting wives, mothers, and sisters as
                            hostages for appearance of men to serve in Red Army. I recommended weeks
                            before leaving Archangel armed Allied intervention for restoration of
                            order knowing that same would involve extinction of Bolshevism, which I
                            consider not only irreparably injurious to Russia but disgrace to
                            civilization and reflection on Allies. I consider Bolshevism as
                            practiced in Russia means a return of the race to barbarism if it should
                            prevail throughout society, that is why I studiously avoided encouraging
                            the Soviet <pb facs="0142" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/> Government, refused
                            going Moscow and failed to establish even a <hi rend="italic">modus
                                vivendi</hi> with it. Have never doubted its willingness to make any
                            arrangement that would secure our recognition as <persName corresp="#p_CGV1">Chicherin</persName> message demonstrates. Heard
                            through Radek after <persName>Robins</persName>’ departure that latter
                            was messenger from Soviet to extend to our Government all privileges and
                            concessions granted Germany in Brest treaty but Radek said that did not
                            include England and France. Never heard that <persName>Robins</persName>
                            was permitted to present this proposition to our Government.</p>
                        <p>I think furthermore that if peace consummated with disorder prevailing in
                            Russia or if Bolsheviks permitted to dominate there that Russia will be
                            exploited by Germany so completely as to effectually recoup her losses
                            by war and become again a menace to civilization.”</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Am[erican] mission, Paris, as number 23, January 22, 10
                            a.m.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>