<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Russia</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-02-04T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-02-04T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-04T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-04T18:00:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.77/655: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-02-04T18:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 4, 1919, 6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>568. For the Secretary of State and <persName>McCormick</persName>:</p>
                <p>Your 521 January 31st, 8 p.m. I have given the suggestion made by you most
                    careful consideration, have taken advice of the men in the Department, and then
                    brought the question up at Cabinet today. Everyone is of the same mind that it
                    would be very inadvisable for me to go to Congress at this time with any plan,
                    one, of acquiring money to be expended abroad, or two, having anything to do
                    with Russia. In regard to the first objection, having just been through the
                    fight to obtain the money for the $100,000,000 fund for feeding Europe, I am
                    convinced that I would not be given any consideration whatever, in view of the
                    fact our plans in regard to the railroad—as to who are to contribute and how
                    much it would cost—are so absolutely indefinite. In the Committee on
                    Appropriations the whole fight made on the Food Bill by the opponents and the
                    criticisms made even by our friends was that they did not have information
                    enough. The information in the case of the Food Bill was so much more than
                    anything I could offer at present, I am advised by everyone that an attempt to
                    get any agreement from committee would be hopeless.</p>
                <p>In regard to the second objection, the first question to be asked would be what
                    is the Russian policy. If no answer could be given, the reasons for not being
                    able to give an answer would have no weight. Senator
                        <persName>Johnson</persName> is demanding that troops be withdrawn <pb
                        facs="0361" n="249" xml:id="pg_249"/> from Archangel, and there is
                    considerable support of his position on the ground that our men are being killed
                    and no one knows why they are still there. Of course these criticisms are
                    unjust, but they carry more or less weight. Any attempt to commit Congress to a
                    definite policy on the Siberian railroad, which is only a part of the whole
                    Russian problem, would be hopeless unless some definite information could be
                    given them on the whole subject. The Vice President said that if the Russian
                    question were thrown into Congress at this time, it would probably jeopardize
                    all the appropriation bills.</p>
                <p>In view of the unanimous opinion of all who have been consulted, I think it would
                    be wiser for me not to approach them for money for this purpose. It seems to me
                    that it has to be settled now whether we will accept the compromise arrangement
                    for operating railroad and then take our chance later on of being able to get
                    Congress to assume the responsibility. If Congress then refuses to accept a
                    carefully worked out plan that shows how much money will be required and how
                    much each Government will contribute, then the responsibility will be on
                    Congress, but to get Congress to commit itself to any proposal for financing the
                    railroad—in its present mood when it is badly frightened over the amount of
                    money we are spending and when it is so completely at sea as to what should be
                    done in Russia—would be hopeless.</p>
                <p>Shall I give formal approval. Japanese pressing for answer.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PFL">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
