<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-28T01:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-28T01:13:00-05:00" n="288" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">103.96/2458: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The American member of the Inter-Allied Railway
                                Committee</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SCH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Acting Secretary of State, transmitted by the Consul at
                                Vladivostok</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJK1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caldwell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vladivostok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-05-28T15:00:00+08:47"><hi rend="italic">May 28, 1919,
                                        3 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received May 29, 7:22
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>327. [From <persName corresp="#p_SCH1">Smith</persName>:]</p>
                        <p>Your May 21, 4 p.m.<note n="73" xml:id="d288fn73">Not printed.</note>
                            Committee April 8 passed resolution asking advance 20 million. At that
                            time did not know what governments would participate. Resolution was
                            telegraphed immediately to all governments. France, Japan have not
                            replied. England very recently replied, each government should advance
                            money for materials purchased in its own country. Italy replied, she
                            will not participate. Nothing definite from China but she will not
                            unless money loaned by some other power.</p>
                        <p>English and French representatives have again cabled asking immediate
                            action. Members believe that only England, France, Japan, and America
                            will participate and have asked that each government advance one million
                            deposit as requested. Now that Committee know what governments will
                            participate, definite steps will be taken to adjust matters in future
                            for prompt action. <persName corresp="#p_SCH1">Smith</persName>.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJK1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Caldwell</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Executive Order No. 3094–A, June 5, 1919,
                                    providing funds for the maintenance or improvement of the
                                    Trans-Siberian and Chinese Eastern Railways</hi></head>
                            <p>Whereas it has become expedient to dissolve and to liquidate the
                                affairs of the War Trade Board of United States Russian Bureau
                                Incorporated, whereof the entire capital stock was purchased with
                                the sum of $5,000,000 allotted by the President to the War Trade
                                Board by Executive Order, of October 5, 1918,<note n="74" xml:id="d288fn74">For the establishment of this fund, see <ref target="frus1918Russiav03#pg_147"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1918, Russia, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 147</ref> ff.</note> by virtue of the
                                authority vested in him by “An act making appropriations for sundry
                                civil expenses of the Government for the fiscal year ending June 30,
                                1919, and for other purposes”, approved July 1, 1918, appropriating
                                the sum of $50,000,000, “For the national security and defense and
                                for each and every purpose connected therewith to be expended at the
                                discretion of the President”:</p>
                            <p>I hereby order that any and all sums of money which upon or pursuant
                                to such dissolution shall accrue or be distributed to the <pb facs="0378" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> War Trade Board or to the
                                stockholders of said corporation shall be by said board or
                                stockholders paid into the United States Treasury and returned to
                                the appropriation aforesaid.</p>
                            <p>I hereby further order that any and all moneys so paid into the
                                United States Treasury and returned to the aforementioned
                                appropriation be, and they hereby are, allotted to the Secretary of
                                State to be by him expended for purposes connected with the
                                maintenance or improvement of the Trans-Siberian and Chinese Eastern
                                Railways and, for such purposes, the Secretary of State may, if he
                                deems advisable, advance all or any portion of the moneys hereby
                                allotted to the Inter-Allied committee, which is exercising
                                supervision over said railways, or to its nominees, upon such terms
                                as may be specified by the Secretary of State.</p>
                            <p>The foregoing does not affect in any way the special allotment of
                                $5,000,000 made to the Secretary of State by the President’s letter
                                of September 19, 1918,<note n="75" xml:id="d288fn75">Not
                                    printed.</note> from the appropriation for “National Security
                                and Defense” for the provision of winter supplies for the civilian
                                population of the Archangel district of Russia, which allotment was
                                transferred to the War Trade Board of the United States Russian
                                Bureau, Incorporated, on November 27, 1918, by direction of the
                                President.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow
                                            Wilson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>