<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-06-23T17:53:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-06-21T01:07:00-05:00" n="311" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/4736: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_RPS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Reinsch</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1919-06-23T18:53:00-04:00" notBefore="1919-06-21T11:00:00+04:53"><hi rend="italic">undated</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received June 23, 1919, 6:53
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Following from [<persName corresp="#p_HEL1">Harris</persName> at]
                            Omsk:</p>
                        <p>“278, June 21, 11 a.m. Consul Thomson, Irkutsk, gives the following
                            reason for Czech disturbances that city: five years’ absence from home
                            including experiences in prison camps; lack of communication with home
                            Government and folks during that period; demoralizing effect of
                            environment in Russia necessitating their organizing and fighting in the
                            midst of anarchy disorder and Bolshevism; disappointment at failure of
                            Allies to take declarative attitude in Russian affairs; the attainment
                            of Czecho-Slovakian freedom has deprived them of great cause which
                            induced them to fight last year in Russia; soldiers feel that they are
                            needed at home to protect new state.</p>
                        <p>I respectfully point out to the Department that if Czech soldiers are not
                            sent home before cold weather there is almost a certainty that very
                            serious trouble will arise. It appears to me that Allies must very
                            seriously consider question of replacing Czech soldiers by their own
                            troops if the railway is to be properly guarded in the future. I
                            consider it an impossibility that the Russians themselves will be able
                            to spare sufficient soldiers from the front in order to effectively
                            protect railway in its operation. <persName corresp="#p_HEL1">Harris</persName>.”</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RPS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reinsch</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>