<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Georgian Delegation at Paris to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Russia</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="36"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d36">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conference 861 G.00/10</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Georgian Delegation at Paris</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]<note n="45" xml:id="d36fn45">File
                            translation revised.</note>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 47</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-02-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 8, 1919</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>No reply has reached us from the Great Allied and Associated Powers concerning
                    the questions outlined in our preceding notes and connected with the
                    independence of Georgia. It seems that the governments of the above-mentioned
                    powers reserve to themselves the right of discussing the Georgian problem in
                    connection with all questions concerning the former Russian Empire.</p>
                <p>However, this method of procedure cannot fail to present certain very serious
                    inconveniences, for it complicates for the Conference the solution of the
                    Russian problems, by multiplying in a quite artificial manner the elements
                    composing it, in place of simplifying it by the natural division of the
                    questions.</p>
                <p>Like Poland and Finland, and more so than Bessarabia, Georgia is in truth outside
                    of the Russian problem. But Georgia has some claims, which she wishes to
                    emphasize, and which are peculiar to her. Never conquered by the Russian armed
                    force (as were the other countries above mentioned), Georgia became a part of
                    the <pb facs="0160" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> Russian Empire as a result of
                    certain bilateral political arrangements, which were soon abolished by Russia.
                    After the crumbling of this Empire, the Georgian people, liberated from the
                    century-old yoke, declared itself free, proclaimed its independence, and created
                    a political organization based on its own will and sovereignty. Notification was
                    given of this to all the Powers, and it is the international consecration of an
                    existing situation of fact that Georgia expects from the Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>The territories which the Georgian people claims as its patrimony already
                    belonged to it in very remote times, when neither Russia, nor any of the powers
                    playing now a principal role in European politics, yet existed. In its
                    historical frontiers, the Georgian people, rejuvenated by its profoundly
                    democratic aspirations, still remains the dominating element, and its purpose is
                    to organize its political independence in full harmony with the neighboring
                    peoples.</p>
                <p>Separated from Russia by the Caucasus range, Georgia, formerly the principal base
                    for Russian aggressions in Asia, has no vital importance for the peaceful Russia
                    of tomorrow, and it cannot be seen by what reasons one can justify the refusal
                    to recognize the independence of a country which, from a geographical,
                    ethnological, and historical point of view, fulfills all the conditions required
                    for an independent political existence.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, how can the solution of a problem as simple, concise,
                    and mature as the Georgian be made to depend on the settlement of the Russian
                    chaos, in which already the restoration of a certain political unity of the
                    Great Russians alone presents enormous difficulties, and in which the question
                    of the Ukraine, and of White Russia, not to mention others, is full of
                    complications of an international bearing?</p>
                <p>It is evident that, in order to begin a regular existence, Georgia cannot wait
                    for the end of an evolution, of which even the principal phases cannot yet be
                    clearly seen.</p>
                <p>Georgia must enter into economic relations with foreign countries, notably with
                    the Western Powers, and organize its life without delay and without having to
                    wait for the outcome of the political convulsions which we are witnessing now in
                    the countries situated between the Baltic Sea and the shores of the Pacific.</p>
                <p>Georgia can no longer be considered as a dependency of another state; it must
                    find its own and assured place in hither Asia, and for this it is necessary that
                    the Georgian cause be now studied and discussed by the great powers, whose will
                    and suffrage will be at the basis of the international public order which is now
                    being organized.</p>
                <p>These powers are not unaware of the events which, for a time, removed Georgia
                    from contact with their policy, on account of her geographical isolation.
                    However, very many are the Georgian officers <pb facs="0161" n="49"
                        xml:id="pg_49"/> and soldiers who have gloriously fallen for the common
                    cause of the Allies on the different fronts from Riga to Mesopotamia. The
                    country which has shed this blood did not take part in the political adventure
                    which later ended in the treaty of Brest Litovsk; this document and its authors
                    were never recognized by Georgia.</p>
                <p>Having fought for the Allies, and later, alone, against the Bolsheviks and the
                    Turks, Georgia, it seems, ought to have the right of counting on the sympathy of
                    the Allied Powers, not to mention the principles enunciated by these powers,
                    which form, as it were, the unshakeable foundation of the political claims of a
                    people as old, as organized, and as distinct as the Georgian people.</p>
                <p>In view of the preceding, the undersigned, delegates of the Government of the
                    Georgian Republic, have the honor of making the following requests:</p>
                <p>The Georgian question must be isolated from all other Russian problems; it must
                    be immediately submitted to the Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>The Inter-Allied Conference, first of all, should give its decision on the
                    principle of the independence of Georgia and on the regulation of its frontiers,
                    as well as on other questions resulting from the recognition of Georgia as an
                    independent republic.</p>
                <p>It would be of great advantage to form a special commission for the thorough
                    study of the Georgian question. Having heard the delegates of Georgia and those
                    of the other parties concerned, this commission would submit its report to the
                    Inter-Allied Conference, whose function it is to prepare the constitutional
                    elements of the definitive settlement, which will be the crowning of the work of
                    the Peace Conference.</p>
                <closer>Georgian Delegates: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">C. Gvarjaladze</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Z. Avalu</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Ghambashidze</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
