<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Appendix I to C. F. 37—Despatch to Admiral Kolchak</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Russia</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="390"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conference 180.03401/37</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Appendix I to C. F. 37—Despatch to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KAAV1">Admiral Kolchak</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="90" xml:id="d390fn90">The minutes of the meeting of the Council of Four
                        (C. F. 37) of May 27, 1919, 4 p.m., are not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-05-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">26th May, 1919.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="right">M. 190 (Final Revise)</p>
                <p>The Allied and Associated Powers feel that the time has come when it is necessary
                    for them once more to make clear the policy they propose to pursue in regard to
                    Russia.</p>
                <p>It has always been a cardinal axiom of the Allied and Associated Powers to avoid
                    interference in the internal affairs of Russia. Their original intervention was
                    made for the sole purpose of assisting those elements in Russia which wanted to
                    continue the struggle against German autocracy and to free their country from
                    German rule, and in order to rescue the Czecho-Slovaks from the danger of
                    annihilation at the hands of the Bolshevik forces. Since the signature <pb
                        facs="0480" n="368" xml:id="pg_368"/> of the Armistice on November 11th,
                    1918, they have kept forces in various parts of Russia. Munitions and supplies
                    have been sent to assist those associated with them at a very considerable cost.
                    No sooner, however, did the Peace Conference assemble than they endeavoured to
                    bring peace and order to Russia by inviting representatives of all the warring
                    Governments within Russia to meet them in the hope that they might be able to
                    arrange a permanent solution of Russian problems. This proposal and a later
                    offer to relieve the distress among the suffering millions of Russia broke down
                    through the refusal of the Soviet Government to accept the fundamental condition
                    of suspending hostilities while negotiations or the work of relief was
                    proceeding. Some of the Allied and Associated Governments are now being pressed
                    to withdraw their troops and to incur no further expense in Russia on the ground
                    that continued intervention shows no prospect of producing an early settlement.
                    They are prepared, however, to continue their assistance on the lines laid down
                    below, provided they are satisfied that it will really help the Russian people
                    to liberty, self-government, and peace.</p>
                <p>The Allied and Associated Governments now wish to declare formally that the
                    object of their policy is to restore peace within Russia by enabling the Russian
                    people to resume control of their own affairs through the instrumentality of a
                    freely elected Constituent Assembly and to restore peace along its frontiers by
                    arranging for the settlement of disputes in regard to the boundaries of the
                    Russian state and its relations with its neighbours through the peaceful
                    arbitration of the League of Nations.</p>
                <p>They are convinced by their experiences of the last twelve months that it is not
                    possible to attain these ends by dealings with the Soviet Government of Moscow.
                    They are therefore disposed to assist the Government of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAAV1">Admiral Koltchak</persName> and his Associates with
                    munitions, supplies and food, to establish themselves as the government of all
                    Russia, provided they receive from them definite guarantees that their policy
                    has the same objects in view as that of the Allied and Associated Powers. With
                    this object they would ask <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Admiral
                        Koltchak</persName> and his Associates whether they will agree to the
                    following as the conditions upon which they accept continued assistance from the
                    Allied and Associated Powers.</p>
                <p>In the first place, that, as soon as they reach Moscow they will summon a
                    Constituent Assembly elected by a free, secret and democratic franchise as the
                    Supreme Legislature for Russia to which the Government of Russia must be
                    responsible, or if at that time order is not sufficiently restored they will
                    summon the Constituent Assembly elected in 1917 to sit until such time as new
                    elections are possible.</p>
                <pb facs="0481" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/>
                <p>Secondly, that throughout the areas which they at present control they will
                    permit free elections in the normal course for all local and legally constituted
                    assemblies such as municipalities, Zemtsvos, etc.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, that they will countenance no attempt to revive the special privileges
                    of any class or order in Russia. The Allied and Associated Powers have noted
                    with satisfaction the solemn declaration made by <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1"
                        >Admiral Koltchak</persName> and his associates that they have no intention
                    of restoring the former land system. They feel that the principles to be
                    followed in the solution of this and other internal questions must be left to
                    the free decision of the Russian Constituent Assembly; but they wish to be
                    assured that those whom they are prepared to assist stand for the civil and
                    religious liberty of all Russian citizens and will make no attempt to
                    reintroduce the régime which the revolution has destroyed.</p>
                <p>Fourthly, that the independence of Finland and Poland be recognised, and that in
                    the event of the frontiers and other relations between Russia and these
                    countries not being settled by agreement, they will be referred to the
                    arbitration of the League of Nations.</p>
                <p>Fifthly, that if a solution of the relations between Esthonia, Latvia, Lithuania
                    and the Caucasian and Transcaspian territories and Russia is not speedily
                    reached by agreement the settlement will be made in consultation and
                    co-operation with the League of Nations, and that until such settlement is made
                    the Government of Russia agrees to recognise these territories as autonomous and
                    to confirm the relations which may exist between their <hi rend="italic"
                        >defacto</hi> Governments and the Allied and Associated Governments.</p>
                <p>Sixthly, the right of the Peace Conference to determine the future of the
                    Roumanian part of Bessarabia, be recognised.<note n="91" xml:id="d390fn91">The
                        insertion of the foregoing clause was approved at the meeting of May 27, 4
                        p.m.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Seventhly, that as soon as a Government for Russia has been constituted on a
                    democratic basis, Russia should join the League of Nations and co-operate with
                    the other members in the limitation of armaments and of military organisation
                    throughout the world.</p>
                <p>Finally, that they abide by the declaration made by <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1"
                        >Admiral Koltchak</persName> on November 27th, 1918, in regard to Russia’s
                    national debts.<note n="92" xml:id="d390fn92">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_356">p. 356</ref>; cf. <ref
                            target="frus1918Russiav02#pg_447">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1918, Russia, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 447</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Allied and Associated Powers will be glad to learn as soon as possible
                    whether the Government of <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Admiral
                        Koltchak</persName> and his associates are prepared to accept these
                    conditions, and also whether in the event of acceptance they will undertake to
                    form a single <pb facs="0482" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> government and army
                    command as soon as the military situation makes it possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGEB1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">G. Clemenceau</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LGD1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">D. Lloyd George</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_OVE1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">V. E. Orlando</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow Wilson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SM1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Saionji</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
