<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-14T07:07:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-14T07:07:00-05:00" n="433" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/5052: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRS1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morris</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">temporarily at Omsk, to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Omsk</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-14T17:00:00+04:53"><hi rend="italic">August 14,
                                        1919, 5 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received August 17, 7:50
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Your July 24 [<hi rend="italic">26</hi>], 6 [<hi rend="italic">4</hi>]
                                p.m.<note n="46" xml:id="d433fn46">Transmitted in telegram of the
                                same date to the Consul General at Omsk, <ref target="#pg_398">p.
                                    398</ref>.</note> I do not know the extent of the popular
                            support given to <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Kolchak</persName> west of
                            Irkutsk two or three months ago. I can only report that the policy
                            adopted from the military service [<hi rend="italic">moment?</hi>]
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Kolchak</persName> became Supreme Ruler
                            was the substitution of military for civil administration throughout
                            Siberia. Conditions at Krasnoyarsk, for instance, under Rosanoff were
                            worse if possible than at Chita and Vladivostok under
                                <persName>Seminoff</persName> and <persName>Rinoff</persName>; the
                            same conditions prevailed at Tomsk and even here at Omsk. The following
                            is a translation of a resolution pointing out the effect of this policy,
                            unanimously adopted on July 7th in a self-government [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] of the Zemstvo of Irkutsk province and confidentially
                            transmitted to me: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“As the measures taken by the Government at Omsk which have for
                                    their object the revival of government privileges existing under
                                    the old regime tend simply to further the economic deterioration
                                    and political ruin of the country, the people are loudly
                                    expressing their dissatisfaction, disappointment and enmity
                                    towards stricter measures as the curtailment of the rights of
                                    local organs of administration, the systematic and organized
                                    fight with every form of social development, the suppression of
                                    all citizen rights, the employing of force in fighting the press
                                    and freedom of speech, the interference of military authorities
                                    with civilian life, the self-assumed authority of many
                                    individual <pb facs="0526" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/> agents of
                                    government and the refusal [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] in the
                                    name of free trade to the ever increasing speculation.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>This point of view was supported by the Japanese and tolerated by the
                            British and French representatives and opposed only by <persName corresp="#p_GMGWS1">General Graves</persName> in eastern Siberia who
                            clearly saw from the beginning what the result of such point of view
                            would be, and waged against it whenever possible. He was rewarded by the
                            bitter hatred and antagonism of all the reactionary elements and also, I
                            regret to say, with the severe criticism of some Americans who do not
                            understand the interest.</p>
                        <p>The present reverses are not due to over-extension; but to the fact that
                            the soldiers of the Siberian Army are demoralized by the conditions
                            which I have pointed out in my previous telegrams and therefore will not
                            fight. <persName corresp="#p_JGM1">Generals Janin</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_KMGAWF1">Knox</persName> have returned and
                            report conditions like those on the eastern front two years ago.
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMGWS1">General Graves</persName>, at my
                            request, has gone to Ishim to see for himself the conditions there and
                            to find out whether there is any chance of reorganizing the army.</p>
                        <p>As I have explained in previous telegrams, <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Admiral Kolchak</persName> and his colleagues now realize their
                            mistake. I was greatly surprised to learn from Sukine today that some of
                            the immediate reforms which were discussed in our conferences have been
                            adopted: a committee consisting of the Minister of Justice to Oran [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>], the Minister of the Interior and <persName corresp="#p_DGMK1">General Dietrichs</persName> has been organized
                            with power to hear and summarily to dispose of any complaints of abuse
                            of military power extraterritorial [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] courts.
                            Better still the economic conference which has been sitting here and has
                            asked for some part in framing the policies of the Government has been
                            created as a consulting beyond that [<hi rend="italic">body?</hi>] to
                            whom the ministers will report proposed measures for discussion and
                            suggestion; and finally the provincial Zemstvos are to be revived and
                            recognized. I fear these reforms may be too late but they give promise
                            of a united [omission].</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MRS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>