<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Vladivostok ( (Caldwell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Russia</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-09-30T01:13:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-09-30T01:13:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-09-30T01:13:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-09-30T01:13:00-05:00" n="565"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/5313: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Vladivostok</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJK1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caldwell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vladivostok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-09-30T15:00:00+08:47">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 30, 1919, 3 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received 10:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>529. As will be seen by reference to <persName corresp="#p_GMGWS1">General
                        Graves</persName>’s telegrams to the War Department conditions in
                    Vladivostok and eastern Siberia have become much worse since the arrival of
                    General <persName>Rozanoff</persName>, who is plainly hostile toward Allies with
                    the exception of possibly Japan. <persName>Kalmikoff</persName> and his Cossacks
                    are allowed to come into Vladivostok and two men in Cossack uniforms murdered a
                    Cossack Colonel in broad daylight in the city. There is very bad feeling between
                    the Russian soldiers and Allies resulting in killing of one American and one
                    Czech soldier by Russian officers.</p>
                <pb facs="0635" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/>
                <p>Allied military commanders finally demanded that General
                        <persName>Rozanoff</persName> remove from Vladivostok fortress those troops
                    he has brought. General <persName>Rozanoff</persName> referred matter to Omsk as
                        [<hi rend="italic">and?</hi>] he yesterday informed Allied commanders that
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAAV1">Kolchak</persName> had telegraphed not to
                    remove Russian troops from Vladivostok fortress but to use all possible means to
                    prevent their removal.</p>
                <p>Allied commanders met yesterday asking diplomatic representatives to be present
                    and discussed situation, all being agreed that their demands must be complied
                    with. General <persName>Inagaki</persName> was particularly positive as to this
                    but stated that it would not cause a very serious situation. General
                        <persName>Rozanoff</persName>’s refusal to comply with demand of the Allied
                    military commanders was unexpected as he had indicated compliance when it was
                    first presented. …</p>
                <p>In any case very serious situation is created which may cause actual battle
                    between Allied and Russian troops in Vladivostok in the near future if immediate
                    steps are not taken in Omsk to settle the matter. It appears certain that
                    General <persName>Rozanoff</persName> has placed matter before <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAAV1">Kolchak</persName> in wrong light or he would not have
                    sent such orders as he did without making any inquiries of Allied
                    representatives. After meeting of the Allied military commanders, at which
                    diplomatic representatives were present, the latter met and agreed to telegraph
                    to their respective representatives in Omsk and to their respective governments
                    that they fully agreed as to the necessity for the removal from Vladivostok of
                    the troops recently brought in by General <persName>Rozanoff</persName> and that
                    the removal of General <persName>Rozanoff</persName> would gradually ease the
                    situation. Repeat to Tokio and Omsk.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJK1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caldwell</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
