<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-20T20:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-20T20:13:00-05:00" n="632" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d632">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.77/1033: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The American member of the Inter-Allied Railway
                                Committee</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SCH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Secretary of State, transmitted by the Consul at Vladivostok</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_CJK1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caldwell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vladivostok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-21T10:00:00+08:47"><hi rend="italic">August 21,
                                        1919, 10 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received August 22, 3:21
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>474. Following from <persName corresp="#p_SCH1">Smith</persName>.</p>
                        <p>“Some months ago Committee passed regulation that in case of any
                            infraction of rules regarding train movements, railway officials were to
                            apply to military forces guarding that particular sector to restore
                            order. This was done especially on account of
                                <persName>Semenoff</persName>. All military have followed rule
                            except Japanese. Committee sent several letters to commanders but
                            Japanese did not reply. Again, July 25th we reiterated request and
                            recently received reply from <persName corresp="#p_OGK1">General
                                Otani</persName> as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>‘In view of the fact that Japanese troops are located in the
                                    commonwealth with the aim of maintaining order and political
                                    quietness, they must, of course, render assistance to the
                                    railways against malefactors tending to harm railway movement in
                                    case their duty will require it. However, all misunderstandings
                                    arising with regard to railways among Allied troops, including
                                    Russians, and Allied agents, which by their character are
                                    subject to decision by corresponding governments or diplomatic
                                    agencies [and] representatives, as well as small incidents which
                                    can be liquidated by Russian authorities or militia, or
                                    incidents of a similar character, do not allow Japanese troops
                                    to interfere with them.’</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>When letter was read to the Committee <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Matsudaira</persName><note n="22" xml:id="d632fn22"><persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tsuneo Matsudaira</persName>, Japanese member
                                of the Inter-Allied Railway Committee.</note> said that he did not
                            understand the first sentence and feared that English translation was
                            wrong. Chairman handed me letter which was written in Russian and
                            translation was correct; then he stated that the letter was probably
                            written in Japanese and wrongly translated into Russian. He will
                            investigate and report. … No recent complaints about
                                <persName>Semenoff</persName> received. <persName corresp="#p_SCH1">Smith</persName>.[”]</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJK1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Caldwell</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>