<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="884" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d884">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.00/4443: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate
                                    Peace</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-05-06"><hi rend="italic">May 6</hi> [<hi rend="italic">7?</hi>], <hi rend="italic">1919</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received May 7, 4:16
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>2027. [From <persName>Ravndal</persName> at Constantinople:] <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“May 6th, 5 p.m. From <persName corresp="#p_JWL1">Jenkins</persName>, repeat Washington.</p>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>‘Aid to Volunteer Army. I respectfully refer to my telegram
                                        from Odessa<note n="13" xml:id="d884fn13">Not
                                            printed.</note> regarding report on [<hi rend="italic">Red Cross</hi>] assistance for North Caucasus. The
                                        Volunteer Army has usual defects of any purely Russian
                                        organization but should be assisted not only because of past
                                        achievements but because of the disastrous results which
                                        would follow its annihilation. It has throughout been
                                        faithful to the Allies. It kept the rich North Caucasus from
                                        the Germans and necessitated retention of German and
                                        Bolshevik troops on southeast front during crucial periods
                                        for Allies both in France, Russia and Siberia. Its defeat
                                        would increase prestige of Bolsheviks whose troops could be
                                        transferred to other fronts and would render extremely
                                        difficult the British task of preventing spread of
                                        Bolshevism through Transcaucasia to India. If properly
                                        equipped it could unite with Siberian troops thus hastening
                                        overthrow of Bolsheviks. Fortunately the British are sending
                                        military supplies but there is great need for three Red
                                        Cross units which should be sent immediately for both
                                        humanitarian and political reasons. The intelligent class is
                                        bound to win out eventually in Russia as elsewhere and they
                                        who support it now, will have the prestige in the
                                        future.’</p>
                                </quote>
                                <p rend="right"><persName>Ravndal</persName>”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">American Mission</hi></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>