<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>232. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d232</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">232</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-07-02T15:28:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-07-02T15:28:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-02T15:28:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-02T15:28:00-05:00" n="232"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                <head>232. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d232fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 700.5611/7–261. Secret; Verbatim Text. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BEJ1">Beigel</persName> and cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TWR1"
                            >Tyler</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-07-02T16:28:00-04:00">July 2, 1961, 4:28 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>16. Eyes only Ambassador. [Here follow instructions for classifying and
                    delivering this and a second letter transmitted in telegram 17, <ref
                        target="#d233">Document 233</ref>.]</p>
                <p>“June 30, 1961</p>
                <p>Dear General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>:</p>
                <p>It is almost exactly a month since we met in Paris. Much has happened in that
                    time, and while many members of our two Governments have been in touch with each
                    other on special problems, it seems to me time to write you again. I have the
                    better occasion to do so because I am now able to send the enclosed formal
                    statement confirming the understanding and assurance which we agreed upon with
                    respect to the use of nuclear weapons. This assurance is parallel to the one
                    which has been in force between this Government and Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Obviously, the biggest issue before us now is Berlin. Fortunately, as we
                    discovered in our first conversation, you and I see this problem in essentially
                    identical terms. What has happened in June simply shows that we were right to
                    take it seriously. We, for our part, are closely engaged on serious planning of
                    all sorts to meet a crisis which seems to us to be more serious than any before
                    it. Ours is a large and complex Government, and clear decisions on concrete
                    steps do not come as quickly as I would like. But the direction in which we
                    shall move is just like yours in the movement of a division from Algeria to
                    France. It is action and not appearances that will be effective in our judgment.
                    We shall also move to insure agreement and understanding in this country as a
                    whole, and while there are occasional voices, even in my own party and in the
                    Senate which sound an uncertain trumpet, I can assure you that they do not
                    represent the Government or the people of the United States on this issue.</p>
                <p>In this atmosphere of serious preparation for a test in Berlin, the notion of
                    effective negotiation towards disarmament seems somewhat unreal. Mr.
                        <persName>McCloy</persName> has been meeting with the Russians because it
                    seems to us important not to be hasty in breaking off discussions on which there
                    was agreement some months ago. But we are simply repeating over and over again
                    that there can be no discussion of substance except after a new agreement on an
                    appropriate forum. The time may come, I believe, <pb facs="0692" n="671"
                        xml:id="pg_671"/> when it will be possible and useful to have such serious
                    discussion in a very small circle, but I must say that time does not seem to be
                    now.</p>
                <p>I am personally disappointed that we have not made more progress in this last
                    month toward the establishment of stronger processes of consultation in the
                    intervals between our personal meeting. I do not think either of our foreign
                    secretaries has been idle, but we must not allow the pressures of the day to
                    prevent preparations for continued close consultation, even though some of these
                    pressures are those of the consultation which does in fact go on regularly at
                    many levels. I have talked with <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Dean Rusk</persName>
                    again about this, and he tells me that he is planning to talk about ways and
                    means today through Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> and
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Caccia</persName>, as agents of their two
                    foreign secretaries.<note n="1" xml:id="d232fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> met with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CSH1">Caccia</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                            >Alphand</persName> at 3:05 p.m. to discuss consultations. According to
                        a memorandum of conversation they agreed to discuss in Washington Laos, the
                        Congo, Africa including Algeria, disarmament, and Southeast Asia. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> asked the Ambassadors to seek the
                        opinions of their Foreign Ministers with respect to a pre-September meeting.
                        (Ibid., 396.1/6–3061)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Meanwhile, one of the lessons which I draw from our meeting in May is that there
                    is a sense in which no other consultation can substitute for direct encounters
                    between chiefs of Government.</p>
                <p>It seems to me that if the crisis in Berlin becomes more serious, and perhaps on
                    even more general grounds, it may be useful if you and Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> and I can have a meeting at some
                    convenient time in the autumn. I should be glad to know whether this seems a
                    reasonable idea to you.</p>
                <p>May I conclude by sending my warmest personal regards, in which Mrs. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> joins, to you and to Madame <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d232fn2">On July
                        6 <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> responded saying that he
                        too believed Berlin was the essential problem and agreeing on the
                        desirability of a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_MH1"
                            >Macmillan</persName>. (Ibid., Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D
                        204; printed in part in <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">Charles de
                            Gaulle</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Memoires d’Espoir, Le Renouveau,
                            1958–1962,</hi> p. 272)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">John F. Kennedy</persName>”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
