<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-31T17:14:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                    <head>308. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>In a September 12 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SAM1">Schlesinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Bundy</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KR1">Komer</persName> reported: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“My impression from my talks with Embassy Rome is that we are moving
                                toward consensus on the matter of enhancing the split between the
                                Italian left Socialists and Communists. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName> claims that any remaining
                                differences are essentially those of timing rather than viewpoint.
                                Although I wouldn’t put it quite this strongly, my brief talks with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Horsey</persName>, and Baker (the political
                                officer following the left parties) convince me they’re a good deal
                                less negative than before.”</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>He concluded: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“All in all, I’m convinced that the WH effort to stir up movement on
                                this front over the last six months has been most useful. We have
                                made progress in getting State and CIA to look forward instead of
                                backward on what is essentially a question of opportunities versus
                                risks. To me, the translation of Italy’s economic miracle into
                                meaningful political and social terms is essential to future Italian
                                political stability, and to the final disappearance of a serious
                                threat from the extremist left. These potential gains far outweigh
                                the risks of undermining the center party or encouraging a
                                neutralist trend. Such fears were legitimate in the late Forties and
                                early Fifties, but I just can’t give them the same weight in the
                                prosperous Italy of today. Moreover, what price neutralism in a
                                country which is the most enthusiastic exponent of the European idea
                                because it has the most to gain.” (<persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Italy)</p>
                        </quote></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>