<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>409. Memorandum From President Kennedy to Prime Minister to Prime Minister
                    Macmillan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d409</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">409</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="409"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d409">
                <head>409. Memorandum From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1" type="from"
                        >Kennedy</persName> to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1" type="to"
                        >Macmillan</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d409fn0">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 65 D 533, CF 2212. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Nassau</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-12-21"
                            >December 21, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The United States Government proposes to offer to the French Government
                        the opportunity to participate in the multilateral nuclear force envisaged
                        by the Nassau agreement on terms similar to those agreed with the United
                        Kingdom. However, we do not consider that the agreement on the part of the
                        United States and the United Kingdom to support the development and
                        establishment of such a multilateral force is conditional on participation
                        by France.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It is also our view that participation in the proposed multilateral force
                        should be available to non-nuclear member nations of <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> through the contribution of personnel and
                        resources for the operation of nuclear vessels, including submarines, manned
                        by units of mixed nationality. I propose that an early invitation be
                        extended to such countries to participate in the discussion and developments
                        of such units.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>It is agreed that the Polaris missiles and associated equipment to be made
                        available by the United States to the United Kingdom Government under the
                        provisions of Article 8 of the agreement<note n="1" xml:id="d409fn1"
                            >Paragraph 8 of the Statement on Nuclear Defense Systems.</note> will
                        consist of equipment for fire control, launching, guidance, and
                        navigation.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">John F. Kennedy</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d409fn2">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
