<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="5" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                    <head>5. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d5fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 375.800/5–261.
                            Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_VRD1">Vine</persName> and
                            approved in <gloss target="#t_B1">B</gloss> on May 11.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1961-05-02">May 2, 1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>U.S. Position on European Economic and Political Integration</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>Mr. <persName>George Ball</persName>, Under Secretary for Economic
                            Affairs</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold Caccia</persName>, British
                            Ambassador</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PDD1">David Pitblado</persName>, Economic
                            Minister, British Embassy</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName>G. Lewis Jones</persName>, Minister-Counsellor
                            Designate, American Embassy, London, England</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">J. Robert Schaetzel</persName>,
                            Special Assistant to the Under Secretary for Economic Affairs</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_VRD1">Richard D. Vine</persName>, Bureau of
                            European Affairs, <gloss target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The British Ambassador came in at Mr. <persName>Ball</persName>’s request to
                        discuss the U.S. position on European economic and political
                        integration.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> began by referring to the position that had
                        emerged out of his conversations with <persName corresp="#p_HE1">Heath</persName> and the President’s conversation with <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>. He noted that it was very
                        important indeed that the UK and all other countries involved have a clear
                        and exact understanding of our policies in this regard. He gave <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> an aide-mémoire which <pb facs="0031" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/> spelled out ours in some detail (see
                        Circular 1722).<note n="1" xml:id="d5fn1">Not found. A copy of the
                            aide-mémoire, which stressed U.S. support for the principles of economic
                            and political integration laid out by the Treaty of Rome, was
                            transmitted to London in circular instruction CW 788, July 27. (Ibid.,
                            375.800/7–2761)</note> He stated that he wished particularly to
                        emphasize three points:</p>
                    <p>1) That this was something we were not urging.<note n="2" xml:id="d5fn2">The
                            other two points were never enumerated in the memorandum.</note></p>
                    <p>Before Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> could go any further <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Caccia</persName> interjected to inquire what that
                        something was. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> understood it to mean the organization of the
                        whole industrial world, but while waiting for this longer-term result Europe
                        should organize itself more closely as an interim step. The question is,
                        therefore, is the UK to go into Europe as a step in a process, or does the
                        United States envisage the organization of Europe as a separate thing and an
                        end in itself.</p>
                    <p><persName>Ball</persName> stated that we saw the problem as political. Both
                        Germany and France have strong potential which would tend over the long run
                        to make the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> an inward-looking
                        organization. Britain is a force that can bring cohesion to this movement,
                        but he wanted to stress that he meant Britain and not the Seven as a whole.
                        He also wanted to make clear that this was not a position which we advanced.
                            <persName>Ball</persName> noted that in his conversation with <persName corresp="#p_HE1">Heath</persName> he was asked what we had in mind as
                        pertained to the UK and he replied.</p>
                    <p>In terms of the future of European integration, <persName>Ball</persName>
                        said, Britain is a major pole of attraction for several countries in the
                        Community and tends to be a disruptive force in the pattern of European
                        integration so long as it remains outside the framework. Moreover, we had a
                        great respect for British political genius. If it were brought to bear on
                        the organization of Europe, we would go forward with more assurance with an
                        Atlantic arrangement.</p>
                    <p>As far as the Seven were concerned, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> indicated to us that the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members of the Seven would not have much difficulty on the
                        principle of joining, although there would be difficulties of detail.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> showed Mr.
                            <persName>Ball</persName> an account of the most recent German-British
                        bilaterals in which the clear point emerged that the Germans thought it
                        would be a pity if the British were not steadfast on a derogation for
                        agriculture. Moreover, it seemed clear that the Germans were prepared to see
                        the British in on very liberal terms.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PDD1">Pitblado</persName> said that the UK was tied
                        to a contractual relationship, however, which was more than a trade
                        relationship. <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> further
                        stated that the UK could not say “go jump” to its <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss> partners. This would be damaging to UK prestige. It would
                        not, moreover, be designed for increased unity, but “designed for
                        slaughter.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> stated that this would clearly make for
                        difficulty in the negotiations. He thought the question of <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss> depended largely upon how it was handled,
                        and that we saw no difficulty in talks in two stages.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> specifically addressed
                        himself to that part (paragraph eight) of the aide-mémoire dealing with our
                        position on a Six-Seven accommodation and making a distinction between this
                        and the accession of those countries who could assume the obligations of the
                        Rome Treaty. To put it crudely, he said, if the UK were to stand honorably
                        on its commitments to the Seven, the United States would not lend it its
                        support.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_PDD1">Pitblado</persName> then stated that the Swiss
                        and Swedes would have real difficulty in meeting the obligations of the Rome
                        Treaty.</p>
                    <p><persName>Ball</persName> said that in his view, if the British, Norwegians
                        and Danes were to join then after the dust had settled, some commercial
                        arrangements might be worked out for the Swiss and the Swedes. Otherwise, he
                        said, it would be very difficult for us to do anything. If the negotiations
                        were carried out in one package, he said, it would be on the basis of the
                        lowest common denominator, which would badly weaken the final result. He
                        believed it would be a mistake to clutter up the negotiations at the
                        beginning. It would probably not be negotiable as a total package; it should
                        be taken in steps and probably then could be negotiated. We could assume
                        that there would also be later special arrangements for Finland, Austria,
                        and Portugal.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> said that this was a
                        prescription for the destruction of Europe. This formula was quite different
                        from what the Prime Minister had understood, and was not designed for the
                        increase of unity in Europe but its destruction. Taken at its face, our
                        position was fairly absolute and was aimed at the “bustup” of <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>. Did he really mean that?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> said that as regards a Six-Seven accommodation
                        we were firm in our view, but that the difficulty was not in this, but
                        rather in negotiating technique, which we believed should be staggered. The
                        Swiss and Swedes and others must accept as we have done the fact of the
                            <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> and learn to make adjustments if
                        they are not prepared to accept the obligations and responsibilities of the
                        Rome Treaties. We would have great difficulty in accepting the principle of
                        derogations to take account of the special problems of any country.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schaetzel</persName> pointed out that this
                        was a straightforward continuation of our policy which was based on the idea
                        that the age of preferences was dead. <persName corresp="#p_PDD1">Pitblado</persName> said that Britain was engaged in solemn political
                        obligations.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> wished to recapitulate to
                        make certain that he had understood our position correctly. First, there was
                        to be a “bustup” of <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>. Secondly, the UK
                        would negotiate. Finally, the others would be picked up at a later time.
                        This was unthinkable, he said. He turned to the <pb facs="0033" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> statement of our views on <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>. It is more than a commercial arrangement, he said, and
                        cited the Finnish case. If this was our position, he said, a great many
                        questions would be raised in London, for it implies that the UK has to “rat”
                        on its obligations and simply put its signature on the Treaty of Rome.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schaetzel</persName> pointed out that this
                        had been raised before in London in a thorough discussion of the problem and
                        had not seemed to raise any serious obstacle.</p>
                    <p>Breaking up the <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>, if it were discussed
                        in London, was something <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName>
                        said he had not been informed about. It must have been incorrectly assumed
                        that the UK would “rat on its partners.” The UK has made clear from the
                        beginning that a settlement would have to include the problems of
                        obligations to <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss> and the Commonwealth
                        and the agricultural problem. Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> pointed out that
                        this was an overstatement, since the British public statements on this
                        subject had indicated only that these problems would have to be taken into
                        consideration. If this was the British viewpoint, this was a new
                        understanding as far as we were concerned, since our thinking has been of
                        the negotiations proceeding in two phases.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> inquired whether the US
                        seriously thought that the UK would simply take a blank check and disregard
                        its other commitments. It was not the greater unity of Europe which we
                        appeared to have in mind, but a far smaller thing. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schaetzel</persName> pointed out that if the UK were
                        to join the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> this would provide a much
                        greater unity and that one could not compare moves of Switzerland or Sweden
                        with moves the UK might make. They were not at all of the same order.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Ball</persName> stated that clarity of view was absolutely
                        essential to our relations. He wished to make it clearly understood that he
                        was representing ideas which were approved by the President. (<persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> quickly asked whether the
                        President has seen and approved this aide-mémoire. Mr.
                            <persName>Ball</persName> said he had not although the ideas represented
                        therein had been thoroughly discussed with him and approved by him.) Mr.
                            <persName>Ball</persName> agreed that there might have been a
                        possibility that the views could have been interpreted two ways and during
                        the meeting between <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> and the
                        President there was insufficient time to go into them thoroughly. It is
                        possible that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> did not
                        understand our view on the phasing. <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir
                            Harold</persName> agreed and welcomed this exchange of views in the
                        interest of greater understanding.</p>
                    <p>There was a short discussion of the French views on the whole problem.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CSH1">Sir Harold</persName> believed there was
                        considerable doubt that the French would have the UK on any terms. Mr.
                            <persName>Ball</persName> stated that we believed it was a question of
                        the scope of a settlement and the extent of derogations, and if satisfaction
                        could be gotten on these, the French would probably not be an obstacle.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>