<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>82. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Mission to the
                    European Communities</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-09-20T13:11:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-09-20T13:11:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWMZ9EcUPmDYpbT" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-09-20T13:11:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-09-20T13:11:00-05:00" n="82"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                <head>82. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Mission to the European Communities</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d82fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, INCO Poultry US. Limited Official Use; Operational Immediate. Drafted
                        by Hedges and Rehm (<gloss target="#t_STR1">STR</gloss>) and cleared in
                        draft with <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>, Ball, <persName
                            corresp="#p_FOL1">Freeman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HLH1"
                            >Hodges</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-09-20T14:11:00-04:00">September 20, 1963, 2:11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Busec1">Busec</gloss> 131. Ref: <gloss target="#t_TAGG1"
                        >TAGG</gloss> 1416, <gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">Ecbus</gloss> 310.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d82fn1">Both dated September 19. In <gloss target="#t_TAGG1"
                            >TAGG</gloss> 1416 <persName corresp="#p_BWM1">Blumenthal</persName>
                        reported that the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> would not accept the
                        U.S. figure of $46 million and would make counter withdrawals if concessions
                        totaling that figure were withdrawn. <persName corresp="#p_BWM1"
                            >Blumenthal</persName> suggested that continuing along this line would
                        not benefit the United States and proposed further negotiations and perhaps
                        submitting to <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> the question of the
                        amount of compensation. (Ibid.) <gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">Ecbus</gloss> 310
                        reported that a meeting had been previously arranged with <persName
                            corresp="#p_HW1">Hallstein</persName> for September 23 at which the
                        poultry question could be discussed if Washington agreed. (Ibid.)</note> For
                        <persName corresp="#p_TJW1">Tuthill</persName> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>. Interagency agreement reached on
                    following alternatives for dealing with poultry problem and avoiding collision
                    with <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>. These alternatives should be presented
                    during your Monday meeting with <persName corresp="#p_HW1"
                    >Hallstein</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> Council at its September 23 meeting
                            to provide Commission with meaningful negotiating mandate so that US and
                                <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> can seek immediately to
                            negotiate satisfactory settlement of poultry issue. We would not insist
                            this be accompanied by 11-pfennig reduction in levies but US would
                            welcome this reduction as token of <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>’s
                            good intentions.</p>
                        <p>We would interpret as meaningful a mandate from Council to Commission to
                            seek agreement with US, on ad referendum basis, on reductions in poultry
                            levies that gave reasonable assurance of restoring US poultry trade. We
                            would not expect Council to specify amount required or to endorse either
                            of specific proposals advanced by US in its aide-mémoire. Obviously
                            those proposals were also negotiable. We would want formal indication
                            however that Council was prepared to give serious consideration to any
                            arrangement Commission worked out with US.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>US to defer action on compensatory withdrawals while bilateral
                        negotiations carried out. Definite time limit for such negotiations would
                        have to be set. From every point of view it is essential this matter be
                        brought to prompt conclusion. We think 30 days should allow ample time. At
                        latest negotiations would have to be terminated successfully by October 31,
                        1963, and Council would have to approve results promptly if US not to make
                        compensatory withdrawals.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>If Council does not provide meaningful mandate to negotiate, or, if,
                            following such mandate, US and <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>
                            cannot reach accord on satisfactory reductions in levies within time
                            limits indicated in (2) above, US <pb facs="0239" n="218"
                                xml:id="pg_218"/> will have no alternative but to make compensatory
                            withdrawals. However before making such withdrawals we would be prepared
                            to have trade coverage issue adjudicated by <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                                >GATT</gloss> panel in order avoid further litigation. As reported
                            in <gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">ECBUS</gloss> 277<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d82fn2">Dated September 3. (Ibid.)</note>
                            <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> is prepared to challenge $46 million
                            figure and launch counter-move if US proceeds with withdrawals. We have
                            sufficient confidence in our case to go to adjudication. <gloss
                                target="#t_fyi1">FYI</gloss>. In our view <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                                >GATT</gloss> panel should determine not whether specific $46
                            million is proper but what is proper trade exchange figure under Article
                            XXVIII principles. Framing issue in this manner would leave US free to
                            argue before <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> panel that figure
                            higher than $46 million is valid. <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>
                            should presumably not object to so framing issue if they are as
                            confident as they seem to be that proper figure is far below $46
                            million. If appropriate you may indicate US may plead higher figure
                            since we consider $46 million conservative estimate. End <gloss
                                target="#t_fyi1">FYI</gloss>. We would leave for later discussion
                            whether determination of <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> panel
                            should be approved by <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> Contracting
                            Parties.</p>
                        <p>Adjudication would be limited solely to trade coverage figure and US and
                                <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> would be bound by <gloss
                                target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> panel decision. <gloss
                                target="#t_fyi1">FYI</gloss>. US acceptance adjudication of trade
                            coverage not intended to waive US right to proceed under Article XXIII
                            concerning any aspects poultry <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss>
                            inconsistent with provisions or objectives <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                                >GATT</gloss>. Proposed US withdrawals compensate only for <gloss
                                target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> withdrawal of poultry binding. Neither
                                <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> withdrawal nor payment exacted
                            by US for withdrawal entitle <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> to
                            adopt measures inconsistent with <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>.
                            You should avoid suggesting contrary and may state US understanding this
                            point if appropriate. End <gloss target="#t_fyi1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>If <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> bound by <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                                >GATT</gloss> panel decision it would necessarily follow that <gloss
                                target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> would accept justification of US case
                            under Article XXVIII and would forego any subsequent counter-moves such
                            as Article XXIII action against our withdrawals. We assume from
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Rey</persName>’s statement reported in
                                <gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">ECBUS</gloss> 227 this would create no
                            difficulties for Commission. Pending adjudication US would of course
                            defer issuing withdrawal proclamation.<note n="3" xml:id="d82fn3">On
                                October 16 the United States and the <gloss target="#t_EEC1"
                                    >EEC</gloss> asked the <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                                Council of Representatives to render an opinion on the poultry
                                question. (<gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">Ecbus</gloss> 483 to Brussels,
                                October 16; ibid.) In November the <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                                    >GATT</gloss> panel issued a finding on behalf of the United
                                States but only for $26 million. On December 3 the United States
                                informed representatives of 16 embassies which tariff concession the
                                United States would suspend to compensate for this loss. (Memorandum
                                of telephone conversations, December 3; ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
