<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-02-07T22:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-02-07T22:13:00-05:00" n="94" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                    <head>94. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d94fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 375/2–761.
                            Secret; Priority; Eyes Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FR1">Fessenden</persName>, cleared with <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and the White House, and approved by <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName>. Repeated to
                        Paris.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-02-07T22:13:00-05:00">February 7,
                                1961, 10:13 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>1360. Deliver to Ambassador 9 a.m. 2/8/61. You should seek appointment
                            <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> prior his departure for
                        Paris to convey orally message drawing on text quoted below.<note n="1" xml:id="d94fn1">Drafts of the message to <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> and the statement referred to in footnote 2
                            below were transmitted to the President on February 4 as attachments to
                            a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>. (Ibid.,
                            Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204)</note> In presenting to
                            <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, you should explain that
                        these are President’s views on certain basic matters which he wished
                        conveyed to <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> at earliest
                        opportunity in view President’s knowledge of <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s deep interest in these matters. President also
                        wished to have expressed his deep appreciation of <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s unfailing efforts to promote the goals of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> solidarity and European unity. You should
                        explain also that we plan make statement in <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> shortly explaining our basic position on <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> along lines indicated in statement
                            below.<note n="2" xml:id="d94fn2">For text of the statement to the North
                            Atlantic Council, February 15, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 6, 1961, pp. 333–334.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Begin Text:</hi> The Atlantic Community stands today as the
                        principal cornerstone of human freedom in our world. The nations of Europe
                        and North America which make up the Atlantic Community were among the first
                        to give effect to the ideals and practices of political democracy. At great
                        effort and sacrifice, they have maintained freedom for their <pb facs="0280" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> own peoples and have helped guide to freedom
                        and economic betterment hundreds of millions of peoples in more than thirty
                        new nations.</p>
                    <p>The Atlantic Community is also the central source of strength for the entire
                        free world. Its members possess most of the free world’s capacity for
                        military defense, most of its industrial production, most of its commerce,
                        most of its general economic power and most of its scientific and
                        technological potential. These advantages permit us to secure important
                        benefits for our peoples. But more than this, they enable us to lead the way
                        to freedom and economic betterment for peoples everywhere. We have a great
                        responsibility to mankind as a whole.</p>
                    <p>The keystone of the Atlantic Community is <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Through it, we seek to safeguard the freedom, common
                        heritage and civilization of our peoples and to achieve a basic harmony of
                        purpose in our international relations. The military function of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, the preservation of our common security,
                        is as important as ever. The United States intends to continue its full
                        participation in the common defense. I am convinced that the maintenance of
                        U.S. military strength in Europe is essential to the security of the
                        Atlantic Community and the free world as a whole. We also expect that our
                        friends will want to contribute their full share to the mutual defense
                        effort.</p>
                    <p>The non-military functions of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> are
                        equally important. We must expand and improve the processes of consultation
                        in order to achieve that unity of purpose and action which is indispensable
                        in a perilous age. We must also use <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as
                        a framework for cooperation in other programs and projects aimed at
                        advancing the cause of human freedom everywhere.</p>
                    <p>The United States is convinced that the OECD can also become an effective
                        instrument for cooperation toward our common goals, and I have requested the
                        Congress to give its approval to the Convention. Our own Atlantic economies
                        will obviously benefit from closer cooperation among ourselves. But today
                        our economic challenges are world-wide. Of greatest importance is
                        coordination of our efforts to promote sound economic expansion in the
                        lesser developed countries. It is a sacred trust of the Atlantic Community
                        to build the road to peace and freedom with the paving blocks of economic
                        and technical development. The United States intends to do its part. Here,
                        too, I am sure our partners will want to contribute their full share.</p>
                    <p>We also continue to encourage and support the movement toward European
                        integration. This movement is a powerful and unifying force which can
                        multiply free Europe’s strength and prestige, can furnish increased economic
                        and security benefits to the European peoples and can contribute greatly
                        toward achieving the goals of the broader Atlantic Community.</p>
                    <pb facs="0281" n="260" xml:id="pg_260"/>
                    <p>We are all aware that the Atlantic Community, in recent years, has been
                        hampered by differences of attitude and interest among its members.
                        Differences will always exist, of course, among free nations. I believe it
                        is essential, however, that we work hard to compose our differences on
                        secondary issues in the interest of our paramount concern for peace,
                        security and freedom. It is the firm intention of the United States to move
                        vigorously to sustain and improve the unity, safety and well-being of the
                        Atlantic Community, making full use of all available instruments. The United
                        States Government looks forward to considering with our partners, in the
                        context of long-range planning, the means for accomplishing these goals. <hi rend="italic">End text.</hi><note n="3" xml:id="d94fn3">On February 8
                                <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName> reported that
                                <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, after interrupting a
                            Cabinet meeting to see him, expressed his appreciation for the message
                            and stressed that without vigorous American leadership all else would
                            fail, “no matter how well conceived or carried out.” (Telegram 1214 from
                            Bonn; Department of State, Central Files, 375/2–861)</note></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD1"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>