<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-10-23T23:43:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-10-23T23:43:00-05:00" n="131" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d131">
                        <head>131. Telegram 180295 From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                Nigeria</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d131fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–9
                                Biafra-Nigeria. Secret; Priority. Repeated to London and Abidjan.
                                Drafted by Brubeck (<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>/SN); cleared
                                by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Newsom</persName>, and in U/CF,
                                    <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>, and the White House; and
                                approved by <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d131fn2">The telegram transmitted a
                                message for Major General <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>, Chairman of the Supreme Military Council of
                                Nigeria, from President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>. The United States stood with the Federal Military
                                Government (<gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss>) on its commitment
                                to International Committee of the Red Cross (<gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>) daylight flights without
                                violation. The Biafrans would be asked that Uli not be used for arms
                                flights in daylight hours.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-10-24T04:43:00+00:00">October 24, 1969, 0443Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d131-01" n="1" xml:id="d131-01"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>REF:</head>
                            <item>(a) State 176138 (b) State 176139</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>LAGOS FOR AMBASSADOR<lb/>ABIDJAN FOR FERGUSON</p>
                        <p>1. You should convey message paras 2–4 to Enahoro, Extaff, for <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>. You should note in so doing
                            that we informed <persName corresp="#p_AO1">Arikpo</persName> of these
                            steps (reftels) when in Washington and that we gratified by <persName corresp="#p_AO1">Arikpo</persName>ʼs strong assurances <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> cooperation. (<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>—We not revealing any details re how we communicating
                            with Biafrans END <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.) You may wish use
                            aide memoire with Enahoro. Message is as follows:</p>
                        <p>2. President wishes convey General <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName> his admiration for his humane statesmanship in
                            agreeing to inviolable daylight airlift by <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> into enclave. USG deeply committed to humanitarian
                            program and therefore very distressed continued impasse. We wish see
                            prompt implementation <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> flights and
                            see question of security chief Biafran objection remaining. In effort
                            meet this problem <pb facs="d131-02" n="2" xml:id="d131-02"/> President
                            has by appropriate means arranged Biafrans be informed that USG has full
                            confidence in <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> commitment to
                            cooperate <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> program without any
                            violation for military advantage during daylight relief hours. US
                            associates self with <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> assurances and
                            therefore feels Biafrans have no reasonable basis insist on further
                            guarantees. US also asking Biafran assurance Uli will not be used for
                            arms flights during daylight relief operations. If Biafrans accept
                            daylight flights under these arrangements, USG prepared make public
                            statement at high level expressing confidence in <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> pledge inviolability airlift, gratification <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> statesmanship thus demonstrated, and
                            therefore agreement of two parties to daylight flights.</p>
                        <p>3. Biafrans to be asked for yes or no answer. US assurance
                            non-negotiable. If Biafrans still reject, USG will feel free to express
                            publicly USG view of Biafran position.</p>
                        <p>4. President wishes General <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>
                            understand we fully appreciative solemn undertaking by <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> in accepting daylight airlift. Our
                            present effort intended solely to remove main issue on which Biafrans
                            have based rejection, thus hopefully opening way to <pb facs="d131-03" n="3" xml:id="d131-03"/> actual flights. President instructed you
                            simply convey General <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName> and
                                <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss> full explanation of background
                            and purposes our action, as well as Presidentʼs recognition of <gloss target="#t_FMG1">FMG</gloss>ʼs remarkable humanitarianism in
                            allowing safe passage airlift to other side in civil war.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>