<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-01-16T14:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-01-16T14:40:00-05:00" n="168" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                        <head>168. Transcript of Telephone Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d168fn1">Source: Library of Congress, Manuscripts Division,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box
                                361, Telephone Conversations, Chronological File. No classification
                                marking.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d168fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> stated that Major
                                General <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>, Chairman of
                                the Supreme Military Council of Nigeria, was the key to Africa, but
                                that he resented intrusion. As a practical matter, the United States
                                could not do anything that <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName> did not approve.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-01-16T14:40:00-05:00">January 16, 1970, 2:40 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>R: There is to be a meeting of the Nigerian work group. Elliot tells me
                            the President wants to do something. What is it?</p>
                        <p>K: Good question.</p>
                        <p>R: Have to be careful.. Gowan will be key in Africa. He is resentful of
                            too much intrusion. As practical matter we cannot do anything he doesnʼt
                            want. We donʼt want to be in that posture. I want to say we agree and
                            tell them whatever he wants to use, we will help. He did not like
                            military people flying planes in.</p>
                        <p>K: I understand. Because of reasons, the President wants leadership in
                            domestic areas.</p>
                        <p>R: I could issue a press release</p>
                        <p>K: Forming up what we have done this week. That would be helpful. He just
                            called on the State of the Union but wanted to know what is being done
                            in Nigeria.</p>
                        <p>R: A lot</p>
                        <p>K: If you could prepare a release, that would be best.</p>
                        <p>R: We must put it in a way not to get in trouble with <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>. He thinks relief prolonged the
                            war.</p>
                        <p>K: Probably right</p>
                        <p>R: We will see what we can do.</p>
                        <p>K: The latest figure from Lucet is 110. I asked him about a break down.
                            He just hemmed. They donʼt make it easy to be pro-French.</p>
                        <p>R: I saw Zieglerʼs item on my speech. I just re-stated that I had said
                            before</p>
                        <p>K: The President heard it last night and wanted the press to be sure it
                            was understood. Zeigler wanted to confirm</p>
                        <p>R: Itʼs the same as my testimony.</p>
                        <p>—————further conversation in evening</p>
                        <p>R: Following up on Nigeria. There will be a draft press release on what
                            has been done this week. During the weekend we expect to fly in 50 jeeps
                            for relief.</p>
                        <pb facs="d168-02" n="2" xml:id="d168-02"/>
                        <p>K: Can we announce that?</p>
                        <p>R: Yes. We have asked permission from <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>.</p>
                        <p>K: Exactly what the President wanted to do.</p>
                        <p>R: <persName corresp="#p_FCCJ1">Ferguson</persName> is coming back on
                            Monday. Perhaps the three of us could meet with the President and
                            release that I am going to Nigeria.</p>
                        <p>K: He may not want to announce it. But you should be there. He may be
                            going back to Camp David to work on the State of the Union.</p>
                        <p>R: I will try to have tomorrow formalizing <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Elliot Richardson</persName>ʼs committee. Then another one Sunday.
                            Then after <persName corresp="#p_FCCJ1">Ferguson</persName> can announce
                            about medicines and such.</p>
                        <p>K: What about the Brandt visit. We should tell the Germans itʼs to enable
                            you to be there.</p>
                        <p>R: SEATO meeting</p>
                        <p>K: Do you think that you will skip Saigon?</p>
                        <p>R: Saigon and then Phillipines and then back here for Brandt visit.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>