<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>228. Memorandum From Fernando E. Rondon of the National Security Council
                    Staff to the Presidentʼs Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the
                    National Security Council Staff to the Presidentʼs Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczhNQIs9rGlNS1M" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96008124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Humanitarian assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rechJJ62r5nmf4KiI" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046227"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cultural exchange</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">National reconciliation</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="228"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                <head>228. Memorandum From <persName type="from">Fernando E. Rondon</persName> of
                    the National Security Council Staff to the Presidentʼs Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d228fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 735, Country
                        Files, Africa, Burundi, Vol. I. Confidential; Eyes Only; Nodis. Sent for
                        action. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> checked “Agree” and
                        wrote “done” next to it.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d228fn2">Rondon discussed the Presidentʼs
                        instructions on policy toward Burundi and how to convey them to the
                        Department of State. He also forwarded Ambassador Yostʼs memorandum on
                        Burundi developments, which recommended retaining the greatest possible
                        flexibility in U.S. policy toward Burundi.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-10-10"
                        >October 10, 1972</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Burundi Policy</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you recommended in your memorandum at Tab 2, the President agreed that
                    relations with Burundi should be minimal but he added: “K—also see the Burundi
                    Ambassador.” The purpose of this memorandum is to get those instructions
                    conveyed to State either orally, as we would suggest, or in written form as
                    provided for in Tab 1.</p>
                <p>In addition to informing State about our minimal relationship, the Department
                    would be asked to call in the Burundi Ambassador and tell him that as a result
                    of the systematic killings which took place in his country we cannot consider
                    our relations to be normal. This line would anger the Burundi Government but
                    probably not lead to a break in relations or to an ouster of our mission there.
                    Such an ouster would not be in our interest because of our desire (State and
                        <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> feel strongly about this) to monitor
                    potential anti-Zairian activity in Burundi. (As African maps indicate, Burundi
                    is the back door to the traditionally most restive part of Zaire (Congo). If the
                    PRC or <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> wanted to stir up trouble in
                    Eastern Zaire, Burundi would be the ideal basing point for rebels.) Otherwise,
                    our interests in Burundi are minimal.</p>
                <p>Some further thoughts on our future Burundi policy are contained in the brief
                    paper written by our Ambassador to Burundi at Tab 3. The Ambassador agrees that
                    we should have a minimal presence in Burundi but wants to have the leeway to
                    make small gestures to the Burundi Government in order to: (1) encourage
                    reconciliation, (2) lessen the risk that Burundi will think the West is
                    abandoning it—as Belgium slowly reduces its presence—, and (3) maintain our
                    ability to monitor PRC and <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> activity,
                    particularly if it is directed against Zaire.</p>
                <pb facs="d228-02" n="2" xml:id="d228-02"/>
                <p>We recommend that as outlined at Tab 1 the Presidentʼs instructions be conveyed
                    orally to the Department of State, preferably by General <persName
                        corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> to Ted Eliot, to avoid any possible
                    leakage of the Presidentʼs feelings on this matter. If not, questions might be
                    asked about why it took us so long to convey our outrage to Burundi. If you
                    disagree, and want the record to show our reaction, a memorandum for your
                    signature to the Secretary of State is at Tab 1.</p>
                <p>RECOMMENDATION</p>
                <p>That General <persName corresp="#p_HBMJ1">Haig</persName> orally convey the
                    contents of the memorandum at Tab 1 to Ted Eliot.</p>
                <p>Agree [checked]. [handwritten note]<lb/>Disagree, I will sign the memo at Tab
                    1____.</p>
                <pb facs="d228-03" n="3" xml:id="d228-03"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Tab 1</note>
                    <head>Draft Memorandum From the Presidentʼs Assistant for National Security
                        Affairs (Kissinger) to Secretary of State Rogers</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date>undated</date>.</dateline>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                        <item>United States Policy Toward Burundi</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>As a result of the mass murders which recently took place in Burundi, the
                        President has directed that official relations with that state should be
                        minimal. This is not meant to preclude our contributing to humanitarian
                        assistance efforts providing they reach all segments of the population.
                        Other forms of assistance (i.e., bilateral aid/cultural exchange funds,
                        self-help funds) should, however, be discontinued.</p>
                    <p>The President has also directed that Burundiʼs Ambassador to the United
                        States be called in. The Department should inform the Ambassador of the
                        Presidentʼs strong sense of outrage at the recent systematic killings in
                        Burundi and indicate that American relations with Burundi cannot be
                        considered normal until there is a clear change of policy with respect to
                        human rights in that country.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="d228-04" n="4" xml:id="d228-04"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Tab 3</note>
                    <head>Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State (Eliot)
                        to the Presidentʼs Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (Kissinger)</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date when="1972-10-07">October 7,
                            1972</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>Subject:</head>
                        <item>Burundi</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The attached memorandum to Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                            >Newsom</persName> reflects the current views of Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_YRL1">Robert Yost</persName> on our policy toward Burundi.
                        Ambassador Yost is currently in Washington on consultation.</p>
                    <p>The memorandum is forwarded to supplement the Departmentʼs memorandum of
                        September 24 and to assist further in the Presidentʼs consideration of our
                        future posture toward this country.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Theodore L. Eliot</persName>,
                        Jr.</signed>Executive Secretary</closer>
                    <pb facs="d228-05" n="5" xml:id="d228-05"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Attachment</note>
                        <head>Memorandum From the Ambassador to Burundi (Yost) to the Assistant
                            Secretary of State for African Affairs (Newsom)</head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date when="1972-10-06">October 6,
                                1972</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Developments Affecting US Policy on Burundi</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In view of the considerable current interest in the U.S. relationship
                            with Burundi, I would like to make one or two comments for the record.
                            They are made in the light of events since submission of Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_ETLJ1">Eliot</persName>ʼs memorandum to Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, dated September 24, 1972,
                            and are of course purely personal.</p>
                        <p>1. Recent political developments in Burundi indicate a growth in the
                            strength of the more moderate of the Tutsi factions comprising the
                            cabinet. The Prime Minister can be said to head this faction, although
                            it appears to have the general support if not guidance, of President
                            Micombero. Such national reconciliation as may be possible in the coming
                            months will, I believe, take place more easily under this group than
                            under the leadership of the Simbananiye-Shibura-Rwuri faction. The
                            latter is more radical both on foreign policy matters and on the
                            question of how to deal with the Hutu majority.</p>
                        <p>2. We have indications that the Belgians are seriously considering
                            terminating their military assistance to Burundi over the next year or
                            two. While multilateral and bilateral economic assistance to Burundi may
                            remain at roughly recent levels, the prospect of losing Belgian military
                            support is likely to have a disproportionate effect on the insecure
                            Tutsi regime. In this atmosphere, any U.S. move vis.a.vis Burundi would
                            be examined closely for its implications for total Western intentions
                            toward that country. The GRB is lonely and will certainly seek
                            alternatives if it thinks the West is pulling out.</p>
                        <pb facs="d228-06" n="6" xml:id="d228-06"/>
                        <p>3. Chinese interest in economic [text illegible] in Burundi continues.
                            PRC willingness to help fill the potential military gap cannot be ruled
                            out, though a minority elitist government is not the most comfortable
                            bedfellow for the PRC or perhaps—in the longer term—the most useful one.
                            In any event, both the PRC and President <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                                >Mobutu</persName> continue today to consider Burundi an important
                            piece of real estate at the vulnerable eastern door to Zaire. If the
                            Zaire rebels were given active support by a Burundi government,
                            including the use of sanctuary and supply lines, the Zaire government
                            would be faced with a substantially more serious dissident problem in
                            the East. [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>I therefore believe that it is in the interest of the U.S. to retain the
                            greatest possible flexibility in Burundi, continuing our minimum
                            presence during the current difficult period but leaving us free to make
                            selected gestures toward the GRB if political and intertribal
                            developments within Burundi make this useful and feasible.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
