<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>321. Telegram 1424 From the Embassy in Somalia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d321</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">321</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-07-15T10:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-07-15T10:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-07-15T10:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-07-15T10:45:00-05:00" n="321"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                <head>321. Telegram 1424 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Somalia</gloss> to
                    the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d321fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 33–4, Somali-US. Confidential; Priority.
                        Repeated to Addis Ababa, Jidda, Bonn, London, Nairobi, Panama, Paris, Rome,
                            <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CINSTRIKE1"
                            >CINCSTRIKE</gloss> and COMIDEASTFOR.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d321fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HFL1">Hadsel</persName> transmitted a diplomatic note
                        stating that the vessels would be released on payment of the fine, plus
                        expenses or damages claimed by port authority, and warning that further
                        violations would have grave consequences. All concerned parties were
                        satisfied with result and the ships should depart on July 18.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Mogadiscio</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1971-07-15T15:45:00+00:00">July 15, 1971, 1545Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d321-01" n="1" xml:id="d321-01"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Detention US Owned Ships Somalia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Ref:</head>
                    <item>Mogadiscio 1407 and 1409</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. As of 1430 local time I am pleased to report that Foreign Ministry has finally
                    rpt finally come through with note on ship problem. Text follows:</p>
                <p>Quote: The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Somali Democratic Republic presents
                    its compliments to the Embassy of the United States of America and has the
                    honour to inform the Embassy that in accordance with the Somali Governmentʼs
                    endeavour to maintain and improve the relations <pb facs="d321-02" n="2"
                        xml:id="d321-02"/> between the two countries despite the repeated violations
                    of the territorial waters of the Somali Democratic Republic by United States
                    registered or owned vessels, the Somali Government has decided to release the
                    five vessels on condition that a fine of SHS. SO. 80,000 plus any expenses or
                    damages claimed by Mogadiscio Port Authority be paid.</p>
                <p>However, the Government of the Somali Democratic Republic wishes to inform the
                    United States Government through the Embassy in the most clear terms that any
                    grave consequence of any further violations of the territorial waters of the
                    Somali Democratic Republic by United States registeree or owned vessels will be
                    the sole responsibility of the United States Government.</p>
                <p>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Somali Democratic Republic avails itself
                    of this opportunity to renew to the Embassy of the United States of America the
                    assurances of its highest consideration. Unquote</p>
                <p>2. Comment: Whatever differences we may have with the exact reasoning of the
                    note, important fact is that it confirms release of ships. We should, at same
                    time, stress to Department GSDR is extremely serious about statement contained
                    in second paragraph re grave consequences of any further violation against its
                    territorial waters. Embassy will submit note on additional information to
                    Foreign Office first thing Saturday (next working day). Embassy also believes
                    that USG should take whatever additional steps possible to prevent recurrence
                    such incidents and that we should inform Somali Government fully of extent of
                    our efforts.</p>
                <p>3. We have just conferred with Savage and Verret. They inform us that proposed
                    fine and possible port expenses are satisfactory to them. They will contact port
                    authorities as soon as possible to work out any details of payment and release
                    of ships. Embassy will, of course, give them all possible assistance. With luck
                    ships should be able to leave by July 18th.</p>
                <p>4. I know that the Department will share our relief that this problem is finally
                    resolved. We assume you will inform SEDCO immediately. (phone 713-626-4410)</p>
                <pb facs="d321-03" n="3" xml:id="d321-03"/>
                <p>TM for Nairobi. Would appreciate you making special effort to locate Clements and
                    inform him of decision.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HFL1">Hadsel</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
