<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>72. Department of State Press Statement</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="reccdibbkraMVDFLb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2020000630"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Humanitarian relief</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="72"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <head>72. Department of State Press Statement<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d72fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Records of the Special Coordinator on Relief to Civilian Victims of the
                        Nigerian Civil war, February 1969–June 1970, Lot 70 D 336, Box 517, <gloss
                            target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss>, Records. Unclassified. At the top of
                        page one of the statement, Schott wrote, “Clyde—Here is last Fridayʼs
                        statement. The top page was handed out and the second one only read out.
                        SCS.”</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d72fn2">In this statement, which was handed
                        out to the press on June 6, the Department expressed U.S. regret for the
                        attack by the Nigerian Air Force and reiterated the U.S. position of
                        avoiding political or military involvement in the Nigerian civil war. The
                        attached briefing paper, which was read but not distributed, acknowledged
                        that relief and arms night flights were intermingled, and urged expanded
                        relief through daylight flights and a land corridor.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                        calendar="gregorian" when="1969-06-06">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d72-01" n="1" xml:id="d72-01"/>
                <p>Nigeria—Attack on <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> Planes</p>
                <p>The United States has learned with deep regret of the attack by the Nigerian Air
                    Force on one and possibly more transport aircraft carrying relief supplies into
                    Biafra. The exact number of aircraft involved and the circumstances are not yet
                    clear. We are urgently seeking details.</p>
                <p>The United States has taken a clear position with regard to relief in the
                    Nigerian civil war. We have drawn a sharp distinction between the political
                    issues underlying the conflict and humanitarian relief to both sides. We have
                    consistently avoided military and direct political involvement in the war. At
                    the same time, however, we have played a leading role in the international
                    effort to reduce suffering on both sides. The American people have contributed
                    generously to this cause.</p>
                <p>We have on a number of occasions urged Nigeria to take precautions which would
                    avoid the dangers of action against relief operations. While recognizing the
                    problem created by the intermingling of arms flights and relief flights, the
                    United States Government deplores this attack.</p>
                <p>This incident underlines the urgency of alternative relief arrangements for
                    daylight flights and surface corridors. This has been the mission of Ambassador
                    C. Clyde Ferguson, our Special Coordinator for relief, who has been working with
                    both sides to this end.</p>
                <pb facs="d72-02" n="2" xml:id="d72-02"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">PRESS BRIEFING PAPER</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1969-06-06">June 6, 1969</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">Nigeria—Attack on <gloss target="#t_ICRC1">ICRC</gloss> Planes
                        (Additional Background)</p>
                    <p>ON BACKGROUND, to see this attack in perspective, the following factors must
                        be borne in mind:</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Arms flights and relief flights are intermingled. Both utilize the
                            same major Biafran airstrip, both use similar flight patterns over
                            Nigerian territory to reach it, and both operate only at night.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Thus, there is danger of confusion between the relief flights and the
                            arms airlift, under conditions in which both the approaches and the
                            Biafran airstrip are major military targets for Federal Nigeria. Any
                            Nigerian attempt to intercept an arms flight runs the risk of hitting
                            the relief planes.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We have long been conscious of these dangers. We have reportedly urged
                            both sides to reach agreement on daylight relief flights and surface
                            corridors. This would not only increase the flow of relief supplies into
                            Baifra but would avoid the present and extremely dangerous comingling of
                            relief and arms flights which led to this tragic in incident.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
