<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>91. Telegram 2581 From the Mission to the to the European Office of the
                    United Nations to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d91</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">91</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-07-23T12:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-07-23T12:50:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaRk6wjv6u1EItg" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="genocide"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85053923"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Genocide</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-07-23T12:50:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-07-23T12:50:00-05:00" n="91"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                <head>91. Telegram 2581 From the <gloss type="from">Mission</gloss> to the <gloss
                        type="to">European Office of the United Nations</gloss> to the <gloss
                        type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d91fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–9 Biafra-Nigeria. Limited Official Use;
                        Immediate. Also sent to Paris and USUN. Repeated priority to Lagos. Also
                        repeated to London and The Hague.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d91fn2">The Mission transmitted the Biafran
                        Governmentʼs open letter to Special Coordinator <persName corresp="#p_FCCJ1"
                            >Clyde Ferguson</persName> suggesting acceptance of Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>ʼ statement on relief.
                        Biafra accepted day and night relief flights, day flights to commence
                        immediately, and the Cross River proposal. The letter went on, however, to
                        impose conditions that negated acceptance of the proposals.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1969-07-23T17:50:00+00:00">July 23, 1969, 1750Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Paris for Amb <persName corresp="#p_FCCJ1">Ferguson</persName> (Notify at Hotel
                    Crillon)</p>
                <p>The following is a [garble] press release dated Owerri, July 23. Quote: Title:
                    Open letter from the Biafran Government to Professor C. Clyde Ferguson with
                    reference to statement by Secretary of State, <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                        >William Rogers</persName>.</p>
                <p>“The Biafran government has noted with appreciation the continuing interest
                    showed by the American Government on the question of providing relief to
                    alleviate the sufferings of Biafran victims of Nigeriaʼs war of genocide and, in
                    particular, the recent statement made by Secretary of State, <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">William Rogers</persName>, on the subject.</p>
                <p>The Biafran government wishes to indicate its complete agreement with the three
                    fundamental concepts enunciated in Secretary of State, <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">William Rogers</persName>ʼ statement:”</p>
                <p>“First, that the provision by the international community on assistance to both
                    sides in a war should have international participation to assure that it is
                    administered for the <pb facs="d91-02" n="2" xml:id="d91-02"/> benefit of the
                    civilian victims of the war.</p>
                <p>Secondly, that the relief be transported and distributed in ways that convey no
                    military advantage or incur no military liability to either side.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, that the parties to the conflict refrain from exploiting relief issues
                    for partisan, political and propaganda purposes.</p>
                <p>“The Biafran government wishes to reaffirm its acceptance in principle to
                    day/night relief flights with daylight operations to Uli airport commencing
                    immediately. Effective international or other third party guarantees have also
                    been agreed. The Biafran government also wishes to reaffirm its continued
                    acceptance in principle of the surface route (Cross River) proposed by Professor
                        <persName corresp="#p_FCCJ1">Ferguson</persName> in March and accepted by
                    the Biafran government on that occasion.</p>
                <p>The Biafran government wishes to recall that during his visit to Biafra last
                    March, it was clearly understood and accepted by Professor <persName
                        corresp="#p_FCCJ1">Ferguson</persName> on behalf of the US Government that
                    neither Lagos nor any Nigerian held airport should be used as staging post for
                    bringing relief by air. Calabar and Lagos were also ruled out for the surface
                    route operations as agreement was reached to use Cotonou or a ship anchored in
                    mid-ocean from which relief could be transported by barges or helicopter.</p>
                <p>The Biafran government wishes to emphasize that it has always been willing to let
                    Nigerian representatives inspect the relief material at staging posts outside
                    Nigeria, such as Cotonou and Santa Isabel so as to assure themselves that they
                    are genuine Biafra still stand by this. There can be no question, therefore, of
                    Biafra accepting relief coming from or touching down on any Nigerian held
                    territory. The Biafran government expects for that, in fairness, Biafran
                    representatives will have the same right, to inspect relief going into
                    Nigeria.</p>
                <p>It is well known that the shortest and most economical route for relief to come
                    direct into Biafra from these neutral staging posts. To channel or divert them
                    to Nigeria would be to offer them political and military advantages which is in
                    conflict with <pb facs="d91-03" n="3" xml:id="d91-03"/> two the fundamental
                    concepts enunciated by Secretary of State, <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">William
                        Rogers</persName>, and accepted by the Biafran government as indicated
                    above. On this score, the first proposal in Secretary of State, <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">William Rogers</persName>ʼ subsequent four-point approach
                    for a Nigerian staging base fails to meet the test of neutrality and earlier
                    undertaking that relief should not be used to confer military/political
                    advantage or disadvantage to either side.</p>
                <p>The Biafran people and government, however, remain grateful for all the efforts
                    made by the American people and the US administration in this regard and is
                    willing, as before, to enter into discussions to facilitate increased relief
                    supplies. Unquote. Decon on receipt.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TRW1">Tubby</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
