<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                    <head>125. Memorandum From the Acting Director of the United States Information
                        Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>) to the Assistant
                        Secretary of State for Educational and Cultural Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BLD_1">Battle</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d125fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, DIRCTR Sub Files, 1963–69, Bx 6–29 63–69: Acc:
                            #72A5121, Entry UD WW 257, Box 11, Policy and Plans (<gloss target="#t_IOP_1">IOP</gloss>) General 1963. Confidential. Drafted
                            by <persName corresp="#p_AB_1">Anderson</persName> on May 14 and retyped
                            on May 15 at <persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>’s
                            request.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-outside-research" calendar="gregorian" when="1962-05-14">undated</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> and Education</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>’s educational activities, like all its
                        work, are governed by the President’s Statement of Mission to the Director
                        of January 25, 1963.<note n="2" xml:id="d125fn2">See, <ref target="#d109">Document 109</ref>.</note> The pertinent language is: “The mission
                        of the United States Information Agency is to help achieve United States
                        foreign policy objectives by (a) influencing public attitudes in other
                        nations . . .” This precise statement is one aspect of our continuing
                        efforts to make the information program as directly supporting of and
                        responsive to U.S. foreign policy as is humanly possible.</p>
                    <p>Under recently tightened procedures for preparing country plans, <hi rend="italic">every</hi>
                        <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> activity, including exchanges, must
                        be related to an identified and officially stated U.S. objective in the
                        country involved, and approved by Washington.</p>
                    <p>The most unremitting vigilance is required to keep things going simply from
                        inertia. A media program will tend to continue of its own weight and
                        objectives sandwiched under it unless it is periodically re-examined and
                        justified in terms of objectives. For example, we are now reviewing our
                        support of bi-national centers throughout the world to see specifically if
                        we are getting our money’s worth in progress toward objectives, or just
                        continuing to tread a traditional path.</p>
                    <p>English teaching, exchanges, programs of American studies, school textbooks,
                        and libraries are undoubtedly good in their own right. With our budget, we
                        simply cannot afford to engage in activities because they are “a good thing
                        to do”.</p>
                    <p>Our concept for the use of these tools is, then, the one we apply to all
                            <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> programs. Their use is determined
                        by the answers to the following five questions as they appear in the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Country Plan:</p>
                    <p>1. What are the specific objectives of the United States in “X” country, as
                        determined by the Department of State or specified by the U.S.
                        ambassador?</p>
                    <pb facs="0365" n="328" xml:id="pg_328"/>
                    <p>2. Which of these objectives can be supported by psychological or
                        informational means?</p>
                    <p>3. What, then, become our psychological objectives in terms of changing
                        attitudes?</p>
                    <p>4. What people, individuals or groups, must we influence to achieve each
                        psychological objective?</p>
                    <p>5. What means—programs, projects, media—can we best use to reach these
                        people?</p>
                    <p>It is in the answer to the fifth question that the role of educational
                        activities is finally and specifically determined.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed corresp="#p_WDM_1"><persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Donald M.
                                Wilson</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>