<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>126. Memorandum From the Acting Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (Wilson) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs ()
                    to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (Hilsman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917-72PubDipv06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recfab616ca717a635" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="decolonization" subject="colonialism">Colonialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="126"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                <head>126. Memorandum From the Acting Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>) to the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HRJ_1"
                        >Hilsman</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d126fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, DIRCTR Sub Files,
                        1963–69, Bx 6–29 63–69: Acc: #72A5121, Entry UD WW 257, Box 8, FIELD—Far
                        East (<gloss target="#t_IAF_1">IAF</gloss>), 1963. Limited Official Use.
                        Drafted in <gloss target="#t_IAF_1">IAF</gloss>. Edited by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName> on May 16.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-05-17">May 17, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Plan to Counter Afro-Asian Anti-American Propaganda</item>
                </list>
                <p>We have become increasingly concerned with the leadership which Indonesia has
                    given Afro-Asian propaganda over the last several months, particularly the
                    poorly camouflaged anti-Western, anti-American denunciations which have
                    characterized Indonesian foreign policy statements since the Brunei rebellion of
                    last December.<note n="2" xml:id="d126fn2">The revolt began in December 1962 by
                        anti-colonialist rebel factions in Brunei opposed to inclusion in the
                        Federation of Malaysia, which would have grouped Malaya, Singapore, Sarawak,
                        North Borneo, and Brunei. Although the rebellion failed, Brunei nevertheless
                        opted out of joining the Federation. (“Revolt in Brunei,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Washington Post</hi>, December 12, 1962, p. A20)</note> The clever
                    advantage which Indonesia has taken of Philippine-Malayan differences over
                    Malaysia to drive a wedge between these two pro-Western powers and
                    simultaneously to oblige us to assume a stand in opposition to Philippine
                    aspirations in North Borneo has also complicated our task. A third factor of
                    considerable significance to our program through<pb facs="0366" n="329"
                        xml:id="pg_329"/>out the world is the extent of the rapprochement between
                    Indonesia and Communist China, especially as revealed in the proceedings of the
                    Afro-Asian Journalists’ Conference last month in Djakarta.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d126fn3">The conference took place April 24–May 1. An announcement
                        indicated that conference attendees and organizers resolved “‘to condemn the
                        role played by Israel as agent of world imperialism (and) to condemn the
                        military and nuclear aid given to Israel by the United States.’” The
                        resolution also called for the end of “‘United States imperialist occupation
                        of Formosa.’” (“Jakarta Conference Assails U.S., Israel,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Christian Science Monitor</hi>, May 3, 1963, p. 6)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Various factors have made it difficult for the Agency to undertake a concerted
                    effort to counter the undesirable effects stemming from these developments. I
                    believe, however, that the direct attack on the United States contained in the
                    “Djakarta Declaration” of the Journalists’ Conference not only offers a good
                    opportunity for but also requires a direct rebuttal. It also seems to me that
                    our Embassy’s note of protest delivered to the Indonesian Department of Foreign
                    Affairs on May 3<note n="4" xml:id="d126fn4">Not found.</note> at least
                    partially clears the way for such action.</p>
                <p>The fact that the note was written in the Embassy ten days ago<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d126fn5">May 7.</note> to meet an immediate need makes it unsuitable
                    as a peg for any of our proposed output. However, I wonder if the four
                    additional Conference resolution published after the delivery of the note and
                    accusing the United States of imperialist intervention in Cuba, Laos, Korea and
                    South Viet-Nam may not offer an excuse for drafting another protest intended for
                    public release. Such a note could serve as the opening gun in a campaign to set
                    the record straight on “imperialism” and “neo-colonialism”, two terms which have
                    been overworked in Indonesia recently. We would plan not only to exploit the
                    protest in our press and radio output, but would follow up with additional
                    materials refuting the specific charges levied against the U.S. and its allies
                    and exposing Chinese communist tactics in their attempts to capture the
                    Afro-Asian movement. These materials could take the form of a series of radio
                    and press commentaries and analyses of “imperialism” and “neo-colonialism” as
                    well as pamphlets on such subjects as the Afro-Asian Journalists’ Conference
                    itself.</p>
                <p>Another useful action I think we might take would be to offer the Malayan
                    government modest assistance in its proposed Asian Journalists’ Conference,
                    scheduled for June of this year. For example, if our Embassy in Kuala Lumpur
                    believed it desirable, we could quietly circularize the posts in the area for
                    suggestions as to reliable and objective journalists who might be invited by the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOM_1">GOM</gloss> to attend the conference. We would also
                    plan extensive coverage of the event by all Agency media.</p>
                <pb facs="0367" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/>
                <p>Should it appear not desirable to send another note to the Government of
                    Indonesia, we would still plan—with the Department’s concurrence—to undertake a
                    campaign, as outlined above, to set the record straight. I believe, however,
                    that such a campaign would not be as effective, since much of our audience would
                    tend to regard it as mere words without deeds.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_WDM_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Donald M. Wilson</persName>
                        <note n="6" xml:id="d126fn6">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
