<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                    <head>16. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Policy and Plans, United
                        States Information Agency (<persName corresp="#p_STC_2">Sorensen</persName>)
                        to the Director (<persName corresp="#p_MER_1">Murrow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d16fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Office of Plans, General Subject
                            Files, 1949–1970, Acc. # 67A222, Entry UD WW 379, Themes—General 1963
                            &amp; Prior. No classification marking. Printed from an uninitialed
                            copy. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SAM_2">Sirkin</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_STC_2">Sorensen</persName>. A copy was sent to
                                <persName corresp="#p_WDM_1">Wilson</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-03-06">March 6, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Themes for <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Programs</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Following are 21 themes for your consideration. They are divided into four
                        groups:</p>
                    <p>I. Those specifically dealing with foreign policy and which, to be truly
                        effective, require concerted U.S. Government action including <pb facs="0092" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/> statements and programs by the
                        President and other top leaders as well as <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> emphasis.</p>
                    <p>II. Themes on general American concepts which would be more effective with
                        Government-wide cooperation but are nonetheless susceptible to effective use
                        by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> alone.</p>
                    <p>III. Themes on American life and culture, adapted from a longer list
                        promulgated by the Agency in 1959.</p>
                    <p>IV. Themes on Communist subjects, also adapted from a longer list adopted by
                            <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> in 1959.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Themes in the Field of
                        Foreign Policy—(Requiring Government wide cooperation)</p>
                    <p>1. The <hi rend="italic">strength</hi> of the United States and the free
                        world is being maintained so that it will effectively deter aggression,
                        prevent the outbreak of war, increase the security of free nations and be
                        able to frustrate limited aggressions without turning them into nuclear
                        cataclysms. We consider this strength a sacred trust, to be handled with
                        prudent restraint.</p>
                    <p>2. The United States is taking the initiative in making constructive,
                        realistic proposals for various measures of <hi rend="italic">disarmament.</hi> The United States will be tireless in its efforts to
                        find agreement with the Soviet Union on cessation of nuclear tests,
                        prevention of the spread of nuclear weapons, prevention of surprise attack
                        and reduction of nuclear and conventional weapons and forces.</p>
                    <p>3. A strong, effective <hi rend="italic">United Nations</hi> and steady
                        progress toward the <hi rend="italic">rule of law</hi> in the world
                        community offer the greatest promise for escape from the precarious balance
                        of terror and from the possibility of a world in the grip of an iron
                        tyranny. The <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> is particularly important
                        today for the security of small nations. (One specific application of this
                        theme now would be to stress: “The best way to keep the cold war out of
                        Africa is to keep the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> in.”) The United
                        States will do its utmost to strengthen international institutions which can
                        help keep the peace and create world conditions favorable to the development
                        of all societies in accordance with the desires of their people.</p>
                    <p>4. The United States stands ready seriously to <hi rend="italic">negotiate</hi> outstanding issues with the Soviet Union. But we will
                        not negotiate out of fear and are determined to defend the principles and
                        positions of freedom.</p>
                    <p>5. We are committed to the encouragement of <hi rend="italic">economic and
                            social development</hi>, progress and growth for all people. Accordingly
                        we favor cooperative international action to solve common economic problems,
                        the freest possible flow of international trade and extensive efforts by all
                        industrially advanced countries to help the newly developing nations help
                        themselves.</p>
                    <pb facs="0093" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/>
                    <p>6. Both the fate of civilization and the satisfaction of individual
                        aspirations everywhere depend on <hi rend="italic">education.</hi> The
                        United States is committed to the expansion of educational opportunities and
                        the improvement of the quality of education both at home and <hi rend="italic">abroad.</hi> Taking seriously the Wellsian dictum that
                        civilization is a race between education and catastrophe, the United States
                        is eager to help the new countries lift dramatically the levels of their
                        peoples’ literacy, technical skill, knowledge and understanding of the
                        world.</p>
                    <p>7. Americans, with their rich and varied inheritance from other peoples,
                        acknowledge and appreciate the achievements and values of other cultures.
                        The United States seeks to encourage a maximum of <hi rend="italic">cultural
                            interchange</hi> among nations both for its own sake and for its
                        contribution to international understanding. The United States is
                        particularly interested in the greatest possible contact with the peoples of
                        the Sino-Soviet bloc.</p>
                    <p>8. The community of free nations is being reinvigorated with strengthened
                        defenses, greater attention to mutual consultation and more intensive
                        collaboration on the basis of equality in the political, economic and social
                        spheres.</p>
                    <p>(This theme is primarily of use in Western Europe. It is not popular in the
                        former and present dependent territories in Asia and Africa.)</p>
                    <p>9. The United States supports the independence and self-determination of all
                        peoples, including those in the newly developing parts of the world and
                        those behind the Iron Curtain.</p>
                    <p>(This theme is primarily of use in Asia, Africa, and Eastern Europe. It is
                        not popular among some of our allies in Western Europe.)</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Themes on General American
                        Concepts—(Preferably for Governmentwide cooperation but susceptible to
                        effective use by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> alone)</p>
                    <p>1. Basic to American civilization is respect for the <hi rend="italic">dignity</hi> and rights of the individual. We are striving as a nation
                        to expand and perfect the protection of individual rights at home and we
                        favor the advance of <hi rend="italic">freedom</hi> for all men. We are
                        convinced that nations can achieve industrial development and greater social
                        welfare without resort to tyranny.</p>
                    <p>2. The United States of America today is the spiritual heir of the American
                        Revolution of 1776. We are a people uniquely committed and sympathetic to
                            <hi rend="italic">change</hi>, which has been the keynote of our
                        history. Although we have remained steadfast to the democratic principles on
                        which the nation was founded and have preserved its basic political forms,
                        our laws and institutions have evolved in response to changing needs. We do
                        not cling to the status quo and are eager to help other nations on their
                        road to political, economic and social advancement.</p>
                    <pb facs="0094" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                    <p>3. We are eager to let ideas be argued out freely so that the <hi rend="italic">truth</hi> will prevail in all spheres. We are concerned
                        pragmatically with the <hi rend="italic">realities</hi> both of our own
                        existence and of the world situation. We strive to solve the <hi rend="italic">real</hi> problems which are common to <hi rend="italic">all</hi> societies in the various stages of their development rather
                        than view problems through a prism of outdated dogma and distort solutions
                        to fit a strait-jacket of artificial doctrine. The future belongs to those
                        who respect <hi rend="italic">truth</hi> and deal with <hi rend="italic">reality</hi>.</p>
                    <p>4. The United States, along with other nations, is actively engaged in
                        pushing back the frontiers of science. It is particularly interested in
                        enlisting the achievements of <hi rend="italic">science</hi> and technology
                            <hi rend="italic">in the service of humanity</hi>. It is stepping up its
                        own efforts, and is seeking the cooperation of all other nations, in
                        utilizing scientific advances in combating disease, hunger, poverty and
                        ignorance everywhere.</p>
                    <p>5. One of the main sources of strength of democratic society is its <hi rend="italic">openness</hi>. It helps make possible the fulfillment of
                        individual aspirations and gives free play to the creative energies of the
                        people. Americans are also convinced that nations which insist on
                        concealment of their weapons, forces and aggressive intentions are a menace
                        to peace. The United States will join in challenging the leaders of the
                        Sino-Soviet bloc on this issue and on the additional point that regimes
                        which fear the free movement, thought and voice of their own people are
                        basically weak and lacking in self-confidence. (This concept carries little
                        weight in many parts of Africa and Asia.)</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Themes on American Life
                        and Culture—(Adapted from <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Policy
                        Guidance No. 10, July 14, 1959. For use by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> media.)</p>
                    <p>1. The United States is a pluralistic society in which power is widely
                        dispersed and which functions by achieving compromise among conflicting
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>2. The United States has evolved a “mixed economy” in which government holds
                        a balance among countervailing forces and interests, acts as a stimulator
                        and regulator of private enterprise, and provides basic social security for
                        its citizens.</p>
                    <p>3. American education is preparing unprecedented numbers of young people for
                        lives that will be satisfying for themselves and fruitful for society. At
                        the same time it is working to improve educational standards, expand
                        resources and increase attention to gifted students.</p>
                    <p>4. The United States, despite great problems, has been making substantial
                        progress through government and community effort toward the integration of
                        its multi-racial population and toward the social and economic advancement
                        of minority groups.</p>
                    <pb facs="0095" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Themes on Communist Subjects</hi>—(Chosen and adapted from
                            <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Policy Guidance No. 9, June 3,
                        1959. For use by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> media.)</p>
                    <p>1. Communist policies and actions are essentially anti-nationalistic despite
                        vociferous lip-service in support of freedom for colonial peoples.
                        Nationalities have been suppressed by the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and Communist China. Independent nationalist movements
                        abroad are covertly—and eventually overtly—undermined and opposed. Communist
                        leaders support nationalism only as a “temporary stage on the way to
                        Communism.”</p>
                    <p>2. Communism and freedom of thought and expression are incompatible.
                        Communist societies tolerate only a single approach to the manifold problems
                        of society and the varied creative expressions of the human mind.</p>
                    <p>3. The Communist state disregards the dignity and rights of the individual,
                        interferes with family life and builds up new privileged classes.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>