<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 106.Mr. Hall to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <head>No. 106.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in Central
                                America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-04-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1888</date>. (Received April
                        25.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 800.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my dispatch No. 797, of the 2d
                    instant, I have the honor to inclose a copy of a personal note of this date from
                    Señor Magliano, chargé d’affaires of Italy, in Central America, announcing the
                    approval of the protocol, signed by himself and the minister for foreign affairs
                    of Salvador, through my mediation, under your instructions, in January last. The
                    approval is conditional with the rebate of the one-third of the sum agreed upon,
                    which, as has been shown, belongs to Ex-President Zaldivar. Señor Magliano has
                    already assented to this rebate.</p>
                <p>I respectfully invite your attention to Señor Magliano’s note, wherein he
                    expresses his high appreciation of the great service that his Government has
                    received in the amicable settlement of this serious and delicate question with
                    Salvador, which has been effected through the good offices I was able to render
                    to both-parties while carrying out your telegraphic instruction of the 5th of
                    January last past and your No. 535, of the 11th of the same month.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0278" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 800.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Magliano</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hall</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Italian Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-04-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Yesterday I received the following telegram
                        from Señor Delgad minister for foreign affairs of Salvador:</p>
                    <p>“Our protocol of January 24 has been approved by Congress, with the sole
                        condition that the amount to be paid shall be $180,000.”</p>
                    <p>In giving your excellency this information I consider it my duty to again
                        assure you of my sincere gratitude and appreciation of your efficacious aid
                        in bringing to an amicable conclusion the serious and delicate question that
                        existed between my Government and that of Salvador with reference to the
                        claim of Dr. Sagrini.</p>
                    <p>Your personal intervention, requested by the Government of Salvador,
                        authorized by the honorable the Secretary of State at Washington, accepted
                        by the cabinet of Rome, and most gladly welcomed by me, could not but
                        succeed to the advantage of both parties, inasmuch as your action,
                        undertaken with so much tact, prudence, and ability, was shown to be
                        inspired solely by an impartial feeling of justice and equity, as also by
                        the desire to render a service to two friendly Governments, and with perfect
                        disinterestedness.</p>
                    <p>My Government, being informed by me of what your excellency has done in this
                        matter, will certainly not fail to acquaint you with a due manifestation of
                        their gratitude; in the mean time,</p>
                    <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Roberto Magliano.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
