<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 113.Mr. Hosmer to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="113"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                <head>No. 113.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hosmer</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in Central
                                America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-06-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 9, 1888</date>. (Received June
                        28.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 818.].</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your
                    instructions numbered 574, of April 30, 1888, furnishing many good and
                    sufficient reasons why the clause in the annulled treaty between the United
                    States and Guatemala, relating to peace and friendship, should be still <pb
                        facs="0290" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> in force, and I beg respectfully to
                    inclose to you a copy of my note addressed to the minister for foreign affairs
                    of Guatemala, dated June 6, 1888, in which I attempt to impart your views to
                    that Government.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">James R. Hosmer</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 818]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hosmer</persName> to Señor
                                <persName type="to">Barrutia</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-06-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 6, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: Referring to the note addressed to
                        your excellency by the minister of the United States on the 3d of April
                        last, in which it is stated that Mr. Concepcion Pinto had addressed a
                        communication to this legation for information as to whether the Governments
                        of the United States and Guatemala hold that those parts of the treaty of
                        the 3d of March, 1849, between the two countries relative to peace and
                        friendship are still in force as stipulated in its Article xxxiii, I now
                        have the honor to acquaint your excellency that I am instructed by my
                        Government that it holds that the indicated treaty provisions relating to
                        peace and friendship were not terminable and have not been terminated by the
                        notice given by Guatemala in 1873.”</p>
                    <p>My Government is of the opinion that there is a contradistinction between
                        those provisions of the treaty annulled by notice from Guatemala which
                        relate to intercommereial relations and those which relate to peace and
                        friendship; that the former may be denounced by notice of either of the high
                        contracting parties to the other, but that the latter are, from their very
                        essence and nature, as stipulated by the first article of the treaty and
                        defined by Articles XII and XIII, binding upon both; that the existing
                        condition of peace between the two countries naturally includes friendship,
                        mutually reciprocal and equally obligatory upon both Guatemala and the
                        United States, and that under these circumstances there can be nothing
                        unfair to Guatemala in treating the provisions referred to as in force.</p>
                    <p>Availing myself, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">James R. Hosmer</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
