<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 217.Mr. Denby to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="international-law" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="jurisdiction" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-07-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="217" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                <head>No. 217.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-07-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 9, 1888</date>. (Received August
                        20.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 659.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As matter of information on an interesting
                    question, I have the honor to inclose herewith a translation of the agreement
                    lately made by <pb facs="0454" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> the German minister
                    with the Tsung-li Yamên as to the status of Chinese women married to German
                    subjects.</p>
                <p>The understanding reached is that such women shall be subject to the laws of the
                    husband’s nationality. Under Section 1994, Revised Statutes, second edition<note n="*" xml:id="d217fn1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 1994. Any woman who is now or may hereafter
                        be married to a citizen of the United States, and who might herself be
                        lawfully naturalized, shall be deemed a citizen.</note>, page 350, and
                    section 147<note n="†" xml:id="d217fn2">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 147. It is further provided by law that any
                        woman (who might lawfully he naturalized under the existing laws) married,
                        or who shall be married, to a citizen of the United States shall be deemed
                        and taken to be a citizen, The recognition of this citizenship will be
                        subject to the qualifications above referred to. It is also provided (Rev.
                        Stat., 2168) that when any alien who has made declaration dies before he is
                        actually naturalized, the widow and children of such alien shall be
                        considered as citizens of the United States upon taking the oaths prescribed
                        by law.</note>, Con. Reg., 1888, this result does not follow a marriage
                    where the contracting alien is an American, because under recent statutes no
                    Chinese subject can be naturalized.</p>
                <p>Americans have occasionally married Chinese women.</p>
                <p>Intermarriage with persons of other nationalities is common. I personally know
                    some very respectable families where the mother is Chinese and the father an
                    alien.</p>
                <p>The perplexities attending the condition of a Chinese woman married to an
                    American are manifold and embarrassing. She alone of the family would be subject
                    to Chinese law and beyond the pale of American protection. Her husband’s death
                    would leave her practically without any nationality.</p>
                <p>Doubtless, in practice, such an abhorrent condition would be softened as much as
                    possible by the consuls and the legation. But the absolute law still remains and
                    may constitute a bar to legal assistance to defenseless and dependent women,
                    who, by a life-time of discharge of their duties, may have eminently merited all
                    possible consideration. It is true, I think, as stated in the inclosure, that
                    the general international law recognizes that a woman who marries an alien
                    becomes subject to the jurisdiction of her husband’s nationality. It seems to me
                    that this is a better rule than the statutory exception quoted. While I
                    cordially agree that public policy in the United States demands that Chinese
                    subjects shall not be naturalized, I strongly incline to the opinion that a
                    lawful marriage between a Chinese woman and an American citizen should insure to
                    the wife the same protection which is granted to women of other nationalities
                    upon their marriage with our citizens.</p>
                <p>Without further argument I submit the question to your better judgment.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 659.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Agreement between Mr. von Brandt, German minister, and the
                            Tsung-li Yamên in regard to marriages between Germans and Chinese.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Under the custom in all (foreign) countries, where a woman marries an alien
                        she becomes subject to the jurisdiction of her husband’s nationality. This
                        custom should also follow in the case of Chinese women.</p>
                    <p>German consuls have frequently requested me to instruct them as to the
                        jurisdiction a Chinese woman is under who marries a German subject, and
                        acting under their requests it is right and proper that a mutual
                        understanding should be arrived at upon the question.</p>
                    <pb facs="0455" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/>
                    <p>According to my views a Chinese woman who marries a German subject should be
                        subject to the jurisdiction of the laws of her husband’s nationality. But
                        the fact of her marriage to a subject of Germany should be communicated by
                        the German consul (of the place) to the Chinese local authorities. This
                        would meet the views of both countries.</p>
                    <p>As to existing marriages between Chinese women and Germans, after the present
                        agreement between Mr. von Brandt and the Tsung-li Yamên is settled and takes
                        effect, German consular officers shall then report them to the proper local
                        authorities. If among them there are cases where the parties have failed to
                        request the German consuls to report their marriage to the local authorities
                        and an action at law is brought against the wife it shall be tried and
                        settled by the Chinese authorities, or if it appears that a Chinese woman
                        has been guilty of crime before her marriage, and for that reason marries a
                        German subject for the purpose of placing herself under the protection of a
                        distant country (Germany), on such cases being brought to light the crime
                        committed shall be punished by the Chinese authorities.</p>
                    <p>German women entering into the bonds of matrimony with Chinese subjects shall
                        be subject to the laws of their husband’s nationality.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
