<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 242.Mr. Chang Yen Hoon to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-01-15T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-01-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <head>No. 242.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Chang Yen Hoon</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinese Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington, D. C.</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-01-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 15, 1887</date>. (Received January
                        17.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note dated the 12th instant, the contents of which I have carefully
                    noted.</p>
                <p>I have also several things which I intend to propose to your excellency’s
                    consideration, but, under instructions from the foreign office, I can not do so
                    until all the pending cases are settled.</p>
                <p>Referring to the cases of outrages committed upon the Chinese in the United
                    States in the past years, you kindly gave me repeated assurances, in person,
                    that indemnities would be awarded and the cases set-tied within a certain time,
                    which I, in my dispatches, more than, once commuicated to the foreign office;
                    but, nevertheless, they still remain unsettled; consequently I find myself
                    placed in a rather delicate position, which it seems hard for me to extricate
                    myself from.</p>
                <p>It seems premature for us to enter into negotiations for concluding a treaty, as
                    suggested by you, at the present moment.</p>
                <p>I have a strong desire to maintain the friendly and cordial relations of the two
                    Governments, but as it would lack the spirit of harmony necessary for carrying
                    on negotiations if arguments should only be set forth in correspondence, I shall
                    hope to do myself the honor of having an interview with, your excellency at my
                    earliest convenience.</p>
                <p>Accept, sir, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chang Yen Hoon.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
