<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 244.negotiations for the protection of the chinese in the united
                    states..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Active measures</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="244"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                <head>No. 244.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">negotiations for the protection of the chinese in the
                        united states</hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="received-date" when="1887-03-18">undated</date>].</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">[Left at the Department by the Chinese minister March 18,
                    1887.]</p>
                <p>By article 3 of the treaty of 1880, which reads as follows: “If Chinese laborers,
                    or Chinese of any other class, now either permanently or temporarily residing in
                    the territory of the United States, meet with ill treatment at the hands of any
                    other persons, the Government of the United States will exert all its powers to
                    devise measures for their protection, and to secure to them the same rights,
                    privileges, immunities, and exceptions as may be enjoyed by the citizens or
                    subjects of the most favored nations, and to which they are entitled by treaty,”
                    the Chinese in the United States are entitled to enjoy completely the rights and
                    privileges of protection; but in September of the year 1885 there occurred a
                    case in Bock Springs, Wyoming Territory, where the Chinese were murdered and
                    burned to death by a mob of laborers, and immediately after the wicked class of
                    people in the Western Territories in various ways followed this bad example;
                    consequently, there have been numberless cases in which the Chinese were
                    outrageously treated. Thanks to the United States Government for having sent its
                    troops for the suppression of the riots, by which kind act not a few lives of
                    the Chinese were preserved. The President of the United States having been fully
                    informed of the sad sufferings of the innocent Chinese in the Rock Springs case,
                    and being prompted by a sense of justice, recommended to Congress the necessity
                    of awarding indemnification for the losses and damages sustained by the
                    suffering Chinese. An indemnity bill has been passed accordingly, granting the
                    full amounts claimed. Nevertheless no justice or redress has as yet been done or
                    given on account of the Chinese who were murdered. The acts of expulsion of the
                    Chinese did not die away even until last fall.</p>
                <p>The treaty stipulations require that the United States Government shall exert all
                    its power to devise measures for the protection of the Chinese in the United
                    States in case they should meet with ill treatment at the hands of any other
                    persons, but the population in the Western Territories have made the ill
                    treatment of the Chinese a constant practice, and have looked upon the acts of
                    expelling and burning out the Chinese as sources of pleasure. Consequently, no
                    sooner had the perpetrators in the cases of outrage in Rock Springs and Seattle
                    been arrested than they were released, which could by no means strike terror to
                    the hearts of the evil-doers. The Chinese Government, having the interests of
                    its subjects at heart, being unable to bear any longer with the ill manners with
                    which they are treated in the foreign country, and with a view of averting any
                    possible cause of disturbance and ill feelings between the people of the United
                    States and China which might jeopardize the friendly relations of the two
                    Governments, did, on the 4th day of the seventh month last year (3d August,
                    1886), write to Mr. Denby, the United States minister at Peking, through the
                    foreign office (Tsung-li Yamên), on the subject of China’s purpose of her own
                    accord to prohibit its subjects of the laboring class from emigrating to the
                    United States. There are three important things which China proposes to do in
                    this respect: (1) Those Chinese laborers who have not been to the United States
                    will be strictly prohibited from going thither. (2) Those Chinese laborers who
                    have returned to China from the United <pb facs="0501" n="367" xml:id="pg_367"/>
                    States, where they have no wife or family or relations, money, or property, will
                    not be allowed to go back thither. (3) The Chinese who are now resident in the
                    United States should be entitled to proper protection in conformity with the
                    treaty stipulations. The detailed and minute provisions of the regulation
                    relating to the above are to be discussed and decided upon by me (the Chinese
                    minister) and the honorable Secretary of State. The British minister in Peking
                    has also been communicated with on the subject by the foreign office, with a
                    request that his Government may be informed thereof, to the end that the
                    governor of Hong-Kong may be instructed to assist the Chinese Government in
                    strictly carrying out these regulations to their fullest extent, a copy of which
                    was some time since sent over to your Department.</p>
                <p>In your note of the 12th January last an inhibition was proposed of the
                    immigration of Chinese laborers into the United States for a term of years, and
                    a discussion together of measures for carrying out the same was suggested, so
                    that when agreed to they might be communicated to the Senate for consideration.
                    And in reply of the 15th January last I said I had also several things to
                    propose for your excellency’s consideration.</p>
                <p>Now, I have, in conformity with the instructions from the foreign office,
                    carefully drawn out in detail certain provisions in connection with the proposed
                    prohibition and restriction of the coming of the Chinese laborers into the
                    United States, and the proper protection of the Chinese that are now in the
                    United States, which I send herewith to your excellency, so that we may together
                    discuss the same, in the hope that, when they are agreed upon, you may
                    communicate the same to the Senate and I to the foreign office, for their
                    respective consideration; and upon their approval by the latter the decree of my
                    sovereign will be asked for the permission to have them supplemented to the
                    treaty of November 17, 1880, in order that they may be faithfully carried out by
                    both Governments.</p>
                <p>The proposed provisions are as follows: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>China, having of her own accord prohibited the immigration of its
                            subjects into the United States, will do so from time to time in such
                            manner as may be required by circumstances, there being no necessity for
                            fixing a certain period for that purpose.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>No Chinese laborer who has never been to the United States shall be
                            permitted to go thither. Any such laborer who shall be detected in
                            attempting to go to the United States by fraudulently making use of a
                            return ticket and by personating the name of the person mentioned
                            therein will be visited with a heavy fine.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Any Chinese laborer who has returned to China from the United States
                            can not go thither again unless he really has there his family or
                            relations, money, or property, or accounts contracted through him
                            pending settlement. But before he embarks for the United States he must
                            furnish to the consul-general at San Francisco, for his examination, a
                            full statement setting forth the names of the members of his family or
                            relations, the locality where he has his money or property, and the
                            names of the parties connected with the pending accounts.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Any Chinese laborer who, returning to China from other countries, may
                            desire to pass <hi rend="italic">in transitu</hi> through the United
                            States should be permitted to do so as hitherto without let or
                            hindrance.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>From henceforth any Chinese laborer who desires to leave the United
                            States for China shall, before his departure, report to the
                            consul-general at the port of San Francisco whether or not he has in the
                            United States a family or relations, money or property, or any accounts
                                <pb facs="0502" n="368" xml:id="pg_368"/> pending settlement, in
                            order that the above may be inserted in the certificate for the purpose
                            of examination and investigation.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>The exempt class of Chinese subjects, whether proceeding to the United
                            States as teachers, students, merchants, or from curiosity, if possessed
                            with certificates or documents of proof of other description, shall be
                            at once permitted to land without any detention under any
                            pretense.</item>
                        <label>(7)</label>
                        <item>In the two annual messages of 1885 and 1886 of the President of the
                            United States to congress, his excellency expressed his anxiety for the
                            maintenance of harmony and friendship between the two countries, for the
                            extension of protection over the Chinese subjects in conformity with the
                            treaty stipulations, for the strictly warning of American subjects
                            against ill-treating the Chinese subjects, and that no oppression of
                            individuals of a special race should be tolerated. This gave evidence of
                            the desire of the President to strengthen the friendly relations between
                            the two countries, which is fully appreciated, by both the Chinese
                            Government and its subjects. It is now desirable that the President
                            should be respectfully requested to proclaim to the public that, with a
                            view of preventing its subjects from suffering ill-treatment in the
                            foreign distant land, the Chinese Government has, of its own accord,
                            prohibited the coming of Chinese laborers into the United States; that
                            this measure will ensure the reduction of the number of the Chinese
                            laborers in the United States; that the Chinese subjects, American
                            citizens as well as aliens, shall live peaceably together without any
                            prejudice against each other; that it is provided by article 4 of the
                            treaty of 28th July, 1868, that Chinese subjects in the United States
                            shall enjoy entire liberty of conscience, and shall be exempt from all
                            disability or persecution on account of their religious faith or worship
                            in the United States, and that any person who may hereafter commit acts
                            of murder, arson, and robbery, similar to those in the past, against the
                            Chinese shall be severely punished without the least leniency.</item>
                        <label>(8)</label>
                        <item>It is desired that a United States marshal or other officer should be
                            appointed, and have his office in San Francisco, whose duty it should be
                            to especially attend to those cases wherein Chinese and Americans may be
                            concerned that may have occurred in all the States or Territories of the
                            United States of America. It is necessary that many United States
                            officers should be employed in the places where the Chinese are settled,
                            for the purpose of making inquiries from time to time. If they should
                            hear of any wicked band planning to do injuries or violence against the
                            Chinese they should report the same by telegraph to the United States
                            marshal or other officer thus appointed, to the end that efforts may be
                            made for their protection, and for the arrest and punishment of the
                            wicked band.</item>
                        <label>(9)</label>
                        <item>It is desired that instructions should be given to the military and
                            civil local authorities of all the States and Territories to take, from
                            time to time, active measures for watching the circumstances attending
                            the doings of the respective laboring classes of China, America, and
                            other countries, and that if they should find any feeling of discord
                            amongst them they should make preparations for any emergency of disorder
                            that may arise, either by employing extra number of police officers or
                            enlisting militia for the purpose of suppressing any riot that may break
                            out, and for patrolling the streets, to the end that dangers may be
                            averted by the adoption of precautionary measures. It is further
                            desirable that in case of any outrage, such as arson or expulsion, being
                            committed against the Chinese by lawless bands in any State or
                            Territory, or if <pb facs="0503" n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/> under
                            contemplation, the local authorities on learning of the same may be
                            permitted, as they deem proper, to summon by telegraph the assistance of
                            troops from the vicinity for the suppression of the same, and the
                            officer commanding the same shall at once proceed thither with his
                            troops. There are precedents for this in the treatment and protection of
                            American merchants and missionaries in China by the Chinese
                            Government.</item>
                        <label>(10)</label>
                        <item>It is to be hoped that hereafter if any persons, acting in concert,
                            are guilty of assailing and killing the Chinese with fire-arms they will
                            be punished by hanging, as a warning to others. Those who aid and abet
                            in the assault, armed, should be severely dealt with, and not be
                            permitted to escape punishment. I don’t allude now to ordinary and
                            isolated cases of assault between individuals.</item>
                        <label>(11)</label>
                        <item>Simple expulsion by force of the Chinese by lawless persons, though
                            unaccompanied by arson, murder, or robbery, or bodily injury, is still a
                            violation of the treaty stipulations, and a deliberate purpose to create
                            disorders, and the perpetrators should be punished according to their
                            relative guilt as leaders or followers. The foregoing provisions, Nos.
                            7, 8, 9, 10, and 11, will show what measures I think desirable to have
                            adopted to secure the protection of Chinese subjects in this country in
                            conformity with the treaty stipulations. It is the Government of the
                            United States, and not the State nor local governments, which guarantied
                            to exert all its power to devise measures for the protection of Chinese
                            subjects in the United States, and for this reason I have made the
                            foregoing suggestions. They may not be altogether in conformity to the
                            usual practice in the United States, but they are very much like what
                            the United States ministers and consuls have asked my Government to do,
                            and which it has done for Americans in China. If I correctly understand
                            what has been decided, only a few days ago, by the Supreme Court in this
                            capital, there is no law of the Congress of the United States to punish
                            wicked men for conspiring to injure or intimidate Chinese subjects, or
                            thereby murdering, wounding, assaulting, or robbing them. But the court
                            says that the Congress has the power to pass such laws, and to have them
                            enforced by the Government officers and in its courts, and that it may
                            pass such laws as are necessary to carry out treaty stipulations. If,
                            then, in my foregoing suggestions, I have not conformed in all respects
                            to the practice of your country, I think this very respectable court has
                            sanctioned the spirit of my suggestions, and your excellency’s great
                            wisdom in the practice and duty of your Government will enable you to
                            accept in some amended form the propositions I have made, and we may
                            thus be able to agree upon measures to carry out the guaranties of the
                            treaty which have up to this time been so often violated with
                            impunity.</item>
                        <label>(12)</label>
                        <item>With regard to the losses and damages sustained by the Chinese in all
                            the cases of cruel outrage against them in past years, it is requested
                            that the United States Government should do justice and award
                            indemnities in every case. It is suggested that this can be done by
                            following the precedent in the claims convention of November 8, 1858, by
                            paying to the Chinese Government a sum sufficient to cover all losses,
                            and this sum to be distributed by China, or by agreeing upon a claims
                            commission to estimate and award the losses.</item>
                        <label>(13)</label>
                        <item>Chinese merchants who belong to the exempt class mentioned in the
                            treaty, on their landing at the port of San Francisco, have been often
                            subjected to inconveniences and troubles by being compelled to appear in
                            court, through the acts of the local authorities at that port, in
                            investigating and discriminating the cases of returning Chinese la <pb
                                facs="0504" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> borers thereto in past years.
                            Hereafter they should be permitted to land upon the presentation of
                            their certificates or production of evidence or bond of security,
                            without the necessity of going into court for examination.</item>
                        <label>(14)</label>
                        <item>By article 18 of the treaty of 1858, there is a provision relating to
                            extradition. It would be well to make a treaty agreement, so that
                            hereafter, if any criminals who are Chinese subjects should take refuge
                            in the United States, they may be delivered up to the Chinese consuls in
                            order to be returned to China for trial and punishment.</item>
                        <label>(15)</label>
                        <item>In former years a duty at the rate of 10 per cent, on its cost value
                            was levied on imported rice from China to American ports; at a later
                            date it was raised to $1 for each 100 pounds; and, in 1864, on account
                            of the civil war, it was increased to $2.50 per 100 pounds, just about
                            equal to the cost value of the rice in China. In 1883 it was reduced to
                            $2.25. Now you are enjoying peace and prosperity and your treasury is
                            overflowing, can not you afford to reduce the duty? The Chinese subsist
                            upon rice as your people do upon wheat. It’s high price is a grievous
                            burden upon the poor class of Chinese in this country; it is right,
                            therefore, to ask your Government to take the subject into its kind
                            consideration to the end that the duty may be reduced to $1 per 100
                            pounds, for which the Chinese will feel very grateful. Of course I can
                            not expect that your Government will take off the entire duty as you
                            have from tea and Chinese starch.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">A communication from the <gloss type="from">foreign
                                office</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British minister at
                                Peking</gloss>, sent on the 4th day of the 7th month last year</hi>
                            (3<hi rend="italic">d August</hi>, 1886).</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We have the honor to inform you that cases of
                        repeated outrages recently committed against the Chinese in the United
                        States have rendered it necessary for us to write to the British minister in
                        Peking, and also to the Chinese minister in Washington, with a request that
                        he should communicate with the honorable Secretary of State on the subject,
                        begging him to cause protection to be extended over the Chinese laborers
                        residing there in conformity with the treaty stipulations, and also to the
                        use of strenuous efforts for the apprehension of the perpetrators of the
                        outrages.</p>
                    <p>The prejudice of the people of the United States against the Chinese laborers
                        is so intense that it is next to impossible to remove it, and if no timely
                        precautionary measures are taken in the matter there may be no end to
                        disasters.</p>
                    <p>Now China proposes to prohibit of her own accord the emigration of Chinese
                        laborers into the United States. No Chinese laborer will be permitted to go
                        to the United States, nor any Chinese laborer who has returned to China from
                        the United States where, if he has no family or relations, money or
                        property, will be allowed to go back thither, in order that the Chinese
                        laborers who remain in the United States may gradually be reduced in number,
                        causes of danger be averted, and lives preserved.</p>
                    <p>It appears from inquiries made that Chinese laborers going to the United
                        States generally embark in steamers that sail from Bong-Kong, which renders
                        the examination intended to be made by the Chinese officials difficult. For
                        this reason we have the honor to request that you will kindly communicate
                        with your Government on the subject, to the end that instructions may be
                        given to the governor of Hong-Kong, to devise measures for the examination
                        and prohibition of the emigration above referred to, and to disallow any
                        vessel of any nationality to carry any Chinese laborer as passenger for any
                        port in the United States, so as to strike the evil at its very root.
                        Thereby the future troubles may be avoided.</p>
                    <p>In former years Peru and Spain trafficked in Chinese, and the Hong-Kong
                        government assisted in terminating the evil by examination and prohibition.
                        But the outrages committed against the Chinese laborers in the United States
                        by burning and expulsion are comparatively worse than the traffic alluded
                        to.</p>
                    <p>Your Government is noted for its benevolence and we feel sure that it will
                        not fail to accede to our request in rendering its assistance in the
                        matter.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
