<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 286.Mr. Walker to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="discrimination" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376" lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="286" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                <head>No. 286.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Walker</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-06-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 7, 1888</date>. (Received July
                        10.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 116.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to state that your No. 78, of
                    April 28, last, was received at this legation on the 30th ultimo, and that on
                    the same day I addressed a communication to the minister of foreign affairs, a
                    copy of which I herewith inclose, and that on the 2d instant I received the
                    minister’s reply, a copy of which I have also the honor to inclose, with a
                    translation.</p>
                <p>As soon as any further information on the subject of these communications is
                    received at this legation, I shall hasten to lay it before you.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jno. G. Walker.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 116.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Walker</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Restrepo</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogota</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-05-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 30, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The undersigned, chargé d’affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> of the United States, presents his
                        compliments to his excellency the minister of foreign affairs, and invites
                        his attention to the following statement:</p>
                    <p>It has been brought officially to the knowledge of the undersigned that the
                        local government of the department of Panama has ordered the levy and
                        collection of a capitation tax on citizens of the United States residing in
                        that department from which the subjects of Great Britain are exempt.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned is therefore directed by his Government to call the attention
                        of that of Colombia to these facts, and to say that it insists that there
                        shall be no discrimination against the citizens of the United States,
                        wherever they may reside,” since such discrimination is in violation of the
                        provisions of the 7th article of the treaty of 1846, and of the general
                        principle of the law of nations.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned trusts, therefore, that the supreme Government of Colombia
                        will take early measures to remove this just cause of complaint.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned avails, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Jno. G. Walker.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 116.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Restrepo</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Walker</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Republic of Colombia,<lb/>Ministry of Foreign
                                    Affairs</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-05-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 2, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The compliments of the minister of foreign affairs to the honorable chargá
                        d’affaires of the United States, and he has the honor to reply, by means of
                        the present communication, to your polite note of the 2d of May last.</p>
                    <p>As there are no antecedents in the ministry of foreign affairs which enable
                        it to determine the nature of the contribution of which you speak, and which
                        you say has been levied upon the citizens of the United States in Panama, it
                        is necessary to make inquiry of the administrative authorities of that
                        department.</p>
                    <p>With this object, the undersigned has just dispatched a telegram to the
                        administrator of customs at Buenaventura, directing him to send, by the
                        first mail steamer, a dispatch to the governor of Panama, requesting
                        information as to the character of the tax, upon whom levied, under what
                        form, and all the circumstances, which will enable us to determine its
                        compatibility or incompatibility with treaties, and with the universal rules
                        of the law of nations.</p>
                    <p>I promise your honor that as soon as this information is received it shall be
                        communicated to the honorable legation of the United States, together with
                        the resolution in the case.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned has the honor to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vicente Restrepo.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
