<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 314.Award of the Arbitrator, the President
                                of the United States, upon the validity of the Treaty of Limits
                                of 1858  1858 between Nicaragua and Costa
                                Rica.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">314</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871" lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807" lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846" lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="314" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d314">
                <head>No. 314.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Award of the Arbitrator, the President
                                of the United States, upon the validity of the Treaty of Limits
                                of</hi> 1858 <hi rend="italic">between Nicaragua and Costa
                                Rica.</hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">Grover Cleveland, President of the United States, to whom
                            it shall concern, greeting:</p>
                <p>The functions of arbitrator having been conferred upon the President of
                            the United States by virtue of a treaty signed at the City of Guatemala
                                <pb facs="0591" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> on the 24th day of
                            December, one thousand eight hundred and eighty-six, between the
                            Republics of Costa Rica and Nicaragua, whereby it was agreed that the
                            question pending between the contracting Governments in regard to the
                            validity of their Treaty of Limits of the 15th day of April, one
                            thousand eight hundred and fifty-eight, should be submitted to the
                            arbitration of the President of the United States of America) that if
                            the arbitrator’s award should determine that the treaty was valid, the
                            same award should also declare whether Costa Rica has the right of
                            navigation of the river San Juan with vessels of war or of the revenue
                            service: and that in the same manner the arbitrator should decide, in
                            case of the validity of the treaty, upon all the other points of
                            doubtful interpretation which either of the parties might find in the
                            treaty and should communicate to the other party within thirty days
                            after the exchange of the ratifications of the said treaty of the 24th
                            day of December, one thousand eight hundred and eighty-six.</p>
                <p>And the Republic of Nicaragua having duly communicated to the Republic of
                            Costa Rica eleven points of doubtful interpretation found in the said
                            Treaty of Limits of the 15th day of April, one thousand eight hundred
                            and fifty-eight; and the Republic of Costa Rica having failed to
                            communicate to the Republic of Nicaragua any points of doubtful
                            interpretation found in the said last-mentioned treaty;</p>
                <p>And both parties having duly presented their allegations and documents to
                            the arbitrator, and having thereafter duly presented their respective
                            answers to the allegations of the other party as provided in the treaty
                            of the 24th day of December, one thousand eight hundred and
                            eighty-six;</p>
                <p>And the arbitrator pursuant to the fifth clause of said last-named treaty
                            having delegated his powers to the honorable George L. Rives, Assistant
                            Secretary of State, who, after examining and considering the said
                            allegations, documents and answers, has made his report in writing
                            thereon to the arbitrator;</p>
                <p>Now, therefore, I, Grover Cleveland, President of the United States of
                            America, do hereby make the following decision and award: <list>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">First</hi> The above-mentioned Treaty of
                                    Limits, signed on the 15th day of April, one thousand eight
                                    hundred and fifty-eight, is valid.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. The Republic of Costa Rica
                                    under said treaty and the stipulations contained in the sixth
                                    article thereof, has not the right of navigation of the river
                                    San Juan with vessels of war; but she may navigate said liver
                                    with such vessels of the revenue service as may be related to
                                    and connected with her enjoyment of the “purposes of commerce”
                                    accorded to her in said article, or as maybe necessary to the
                                    protection of said enjoyment.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. With respect to the points of
                                    doubtful interpretation communicated as aforesaid by the
                                    Republic of Nicaragua, I decide as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The boundary line between the Republics of Costa Rica
                                            and Nicaragua, on the Atlantic side, begins at the
                                            extremity of Punta de Castilla at the mouth of the San
                                            Juan de Nicaragua River, as they both existed on the
                                            15th day of April, 1858. The ownership of any accretion
                                            to said Punta de Castilla is to be governed by the laws
                                            applicable to that subject.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The central point of the Salinas Bay is to be fixed by
                                            drawing a straight line across the mouth of the bay and
                                            determining mathematically the centre of the closed
                                            geometrical figure formed by such straight line and the
                                            shore of the bay at low-water mark.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>By the central point of Salinas Bay is to be
                                            understood the centre of the geometrical figure formed
                                            as above stated. The limit of the bay <pb facs="0592" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> towards the ocean is a
                                            straight line drawn from the extremity of Punta Arranca
                                            Barba, nearly true south to the westernmost portion of
                                            the land about Punta Sacate.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Costa Rica is not bound to concur with
                                            the Republic of Nicaragua in the expenses necessary to
                                            prevent the bay of San Juan del Norte from being
                                            obstructed; to keep the navigation of the river or port
                                            free and unembarrassed, or to improve it for the common
                                            benefit.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Costa Rica is not bound to contribute
                                            any proportion of the expenses that may be incurred by
                                            the Republic of Nicaragua for any of the purposes above
                                            mentioned.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Costa Rica can not prevent the
                                            Republic of Nicaragua from executing at her own expense
                                            and within her own territory such works of improvement,
                                                <hi rend="italic">provided</hi> such works of
                                            improvement do Hot result in the occupation or flooding
                                            or damage of Costa Rica territory, or in the destruction
                                            or serious impairment of the navigation of the said
                                            river or any of its branches at any point where Costa
                                            Rica is entitled to navigate the same. The Republic of
                                            Costa Rica has the right to demand indemnification for
                                            any places belonging to her on the right bank of the
                                            river San Juan which may be occupied without her
                                            consent, and for any lands on the same bank which may be
                                            flooded or damaged in any other way in consequence of
                                            works of improvement.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>The branch of the river San Juan known as the Colorado
                                            River must not be considered as the boundary between the
                                            Republics of Costa Rica and Nicaragua in any part of its
                                            course.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>The right of the Republic of Costa Rica to the
                                            navigation of the river San Juan with men of war or
                                            revenue cutters is determined and defined in the second
                                            article of this award.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Costa Rica can deny to the Republic of
                                            Nicaragua the right of deviating the waters of the river
                                            San Juan in case such deviation will result in the
                                            destruction or serious impairment of the navigation of
                                            the said river or any of its branches at any point where
                                            Costa Rica is entitled to navigate the same.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Nicaragua remains bound not to make
                                            any grants for canal purposes across her territory
                                            without first asking the opinion of the Republic of
                                            Costa Rica, as provided in Article <hi rend="smallcaps">viii</hi> of the Treaty of Limits of the 15th day
                                            of April, one thousand eight hundred and fifty-eight.
                                            The natural rights of the Republic of Costa Rica alluded
                                            to in the said stipulation are the rights which, in view
                                            of the boundaries fixed by the said Treaty of Limits,
                                            she possesses in the soil thereby recognized as
                                            belonging exclusively to her; the rights which she
                                            possesses in the harbors of San Juan del Norte and
                                            Salinas Bay; and the rights which she possesses in so
                                            much of the river San Juan as lies more than three
                                            English miles below Castillo Viejo, measuring from the
                                            exterior fortifications of the said castle as the same
                                            existed in the year 1858; and perhaps other rights not
                                            here particularly specified. These rights are to be
                                            deemed injured in any case where the territory belonging
                                            to the Republic of Costa Rica is occupied or flooded;
                                            where there is an encroachment upon either of the said
                                            harbors injurious to Costa Rica; or where there is such
                                            an obstruction or deviation of the River San Juan as to
                                            destroy or seriously impair the navigation of the said
                                            river or any of its branches at any point where Costa
                                            Rica is entitled to navigate the same.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>The Treaty of Limits of the 15th day of April, one
                                            thousand eight hundred and fifty-eight, does not give to
                                            the Republic of Costa Rica the right to be a party to
                                            grants which Nicaragua may make for interoceanic <pb facs="0593" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/> canals; though
                                            in cases where the construction of the canal will
                                            involve an injury to the natural rights of Costa Rica,
                                            her opinion or advice, as mentioned in Article VIII of
                                            the treaty, should be more than “advisory “or
                                            “consultative,” It would seem in such cases that her
                                            consent is necessary, and that she may thereupon demand
                                            compensation for the concessions she is asked to make;
                                            but she is not entitled as a right to share in the
                                            profits that the Republic of Nicaragua may reserve for
                                            herself as a compensation for such favors and privileges
                                            as she, in her turn, may concede.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and have caused the
                            seal of the United States to be hereunto affixed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">Done in triplicate at the city of
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, on <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1888-03-22">the
                                    twenty-second day of March, in the year one thousand eight
                                    hundred and eighty-eight, and of the Independence of the United
                                    States the one hundred and twelfth</date>.</dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Grover
                                Cleveland.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>By the
                                        President:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. F.
                                        Bayard</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of
                                    State.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 314.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Arbitration between the Republics of Costa Rica
                                    and Nicaragua in relation to the validity of the treaty of the
                                    15th April</hi>, 1858.—<hi rend="italic">Report to the
                                    arbitrator, the President of the United States, by George L.
                                    Rives, Assistant Secretary of State.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the President:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 24th day of December, 1886, the
                                Republics of Costa Rica and Nicaragua, by a treaty signed on that
                                day, agreed that the question pending between the contracting
                                Governments in regard to the validity of the “Treaty of Limits” of
                                the 15th April, 1858, should be submitted to arbitration. It was
                                further agreed that the arbitrator of that question should be the
                                President of the United States of America; that within sixty days
                                from the ratification of the treaty of arbitration the contracting
                                Governments should solicit of the arbitrator his acceptance of the
                                charge; that within ninety days from the notification to the parties
                                of the acceptance of the arbitrator they should present to him their
                                allegations and documents; that the arbitrator should communicate to
                                the representative of each Government, within eight days after their
                                presentation, the allegations of the opposing party, in order that
                                the opposing party might be able to answer them within thirty days
                                following that upon which the same should have been communicated;
                                that the decision of the arbitrator must be pronounced within six
                                months from the date upon which the term allowed for the answers to
                                the allegations should have expired; and that the arbitrator might,
                                delegate his powers, provided he did not fail to intervene directly
                                in pronouncing the final decision. It was further provided that if
                                the arbitrator’s award should determine that the treaty of the 15th
                                April, 1858, was valid, the same award should also declare whether
                                Costa Rica has the right of navigation of the river San Juan with
                                vessels of war or of the revenue service; and that he should in the
                                same manner decide, in case of the validity of the treaty, upon all
                                the other points of doubtful interpretation which either of the
                                parties might find in the treaty and communicate to the other within
                                thirty days after the exchange of ratifications of the treaty of
                                arbitration.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with the procedure thus agreed on, the Republic of
                                Nicaragua communicated to the Republic of Costa Rica a statement of
                                eleven points of doubtful interpretation in the treaty of the 15th
                                April, 1858, which it proposed to submit to the decision of the
                                arbitrator. The Government of Costa Rica did not communicate any
                                corresponding statement, and now declares that it finds nothing in
                                that treaty which is not perfectly clear and intelligible.</p>
                    <p>The two Governments having thereafter solicited your acceptance of
                                the charge, you were pleased, on the 30th day of July, 1887, to
                                signify your acceptance of it, and the representatives of both
                                Governments were duly notified of that fact.</p>
                    <p>On the 27th day of October, 1887, both Governments presented to you
                                their allegations and documents. These were duly communicated to the
                                opposing parties, and on the <pb facs="0594" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> 3d day of December, 1887, they both presented answers to the
                                allegations of their opponents. The Spanish documents were
                                subsequently translated and printed.</p>
                    <p>On the 16th day of January, 1888, by an instrument in writing, you
                                were pleased to delegate your powers as arbitrator to me, in
                                pursuance of the provisions contained in the last sentence of
                                Article V of the Treaty of Arbitration, and to direct me to examine
                                into the questions at issue and report my conclusions to you.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with these directions, and after a careful
                                consideration of the allegations of the respective parties, of their
                                answers, and of the documents submitted by each, I have now the
                                honor to submit the following:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">report.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The questions to be passed upon by the arbitrator, as will be
                                observed from the foregoing statement of the Treaty of Arbitration,
                                are capable of being classified under two heads: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">First</hi>. Whether the Treaty of Limits
                                        of the 15th of April, 1858, is valid.</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. If valid, what is its true
                                        meaning in respect of the right of Costa Rica to navigate
                                        the river San Juan with vessels of war or the revenue
                                        service, and also in respect of the eleven points submitted
                                        for decision by the Government of Nicaragua? If the first of
                                        these questions is decided in the negative—that is, if the
                                        Treaty of Limits is decided to be invalid—it will not be
                                        necessary to consider at all the questions under the second
                                        head.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Before discussing the grounds urged by the Government of Nicaragua,
                                on the one hand, as proving the invalidity of the Treaty of Limits,
                                and those urged by the Government of Costa Rica on the other, as
                                establishing its validity, it will be essential to consider briefly
                                the evidence submitted to show what were the recognized boundaries
                                prior to the date of the treaty, and what were the powers of the
                                respective Governments in regard to it. This historical inquiry, it
                                must be remembered, is not a matter of immediate concern, nor is it
                                directly involved in the decision of the questions now submitted to
                                arbitration; but it is important as elucidating the nature of the
                                principal controversy, and as showing the facts upon which the
                                parties base their respective arguments.</p>
                    <p>Two questions, essentially distinct in their character, were in
                                discussion in 1858 touching the boundary of the two Republics. The
                                first of these was the question whether the district of Nicoya
                                lawfully belonged to Costa Rica or to Nicaragua; the second, as to
                                the true boundary line between the Republics from the Caribbean Sea
                                to the borders of Nicoya. The evidence in regard to each of these
                                disputed questions must be reviewed in its order. The district of
                                Nicoya lies on the Pacific side of the continent, and—roughly
                                speaking—is triangular in shape, its apex lying toward the south. It
                                is bounded on the westward by the Pacific Ocean, and on the eastward
                                by the Gulf of Nicoya and the Rio del Salto, or Tempisque, a small
                                stream emptying into the head of the Gulf and having its sources not
                                far from the southerly shore of Lake Nicaragua. The northerly
                                boundary, or base of the triangle, seems to have never been
                                accurately fixed, and its position is a matter of dispute between
                                the Governments of Costa Rica and Nicaragua. The argument of
                                Nicaragua, submitted to the arbitrator, cites the authority of Don
                                Antonia Alcedo and the historian Juarros to the effect that it is
                                bounded by the Lake of Nicaragua on the north, which seems to imply
                                a further boundary line running from the southern end of the lake to
                                the Pacific Ocean. The arguments of the Costa Rican Government, on
                                the other hand, place the northern boundary as far up as the La Flor
                                River; and the records of land titles, and the statements of
                                Stephens and Baily, are cited in support of this view. It is wholly
                                unimportant, however, for the present purpose, to decide which of
                                these opposing Views is correct. It is only needful to point out
                                that a diversity of opinion exists, and that there is no grantor
                                agreement precisely fixing the boundaries of the district.</p>
                    <p>As to the title to the district, the facts are plainer. Nicoya, or,
                                as it is sometimes called, Guanacaste, was undoubtedly recognized as
                                a part of Nicaragua prior to 1826. It is asserted by Costa Rica that
                                at times Nicoya was temporarily united with it, or placed under the
                                control of its authorities; and some evidence is produced tending to
                                show that such a change was made in 1573, 1593, 1692, the middle of
                                the 18th century, and even as late as 1812. But any such connection
                                with Costa Rica can have been but temporary, and it may be regarded
                                as settled that at the time of the declaration of independence from
                                Spain in September, 1821, Nicoya formed a part of Nicaragua. This
                                condition of things seems to be distinctly recognized in the
                                constitution of Costa Rica, adopted 21st January, 1825, in which it
                                is stated that “the territory of the state extends at present from
                                west to east, from the Rio del Salto, <hi rend="italic">which
                                    divides it from Nicaragua, etc.</hi>”</p>
                    <p>It would seem, however, that about 1824 the inhabitants of Nicoya, or
                                some of them, asked to be annexed to Costa Rica. This question was
                                referred to the Federal Congress of Central America, the Federal
                                Republic of Central America having been <pb facs="0595" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> theretofore formed and its constitution
                                adopted 22nd November, 1824, and that body on the 9th December,
                                1825, passed the following decree:</p>
                    <p>“The Federal Congress of the Republic of Central America, taking into
                                consideration, firstly, the reiterated petitions of the authorities
                                and municipal bodies of the towns of the District of Nicoya, asking
                                for their separation from Nicaragua and their annexation to Costa
                                Rica; and, secondly, that the said towns and people actually annexed
                                themselves to Costa Rica at the time in which the political troubles
                                of Nicaragua took place; and, thirdly, the topographical situation
                                of the same district has-been pleased to decree, and does hereby
                                decree: <list>
                            <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 1. For the time being, and
                                        until the demarkation of the territory of each State,
                                        provided by Article VII of the Constitution is made, the
                                        District of Nicoya shall continue to be separated from
                                        Nicaragua, and annexed to Costa Rica.</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. In consequence thereof,
                                        the District of Nicoya shall recognize its dependence upon
                                        the authorities of Costa Rica, and shall have, in the
                                        legislature of the latter, such representation as
                                        corresponds to it.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>It further appears that the Government of Costa Rica thereupon took
                                possession of Nicoya, and has been continuously in possession of it
                                ever since; and was so at the date of the treaty of 1858.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Nicaragua, however, has not always acquiesced in
                                the validity of this act of annexation. It has, on the contrary, on
                                several occasions protested against it; and in its arguments, now
                                before the arbitrator, it contends that the decree above referred to
                                was not recognized at the time; that Nicaragua was not then
                                represented in the Federal Congress; that the decree was, by its
                                terms, only temporary; and that the municipalities of Nicoya as well
                                as the legislature of Nicaragua protested against the action of
                                Congress as soon as they were aware of it.</p>
                    <p>Here, again, it is not necessary for the arbitrator to decide the
                                question of title. But it is clear that in 1858 Costa Rica had been
                                continuously in possession of the district of Nicoya, under a claim
                                of title, for more than thirty-two years.</p>
                    <p>As to the boundary line between the Rio del Salto and the Caribbean
                                Sea, the question was purely one of fact; and it can hardly be said
                                that any very clear or satisfactory answer was possible.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Costa Rica, in the arguments submitted to the
                                arbitrator has presented an elaborate historical review of the two
                                provinces of Costa Rica and Nicaragua under Spanish rule, which, it
                                may be assumed, contains a reference to all the important documents
                                bearing upon the question of boundaries. Passing over the history of
                                the discovery and first settlement of this region in the early part
                                of the XVIth century, it appears that in 1541 the Emperor Charles V
                                decreed that the upper fifteen leagues of the San Juan River should
                                belong to the province of Nicaragua; that the lower or remaining
                                portion of the river should belong to the Government of Costa Rica;
                                and that the use of the river and lake, for purposes of navigation
                                and fishing, should be common to both provinces. In 1561, King
                                Philip II appointed Licentiate Don Juan Cavallon to be “alcalde
                                mayor” of the province of New Cartago and Costa Rica, describing it
                                in the preamble of the letter of appointment as extending along the
                                Northern Sea “up to the outlet, this being included” (<hi rend="italic">hasia el Desaguadero inclusive</hi>). In 1573, by
                                articles of agreement between the Spanish Crown and Diego de
                                Artieda, who was appointed governor and captain-general of Costa
                                Rica, the boundaries of that province were denned substantially as
                                they continued to be down to 1821. The limits of Artieda’s
                                jurisdiction are thus defined:</p>
                    <p>“From the Northern to the Southern Sea in width; and in length, from
                                the boundary of Nicaragua, on the side of Nicoya, right to the
                                valleys of Chiriqui, as far as the province of Veragua on the
                                southern side; and on the northern side, from the mouths of the
                                outlet, which is towards Nicaragua (<hi rend="italic">desde las
                                    bocas del Desaguadero, que es d las partes de Nicaragua</hi>),
                                the whole tract of land as far as the province of Veragua.”</p>
                    <p>No subsequent grant or decree by the Spanish Crown is cited, and,
                                apart from some evidence of acts of possession by the respective
                                Government, there is nothing further to define the boundaries of the
                                two provinces.</p>
                    <p>Soon after the declaration of independence, Costa Rica and Nicaragua,
                                then States of the Republic of Central America, adopted
                                constitutions defining generally their respective boundaries.</p>
                    <p>The constitution of Costa Rica, adopted the 21st January, 1825,
                                provides as follows:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 15. The territory of the State
                                extends at present from west to east, from the river del Salto,
                                which divides it from that of Nicaragua, up to the river Chiriqui,
                                the boundary of the Republic of Colombia; and north and south from
                                one to the other sea, the limits being on the north [sea] the mouth
                                of the San Juan River and the Escudo de Veraguas, and on the south
                                [sea] the mouth of the river Alvarado and that of the Chiriqui.”</p>
                    <p>Nicaragua, by the constitution adopted the 8th of April, 1826,
                                defines her boundaries thus:</p>
                    <p>“On the east, the sea of the Antilles; on the north, the State of
                                Honduras; on the <pb facs="0596" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> west, the
                                gulf of Conchagua; on the south, the Pacific Ocean; and on the
                                southeast the free State of Costa Rica.”</p>
                    <p>These are the last declarations <hi rend="italic">ante litem
                                    motam</hi>. It will he observed that all these documents leave
                                the precise boundary vague and undetermined. Indeed the line to be
                                followed between the Rio del Salto and the “mouths of the Outlet,”
                                is nowhere laid down. Nicaragua contends that a straight line from
                                the mouth of the Rio del Salto to the mouth of the Colorado, the
                                most southerly of the three mouths of the San Juan, is intended.
                                This is met by the argument that as the Rio del Salto was the
                                boundary, that river in its whole length, and not the mouth or any
                                other part of it, was the dividing line; and that the San Juan River
                                proper the northernmost of the three channels at the mouth of that
                                stream—formed the end of the line on the Caribbean Sea. Costa Rica
                                further contends that the boundary line was not straight, but that
                                it followed the course of the San Juan in its whole length and the
                                southern shore of Lake Nicaragua; and she alleges that she was in
                                possession of the territory up to that line—an allegation not
                                admitted by Nicaragua.</p>
                    <p>In my judgment the evidence establishes that the boundary of Costa
                                Rica, under the terms of the Spanish grants (leaving Nicoya out of
                                the question), began at the head of the Gulf of Nicoya, ran
                                northerly along the river del Salto to its source, and thence ran to
                                the mouth of the San Juan River, at the port of San Juan del
                                Norte—this being at the time the mouth of the principal channel or
                                outlet of the stream. But the evidence is not sufficient to form the
                                basis for any satisfactory judgment as to how this line was to be
                                drawn between the source of the del Salto and the month of the San
                                Juan. I perceive no reason for thinking that it should have been a
                                straight line.</p>
                    <p>No decision of this question is, however, necessary; for it is only
                                important, for present purposes, to point out that no precise line
                                of demarkation can be found in any of the earlier documents. Nor is
                                this surprising in view of the fact, to be inferred from the
                                evidence, that the region through which the line ran was a rough,
                                densely wooded and thinly settled country, where no need was felt of
                                any exact delimitation in the days of the Spanish dominion.</p>
                    <p>But with the establishment of the Federal Republic, and, still more,
                                with its dissolution, the questions of boundary began to assume
                                importance.</p>
                    <p>The Federal Constitution seems to have provided by its Article VII
                                for the demarcation of each State; but nevertheless nothing was done
                                towards the establishment of the line between Costa Rica and
                                Nicaragua.</p>
                    <p>In 1838 Costa Rica seems to have urged upon Nicaragua—then assuming
                                the rank of an independent State upon her withdrawal from the
                                federation—a desire for a recognition of the annexation of Nicoya.
                                In 1846, 1848, and 1852 other fruitless negotiations were undertaken
                                with a view to settling the boundary; and in 1858, when the Treaty
                                of Limits was signed, the question, in one form or another, had been
                                before the two Governments for at least twenty years.</p>
                    <p>That the documentary evidence was slight and unsatisfactory, has been
                                already shown; and that Costa Rica had for nearly the same period of
                                twenty years laid claim to more territory than she obtained under
                                the Treaty of Limits, fully appears from her decree of “Basis and
                                Guaranties “of the 8th March, 1841, which asserts as the boundaries
                                of Costa Rica the line of the river La Flor, the shore of Lake
                                Nicaragua, and the river San Juan.</p>
                    <p>I now proceed to state the history of the negotiations which resulted
                                In the treaty in question, and of the executive and legislative acts
                                which are relied on by Costa Rica as constituting a sufficient
                                ratification.</p>
                    <p>The long and bitter struggle in which Nicaragua and other Central
                                American States had been involved, and of which the part played by
                                Walker and the filibusters was the most notorious incident, came to
                                an end in 1857. The Republic of Costa Rica had taken part in that
                                struggle, and her case states as a fact that at the close of the
                                contest the Costa Rican troops held military positions on both sides
                                of the San Juan. The argument of Nicaragua seems to imply that such
                                possession was not taken until after the close of the war; but the
                                fact itself is not in dispute. It was regarded by Nicaragua at the
                                time as constituting a <hi rend="italic">casus belli;</hi> and Costa
                                Rica having failed to withdraw her troops, war was declared by
                                Nicaragua on the 25th November, 1857, although negotiations for a
                                settlement of the difficulty still continued, but without
                                success.</p>
                    <p>In this posture of affairs the Republic of San Salvador offered
                                mediation through its minister Col. Don Pedro Rómulo Negrete. Owing
                                principally, as it would seem, to Colonel Negrete’s earnest efforts,
                                the opposing Governments appointed ministers plenipotentiary, who
                                met with the Salvadorian minister at San José de Costa Rica, and
                                there concluded the Treaty of Limits, the validity of which is now
                                under examination.</p>
                    <p>By that instrument the boundary line is made to begin at Punta de
                                Castilla, at the mouth of the San Juan River; thence it follows the
                                right or southern bank of that stream to a point 3 miles below the
                                Castillo Viejo; thence it runs along the circumference <pb facs="0597" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> of a circle drawn round
                                the outworks of the castle as a center, with a radius of 3 miles to
                                a point on the western side of the castle, distant 2 miles from the
                                river; thence parallel to the San Juan and the lake, at a distance
                                of 2 miles therefrom to the Sapoá River; and thence in a straight
                                line to the center of Salinas Bay on the Pacific, Ocean. The treaty
                                further provides that surveys shall be made to locate the boundary;
                                that the Bay of San Juan del Norte and Salinas Bay shall be common
                                to both Republics; and that Nicaragua shall have, exclusively,
                                dominion and supreme control, of the waters of the San Juan—Costa
                                Rica having the right of free navigation for the purposes of
                                commerce in that part of the river on which she is bounded. It was
                                further agreed that in the event of war between Costa Rica and
                                Nicaragua, no act of hostility was to be practiced in the port or
                                river of San Juan, or on the Lake of Nicaragua; and the observance
                                of this article of the treaty was guarantied by the Republic of San
                                Salvador.</p>
                    <p>It is admitted by the parties to the present arbitration that the
                                treaty was duly ratified by Costa Rica on the 16th April, 1858; and
                                that it was not ratified at all by San Salvador. It is further
                                established that there was some ratification by representatives of
                                Nicaragua—but whether or not such ratification was sufficient is one
                                of the points now in controversy, and it is therefore necessary to
                                examine fully the powers and the proceedings of the Nicaraguan
                                authorities.</p>
                    <p>The Republic of Nicaragua, as appears from the evidence, was a
                                constitutional government of limited powers, which were defined by a
                                written constitution. Nicaragua, as one of the States of the Central
                                American Republic, adopted her first constitution on the 8th April,
                                1826. Upon the dissolution of the Federal Republic she assumed the
                                rank of an independent nation; and in 1838 adopted a new
                                constitution, which her representatives now contend was in full
                                force and vigor at the time of the execution of the Treaty of
                                Limits. The full text of the Nicaraguan constitution of 1838 is not
                                contained in the arguments which have been laid before the
                                arbitrator; but it sufficiently appears that power was vested in an
                                elective President and a Congress. It also appears that by article 2
                                (cited in full below), the boundaries of the State were defined; and
                                that by article 194, quoted in the argument of Nicaragua, a
                                complicated method of amendment was provided, of which the only
                                feature now necessary to notice is that no proposed amendment shall
                                take effect until it has been approved by two successive
                                legislatures.</p>
                    <p>In 1857 the necessity for a complete revision of the constitution of
                                1838 seems to have been generally recognized. The long and
                                exhausting conflicts which had been waged from 1854 to 1857, and the
                                existence, during the greater part of that time, of two hostile
                                governments, each claiming to exercise constitutional and supreme
                                power throughout the country, had demonstrated, to the satisfaction
                                of the inhabitants, the importance of changes in the organic law.
                                Accordingly a constituent assembly, with ample powers, was duly
                                elected. The due election, and the full constituent powers of this
                                body, are facts not disputed in the arguments now submitted on
                                behalf of Nicaragua.</p>
                    <p>In November, 1857, the constituent assembly met, and addressed itself
                                at once to the task of framing a new constitution for Nicaragua, as
                                well as of legislating upon the ordinary affairs of the nation.</p>
                    <p>On the 18th of January, 1858, the previous negotiation with Costa
                                Rica having failed, the assembly ordered new commissioners to be
                                appointed to negotiate treaties of peace, limits, friendship, and
                                alliance between Nicaragua and Costa Rica.</p>
                    <p>On the 5th February, 1858, a further and supplemental decree on the
                                same subject was adopted, which is as follows:</p>
                    <p>“The constituent assembly of the Republic of Nicaragua, in use of the
                                legislative faculties with which it is invested, decrees: <list>
                            <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 1. For the purpose that
                                        the executive may comply with the decree of January 18
                                        instant, the said executive is hereby amply authorized to
                                        act in the settlement of the difficulties with Costa Rica in
                                        such manner as it may deem best for the interest of both
                                        countries, and for the independence of Central America,
                                        without the necessity of ratification by the legislative
                                        power.</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. Such treaties of limits
                                        as it may adjust shall be final, if adjusted in accordance
                                        with the bases which separately will be given to it; but, if
                                        not, they shall be subject to the ratification of the
                                        assembly.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>What were the separate bases of negotiation given to the Nicaraguan
                                Executive does not appear from any of the documents submitted to the
                                arbitrator. But it is not distinctly asserted by the representatives
                                of Nicaragua that such instructions were disregarded in the
                                negotiation of the treaty, the arguments relied on to prove its
                                invalidity resting upon entirely different grounds, which will be
                                stated hereafter.</p>
                    <p>On the 15th April, 1858, the treaty of limits was signed by the
                                plenipotentiaries of Costa Rica, Nicaragua, and San Salvador; and on
                                the 26th April, 1858, ratifications were personally exchanged by the
                                Presidents of Costa Rica and Nicaragua, who met for the purpose on
                                Nicaraguan territory at the city of Rivas. The treaty had not <pb facs="0598" n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/> then been passed upon by
                                the assembly, the decree of ratification being by the President
                                alone. It is as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Tomas Martinez</hi>, the
                                President of the Republic of Nicaragua:</p>
                    <p>“Whereas General Máximo. Jerez, envoy extraordinary and minister
                                plenipotentiary of Nicaragua to the Republic of Costa Rica, has
                                adjusted, agreed upon, and signed, on the 15th instant, a treaty of
                                limits, fully in accordance with the bases which, for that purpose,
                                were transmitted to him by way of instructions; finding that said
                                treaty is conducive to the peace and prosperity of the two
                                countries, and reciprocally useful to both of them, and that it
                                facilitates, by removing all obstacles that might prevent it, the
                                mutual alliance of both countries, and their unity of action against
                                all attempts of foreign conquest; considering that the Executive has
                                been duly and-competently authorized by legislative decree of
                                February 26th ultimo to do everything conducive to secure the safety
                                and independence of the Republic; and by virtue, furthermore, of the
                                reservation of faculties spoken of in the Executive decree of the
                                17th instant:</p>
                    <p>“Does hereby ratify each and all of the articles of the treaty of
                                limits, made and concluded by Don José Maria Cañas, minister
                                plenipotentiary of the Government of Costa Rica, and Don Máximo
                                Jerez, minister plenipotentiary of the Supreme Government of
                                Nicaragua, signed by them on the 15th instant and ratified by the
                                Costa Rican Government on the 16th. And the additional act of the
                                same date is likewise ratified.”</p>
                    <p>On the 28th May, 1858, thirty-two days after the ratification, and
                                forty-three days after the signature of the treaty of limits, the
                                following decree was passed by the constituent assembly:</p>
                    <p>“The constituent assembly of the Republic of Nicaragua, in use of the
                                legislative powers vested in it, decrees:</p>
                    <p>“Sole Article. The treaty of limits concluded at San José on the 15th
                                of April, instant, between General Don Máximo Jerez, minister
                                plenipotentiary from this Republic, and General Don José Maria
                                Cañas, minister plenipotentiary from the Republic of Costa Rica,
                                with the intervention of Colonel Don Pedro Rómulo Negrete, minister
                                plenipotentiary from Salvador, is hereby approved.”</p>
                    <p>On the 19th August, 1858, the constituent assembly adopted the new
                                constitution, of which it is only needful to cite the first article,
                                viz:</p>
                    <p>“The Republic of Nicaragua is the same which was, in ancient times,
                                called the Province of Nicaragua, and, after the independence, State
                                of Nicaragua. Its territory is bounded on the east and northeast by
                                the Sea of the Antilles; on the north and northwest by the State of
                                Honduras; on the west and south by the Pacific Ocean, and on the
                                southeast by the Republic of Costa Rica. The laws on special limits
                                form part of the constitution.”</p>
                    <p>No further formal ratification of the treaty of limits was ever had;
                                but the arguments submitted by Costa Rica cite a number of instances
                                in which the Government of Nicaragua, during the period between 1858
                                and 1870, recognized the treaty as a valid and binding
                                instrument.</p>
                    <p>Since 1870 the Government of Nicaragua has contended that the treaty
                                is invalid; and that view is now urged upon three distinct grounds,
                                which are stated as follows in the argument submitted on its
                                behalf:</p>
                    <p>“The Government of Nicaragua affirms the invalidity of the treaty of
                                1858, and insists that it ought not to be bound thereby, for the
                                reason— <list>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">First</hi>. That it has not received
                                        that sanction which the constitution of the state of
                                        Nicaragua requires to give effect to, and validate, a treaty
                                        of its character.</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. It has not been ratified
                                        by the government of San Salvador, so as to give effect to
                                        the guaranties on behalf of that Government of the tenth
                                        article of the treaty.</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. That the pretended
                                        ratifications of the treaty were exchanged before the treaty
                                        had been submitted to the Congress of Nicaragua, and it was
                                        not approved by the first Congress of Nicaragua until after
                                        the expiration of the forty days provided for the exchange
                                        of ratifications in Article <hi rend="smallcaps">xii.</hi>”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I shall consider each of these three reasons in order.</p>
                    <p rend="center">I.</p>
                    <p>The argument very forcibly presented on behalf of Nicaragua to
                                establish the first ground of objection—the Jack of such a sanction
                                as was required by the constitution to give effect to, and validate,
                                a treaty of the character of the one in question—is as follows: The
                                constitution of 1838 was in full force on the 15th of April, 1858;
                                that constitution fixed the boundaries of Nicaragua; the treaty of
                                limits curtailed the boundaries so fixed by the constitution; it was
                                therefore, “in direct and flagrant violation of the fundamental law
                                of the state, and to have validity must receive the same formal
                                ratification that an amendment to the constitution itself demands;”
                                the constitution provides that an amendment adopted by one
                                legislature in the manner <pb facs="0599" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                                prescribed, by two-thirds vote of both houses, “shall not be
                                considered as valid nor form part of the constitution until it has
                                received the sanction of the next legislature the treaty of limits
                                was never sanctioned by a second legislature; therefore it is not
                                valid.</p>
                    <p>This argument, it will be perceived, rests wholly upon the
                                fundamental assumptions that the constitution of 1838 was in force,
                                and that it fixed the boundaries of Nicaragua If, as a matter of
                                fact, that constitution was not in force, or if the boundaries were
                                not definitely fixed by its provisions, then the whole argument
                                falls; for the treaty is then a mere treaty of limits, settling
                                disputed boundaries, and is cot one involving a cession of territory
                                and an amendment to the constitution. It is not pretended that a
                                treaty fixing boundaries requires, on general principles, any
                                extraordinary sanction.</p>
                    <p>The general doctrine that in determining the validity of a treaty
                                made in the name of a state, the fundamental laws of such state must
                                furnish the guide for determination, has been fully and ably
                                discussed on the part of Nicaragua, and its correctness may
                                certainly be admitted. But it is also certain that where a treaty
                                has been approved by a government, and an effort is subsequently
                                made to avoid it for the lack of some formality, the burden is upon
                                the party who alleges invalidity to show clearly that the
                                requirements of the fundamental law have not been complied with. In
                                my judgment, Nicaragua has failed in establishing a case under this
                                rule,</p>
                    <p>In the first place, it may well be doubted whether the constitution
                                of 1838 can be said to have been in full force and effect at the
                                time of the execution of the treaty on the 15th April, 1858, The
                                legislative power was then vested in a constituent assembly—a body,
                                it would seem, expressly chosen for the purpose of amending the
                                constitution in any way it saw fit. To say that such a body could
                                not adopt a decree which in effect modified the constitution, is to
                                deny to it the power to carry out the very objects for which it
                                existed.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, the constitution framed by the assembly, and promulgated on
                                the 19th August, 1858, defining the boundaries of Nicaragua, adds
                                that “the laws on special limits form part of the constitution.” If
                                therefore the decree of the 28th May, 1858, and the other, acts of
                                the assembly, were in any respect in sufficient as involving some
                                unconstitutionality, the defect was supplied by practically
                                embodying the treaty of limits, and the decree approving it, in the
                                new constitution, thus giving the highest sanction possible to this
                                legislation.</p>
                    <p>But whether or not the constitution of 1838 was in full force in
                                April and May, 1858, I am clearly of opinion that it did not
                                definitely fix the boundaries of the state. The power of defining
                                absolute boundaries by a constitution is not denied. The question is
                                merely whether the constitution of 1838 did in fact contain such a
                                definition of the boundaries of Nicaragua as to preclude their
                                adjustment by any ordinary treaty.</p>
                    <p>The provisions of that constitution respecting boundaries are as
                                follows:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2. The territory of the State is
                                the same as was formerly given to the Province of Nicaragua; its
                                limits being on the east and northeast the Sea of the Antilles; on
                                the north and northwest the State of Honduras; on the west and south
                                the Pacific Ocean; and on the southeast the State of Costa Rica. <hi rend="italic">The dividing lines with the bordering States shall
                                    be marked by a law which will make a part of the
                                    constitution.</hi>”</p>
                    <p>Thus it appears that “the dividing lines with the bordering States”
                                were expressly not defined. It was plainly the intention to leave
                                the constitution incomplete in this respect, though a means of
                                completing it was provided by allowing the passage of an ordinary
                                law by a single legislature. It is not pretended that any law
                                marking the boundary on the side of Costa Rica was passed before the
                                execution of the treaty of limits. The decree approving the treaty
                                is the only attempt, so far as appears, to comply with this
                                provision of the constitution. The statement that the boundary is
                                “on the southeast the State of Costa Rica” defines nothing. What
                                were the limits of Costa Rica in 1838 was a matter of dispute. No
                                precise decision was possible, and I have already expressed my
                                opinion that the evidence laid before the arbitrator is altogether
                                too vague to afford grounds for any satisfactory judgment. The
                                constitution of 1838, therefore, did not fix the boundaries of
                                Nicaragua definitely.</p>
                    <p>These views are strengthened by a consideration of the evidence
                                adduced on the part of Costa Rica to prove acquiescence by Nicaragua
                                for ten or twelve years in the validity of the treaty. I do not
                                regard such acquiescence as a substitute for ratification by a
                                second legislature, if such had been needed. But it is strong
                                evidence of that contemporaneous exposition which has ever been
                                thought valuable as a guide in determining doubtful questions of
                                interpretation.</p>
                    <p>I conclude, therefore, that the first ground of objection stated by
                                Nicaragua is untenable.</p>
                    <p rend="center">II.</p>
                    <p>The second ground of objection urged by Nicaragua to the validity Of
                                the treaty is that it has not been ratified by the Government at San
                                Salvador, so as to give effect to the guaranties on behalf of that
                                Government of the <hi rend="italic">tenth</hi> article of the
                                treaty.</p>
                    <pb facs="0600" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/>
                    <p>It is argued, in support of this objection, that the guaranty of the
                                mediating government against hostilities on the river and lake was
                                of great importance to Nicaragua; that it might well have been the
                                controlling consideration in the mind of the negotiator of the
                                treaty that led him to agree to the relinquishment of claims to
                                great tracts of territory; that the failure of San Salvador to
                                ratify this treaty took from it one of the chief considerations
                                moving to Nicaragua; and that, the consideration never having taken
                                effect, the treaty never became of valid or binding force. It is
                                added that this was in effect a tripartite treaty, and unless all
                                the parties became bound neither of them was.</p>
                    <p>In my opinion this argument is unsound. The treaty was not
                                tripartite, but was between Costa Rica and Nicaragua only, with an
                                independent and separable clause of guaranty as to a single feature
                                of the arrangement on the part of San Salvador. Without the guaranty
                                the treaty was complete as between the two principals, if they saw
                                fit to accept it in that shape. The non-ratification by the Republic
                                of San Salvador was known to the Government of Nicaragua when
                                ratifications were exchanged with Costa Rica. It follows therefore
                                that Nicaragua never lost any of the considerations which induced
                                her to consummate, by an exchange of ratifications, the negotiations
                                for the treaty.</p>
                    <p>The facts may be briefly recalled.</p>
                    <p>On the 15th April, 1858, the treaty of limits was signed. In form it
                                is a convention agreed upon by the representatives of Costa Rica and
                                Nicaragua, and declares that they having exchanged their respective
                                powers, “which were examined by Hon. Senor Don Pedro R. Negrete,
                                exercising the function of fraternal mediator in these
                                negotiations,” had agreed to and adjusted the terms of the treaty.
                                The treaty itself, after reciting the desire of Costa Rica and
                                Nicaragua for peace, fixes the boundary line between them; provides
                                for a survey of the line, and for the common use and defense of the
                                Bay of San Juan del Norte and Salinas Bay, and of that portion of
                                the San Juan River on which Costa Rica borders; grants the use in
                                common of the Punta de Castilla until Nicaragua recovers full
                                possession of all her rights in the port of San Juan del Norte;
                                forbids the levying of custom duties at Punta de Castilla while San
                                Juan del Norte remains a free port; defines the jurisdiction over
                                and right of navigation on the waters of the San Juan River; secures
                                existing contracts of canalization or public transit made by the
                                Government of Nicaragua and regulates the execution of future
                                contracts; and neutralizes the port and river of San Juan and the
                                Lake of Nicaragua in the event of war between Costa Rica and
                                Nicaragua. Then follows this:</p>
                    <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Article X</hi>. The stipulation of the
                                foregoing article (that relating to neutrality) being essentially
                                important for the proper custody of both the port and the river
                                against foreign aggression, which would affect the general interests
                                of the country, the strict performance thereof is left under the
                                special guaranty, which in the name of the mediator government its
                                minister plenipotentiary herein present is ready to give and does
                                hereby give in use of the faculties vested in him for that purpose
                                by his Government.”</p>
                    <p>Finally, Costa Rica and Nicaragua mutually give up all claims against
                                each other, and “the two contracting parties “waive all claims for
                                damages which either have against the other.</p>
                    <p>This instrument is plainly neither in form nor in substance
                                tripartite. The “two Governments,” the “two contracting parties
                                “spoken of in the treaty, are always Costa Rica and Nicaragua, never
                                San Salvador. San Salvador is not in form a contracting party at
                                all. And in substance that Government is not a party to the
                                agreement, the clause containing the guaranty being entirely
                                separable from all the rest.</p>
                    <p>As a proposition of international law, it may be regarded as settled
                                that a guaranty is always merely subsidiary to the principal
                                contract.</p>
                    <p>“Le traité par lequel un état se porte garant d’un traité conclu
                                entre deux autres puissances, est un traité accessoire destiné à
                                assurer l’exécution du traité principal.” (Bluntschli, 430 <hi rend="italic">note</hi>, Lardy’s trans.)</p>
                    <p>“Lagarantie peut être comprise dans les stipulations annexées au
                                traité principal qu’on veut garantir, et devient alors une
                                obligation accessoire.” (Vattel, Droit des Gens. Ed. 1863, Liv. II,
                                ch. 16, § 240; note by Pradier Fodéré, the editor.)</p>
                    <p>“Lorsque la garantie est destinée à assurer l’inviolabilité d’un
                                traité, elle forme toujours une obligation et un traité accessoiré
                                    (<hi rend="italic">pactum accessorium</hi>), même quand elle
                                ferait partie de Facte principal.” (Klüber, Droit des Gens., §
                                158.)</p>
                    <p>It follows that the clause of guaranty in the treaty of limits is no
                                part of the principal agreement, and that on general principles the
                                rest of the treaty would not stand or fall with this subsidiary or
                                accessory contract.</p>
                    <p>The necessity for ratification by contracting powers may be fully
                                admitted. But even conceding to it as high an importance as the
                                execution of deeds by individuals, the failure of a guarantying
                                State to ratify will not necessarily invalidate a treaty which the
                                principal contracting parties have concluded by an exchange of
                                ratifications as between themselves.</p>
                    <pb facs="0601" n="467" xml:id="pg_467"/>
                    <p>The analogy of individual deeds may serve to illustrate the point now
                                under discussion. The case may readily he imagined of a deed between
                                two parties as principals, with a third party as guarantor. Leases
                                of this character are not infrequent. If such a deed were prepared
                                by the agents of the three parties, and if the two principal parties
                                were to sign, seal, acknowledge, and formally deliver to each other
                                duly-executed duplicates of the deed, without waiting for the
                                signature of the guarantor, it is too plain for argument that
                                neither could subsequently object, and claim the right to rescind,
                                because the deed had not been executed and delivered by the
                                guarantor.</p>
                    <p>So in this case. The Presidents of Costa Rica and Nicaragua in
                                person, on the 26th April, 1858, formally exchanged ratifications of
                                the treaty, without waiting for San Salvador. The arguments now
                                advanced by Nicaragua as establishing the invalidity of the treaty
                                might perhaps have been urged as reasons for refusing to exchange
                                the ratifications until San Salvador was ready to unite in the act.
                                But the Government of Nicaragua was silent when it ought to have
                                spoken, and so waived the objection now made. It saw fit to proceed
                                to the exchange of ratifications without waiting for San Salvador.
                                The treaty was complete without Article X. To all the other articles
                                and stipulations it contained Costa Rica and Nicaragua alone might
                                fully bind themselves. They did so, irrevocably, by a formal
                                exchange of ratifications; and neither may now be heard to allege,
                                as reasons for rescinding this completed treaty, and facts which
                                existed and were known at the time of its consummation.</p>
                    <p>I conclude, therefore, that the <hi rend="italic">second</hi> ground
                                of objection stated by Nicaragua is untenable.</p>
                    <p rend="center">III.</p>
                    <p>The third ground of objection urged by Nicaragua to the validity of
                                the treaty is “that the pretended ratifications of the treaty were
                                exchanged before the treaty had been submitted to the Congress of
                                Nicaragua, and it was not approved by the first Congress of
                                Nicaragua until after the expiration of the forty days provided for
                                the exchange of ratifications in Article <hi rend="smallcaps">xii</hi>.”</p>
                    <p>It will be remembered that on the 5th February, 1858, the constituent
                                assembly of Nicaragua passed a decree by which the Executive was
                                “amply authorized” to treat with Costa Rica “without the necessity
                                of ratification by the legislative power; “and that it was further
                                decreed that such treaties of limits as the Executive might adjust
                                should be final, if in accordance with certain separate
                                instructions. Acting under this grant of power, the President of
                                Nicaragua concluded and ratified the present treaty on the 26th
                                April, 1858, eleven days after its signature by the
                                plenipotentiaries, without “ratification by the legislative power.”
                                On the 28th of May, 1858, the constituent assembly adopted a decree
                                approving the treaty; and this decree was signed by the President on
                                the 4th June, 1858.</p>
                    <p>The argument now presented by Nicaragua is twofold, and raises two
                                points, <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, that the treaty is invalid
                                because ratifications were exchanged before approval by the
                                assembly, and, <hi rend="italic">second</hi>, that it is invalid
                                because such approval was given more than forty days after
                                signature.</p>
                    <p>As to the first of these points, it would perhaps be enough to say
                                that Nicaragua can not now seek to invalidate the treaty on any mere
                                ground of irregularity in the order of its own proceedings. If its
                                legislature did in fact approve the treaty that is enough for the
                                present purpose. Whether such approval was expressed before or after
                                the exchange of ratifications is an immaterial matter now, certainly
                                so far as Nicaragua is concerned.</p>
                    <p>But it does not appear that there was any real irregularity in these
                                proceedings. The full text of the Nicaraguan constitution of 1838
                                not being contained in the arguments submitted to the arbitrator, it
                                is not made clear just what restrictions upon the treaty-making
                                power that instrument imposed. Ratification by legislative authority
                                is not always required, even in constitutional governments. The
                                necessity for legislative ratification is not to be presumed, but
                                must be established as a fact. Still less can there be any
                                presumption as to the form and manner in which the legislative
                                sanction is to be expressed. In the present instance the constituent
                                assembly, a body of extensive powers, expressed in advance its
                                approval of any treaty of limits that might be concluded by the
                                Executive upon certain bases. It is not shown that the authority so
                                given was exceeded, and it can not be said, in the absence of an
                                express prohibition, that this mode of dealing with the subject was
                                improper.</p>
                    <p>Again, the fact of the subsequent approval of the treaty by the
                                assembly is satisfactory proof that that body approved not only the
                                terms of the instrument, but also the manner in which the Executive
                                had exercised the authority conferred by the decree of the 5th
                                February, 1858. The time and manner of exchange of ratifications was
                                before the assembly, and it was fully aware that the time agreed
                                upon for exchange had passed. Its action, under these circumstances,
                                shows that it was of the <pb facs="0602" n="468" xml:id="pg_468"/>
                                opinion, that the treaty had been legally and in due time ratified
                                by the President, in pursuance of the special powers conferred upon
                                him.</p>
                    <p>In any event, all irregularities would seem to have been effectually
                                cured by this subsequent approval of the constituent assembly. <hi rend="italic">Ratihabitio retrotrahitur, et mandato
                                    equiparatur</hi>, is a recognized maxim of municipal law; and
                                the reasons of that rule may fairly be regarded as applying to cases
                                like the present.</p>
                    <p>That irregularities and defects in the formalities of ratification
                                may be supplied and made good by subsequent acquiescence in and
                                approval of the treaty, is laid down by Heffter (Droit
                                International, § 87 f<hi rend="italic">fin.</hi>):</p>
                    <p>“Mais il est constant qu’elle (<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>,
                                ratification) peut être suppléée par des actes équivalents, et
                                notamment par l’exécution tacite des stipulations arretées.”</p>
                    <p>And this opinion is cited by Pradier-Fodéré in his translation of
                                Grotius (Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 270, note 1). See
                                also Hall’s International Law, page 276.</p>
                    <p>The second point—that the legislative sanction was not given until
                                after the expiration of the forty days fixed by the treaty for the
                                exchange of the ratifications— seems clearly untenable. Costa Rica,
                                and not Nicaragua, might have complained of this delay. Assuming
                                that subsequent legislative approval was needed, Costa Rica might,
                                if it had desired to do so, have declared the negotiations at an end
                                on the expiration of the forty days. But it was not bound to do so.
                                It had a perfect right to waive this limitation of time. Either
                                party to a treaty may extend the time of the other, either by
                                express agreement or by acts indicating acquiescence. Nicaragua
                                cannot be permitted to say, as she does in effect say, in this
                                branch of her argument, “it is true that this treaty was approved
                                unreservedly by both executive and legislative branches of the
                                Government; but such an approval is worthless, as it was expressed
                                not forty but forty-three days after the signature of the
                                treaty.”</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">fact</hi> of approval being established, the
                                    <hi rend="italic">time</hi> of approval is immaterial, provided
                                the other party by its acquiescence has seen fit to waive delay.</p>
                    <p>I conclude, therefore, that the <hi rend="italic">third</hi> ground
                                of objection stated by Nicaragua is untenable.</p>
                    <p>And having examined in detail the three reasons urged by Nicaragua
                                for holding the treaty invalid, and finding all these reasons
                                untenable, I conclude that the arbitrator should decide in favor of
                                the validity of this treaty.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">G. L.
                                        Rives.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of
                                        State</hi>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-03-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
