<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 376.Mr. Bayard
                            to Mr. McLane.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663" lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="376" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                <head>No. 376.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">McLane</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-04-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6,
                            1888</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 320.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your No. 554 of February 24 last,
                        inclosing copies of the treaties between France and Anjouan (Johanna) by
                        which the former has assumed a protectorate over the latter and has
                        established a resident in the island, I call your attention to article 5 of
                        the treaty of April 21, 1886, which reads as follows in your translation:
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The rights of foreigners at present established in the island remain
                                reserved without in any case the French Government being responsible
                                for the execution of previous <hi rend="italic">deeds</hi> and <hi rend="italic">conventions</hi> (faits et conventions). If there
                                should be disputes on the subject of these <hi rend="italic">deeds</hi> and <hi rend="italic">conventions</hi>, the
                                Government of the Republic shall be taken as arbitrator.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>There is at present an American citizen resident in the island of Johanna,
                        Dr. B. F. Wilson, who now claims damages against the Sultan for injuries
                        growing out of violation by the Sultan of contracts entered into between
                        them. At various times, beginning with 1871, contracts were made by which
                        the Sultan was to furnish certain labor to enable Dr. Wilson to work a sugar
                        plantation called Patsy. In 1878, a lease for thirty years was granted, the
                        Sultan furnishing certain slave labor and permitting his free subjects to
                        work for hire. Under this lease Dr. Wilson expended large sums of money, and
                        the plantation was rapidly improving, the production of sugar increasing
                        each year from 1879 till 1882, when difficulties arose between the Sultan
                        and Dr. Wilson.</p>
                <p>The latter was subjected to a series of annoyances and violations of
                        contract, the Sultan taking away his slaves, terrorizing the freedmen so
                        that they refused to work, sending soldiers to kill Dr. Wilson, firing into
                        his house, and destroying a small vessel owned by him. Dr. Wilson claims
                        that his sugar crop, during the years 1882 and 1883 was much diminished, and
                        the estate so injured that he has never since been able to increase its
                        production as he would have done but for this interference; and in this he
                        is sustained by independent and apparently impartial testimony.</p>
                <pb facs="0662" n="528" xml:id="pg_528"/>
                <p>It is alleged in reply that Dr. Wilson had aided and abetted the Sultan’s
                        brother, Prince Mohammed, who in the year 1882 was in a state of open
                        rebellion against his authority. This Dr. Wilson denies, and his denial is
                        supported by the testimony of Prince Mohammed’s principal officer in that
                        rebellion, who declares that although Dr. Wilson’s assistance was solicited
                        by the rebels, it was distinctly and positively refused.</p>
                <p>It would seem therefore that Dr. Wilson has been seriously injured in his
                        planting operations by the Sultan’s violation of his contract; that even his
                        life has been in jeopardy, and that a claim for damages properly arises. The
                        Sultan, who had corresponded directly with this Department, was so informed,
                        but he has not replied to this communication. I am of opinion that the case
                        is such as may be submitted to the arbitration of the French Government,
                        under the article of the treaty of 1886, above quoted, if Dr. Wilson shall
                        think it to his interest to adopt that course.</p>
                <p>You are instructed therefore to bring the case verbally to the attention of
                        the French Government, stating its general features, and to ask whether it
                        will direct the resident in Anjouan to receive all the proofs which may be
                        offered by both the parties to the controversy, and whether, having these
                        before it, it will arbitrate the claim, or whether some other way may be
                        more proper for obtaining for Dr. Wilson the benefit of French
                        arbitration.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. F.
                            Bayard.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
