<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 535.Mr. Phelps to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d535</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">535</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-09-11T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="535" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d535">
                <head>No. 535.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Phelps</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-09-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 11, 1888</date>. (Received September
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 823.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It is with very great gratification that I
                    inclose the copy of a letter which I have just received from the foreign office
                    with respect to Messrs. Taylor and Armistead, graduates of the United States
                    Naval Academy <pb facs="0881" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> and for the past three
                    years private students of marine engineering at the Royal Naval College,
                        Greenwich.<note n="*" xml:id="d535fn1">For conditions regulating the
                        admission of students to the Royal Naval College at Greenwich, see Mr.
                        Welsh’s No. 257 to the Department, <ref target="frus1879#pg_472">F. R.,
                            1879, pp. 472</ref>–<ref target="frus1879#pg_478">8</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>You will observe that in the recent final examination Mr. Taylor obtained the
                    first place, with a total of 8,234 marks, an amount that has only once been
                    exceeded; and he was awarded a professional certificate of the first class,
                    besides being highly commended by the director of studies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Armistead obtained the fifth place in the same examination and was awarded a
                    professional certificate of the second class.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. J. Phelps.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 823.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">T. V. Lister</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Phelps</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-09-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 8, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my letter of the 15th
                        October, 1885, on the subject of the admission of two graduates of the
                        United States Naval Academy at Annapolis as private students of marine
                        engineering at the Royal Naval College, Greenwich, I have the honor to
                        inform you that I have received a communication from the lords commissioners
                        of the admiralty with regard to the places obtained by those gentlemen in
                        the final examination of students of marine engineering and private students
                        at the college in July last.</p>
                    <p>Their lordships state that Mr. Taylor obtained the first place in that
                        examination and was awarded a professional certificate of the first class,
                        with a total of 8,234 marks, an amount that has only once been exceeded in
                        this examination, and that the director of studies reports that “Mr. Taylor
                        has great natural ability, and has worked very steadily throughout his three
                        years’ course.”</p>
                    <p>With regard to Mr. Armistead, the lords commissioners have informed me that
                        he obtained the fifth place in the same examination, and was awarded a
                        professional certificate of the second class.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">T. V. Lister</hi>
                            </persName>.</signed>
                        <lb/>(For the Marquis of Salisbury.)</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
