<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 669.Mr. Rives to Mr. Thompson.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d669</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">669</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="jurisdiction" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="asylum" subject="asylum" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331" lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recbmmC3Qhr3E4JGh" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="political-refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112309" lcsh-match="exact">Political refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="consular-offices" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="civil-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="bilateral-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791" lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="international-law" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" subject="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="exact">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="669" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d669">
                <head>No. 669.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rives</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Thompson</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-10-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 31, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 56.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As you will perceive by the inclosed copy of
                    correspondence I had with Mr. Goutier, consul at Cape Haytien, the Department
                    has been constrained to correct his recent repetition of the error into which he
                    fell, in October, 1885, of announcing to the consular agents within his
                    jurisdiction that “the United States Government does not recognize the right of
                    asylum in consulates for political refugees.”</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. L. Rives</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Secretary.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="1073" n="937" xml:id="pg_937"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No, 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goutier</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Rives</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cape Haytien</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-10-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1888</date>. (Received October
                            26.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 912.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I deemed it prudent, at the outset of this
                        revolution, to caution our consular agents at Gonaïves and Port de Paix,
                        against receiving refugees in their consular agencies, and I inclose No. 1,
                        a copy of my letter to Mr. Etéart Dupuy, on that subject.</p>
                    <p>The people here have protested against the provisional government, and are
                        preparing for secession and civil war, should General Légitime remain a
                        candidate for the Presidency.</p>
                    <p>I have been doing all that I can to bring about a better feeling, but to no
                        avail. As a last resource, I have just written to our minister, Dr.
                        Thompson, and inclose No. 2, a copy of my letter.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanislas Goutier</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goutier</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Dupuy</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cape Haytien</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-08-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 16, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 547.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In view of the revolutionary state of this
                        country, I deem it my duty to inform you that the United States Government
                        does not recognize the right of asylum in consulates for political refugees;
                        consequently you have no right to receive refugees in your consular
                        agency.</p>
                    <p>Should you so receive them, and difficulty in consequence arise, you would,
                        in that case, have forfeited all claims to the support of the Government of
                        the United States.</p>
                    <p>However, as consular officer of a great Christian nation, you may be expected
                        to use, on all proper occasion, judiciously, your good offices in behalf of
                        moderation and humanity, exercising at the same time a wise discretion in
                        seeking to avoid all difficulties and misunderstandings with the authorities
                        of the Government within your consular agency.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanislas Goutier</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goutier</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Thompson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cape Haytien</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-10-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 551.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The entire north and northwest are decidedly
                        in earnest in their intention to secede should General Légitime continue to
                        be a candidate for the Presidency. More than this, they are already
                        preparing for it; they are preparing for war.</p>
                    <p>I can give you no idea of the hostile feelings of the people of Cape Haytien,
                        as well as the country people. There is but one cry for vengeance since the
                        death (but they say the murder) of General Séide Télémaque and a number of
                        his men.</p>
                    <p>In view of this impending fratricidal war and its disastrous results the
                        consuls here are of opinion that the diplomatic and consular corps at Port
                        au Prince might, by using such means as they deem proper, by appealing to
                        the patriotism of the members of the provisional government, or the existing
                        authorities, induce them to have General Légitime’s name withdrawn from the
                        list of candidates for the Presidency, being that alone can save Hayti from
                        all the horrors of civil war with its direful consequences.</p>
                    <p>I most respectfully recommend these suggestions, hastily put together, to
                        your earnest consideration and superior knowledge; and I do so with more
                        confidence, knowing your sympathy for this struggling Republic.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanislas Goutier</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul</hi>
                            </persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1074" n="938" xml:id="pg_938"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rives</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Goutier</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-10-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 31, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 351.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 912, of the 8th instant,
                        transmits your circular instruction of August 16 last, to the consular
                        agents at Gonaïves and Port de Paix, cautioning them as regards the
                        so-called “right” of political asylum.</p>
                    <p>Your caution was timely, in view of the distressing events then apprehended,
                        and which have since taken place in Hayti; and it is only regretted that you
                        have again fallen into the error of announcing that “the United States
                        Government does not recognize the right of asylum in consulates for
                        political refugees,” which error the Department pointed out and corrected in
                        its instruction to Mr. Thompson, No. 29, of November 7, 1885. That
                        instruction, including your dispatch to the Department of October 14, 1885,
                        No. 757, which called it forth, is printed in the volume of <ref target="frus1886#pg_530">Foreign Relations for 1886: pages
                            530</ref>–<ref target="frus1886#pg_531">531</ref>, but in case you
                        should not possess the book, a copy of the correspondence referred to is
                        attached hereto for your convenient information.</p>
                    <p>The position of this Government, briefly summarized, is this: We do not
                        regard extraterritorial asylum, either in a legation or a consulate, as a
                        right to be claimed under international law. We do not sanction or invite
                        the exercise of asylum in those countries where it actually exists as a
                        usage, but in such cases we recognize and admit its existence, and should
                        circumstances bring about the uninvited resort-of a political refugee for
                        shelter to a consulate or legation of the United States, we should expect
                        equal toleration and privilege in this regard with that allowed by such
                        local usage to any other consulate or legation.</p>
                    <p>This statement shows the error into which you have fallen in instructing the
                        consular agents that, should they receive political refugees, and difficulty
                        arise in consequence, they would “in that case have forfeited all claims to
                        the support of the Government of the United States.” Only the reported facts
                        of an actual case arising could enable the Department to determine whether
                        an abuse of the local usage had been committed.</p>
                    <p>The present instruction taken in connection with the memorandum on the
                        subject communicated to you with the Department’s No. 185 of August 23,
                        1884, will doubtless make this complex and delicate question sufficiently
                        clear for your guidance.</p>
                    <p>A copy of this correspondence will be sent to the legation at Port au Prince
                        for its information.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">G. L. Rives</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Assistant Secretary.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Thompson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 7, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 29.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The subject of asylum in Hayti, to which
                        reference was made in my instruction No. 28 of the 3d instant, is again
                        brought to the Department’s attention by the representations of Mr. Goutier,
                        United States consul at Cape Haytien, a copy of whose dispatch, No. 757, of
                        the 14th ultimo, is herewith inclosed for your information.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Goutier sets out with an erroneous summing up of the position taken by
                        this Government in the premises. He says in one place that “the United
                        States does not <hi rend="italic">recognize</hi> the right of asylum in her
                        consulates;” and, further, that “it is plainly set forth that this right is
                        not admitted.”</p>
                    <p>The statement properly should be that the Government of the United States
                        does not <hi rend="italic">claim</hi> for its legations abroad any
                        extraterritorial privileges of asylum, and consequently makes no such <hi rend="italic">claim</hi> in respect of consular offices, or private
                        residences of American citizens, or American merchant vessels in port. If,
                        as a custom, in any country, the practice of asylum prevails, and is tacitly
                        or explicitly recognized by the local authorities in respect of legations,
                        consulates, private dwellings, or vessels of another nationality, the
                        exercise of the consuetudinary privilege by Americans could not be deemed
                        exceptional; and if, under any circumstances, refugees find their way to
                        places of shelter under the American flag, or in the domicile of American
                        citizens, we should certainly expect such privileges as would be accorded
                        were the like shelter under the flag or domicile of another power. But we
                        claim no right or privilege of asylum; on the contrary, we discountenance
                        it, especially when it may tend to obstruct the direct operation of law and
                        justice.</p>
                    <pb facs="1075" n="939" xml:id="pg_939"/>
                    <p>Mr. Goutier next refers to the case of the insurgent who took refuge on the
                        French hark <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>, and says that with the
                        Department’s instructions in view he would have been much perplexed had the
                        vessel been American, for, says he, “it would have been my duty to allow the
                        authorities to go on board and arrest that Haytian insurgent.” And Mr.
                        Goutier goes on to argue that if any other power claims the right of asylum
                        in a given case, the United States could not forego a similar claim without
                        loss of prestige.</p>
                    <p>As we understand the case of the <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>, the local
                        authorities applied to the consul for permission to go on board and take the
                        fugitive. In a case which recently arose in Cuba, where application was made
                        to a consul to order the delivery of a person then on board an American
                        vessel in port, who was accused of common crimes, and where the consul,
                        after examining the charge against the person, ordered the captain to
                        deliver him up, this Department held that the consul had no authority to
                        order such surrender.</p>
                    <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>It does not seem pertinent to the present instruction to discuss the ethics
                        of humanity, to which Mr. Goutier adverts. Section 48 of the Department’s
                        lately issued personal instructions to its diplomatic agents abroad is
                        abundant evidence that the principles of common humanity, where arbitrary
                        pursuit of merely political offenders is concerned, have not been overlooked
                        in its ruling.</p>
                    <p>This instruction will enable yon to answer Mr. Goutier, and you are requested
                        to do so. It will also serve for your guidance in dealing with questions of
                        this nature which may hereafter arise.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">T. F. Bayard.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goutier</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hunter</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cape Haytien</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 14, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 757.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We have been instructed that the Government
                        of the United States does not recognize the right of asylum in her
                        consulates, and in the confidential memorandum sent last year to the German
                        minister at Washington in relation to the views of our Government on the
                        right of asylum in Hayti, it is plainly set forth that this right is not
                        admitted.</p>
                    <p>If that Haytian insurgent who had taken refuge on board of the French bark
                            <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>, as related in my No. 756 of the 12th
                        instant, and the French vice-consul would not permit the authorities to go
                        on board for the purpose of arresting him, had taken refuge on board of an
                        American vessel, with these instructions in view, I would have been much
                        perplexed, for it would have been my duty to allow the authorities to go on
                        board and arrest that Haytian insurgent.</p>
                    <p>His doom would have been sealed! Still it seems to me that a consul of the
                        United States ought to occupy in Hayti the same position as that occupied by
                        the consuls of the other great powers. For such a difference in affording
                        protection in this country would be looked upon by the ignorant masses as a
                        mark of inferiority, and would give a certain prestige, even to consuls of
                        second-class powers, not enjoyed by those of the American nation.</p>
                    <p>I know that the action of the French vice-consul in refusing to permit the
                        authorities to go on board the French bark <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi> to
                        arrest that Haytian insurgent, as well as the so called right of asylum in
                        Hayti, are in direct violation of international law and usage.</p>
                    <p>Still* ** we can not be surprised to find the great powers rather reluctant
                        to relinquish a course of action which, in some instances, has been abused;
                        but these abuses fade to insignificance when placed beside the countless
                        good they have accomplished.* * * I shall endeavor to keep my consulate free
                        of refugees, without it be in exceptional cases where human life is wantonly
                        destroyed. Then, as consul of a great Christian nation, obeying the supreme
                        law of humanity, I would be impelled to save as many lives as I possibly
                        could.</p>
                    <p>I would be thankful should the Department be pleased to outline some general
                        instructions, in order that I might act knowingly, especially should
                        Haytians seek protection on board of American vessels in this port.</p>
                    <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanislas Goutier</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul</hi>
                            </persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
