<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 83.Mr. Hall to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <head>No. 83.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in Central
                                America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-12-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 21, 1887</date>. (Received January 12,
                        1888.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 755.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to and in continuation of my
                    dispatch No. 754, of the 15th, I had the honor to transmit to you, on the 19th
                    instant, a telegram announcing information received by me from the President of
                    Nicaragua, to the effect that Costa Rica has withdrawn objections to the
                    possible operations of the ship-canal surveying party on Costa Rican
                    territory.</p>
                <p>The translated text of President Carazo’s telegram is as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Minister <hi rend="smallcaps">Hall</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Guatemala:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President of Costa Rica has addressed me the following telegram:</p>
                        <p>I have the pleasure to inform you that, at the solicitation of the canal
                            company, my Government has granted permission, under this date, for
                            making the necessary surveys in Costa Rican territory for locating the
                            line of the canal.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0236" n="102" xml:id="pg_102"/>
                <p>Señor Esquivel, minister for foreign affairs of Costa Rica, under date of the 2d
                    ultimo, addressed a note to Señor Zavala, minister for foreign affairs of
                    Nicaragua, in which be confirms and reiterates a former protest against the
                    present interoceanic canal concession, granted by Nicaragua to Messrs. Menocal
                    and associates, as an infraction of article 8, of the treaty of 1858, for the
                    reason that the consultative voice of Costa Rica had not been heard.</p>
                <p>In regard to the treaty of 1858, Señor Esquivel claims that until it shall have
                    been declared by the arbitrator to be null and void, its observance is binding
                    upon both countries, and that, even in such event, it will remain in force until
                    the question of boundaries, which must result from the arbitrator’s award, shall
                    have been settled.</p>
                <p>He arraigns the canal concession upon the ground that the rights of Costa Rica to
                    navigate the San Juan River, the right in common with Nicaragua to the Bay of
                    San Juan del Norte (rights which Nicaragua has not conceded nor has Costa Rica
                    possessed), are attacked and impaired thereby. He also alleges that the
                    completion of the canal will result in grievous injury to the territory of Costa
                    Rica, to her commerce, and to her river routes of communication; that the San
                    Juan will be rendered useless for Costa Rican navigation; that the courses of
                    Costa Rican rivers will be changed, and that many other grave injuries will be
                    done to that Republic.</p>
                <p>In the face of these charges he declares that the Costa Rican Government has no
                    desire to create obstacles to the construction of the canal; that it is an
                    enterprise of world-wide importance and interest, and that for a long time it
                    has been the great desideratum of all Central American patriots.</p>
                <p>These charges are, beyond a doubt, unfounded, and I am not aware that they have
                    ever been made before; especially the charge that the courses of Costa Rican
                    rivers will be changed and their navigation injured. The only effect the
                    elevation of the waters of the San Juan to the level of the lake, as has been
                    proposed, could have would be to make some of the Costa Rican streams which
                    empty into it navigable during the whole year, whereas now they are mere creeks,
                    during the so-called dry season. That section of Costa Rican territory near to
                    the lake and the San Juan River is now almost wholly unproductive and sparsely
                    inhabited. The completion of the canal would no doubt render it as valuable as
                    any portion of Nicaraguan territory through which the proposed canal will pass.
                    So well convinced of this fact were the prominent citizens of Costa Rica, as I
                    reported to the Department in my dispatch No. 300, of January 12, 1885, that
                    immediately after the signing of the canal treaty of 1884 the then President
                    Fernandez and the now President Soto, as well as many other notabilities of that
                    Republic, hastened to secure large tracts of public lands near to its proposed
                    route.</p>
                <p>The Nicaraguan minister, Señor Zavala, in reply to Señor Esquivel, expresses
                    surprise and concern at receiving this uncalled-for protest in regard to a
                    question which, having been submitted to arbitration, is beyond their
                    discussion, but is again brought up at the very moment when a corps of
                    engineers, charged with making the final surveys of the route, is about to
                    arrive in Nicaragua, and that wire it not known that the Costa Rican cabinet is
                    guided by enlightened counsels, it might well be supposed that the protest has
                    no other object than the creation of obstacles to the consummation of a work of
                    great interest, upon which the Central American States found all their hopes for
                    the future, and that this conduct of Costa Rica is in complete opposition to
                    that which it formerly observed whenever the same subject has been
                    discussed.</p>
                <pb facs="0237" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/>
                <p>He further reminds the Costa Rican minister that the canal concession recently
                    granted to Señor Menocal and associates is essentially the same as the one
                    granted to same parties in 1880, to which Costa Rica made not the slightest
                    objection; on the contrary, it accepted the idea, suggested by Nicaragua, to
                    join with the other Central American States in offering to the company a
                    guaranty of 3 per cent, profits upon the capital to be invested in the
                    enterprise; thus approving and assenting to the legality of all that Nicaragua
                    had done in granting the concession. The Government of Nicaragua is therefore at
                    a loss to understand what can possibly be the motives of the Government of Costa
                    Rica for protesting against acts which have already received its
                    approbation.</p>
                <p>The rejection by the Nicaraguan Congress of the treaty of July last between those
                    governments has evidently aroused a feeling of deep resentment on the part of
                    the Costa Rican Government, which will make any mutual settlement next to
                    impossible.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 In No. 755.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Esquivel</persName> to Señor
                                <persName type="to">Zavala</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Costa
                                    Rica</hi>)</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1887-11-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 2, 1887</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: On the 14th of May of the current
                        year the Costa Rican Government, through this department and the worthy
                        medium of your excellency, communicated to that of Nicaragua that it did not
                        consent to the infraction of article 8 of the treaty of 15th April, 1858,
                        committed by the Government of that Republic in entering into a contract for
                        the construction of an inter-oceanic canal without having heard the
                        consultative voice of the Government of Costa Rica, which had protested
                        against such contract, that the just rights of the Republic may in no wise
                        be prejudiced.</p>
                    <p>In reply to that protest, your excellency in a note, dated the 23d of June
                        was pleased to state that the Nicaraguan Government had no desire to reopen
                        a discussion in which both countries had been so long engaged, which is
                        submitted to arbitration, adding that it sustains the nullity of the treaty
                        of 1858 and that the instructions your excellency had received were limited
                        to a manifestation that the Government of Nicaragua did not consider itself
                        bound to solicit the consultative voice of Costa Rica in regard to the
                        disadvantages which the negotiations might possess for the two countries,
                        using the words of article 8 of the said treaty, and that in the event of
                        the treaty being declared valid, that will be one of the points which would
                        be submitted to the decision of the arbitrator.</p>
                    <p>After the communication to which I allude, those days followed in which the
                        hope was entertained that the differences between Costa Rica and Nicaragua
                        would be arranged by a proposed conference of the two presidents. To-day
                        that hope has vanished in consequence of the rejection of the treaty of
                        Managua. My Government is not only in the position of confirming its former
                        protest, but of amplifying it upon reasons based upon a study of the
                        contract concluded between the Government of that Republic and Señor Aniceto
                        G. Menocal for the opening of the interoceauic canal.</p>
                    <p>It has always been clear to my Government that the treaty of 1858 is
                        synallagmatic. It became, in this Republic and in that a law, and as such
                        was observed during long years. It can not be held to be null and void at
                        the will of one only of the contracting parties. The question whether the
                        treaty is valid or not is submitted to arbitration, and my Government
                        tranquilly awaits the arbitrator’s decision. Until that treaty, which is
                        revested with extraordinary solemnities, shall have been declared null, its
                        observance is binding upon the two Republics.</p>
                    <p>There is still more upon this point. Even in the case that the arbitration
                        should declare the treaty of 1858 to be null, which my Government really
                        does not expect, according to the convention concluded in Guatemala it must
                        continue in force until it shall have been definitely settled by treaty or
                        by new arbitration, what will then become a question of boundaries; an old
                        and grave question which the treaty of 1858 cut short, and about which the
                        opinions of our respective Governments are wide apart.</p>
                    <pb facs="0238" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/>
                    <p>Under these circumstances your excellency’s Government entered into a
                        canalization contract without hearing the Government of Costa Rica,
                        notwithstanding the stipulations of the treaty of 1858, and notwithstanding
                        that the contract to which I allude profoundly injures the national
                        interests of this Republic, which, according to the treaty, is riparian in a
                        part of the right bank of the San Juan; it has perpetual rights of
                        navigation on this river and common right with Nicaragua in the Bay of San
                        Juan del Norte, and its boundaries on the Pacific side extend to the central
                        point of the Bay of Salinas. Failing to obtain the positive right arising
                        from the treaty of 1858, Costa Rica supported by her legitimate titles,
                        would be restored to her former boundaries marked by the lake, the San Juan
                        River, and the River La Flor.</p>
                    <p>These precedents being established, I pass to the contract between that
                        Republic and Mr. Menocal. Several of its clanses, as well as the surveys
                        made up to to-day, indicate that the San Juan River will serve as the bed of
                        the projected canal; that the banks of the river can be occupied, the mouth
                        of the river changed, and the courses of other rivers running into Costa
                        Rica territory, and in which she has indisputable rights, changed. The right
                        to navigate the San Juan, the riparian rights to the same, and the right in
                        common with Nicaragua to the Bay of San Juan del Norte are attacked and
                        impaired by the contract to which I al ude, and its execution would result
                        in grievous injury to the territory of this Republic, to its commerce, and
                        to its river routes of communication.</p>
                    <p>It is true that it has been agreed that the excavations for the interoceanic
                        canal are to be made in Nicaraguan territory, but it is none the less true
                        that without violating that principle the waters of the San Juan can not be
                        made use of, so that it will he rendered useless for the navigation to which
                        Costa Rica has aright. Enormous modifications are to be made in the bays,
                        and the present courses of Costa Rican rivers are to be changed and in this
                        way grave injuries will be done to this Republic, ad greater still should
                        the canal company change the traced route in virtue of the freedom of action
                        which the contract I refer to concedes them.</p>
                    <p>For all this the Government of Costa Rica is under the necessity of
                        confirming and does confirm and extend her former protest, and will not
                        consent at any time that the excavation of the canal shall prejudice the
                        rights of this Republic, whether by taking a part of her territory or the
                        waters in which she has the right of navigation, or by modifications of the
                        bay in which she has a common right, or by deviating the rivers that run in
                        Costa Rican territory.</p>
                    <p>My Government is far from wishing to create obstacles to the canal
                        enterprise; no one can attribute such intentions to a progressive
                        administration, animated by Central American spirit, but it is its strict
                        duty to maintain unharmed the rights and prerogatives of the country whose
                        destines are confided in it.</p>
                    <p>Aware of the immense utility of an interoceanic canal, an enterprise which
                        may be considered of universal importance, and which has for a long time
                        been considered the desideratum of Central American patriots, my Government
                        has always been and is disposed to hear propositions respecting the part
                        that pertains to it in a work in which nature and her laws give joint rights
                        to this Republic.</p>
                    <p>Notwithstanding, however great may be the importance of the projected canal,
                        and although the construction thereof can count upon its sympathy, my
                        Government can not consent to the carrying out of the work to the sacrifice
                        of this nation, and it considers that the hour has arrived to formulate the
                        present protest which the Government of your excellency should receive in no
                        other light than as the fulfillment of the obligation of mine ever to
                        preserve harmless the rights of Costa Rica.</p>
                    <p>I improve, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ascension Esquivel</hi>
                            </persName>,</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 755.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Zavala</persName> to Señor
                                <persName type="to">Esquivel</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua, Nicaragua</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-12-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2, 1887</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: With deep concern and not without
                        surprise I have received the courteous note of your excellency, dated 2d
                        November last, substantially confirming and amplifying your protest of the
                        14th of May of the present year against the canal concession to Mr. Aniceto
                        Menocal, because the consultative voice of that Government had not been
                        heard.</p>
                    <p>Indeed, Mr. Minister, that new and uncalled for protest upon a subject which,
                        is already beyond the discussion of our respective Governments, it having
                        been submitted to arbitration, is again brought up at the very moment when a
                        corps of engineers charged with making the final studies for locating the
                        line of the interoceanic canal, is about to arrive at our shores; it could
                        not otherwise than cause surprise and unfavorable <pb facs="0239" n="105"
                            xml:id="pg_105"/> impression upon my Government, because if it were not
                        known that the deliberations of the enlightened Costa Rican cabinet are
                        guided by an elevated spirit, it might be supposed that it was intended to
                        create obstacles to the execution of a great work of universal interest,
                        upon which these countries base all their future hopes. Moreover, it is in
                        complete opposition to the conduct formerly observed by that Government,
                        whenever this enterprise, of such vital importance, has been discussed.</p>
                    <p>In the opinion of my Government the note of this Department of the 23d June,
                        in reply to that of your excellency of the 14th of May last, sufficiently
                        explains its ideas upon the question submitted to arbitration, and its
                        purposes, whatever may be the nature of the award, should have completely
                        tranquillized the Government of your excellency.</p>
                    <p>Unless the Government of Costa Rica wishes to withdraw from the cognizance of
                        the arbitrator, the question pending in regard to the validity of the treaty
                        of 15th April, 1858, any protest or allegation in regard to rights to be
                        derived from that treaty would be out of place because based upon a document
                        whose substance is under judicial consideration; nor is this new arrangement
                        justified by the circumstance that the efforts of both Governments to
                        arrange the difficulty directly have failed, inasmuch as the proposed treaty
                        of 26th July last contains a provision therefor in the event of its not
                        being projected; and, moreover, the contracting parties agreed therein to
                        submit to the arbitrator’s award.</p>
                    <p>The present reply, therefore, must be limited substantially to a repetition
                        of the note of this department of the 23d of June last; but I deem it not
                        out of place to make the following observations:</p>
                    <p>The canal concession lately granted to Mr. Menocal is essentially the same as
                        the one granted to the same party in 1880. In the former as well as in the
                        present concession the engagements of Nicaragua were limited exclusively to
                        her own territory and waters. So true is this that your excellency’s
                        Government in a note dated the 24th June of the same year (1880) recognized
                        that in the contract referred to the boundary line as determined by the
                        second article of the treaty of 1858 had been respected; a declaration the
                        more honorable for Nicaragua, and an irrefutable proof of the spirit of
                        harmony and fraternity which animated her Government, inasmuch as for a long
                        time previous to the date of that concession my Government had persisted in
                        the nullity of the referred to treaty. Subsequently the Government granted
                        an extension of time for carrying out that contract., and not only the
                        Government of your excellency remained silent upon the points now referred
                        to in its reiterated protest, but in 1884 it accepted the idea of offering a
                        guaranty to the same association of 3 per centum upon the capital invested
                        in the enterprise, thus approving and assenting to the legality of all that
                        Nicaragua had done in granting those concessions.</p>
                    <p>With these antecedents my Government is unable to understand upon what
                        motices that of your excellency has decided to protest against perfectly
                        legal acts which have already received its approbation.</p>
                    <p>Nicaragua has sustained the insubsistence of the treaty of 1858, because it
                        has never been perfected, and she is convinced that the arbitrator will
                        declare it to be null, for the reason that it is a doctrine current with
                        writers upon international law that a compact which is void does not cease
                        to be void even when it may for a time have been observed. Notwithstanding
                        that treaty is now submitted to an arbitrator’s decision, Nicaragua would
                        not now attempt to carry her pretensions of dominion to the Salto River, to
                        which her primitive rights extend; neither is she disposed to consent that
                        Costa Rica shall exercise rights dependent solely upon the validity of the
                        treaty, much less when the treaty is interpreted in the sense maintained by
                        the Government of your excellency.</p>
                    <p>In the opinion of my Government any discussion in regard to the rights of
                        Nicaragua and Costa Rica in the case provided for by article 8 of the
                        Arbitration Convention of Guatemala is premature, but I must at once say to
                        your excellency that the article mentioned refers to a period subsequent to
                        the arbitrator’s declaration; it says nothing in regard to the rule that
                        must be observed previous to that decision; it respects the established <hi
                            rend="italic">status quo</hi>, otherwise it would give temporary
                        validity, although in appearance only, to a treaty which should have been
                        declared insubsistent, while the interpretations which each party would give
                        to its stipulations would bring us back to the same or a worse situation
                        than the one we are trying to get out of.</p>
                    <p>I can not let pass without observation the opinion expressed in your
                        excellency’s note wherein you state “that the works of the canal would
                        result in grievous injury to the territory of Costa Rica, to her commerce,
                        and to her river routes of communication, and that the right to navigate the
                        San Juan, the riparian rights to the same river, and the right in common
                        with Nicaragua to the Bay of San Juan del Norte are attacked and
                        impaired.”</p>
                    <p>Those rights, if they should become effective through a declaration of the
                        validity of the treaty of 1858, would never give Costa Rica the right to
                        deprive Nicaragua of her free action as lord and owner of the territory and
                        waters.</p>
                    <p>On the other hand the same contract establishes that in whatsoever way the
                        work <pb facs="0240" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/> of the canal may he carried
                        out, the canal company is under the obligation to canalize the lower San
                        Juan and to re-open the bay so that the right of navigation, which by the
                        treaty would pertain to Costa Rica, far from being impaired, would be
                        benefited by the construction of this work. From this stand-point the
                        protest is still less explicable.</p>
                    <p>Having made these observations, which my Government has deemed indispensable
                        in fulfillment of the high duties confided to it, and which the Government
                        of your excellency with its enlightened judgment will appreciate in their
                        full value, it remains for me to say to your excellency that they do not
                        lessen in any manner the vehement desire of my Government to see our old
                        differences cut short forever, and that the cordial harmony existing between
                        the two Republics may remain inalterable. With these purposes, I have the
                        honor, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Adrian Zavala.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
