<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-07-26T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-07-26T15:00:00-05:00" n="107" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a3/79: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dawes</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-07-26T16:00:00-04:00">July 26, 1929—4
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>192. Your 204, July 25, 1 p.m. In view of the meeting of Mr. Gibson and
                            yourself with Mr. MacDonald on Monday, it seems to us desirable to
                            review the position of negotiations to date and explain for the guidance
                            of yourself and Mr. Gibson our views as to the several matters.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">First point</hi>—We may summarize
                                accomplishments in agreement with the British up to the present
                                moment as: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>We have agreed that the conference shall be inaugurated as
                                        a consequence of the Kellogg Pact.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>We have agreed on parity in combatant strength.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>We have agreed that this parity should be separately by
                                        categories of capital ships, aircraft carriers, destroyers,
                                        cruisers and submarines.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>We have agreed not to disturb the provisions of the
                                        Washington Treaty, thereby fixing ratios of capital ships
                                        and aircraft carriers but see paragraph (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">infra</hi> under second
                                        point.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>We have agreed that a yardstick shall be adopted by which
                                        comparative value of the ships within the categories shall
                                        be measured.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>The American Government agrees, subject to reaching an
                                        agreement on other questions, to scrap excess destroyers and
                                        excess submarines down to the British level either at
                                        present or by 1936.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>We agree with Mr. MacDonald as to the principle of total
                                        abolition of submarines in international war. We realize
                                        with him that it may be impossible to secure consent of
                                        other nations, but we should make a mutual effort in this
                                        direction.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Second point</hi>—There are left the following
                                points which we would like to have settled in principle as necessary
                                to assure the success of a conference. <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>We should like an agreement that all replacements of
                                        capital ships under the Washington Treaty shall be postponed
                                        until after 1936. This will give a holiday from major naval
                                        construction (capital ships and aircraft carriers) until
                                        after that date, and as at that time under that Treaty it
                                        will be necessary to revise the programs, that would be an
                                        appropriate date at which again to seek a further general
                                        revision of naval strength downward.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Entirely in accord with the suggestion that we must have a
                                        yardstick, we consider it essential that we should agree
                                        upon certain principles upon which the yardstick shall be
                                        based before we can present a definitive series of figures.
                                        It is our suggestion that in the cruiser category, for
                                        instance, we should take the new 10,000 ton, <pb facs="0299" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> 8-inch gun cruiser as
                                        representing the standard, and that we should in measuring
                                        the relative combatant strength of other ships in the
                                        cruiser category, consider the elements of the yardstick at <list>
                                            <item>Displacement.</item>
                                            <item>Age.</item>
                                            <item>Guns.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>Our general view is that protection, speed, habitability,
                                        et cetera, are entirely relative to the other factors, and
                                        do not require special consideration. No doubt these factors
                                        may deserve different weight for other categories. </item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>We suggest that for cruisers we should adopt 20 years of
                                        age as the scrappable age, for destroyers 16 years, and for
                                        submarines, 13 years.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>It is our impression that we should seek to equate our
                                        cruiser, destroyer and submarine tonnage as at 1936 instead
                                        of today, as this will better accommodate the British
                                        situation.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>If the principles of paragraphs (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) can be adopted, we have resolved technical
                                        questions purely into the question as to the discounts from
                                        the standard that are to be allowed for age and gun calibre.
                                        We realize that technical difficulties will arise over the
                                        determination of these two factors, in which there will need
                                        to be a spirit of compromise, but we think that the whole
                                        problem will be infinitely simplified if we can agree upon
                                        the principles which we are to submit to the naval
                                        experts.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>We are, of course, anxious to arrive at a situation which
                                        will allow us to reduce our authorized cruiser program,
                                        which would imply arriving at a theoretical tonnage in 1936
                                        of somewhere from 200 to 250 thousand tons. We have made
                                        some rough calculations as to our own and the British
                                        fleets, taking into account age and gun calibre and taking
                                        into account the number of ships that would be scrapped by
                                        1936 under the 20 year age limit, and taking into account
                                        the cessation of construction of the three new eight-inch
                                        cruisers and the two projected six-inch cruisers of the
                                        British Navy, and we believe that we could work it out
                                        quantitatively at about these limits.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Our view is that if we can agree to these principles a
                                        preliminary conference should be had in London,
                                        representative of the Five Powers, seeking their adherence
                                        to such of these principles as concern them.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Under the Washington Arms Treaty we are compelled to hold
                                        a conference of the five naval powers by 1931. We could by
                                        mutual consent merge these conferences into the one proposed
                                        for next December and avoid the necessity of holding two
                                        conferences on much the same subjects.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0300" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>A formal conference should be called in December,
                                        following Mr. MacDonald’s visit. The result of that visit
                                        undoubtedly will be to further the building of good will and
                                        to pave the way for mutual understanding.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>