<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a Conversation With the Japanese
                    Ambassador ( (Debuchi))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="179"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a3/387</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a Conversation With
                        the Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Debuchi</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-11-12">November 12,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>After explaining that what I said was tentative and in no sense an ultimatum and
                    that I was prepared to go to the conference with an open mind, and further, that
                    what I said had no connection with the British, I went over the <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="86" xml:id="d179fn86">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                    </note> with the Japanese Ambassador explaining the positions throughout and
                    pointing out clearly among the other points that the West Pacific bases question
                    would be affected by the opening of the ratio question, and explained to him how
                    strongly our people out there felt about the result of the <pb facs="0410"
                        n="274" xml:id="pg_274"/> last conference on the base question. I told him
                    that the last part of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> was merely an
                    attempt to put on record for him what I never had an opportunity to put in
                    writing but thought I had told it verbally many times, namely, the substance of
                    our conversations with the British during the summer.</p>
                <p>After I had finished he expressed his disappointment on the subject of the ratio
                    and was evidently very much troubled as to how he could explain it to his
                    people. He will come here next week and asked for at least an hour’s conference.
                    Incidentally he said that he had been at the Washington Conference and pointed
                    out that Balfour<note n="87" xml:id="d179fn87">Rt. Hon. Arthur James Balfour,
                        member of the British delegation at the conference on the Limitation of
                        Armament, Washington, November 12, 1921–February 6, 1922.</note> had
                    reserved the question of small cruisers from the 5–5–3 agreement, so far as
                    Britain was concerned; also that the question had been brought up again at
                    Geneva in 1927<note n="88" xml:id="d179fn88">Three-Power Conference; see <ref
                            target="frus1927v01#pg_1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1927, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> by Japan and that he
                    got the idea that America was friendly to 10–10–7. For these reasons he was
                    afraid that our opposition to opening it, he thought, was unreasonable. I
                    pointed out to him that he had not shown any change of situation from 1922 when
                    I had understood the 5–5–3 ratio had been accepted by the Japanese
                    representatives as a sufficiently defensive position for them. We talked at
                    considerable length in a very frank way and it was agreed that he should come in
                    next week.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>H[<hi rend="smallcaps">enry</hi>] L. S[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >timson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
