<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="269" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">868.111/42</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-03-01">March 1, 1929</date>.<lb/>[Received March
                                    27.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 841</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that,
                                pending the conclusion of the naturalization treaty with the
                                Hellenic Government, I have recommended that temporary measures be
                                taken which would facilitate the arrival in this country of persons
                                of Greek origin who, under the normal application of laws and
                                regulations, might be held for military service or the payment of
                                fines, and I have now received a note from the Ministry of Foreign
                                Affairs covering this matter in satisfactory form, and in the
                                following terms: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“In reply to the Note No. 204 a. p. addressed by the American
                                        Legation to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the latter has
                                        the honor to state that the Government of the Republic has
                                        decided to postpone all <pb facs="0598" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> proceedings because of military
                                        obligations, as respects excursionists departing from the
                                        United States, of Hellenic origin, during the whole of their
                                        sojourn in Greece. The measures taken in favor of the said
                                        excursionists will be applicable from March 1st to October
                                        1st, 1929.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is understood from the competent officials at the Foreign Office
                                that Greek Consuls in the United States have been instructed to
                                issue to such excursionists a special certificate upon which his
                                Greek visa will be placed.</p>
                            <p>I suggest that the above information be communicated to the press for
                                the benefit of the public.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert P.
                                Skinner</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>