<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Minister in Guatemala (
                    (Geissler))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d404</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">404</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-08-24T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-08-24T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-08-24T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-08-24T13:00:00-05:00" n="404"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d404">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.79611 Pan American Airways, Inc./619:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Minister in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Geissler</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-08-24T14:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 24, 1929—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>49. Your 106, August 19, 6 p.m. and 107, August 20, 11 a.m. It is evident that if
                    Pan American Airways is to establish a two day service from Brownsville to the
                    Canal Zone as planned it will be impracticable to change planes and crews at the
                    Guatemalan border. This service is designed to handle mail from the eastern and
                    central parts of the United States and would not necessarily compete with any
                    other service covering the western part. The Department is assured that the
                    Compañia Mexicana de Aviación will not run farther south than Guatemala <pb
                        facs="0716" n="580" xml:id="pg_580"/> City. The Department as you know does
                    not ordinarily support foreign corporations even when all of the stock is
                    American owned but in this case it has been decided after careful consideration
                    that an exception is warranted for the reasons stated and because of the direct
                    interest of the United States Post Office therein. You will therefore please
                    make such representations to the Guatemalan Government as you consider
                    appropriate to obtain permission for the Compañia Mexicana de Aviacion to bring
                    the United States mails into Guatemala from Mexico.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carr</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
