<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="523" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d523">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/3242½</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a
                                Conversation With the Chilean Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Davila</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-12-01">December 1, 1928</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Chilean Ambassador informed me today that his Government had
                            instructed Figueroa, the Chilean Ambassador to Peru, to offer to Peru
                            all the territory north of a line on an average of about ten kilometers
                            north of the railroad. The line could not be exactly ten kilometers
                            because it would not in every place conform with the line of the
                            railroad but it would be as near as could be. Also that Chile would
                            complete all public improvements in Tacna at its own expense, estimated
                            at about six million Chilean pesos.</p>
                        <p>The Chilean Ambassador also said that Chile would be willing to make
                            Arica a free port to Peru the same as Bolivia has at the present time
                            and they would have their own Customs House and the same duties in the
                            port that Chile and Bolivia now have. Chile now has a preferential duty.
                            In this way Peru would have the same preferential low duties which Chile
                            and Bolivia now enjoy; that Peru would enjoy the same tariffs on the
                            railway and the Arica Tacna provinces would have access to the same
                            ports and the same rights that they now enjoy.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>