<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-09-22T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-09-22T12:00:00-05:00" n="831" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d831">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">715.1715/325: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Honduras</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tegucigalpa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-09-22T11:00:00-06:00">September 22, 1929—11 a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 9:30
                                    p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>89. In carrying out the instructions in the Department’s telegram No.
                                62, September 19, 6 p.m., I addressed a note to the Foreign Office
                                and last evening received a reply thereto, dated September 21, in
                                which the Minister for Foreign Affairs, after repeating the
                                substance of my note, continues as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“In reply I have the honor of informing Your Excellency that
                                        the Government of Honduras, in decreeing martial law in the
                                        zone which was specified in the decree itself, did so with
                                        the knowledge of the Government of Nicaragua, without any
                                        protest, and with the principal object of cooperating, as a
                                        Government friendly to Nicaragua, in the pacification of the
                                        Segovias which for so long were suffering the consequences
                                        of the Sandinista rebels, Honduras having given its
                                        effective cooperation, notwithstanding the economic and
                                        other sacrifices on its part. With this end in view my
                                        Government ordered that armed details should watch the
                                        frontier of both countries so as to pursue and capture the
                                        rebels, but without ordering any violent act against
                                        Nicaraguan forces, nor the capture of any person, other than
                                        rebels. I must inform you also that my Government has
                                        already ordered the withdrawal of these Honduran soldiers
                                        and the liberation of the prisoners, in case that which is
                                        said is true. In these circumstances, according to the
                                        suggestion of Your Excellency, there will now be no
                                        difficulty in carrying to a conclusion the proceedings
                                        indispensable to the execution of the award of His Majesty
                                        the King of Spain amid the cordial and friendly relations
                                        which fortunately exist between Honduras and Nicaragua. And
                                        my Government heeding the suggestion which, in the name of
                                        the Government of the United States, Your Excellency was
                                        good enough to make that, Honduras withdraw[ing] from any
                                        territory hitherto occupied by Nicaragua, as a preliminary
                                        step, there will be no difficulty to any further
                                        negotiations, I must inform you that His Excellency the
                                        Minister of Nicaragua, General Augusto J. Caldera, has
                                        proposed informally to His Excellency the President of this
                                        Republic the naming of a commission of engineers, one by
                                        Honduras, another by Nicaragua and another by the Government
                                        of the United States, the third named at the request of the
                                        Governments of those two republics in order that they might
                                        proceed to the definite tracing of the boundary line, taking
                                        as a base the above-mentioned award; in this conception I am
                                        happy to inform you that Honduras would be glad if the
                                        enlightened Government of Your Excellency, interested as it
                                        is in the removal of causes which impede the maintenance of
                                        the tranquillity of the two countries, would have the
                                        goodness to interpose its good offices with the Nicaraguan
                                        Government with the object that this commission may be named
                                        with the shortest possible delay, to the above mentioned
                                        end, so that this matter may be concluded as soon as
                                        possible, offering in <pb facs="1117" n="981" xml:id="pg_981"/> advance the gratitude of the
                                        Government and people of Honduras to Your Government for its
                                        efforts.</p>
                                    <p>I avail myself of this opportunity, et cetera.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Repeated to Nicaragua.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Summerlin</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>