<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Instrument of Cession Signed on April 17, 1900, by the Representatives of the
                    People of Tutuila</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d853</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">853</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="853"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d853">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Instrument of Cession Signed on April 17, 1900, by the
                        Representatives of the People of Tutuila</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">To All To Whom These Presents Shall Come,
                    Greeting</hi>!!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> the Governments of Germany, Great Britain, and
                    of the United States of America have on divers occasions recognized the
                    sovereignty of the government and people of Samoa and the Samoan Group of
                    Islands as an independent State: <hi rend="smallcaps">And Whereas</hi> owing to
                    dissensions, internal disturbances, and civil war the said Governments have
                    deemed it necessary to assume the control of the legislation and administration
                    of said State of Samoa: <hi rend="smallcaps">And Whereas</hi> the said
                    Governments have on the sixteenth day of February 1900 by mutual agreement<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d853fn2">For text of convention, see <ref
                            target="frus1899#pg_667">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1899, p. 667</ref>.</note>
                    determined to partition said State: <hi rend="smallcaps">And Whereas</hi> the
                    Islands hereinafter described being part of the said State have by said
                    arrangement amongst the said Governments been severed from the parent State and
                    the Governments of Great Britain and of Germany have withdrawn all rights
                    hitherto acquired claimed or possessed by both or either of them by Treaty or
                    otherwise to the said Islands in favor of the Government of the United States of
                    America: <hi rend="smallcaps">And Whereas</hi> for the promotion of the peace
                    and welfare of the people of said Islands, for the establishment of a good and
                    sound Government, and for the preservation of the rights and property of the
                    inhabitants of said Islands, the Chiefs, rulers and people thereof are desirous
                    of granting unto the said Government of the United States full power and
                    authority to enact proper legislation for and to control the said Islands and
                    are further desirous of removing all disabilities that may be existing in
                    connection therewith and to ratify and to confirm the grant of the rule of said
                    Islands heretofore granted on the 2nd day of April 1900 <hi rend="smallcaps">Now
                        Know Ye</hi>:— <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That we, the Chiefs whose names are hereunder subscribed, by virtue of
                            our office as the hereditary representatives of the people of said
                            Islands in consideration of the premises hereinbefore recited and for
                            divers good considerations us hereunto moving, have Ceded, Transferred,
                            and Yielded Up, unto Commander B. F. Tilley of U. S. [S.] <pb
                                facs="1147" n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/> “Abarenda” the duly
                            accredited representative of the Government of the United States of
                            America in the Islands hereinafter mentioned or described for and on
                            behalf of the said Government All Those the Islands of Tutuila and Aunuu
                            and all other Islands, rocks, reefs, foreshores, and waters lying
                            between the thirteenth degree and the fifteenth degree of south latitude
                            and between the one hundred and seventy first degree and the one hundred
                            sixty seventh degree of west longitude from the Meridian of Greenwich
                            together with all sovereign rights thereunto belonging and possessed by
                            us To Hold the said ceded territory unto the Government of the United
                            States of America To Erect the same into a separate District to be
                            annexed to the said Government to be known and designated as the
                            District of “Tutuila”.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Government of the United States of America shall respect and
                            protect the individual rights of all people dwelling in Tutuila to their
                            lands and other property in said District, but if the said Government
                            shall require any land or any other thing for Government uses, the
                            Government may take the same upon payment of a fair consideration for
                            the land or other thing to those who may be deprived of their property
                            on account of the desire of the Government.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Chiefs of the towns will be entitled to retain their individual
                            control of the separate towns, if that control is in accordance with the
                            laws of the United States of America concerning Tutuila, and if not
                            obstructive to the peace of the people and the advancement of
                            civilization of the people, subject also to the supervision and
                            instruction of the said Government. But the enactment of legislation and
                            the General Control shall remain firm with the United States of
                            America.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>An investigation and settlement of all claims to title to land in the
                            different divisions or districts of Tutuila shall be made by the
                            Government.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>We whose names are subscribed below do hereby declare with truth for
                            ourselves, our heirs, and representatives by Samoan Custom, that we will
                            obey and owe allegiance to the Government of the United States of
                            America.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">In Witness Whereof</hi> We Have Hereunto Subscribed Our
                    Names And Affixed Our Seals On This 17th Day of April 1900 A. D.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Fofo and Aitulagi</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Tuitele of Leone</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Faiivae of Leone</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Letuli of Iliili</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Fuimaono of Aoloau</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Satele of Vailoa</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Leoso of Leone</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Olo of Leone</hi>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="1148" n="1012" xml:id="pg_1012"/>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Namoa of Aitulagi</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Malota of Aitulagi</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Tunaitau of Pavaiai</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Lualemana of Asu</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">x Amituagai of Ituau</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Sua and Vaifanua</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pele x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mauga x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leiato x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Faumuina x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Masaniai x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tupuola x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Soliai x</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mauga x</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">The foregoing Instrument of Cession<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d853fn3">Received by the Secretary of the Navy on August 1,
                            1900; filed in the Department of State on March 1, 1902.</note> was duly
                        signed by <hi rend="smallcaps">Leoso</hi> in the presence of and at the
                        request of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Chiefs</hi> and representatives of the
                        Division of Fofo and Aitulagi and by <hi rend="smallcaps">Pele</hi> in the
                        presence of and at the request of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Chiefs</hi> and
                        representatives of the Division of Sua and Vaifanua in Tutuila in conformity
                        with a Samoan Custom as to signatures to documents in my presence at
                            <placeName>Pagopago</placeName> on <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1900-04-17">the 17th day of April 1900 A. D.</date> immediately
                        prior to the raising of the United States Flag at the United States Naval
                        Station, Tutuila.</dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. W. Gurr</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">A Barrister of the Supreme Court of Samoa</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
