<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="141" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d141">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Thompson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-02-09"><hi rend="italic">February 9, 1894</hi></date>.
                            (Received March 19.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 161.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit a copy of a
                        translation of note from Rear-Admiral Saldanha da Gama, purporting to be
                        addressed to Admiral Benham, which has been secretly circulated among
                        Brazilians, ostensibly to create a sympathy for the insurgent cause.</p>
                    <p>Having secured the copy only on the eve of the departure of the mail, I have
                        not been able to confer with Admiral Benham about it.</p>
                    <p>My recollection is that no discharge of cargoes from ships with? lighters and
                        tugs was made during the interim between the date of the announcement by
                        Admiral Saldanha da Gama that he would endeavor to stop the passage of goods
                        to the custom-house and the action of Admiral Benham which caused the
                        withdrawal of the restriction. A few American ships came to the docks on
                        their own responsibility and were successful in discharging and taking on
                        cargoes without interference during that time.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thos. L. Thompson.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                            161.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Rear-Admiral <persName type="from">da
                                    Gama</persName> to Rear-Admiral <persName type="to">Benham</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">On
                                        board the Cruiser Liberdade</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-01-30"><hi rend="italic">January
                                        30, 1894</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Your Excellency the Commander-in-Chief
                                of the North American Naval Forces:</hi></p>
                        <p>All ships lying in this port, both war ships and merchantmen, were
                            witness of the grave and open opposition that the navy, under my
                            command, suffered yesterday morning from the naval forces under the
                            command of your excellency Rear-Admiral Benham, of the U. S. Navy.</p>
                        <p>Starting from the principle that the revolutionary element in Brazil, of
                            which the fleet that operates in this port is but a factor, has not yet
                            been recognized as belligerents, and basing on this the duty of
                            protecting, <hi rend="italic">quand même</hi>, the maritime commerce
                            under your country’s flag, your excellency believed it lawful to use
                            with ostentation the important naval force under your command and
                            obliged the revolutionary fleet to consent that three North American
                            merchant ships, instead of effecting their discharge on anchor, do it
                            alongside this city’s wharves.</p>
                        <p>The measures adopted by the forces under my command have never been of a
                            nature offensive to the interests of foreign maritime commerce. On the
                            contrary, they have constituted a modus vivendi, in accordance with
                            which, in return of the <pb facs="0236" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/>
                            merchant ships not getting alongside the wharves, for it would embarrass
                            our military operations, we agreed in allowing tow boats, launches, and
                            discharging lighters, which, as Brazilian bottoms, are liable to be
                            seized by us, to do their work in port under the protection of foreign
                            flags.</p>
                        <p>These measures have been so far accepted and respected by the commanders
                            of foreign naval forces lying in this port, including those of the U. S.
                            Navy, which has been represented here, we might say, from the beginning
                            of the present situation.</p>
                        <p>The delay of our recognition as belligerents by the foreign nations
                            having transactions with Brazil, though not giving us privileges granted
                            by international law, can not prohibit us, however, of using vigilance
                            in behalf of our defense and maintenance. If Ave have no legal existence
                            in its exact international meaning, our existence in fact as combatants
                            for nearly half year in the port of the country’s capital in face of the
                            center of our adversary’s power can not, however, be denied. The case is
                            entirely new. For the first time a revolutionary force is maintained
                            such a long time inside a harbor in situation of preventing all its
                            movement.</p>
                        <p>But your excellency Rear-Admiral Benham did not understand so. On the
                            pretention, as he asserts, of protecting by all means American maritime
                            commerce in whichever way it suit your excellency, through your imposing
                            attitude of yesterday, puts us in the choice of either fighting with the
                            nation that he represents, which is not our intention nor our desire
                            when we are fighting to free our country of a dictatorial government, or
                            break on our part, and in the only interest of his countrymen, the modus
                            vivendi accepted up to this date.</p>
                        <p>Leaving on one side the moral offense resulting from the action, and
                            against which I protested yesterday by voice of cannon and by panic, it
                            remains now to be known whether this alteration of the modus vivendi
                            agreed for will not modify it completely.</p>
                        <p>On the face of the demonstration, against which I can not pretend in this
                            moment react by force as well, I have to consent in future in allowing
                            American ships to get alongside the <hi rend="italic">Trapiches</hi>,
                            and this, by the principle of impartiality, gives the right of granting
                            the same advantage to all other foreign merchant ships that come to this
                            port.</p>
                        <p>Therefore the concessions which relatively to the shipping in this harbor
                            we believe to be fair to allow for the benefit of foreign maritime
                            commerce by intervention of the same commanders of the respective naval
                            forces are canceled and against our interests.</p>
                        <p>As your excellency will have to judge how unjust and disadvantageous this
                            situation is for ourselves who believe to be fighting for a noble and
                            national cause, we beg your excellency to accept the assurance of our
                            great esteem and respect.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Luiz Phillippe Saldanha da
                                    Gama</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Commander-in-Chief of the
                                    Forces in Revolution against the Government of Marshal Floriano
                                    Peixoto in the Port of Rio de Janeiro.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>