<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Conger to Mr. Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-05-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="18"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Conger</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 3, 1893</hi>
                        </date>. (Received May 31.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 436.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to report another important change in the
                    cabinet of Vice-President Peixoto.</p>
                <p>On the 27th ultimo Dr. Innocencio Serzedello Oorrea tendered his resignation as
                    minister of finance, and on the 28th Admiral Custodio José de Mello surrendered
                    the portfolio of marine.</p>
                <p>On the 30th Dr. Felisbello Firmo de Olivier a Freire, the recently appointed
                    minister of foreign affairs, was transferred to the ministry of finance, still
                    having charge of the foreign ministry ad interim, and Admiral Felippe Firmino
                    Rodrigues Chaves was appointed minister of marine.</p>
                <p>The reasons given for the resignation of Serzedello Correa were a general
                    disagreement with the vice-president on matters of financial administration.
                    Admiral Custodio de Mello sets forth as his grievances the refusal of the
                    vice-president to adopt his views for a settlement of the civil war now in
                    progress in Rio Grande do Sul, and a general disposition on the part of the
                    vice-president to manage matters without consultation with him. This is a very
                    serious rupture in the vice-president’s official family; from the fact that
                    these two resigned ministers were the strongest and most influential characters
                    in the cabinet, Admiral de Mello having been the chief organizer and leader of
                    the movement of November 23, 1891, which deposed Marshal Deodora from his
                    assumed dictatorship, and restored the legal government with Vice-President
                    Peixoto at its head.</p>
                <p>It is also currently reported and believed that both Dr. Serzedello and Mello are
                    candidates for the Presidency at the election which must take place in March
                    next.</p>
                <p>What the result of this crisis will be can only be conjectured; but as the
                    immediate future will shortly disclose it, I shall not offer any prophecy. As
                    setting forth more particularly the situation, I inclose a copy of an editorial
                    clipped from the Rio News, together with the letter of Admiral Custodio de
                    Mello.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. H. Conger.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 436.—Clipping from the Rio News
                            of May 2, 1893.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">cabinet changes.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The long impending rupture in the cabinet took place on the 27th, the
                        minister of finance offering his resignation on that day and the minister of
                        marine withdrawing from the council of ministers to send in his resignation
                        on the following day. That <pb facs="0141" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/>
                        dissensions existed has long been known, and it was also known that they
                        were sufficiently serious to make it impossible for the cabinet to act
                        harmoniously much longer. The resignation of Dr. Limpo d’Abreu a fortnight
                        since was of too personal a character to indicate the course which other
                        members of the cabinet would pursue, but as it was well known that the
                        ministers were not entirely agreed upon the coercive policy begun in Rio
                        Grande it was certain that the recent policy adopted by the minister of war
                        could not fail to bring these differences to an issue. This was practically
                        what occurred at the cabinet meeting of the 27th. Instead of appearing the
                        minister of finance sent in his resignation, which was based on the
                        financial policy of the executive, and the minister of marine withdrew to
                        prepare a letter tendering his resignation for the following day.</p>
                    <p>The immediate cause of the resignation of the minister of finance was a
                        communication received by him from the President on Thursday evening
                        containing a memorandum for a decree reforming the tribunal de contas, or
                        annulling its acts in trying to restrict public expenditures to the
                        legislative appropriations. The requirements of the army in Rio Grande have
                        caused many extraordinary and unauthorized expenditures, and the opposition
                        properly shown by the tribunal to these unwarranted uses of the public money
                        led the President to resolve upon its practical dissolution. Although
                        Minister Serzedello has not been particularly sensitive over these
                        dictatorial acts of authority, he resolved not to be an accomplice in the
                        destruction of so necessary a branch of the treasury as this auditing
                        commission.</p>
                    <p>In his letter of resignation he first alludes to the critical situation of
                        the treasury and to the “urgent measures” which he presented at the last
                        cabinet meeting to secure economy in expenditures. Among these were the
                        suppression of advances and commissions abroad, a reduction of expenses
                        abroad, the postponement of all public works not urgently required, a
                        reduction in the China and Chicago commissions, and the recall of all naval
                        vessels in foreign waters, the expenditures for all of which are now
                        increasing the deficit.</p>
                    <p>As to the tribunal de contas, he considers it the best protection the
                        Treasury can have, and for this reason he considers the proposed reform a
                        serious error. Instead of auditing accounts and refusing those not regular,
                        or not legal, it will become simply an instrument for conferring and
                        registering them, without power to protect the treasury against abuses in
                        expenditures.</p>
                    <p>The reasons for the resignation of the minister of marine are both political
                        and administrative, and as they relate to the civil war in Rio Grande we
                        give them in full:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">letter of resignation of the minister of marine.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>, <hi rend="italic">April 28,
                            1893</hi>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshal</hi>: Much more than a month ago I had the
                        honor of apprising your excellency, in a cabinet council, of the possibility
                        of a pacific solution of the conflict in which Rio Grande do Sul is engaged.
                        My purpose was patriotic, and would, by means of a conciliation, have
                        relieved that state of the Republic from a situation which has converted it
                        into a perennial source of hatreds and internal discords.</p>
                    <p>In order to not disturb the country at a time when the action of the
                        government in a time of such political gravity should be homogeneous, I did
                        not at once hand in my resignation of the portfolio which I held, and,
                        insisting on the solution proposed and which your excellency afterwards
                        undertook to realize, I hoped to see peace soon reestablished in that
                        unhappy state.</p>
                    <p>In view, however, of the mission with which the minister of war has been
                        charged by your excellency of continuing the conflict which is imbruing Rio
                        Grande do Sul with blood, I consider my permanence in the government
                        unprofitable, since it was not permitted me to secure that desideratum of
                        mine for internal policy and public peace.</p>
                    <p>In a ministerial conference realized on the 20th instant, after hearing me,
                        your excellency was good enough, in accord with the whole ministry, to
                        accept my reasons, and then again undertook to transmit your orders in a
                        sense of a pacification.</p>
                    <p>After a promise so categorically and twice confirmed, it was not permitted me
                        to doubt that it would be at once realized, and therefore, to my amazement,
                        I was yesterday surprised with a declaration in a sense wholly opposed to
                        the preceding undertakings and solemnly agreed to by your excellency.</p>
                    <p>I was and am of opinion that the federal government ought to sustain the
                        governors elected by the states. The principle, however, can not be
                        absolute. It admits exceptions like all those which regulate the guidance of
                        public opinion. It is publicly known and felt that the actual administration
                        in Rio Grande do Sul does not represent the majority of our compatriots in
                        that state. It is not a chosen government imposed by popular opinion, and
                        under such conditions it is a weak government, which can only be sustained
                        by the support of the federal military forces.</p>
                    <p>Now, marshal, the republican situation needs stability; its institutions need
                        to be consolidated, and the first condition of steadiness which the Republic
                        stands in need <pb facs="0142" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/> of is, precisely,
                        peace and public tranquility, avoiding henceforth and forever these internal
                        commotions which disturb our credit and hold the country constantly under
                        the threat of armed agitations and the surprises of sanguinary
                        conflicts.</p>
                    <p>I have within me the unalterable conviction that the revolutionary movement
                        of the south has no purpose of restoration. At the front of it are to be
                        found historic republicans, whose political traditions exclude every
                        suspicion of an attempt against the political institutions of the country.
                        Most of them fought after the <hi rend="italic">coup d’ état</hi> of 3d
                        November for the revindication of national honor and dignity, cooperating in
                        the great movement of reaction in favor of legality.</p>
                    <p>Under such conditions it would be a libel to assert that the revolutionists
                        are lighting to-day for another cause that shall not be a guarantee of the
                        rights and liberties which have been trampled under foot. We ought at least
                        to judge these our compatriots with the impartiality which old servitors of
                        the country are entitled to and by their political antecedents.</p>
                    <p>You now say that you can not adopt by suggestion because the constitution is
                        opposed to the means that would have to be used to carry it out.</p>
                    <p>But, marshal, your excellency must understand that no law can be opposed to
                        order, nor be made an obstacle to the progress and development of a nation.
                        If our constitution is, in your opinion, an obstacle to the pacification of
                        Rio Grande do Sul, the executive, whose duty it is to maintain domestic
                        peace and watch over public tranquility, and which can not, therefore, leave
                        to an armed struggle the fate of the whole state, should, in my opinion, in
                        a question of public safety, like that which is now agitated, adopt
                        extraordinary and even extra-legal measures to save the country at all
                        hazards.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency thinks that a reconciliation with the revolutionists may be
                        effected after the federal troops have won a victory over the enemy; but if
                        you admit the possibility of a conciliation after a battle, why not admit it
                        before a battle?</p>
                    <p>What, then, justifies this bloodshed? Does the Federal army require it?</p>
                    <p>It is assuredly not the blood of immolated brethren that will give it glory
                        and luster.</p>
                    <p>And who can assure us that this victory is certain? Who knows what means of
                        action are at the disposal of the revolutionists, who certainly have the
                        advantage of being inured to the effects of the climate which can not fail
                        to decimate our brave, intrepid, and valiant northern soldiers.</p>
                    <p>And what if the revolutionists, whose policy seems to be to wear out our
                        soldiers, refuse to give battle?</p>
                    <p>You perceive, then, marshal, that you propose a solution that does not
                        correspond to the present political emergency, nor find any justification
                        whatever in history. Your policy, then, endangers the public weal,
                        aggravating a situation that can not be maintained and against which protest
                        the simplest precepts of humanity and all feelings of republican fraternity.
                        It is a perennial source of evils for the Republic, since you indefinitely
                        postpone a just and reasonable solution for a crisis to which you should
                        have long since put an end.</p>
                    <p>There is another circumstance of great political weight which strengthens my
                        purpose of resigning my portfolio, and that is the want of skill with which,
                        in my opinion, the military operations have been conducted and from which
                        resulted the disaster at Alegrete, a disaster which will inevitably be
                        followed by others.</p>
                    <p>No one more than myself, marshal, renders homage to the spirit of rectitude
                        which governs your conduct in public and private life, and which places it
                        above the suspicion of any motive not dictated exclusively by your concern
                        for the public weal, and it is, consequently, to be regretted that you
                        should retain in the Republic of Uruguay as a purchasing agent for the army
                        a man who, according to information received from trustworthy sources,
                        including a letter from our minister in Montevideo, is wanting in
                        respectability, and is otherwise unqualified for so responsible a
                        position.</p>
                    <p>I regret, I repeat, that the information which has been furnished to you in
                        regard to this commissioner does not coincide with that to which I have just
                        referred.</p>
                    <p>In addition to what has herein been set forth, your excellency has not only
                        failed to consult me in regard to matters connected with the revolutionary
                        movement in Rio Grande do Sul, but has actually withheld them from my
                        knowledge in a manner highly offensive to the honorable office that I hold.
                        Some of the most important acts have been performed without my
                        intervention.</p>
                    <p>There has been nothing to justify this treatment, and your excellency can not
                        deny that I have displayed the utmost solicitude in affairs of state,
                        offering free and loyal support to the head of the Government and giving the
                        republican administration all the political and moral force which it has
                        needed in the arduous task, imposed upon us by circumstances, of upholding
                        the sway of the law. Neither my political self-respect nor the elevated
                        office which I hold will permit my remaining in the position in which your
                        excellency has thus placed me.</p>
                    <p>I hold, marshal, that I do not merely share the political responsibility of
                        the Government <pb facs="0143" n="35" xml:id="pg_35"/> and of its
                        administrative acts; it is my duty as minister to manage public affairs and
                        to be responsible for the events that may result from the manner in which
                        they are managed, especially at this period, bristling with difficulties.
                        Thus, equally upon the head of the Government and his ministers public
                        opinion is entitled to exercise the right of criticism and censure. I can
                        not, then, submit to the role of an automaton, nor will a republican
                        administration find worthy men who will sacrifice the nobility of their
                        political mandate to an office which does not elevate, but degrades; which
                        does not ennoble, but humiliates.</p>
                    <p>For these reasons I present my resignation; but outside of the Government I
                        will continue to serve the Republic, upholding its institutions and legally
                        constituted authorities, with the same devotion, fortitude, and loyalty with
                        which I have served it as minister.</p>
                    <p>With the utmost respect and esteem I have the honor to sign myself,</p>
                    <p>Your friend, admirer, and obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Custodio de Mello.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
