<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-06-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Gresham</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Denby</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-06-05"><hi rend="italic">June 5,
                            1893</hi>.</date></dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 804.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit herewith for your information
                        copies of correspondence exchanged with the Chinese minister in this
                        capital, relative to the application of the Chinese immigration act of May
                        5, 1892, to the test cases recently brought before the Supreme Court to
                        determine the constitutionality of that act, and to the apprehensions felt
                        by the minister lest the date fixed for the enforcement of the Geary act
                        might be marked by mob violence against the Chinese in the Pacific
                        States.</p>
                    <p>The minister’s fears in the latter regard proved groundless, as I felt
                        confident would be the case.</p>
                    <p>In pursuance of the intimation conveyed in Mr. Wharton’s note to Mr. Tsui, of
                        December 10, 1892, that the constitutionality of the Geary act could be
                        tested only before the judicial branch of this Government, certain test
                        cases were brought before the Supreme Court immediately after the act went
                        into operation on the 5th ultimo, and by the understanding reached, as shown
                        in the correspondence, the proceedings were expedited, and the decision of
                        the court rendered on the 15th ultimo sustaining the law. When it shall be
                        printed copies will be sent to you.</p>
                    <p>In recent conversations with the Chinese minister since the decision the
                        alarming reports of anticipated acts of retaliation in both countries have
                        been discussed. I have told Mr. Tsui I was satisfied that if the Chinese
                        protect Americans in China and prevent assaults upon them we would be able
                        to protect the Chinese in this country, but that should Americans in
                        China—missionaries, merchants, and others—be injured in person or property
                        it might not be possible to control sentiment here and to effectively
                        protect the widely scattered Chinese.</p>
                    <p>The minister, in return, assured me that there was nothing in his latest
                        official advices to justify the belief that Americans in China were now
                        imperiled, and that no efforts would be spared for their protection should
                        they be threatened with danger. As regards the execution of the act of May
                        5, 1892, I have stated to the minister that while the President can not
                        suspend a law of Congress, which it is his constitutional duty to execute,
                        and while it was impossible to give assurance that the Geary act would not
                        be enforced, its terms and requirements will necessarily cause its
                        enforcement to be attended with some delay; so that there was no reason to
                        believe that the Chinese who have refused compliance with the statute will
                        be deported in large numbers between now and the assembling of Congress, at
                        which time there is ground to anticipate further legislation on the
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>The situation appears, in the main, to be favorable to a rational disposition
                            <pb facs="0343" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> of the whole matter. Some
                        harsh features of the Treasury regulations for the enforcement of the Geary
                        law have been modified, a circumstance which Mr. Tsui assures me is highly
                        appreciated. In the absence of an adequate appropriation for the deportation
                        of nonregistered Chinese, the operations of the Treasury Department are
                        necessarily limited for the present mainly to the cases of the those who are
                        found to have come to the United States unlawfully.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. Q. Gresham</hi>.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>