<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Gresham to Mr. Tsui Kwo Yin.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="protection-of-americans-abroad" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="protection-of-americans-abroad">protection of Americans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="267"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d267">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Gresham</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Tsui Kwo Yin</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 19, 1893</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your note to this Department of June
                    2, 1891, in which you stated that “the Imperial Chinese Government, in order to
                    facilitate a more perfect compliance with the terms of section 6 of the law of
                    the Congress of the United States of July 5, 1884, has authorized the consuls of
                    China in foreign countries to issue, in behalf of their Government, to the
                    exempt class of Chinese residents in said countries the certificate of identity
                    required by said law,” I now have the honor to request that you will kindly
                    inform this Department what is the nature of the instructions, if any, of the
                    Imperial Government to its consular officers in foreign countries in regard to
                    this subject; and also whether any action has been taken by your Government with
                    respect to the issuance of certificates to persons of the exempt class by its
                    officers resident in China.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Q. Gresham.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of a conversation between the Secretary of
                            State and the Chinese minister.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi> (by his interpreter). Immediately
                        after going to the legation from the State Department a few days ago, I sent
                        to my Government a dispatch covering the substance of the interview between
                        the Secretary of State and myself, and yesterday I received a reply
                        expressing great satisfaction at hearing that the Secretary did not think
                        there would be serious trouble growing out of the Geary law and the decision
                        of the Supreme Court sustaining its validity.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary</hi>. I hope you understood me correctly
                        in our last interview?</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>. I think I did; and that I correctly
                        reported it. I wish information upon two points. Do you feel reasonably
                        certain that the Chinese in this country will not be abused, beaten,
                        wounded, and murdered as in the past; and do you think the Geary law will at
                        once be enforced?</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary</hi>. I am satisfied that if the Chinese
                        protect Americans in China and prevent assaults upon them, we will be able
                        to protect the Chinese in this country; but should Americans in
                        China—missionaries, merchants, and others—be injured in their persons and
                        property, and the fact become known in this country, we might not be able to
                        protect your countrymen here. I told you before and I repeat it again, that
                        the President can not suspend a law of Congress; that it is his duty to
                        execute the laws, and, while I can give you no promise that the Geary law
                        will not be enforced, I can say that, owing to its terms and requirements,
                        its enforcement will necessarily be attended with some delay. I do not
                        believe the Chinese will be deported in large numbers between now and the
                        assembling of Congress, when I have reason to believe there will be further
                        legislation on the subject.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>. I am very glad to hear this. Do I
                        understand that no Chinese will be deported between now and the assembling
                        of Congress?</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary</hi>. Some may be deported, but for
                        reasons, part of <pb facs="0359" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/> which I have
                        given, they will not be deported in large numbers before then.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister.</hi> You told me that some of the harsh
                        features of the regulations of the Secretary of the Treasury for the
                        enforcement of the Geary law would be modified, and that, inasmuch as a
                        validity of that law was doubted by some, the administration would likely
                        delay efforts at enforcement until the constitutionality was passed upon by
                        the Supreme Court. I know that you were candid in that statement, because
                        the regulations of the old Secretary were materially modified, some of the
                        harshest features being omitted, and the constitutionality of the law was
                        submitted to the Supreme Court before any deportations were ordered; and I
                        believe you are now perfectly candid in your statements. On my return to the
                        legation I shall take pleasure in sending a dispatch to my Government
                        expressing my confidence that it may safely rely upon what you have
                        communicated to me to-day.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary</hi>. May I ask if in your dispatch which
                        you received from your Government yesterday anything was said upon the
                        subject of the protection of Americans in China?</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>. The dispatch stated that there was
                        nothing to justify the belief that Americans in China were now in danger,
                        and no effort would be spared for their protection should they be threatened
                        with danger.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
