<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Lincoln to Mr. Foster.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d308</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">308</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="308"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lincoln</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-02-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 7, 1893</hi>
                        </date>. (Received February 17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 910.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your instruction numbered 988, of
                    December 7, and to Mr. White’s dispatch in reply, dated the 4th of January last,
                    numbered 885, I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy of a note which I have
                    received from the Earl of Rosebery, with a series of accompanying documents
                    relative to the complaint of Capt. Kustel against Capt. Davis, of Her Majesty’s
                    ship <hi rend="italic">Royalist</hi>.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert T. Lincoln.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 910]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lord <persName type="from">Rosebery</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Lincoln</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-02-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 1, 1893</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my note to Mr. White of the
                        27th December last, I have the honor to inform you that I learn from Her
                        Majesty’s secretary of state for the colonies that he has requested the
                        Admiralty to forward to Capt. Davis for his observation the statement which
                        you communicated to me on the 22d of December relative to the conduct of
                        that officer towards Mr. Kustel, an American citizen trading in the Gilbert
                        Islands.</p>
                    <p>Fending the receipt of Capt. Davis’s reply, I take this opportunity of
                        transmitting to you for the consideration of your Government a report on Mr.
                        Kustel’s proceeding’s sent home by that officer in July last.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rosebery.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Davis</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">British Commander of naval farces in
                            Australia</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist, at Tarawa</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Gilbert Group</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 17, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on my
                        arrival at Tarawa Island, Gilbert Group, on the 7th of June, 1892, a native
                        Tabantia laid before me a complaint against one Albert Kustel, an American
                        subject, a trader on that island. Tabantia handed me a revolver and five
                        cartridges, also a letter from the Rev. A. C. Walkup, who is in charge of
                        the American mission in the Gilbert Group.</p>
                    <p>Kustel being absent in a schooner, I left a letter for him, acquainting him
                        of the charge preferred against him.</p>
                    <p>On a subsequent date, I obtained sworn evidence concerning this outrage from
                        Peter Grant, an American subject, also a trader in the same island.</p>
                    <pb facs="0418" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/>
                    <p>On arrival at Butaritari Island, on the 6th of July, I found Kustel’s
                        schooner lying there. I requested Kustel to meet me on shore at the king’s
                        house the following day in connection with this case.</p>
                    <p>I read the evidence I had taken to him. He acknowledged that the native’s
                        statement was correct except that the revolver was taken from his pocket,
                        not his hand. He also took exception to the language stated by Peter Grant
                        to have been used on the occasion, stating that it was not his habit to use
                        bad language.</p>
                    <p>I pointed out to him that although the offense had been committed before the
                        protectorate was established, the complaint had been made since. This being
                        the case I would give him the opportunity of making reparation to the
                        native. After some hesitation he offered to pay him $10. I told him I did
                        not consider that sum sufficient compensation for pointing a loaded revolver
                        at a native’s head, threatening to shoot him, and tying him up. He then said
                        he wished the matter referred to his own Government. Seeing no other course
                        open to me, I informed him I would grant his request.</p>
                    <p>As this man bears a very bad character in the group, I took the opportunity
                        to personally inform him of the British law concerning the supplying of
                        arms, etc., and intoxicating liquors to natives; at the same time warning
                        him that a repetition of such an offense as that to which he had pleaded
                        guilty would probably lead to his expulsion from the Gilbert Islands.</p>
                    <p>Calling at Tarawa on my way south, I made further inquiries concerning this
                        man, and obtained sworn depositions from his wife (a half-caste woman), from
                        the King, also from Kamudgi, the King’s son, and Mr. Meyer, a trader, which
                        prove without doubt this man’s ill doings in the island of Tarawa.</p>
                    <p>I beg to inclose papers concerning this matter; also an extract from the
                        minutes of proceedings of a court held for the trial of Eno, a trader of
                        Kustel’s.</p>
                    <p>I trust that, for the welfare of the islands over which Her Majesty has
                        assumed a protectorate, no time may be lost in this case being fully
                        reported to the United States Government.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Captain.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Walkup</persName> to <gloss
                                type="to">whom it may concern</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tarawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-11-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 19, 1891</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To whom it may concern:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Tabantia, a native of Tarawa, gave me the following testimony and showed me a
                        revolver and five shells and handkerchief:</p>
                    <p>That Capt. Kustel, a trader of Tarawa, met him on the path south of the
                        village of Ukiangang, caught him and pulled him, pointing a revolver at his
                        forehead saying, “Go to the boat.” Also tied his left hand with his
                        handkerchief and was pulling him, when he snatched the revolver and ran and
                        fired off a shell.</p>
                    <p>Peter Grant, Eno (native of Tahiti), Tabantia, a native, were with Kustel,
                        while ten Tiraki and ten Zenoi were with him.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. C. Walkup</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Missionary of A. B. C. F. M., Boston, Mass. in charge
                                of Gilbert Island work, on Morning Star.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist, at Tarawa Island</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Gilbert Group</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-06-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 7, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Tabantia, a native of Tarawa, states: About six or eight months ago, whilst
                        walking along to pick cocoanuts, Capt. Kustel came up to me and told me to
                        go to his boat. I told him I did not want to go. He caught hold of my hand
                        and told me again to go. I said, “No.” He tied his handkerchief around my
                        wrist and pointed a loaded revolver at me. I snatched it from him and ran
                        away. He has since asked me to give him back the revolver, but I would not.
                        I have it now in my possession and five cartridges which I took out of it.
                        Mr. Walkup, the missionary, told <pb facs="0419" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/>
                        me to keep it and give it to a man-of-war when one came to Tarawa. He also
                        gave me the letter which I now give you.</p>
                    <p>When Capt. Kustel tried to take me to his boat Peter Grant, a trader, and
                        Eno, a native of Tahiti, were with him.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tabantia</hi> (his x mark).</signed>
                        <lb/>Witnesses:<lb/>
                        <signed>F. St. <hi rend="smallcaps">L. Luscombe</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lieutenant</hi>.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Assistant Paymaster.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain Her Majesty’s Ship Royalist.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Davis</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Kustel</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist, at Tarawa Island</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Gilbert Group</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-06-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 8, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acquaint you that Her Majesty,
                        Victoria, Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, has assumed a protectorate
                        over the Gilbert Islands, and that it is contrary to British law that any
                        arms, ammunition, explosive substances, or intoxicating liquors be supplied
                        to natives of the Pacific Islands.</p>
                    <p>I also have to acquaint you that charges of intimidation and threatening the
                        lives of natives have been preferred against you, and it will be my duty to
                        forward these charges to the United States authorities, as I understand you
                        are an American citizen, I take this opportunity to warn you that a
                        repetition of the offenses with which you have been charged will probably
                        lead to your expulsion from the Gilbert Islands.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Captain.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tarawa Island</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-06-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 16, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Peter Grant, trader of Tarawa, having been sworn, stated:</p>
                    <p>About four months ago I was walking along the road with Kustel and Eno. We
                        met Tabantia, and Kustel tied Tabantia’s hands with his handkerchief and
                        said: “You son of a______, if you don’t come on board my ship I’ll kill
                        you.” When Kustel was about to tie up Tabantia’s hands he had a revolver in
                        his hand, which he pointed at the native’s head, and whilst he was tying
                        Tabantia’s hands the man snatched it out of his pocket and ran away and
                        fired it in the air.</p>
                    <p>“Kustel, Eno, and myself then went to my house, and the native the other
                        way.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">P. Grant.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>Witness:<signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Paymaster, R. N.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain Her Majesty’s Ship Royalist.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 7 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Davis</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Kustel</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist</hi>, <hi rend="italic">at
                                    Butaritari</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 7, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>You having this day declined to make suitable reparation to Tabantia, the
                        Tarawa native, whom, by your own admission, you assaulted on Tarawa Island,
                        about November, 1891, I shall request the commander in chief to communicate
                        with the United States Government on the subject.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Captain and one of Her Majesty’s Deputy Commissioners
                                for the Western Pacific.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0420" n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 8 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">At Tarawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 14, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Emma Kustel, wife of Albert Kustel, have been sworn, states:</p>
                    <p>I am the wife of Albert Kustel, have lived on Tarawa for about four years. I
                        saw Eno this morning; Eno trades for my husband. Everything Eno sells he
                        sells for my husband. He does not trade on his own account. Eno lives about
                        4 miles from here. He buys his own trade. My husband pays him for trading.
                        No license is being paid now for traders. When it was paid Eno’s license was
                        paid by my husband. My husband has never authorized Eno to sell firearms or
                        ammunition. All trade in firearms from this house is done by my husband. Eno
                        once bought fifty cartridges. Whatever gin Eno has brought here, he has
                        always said it has been for his own use. My husband has sold 10 rifles and
                        800 rounds of ammunition to the King’s party. My husband has sold gin to the
                        King; the first bottle he wanted was because his wife was sick, which he
                        took away and drank himself. He came again and got a second bottle from the
                            <hi rend="italic">Fleur-de-Lys</hi> (Kustel’s schooner), for which he
                        did not pay. The last bottle he got was before the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Royalist</hi> came here first.</p>
                    <p>The native Jacob signed articles on board my husband’s ship for a month, I
                        believe. After being there a week he went away to get his clothes, and then
                        did not return. The King ordered him to return, and he ran away again, and
                        the schooner went away without him.</p>
                    <p>I do not know anything of my husband’s trouble with native Tabantia, as I was
                        on board the ship at the time.</p>
                    <p>I know there was a fine on the island, agreed to by the traders, that whoever
                        sold liquor to a native should be fined $100. Ah Tong, a trader Chinaman,
                        was fined $100 for doing this. When my husband sold grog to the King, he did
                        not pay this fine. When the Chinaman was accused of selling gin it appears
                        that Kamudgi (King’s son) went to the house and demanded it for his father.
                        The Chinaman not being willing to sell it, Kamudgi took it. This is what I
                        have heard.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Emma Kustel</hi> (her x mark).</signed>
                        <lb/>Witness:<signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">George D. Twigg</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Staff
                                Surgeon.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Assistant Paymaster</hi>
                        </signed>.</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain Her Majesty’s Ship Royalist and Deputy
                                    Commissioner.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 9 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist</hi>, <hi rend="italic">at Tarawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 14, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Tenmaton, king of Tarawa, having been cautioned to speak the truth, states:
                        About three months ago I purchased about six bottles of gin from Kustel—one
                        time two bottles and one time three, for which I paid $1.50 for each bottle.
                        Kustel’s wife handed me the gin. Kustel asked for the money, which she took
                        and passed to him for payment.</p>
                    <p>I also bought one Martini-Henry rifle and one Snider rifle, for which I paid
                        $25 the first and $20 the other; and thirty rounds of ammunition. These I
                        purchased from Kustel’s wife in his house. Kustel told me to go and see them
                        and buy them. Tentickimarch and Kamudji were with me when I bought them.
                        Kunstel told Ten-tokorigi to tell me to go and fight quick, which he
                        did.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tenmaton.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>Witnesses:<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">F. St. L. Luscombe</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lieutenant</hi>.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Assistant Paymaster</hi>.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jem Macke</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Native</hi> (<hi
                                rend="italic">King’s Secretary</hi>).</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tekiatowa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Interpreter.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain and Deputy Commissioner.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 10 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royalist</hi>, <hi rend="italic">at Tarawa
                                    Island</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 14, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Kamudgi, native of Tarawa, having been cautioned to speak the truth,
                        said:</p>
                    <p>I have been on two or three occasions to Kustel’s house with the late King’s
                        wife to buy gin. I did not go inside the house, but waited until she came
                        out. I have <pb facs="0421" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/> seen her carry it to
                        the King. On one occasion she took $2 and brought away one big bottle and
                        two small bottles of gin.</p>
                    <p>On one occasion I got a revolver from Kustel’s wife; it was broken, but I
                        mended it.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tekamatie.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>Witnesses:<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">F. St. L. Luscombe</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tekiatowa</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Interpreter</hi>.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Paymaster.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain Her Majesty’s Ship Royalist, and Deputy
                                    Commissioner.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 11 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">At Tarawa</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-07-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 14, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>John Herman Edward Meyer, having been sworn, stated:</p>
                    <p>About two months ago I saw Kustel give the King of Tarawa a glass of gin,
                        which he drank. It is known throughout the island that Kustel has sold
                        spirituous liquor to the late King, the present King, and to Kamudgi, a
                        chief, son of the present King. Kustel has sold ammunition and firearms to
                        natives. About six months ago he sold some Winchester rifles, with
                        ammunition, to the late King. I know Kustel sold a rifle to a native,
                        Tauginou, a few months ago, for which he had not sufficient money to pay, so
                        is now, to the best of my belief, paying in copra.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Meyer.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>Witness:<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan S. O. Grant</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Assistant Paymaster</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Before me:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Captain Her Majesty’s Ship Royalist, and Deputy
                                    Commissioner.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 12 in No. 910.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extract from minutes of proceedings of a court held on
                            July 15, 1892, on board Her Majesty’s ship Royalist, at Tarawa Island,
                            for the trial of Eno, a native of Raratonga.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>4. For that he, the said Eno, did burn down the house of Jacob, a native of
                        Tarawa.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>He admitted the truth of the charges, but said * * * with reference to fourth
                        charge, he was ordered to do it by Kustel.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. H. M. Davis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Captain.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
