<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sir Julian Paunceforte to Mr. Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d336</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">336</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="336"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d336">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Julian Paunceforte</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 31, 1893</hi>
                        </date>. (Received May 31.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your note of March 24 last,
                    copy of which I duly communicated to the Government of Canada, and to previous
                    correspondence on the subject of wrecking privileges in the Welland Canal, I
                    have the honor to inclose copy of an approved minute of council which I have
                    received from the Earl of Derby, recommending the cancellation of the order in
                    council of November 19 last, as being no longer expedient or necessary.</p>
                <pb facs="0449" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/>
                <p>Although your note of March 24, above referred to, is not mentioned in this
                    communication, I have been informed by the Governor-General of Canada by
                    telegraph that the minute is intended to cover it, and generally to close the
                    question.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Julian Pauncefote.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Certified copy of a report of a committee of the honorable
                            the privy council, approved by his excellency the Governor-General in
                            council on May 17, 1893.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The committee of council have had under consideration the annexed dispatch,
                        dated February 27, 1893, from the British minister at Washington, covering
                        an extract from the Congressional Record, No. 59, of February 25, 1893,
                        showing the amendment by the Senate of the act of May 24, 1890, which
                        amended the act of June 10, 1878, relating to reciprocal wrecking in waters
                        coterminous to the United States and Canada, such amendment being the
                        striking out of the words “the Welland Canal” from the act, words which have
                        hindered the completion of the arrangements contemplated by that act and by
                        the reciprocal Canadian act. As explained by the Hon. Senator Sherman, who
                        introduced the resolution, the privilege (the Welland Canal being so
                        omitted) is to be exercised “on the lake waters, the lakes running from Lake
                        Superior down to the mouth of the St. Lawrence,” a concession which is in
                        accord with the Canadian act.</p>
                    <p>The acting minister of railways and canals, to whom the said dispatch was
                        referred, observes that the passage of the order in council of the 19th
                        November last authorizing the exercise of wrecking privileges in the Welland
                        Canal by United States vessels was only conceded in order to meet the
                        wording of the act now amended and the urgent wishes of the U. S. Government
                        to bring its provisions into force, such exercise of privilege not being in
                        itself a desirable one from the point of view of Canadian interests.</p>
                    <p>The minister recommends, inasmuch as by the excision of the objectionable
                        words in the United States act, the difficulty appears to have now been
                        removed to the satisfaction of all parties, the cancellation of the order in
                        council of the 19th November last, above mentioned, as being no longer
                        necessary or expedient.</p>
                    <p>The minister further recommends, inasmuch as the said order in council has
                        been communicated to the U. S. Government, that a certified copy of this
                        minute be transmitted to Her Majesty’s minister at Washington for
                        communication to the U. S. Government.</p>
                    <p>The committee submit the same for your excellency’s approval.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John J. McGee</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Clerk of the Privy Council.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Julian Pauncefote</persName> to
                            Lord <persName type="to">Stanley</persName>, of Preston.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Legation</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-02-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 27, 1893</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: With reference to my dispatch No. 2 of
                        the 3d ultimo, transmitting the reply of the U. S. Government to the last
                        communication of the Dominion Government respecting wrecking privileges in
                        the waters contiguous to the two countries, I have the honor to inclose an
                        extract from the Congressional Record of the 25th instant, in which it
                        appears that the Senate have agreed to an amendment in the act of Congress
                        of June 19, 1878, relating to wrecking in coterminous waters whereby the
                        difficulty which has arisen from the inclusion of the Welland Canal in that
                        act will be removed.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Julian Pauncefote</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extract from the Congressional Record, No. 59, of February
                            25, 1893</hi>.</head>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sherman.</hi> I shall be absent from the Chamber
                        after a little while, and I ask the Senator to allow me to offer an
                        amendment. It has been shown to him.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dawes</hi>. Very well.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sherman</hi>. At the end of line 8, on page 28, I
                        move to insert:</p>
                    <p>That an act to amend an act entitled “An act to aid vessels Avrecked or
                        disabled in waters coterminous to the United States and the Dominion of
                        Canada,” approved <pb facs="0450" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/> June 19, 1878,
                        be, and is hereby, amended by striking out the words “the Welland
                        Canal.”</p>
                    <p>If Senators do not know what the amendment is, I will state it in a few
                        words. Congress passed an act authorizing aid to be given to vessels wrecked
                        or disabled in the waters coterminous to the United States and the Dominion
                        of Canada upon condition that Canada would pass the same kind of a law, so
                        that the wrecking vessels on all the lake shores and the waters of that
                        region shall go to the rescue of vessels of the other country. It was to be
                        mutual.</p>
                    <p>Canada passed the same law; but unfortunately in the law passed by our
                        Congress we included the Welland Canal, which is a canal on the Canadian
                        side, and it is found that the two acts are not exactly reciprocal.
                        Therefore the two countries, although both are willing, have not been able
                        to allow this wrecking privilege to the vessels of the different nations. I
                        have a letter here from the Secretary of State and other information on the
                        subject, but that is the whole scope of the amendment. By striking out “the
                        Welland Canal” the wrecking arrangements can be carried into execution by
                        the two countries.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cullom</hi>. On the lakes?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sherman</hi>. On the lake waters, the lakes, running
                        from Lake Superior down to the mouth of the St. Lawrence.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">McMillan</hi>. I ask the Senator if the vessel
                        interests are not entirely satisfied with the amendment he has offered?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sherman</hi>. Yes. I have here a memorial of vessel
                        interests in favor of it and urging prompt action by the Senate upon the
                        provision. It came to the Committee on Foreign Relations so late that I was
                        not able to present it in the ordinary form; but there is no doubt it is
                        considered a desirable thing by the vessel owners and by the wreckers all
                        along that immense line. The amendment should be adopted in order to relieve
                        the Department from the difficulty. It is recommended by the Secretary of
                        State.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">President pro tempore</hi>. The question is on
                        agreeing to the amendment of the Senator from Ohio (Mr. Sherman).</p>
                    <p>The amendment was agreed to.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
