<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-12-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="385" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Coombs</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo
                                Japan</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-12-17"><hi rend="italic">December 17, 1892</hi></date>. (Received
                            January 14.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 62.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith copies of
                        receipts, one from the “Chartered Bank of India, Australia, and China,”
                        showing the proceeds in yen of my draft on the Secretary of State for $350
                        United States gold, in behalf of the rescuers of the wrecked vessel <hi rend="italic">North American</hi>, and the other from the governor of
                        Tokushima Ken for my personal check for yen 520.45, being the amount of
                        proceeds of said draft. The draft had originally been drawn in favor of His
                        Imperial Japanese Majesty’s minister for foreign affairs, and had been
                        indorsed by him and made payable to the governor of Tokushima Ken. The
                        governor seemed to be in doubt as to the amount in exchange which he could
                        get and asked my assistance. I forwarded the draft to the bank, with the
                        result shown by the inclosed copy of their receipt.</p>
                    <p>The money is to go toward the purchase of bonds in Tokushima Ken, which are
                        supposed to be worth a yearly interest of about 90 yen. This will be devoted
                        to the purchasing of fishing nets and such things as will assist the
                        villagers in the pursuit of their occupation.</p>
                    <p>I explained to the governor that the United States would always be interested
                        in hearing of the disposition of this fund in a manner most beneficial to
                        those people. I was promised by the governor a copy of his report to His
                        Imperial Japanese Majesty’s minister for foreign affairs giving an account
                        of the investment of this money. When received I shall have the honor of
                        transmitting copy of this report to you.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank L. Coombs</hi></signed></closer>
                    <pb facs="0497" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 62.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Combs</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Coombs</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chartered Bank of India, Australia, and China</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Yokohama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-12-13"><hi rend="italic">December 13, 1892</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: We are in receipt of your letter of
                            this date inclosing draft for $350, proceeds of which, at 67¼, $520.45,
                            which we have credited to your account.</p>
                        <p>Yours, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. Coutts</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Agent.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 62.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-12-15"><hi rend="italic">December 15,
                                    1892</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Received from Frank L. Coombs, United States minister, check on the “One
                            Hundred and Nineteenth National Bank” at Tokyo, Japan, for 520.45 yen,
                            being the full proceeds in exchange for draft on the Secretary of State
                            of the United States, indorsed to me by Mutsu Munemitsu, His Imperial
                            Japanese Majesty’s minister for foreign affairs, for the sum of $350,
                            gold coin of the United States.</p>
                        <p>Yen 520.45.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Yoshiomi Seki</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Governor of Tokushima Ken.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>