<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="41" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Thompson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-09-11"><hi rend="italic">September 11, 1893</hi></date>.
                            (Received October 6.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 4.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith copy of
                        the proclamation of Admiral Custodio José de Mello, who is the leader of the
                        revolutionary movement now in progress.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thos. L. Thompson.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <pb facs="0156" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 4.—From the Jornal do
                                Commercio.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Admiral de Mello’s proclamation to his
                                fellow-citizens.</hi></head>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Fellow-Citizens</hi>: The revolutionary movement of
                            the 23d of November had no other object than the restoration of
                            constitutional government and the free action of the constituted powers
                            which the <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> of the 3d of November
                            destroyed, to the general consternation of the nation and especially of
                            all those who were responsible for the establishment of the republican
                            government.</p>
                        <p>The dictatorship of the 3d of November seemed to be utterly irresponsible
                            in the administration of the finances of the Republic; if, on the one
                            hand, it aroused unconfessed ambitions and less legitimate
                            self-interest, on the other it lowered the national character, making it
                            ridiculous, and gave the impression that the nation, incapable of
                            creating free institutions and of living in its own shade, would submit,
                            subdued and without protest, against an autocracy that covered us with
                            indignity and humiliation.</p>
                        <p>You are aware of the part that fell to me, determined by the events which
                            occurred in this memorable period of revolutionary operations against
                            the arbitrariness of power; I served the cause of the public welfare on
                            the 23d of November; I filled with honor as a soldier and with a
                            comprehension of my civic duties as a Brazilian the post which my
                            country had a right to exact.</p>
                        <p>And if since that day some particles of public authority descended to my
                            modest hearth, it was not from suggestion of my own, but from those of
                            political responsibility which the vicissitudes of the revolution
                            determined, creating a new state of affairs.</p>
                        <p>As long as I was in the government I tried to maintain my patriotic
                            views, sustaining, with irrefutable logic, the supremacy of the
                            constitution and submission to the laws. Not a single day passed that,
                            as minister, I was not on the alert for the advancement of public right
                            and freedom against an invasive and absorbent form of administration,
                            which, joining in its hands all the political functions of the nation,
                            all the emblems of popular sovereignty, attempted by arbitrariness and
                            transgression of power to climb all the steps of political control and
                            to annul all constitutional privileges.</p>
                        <p>Against the constitution and against the integrity of the nation itself
                            the chief of the executive power put the national army into movement at
                            will and sent it to the unfortunate States of Santa Catherina and Rio
                            Grande do Sul.</p>
                        <p>Against whom? Against outside enemies? Against foreigners? No. The
                            President of the Republic armed Brazilians; against Brazilians he raised
                            legions of so-called patriots, carrying mourning, desolation, and misery
                            to all the corners of the Republic, merely in order to satisfy his
                            personal caprice and to strengthen for the future, by terror, his iron
                            dictatorship.</p>
                        <p>Sentinel of the national treasury, as he promised to be, the chief of the
                            executive power perjured himself and deluded the nation, opening the
                            coffers of the public treasure with profane hands, and, by a political
                            system of subornation and corruption, sacrificing the authority which,
                            in an unlucky honr, the revolution of the 23d of November placed in his
                            hands.</p>
                        <p>Bankruptcy already beats at our door with all its train of horrors and
                            miseries.</p>
                        <p>Fellow-citizens: In the fatal decline of power that loses itself, the
                            Republican administration descends to every abuse. Mutilated and wounded
                            innumerable times, the constitution of the 24th of February has no
                            longer any form by which it may be recognized as the supreme law of
                            public liberties and the guaranty of citizens. Self-willed power reigns
                            everywhere.</p>
                        <p>I can not remain inactive in this fearful position of my country. The men
                            by whose actions the political events were determined can not but
                            concentrate in themselves the tendencies and the aspirations of an
                            epoch.</p>
                        <p>The nation is anxious to see itself freed from a government that degrades
                            it; the time is therefore come for the reconquest of rights that were
                            suppressed and trampled underfoot.</p>
                        <p>In the life of nations, as in that of individuals, there are moments for
                            decisive action.</p>
                        <p>To struggle not to see our country degraded and thrown down; to fight for
                            the principles of liberty, which human honor sanctified as the first
                            attribute of our mind and nature; to hand down spotless to our sons the
                            name and honor of the ancestors who made free the Government of
                            Brazil—this is the position in which we find ourselves.</p>
                        <p>Officer of the navy, Brazilian and citizen of a free country, I once more
                            find myself on the field of revolutionary action to offer battle to the
                            annihilators of the constitution and to restore the rule of law, order,
                            and peace.</p>
                        <p>No suggestion of power, no wish for government, no aspiration to
                            obtaining control <pb facs="0157" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> by the
                            exercise of violent efforts on my own part induce me to enter upon this
                            revolution.</p>
                        <p>That the Brazilian nation may assume possession of its sovereignty and
                            know how to direct it within the limits of the Republic, this is my
                            desideratum, this my supreme purpose.</p>
                        <p>Long live the Brazilian nation. Long live the Republic. Long live the
                            constitution.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Custodio José de Mello</hi>.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Capital
                                        Federal</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-09-06"><hi rend="italic">6th of September,
                                    1893</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>