<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Foster to Señor Cayetano Romero.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d428</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">428</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="428"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d428">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Señor <persName
                            type="to">Cayetano Romero</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 23, 1893</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to say that I hastened to make
                    known to the Secretary of War the contents of Mr. Mariscal’s note of 31st
                    ultimo, left here by you on the 13th instant, in which were communicated certain
                    suggestions on the subject of preventing hostile incursions into Mexico from the
                    Texas border; and I now transmit a copy of a letter giving his views in the
                    matter, which, while they appear to be mainly in accord with those of your
                    Government, indicate the conditions which interfere with the adoption of the
                    proposed expedient of providing for reciprocal crossing of the frontier by
                    troops of both countries.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John W. Foster.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Elkins</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">War Department,<lb/>Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 19, 1893</hi>
                            </date>. [Received January 21.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
                        of your letter of the 13th instant inclosing for my confidential information
                        a copy of a dispatch from the minister of foreign affairs of the Republic of
                        Mexico, delivered to you by the chargé d’affaires of that Government in this
                        city, in relation to the pursuit of outlaws on the frontier, to which you
                        invite my attention, and especially to the two recommendations made by the
                        minister respecting the movement of troops, concerning which you request the
                        views of the Department at as early a date as practicable.</p>
                    <p>The communication of the minister was referred to the Major-General
                        Commanding the Army, and I invite attention to the inclosed letter from him,
                        dated the 17th instant, expressing his views on the subject, in which I
                        concur.</p>
                    <p>The suggestion relative to the disposition of the United States troops and
                        the Mexican troops on the lookout for these outlaws, the Major-General
                        Commanding the Army remarks in his letter, is a timely one, and the
                        suggestion will be conveyed from the headquarters of the Army to the
                        commanding general, Department of Texas, for his guidance.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">S. B. Elkins</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Gen. <persName type="from">Schofield</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Elkins</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters of the Army</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Washington, D. C.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 17, 1893</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the copy, furnished you by the
                        State Department, of a dispatch from the minister of foreign affairs of the
                        Republic of Mexico to the chargé d’affaires of that Government in this city,
                        and dated December 31, 1892, I have the honor to offer the following
                        suggestions:</p>
                    <p>Preventive measures have not in any country been found sufficient to always
                        prevent attempts at crime, nor always to prevent some success in such
                        attempts. It can not be hoped to accomplish even so desirable an object as
                        this always without the employment of means largely in excess of those which
                        any government has regarded itself as justifiable in employing.</p>
                    <p>Considering the physical features of the border country between the United
                        States and Mexico, and the character of a large portion of the population
                        inhabiting that country on either side of the boundary line, it is not
                        strange that the general experience of these and other nations should have
                        found no exception there, and yet the number of successful incursions from
                        the one side to the other of the Rio Grande has in fact been very small, and
                        the damage done not very great. The vigilance of the military forces of the
                        two nations on either side of the river has sufficed to <pb facs="0548"
                            n="440" xml:id="pg_440"/> make such lawless attempts very dangerous and
                        unprofitable to the criminal whose robber designs have been only thinly
                        veiled under a pretense of political purpose.</p>
                    <p>The military force employed by the United States on that frontier has been,
                        and now is, quite as large in proportion to the service required as the
                        aggregate strength of the Army will permit, and it is believed as large as
                        the international obligations of the United States require. It is believed
                        that future attempts at such lawless incursions from Texas into Mexico
                        should be deterred by the pursuit, arrest, and punishment of criminals who
                        have heretofore been engaged in such lawless acts, rather than by a large
                        military force constantly on guard along the Rio Grande, and this for
                        various reasons, among others, the manifest fact that such guarding of the
                        border would do nothing to change the character or purpose of the lawless
                        population in that part of the country on either side of the river, and
                        would make it certain that whenever any other military exigency should cause
                        the troops to be withdrawn these criminal raids into Mexico would
                        immediately be renewed without risk to the criminals. This pursuit and
                        arrest and punishment of those who have thus violated the neutrality laws of
                        the United States devolves primarily upon the civil authorities of the
                        Government, or of the State of Texas. In this work the troops can only aid
                        the United States marshals as a part of their posse.</p>
                    <p>This leads to the manifest conclusion respecting the suggestion of the
                        Mexican Government, that the troops of either country may, in pursuit of
                        lawless raiders, follow them across the river into the territory of the
                        other country. Since not even the troops of the United States can,
                        independently of the civil authority, make such pursuit in the State of
                        Texas, but must do so in aid of the marshal’s posse, far less would it be
                        possible for the troops of a foreign nation to do the same thing. Indeed, in
                        the arrangement heretofore made between the United States and Mexico for the
                        pursuit of savage Indians across the line, the stipulation was made, it is
                        believed, at the instance of the Mexican Government, that this should only
                        take place in a portion of the country which is wild, mountainous, and
                        uninhabited by civilized people. It would be manifestly impossible for
                        either country to allow the troops of the other to pursue even savage
                        Indians into a territory of the other country inhabited by citizens.</p>
                    <p>The Mexican minister makes one suggestion which I am happy to appreciate as
                        very timely, namely, that in the disposition of the United States troops on
                        the one side and of the Mexican troops on the other such concert of action
                        may be had between the commanding officers of the two forces as to double
                        the effect, by stationing the Mexican troops at one crossing and those of
                        the United States at another alternately. I will immediately convey to the
                        commanding general, Department of Texas, this suggestion for his
                        guidance.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. M. Schofield</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Major-General Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
