<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="519" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d519">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wharton</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">White</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-03-02"><hi rend="italic">March 2,
                            1893</hi>.</date></dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 64.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge your Xo. 55, February
                        13, relating to the application of Hugo Sundel for a passport, and
                        requesting instructions.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sundel avers that his certificate of naturalization, obtained in 1872,
                        was stolen in 1881, and that passport 304 was issued him by our legation at
                        St. Petersburg August 25, 1882. The inference naturally is that satisfactory
                        proof of the fact of naturalization was then made, for at that time the
                        alleged loss of the certificate had already occurred. Whatever impediment
                        the absence of the certificate of naturalization may now offer would seem to
                        have existed in 1882 with equal force. There is no record of any passport
                        being issued by the Department in 1872 or 1873, between Sundel’s
                        naturalization and departure for Europe. The Department has no record of the
                        passports issued by our legation at St. Petersburg in 1882, but the grounds
                        for issuing may perhaps be determined by the records at your legation.</p>
                    <p>The fact that Sundel lived but a short time in the United States beyond that
                        required to obtain naturalization, and that since then he has resided in the
                        country of his origin for a period of twenty years, seems to require proof
                        of <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> conservation of his American status
                        beyond his general statement of an intent to return to this country within
                        two years with the purpose of fulfilling the obligations assumed by his
                        naturalization.</p>
                    <p>Unless Hugo Sundel shows to your satisfaction that the statement of his
                        intention of returning is made in good faith and is likely to be fulfilled,
                        you may withhold the issuance of a passport to him.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William F. Wharton</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>