<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Snowden to Mr. Foster.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d546</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">546</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-01-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-01-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="546"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d546">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Snowden</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 14, 1893</hi>
                        </date>. (Received January 30.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 63.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on the
                    arrival of Commander Taylor I wrote to the Secretary of State, as promised in my
                    note of the 6th instant, informing him of the fact and requesting that he
                    indicate an early day to receive us and enter into an examination of the Ponapé
                    incident. No reply coming within a reasonable time, I requested an interview, at
                    which the minister informed me that he had been so much occupied with the
                    Morocco incident that he could not indicate a time at which he could take up the
                    case. He added that the Morocco affair was about closed, and he would give
                    immediate attention to my request.</p>
                <p>I took occasion to point out to him the very serious view taken of the Ponapé
                    incident in America, of the President’s having referred to it in his annual
                    message to Congress, and the great importance attaching to an early settlement.
                    I suggested as a preliminary to our consideration of the case, as to the injury
                    inflicted upon the persons and property of the missionaries, that his Government
                    give orders authorizing their return to the island, in which for nearly forty
                    years they had exercised their educating and Christianizing efforts. He answered
                    by saying that he feared the return of the missionaries to the island was the
                    most difficult point in the whole case, as public opinion had been inflamed by
                    the belief that their presence was the cause of the death of so many Spanish
                    officers and soldiers.</p>
                <p>I answered that national obligations must be observed in spite popular prejudice;
                    that in the case under consideration Spain has given unqualified guaranties as
                    to protecting the rights of the missionaries before and after its formal
                    occupation of the islands, and that the missionaries had given no occasion for
                    any change of policy, nor <pb facs="0671" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> for the
                    prejudice he referred to as existing against them. On the contrary, their
                    efforts had been exerted for the maintenance of peace between the natives and
                    the Spanish authorities, of which there was abundant evidence; that they were in
                    every sense entitled to their good will and kindly protection, instead of which
                    they were made to suffer the greatest injuries.</p>
                <p>I waived a further discussion at the time by saying that for his convenience I
                    would submit at our next meeting a statement giving without argument a narration
                    of events from the arrival of the missionaries at Ponapé in 1852 until the day
                    they were forced to leave.</p>
                <p>It was my intention, and I think I succeeded in impressing the minister with the
                    importance our Government attaches to an early and honorable settlement of this
                    most unfortunate incident.</p>
                <p>Unless I hear from him to-morrow I shall again request an audience, at which I
                    will present Commander Taylor and press the case with vigor.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Loudon Snowden</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
