<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bonsal to Mr.
                                Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">564</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-06-05T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-06-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="564" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d564">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bonsal</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-06-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 5, 1893</hi>
                        </date>.
                            (Received June 17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 4.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to inclose a copy in English of Mr.
                        Snowden’s note to the minister of state, in regard to his interview of May
                        27, under date of May 31, and also the reply in Spanish and English from the
                        minister of state, under date of June 2.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen Bonsal.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 4.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Snowden</persName> to
                                Señor <persName type="to">Moret</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 31,
                                1893</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: Referring to the happy results
                            arrived at on the 27th instant, in the conference I had the honor to
                            have with your excellency and his excellency the minister of Ultramar on
                            the Carolines incident, I write to say that under my instructions the
                            conclusions reached and the terms agreed upon are satisfactory to my
                            Government.</p>
                    <pb facs="0692" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/>
                    <p>In our conference it was agreed: <list>
                            <item>First. That the American missionaries are to be permitted to
                                    return to Ponapé and resume their civilizing work, under
                                    conditions that will afford protection to their persons and
                                    property.</item>
                            <item>Second. His Majesty’s Government agrees to pay to the United
                                    States the sum of seventeen thousand five hundred dollars
                                    ($17,500) in full settlement of all claims of the
                                    missionaries.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I beg your excellency will honor me with a note confirming the
                            above-named agreement entered into by the representatives of His
                            Majesty’s Government and myself as the representative of the United
                            States of America.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to assure you of the pleasure I
                            experience at the happy termination of an unfortunate and irritating
                            incident long pending between our two countries and to convey to your
                            excellency an expression of my hearty appreciation of your generous and
                            effective efforts which so largely conduced to its final adjustment.</p>
                    <p>I seize, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">a. Loudon
                            Snowden.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                            4.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Moret</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Snowden</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of
                                    State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName type="venue">
                                <hi rend="italic">Palace</hi>
                            </placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-06-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 2, 1893</hi>.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: On acknowledging receipt of your
                            excellency’s note dated May 31 last, I have the pleasure to confirm the
                            good impressions caused to your excellency by your interview with the
                            minister of the colonies and myself, which took place on the 27th of May
                            last. In said interview we in fact agreed that in consideration of the
                            delivery of $17,500 every claim presented to Spain either by the
                            Methodist missionaries who resided during the last years in the Caroline
                            Islands, or by Mr. Doane and by the United States Government would
                            finally be ended.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the return to the island of Ponapé of the above-mentioned
                            missionaries your excellency will doubtless remember that in the
                            alluded-to conference ray colleague, the minister of ultramar (the
                            colonies) insisted upon the idea that this matter was considered by him
                            entirely separated and independent from the settlement of the pending
                            disputes relating to the pecuniary indemnity. In spite of this it is my
                            duty to say that the Spanish Government never placed any obstacle to
                            said return, nor does it place any now, but it has always stated that it
                            (the Government) would consider the said return dangerous as long as the
                            authorities of that island do not give the Government the assurances
                            that it has at its disposal permanent means to guarantee their absolute
                            safety.</p>
                    <p>It is therefore definitely understood that the Government reserves the
                            right of fixing the moment when the above referred to missionaries may
                            return to the island of Ponapé, and that if they should return before
                            that moment the Spanish Government rejects all responsibility for the
                            dangers which may be run by their persons and properties.</p>
                    <p>For my part it is very gratifying to me to state also to your excellency
                            the pleasure with which his majesty the King’s Government sees the happy
                            termination of a long-pending controversy and which gave occasion for
                            unpleasant discussions between both countries.</p>
                    <p>The United States Government and your excellency, as its worthy
                            representative, have shown with this motive the friendly dispositions
                            which Spain gladly acknowledges and which tend to render more intimate
                            the intercourse with both countries.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">S. Moret.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
