<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>127. Circular Airgram From the Department of State to to All Diplomatic
                    Posts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-11-08T18:17:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-11-08T18:17:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear war</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-08T18:17:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-08T18:17:00-05:00" n="127"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                <head>127. Circular Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                    to <gloss type="to">All Diplomatic Posts</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d127fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 761.001/11-861. Confidential. Drafted by Anderson (<gloss
                            target="#t_SOV1">SOV</gloss>) on November 7; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>, <gloss target="#t_RSB1"
                        >RSB</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>; and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_GJC1">Guthrie</persName>. Repeated to Budapest,
                        Bucharest, Moscow, Prague, Sofia, and Warsaw.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-11-08T18:17:00-05:00">November 8, 1961, 6:17 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>-414. The following assessment of the 22nd
                    Congress of the <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d127fn1">October 17-31.</note> was initially prepared for
                    the presentation to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council of the
                    United States views on this event. At your discretion, you are authorized to
                    draw on it in discussions with appropriate local officials.</p>
                <p>Only time and specific developments will reveal the true significance of this
                    Congress. The following brief analysis is, therefore, only tentative.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The general course of the Congress indicated careful advance preparation;
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs dominance in Soviet
                        leadership was readily apparent in the re-endorsement of the basic lines of
                        the 20th Party Congress and in the choice of the focal points for the 22nd
                        Congress. The dominant aspects of the Congress (campaigns against the Stalin
                        era; the anti-party group, Albania and indirectly Communist China; strong
                        reaffirmation of the 20th Congress line; and the lack of emphasis on new
                        Party Program) reflect <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs
                        decision to reassert strongly Moscowʼs primacy in the bloc and the world
                        communist movement.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In foreign policy, reaffirmation was given to (a) avoidance of actions
                        entailing a serious risk of nuclear war; (b) endeavors to seek through
                        negotiations with the West agreements favorable to Soviet objectives; (c)
                        assertive Soviet efforts in the underdeveloped areas, and (d) a <pb
                            facs="0337" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/> vigorous “struggle” under
                        “peaceful coexistence” in East-West relations.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The moves against Stalinist methods, anti-party group and Albanian
                        leadership were undoubtedly related and have the effect of clarifying
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs personal leadership
                        status. The move to correct the Albanian problem was intended as a thinly
                        veiled challenge to the Chinese Communists within the context of a
                        “domestic” <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss> Congress and Soviet East
                        European considerations (Albania).</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The open attacks on Stalin and the specific revelations of the brutal acts
                        attributed to his regime have evoked public discussion within the Soviet
                        Union and are likely to result in considerable disorientation and confusion
                        of the Soviet people unless the effects are carefully channeled. These,
                        combined with public discussion in recent years of incompetence and
                        deceptive acts of minor officials, could undermine faith in the Party
                        leadership.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The form and method of the Chinese Communist response are still not
                        indicated. One timing factor supporting <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                            >Khrushchev</persName>ʼs move may have been Communist Chinaʼs basic
                        internal economic weaknesses at this time. The 22nd Congressʼ developments
                        confirmed earlier indications that the 81 Party Statement of 1960<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d127fn3">See <ref target="#d16fn1">footnote 1, Document
                            16</ref>.</note> was a “papering over” effort required by the failure to
                        achieve a real reconciliation of views.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The Party Program was obscured by other events at the Congress. Quite
                        aside from <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs desire to
                        focus attention on other matters, this treatment appears consistent with the
                        fact that the Program was not an inspiring document.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>It is too early to assess the ultimate effects of the changes in the top
                        Party organs, but <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs
                        pre-eminence has not suffered. While it is clear there is opposition to
                        individual <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> policies, there
                        is no evidence of any organized opposition to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                            >Khrushchev</persName>ʼs leadership as such. An action against the
                        anti-party group will, however, serve as a warning to those who might be
                        tempted to go too far in opposing the specific policies of <persName
                            corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The reasons for “lifting” the apparent deadline for a separate German
                        treaty were not clear.<note n="4" xml:id="d127fn4">
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> told the Congress that
                            if the West showed readiness to settle the “German problem,” then “we
                            shall not insist on the peace treaty being signed necessarily before 31
                            December 1961.” (Current Weekly Intelligence Review, October 20; Central
                            Intelligence Agency: Job 79-S01060A) <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                                >Khrushchev</persName> wrote <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                                >Kennedy</persName> in a November 9 letter that “in order to create
                            the best possible conditions for the achievement of an agreed settlement
                            the Soviet Government has decided not to insist that the peace treaty be
                            signed by the end of this year.” In the same letter <persName
                                corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> proposed, since the West had
                            taken issue with his earlier proposal to station a token force of Soviet
                            troops in West Berlin when it became a “free city,” that no Four Power
                            forces be stationed there but instead a <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                                >UN</gloss> force be introduced to guarantee the status of the city.
                            For text, see <ref target="frus1961-63v06#pg_45">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1961–1963, vol. VI, pp.
                                45</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v06#pg_57">57</ref>.</note> One
                        factor undoubtedly was the apprehension <pb facs="0338" n="310"
                            xml:id="pg_310"/> that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the
                        West were on a collision course. Another factor may well have been the
                        normal evolving of a pre-negotiation position. In any event, the build-up of
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces and the firmness of the
                        West on basic principles clearly played an important role. The fact of the
                        existence of discussions with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                        afforded <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> the opportunity
                        to lift the deadline without an apparent loss of face.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Clearly, Soviet objectives and their determination to achieve those
                        objectives remain undiluted; however, the implications for Western policy as
                        regards intra-bloc and Sino-Soviet ramifications are not fully evident. It
                        is, however, evident that the West must anticipate a continuous application
                        of pressure on sensitive issues and, particularly, must prepare for an
                        increased communist drive in the underdeveloped areas. As regards the Berlin
                        and German problem, there is even a greater need for unity, preparedness and
                        firmness of purpose.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
