<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-01-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="141" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d141">
                    <head>141. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_TWR1" type="from">Tyler</persName>) to
                        Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d141fn0">Source: Department of State,
                            Central Files, 761.5411/1-262. Secret; Eyes Only. Drafted by Donald A.
                            Wehmeyer, Office of the Legal Advisor for European Affairs; concurred in
                            by Richard Kearney, Assistant Legal Advisor for European Affairs,
                                <persName corresp="#p_ORI1">Robert Owen</persName> (<gloss target="#t_SOV1">SOV</gloss>), and <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>; initialed by <persName corresp="#p_TWR1">Tyler</persName>; and transmitted to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> through <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-01-02">January 2,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Possible <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> Exchange</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Background:</hi></p>
                    <p>You may recall that on November 24, 1961 you sent a letter to the Attorney
                        General (Tab A) setting forth the Departmentʼs position on a possible
                        Powers-Abel exchange.<note n="1" xml:id="d141fn1"><p>Not printed. In this
                                letter <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> wrote:</p>
                            <p>“I do not believe that foreign policy considerations as such need be
                                a factor influencing the Justice determination in consultation with
                                the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> as to whether we should
                                proceed in an attempt to obtain the release of Powers in exchange
                                for the release of <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>.”</p></note></p>
                    <p>This matter has been discussed on several occasions by representatives of the
                        Department and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> with Mr.
                            <persName>Oehmann</persName>, Special Assistant to the Attorney General.
                        The various facets of the problem have been carefully explored, including
                        whether, if an exchange is agreeable from the standpoint of Justice, we
                        should try to get more than <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>
                        for <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>, i.e., whether we should try
                        to get a package including some or all of those mentioned below. While there
                        are of course Americans held in various bloc countries (Communist China,
                        North Vietnam, etc.), for practical purposes it seemed logical to limit any
                        potential “package” to the following: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Marvin Makinen, a 23 year old American student in Berlin who was
                                arrested in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> this July. He
                                was sentenced in September, 1961, <pb facs="0372" n="344" xml:id="pg_344"/> to eight years for espionage and is in prison
                                in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. A moderate amount of
                                interest and pressure on the Department has developed from Makinenʼs
                                family and friends.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Frederick Pryor, a 28 year old student in Berlin working on a
                                Ph.D. dissertation on “Communist Foreign Trade”. He made many
                                contacts in East Germany, including some with persons in ill favor
                                with the <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> regime. He
                                was arrested August 25 and detained apparently on espionage grounds.
                                A show trial is expected in January. His parents have been very
                                active on his behalf, including an extended stay in Berlin. They
                                have received a letter from “Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>” proposing an exchange. The family knows
                                nothing of the status of the Donovan-Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> channel and believe they may
                                play a leading role in a possible exchange.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Victor Pankey-Gilbert Ferrey, the two college boys who were caught
                                trying to smuggle a girl from East to West Berlin, and were
                                sentenced to two years. A moderate amount of pressure and interest
                                has been exerted through family and Congressional sources.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The possibility of a “peel off” negotiation has also been considered, i.e.,
                        ask for a 5 for 1 deal, then, if this is not acceptable, drop our asking
                        price in stages down to a straight man for man exchange.</p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has presented a strong position favoring
                        a direct <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> exchange, believing that attempting to
                        get a 5 for 1 or other combination “package” might complicate the effort to
                        extricate <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>. Their evaluation of
                        the importance of obtaining <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>ʼ
                        release has increased since their memorandum on the subject was prepared in
                        November (Tab B).<note n="2" xml:id="d141fn2">Not printed.</note></p>
                    <p>The probable adverse reaction from the families and others interested in the
                        individuals held by the Communists to a straight <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> exchange
                        was discussed at the Department of Justice and, we understand, was brought
                        specifically to the attention of the Attorney General.</p>
                    <p>The Department has now been informed that the Attorney General has decided: <list>
                            <label>1)</label>
                            <item>that he will agree to a <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>
                                exchange;</item>
                            <label>2)</label>
                            <item>that he will envisage an arrangement other than that previously
                                stipulated, i.e., that <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>
                                be back in the United States before <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> is released;</item>
                            <label>3)</label>
                            <item>that he favors a direct <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>
                                exchange, with no “strays” rung in, which he believes would create
                                complications which might ruin the operation.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>An additional factor of significance relating both to the scope of the
                        exchange as well as public reaction is that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has developed a detailed plan for handling <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName> should he be released. They would
                        like to undertake a secret operation under which the release would not be
                        disclosed for a considerable period of time and <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName> would in effect be <pb facs="0373" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> kept “under wraps” while he is debriefed and his
                        future activities arranged.</p>
                    <p>Some thought has been given to the technique of a possible approach to the
                        Soviets. Preliminary judgment in the Department of Justice, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and the Department favors using James
                        Donovan, <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>ʼs New York lawyer for
                        this purpose. The most recent letter from Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> to him<note n="3" xml:id="d141fn3">Not printed, but
                            most of this letter is published in Donovan, Strangers on a Bridge, pp.
                            367-368.</note> has remained unanswered while the decision of the
                        Attorney General on its wording was awaited. It is now believed preferable
                        to consider having Donovan go to Germany to establish direct contact with
                        Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> and her Soviet contacts and
                        seek to make arrangements. Donovan is highly regarded by <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> for this role as he has cooperated closely
                        with the Government in all matters relating to the correspondence with Mrs.
                            <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> and also has the advantage
                        of apparently having achieved considerable respect from the communist side
                        as a result of his spirited and able defense of <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>. <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has sounded him
                        out in the past few days and ascertained that he is prepared to act as
                        intermediary. It is envisaged that if it is now agreed that he will be so
                        designated he will be requested to come to Washington very soon for a
                        careful briefing.<note n="4" xml:id="d141fn4">Presumably the meeting
                            discussed ibid., pp. 371-372.</note><gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                        will finance the effort.</p>
                    <p>The principal aspect which we believe should be called to your attention
                        relates to the “package-no package” decision. We thought that if for any
                        reason you believe an effort should be made to arrange a “package” exchange
                        for <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>, that you might wish to
                        discuss the matter personally with the Attorney General and perhaps Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>. The chief advantage of a
                        package deal, as we see it, is that it would give the Administration a
                        better position vis-à-vis the families, possible Congressional inquiries,
                        and the public.</p>
                    <p>If you agree that proceeding on a direct <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName> exchange
                        is appropriate in view of the circumstances, so that State-Justice-<gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> concurrence exists on the point, we will
                        continue our separate efforts to secure the release of the other Americans
                        mentioned above. We also have asked <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> to
                        check whether the West Germans are holding any East German or Soviet agents
                        who might be “borrowed” as possible trading material for Pryor and possibly
                        Ferrey and Pankey.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d141fn5"><persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> approved
                            recommendations 1 and 3 and did not approve recommendation 2.</note></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That we proceed on basis of direct exchange of <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName> for <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName>.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>If you believe that attempt should be made to arrange a “package”
                            exchange for <persName corresp="#p_ARI1">Abel</persName>, that you speak
                            to the Attorney General and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> regarding this point.</item>
                        <pb facs="0374" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>That, subject to approval by Attorney General and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, James Donovan be authorized to act as
                            intermediary, following briefing of him as to his mission.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>