<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>179. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="179"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <head>179. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d179fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.00/4-662. Confidential.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> on April
                        9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-04-06">April 6,
                            1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Interpretation of U.S. Policy</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoli Dobrynin</persName>, Soviet
                        Ambassador</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Llewellyn E. Thompson</persName>, American
                        Ambassador to Moscow</item>
                </list>
                <p>At a luncheon conversation today <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    raised the question of the Alsop article and the stir this had caused in
                        Moscow.<note n="1" xml:id="d179fn1">“<persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                            >Kennedy</persName>ʼs Grand Strategy,” <hi rend="italic">Saturday
                            Evening Post</hi>, March 31, 1962. In this article <persName>Stewart
                            Alsop</persName>, basing his remarks on an interview with the President,
                        wrote that in some circumstances the United States might employ a first
                        strike.</note> He said they had been particularly upset about the timing of
                    the article. I explained that the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi>
                    had a lead time of, I thought, something in the neighborhood of five weeks. He
                    said he thought that surely in an article of this importance the article could
                    have been changed in order not to be related to the discussions of the Berlin
                    problem. I said I was sure that this was not possible since the Post was
                    published in millions of copies and I also felt certain that no one had really
                    considered at the time the interview was given what the situation might be at
                    the time it was published. I explained that the way these things usually work,
                    as far as I understand them, was that the President would give an interview and
                    that the text might be checked by the Presidentʼs staff in the White House, but
                    probably not by him personally.</p>
                <p>I expressed the opinion that one of our difficulties in relations between the
                    United States and the Soviet Union was their tendency to read into press stories
                    policy indications that were actually non-existent. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that he knew of the frequent and close contact the
                    President had with the press, and he was therefore inclined to take press
                    stories as much more indicative of the Presidentʼs policy than was the case with
                    President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>. I pointed out that
                    there were a great many people who talked to the press besides the President and
                    that this tendency to read Government policy implications into press stories was
                    a great mistake, since a great many press stories had absolutely no relation to
                    government policy.</p>
                <p>I said I thought there was one area in which he could greatly improve over
                    previous practice, and that was that when he was in doubt about what some press
                    story or government action meant, he should <pb facs="0432" n="404"
                        xml:id="pg_404"/> contact appropriate officials in the State Department and
                    informally get their opinions. I said that, from my observations, the Soviets
                    tended to read into instances policy implications which did not exist, and that
                    very often there was a simple explanation which our people will be glad to give
                    him. He expressed surprise that he could ask for this kind of information and
                    said he was somewhat put off by the fact that every time he called at the State
                    Department, it turned out to be a big operation with the press waiting for him
                    when he left. I explained that this was inevitable but that there was no need
                    for him to make any substantive comment and that, after a while, the press would
                    become used to this, although they would always be there in case he had
                    something to say.<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">During the luncheon conversation
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> also asked <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName>ʼs advice about contacts with the
                        Department of State, Congress, and the Cabinet and compared various aspects
                        of the Department of State and the Soviet Foreign Ministry. Memoranda of
                        these conversations are in Department of State, Central Files,
                        611.61/4-662.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
