<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="187" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                    <head>187. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d187fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>
                            Library, National Security File, National Intelligence Estimates.
                            Secret. Submitted by the Director of Central Intelligence and concurred
                            in by the U.S. Intelligence Board on May 2.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11-9-62</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-05-02">May 2,
                            1962</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">TRENDS IN SOVIET FOREIGN POLICY</p>
                    <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                    <p>To estimate probable Soviet courses of action in foreign policy over the next
                        year or so and to examine some factors affecting the Soviet outlook on
                        international politics over a longer period.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Despite attacks on the general line of Soviet foreign policy by the
                            Chinese and other Communists over the last two years or so, and despite
                            some disappointment with the results of that line on the part of the
                            Soviets <pb facs="0443" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/> themselves, we believe
                            that the general principles and tactical methods of Soviet foreign
                            policy are likely to be continued for some time to come. (Paras. 10-12,
                            43-46, 62)</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Soviet leaders retain basic confidence in their
                            ideologically-motivated belief that the Communist system is destined to
                            prevail worldwide. But the aggressive quality of their policies derived
                            from this belief will continue to be limited by their full appreciation
                            of the dangers of general nuclear war, and their unwillingness to run
                            serious risks of such a conflict. This does not mean, however, that the
                            Soviets would always estimate such risks correctly nor that they would
                            abandon vital interests to avoid them. (Paras. 13-17)</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Soviet tactics of struggle under the slogan of “peaceful coexistence”
                            rest on two basic assumptions: (a) that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs economic system will demonstrate its superiority and
                            increasingly give it a power advantage; and (b) that the “masses,” first
                            in the underdeveloped and former colonial countries but ultimately in
                            advanced Western states also, will increasingly join the Communists in
                            the struggle to overthrow the “system of Western imperialism.” (Paras.
                            25, 42-46)</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The greater stress placed by the Soviets in the last year or two on
                            wars of “national liberation” is in part a response to Chinese criticism
                            that the Soviets were magnifying the dangers of war with the West and
                            underplaying the necessary role of violence. Despite these Chinese
                            pressures, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has not given full
                            political and material support or committed its prestige to all armed
                            anti-Western movements in the underdeveloped areas. We believe that the
                            Soviets will continue to follow an opportunistic policy in this regard.
                            (Paras. 21-22)</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Although the Soviets are unlikely, as a matter of general policy, to
                            use their own forces to achieve local gains, they might do so in some
                            area adjacent to Bloc territory if they judged that the political
                            circumstances were favorable and believed that the West would not make
                            an effective military response. They would probably employ Soviet forces
                            as necessary if some Western military action on the periphery of the
                            Bloc threatened the integrity of the Bloc itself. (Para. 20)</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>We see no prospect for acceptance by the Soviets of a permanently
                            stabilized situation in Germany, which they will continue to regard as a
                            key area of struggle. While a direct challenge to the Western position
                            in Berlin proceeding from a separate “peace treaty” with East Germany
                            cannot be excluded, it seems more likely that the Soviets will continue
                            to pursue their aims by diplomatic pressure and by small unilateral
                            steps designed to whittle away the Western position and to establish the
                            de facto sovereignty of the East German regime. (Paras. 29-37)</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>It is unlikely that a change in Soviet leadership would produce any
                            major shift in the Soviet outlook or lead to policies carrying increased
                            dangers of war. However, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs present role testifies to <pb facs="0444" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> the importance of the individual leader in
                            the conduct of Soviet policy, and the man or group which succeeds him
                            may introduce significant changes in style and even in the weight
                            attached to various tactics. (Para. 63)</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Over the long run, the concept of ineradicable hostility between
                            systems may gradually come to carry less weight in determining Soviet
                            international conduct. The chances of such a long-run change depend to
                            some extent upon the strength of certain evolutionary trends within
                            Soviet society and, to a greater extent, on the impact of divisions
                            within the Communist movement. But most of all they depend on whether
                            fundamental Communist beliefs are sustained by successes in the
                            East-West struggle or, over an extended period of time, are challenged
                            by failure to achieve substantial progress in that struggle. Thus US
                            strength, maintained at an adequate deterrent level, and the
                            effectiveness of US policy, are crucial factors bearing upon this
                            possible evolution in the Soviet outlook. (Paras. 64-69)</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Even if such a tendency should emerge, however, strong national
                            aspirations would continue to sustain great East-West conflicts of
                            interest. The requirements of Soviet national security, prestige, and
                            ambition, as seen by the Soviet leaders and people, would still bring
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> into collision with the
                            interests of other states, even if communism lost all of its fanatical
                            character. The most that could be expected would be that some issues
                            would become more tractable and negotiable, particularly those which
                            were not deeply rooted in the national interests of the Soviet state.
                            (Paras. 65, 69)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">I. The Soviet Outlook</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The mood of exuberant confidence which marked the conduct of Soviet
                            foreign policy two or three years ago seems in the last year or so to
                            have sobered somewhat. In the aftermath of the Sputnik success of 1957
                            the Soviets appeared for some time to entertain expectations of early
                            advances at the expense of the West. But the promising factors which
                            spurred the Soviet mood in that period seem to have lost some of their
                            force and new complications have arisen.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>As the Soviets contrast 1962 to, say, 1958, they must recognize that
                            the significant advantage they then believed they would acquire in
                            missiles and therefore in strategic posture has failed to materialize.
                            The prospects for a settlement of the Berlin and German question in
                            accord with Soviet objectives, which probably seemed good through 1959
                            and the spring of 1960, were not realized, and the attempt to resume
                            pressure on this subject in mid-1961 brought a sharp rise in the pace of
                            the arms race. This development in turn tightened the chronic squeeze on
                            Soviet resources at a time when some domestic programs, notably in
                            agriculture, <pb facs="0445" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> in housing, and
                            in some branches of investment, were falling well short of expectations.
                            Added to these concerns, there has been since at least the spring of
                            1960 an ever sharpening crisis in relations with Communist China. This
                            development has brought confusion and uncertainty to the international
                            Communist movement, which the Soviets see as an important instrument of
                            their challenge to the West.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>This is not to say that the last year or two has been marked only by
                            disappointments. On the contrary, there have been significant successes
                            also. The Soviets have doubtless viewed the Cuban development as a gain.
                            Also they evidently believe that trends generally in Latin America and
                            in some other parts of the underdeveloped world show great promise in
                            the long term. They probably regard the “national liberation” struggles
                            in Laos and South Vietnam as progressing on the whole favorably.
                            Nevertheless, the more rapid general advance of Communist fortunes which
                            the Soviets seemed to have anticipated two or three years ago has failed
                            to materialize. Their confidence in the outlook at present, while still
                            strong, seems to have assumed a somewhat more dogged quality and to be
                            keyed to an expectation of slower advance. There has been no evidence,
                            however, of any fundamental reappraisal of policy in the light of a
                            somewhat disappointing record of events. Indeed the general principles
                            and tactical methods of Soviet foreign policy which <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> had developed earlier were
                            reaffirmed at the XXII Party Congress of late 1961.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>The visible growth of Soviet power and of Soviet influence abroad is
                            the primary factor sustaining the Sovietsʼ basic confidence. Thus the
                            Soviets feel that the present relation of forces enables them to
                            challenge the Western <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName> at
                            crisis points everywhere although they appreciate that the risks of
                            nuclear warfare impose caution on themselves as well as their opponents.
                            The US, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> now asserts,
                            must realize that the time has passed when it could have its own way in
                            the world, even in an area like Latin America; it must recognize
                                the<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs claim to be its great
                            power equal, and therefore entitled to be involved in the settlement of
                            all major international questions.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>In addition to these considerations, the Soviet outlook on foreign
                            policy is also conditioned by the ideology of Marxism-Leninism. This
                            doctrine leads the Soviet leaders to see the world movement of
                            historical forces as favorable to them, to believe that they can
                            associate all sorts of popular and national aspirations with their
                            cause, to regard the developed societies of the West as transitional and
                            destined to give way. Such an outlook contains by itself few tactical
                            prescriptions; it can be used to justify periods of waiting as well as
                            the vigorous exploitation of opportunities. But it anchors Soviet policy
                            to the premise that international politics is at bottom a clash of
                            systems which precludes any genuine, lasting accommodation with the
                            West.</item>
                        <pb facs="0446" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>Soviet doctrines, however, are not unchanging. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> has been resourceful in
                            introducing reformulations which reflect a growing awareness of the
                            dangers and complexities confronting the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> as it extends its operations in the world arena. He
                            has placed great stress, often at the cost of ideological confusion and
                            conflict, on the preventability of war, on the decisiveness of economic
                            competition, on the legitimacy of cooperation with non-Communist and
                            even anti-Communist governments. These theses are intended to permit the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to pursue its external
                            objectives with greater flexibility and sophistication. At the same
                            time, they are designed to justify policies which permit careful control
                            of military risks and accord high priority to the goal of domestic
                            economic growth.</item>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>The US occupies a special place in the Soviet outlook. The primary
                            element in the Soviet attitude is, of course, the concept of Washington
                            as the stronghold of the enemy camp. In addition, however, the Soviets
                            have great respect and even admiration for US material achievements. As
                            rulers of a nation which has newly reached the status of a superpower,
                            they greatly value any American acknowledgements of equality and,
                            conversely, are highly sensitive to any American derogation of or
                            challenge to their prestige. This factor also contributes to the
                            recurrent Soviet impulse toward bilateralism. Moscow sometimes appears
                            to be intrigued with the notion that the two greatest powers could
                            somehow combine to contain or override the interests of lesser powers.
                            But this idea, which appears out of harmony with the premise of basic
                            conflict of systems, has not been accompanied by a readiness to
                            compromise on the major issues in dispute between the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. We believe that, in the future as
                            well, this idea is more likely to affect the manner in which the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> approaches these issues, and that
                            only occasionally, than to alter the substance of its positions.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Attitudes Toward War</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>Fundamental hostility toward the non-Communist world defines one limit
                            of Soviet foreign policy; so long as it persists, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will regard international issues as
                            opportunities progressively to weaken and undermine its opponents, and
                            not as occasions for conciliation which would guard the interests of all
                            parties. The other limit, which puts a check upon this aggressiveness,
                            is the Soviet leadersʼ awareness that their own nation and system would
                            face destruction in a general nuclear war. Both their statements and
                            their actions in recent years have demonstrated their unwillingness to
                            run any considerable risks of this eventuality. This does not mean,
                            however, that they would always estimate the risks correctly, nor does
                            it mean that they would abandon interests they considered vital in order
                            to avoid grave risk of nuclear war.</item>
                        <pb facs="0447" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>The Soviet leaders evidently continue to base their military and
                            foreign policy planning on the assumption that the present overall
                            military relationship, in which each side can exert a strong deterrent
                            upon the other, will continue for some time to come. They are clearly
                            determined to maintain and improve their strong military posture. In
                            addition, they are vigorously pursuing programs of research and
                            development in advanced weapons to acquire whatever military advantage
                            they can, and they would, of course, make heavy political use of any
                            successes they achieve. It is possible that some future technological
                            breakthrough would persuade them that they had acquired a decisive
                            advantage and could therefore press the West with far more aggressive
                            policies. We do not believe, however, that the Soviets base their
                            policies upon the expectation that they will be able to achieve, within
                            the foreseeable future, a military posture which would make the
                            deliberate initiation of general war a rational decision; the Soviets
                            realize that the US is determined to maintain second-strike capabilities
                            which would visit intolerable destruction upon them. In any case their
                            policies rest on the conviction that Communist victory can be won
                            without resort to nuclear war.</item>
                        <label>19.</label>
                        <item>The overt Soviet position on limited wars is that these will grow,
                            rapidly and inevitably, into general nuclear war and are therefore also
                            to be avoided. In our view this formulation is primarily designed to
                            deter the West from the local use of force and does not mean that the
                            Soviets would themselves immediately expand any local conflict into
                            general war; rather, if at all possible they would employ political
                            means to prevent such escalation. In circumstances where they enjoyed a
                            local preponderance of power but important Western interests were at
                            stake, they would probably use that power with restraint in order not to
                            confront their opponent with the painful choice of enlarging the
                            conflict or accepting a conspicuous defeat.</item>
                        <label>20.</label>
                        <item>We believe that the Soviets are unlikely, as a matter of general
                            policy, to assume the military and political risks involved in using
                            their own forces to achieve local gains. Nevertheless, they might do so
                            in some area adjacent to Bloc territory if they judged that the West,
                            either because it was deterred by Soviet nuclear power or for some other
                            reason, would not make an effective military response. They would
                            probably employ Soviet forces as necessary if some Western military
                            action on the periphery of the Bloc threatened the integrity of the Bloc
                            itself. Even in the latter case, however, they would attempt to use
                            their forces in a way calculated to bring hostilities to a conclusion
                            short of general war. At a much lower level, they will almost certainly
                            encourage and support the use of force by pro-Communist forces when they
                            believe that a local situation is ripe for forceful exploitation and
                            that the challenge to Western interests is not <pb facs="0448" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> great enough, and their own involvement not direct
                            enough, to involve risks of a direct encounter between US and Soviet
                            forces.</item>
                        <label>21.</label>
                        <item>This estimate of Soviet views on general and local war is generally
                            consistent with the positions laid out by <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> on 6 January 1961, when he defined various
                            types of wars and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs attitude
                            toward them. On that occasion, in addition to stating Soviet opposition
                            to both world wars and local wars between states, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> distinguished a category of
                            “wars of national liberation, or popular uprisings.” Such internal wars,
                            ranging pro-Soviet or anti-Western forces against colonial or
                            pro-Western regimes, he declared to be “just” and deserving of Communist
                            support. He was carefully vague, however, in discussing the forms which
                            this support would take, and in particular he neither promised nor
                            hinted that Soviet forces would join in the fighting. It has become
                            clear in the past year that this was not a statement of intent to usher
                            in a new phase of vigorous Soviet incitement of such conflicts
                            everywhere, or of maximum military assistance to “national liberation”
                            forces.</item>
                        <label>22.</label>
                        <item>Instead, it seems likely that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs emphasis on “national liberation” warfare,
                            not a new idea at all, was intended in part to meet Chinese criticisms
                            then being made that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, by its
                            undifferentiated stress upon the need to avoid war, was in fact ruling
                            out altogether the use of force in advancing the Communist cause. This
                            charge is a major component in the Chinese attack upon the correctness
                            of Soviet policies and, therefore, upon the legitimacy of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs traditional leadership of the
                            Communist movement. It is also designed to win for China the allegiance
                            of Communists and radicals in the less developed countries, who are less
                            firmly tied to Soviet leadership than their European counterparts.
                            Despite these Chinese pressures, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has not given full political and material support or
                            committed its prestige to all armed anti-Western movements in the
                            underdeveloped areas. We believe that the Soviets will continue to
                            follow an opportunistic policy in this regard.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The Strategy of “Peaceful Coexistence”</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>23.</label>
                        <item>In the Soviet leadersʼ assessment of the forces at work in the modern
                            world, there are a host of issues, trends, and sentiments which can be
                            turned to their account. The strategy of “peaceful coexistence,” which
                            is the fruit of this assessment, is intended to focus the attention and
                            energies of Communists everywhere upon the incessant exploitation of
                            these forces. This strategy puts great stress on the virtues of
                            flexibility and expediency, and allows for a wide variety of
                            contradictory tactics, frequently pursued simultaneously. Thus military
                            intimidation goes hand in hand with championing of the peace theme,
                            bourgeois governments are courted while their local Communist opponents
                            receive Soviet support, and the Western <persName corresp="#p_PFG1">Powers</persName> are treated to promises of détente <pb facs="0449" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> while their colonies and
                            ex-colonies are urged to turn against the “imperialists” and while
                            Moscow maintains its demands for concessions on Berlin.</item>
                        <label>24.</label>
                        <item>One noteworthy tactic of this strategy is the raising periodically of
                            demands for Summit meetings. Because his success in Soviet politics has
                            depended partly on his personal qualities, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is probably prone to overestimate the effect
                            on foreign statesmen of the pressure he brings to bear in personal
                            encounter. He also believes that, at such a meeting, his Western
                            counterparts will be under greater pressure than he to avoid a “failure”
                            and will therefore be obliged to make concessions to Soviet positions.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> clearly has a
                            personal penchant for meetings with the President, which we believe
                            reflects his desire that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> shall
                            be acknowledged as Americaʼs great power equal and that he himself shall
                            personify this equality. Finally, he probably also conceives of Summit
                            meetings as a way of further entrenching his own leadership in the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the validity of his own
                            prescriptions for dealing with the West.</item>
                        <label>25.</label>
                        <item>Central to the “peaceful coexistence” strategy is the belief that time
                            is on the side of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and that,
                            without general war, the Western position can be gradually but steadily
                            eroded. This belief in turn rests in great part upon the Soviet
                            conviction that economic competition is the decisive factor in the
                            struggle of the two systems. This is the meaning of the slogan
                            emphasized so prominently at the XXII Congress, that the Soviet Party
                            “considers Communist construction in the Soviet Union as the fulfillment
                            of its international duty to the working people of all countries.” The
                            Soviet leaders expect that tangible economic successes in physical power
                            and popular well-being will prove so impressive and attractive, and so
                            disheartening to their opponents, that their own position and prospects
                            in the international arena will be steadily enhanced.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The Chinese Critique of Soviet Policy</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>26.</label>
                        <item>But this slogan, however closely it is linked in the Soviet outlook
                            with the prospects of the Communist movement, clearly implies that the
                            claims of that movement will be subordinated to the security concerns
                            and national interests of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. And
                            so it is precisely at this point, where the theses on war and economic
                            competition combine to produce the strategy of “peaceful coexistence,”
                            that the Chinese Communists have raised a fundamental dissent. They
                            perceive in this Soviet analysis a justification for denying priority to
                            courses of action which meet Chinese interests but fail to serve
                            directly the objectives of the<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. The
                            Chinese leaders see confirmation of their suspicions in a host of
                            indicators: Soviet reluctance to provide them with advanced weapon
                            capabilities, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs
                            recurrent moves toward détente and direct dealings with the Western
                            leaders, Moscowʼs stress on the disarmament issue, and its unwillingness
                            to give support to all-out tactics of militancy in all areas of <pb facs="0450" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> contention with the West.
                            Perhaps most important, the Chinese object to the Soviet leadersʼ
                            insistence upon building communism in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> first and their concomitant refusal to delay domestic
                            progress in order to bring all members of the Bloc up to the level of
                            their own country.</item>
                        <label>27.</label>
                        <item>There is some truth, we believe, in Chinese contentions, but it is an
                            old truth. Ever since its founding the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has regularly subordinated the claims of foreign
                            Communist parties to national objectives whenever a conflict arose
                            between them. The essential difference now is that, with the growth of
                            the international movement and especially with the accession of some
                            parties to state power, these claims have become more diverse and
                            urgent. In particular, China has sufficient power and independence to
                            defy Soviet discipline and to argue its case with great force.</item>
                        <label>28.</label>
                        <item>We have analyzed in a recent estimate the way in which the Soviets
                            sought at the XXII Congress, by the attacks on Stalin, Albania, and the
                            “antiparty group,” to discredit Peipingʼs policy views.<note n="1" xml:id="d187fn1">11-5-62, “Political Developments in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the Communist World,” dated
                                21 February 1962. [Footnote in the source text. <ref target="#d160">Document 160</ref>.]</note> Then and subsequently, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has reasserted its foreign policies
                            in the face of opposition within the movement and has served notice that
                            adherence to “peaceful coexistence” is a matter of Communist discipline.
                            The Chinese have nevertheless continued publicly to oppose and criticize
                            Soviet policies, making use of doctrinal arguments which find
                            considerable response among Communists who cling to the orthodoxy of an
                            earlier day. We believe that there is no longer much chance of a
                            fundamental resolution of Sino-Soviet differences, and that in the
                            continuing competition between the two the<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, despite its vigorous rebuttal of Chinese criticisms,
                            will find itself unable to ignore them entirely in framing its tactics.
                            This factor will not, in our view, cause the Soviets to run
                            significantly greater risks in East-West confrontations than they are
                            now willing to contemplate. But, depending upon the course of this
                            competition, it will exert greater or lesser pressures on the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to display militancy against the West
                            and to achieve tangible successes which demonstrate the correctness of
                            Moscowʼs policies.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">II. Soviet Policies in the Near Future</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Berlin and Germany</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>29.</label>
                        <item>The issues arising from the division of Germany remain, as they have
                            for the entire postwar period, the most critical in the whole
                            confrontation between East and West. The Soviets wish to bolster beyond
                            challenge the internal stability of the East German Satellite regime,
                            always the potential weak link in the East European system, where a
                            breakdown of Communist power could place in hazard all the regimes under
                            Soviet hegemony in that area. The concurrent Soviet offensive aim <pb facs="0451" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> is to limit the West German
                            contribution to the strength of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            and ultimately to separate the Federal Republic from its Western
                            partners. Both of these objectives have inspired the three year old
                            Soviet effort to erode the Western position in Berlin and ultimately to
                            effect a withdrawal of the allies from the city. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> believes that, if he is
                            successful, this would be a long step toward establishing the permanence
                            and stability of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and would at
                            the same time deliver a body blow to West Germanyʼs confidence in its
                            allies and, indeed, to the confidence and cohesion of the entire <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Alliance.</item>
                        <label>30.</label>
                        <item>More than three years of postponement, however, clearly signifies
                                the<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs awareness of the dangers
                            inherent in unilateral actions encroaching upon Western rights in
                            Berlin. The chief result of the stiff Soviet demands put forth again in
                            June 1961 was to provoke from the US a display of firmness and a
                            military buildup; as a consequence, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> felt obliged to undertake increased military
                            expenditures and demonstrations which in turn curbed <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs efforts to readjust
                            economic priorities in favor of the consumer. In this situation, he was
                            quick to use the subsequent US initiative for bilateral talks as a
                            pretext for withdrawing his 31 December deadline for a separate
                            treaty.</item>
                        <label>31.</label>
                        <item>In the light of this record, we think it unlikely that the Soviets are
                            resolved to bring the Berlin issue to a head in some fixed period of
                            time. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, by closing the sector
                            border, has overcome the refugee problem in a way which avoided a direct
                            infringement on essential Allied rights. Nevertheless, the building of
                            the wall has reduced only one of the urgencies in their Berlin problem,
                            and their basic objectives remain unsecured. In addition, Soviet
                            prestige, and that of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            personally has been deeply committed to demonstrable progress in this
                            question. The Soviets must fear that continued failure to advance will
                            not only hearten their Western opponents, but will also lend greater
                            weight among Communists to Chinese criticisms that the “peaceful
                            coexist-ence” strategy is a failure and in reality disguises the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs abandonment of militant struggle
                            against the West.</item>
                        <label>32.</label>
                        <item>Thus we believe that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will
                            continue its efforts to obtain at least minimal concessions through
                            negotiation. Its tactics in current diplomatic conversations and
                            periodic harassment on the access routes to West Berlin are intended to
                            serve this end. At the same time, however, other Soviet maneuvers
                            suggest an effort to broaden the scope of East-West discussions in a
                            fashion which would obscure a fundamental stalemate over the Berlin
                            question. These maneuvers are probably intended to preserve Soviet
                            flexibility while diplomatic probing of the Allied position on Berlin
                            continues. In addition, they permit the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to explore the possibilities of making gains in
                            related political areas, such as European security arrangements or
                            greater recognition for East Germany, which could for a time compensate
                            for the lack of progress toward their objectives in Berlin.</item>
                        <pb facs="0452" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                        <label>33.</label>
                        <item>We believe that, despite their hitherto essentially unyielding stand
                            on the terms of a Berlin solution, there will be some flexibility in
                            actual Soviet negotiating tactics. Among the various provisions
                            associated with the “free city” proposal, probably the demand for a
                            change in the status of West Berlin has the greatest immediate
                            importance to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. The Soviets
                            probably do not expect to obtain Western agreement to this demand,
                            however, and they are likely at some point to accept some “compromise”
                            formula. It might provide for the allies to remain in West Berlin and to
                            enjoy access to the city in exchange for undertakings which the Soviets
                            could represent as a change in the cityʼs status and some de facto
                            recognition of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. This would have
                            the additional advantage of allowing them subsequently, with minimum
                            risk, to fulfill their commitment to sign a separate peace treaty,
                            particularly if the new arrangements left open to the allies the
                            face-saving device of treating East German controllers as Soviet agents.
                            The Soviets might even accept, as part of a Berlin arrangement, some
                            form of international supervision over access, but they would seek to
                            inject the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> as fully as possible into
                            these procedures.</item>
                        <label>34.</label>
                        <item>We have regularly estimated that, if the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> reached the conclusion that the allies were unwilling
                            to grant any significant concessions in negotiations, it would proceed
                            along the road of a separate peace treaty. Repeated Soviet
                            procrastination on various pretexts, however, has demonstrated the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs extreme reluctance to take
                            this step. While we believe that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would not accompany the signing of a treaty with an
                            immediate and absolute challenge to Allied access, the Soviets would not
                            wish such a treaty to be entirely meaningless, yet its risks would
                            increase in proportion to the meaningfulness of its implementation.
                            Accordingly, there is a good chance that they will continue for some
                            months to exercise their pressures through a variety of local
                            harassments, hoping in this way to demoralize both the allies and the
                            West Berliners and thus to create more favorable conditions for later
                            negotiations. But we cannot exclude the possibility that a combination
                            of circumstances might lead the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>,
                            sometime during the next year or so, to embark on a course of major
                            unilateral steps of the kind threatened under a separate peace
                            treaty.</item>
                        <label>35.</label>
                        <item>Whatever their tactics in the period immediately ahead, we think it
                            highly unlikely that during the next few years the Soviets will come to
                            regard Berlin as an issue to be settled by a genuine and lasting
                            compromise which stops short of incorporating the western half of the
                            city into East Germany. Their objectives in this area are deeply rooted
                            in their view of Soviet security requirements: nor will they soon
                            abandon the idea that the changed relation of forces between East and
                            West has rendered West Berlin an anachronism which they need not
                            tolerate forever.</item>
                        <pb facs="0453" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/>
                        <label>36.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> intends, by demonstrating
                            the firmness of its hold upon East Germany and its ability to threaten
                            West Berlin, to stimulate doubts in the Federal Republic about the
                            validity of Bonnʼs whole foreign policy orientation. As a supplement to
                            this approach, the Soviet Government has recently stepped up its efforts
                            to urge upon German opinion the advantages of a more neutral posture.
                            The Soviets are encouraged in this effort by the recent political gains
                            of the Free Democrats and the prospects of <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>ʼs departure. They are likely to develop this
                            tactic further in the coming year.</item>
                        <label>37.</label>
                        <item>The more active policy the Soviets have lately pursued toward West
                            Germany probably reflects also their concern about the advance of the
                            Common Market and the European unity movement. They have already made it
                            clear that they regard affiliation of the European neutrals with the
                            Common Market as a threat to their interests. Their understanding of the
                            European unity movement has probably never been very clear, perhaps
                            because the phenomenon of “capitalist” states submerging national
                            interests in supranational institutions is in flat contradiction to
                            Marxist-Leninist teachings. But their misgivings about this development,
                            which they have few means to combat, are evidently real. Most of all
                            they would be prone to suspect that the Germans will come to dominate
                            “Europe” and find in it the means of power to pursue “revanchist” aims.
                            In addition, they are bound to fear the disruptive effects on their
                            inherently unstable and relatively impoverished Satellite empire of a
                            Europe growing in unity, strength, and prosperity.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Disarmament</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>38.</label>
                        <item>Soviet behavior in the disarmament field in the last year or so has
                            reinforced our earlier judgments that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs primary objectives in this area are to identify
                            itself with universal desires for peace and an end to the arms race and
                            to inhibit and discredit Western policy. Thus agitation for disarmament
                            is conceived by the Soviets as political action intended to bring about
                            alignments favorable to their interests, and also to make it difficult
                            for their opponents to employ force against Communist advances. We
                            believe that the Soviets do have an interest in reducing their present
                            and particularly their prospective military burden. The economic
                            argument for disarmament, which in the past clearly has not been
                            compelling, may acquire increasing weight if the armaments race is not
                            contained. As for the dangers of war, the Soviets still prefer to rely
                            on their own armed strength, and on the control which they intend to
                            retain over the development of crisis situations, rather than to meet
                            Western requirements for inspection and to forfeit the political
                            advantages of their great military power.</item>
                        <label>39.</label>
                        <item>We believe that, at least during the near future, Soviet activity in
                            this field will continue to aim at political exploitation and the
                            imposition of restraints upon their opponents rather than at agreements
                            on terms <pb facs="0454" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/> which the West would
                            find acceptable. Along with their advocacy of general and complete
                            disarmament, they will maintain an interest in some partial measures,
                            especially those which have a specific political import. A nuclear free
                            zone, for example, tends not only to impede Western nuclear deployment
                            and sharing, but applied to Germany has the effect of imposing a special
                            denial on the Federal Republic and weakening its military and political
                            ties with its Western partners. The Soviets will also advocate schemes
                            in the European security field which would promote the de facto
                            recognition of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and require a
                            reduction in the American military presence in Europe. They will also
                            try to make use of the disarmament negotiating process for other ends:
                            cultivating support among participating nonaligned states, establishing
                            the principle of tripartitism, and achieving direct contact with Western
                            leaders.</item>
                        <label>40.</label>
                        <item>Having completed an extensive nuclear test series last fall, the
                            Soviets are now seeking to maximize the political costs of further
                            Western testing, coupling propaganda with repeated offers to sign a test
                            ban treaty based on national detection systems. Now that the US has
                            resumed atmospheric testing, we think it certain that Soviet tests will
                            follow. At the same time, however, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will continue to agitate the test ban issue if only
                            because of the general political appeal of this question. But we do not
                            foresee any considerable movement toward Western terms in the Sovietsʼ
                            position over the next year or so. They probably consider that they have
                            a high priority requirement for further testing and in any case they
                            will almost certainly continue to resist the inspection features of
                            Western test ban proposals.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Here follow paragraphs 41-61 on future Soviet policies on the United
                        Nations, underdeveloped areas, Africa, the Middle East, Latin America, and
                        Asia and the Far East.]</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">III. Sources of Possible Long-term Change
                            in the Soviet Outlook</hi></p>
                    <p>62. In the opening section of this estimate, we have set forth certain broad
                        considerations underlying Soviet foreign policy which are likely to remain
                        generally valid for some time to come. We recognize, however, that the
                        environment in which Soviet policy is made is changing. It may therefore be
                        useful to examine three major factors—the course of developments within the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, changing relations inside the
                        Bloc and the Communist movement, and the movement of events in the East-West
                        competition—and to consider how they might in the long run affect the Soviet
                        outlook on international politics.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Internal Developments</hi></p>
                    <p>63. Within the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs removal from the scene might
                        be followed by a prolonged power struggle which could produce confusion and
                        uncertainty in foreign policy or considerable fluctuations in tactics. Apart
                        from this possibility, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs
                        present role testifies to the importance <pb facs="0455" n="427" xml:id="pg_427"/> of the individual leader in the conduct of Soviet
                        policy, and the man or group which succeeds him may introduce significant
                        changes in style and even in the weight attached to various tactics. We
                        think it certain, however, that such a leadership would appreciate, as fully
                        as does the present one, the consequences of nuclear war. Further, this
                        leadership would be unlikely to take a substantially different view either
                        of the interests of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> or of the
                        risks justified by these interests. We do not believe, therefore, that a
                        change of Soviet leadership would in itself produce any major shift in the
                        Soviet outlook or lead to policies carrying increased dangers of war.</p>
                    <p>64. Present trends suggest that, over the long run, popular aspirations are
                        likely to acquire a larger influence in Soviet domestic politics.<note n="2" xml:id="d187fn2"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11-5-62, “Political
                            Developments in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the
                            Communist World,” (paragraphs 33-37), dated 21 February 1962 for a more
                            complete discussion of this matter. [Footnote in the source
                            text.]</note> We believe that such a development would have some effect
                        on the conduct of foreign policy, but this process would almost certainly be
                        gradual and subject to setbacks. Even now the Soviet people are not
                        enthusiastically committed to all aspects of Communist ideology. In
                        particular, they are not obsessed with the idea of ineradicable and total
                        conflict, on ideological grounds, between themselves and the non-Communist
                        world. Their desire for peace and for more rapid gains in material welfare
                        is pronounced. To the extent that these attitudes become more important in
                        formulating Soviet foreign policy, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs reluctance to enter upon risky confrontations with the
                        West—especially for the sake of advancing the Communist cause in remote
                        areas—would be reinforced.</p>
                    <p>65. At the same time, the Russian people possess strong nationalist feeling.
                        They welcome and support a vigorous assertion of Soviet power on the world
                        scene in furtherance of Soviet national interest. Accordingly, we believe
                        that, even if Soviet politics come to represent popular opinion to a greater
                        degree than at present there would not necessarily be any substantial
                        lessening of international conflict. But the nature of such conflict, and
                        the atmosphere in which it took place, would change, becoming less
                        ideological and more traditional. While East-West disputes would persist,
                        there would be a better chance of the occasional recognition of areas of
                        common interest between the contending powers.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Relations in the Communist World</hi></p>
                    <p>66. Soviet control over the international Communist movement is likely to be
                        further diminished in the face of pressures for national autonomy. This
                        process, insofar as it enables individual parties to give a more national
                        cast to their policies, may increase the effectiveness of Communist
                        political appeals in some areas. This result, however, is likely to be more
                        than offset by the spectacle of policy conflicts and doctrinal argument <pb facs="0456" n="428" xml:id="pg_428"/> within the movement. These
                        consequences will tend to rob Soviet policy of the special authority which
                        it has derived from the concept of a wholly united movement based on a
                        single agreed interpretation of human society. In addition, some of the
                        Soviet energies now directed against the West may be diverted to combating
                        Chinese policies in various areas.</p>
                    <p>67. Behind these difficulties for the execution of Soviet policy, however,
                        lies the possibility of an important change in the Soviet outlook itself. If
                        the Chinese challenge produces a definitive and open Sino-Soviet break, and
                        if China subsequently progresses toward great power status and develops an
                        effective rivalry to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> as a claimant
                        to leadership of the Communist movement, the Soviet view of world politics
                        as essentially a bipolar struggle would be increasingly difficult to
                        sustain. In these circumstances, the Soviet leaders might come to feel that
                        in some matters their interests paralleled those of the West rather than
                        those of their enormous and uncontrollable neighbor.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The Course of East-West Competition</hi></p>
                    <p>68. Perhaps the most significant factor which will affect the Soviet outlook,
                        however, is the success or failure which the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs foreign policy encounters in the years to come.
                        Successes in expanding Soviet influence, major weakenings in Western
                        positions, and in particular any further advances of direct Communist rule
                        will act to confirm the Soviet leaders in their analysis of a fundamental
                        conflict of systems destined to end in their triumph. However, they have
                        already experienced difficulty in translating real gains in military power
                        into concrete political successes under conditions of nuclear stalemate. And
                        in the underdeveloped areas, it has proven far more difficult to move the
                        newer nations into a full association with Soviet policies and thence along
                        the path toward Communist control than the Soviets thought it would be when,
                        in an earlier phase, these countries were emerging from Western rule. If
                        Soviet objectives should be continually frustrated, the Soviet leaders would
                        have to reappraise the validity of some of their key doctrines. They might
                        in this case gradually relax their effort to extend communism
                            everywhere.<note n="3" xml:id="d187fn3">The <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> representative to the <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> does not concur with paragraph 68, feeling that: if
                            Soviet objectives should be continually frustrated, the Soviet leaders
                            would have to reappraise their tactics in applying some of their key
                            doctrines. They might, in this case, find it necessary to delay their
                            efforts to extend communism everywhere. [Footnote in the source
                            text.]</note> Alternatively, they might become far more aggressive in
                        order to make good on the traditional commitment to make communism a world
                        system; but, assuming that the West retained its deterrent power, this seems
                        less likely because of the greater risks such a course would involve. Thus
                        US strength, maintained at an adequate deterrent level, and <pb facs="0457" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/> the effectiveness of US policy are crucial
                        factors bearing upon this possible evolution in the Soviet outlook.</p>
                    <p>69. In sum, none of the factors discussed above portends any early or sharp
                        change in the basic Soviet outlook upon the external world. Still less do
                        they suggest that any deliberate renunciation of Marxism-Leninism, or of the
                        international movement built upon it, is likely. They do point, however, to
                        the possibility that in time—almost certainly a long time—the special
                        intensity which ideological hostility imparts to world politics may
                        diminish. Such a development would not mean that international conflicts of
                        interest ceased to exist, or even that the danger of general war was
                        appreciably reduced. On the contrary, the requirements of Soviet national
                        security, prestige, and ambition, as seen by the Soviet leaders and people,
                        would still bring the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> into collision
                        with the interests of other states, even if communism lost all of its
                        fanatical character. The most that could be expected would be that some
                        issues would become more tractable and negotiable, particularly those which
                        were not deeply rooted in the national interests of the Soviet state, and
                        that the occasional recognition of a measure of common interest between the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and its adversaries would not be
                        invariably stifled by ideological hostility.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>