<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                    <head>301. Memorandum From the Ambassador at Large (<persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1" type="from">Thompson</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d301fn0">Source: Department of State,<gloss target="#t_SAL1">S/AL</gloss> Files: Lot 67 D 2, <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> Memos. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName>. A copy was sent to <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> on March 4.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-03-02">March 2,
                            1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Incoming telegram, Moscow 2124, dated February 27, 1963<note n="1" xml:id="d301fn1">In this telegram, which was not attached to the
                                source text, the Embassy in Moscow reported three rumors that had
                                begun circulating in the past week regarding <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs status and a further
                                tightening of controls in Soviet cultural and economic fields.
                                (Ibid., Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                                    15-1<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>)</note></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>With reference to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName>ʼs
                        cable (attached), I think there is indeed some possibility that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is in some trouble at home. I
                        think it unlikely that this could be serious enough to lead to his removal,
                        although this cannot be excluded, but it is probably serious enough to mean
                        that he will have to be circumspect in his actions during the next few
                        months.</p>
                    <p>The concrete signs are few, and all of them could have other explanations;
                        for example, the mildness of his campaign speech,<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">For text of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs February 27 speech see <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Izvestia</hi>, February 28,
                            1963.</note> in the light of the vicious Chinese attack upon him. The
                        nature of the Chinese attack on him, personally, must mean one of two
                        things—either the Chinese think there is some prospect of bringing about his
                        downfall eventually, or, they think that there is no prospect whatever of
                        patching up their quarrel with the Russians. Another indicator may be the
                        steps taken by some prominent military figures recently to emphasize that
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs role in the
                            <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName> of Stalingrad was chiefly
                        that of a morale-builder, rather than a military strategist. The probable
                        explanation of this is that the military are building a backfire against the
                        possibility of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> again
                        unilaterally cutting back ground forces.</p>
                    <p>It is well to remember that throughout his Administration, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> has taken a number of bold
                        actions which although they have, in general, had broad appeal to the
                        masses, have adversely affected influential segments of the regime. Among
                        these might be mentioned those adversely affected by the abolition of the
                        machine tractor stations, military elements who resent Party control,
                        professional members of the Secret Police, the partisans of those who have
                        been purged during the <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                        era—particularly <persName corresp="#p_ZGYA1">Zhukov</persName>,
                        professional educators and members of the Soviet elite who resented the
                        educational reform, members of the Leningrad party setup who resent
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs obvious <pb facs="0668" n="640" xml:id="pg_640"/> preference for the “southerners,”
                        the members of the disbanded industrial ministries, the old-line Party
                        apparatchiki who resent both <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs internal and external policies, the
                        intellectuals who resent the continuance of Party control, the Jewish
                        community who are aware of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs anti-Semitism, the industrial managers and
                        technicians who resent the degree of responsibility given the Party for
                        managing the economy, the Stalinists in the Party who are gradually being
                        eliminated, large segments of the youth who resent the slowness in adapting
                        the regime to modern times and, probably most importantly, large numbers of
                        middle and lower Party professionals who are likely to be adversely affected
                        by the recent decision to bifurcate the Party organization into industrial
                        and agricultural committees.</p>
                    <p>In all, this makes a rather formidable group, and when viewed in the light of
                        Soviet reverses over Cuba and the split with Red China, must mean a fairly
                        high degree of dissatisfaction with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs leadership. Offsetting this, is the fact that
                        the Presidium and, to a large extent, the Central Committee are packed with
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> followers.</p>
                    <p>There was some indication in <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs campaign speech that his problems were
                        beginning to get him down when he referred to his pleasure at renewing his
                        faith by contact with the people. Probably the biggest problem facing
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is how to deal with
                        the agricultural problem and maintain Soviet goals in other fields. His
                        success or failure in dealing with this problem could well determine his
                        ability to maintain his leadership.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>