<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-09-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="358" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                    <head>358. Current Intelligence Weekly Review<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d358fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency: Job 79-S01060A.
                            The first article is Confidential; the second is Secret; No Foreign
                            Dissem; Background Use Only. Prepared by <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>ʼs Office of Current Intelligence. The source text
                            comprises pp. 3-6 of the issue.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-09-27">September 27,
                            1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Sino-Soviet Relations</hi></p>
                    <p>Moscow and Peiping are relentlessly pursuing their political warfare aimed at
                        discrediting each other and winning the allegiance of foreign parties. The
                        Chinese and Soviet parties are each apparently <pb facs="0799" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/> operating on the assumption that the conflict will be
                        protracted and inconclusive. Neither side seems to believe that the other
                        will allow itself to be provoked into some irreparable action that would
                        precipitate a complete break in party relations and possibly even diplomatic
                        ties. At the same time, each party is making strenuous efforts to place
                        itself in the strongest possible position in the event they are forced into
                        open rupture.</p>
                    <p>The Soviet leaders clearly are confident that Peipingʼs refusal to sign the
                        nuclear test ban treaty has provided them with a potent weapon in their
                        drive to discredit and isolate the Chinese Communists. The long Soviet
                        Government statement published on 21 and 22 September<note n="1" xml:id="d358fn1">For text, see <hi rend="italic">Current Digest of the
                                Soviet Press</hi>, vol. XV, No. 38, October 16, 1963, pp.
                            3-15.</note> claimed that the Chinese have suffered a “serious moral and
                        political defeat” and that their rejection of the treaty “amounts to
                        complete apostasy” from the world Communist line. The whole thrust of the
                        statement was to portray the Chinese leaders as bloodthirsty warmongers who
                        are ready to embark on irresponsible adventures. It warned that Peipingʼs
                        desire to acquire nuclear weapons causes “serious doubts concerning the
                        foreign policy aims of Chinaʼs leaders,” and charged that they are committed
                        to a “military solution of the contradictions between socialism and
                        capitalism.”</p>
                    <p>The Soviet statement replied to recent Chinese charges of Soviet subversive
                        activities in Sinkiang Province by claiming that Chinese “servicemen and
                        civilians” have “systematically violated” the Soviet frontier since 1960.
                        Moscow for the first time took notice of Peipingʼs declared intention to
                        revise or abrogate “unjust” territorial settlements imposed on China by the
                        “imperialists.” The statement warned that “artificial creation” of
                        territorial disputes would mean “embarking on a very dangerous path” and
                        strongly implied that Moscow will refuse to recognize Peipingʼs claims.</p>
                    <p>In the latest polemical exchanges both parties have gone so far as to call
                        into question each otherʼs readiness to fulfill commitments under the
                        Sino-Soviet Treaty of 1950. Peiping repeatedly has cast doubt on Soviet
                        commitments and has accused the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> of
                        “flagrant violations” of the treaty. The Soviet statement charged Peiping
                        with seeking to justify its desire to acquire nuclear weapons by denouncing
                        Moscow as an “undependable ally.” It warned the Chinese against assuming
                        that they could enjoy Soviet nuclear protection and at the same time
                        continue to attack the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. To underscore
                        this warning, Moscow quoted the Russian proverb: “Do not foul the well; you
                        may need its waters.”</p>
                    <p>The Soviet statement concluded with a pro forma appeal for a cessation of
                        polemics, but also with a thinly veiled threat of unspecified retaliatory
                        actions if Peiping persists in attacking the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. It warned that the <pb facs="0800" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/> Chinese “must clearly realize that the most resolute
                        rebuff from the Soviet party and people awaits them on this road.” Moscowʼs
                        handling of two recent frontier train incidents suggests that any future
                        Soviet reprisals may include a drastic curtailment or complete termination
                        of the Chinese training program in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. It is possible that the Russians are even contemplating a
                        complete break in economic relations along the lines of Soviet action
                        against Albania in 1961. There are also rumors in Moscow of a Soviet
                        decision to break state relations with Peiping.</p>
                    <p>A <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> article on 19 September, which blamed the
                        Chinese for the failure to settle the Sino-Indian border dispute,
                        constitutes Moscowʼs strongest and most extensive criticism to date of
                        Peipingʼs policy on this issue. In an obvious attempt to discredit China in
                        Afro-Asian eyes, <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> deplored Peipingʼs refusal to
                        “listen to the voice of reason” as embodied in the Colombo proposals of
                        December 1962 and accused the Chinese of playing into the hands of the
                        imperialists.</p>
                    <p>Peiping has shown its extreme sensitivity to Moscowʼs damaging charges that
                        the Chinese leaders are “war maniacs”—inadvertently confirmed by a fumbling
                        Chinese attempt on 1 September to “explain” Maoʼs remarks in 1957 concerning
                        the probable outcome of a nuclear conflict<note n="2" xml:id="d358fn2">A
                            reference to Maoʼs speech in Moscow, November 1957, quoted in a
                            “Statement by the Spokesman of the Chinese Government,” September 1,
                            1963, which is printed in <hi rend="italic">People of the World, Unite
                                for the Complete, Thorough, Total and Resolute Prohibition and
                                Destruction of Nuclear Weapons!</hi> (Peking, 1963), p.
                        42.</note>—by attempting to return the polemical warfare to the area in
                        which they have the better weapons. In the second major Chinese article in
                        the projected series replying to the Soviet party pronouncement of 14 July,
                        Peopleʼs Daily on 13 September adopted a disdainful, patronizing tone toward
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> and assumed the role
                        of faithful defender of Communist orthodoxy against the heretical Soviet
                        premier.</p>
                    <p>The article, which was designed to exploit the disarray and demoralization in
                        foreign parties created by <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs attacks on Stalin, was addressed primarily to
                        hard-line factions in these parties to whom Peiping looks for support. It
                        tried to show that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is
                        unworthy to head the world Communist movement and defined the ideal
                        “head-quarters of the proletariat” in terms which fit only the Chinese
                        Communist Party.</p>
                    <p>The article struck directly at <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs most vulnerable point by emphasizing that he
                        had been “particularly active” in carrying out Stalinʼs suppression of
                        Soviet “counterrevolutionaries” in the 1930s. With surpassing insolence,
                        Peiping claimed that even a majority of people in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> itself disapproved of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs attacks and “cherish” Stalinʼs
                        memory.</p>
                    <pb facs="0801" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/>
                    <p>While the Chinese strain to gain adherents outside China, there are
                        indications that the Sino-Soviet rift, added to domestic economic
                        difficulties, is creating morale problems in China. According to a report of
                        an official inquiry into popular attitudes in a county of Kwangtung
                        Province, many people are alarmed by the loss of Soviet support for
                        industrialization and are pessimistic about the future. The US consul
                        general in Hong Kong comments that this and another recent report show that
                        Peipingʼs challenge to Moscow—while appealing to Chinese xenophobia—has also
                        generated apprehension over the regimeʼs motives and possibly deepened
                        doubts about its present course. (Confidential)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Soviet Foreign Policy Outlook</hi></p>
                    <p>The dominant factor shaping Moscowʼs present foreign policy outlook appears
                        to be its desire to avoid new crisis situations with the West while dealing
                        with the increasingly bitter and damaging struggle with the Chinese
                        Communists for leadership of the Communist movement. The serious economic
                        problems facing the Soviet leaders, highlighted by the recent large-scale
                        grain purchases in the West, probably have also strengthened their interest
                        in a general improvement in Soviet-Western relations.</p>
                    <p>The moderate and “statesmanlike” tone of Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>ʼs speech to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> General Assembly on 19 September<note n="3" xml:id="d358fn3">For excerpts from the text, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1963</hi>, pp. 509-524.</note> was the
                        most recent example of Soviet efforts to encourage a détente atmosphere. He
                        urged all governments to use the favorable situation created by the test ban
                        treaty to agree on further measures to ease tension and he carefully
                        refrained from direct criticisms of US policy in such sensitive areas as
                        Cuba and Southeast Asia. He gave only perfunctory attention to the German
                        and Berlin problems and repeated <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>ʼs theme that, from the bloc viewpoint, the Berlin
                        Wall has reduced the urgency of a German peace treaty.</p>
                    <p>In keeping with longstanding Soviet “détente tactics,” <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>ʼs speech focused primarily on
                        disarmament. His proposals for a heads-of-government meeting of the
                        18-nation disarmament committee during the first half of 1964 and for a
                        US-Soviet treaty banning nuclear weapons in outer space were intended to
                        demonstrate the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>ʼs constructive
                        attitude. He also sought to underline Soviet flexibility by offering a
                        further “concession” in Moscowʼs general disarmament plan which would permit
                        the US and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to retain a limited
                        number of missiles and nuclear weapons until the end of the last stage of
                        the disarmament process.</p>
                    <p>The Soviet leaders appear to see little early prospect for further agreements
                        comparable to the test ban in importance. They are under no pressure, and
                        they remain unwilling to make concessions as the price for agreement on
                        major issues such as Berlin and Germany. They probably <pb facs="0802" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/> believe, moreover, that West German and French
                        opposition will preclude agreement on such measures as a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>-Warsaw Pact nonaggression treaty, a
                        reduction of foreign forces in the two Germanys, and a nuclear-free zone in
                        Central Europe. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, however,
                        probably hopes to draw the US and its allies into a protracted period of
                        negotiation on partial disarmament and European security matters. He would
                        calculate that such talks would intensify differences among the Western
                        allies and increase the reluctance of some <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members to proceed further with a multilateral <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nuclear force.</p>
                    <p>While the Russians see no present opportunities for advancing their aims on
                        major European questions, they apparently attach considerable importance to
                        further bilateral agreements with the US as a means of keeping alive the
                        momentum and atmosphere created by the test ban treaty. In addition to
                        Soviet interest in agreements banning nuclear weapons in outer space and
                        establishing legal principles for the peaceful uses of space, Moscow has
                        indicated a desire to conclude a consular convention and a civil air
                        transport agreement.</p>
                    <p>Although the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has termed President
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>ʼs <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> address<note n="4" xml:id="d358fn4">For excerpts from the
                            text, see ibid., pp. 525-531. For full text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">John F. Kennedy</persName>, 1963</hi>, pp.
                            693-698.</note> an “encouraging” and “sober” approach to world problems,
                        it has not yet reacted publicly to his proposal for a joint manned lunar
                        landing project. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, however,
                        told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> on 10
                        September that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> agrees in principle
                        to the US concept of joint cooperation in outer space programs. (Secret; No
                        Foreign Dissem; Background Use Only)</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>