<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-03-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="45" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                    <head>45. Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet
                            Union</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d45fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                            Files, 611.61/3-1461. Secret; Limit Distribution.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-03-14">March 14,
                            1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>G-666. Returning from my meeting with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> at Novosibirsk I had a two-hour conversation with
                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, head of the America
                        Section in the Foreign Office. I found this of considerable interest,
                        particularly in view of the fact that <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> has served in the United States and is as friendly
                        toward us as any communist official I know. I began by expressing
                        discouragement at the prospect of reaching agreement with Soviet Union on
                        major issues in view of the wide disparity between the way the two countries
                        saw the same problem. I suggested there was a double distortion in the
                        Soviet view of these issues. In the first place they saw everything through
                        the prism of Marxism and secondly, I could not help but believe that they
                        did not get an objective picture of a given situation because of the
                        tendency which had existed for years of reporting facts which tended to
                        support Soviet positions. When <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asserted that they had excellent factual
                        information, I agreed this might be true but I was convinced they did not
                        understand what motivated western countries.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that from his experience
                        in the United States he thought we would fall behind the Soviet Union in
                        economic development because we lack a goal. The Soviet people have the goal
                        of overtaking the United States and are prepared to sacrifice and work hard
                        for this. In his opinion this was far more effective than in the US where
                        many people are satisfied with what they have and see no reason to strain
                        themselves to increase production. I agreed that there was something in this
                        thesis. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> went on to observe
                        that when the Soviets achieve their goal of overtaking us this would have a
                        major effect upon the standing of our two countries in the rest of the
                        world. He said the US was a rich country and therefore all less developed
                        countries looked to us for assistance and this gave us great influence. In
                        the future it would be the Soviet Union to which they would turn.</p>
                    <p>Latin America having come up in this connection, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said he thought we had made every possible mistake
                        in dealing with <persName corresp="#p_CF1">Castro</persName>ʼs Cuba.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CF1">Castro</persName> had made overtures toward
                        us which had been rejected, he had visited the US and had received what
                        amounted to a rebuff, and each move we made to punish him was met by a
                        counter-move on his part. I suggested that the opposite was true in that we
                        had been most patient and had finally broken relations when virtually forced
                        to do so by <persName corresp="#p_CF1">Castro</persName>. I referred also to
                        his dictatorial moves in dismissing most of the judiciary <pb facs="0127" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> and in arbitrarily executing hundreds of honest
                        Cubans. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that bloodshed
                        was of course deplorable. He pointed out that Lenin had wished to avoid it
                        in the Soviet Union but was obliged to resort to terror in order to deal
                        with counter-revolution.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> discussed the Laos situation
                        and our efforts to curtail the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> agenda,
                        which I have already reported.<note n="1" xml:id="d45fn1">See <ref target="#d34">Document 34</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>In this connection I urged that at any time there was doubt about our
                        intentions or our policies, they should ask us frankly rather than guess. He
                        admitted that there were frequent misunderstandings. I pointed out that the
                        removal of such misunderstandings was one of the principal reasons for the
                        current approach to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Discussing the Congo, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said he
                        thought our policy was influenced by our commercial interests there. I said
                        I was sure this was not the case and thought we had very little commercial
                        interest in that country. He mentioned diamond interests and oil companies.
                        I said that we had important interests in some of the newly-established
                        African countries but I thought that the Congo had been dominated
                        commercially by the Belgians and I was not aware of any important tie-up
                        with American industry. In any event I could assure him that there were no
                        commercial interests in a position to influence US policy decisions. (This
                        seems to me a good example of the Marxist slant which Soviets give to every
                        problem.)</p>
                    <p>I was struck by the extent to which <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> is convinced that the Soviet Union will achieve its
                        goals and that democratic capitalism is doomed.</p>
                    <p>In the course of the discussion <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked for my opinion of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMA1">Menshikov</persName>. I did not consider it expedient
                        to answer this directly. I referred however to his intense activity in
                        buttonholing various American public figures and by other indirect remarks
                        indicated that I did not think he had been very successful. Later on I had
                        occasion to remark that the type of official who in my opinion would succeed
                        in the US was <persName corresp="#p_KVV1">Kuznetsov</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> remarked “A number of us in the
                        Foreign Ministry would agree with you.”</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1"><hi rend="strong">Thompson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>