<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="68" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                    <head>68. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>The opening of the International Conference on Laos in Geneva, scheduled for
                        May 12, 1961, was postponed in order to resolve a dispute between the West
                        and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> on the seating of Laotian
                        delegations. In telegram <gloss target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 118 to the
                        Department of State, May 14, Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> reported that Soviet Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> continued his insistence that the
                        Pathet Lao delegation be one of the three Laotian delegations seated.
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> did agree, however, to a
                        statement that all three were delegations “from” and not “of” Laos.
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> recommended that the United
                        States agree to the opening of the conference on that basis, though taking
                        every opportunity to make clear that the U.S. considered the Royal Laotian
                        Government the only government in Laos. The conference convened on May 16.
                        For text of telegram <gloss target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 118, see <ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_193"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi>
                            1961–1963, volume XXIV, pages 193</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_195">195</ref>.</p>
                    <p>In telegram <gloss target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 164 to the Department of
                        State, May 17, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, expressed concern
                        that events were moving more rapidly in Laos than had been expected “with
                        respect to a coalition government which we will not like.” He noted that the
                        “Commies in Geneva are full of confidence and appear to be utterly relaxed
                        about achieving their goals in Laos.” Their speeches were moderate and their
                        demeanor friendly. “I find it difficult to believe that this is because they
                        want a neutral Laos as we see it.” For text, see <ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_199">ibid., pages 199</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_200">200</ref>.</p>
                    <p>In telegram Confe 65 from Geneva, May 27, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell
                            Harriman</persName>, then acting head of the U.S. delegation at the
                        Conference on Laos, decried continued Soviet stalling tactics at the
                        conference and increasingly active fighting in Laos. “Soviet maneuvers have
                        placed us in exact position we earlier declined to accept, namely, attending
                        conference before cease-fire effective.” For text, see <ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_209">ibid., pages 209</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v24#pg_210">210</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>