<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>8. Current Intelligence Weekly Review</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-01-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="reclDWPzWLFcH99Zg" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recujbZvPfRFtp7HU" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Nuclear test
                        ban</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="reclbsHvbXLer8sMP" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">On-site inspections</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-01-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="8"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                <head>8. Current Intelligence Weekly Review<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d8fn0"
                        >Source: Central Intelligence Agency: Job 79-S01060A. Top Secret; [<hi
                            rend="italic">codeword not declassified</hi>]; <gloss
                            target="#t_NOFORN1">Noforn</gloss>. Prepared by <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                            >CIA</gloss>ʼs Office of Current Intelligence. The source text comprises
                        pp. 1-3 of Part II of the issue.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-01-18">January 18, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">PART II</p>
                <p rend="center">NOTES AND COMMENTS</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">East-West Relations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> last week used propaganda charges of US
                    harassment of Soviet merchant vessels to convey the impression that the new US
                    administration is obligated to take unilateral measures to improve
                    Soviet-American relations. In a press conference in Moscow on 12 January,
                    Minister of Merchant Marine Viktor Bakayev charged that US military aircraft and
                    ships were systematically conducting “provocative actions” against Soviet
                    vessels.</p>
                <p>The main purpose of the press conference and a subsequent note to the US on 14
                        January<note n="1" xml:id="d8fn1">For text of the Soviet note of January 14,
                        see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 6, 1961,
                        p. 178.</note> probably was to create an issue of a secondary nature which
                    the Soviet leaders may use to differentiate between the two US administrations.
                    Twice during his press conference Bakayev expressed hope that the “new
                    government” of the US would denounce the actions and put an end to the
                    “provocations of the American armed forces.” He said such a move would make a
                    “good contribution to the improvement of Soviet-American relations.”</p>
                <p>Bloc propaganda has also gone to some lengths on such other issues as Laos and
                    Cuba to make clear that its criticism of the US was directed at the “outgoing
                        <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> administration” and to
                    differentiate sharply between the present unsatisfactory state of
                    Soviet-American relations and Moscowʼs expectations of improved relations under
                    the new President.</p>
                <p>The bloc has also used President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>ʼs State of the Union message<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d8fn2">For text of the message, January 12, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName
                                corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>, 1960-61</hi>, pp.
                        913-930.</note> to emphasize that improvement of Soviet-American relations
                    will depend primarily on the attitude of the new US administration. A <gloss
                        target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> review described the message as an attempt to
                    “whitewash reality” and convince the new President that the present “bankrupt
                    policy” should be continued. <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> also claimed
                    that while the speech evoked no <pb facs="0054" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/>
                    interest, the inaugural address of the new President was being “awaited with
                    much interest.”</p>
                <p>Other Soviet broadcasts asserted that the change in administrations will mean a
                    change in the atmosphere of Soviet-US relations, and that statements by members
                    of the new administration already “testify to their correct understanding” of
                    important international problems. The Hungarian news service reported a press
                    editorial which presumed that the new US administration would end the
                    “dead-lock” in Western policy and resume East-West negotiations, “if not on the
                    highest level at least under conditions making possible the examination of the
                    most important international questions.”</p>
                <p>Soviet spokesmen have privately continued to stress the need for top-level talks
                    on disarmament, a nuclear test ban agreement, and the Berlin and German
                    questions. The Soviet military attaché in Turkey, obviously under instructions,
                    sought out his US counterpart and stressed the importance of an early meeting
                    between the new President and <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    and a “rapid agreement” on disarmament.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (10 lines of 2-column source text) not
                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>Bloc diplomats have also apparently inspired press reports that <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is prepared to withhold pressure for
                    immediate East-West negotiations provided the US indicates its willingness
                    eventually to discuss disarmament, a nuclear test ban, and the German question.
                    A <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> correspondent in Geneva told a reliable
                    American observer that there would be “no trouble” on Berlin “for awhile,” but
                    that eventually the question should be settled on the basis of a free city. He
                    implied, however, that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would settle
                    for a more limited agreement involving public renunciation of support for
                    refugee and émigré organizations, which Moscow would represent as a step toward
                    American recognition and acceptance of the situation in Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>This line is similar to that taken by East German party chief <persName
                        corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> in a speech to his central committee
                    meeting last month in which he listed removal of “harassing centers” and
                    renunciation of “revanchist propaganda” as two conditions which would assure a
                    “peaceful solution.” These minimum demands, however, were linked to some form of
                    recognition of East Germany.</p>
                <p>While a period of conciliatory gestures toward the US and restraint on Berlin
                    seems to be developing, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> has at
                    the same time sought to maintain a certain sense of urgency over Berlin. The
                    re-emergence of the separate peace treaty threat in private talks coincides with
                    reports from bloc sources that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    is committed to carry out this threat if he fails to obtain his objectives
                    through negotiations. In his 6 January speech<note n="3" xml:id="d8fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d13fn1">footnote 1, Document 13</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> warned that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> was fully determined to <pb facs="0055"
                        n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/> sign a separate treaty with East Germany if the
                    Western powers refused to recognize the “real situation” in Berlin and Germany.
                    He gave no indication of an immediate action, but instead pledged the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> “to continue, step by step, to bring
                    aggressive-minded imperialists to their senses.”</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> believes that since
                    the Soviet party congress—scheduled for October—follows so soon after the German
                    elections, it is unlikely that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    will await the outcome of these elections before forcing the issue of
                    Berlin.</p>
                <p>Thus, while <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> appears to have
                    disregarded his earlier deadline of April—mentioned to the West German
                    ambassador last fall—he has in effect implied a new deadline for East-West
                    negotiations before the West German elections this September; moreover, he has
                    made it clear that pressure on the West may be gradually applied if his campaign
                    for negotiations appears to be lagging.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> correspondent stressed that a nuclear
                    test ban was a more critical problem than Berlin. He hinted that when
                    negotiations resumed, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would be
                    prepared to reach a “reasonable agreement” on the issue of the number of annual
                    on-site inspections of areas where detection equipment indicated a possible
                    nuclear explosion. Thus far, the Soviet delegation at Geneva has refused to
                    negotiate the issue since proposing three inspections in the<gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> each year. The Soviets, however, have hinted
                    that their proposal is subject to amendments, but only if the Western powers
                    concede that the basis for determining the number of inspections will be an
                    arbitrary political decision rather than a scientific estimate of the probable
                    number of suspicious natural occurrences, such as earthquakes.</p>
                <p>Thus far Soviet propaganda has not commented on American press reports of the
                    special task force recommendation to the new President that nuclear test ban
                    talks and disarmament negotiations be deferred for several months.</p>
                <p>Press reports of the full text of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>ʼs 6 January speech, on the results of the Moscow
                    conference of Communist leaders, indicate that it is intended as a definitive
                    Soviet interpretation of the doctrinal and policy questions covered in the
                    Moscow declaration of 6 December. Publication of the full text of this speech
                    was delayed until 17 January, in the party journal <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kommunist</hi>. Publication at this time is probably intended to complement
                    an expected Central Committee resolution on the Moscow conference.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
