<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>81. Telegram From the Embassy in Yugoslavia to Secretary of State to
                    Secretary of State Rusk, at Paris, at Paris</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-06-02T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-06-02T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-06-02T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-06-02T09:00:00-05:00" n="81"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                <head>81. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Yugoslavia</gloss> to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName>, at
                        Paris<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d81fn0">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 611.61/5-3161. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_NIACT1"
                            >Niact</gloss>. Also sent to the Department as telegram 981, which is
                        the source text.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-06-02T15:00:00+01:00">June 2, 1961, 3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>66. Washington personal for Acting Secretary. Paris personal for Secretary.<gloss
                        target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 830, repeated Paris 5140.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d81fn1">Telegram 830, May 31, asked <persName corresp="#p_KGF1"
                            >Kennan</persName> to send the President his advice, suggestions, and
                        analysis for the meeting with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                            >Khrushchev</persName>. (Ibid., 611.61/6-261)</note> Much appreciate
                    suggestion I send President my views in connection with Vienna meeting but fear
                    there is little I can say that would be helpful. Am not informed as to
                    background <pb facs="0197" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> considerations that led to
                    arrangement of meeting at this time and am not entirely certain as to underlying
                    expectations and hopes with which we are approaching it.</p>
                <p>I do not share frequently stated view that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> needs to be personally assured at this time of our
                    determination to resist any overt encroachment that would bring into play our
                    obligation under <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or existing alliances. He is
                    well acquainted with our situation in these respects and knows that we will not
                    hesitate to react with determination if challenged in this manner. He does not,
                    I am sure, propose to offer us such challenges, if he can help it, particularly
                    such as would threaten to embroil us directly with Soviet forces. Whatever
                    pressures he may be planning to exert on US in Berlin in coming period, they are
                    not likely to be ones which, in his opinion, would present us with an overt and
                    clear challenge of this nature.</p>
                <p>It would not be useful for me to attempt to enter at this date into discussion of
                    our positions on those great questions, such as Germany, Berlin, Korea-Japan, et
                    cetera, in which Russian interests and our own are both normally involved, which
                    constitute in my view center and source of deepest tensions. On other hand, I am
                    skeptical of usefulness of any detailed discussion with <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> of peripheral situations such as
                    Laos, Cuba, and Iran. Soviet responsibility as a rule is not formally involved
                    in these situations; and where Soviet policies have contributed to their
                    exacerbation, these have been only one of many factors.</p>
                <p>It seems to me evident that decisions of eighty-one parties meeting in Moscow
                    last fall rested on agreed calculation, as between Russians and Chinese, that
                    Americaʼs world position and influence could probably be effectively shattered
                    in coming period, and the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> group
                    politically isolated by series of sharp indirect political pressures, ruthless
                    exploitation of colonial issue, and all-out propaganda attack. I think it could
                    usefully be emphasized to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> that
                    a political program founded on such calculation is not only wholly inconsistent
                    with any attempt to improve international atmosphere but could scarcely be
                    expected to achieve completion without at some point creating situations where
                    our military obligations would become involved and complications created beyond
                    anyoneʼs control. It could be justly put to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> that inflammatory and insulting language in which
                    recent Soviet statements have been cast constitutes alone a grievous disservice
                    to any efforts to improve world situation and plays directly into hands of those
                    who view with disfavor or despair the prospect of any improvement in
                    Soviet-American relations.</p>
                <p>In light of above, it seems to me general tenor of Presidentʼs approach could
                    well be that (1) basic political problems dividing us from Russians and Chinese
                    in European and East-Asian areas, outside of disarmament, are of such difficulty
                    that much time and patient preparation of public opinion would be involved
                    before any practical negotiating approach <pb facs="0198" n="170"
                        xml:id="pg_170"/> could be made to their solutions; (2) we would like to
                    start on the long task of cultivating a suitable atmosphere and climate of
                    opinion in which to tackle these questions; but (3) it is idle to attempt this
                    in face of the impressions recently created by violent Russian statements, by
                    obvious attempt to destroy United Nations Secretariat, and by equally obvious
                    effort to exploit colonial and other issues with a view to blackening American
                    image before world public, distorting American action and intentions, and sowing
                    hatred and mistrust of American people.</p>
                <p>Though aware that my views in this respect are at variance with those of many
                    prominent American students of Soviet scene within and without government, I
                    have still not seen evidence to convince me that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> is an absolute dictator of policy within the
                    Communist orbit or that he does not have to take into account views of other
                    people and parties. Do not believe that hints transmitted to us from time to
                    time along this line (most recently to me personally by Soviet Ambassador here,
                    yesterday) are wholly without substance. I think <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> has, for various reasons, a greater interest in
                    relaxation of tensions between Russia and the West than have his Chinese allies;
                    that it was not without inner hesitations and conflicts that he was led last
                    fall to accept the aggressive Chinese line on spreading of socialism by means
                    short of all-out war; and that he could well use some help from outside in
                    arguing for a somewhat more moderate and prudent course on part of communist
                    parties. For this reason, I hope his personal position, and possible effects of
                    Vienna talks on it, will not be left out of our consideration as we plan our
                    approach to the meeting.</p>
                <p>From the particular vantage point of Belgrade, it is evident that noncommitted
                    world now stand at very crucial parting of the ways. If some relaxation of
                    over-all world tensions is not achieved, it seems to me very likely that there
                    will be serious split between that group of unaligned nations which is violently
                    anti-Western and anti-American and that which would like to preserve decent
                    relations with the West. This issue may be at stake in forthcoming Cairo
                    meeting. To extent that Vienna meeting creates impression of improvement of
                    Soviet-Western relations, Yugoslavia, whose influence together with that of
                        Nehru<note n="2" xml:id="d81fn2">Jawaharlal Nehru, Prime Minister of
                        India.</note> may be decisive in determining trends within the nonaligned
                    group, will be cautioned against association with anti-Western tendencies. If,
                    however, no improvement in East-West relations is achieved at this time,
                    position of Yugoslavia and other neutrals may be expected to become more
                    difficult; and in this case, as things now stand, there would be small hope of
                    drawing this country generally to the pro-Western camp.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kennan</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
