<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-14T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-14T19:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">845.00/11–1047: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-14T19:00:00-05:00">November 14, 1947—7 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>751. Convey substance following Bajpai (<gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 1036 Nov 10): When original <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> request planes referred President
                                he expressed sympathy <pb facs="0190" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/> but
                                stipulated planes could only be provided in response joint <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>
                                request. Considerations which led President make this stipulation
                                still exist, and US Govt regrets it cannot act on request one
                                Dominion for planes to be used interdominion flights. Moreover,
                                while US Govt recognizes protection and movement refugees still
                                present great problems both Dominions, <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> efforts
                                protect refugees have largely eliminated imminent mortal danger
                                refugees which prevailed early Oct and which was then primary factor
                                in leading US Govt give sympathetic consideration provision its
                                planes.</p>
                            <p>Following for your info only. In view President’s stipulation, Dept
                                would have to refer matter White House again to obtain authority act
                                on request from <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> only. Dept does
                                not feel justified do this or press Air Force provide planes now for
                                following reasons. (1) Improvement refugee situation noted above.
                                Dept fully aware continuing potential danger but doubts that US aid
                                on practicable scale would remove danger. (2) Karachi tel 158 Oct
                                    30<note n="1" xml:id="d116fn1">Not printed.</note> reported
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> had moved 8000 non-Muslim
                                refugees from <gloss target="#t_NWFP1">NWFP</gloss> by rail. Hence,
                                refugee group of primary concern <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                                apparently can be moved without planes. (3) <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> obviously not enthusiastic about US planes as Lewis
                                never approached, and <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> made
                                special effort move <gloss target="#t_NWFP1">NWFP</gloss> group by
                                rail. (4) <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> has obtained more than
                                ten planes originally requested US from other sources including
                                    <gloss target="#t_BOAC1">BOAC</gloss> and internal airlines,
                                although planes from latter source appear have been used for
                                movement troops and military supplies to Kashmir and not for
                                refugees. (5) Provision US planes at present obviously would not
                                contribute improvement <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> relations which as you point out
                                have so deteriorated that relatively small US gesture would be
                                ineffective. As you are aware, Dept from outset emphasized view that
                                primary justification for and objective of provision US planes was
                                closer <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> cooperation.</p>
                            <p>Dept appreciates and has carefully considered Emb point of view this
                                matter but feels factors enumerated foregoing paragraph impel
                                negative response <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> request.</p>
                            <p>Sent Delhi 751 Rptd London 4852 and Karachi 179 Karachi pass to
                                Lahore.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>