<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum Prepared for the Use of the Under Secretary of
                        State for Economic Affairs (Clayton)
                        An early draft of this memorandum was prepared in Mr. Acheson’s morning
                            meeting of June 5, 1947. A revision of the above dated June 9, 1947,
                            bears the following notation: “Mr. Secretary: The attached memorandum
                            contains suggestions as to the line it would be advisable for Mr.
                            Clayton to take in discussing with representatives of European
                            Governments the question of further American aid to Europe.
                        “This memorandum has been concurred in by Mr. Acheson and Mr.
                            Lovett.—George F. Kennan.” Secretary Marshall in a chit made the
                            following comments: “Dear Lovett: It seems to me that this statement
                            indicates too much of American cash and too little of European
                            organization, however elementary, to facilitate the European states in
                            helping themselves and in making it possible for American aid to be more
                            effective.—GCM.” Mr. Lovett, then a Special Assistant to the Secretary,
                            redrafted the memo and said: “Mr. Secretary, I have taken a crack at
                            rewriting this memo which is designed for use by Mr. Clayton as a
                            reminder of the points to be covered in any conversations he has on this
                            subject. Do the changes meet your views? The first draft is attached for
                            comparison.—L.” (Lot 64 D 563, Box 20042, 1947 Chron File)
                        The Lovett draft was revised by Secretary Marshall and this revision is
                            printed here. It bears the notation “O.K. as
                            amended G.C.M.”
                        Under Secretary Clayton arrived in London for talks with British
                            officials which began on June 24, 1947.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d143</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">143</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 64 D 563, Box 20027</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared for the Use of the Under Secretary of
                        State for Economic Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Clayton</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d143fn1">
                        <p>An early draft of this memorandum was prepared in Mr. Acheson’s morning
                            meeting of June 5, 1947. A revision of the above dated June 9, 1947,
                            bears the following notation: “Mr. Secretary: The attached memorandum
                            contains suggestions as to the line it would be advisable for Mr.
                            Clayton to take in discussing with representatives of European
                            Governments the question of further American aid to Europe.</p>
                        <p>“This memorandum has been concurred in by Mr. Acheson and Mr.
                            Lovett.—George F. Kennan.” Secretary Marshall in a chit made the
                            following comments: “Dear Lovett: It seems to me that this statement
                            indicates too much of American cash and too little of European
                            organization, however elementary, to facilitate the European states in
                            helping themselves and in making it possible for American aid to be more
                            effective.—GCM.” Mr. Lovett, then a Special Assistant to the Secretary,
                            redrafted the memo and said: “Mr. Secretary, I have taken a crack at
                            rewriting this memo which is designed for use by Mr. Clayton as a
                            reminder of the points to be covered in any conversations he has on this
                            subject. Do the changes meet your views? The first draft is attached for
                            comparison.—L.” (Lot 64 D 563, Box 20042, 1947 Chron File)</p>
                        <p>The Lovett draft was revised by Secretary Marshall and this revision is
                            printed here. It bears the notation “<hi rend="italic">O.K</hi>. as
                            amended G.C.M.”</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary Clayton arrived in London for talks with British
                            officials which began on June 24, 1947.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-01">June
                        1947</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>We Americans are deeply concerned over the production and exchange difficulties
                    which you people in Europe are experiencing.</p>
                <p>We had hoped that the outside aid which your countries have already received
                    would have sufficed, together with the facilities of the agencies which have now
                    been established for international financial assistance, to bring you to a point
                    where your import requirements could be <pb facs="0266" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/> handled on a normal commercial basis. We recognize that many of the factors
                    which have caused these hopes to be disappointed are ones which were beyond
                    anyone’s control, and that for some of the others we share a measure of
                    responsibility.</p>
                <p>We are most anxious to find out from you the causes why the various measures
                    undertaken by the European Governments themselves and the assistance furnished
                    from the United States and other non-European countries have not further
                    advanced the restoration of economic health in Europe. Only if we and you have a
                    clear understanding of the real causes of the present serious economic situation
                    of Europe can remedies to correct the situation be intelligently sought.</p>
                <p>We regard the question of the restoration of economic health in Europe as a
                    matter requiring joint consideration. Before the U.S. Government can take any
                    effective action to be of help it must know from the European Governments
                    directly concerned what measures these Governments either jointly or separately
                    have in mind in order to remove the causes of the present troubles. This is
                    particularly important because it affects the whole problem of future American
                    aid for Europe.</p>
                <p>It is generally recognized in the United States that a stable and self-supporting
                    Europe is a matter of immediate interest to the American people. Our people have
                    already demonstrated their willingness to aid Europe. But they are naturally
                    concerned that any future aid shall be productive of more effective results than
                    the aid they have extended in the past. And unless the American Congress can
                    receive some convincing reassurance on this point, we doubt that its members
                    would feel justified in making further appropriations of American money for this
                    purpose.</p>
                <p>You Europeans know your own continent and your own problems better than we ever
                    can. Furthermore, it is you who are administering the economies of Europe. For
                    these reasons we would like to have your ideas and plans as to the future course
                    of European recovery and for joint or cooperative efforts among you. It would be
                    much easier for us to consider the whole question of further American assistance
                    to Europe if you could provide us with facts and figures showing just how you
                    envisage the restoration of your economy.</p>
                <p>What we are interested in here is in learning the size and character of the
                    specific problems. What are the bottlenecks impeding recovery? What form of
                    outside help added to your internal efforts would prove most effective, and what
                    are the prospects of prompt cooperative efforts?</p>
                <p>Our people would wish to have the assurance that in facing these problems maximum
                    advantage has been taken of the possibilities for better exchange among European
                    nations. We know that this is more a <pb facs="0267" n="249" xml:id="pg_249"/>
                    question of creating export surpluses than of reducing barriers. We also
                    recognize as one of the powers occupying Germany, the importance of making
                    surpluses from that country available to the other peoples in Europe. We will
                    continue to do our best to make the US–UK zones in Germany useful and productive
                    units in any European pattern.</p>
                <p>In this connection, it would be a great help to us if any or all of you could get
                    together and give us your common views on these matters. We have no desire to
                    force on you any measures which you would not feel would be timely and useful.
                    But Americans would feel greater confidence about the effectiveness of their
                    support if there were some degree of agreement on the course of and the measures
                    required for your recovery.</p>
                <p>Many things have been said in Europe about the aims which underlie American
                    assistance to other countries and the conditions which might be attached to this
                    assistance. Most of these statements were foolish or unjust, or both. But there
                    is one condition which Americans will attach to any future aid and with good
                    reason: namely, that it should really do its work of putting the economies of
                    European countries on their feet.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
