<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="161" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d161">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 122, Box 13113</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Policy
                                        Planning Staff</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennan</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</hi>
                                        (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Thorp</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-24">June 24,
                                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>The Policy Planning Staff will require, in connection with its
                                    examination of the problems of European reconstruction, a series
                                    of brief background studies relating to certain important items
                                    of European economy. These are the items which may constitute
                                    the basis of the functional approach to problems of European
                                    recovery, now under discussion in many quarters of Europe.</p>
                                <p>The fields of European economy which I have in mind in this
                                    connection are the following: <list>
                                        <item>Coal</item>
                                        <item>Electric power</item>
                                        <item>Steel</item>
                                        <item>Agriculture</item>
                                        <item>Food</item>
                                        <item>Inland transport</item>
                                        <item>Shipping and shipbuilding</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>You may think of others which should be included. The principal
                                    criterion in my mind is that they should be fields of activity
                                    which might be supposed to have key significance in Europe’s
                                    recovery and ones which would lend themselves to treatment on an
                                    overall European basis rather than a national basis.<note n="1" xml:id="d161fn1">On the previous day, a Working Group on
                                        European Reconstruction, drawn from the offices responsible
                                        to the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs,
                                        met to consider “ways and means of implementing the European
                                        Reconstruction program”. (Memorandum of June 23 Meeting, Lot
                                        122, Box 13113.)</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>Since it is impossible to draw up any common set of terms of
                                    reference for these studies, I enclose individual papers<note n="2" xml:id="d161fn2">Enclosures not printed.</note> on
                                    each of the items mentioned setting forth the points in which I
                                    am particularly interested. They will serve at least to reveal
                                    the nature of the inquiry. The persons preparing the study are
                                    welcome to add other items if they consider them pertinent to
                                    the general purpose of the inquiry.</p>
                                <p>These studies need not be exhaustive. We merely want the main
                                    outlines of the facts which bear on the situation. I am afraid
                                    that we will need the completed studies at a very early date if
                                    they are to be useful in the work which the Planning Staff now
                                    has in hand. They should, if possible, be completed by the
                                    Fourth of July weekend or, if that is simply not possible in
                                    certain instances, by July 15. But we would prefer to have brief
                                    skeleton surveys at an early date rather than long and detailed
                                    studies later. If questions of priority are involved, I am sure
                                    that Mr. Lovett will agree with me on the <pb facs="0286" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/> overriding importance of getting
                                    into the Secretary’s hands at a very early date a workable study
                                    of the main elements of the European reconstruction problem and
                                    will be prepared to support any requests we may have to make of
                                    other people for rapid action on these inquiries.</p>
                                <p>I am addressing this request to you with the feeling that you
                                    will know better than I do what can be done in the sections of
                                    the Department under your supervision and what should be farmed
                                    out elsewhere in the Department and the Government. (Presumably
                                    the food study, for example, can be farmed out at once to
                                    Agriculture.) In general, there is a virtue in spreading
                                    responsibility for this type of study as widely as possible.</p>
                                <p>Many of the questions may look so naively broad as to horrify the
                                    scholarly economist. If so, tell your people to disregard their
                                    consciences, take a deep breath, and let us have their best
                                    guess.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>G[<hi rend="smallcaps">eorge</hi>] F. K[<hi rend="smallcaps">ennan</hi>]</signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>