<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chairman of the CEEC
                        Washington Delegation (
                        Franks
                    ) to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Lovett
                    )A covering memorandum on the file copy
                        indicates that the “aide-mémoire was left with Mr.
                        Lovett by Sir Oliver Franks at their conversation on the evening of 22
                        October.”</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d262</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">262</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="262" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 122, Box 19B</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_CEEC1">CEEC</gloss>
                        Washington Delegation</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Franks</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d262fn1">A covering memorandum on the file copy
                        indicates that the “<hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> was left with Mr.
                        Lovett by Sir Oliver Franks at their conversation on the evening of 22
                        October.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Unofficial Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>When I arrived just over a week ago, you were good enough to say that we were
                    engaged upon a common endeavour and that you counted on both of us approaching
                    the problem in a spirit of frankness and in straightforward discussions. I hope
                    therefore you will regard what I have to say today in that light.</p>
                <p>I cannot too much stress that the programme which is before you now is important
                    in its political as much as in its economic aspect. The Paris Conference,
                    following so closely on Mr. Marshall’s speech, has created a new hope in men’s
                    minds in Europe. They feel that the Marshall Plan offers a last chance to
                    Western Europe to recover from the economic and political effects of the war and
                    to lead a way of life which, in its reliance on free political institutions,
                    freedom of speech, equality before the law and the value of the individual to
                    the state, is broadly similar to the way of life followed and enjoyed by the
                    people of the United States. They therefore feel that the initiative taken by
                    Mr. Marshall is, perhaps, the most important single step that any government has
                    taken since the war. For in it they see made manifest <pb facs="0465" n="447" xml:id="pg_447"/> the interest which the United States has in the solution
                    of their economic problems and in the consequent preservation of the way of life
                    they wish to continue to lead. They therefore look forward with hope and
                    confidence to working with the United States Government to achieve what they
                    believe that Government considers is a common end.</p>
                <p>The Paris Conference, furthermore, has made people in Western Europe feel that
                    they have responded successfully and in full measure to the initiative of the
                    United States Government and they are now looking to these discussions in
                    Washington as the next step in the fulfilment of this common endeavour.</p>
                <p>If this hope is to be preserved and the new spirit of a common purpose which was
                    such a feature of our work in Paris is to be kept alive, it is essential not
                    only that our present discussions should succeed, but that from them there
                    should emerge a programme which the people of Western Europe believe is likely
                    to lead to a full measure of recovery in a relatively short time. Hopes are
                    fresh and it is vital they should not be disappointed or deferred.</p>
                <p>The programme is a <hi rend="italic">recovery</hi> programme and not a programme
                    of temporary relief. It has therefore to be a large programme and the amounts
                    available under it have to be sufficient to do the job. Otherwise it loses its
                    character, becomes a further instalment of relief, and at its end the people of
                    Western Europe will be on your doorstep again. By then, however, both they and
                    you will be further disillusioned and, more importantly, Europe may have gone so
                    far down the hill that full recovery may have become impossible and the social
                    and political fabrics of Western Europe so altered and strained as to force
                    other solutions than those for which we are both working and hoping. The forging
                    of the recovery of Western Europe can only be done once and it has to be done
                    now.</p>
                <p>The programme which is now before you is not perfect and has faults and to remove
                    these faults and to work to something better is certainly desirable: but I
                    should be misleading you if I were not to say at this stage that I am a little
                    disturbed at the way the discussions of the Technical Committees have been
                    going. There seems to be a tendency in these discussions to “chip away” and the
                    risk is that the cumulative effect of this process, if it is allowed to
                    continue, would have the result that the amount the Administration might support
                    before Congress might in aggregate be sufficient only to support a relief
                    programme and not a full programme of recovery.</p>
                <p>With few exceptions, your technical people have not questioned the reasonableness
                    of the quantities of the things the programme asks for. The “chipping away”
                    process therefore can only be on availability of supplies or on the assumptions
                    we have made about their cost. In taking <pb facs="0466" n="448" xml:id="pg_448"/> a four-year period, one has got to make assumptions on both these points and,
                    in making assumptions, there is naturally plenty of room for difference of
                    opinion. Therefore, what is really important is to decide whether the
                    assumptions we have made are broadly reasonable.</p>
                <p>As far as availability is concerned, the quantities in many critical items were
                    cut in Paris below the full statement of requirements. To meet even these
                    reduced requirements would in some commodities call for some physical sacrifice
                    in the shape of exports from the United States. This may well create problems of
                    real difficulty. But if, for example, the cereals programme has radically to be
                    revised over the entire four years, the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> programme
                    may be endangered and the date at which recovery in Western Europe will be
                    complete will be seriously delayed. And no one knows how far that process can be
                    pushed without destroying the programme. Even as it is the people of Europe must
                    live to some extent on deferred hope.</p>
                <p>As for prices, I think that we have if anything been too optimistic. For example,
                    on foodstuffs, which account for 60% of the total, some of your experts have
                    told us that we have been rash in assuming that food prices will not rise during
                    the next twelve months and will fall during the last thirty-six months of the
                    programme. Already many prices have gone up substantially above the level
                    assumed in the Report. In July wheat was $2.60 a bushel. It is now $3. Fats
                    prices in the United States are now 25 % above the level taken in the
                    Report.</p>
                <p>For all these reasons, therefore, I hope that the Administration will feel able
                    to support a programme of the order of magnitude which will permit Europe to
                    move forward to recovery within something like the period contemplated in the
                    Report. I do not at all suggest that the Administration should accept the
                    precise amounts mentioned in the Report, but I do venture to suggest that the
                    size of what is recommended should not greatly differ from what the sixteen
                    countries have stated they will need. A few billions of dollars (and I am not
                    suggesting that a billion dollars is a small sum) may make all the difference
                    between success and failure. I fully realise that the combination of political
                    circumstances in this country which you mentioned to me at our first meeting
                    puts the Administration in a position of real difficulty. But this chance will
                    not occur again and I am convinced it is vital that the opportunity be seized
                    and the work begun on a scale to give it the fullest chance of success.</p>
                <p>In addition to this main point, there are three others which I would like to
                    mention to you. We have discussed them among ourselves and I feel sure that you
                    have also, but we have not yet had the occasion to talk about them together. I
                    think it is important, however, that we should lest opinion should harden before
                    we have had a chance to explore each other’s points of view.</p>
                <pb facs="0467" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/>
                <p>My first point concerns the form which aid might take. I feel sure that you must
                    have discussed whether aid should be given in the form of dollars or in the form
                    of goods. The final decision on this point must, of course, lie with the
                    Congress. But it may nonetheless be useful to give you our views. We would much
                    prefer aid in the form of dollars than in the form of commodities. There are
                    many arguments in support of this.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(i)</label>
                    <item>European recovery as planned in the Paris Report is not possible unless
                        the whole of the deficit with the Americas is covered. If aid were to be
                        limited to supplies from the United States, Europe would be forced to take
                        all steps possible to obtain the supplies and services from the rest of the
                        American Continent that are needed. These steps might well endanger the
                        actual basis upon which the European recovery programme is based. For
                        example, if the United Kingdom had no dollars with which to buy Argentine
                        wheat, it might be forced to send such extra coal as it has available for
                        export not to Europe as contemplated in the Paris Report, but to Argentina.
                        If this happened, the whole fabric of the recovery programme would begin to
                        crumble. In any case, whatever bargains were made with the rest of the
                        American Continent the full supplies needed for the recovery programme would
                        probably not be forthcoming.</item>
                    <label>(ii)</label>
                    <item>The deficit with the Americas is not made up entirely of commodities.
                        There are many items which appear for the most part among invisibles for
                        which Europe will want dollars, for example, payments for films, service of
                        American obligations, shipping disbursements, etc.</item>
                    <label>(iii)</label>
                    <item>Although aid given in terms of commodities does not necessarily imply
                        government procurement, it may tend towards this. Government procurement
                        over the whole field of the commodities which the European countries wish to
                        obtain from the United States would introduce rigidities where now there is
                        the flexibility of private trade and we cannot believe that it is in the
                        interests of either the United States or the European countries that this
                        should be so. It must be borne in mind that after the period of the
                        programme Europe will still wish to import from America and pay for
                        considerable quantities of these goods and it is surely wise that so far as
                        possible the normal trade channels should be left available.</item>
                </list>
                <p>My second point is this. It is natural that in an operation of the sort which we
                    are now discussing people should tend to think in terms of the Lend Lease
                    arrangements. I would like to suggest, however, that there are certain dangers
                    in this way of thought. The purpose of Lend Lease was to provide the Allied
                    countries with those foodstuffs, raw materials and equipment which were
                    essential to the prosecution of the war and it was natural, therefore, to attach
                    as conditions to the provision of such supplies restrictions on the use of these
                    materials in the export trade. If, however, restrictions of this sort were to be
                    imposed either on the supplies purchased with any dollars which might be made
                    available or on the use of the supplies themselves, the <pb facs="0468" n="450" xml:id="pg_450"/> purpose of the recovery programme would be frustrated for
                    it is the intention of that programme, among other things, to bring about an
                    equilibrium in Europe’s balance of payments by a greatly increased flow of
                    European exports.</p>
                <p>My final point is this. The organisation and individuals who physically receive
                    the goods and services supplied to Europe from the United States and the rest of
                    the American Continent will naturally pay for them in the local currency of
                    their own country. The United States Government may wish to impose certain
                    restrictions on the use of these funds. For example, it may wish to stipulate
                    that they be not used for financing current expenditure. Such restrictions will
                    tend to be different for each country. But the sums involved will necessarily be
                    large; it is important that the restrictions imposed on their use should not
                    interfere with or prejudice the economic and financial control of the whole
                    economy that must be exercised by the government of each country. In particular,
                    the vesting of these funds not in the government but in some independent
                    organisation might gravely impair this necessary central control.</p>
                <p>There are also serious political dangers in such restrictions. The interpretation
                    of them in the future—and a long future—may be a potential source of irritation
                    in the relations between the United States Government and the governments of the
                    participating countries. If the United States decides to support the European
                    recovery programme, it will in the nature of things have an inherent control
                    over it which it will be in a position to exercise without resort to mechanical
                    devices that might cause the irritation mentioned above.</p>
                <p> , .</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-22">22nd October,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                    <signed>O. S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Franks</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
