<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The French Embassy to the Department of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d405</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">405</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-07-07T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="405" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d405">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.504/7–747</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">French Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-07">July 7,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Embassy of France has the honor to refer to its note No. 164 of May 7 and its
                        <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of June 16 and 18.<note n="1" xml:id="d405fn1">Neither printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>During the past months, the French Government has spared no pains in scrupulously
                    carrying out the agreement which it signed on March 11, 1947<note n="2" xml:id="d405fn2">See telegram No. 1116 from Paris, March 13, 1947, footnote
                        1, <ref target="#pg_629">p. 629</ref>.</note> concerning the repatriation of
                    German prisoners whose custody was entrusted to it by the American authorities.
                    Between March 1 and July 1, 1947, it succeeded in effecting a total of 87,000
                    repatriations, 7,000 more than the number set for the same period on the basis
                    of 20,000 repatriations per month. If one adds that, from January 1 to March 1,
                    15,000 prisoners had already been returned to Germany, this gives a figure of
                    102,000 men, or nearly one quarter of the total number of prisoners transferred
                    by the United States to France and left under French control, who have been
                    repatriated.</p>
                <p>When the French Government agreed to fix the monthly number of repatriations at
                    20,000, it relied upon the promise contained in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of December 3, in which Mr. Jefferson Caffery indicated
                    that the American authorities in Germany would receive instructions, if the
                    French Government expressed such desire, to cooperate in the recruitment of
                    German workers for France.</p>
                <pb facs="0653" n="635" xml:id="pg_635"/>
                <p>As a matter of fact, the recruitment of free labor in Germany by the French
                    authorities has encountered long delays on the part of the American authorities
                    and financial terms which were not acceptable to the French Government. In order
                    to overcome these difficulties, the latter proposed to the American Government
                    certain solutions which were, specifically, the subject of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of June 18. It sincerely regrets that there was not
                    greater haste in concluding the agreement sought.</p>
                <p>While such agreement failed to materialize the aggravation of the general labor
                    situation only rendered the solution of this problem more difficult for the
                    French Government.</p>
                <p>The strikes which have occurred in the coal mines and on the railroads have
                    caused a serious diminution of the raw materials which are indispensable to the
                    French economy.</p>
                <p>With the approach of a harvest which is of exceptional importance and seriousness
                    for the country, the French Government, placed under the obligation of improving
                    at all costs, the tragic situation of its wheat supply feels itself obliged not
                    to divert more than a minimum amount of labor from the agricultural
                    population.</p>
                <p>The failure of the Italian Government to carry out the commitments made in the
                    labor agreement, in which France took the initiative, has reduced to 5 or 6,000
                    the recruitment of 17,000 workers per month anticipated in the application of
                    that agreement.</p>
                <p>The hiring of displaced persons in Germany cannot give substantial results before
                    harvest time.</p>
                <p>If, moreover, in conformity with the Agreement of March 11, work contracts in the
                    number fixed are to be distributed at once to the German prisoners, the
                    transformation of the latter into free workers, by making it easier for them to
                    leave their work and to return to Germany, even in spite of their contracts,
                    entails grave risks for the French economy in the critical period through which
                    it is now passing.</p>
                <p>Lastly, the French Government is obliged to permit the workers born in Eastern
                    Europe who formally express the desire to do so, to return to their countries.
                    These elements furnish the French economy with workers who are particularly
                    useful by reason of their specialization in mining and agricultural work.
                    Anxious to lose as few of these workers as possible, the French Government has
                    taken every precaution to make sure that their departure was really voluntary
                    and was not caused by any pressure; it could not, however, oppose the return of
                    these free workers to their countries when they sincerely expressed the desire
                    to do so. While in 1946 these repatriations to the Eastern countries were
                    limited to 7,000 Poles and 2,000 Yugoslavs, or a total <pb facs="0654" n="636" xml:id="pg_636"/> of 9,000 workers, the departures amount, during the
                    present year, to much larger figures, which consist of: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>17,000 Poles, comprising 8,000 employed in coal, iron and potassium
                            mines, 3,000 miscellaneous workers and 6,000 agricultural workers;</p>
                        <p>2,000 Yugoslavs, several hundred of whom are miners, the others being for
                            the most part agricultural workers;</p>
                        <p>10,000 Ukrainians and Byelorussians, chiefly agricultural workers.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>To this total of 29,000 workers are added the members of their families, a large
                    number of whom are employed in the French economy.</p>
                <p>In the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of June 16, the Embassy of France was
                    instructed to state that the recruitment of free German workers conditioned the
                    ability of the French Government to maintain the repatriation of German
                    prisoners of war at the monthly figure contemplated. It stressed the urgency
                    presented for this reason by the conclusion with the American authorities of an
                    agreement on the recruitment of free German workers, analogous to the one which
                    was being negotiated with the British authorities.</p>
                <p>The apprehensions of the French Government have become a reality. The situation
                    set forth above places it under the unavoidable obligation, under penalty of
                    causing in the French economy a crisis which may have serious repercussions, to
                    reduce, taking into consideration the provisions of paragraph 3 of the Agreement
                    of March 11, the repatriations of German prisoners from 20,000 to 10,000, during
                    each of the two months of July and August.</p>
                <p>The French Government will make every effort possible to compensate for this
                    reduction in the coming months, by exceeding the repatriation quotas
                    established. It is confident that it will succeed in doing so if an improvement
                    in the general labor situation in France can be effected and particularly if the
                    contingents not only of displaced persons but also of German free labor which
                    the French Government has been trying to obtain for several months are received.
                    The French authorities would therefore attach the greatest importance to
                    receiving without delay the reply of the American Government to the offers
                    appearing in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of June 18, a reply which,
                    they very much hope, will be favorable.<note n="3" xml:id="d405fn3">On July 15
                        Frances E. Willis, Assistant Chief of the Division of Western European
                        Affairs, gave to Armand Bérard, Minister Counselor in the French Embassy, an
                            <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> expressing regret that the French
                        Government felt compelled to reduce the rate of repatriation during July and
                        August and the hope that it would be possible to compensate for this
                        reduction in the following months. Miss Willis added that instructions had
                        been sent to the American Embassy in Paris to approach the French Government
                        with a view to working out an agreement. (851.504/7–1547)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>H[<hi rend="smallcaps">enri</hi>] B[<hi rend="smallcaps">onnet</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
