<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-25T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-25T19:00:00-05:00" n="417" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d417">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">859B.20/4–2347: Telegram</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                            Denmark</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-25T19:00:00-05:00">April 25, 1947—7 p. m.</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>230. For your TopSec info only, <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 253 Apr 23.<note n="1" xml:id="d417fn1">Not
                                        printed; in it Ambassador Marvel reported that since January
                                        1947, Foreign Minister Rasmussen had made several press
                                        statements indicating that negotiations with the United
                                        States regarding the termination of the 1941 Greenland
                                        Defense Agreement were still going on and that Denmark
                                        considered the time ripe for such negotiations
                                        (859B.20/4–2347).</note> In informal conversations here Dan
                                    Amb Kauffmann has given us impression (whether with
                                    authorization of Rasmussen or not we do not know) that (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Rasmussen is fully aware that while
                                    reactions US Govt to his memo of Dec 5<note n="2" xml:id="d417fn2">Not found in Department of State
                                        files.</note> are embodied in Mr. Byrnes’ conversation and
                                    memo of Dec 14,<note n="3" xml:id="d417fn3">Regarding the
                                        conversation and memorandum under reference, see footnote 3,
                                            <ref target="#pg_657">p. 657</ref>.</note> these do not
                                    constitute formal US proposals; and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                    Rasmussen’s press statements are not to be considered as Dan
                                    reply to Mr. Byrnes’ suggestions but as a means of satisfying
                                    those segments of Dan public opinion which desire or claim to
                                    desire withdrawal of US from <gloss target="#t_GREEN1">Green</gloss>, while at same time protecting Dan bargaining
                                    position if and when formal negotiations eventuate.</p>
                                <p>Kauffmann has remarked that it is necessary for Rasmussen to give
                                    impression to Dan public opinion that discussions are under way
                                    although he fully realizes that such is not in fact the
                                    case.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>