<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Denmark (
                        Marvel
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d426</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">426</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-06-26T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-26T03:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-26T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-26T03:00:00-05:00" n="426" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d426">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24559B/6–2647: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Marvel</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-26T10:00:00+02:00">June 26, 1947—10 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>425. After first hectic day here Kauffmann dined with me alone. He feels approach
                    to Greenland problem must be made slowly, pointing out Communist resolution is
                    out of the way, Parliament is in recess and General Assembly of UN meets in
                    early fall. Consequently discussions on Greenland could appropriately come up
                    thereafter. He suggested that I come to Washington in late fall and believed
                    conversations with the Secretary or Under Secretary Lovett would result in a
                    solution. He emphasized that there was no possibility of a sale. After <pb facs="0691" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> he has conferred with Danish officials
                    he will give me more definite views as to Danish course of action.</p>
                <p>Above recommendation for schedule of Greenland talks which undoubtedly will be
                    followed by Danish Government makes it difficult to tie in refugees with
                    Greenland problem as suggested my Top Secret telegram 405 June 19. However in
                    view of Danish approach described <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 422
                    June 25<note n="1" xml:id="d426fn1">Not printed; it reported that the Danish
                        Government hoped to obtain commitments from the American, British, and
                        French Governments to accept additional refugees into their zones of
                        occupation in Germany prior to requesting the Soviet Government to fulfill
                        its 1946 promise to accept into its zone half of the German refugees
                        remaining in Denmark (840.48 Refugees/6–2547).</note> it appears advisable
                    to consider receiving immediately additional refugees into US Zone in order to
                    capitalize on fact Russian removal of additional refugees (if such takes place)
                    will be result of US initiative. Consequently urge US agree to accepting 12,000
                    additional refugees and that Berlin be so advised by direct order from
                    Washington. Most important, if this is done, that it be ordered prior to any
                    Russian commitments (which means immediate action) so that situation will not
                    develop as it did in March when timing of American action largely diluted
                    potential political capital.</p>
                <p>Kauffmann departs July 15 and after tour of European capitals and Iceland will
                    arrive back in US August 5.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marvel</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
