<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recco4TvraiYB3Tfh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007556"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radar</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="433"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">859B.20/10–2247</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-22">October 22,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Gustav Rasmussen, Danish Foreign
                                Minister<note n="1" xml:id="d433fn1">Foreign Minister Rasmussen
                                arrived in New York on October 17 to serve as head of the Danish
                                Delegation to the Second Regular Session of the United Nations
                                General Assembly, September 16–November 29, 1947. The Secretary of
                                State headed the United States Delegation.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Henrik de Kauffmann, Danish Ambassador</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">The Secretary</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In raising the subject of termination of the agreement of April 9, 1941 for the
                    defense of Greenland the Danish Foreign Minister referred to an impression in
                    Washington and London that his Government was subject to Soviet pressure for
                    termination of the agreement. He said that no such pressure had been brought to
                    bear by the Soviet Government, the only time the matter had even been mentioned
                    was on <pb facs="0699" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"/> one occasion when the Soviet
                    Minister at Copenhagen had asked him as to the truth of press reports that the
                    United States Government was attempting to buy Greenland. He was then in a
                    position to refer the Minister to the public statement Mr. Rasmussen had made a
                    few days earlier to the effect that Greenland was not for sale. The Soviet press
                    and radio had been critical of the United States for continuing to maintain
                    forces in Greenland but had not yet criticized the Danish Government. I observed
                    that the Soviet Government was too astute to use direct pressure when it had at
                    its disposal local means of exerting influence and pressure. Mr. Rasmussen said
                    that pressure for termination of the agreement came from various sections of
                    Danish public opinion [in] addition to the Communists. I recognized that this
                    was a subject on which the Communists could easily get general support. He hoped
                    it would be possible for him to say that the consultations provided in Article
                    10 of the agreement were making progress, as for example to announce that the
                    weather stations were progressively being transferred from American to Danish
                    hands.</p>
                <p>I developed to him forcefully and at some length the importance of Greenland as a
                    vital and vulnerable link in the defense of the Western Hemisphere as a whole.
                    If the Danes could defend it adequately that would be fine but they clearly were
                    not in a position to do so. We could not afford to have it undefended. Enemy
                    occupation of Greenland would not only endanger our whole system of hemispheric
                    defense but would expose our vital industrial areas. I said I had hoped that the
                    Danes would understand its importance to us and be able to make suggestions as
                    to how our defense needs could be met in a form that would be politically
                    possible for them. I had hoped that Ambassador Kauffmann would bring such
                    suggestions on his return from Denmark.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kauffmann stated that time was needed to solve the problem and that an
                    improvement in the present international atmosphere would help. Three types of
                    installations were involved: the weather stations, the air fields, and the
                    proposed radar installations in the north. He liked the approach indicated in
                    the Department’s press release of May 29, 1947 in which we indicated readiness
                    to explore with the Danish Government the basis of a new agreement “in keeping
                    with the letter and spirit of the Charter of the United Nations which would take
                    fully into account Danish sovereignty over Greenland and legitimate United
                    States and hemispheric defense requirements”. He also saw possibilities in a
                    regional defense agreement to include Canada and possibly other countries of
                    this hemisphere.</p>
                <p>I indicated that this regional approach including Canada might be explored.
                    Referring again to the imperative need for adequate defense of Greenland, I
                    suggested that the Danish political problem might be <pb facs="0700" n="682"
                        xml:id="pg_682"/> met by a formula similar to that which we had been
                    prepared to offer the Australian Government in connection with Manus Island,
                    namely that we would be prepared to make annual payments to the Danish
                    Government to enable it to maintain installations which we had erected in
                    Greenland during the war in return for the right to use those facilities as
                    needed and to station a few men there to look after supplies. I pointed out that
                    we would not be in a position to maintain substantial forces there in peace
                    time.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister did not reply but the Ambassador repeated that time would be
                    needed to work out an agreement. In the meantime the 1941 agreement continued in
                    effect and the conversations would continue.</p>
                <p>(After the conversation had ended Mr. Achilles<note n="2" xml:id="d433fn2"
                        >Theodore C. Achilles, Adviser to the United States Delegation to the
                        General Assembly.</note> asked the Foreign Minister whether he considered
                    the suggestion of annual payments in return for the right to use the
                    installations a promising one from the Danish point of view. He replied that he
                    must necessarily speak personally since he was not even sure that he would be in
                    the new government to be set up following the elections on October 28, but that
                    he personally thought the approach a very good one.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
