<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-04-26T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-04-26T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-04-26T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-04-26T13:00:00-05:00" n="450"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d450">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.6131/4–2647: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">u.s. urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-04-26T13:00:00-05:00"
                            >April 26, 1947—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1530. The French claim that the U.S. Govt promised shipment of 553,000 tons of
                    grain to France in the period February–June 1947 <pb facs="0722" n="704"
                        xml:id="pg_704"/> arises from a misunderstanding on the part of the French
                    dating from the time of the visit of Minister Prigent to Washington in February.
                    The misconception was threefold, namely, (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) combining of
                    recognized import requirements of Metropolitan France and French North Africa
                    and applying the resultant total to Metropolitan France alone, (<hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>) failure to understand that the <gloss
                        target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss> recommended figure for shipments to France or
                    any other country applies to total shipments from all sources and does not
                    include specific recommendations concerning the source of such shipments, and
                        (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) ignoring of the fact that the United States as a
                    supplying country member of that Council has during the present half-year
                    announced its export programs month by month, not singling out any countries for
                    special consideration by allocation of grain covering longer periods.</p>
                <p>The figure 553,000 was combined by Monsieur Prigent himself in a letter of
                    February 18 to the Secretary of Agriculture as follows: <table cols="2" rows="6">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Seed wheat to be shipped from the U.S. in
                                February</cell>
                            <cell role="num">17,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">March program from the United States</cell>
                            <cell role="num">68,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Balance to be shipped April, May and
                                June</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#underline" role="num">277,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Total for Metropolitan France</cell>
                            <cell role="num">362,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Total to be shipped to French North
                                Africa</cell>
                            <cell role="num">191,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Total to France and French North
                                Africa</cell>
                            <cell role="num">553,000 tons</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>There is therefore no basis whatever for the French to talk of a promised total
                    of 553,000 for France itself when they themselves stated that the figure
                    applying to France in this connection was 362,000 which was in harmony with
                        <gloss target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss> figures for shipment to France from
                    all sources.</p>
                <p>In connection with the Minister’s visit the <gloss target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss>
                    made an upward revision of the French requirement from 450,000 for the crop-year
                    July 1946–June 1947 to 877,000 which took into account the wheat frost-kill in
                    France and made allowances for 100,000 tons imported for feed use.</p>
                <p>In calculating balance still due to France from February forward, <gloss
                        target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss> found that known shipments from all sources
                    plus the U.S. March and April programs totalled 600,000 tons (about 500,000 of
                    which had moved during last half of 1946) leaving balance of 277,000 tons to
                    move from all sources. This is balance referred to in Mr. Prigent’s letter to
                    Secretary of Agriculture as being expected by French to move to France from
                    United States in addition to already announced February and March programs to
                    make a total of 362,000.</p>
                <p>In letter of reply addressed to French Ambassador on March 4, Secretary of
                    Agriculture indicated that February and March programs <pb facs="0723" n="705"
                        xml:id="pg_705"/> and also an April program of 123,000 tons to France and
                    French North Africa could be regarded as specific commitments from United
                    States, but that no commitments were yet possible regarding quantities to be
                    programmed from United States in months of May and June, although United States
                    would do its best to furnish as much of balance as possible. Likewise letter
                    made clear that no promise could be made with regard to North Africa.</p>
                <p>In actuality the United States with programs as announced through June and
                    including recent emergency allocations of 33,000 and 36,000 tons respectively
                    expects to make available 359,000 tons to Metropolitan France as compared to the
                    362,000 referred to by Monsieur Prigent in his letter.</p>
                <p>This is broken down as follows: <table cols="2" rend="width: 50%"
                        rendition="#center-block" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">February</cell>
                            <cell role="num">17,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Part of March program moved to France</cell>
                            <cell role="num">35,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Part of April program being moved to
                                France</cell>
                            <cell role="num">56,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">May program</cell>
                            <cell role="num">100,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">June program</cell>
                            <cell role="num">82,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Emergency programs</cell>
                            <cell role="num">69,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">359,000</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>Meantime shipments to France from Argentina have brought total known shipments
                    plus U.S. programs to France thru June to a total for the crop year of 960,000
                    tons, thus actually exceeding the <gloss target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss>
                    recommended total of 877,000 tons for France from all sources by 83,000
                    tons.</p>
                <p>As for French North Africa, shipments to this area from United States in March
                    and April will total 92,000 tons. 38,000 were shipped to French North Africa
                    from other sources earlier in the year, making total shipment of 130,000
                    tons.</p>
                <p>The requirement now recognized for French North Africa in <gloss
                        target="#t_IEFC1">IEFC</gloss> is 207,000 tons. The balance not yet covered
                    is therefore 777,000 [<hi rend="italic">77,000?</hi>]. However, this shortfall
                    is more than made up by the excess shipped from all sources to France, namely
                    87,000 [<hi rend="italic">83,000?</hi>] tons. Thus known shipments and U.S.
                    programs through June to France and French North Africa taken together more than
                    meet the total for these areas recommended by <gloss target="#t_IEFC1"
                        >IEFC</gloss> without taking into account additional shipments which will
                    continue to be made from Argentina.</p>
                <p>Sent Paris as 1530 rptd Geneva for Clayton as 223.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
