<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in France (
                        Caffery
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d486</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">486</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-25T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-25T04:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="wheat" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366" lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="grain" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208" lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-25T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-25T04:00:00-05:00" n="486" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d486">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.61311/9–2547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-25T10:00:00+01:00">September 25, 1947—10 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4152. Many of our best informed friends, among them publishers-editors of <hi rend="italic">Ouest France</hi>, largest provincial daily in France, right
                    wing of <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss>, Gaullist tendencies, 430,000
                    circulation, covering 12 departments <pb facs="0778" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/>
                    Brittany and west with 28 regional editions; <hi rend="italic">Le Maine
                        Libre</hi>, Le Mans daily, Socialist, 80,000 circulation; <hi rend="italic">L’Ouest Republicain</hi>, Rennes daily, Socialist, 20,000 circulation, are
                    deeply concerned over extremely violent Communist Party propaganda, in view
                    October municipal elections, in rural districts heretofore predominantly
                    anti-Communist, and over danger of Communist gains there as result of this
                    propaganda. Communist campaign is based largely upon current 200 gram French
                    bread ration. Arguments most frequently advanced are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>US has sent less cereals than promised;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>US is now sending less than it could send, in order to aggravate
                            French shortage and at critical moment to send more on condition that
                            France submit to American anti-democratic imperialistic
                            conditions;</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>US sends mildewed corn to France keeping wheat and good corn for
                            German civilians of American zone;</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>US allows German civilians daily bread ration at least double that of
                            France;</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Ramadier has sold out to Americans and will not procure wheat from
                            Russia although stocks are available there;</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Severe crop fires in August and September are acts of arson, fires
                            being set by Fascist agents, ex-Vichy militia and Gestapo men, working
                            for reactionary clique, De Gaulle and American interests with Truman’s
                            blessing in order to further deplete French stocks and thus the more
                            easily to force France to submit to American conditions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The journalists mentioned above have all volunteered the opinion that a statement
                    by a high ranking official of US Government re shipments which have been made to
                    France would be most helpful in counteracting Communist efforts in rural areas.
                    They have also expressed the opinion that to obtain the maximum usefulness such
                    a statement should have a “newsworthy peg” and that repetition would greatly
                    strengthen its impact.</p>
                <p>These unsolicited views have served to strengthen my own conviction that we
                    should proceed at once with the plan outlined in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 3304, September 3 and that, as indicated in <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 4021, September 17, the statement should be
                    made by a high American official. My own view is that the statement would carry
                    great weight if made by Under Secretary Lovett who has received excellent press
                    in France in recent weeks as result of his sympathetic approach to question of
                    interim aid.</p>
                <p>It is reported in today’s press that Ambassador Bonnet has recently made
                    representations to our government for additional allocations of wheat. It seems
                    to me that Bonnet’s representations might serve as a suitable “peg” for a
                    statement focused on the French situation, and that he might be called in and
                    given the statement after which it could be given to the press. The statement
                    itself might begin with a reference to Bonnet’s representations which would have
                    the advantage of <pb facs="0779" n="761" xml:id="pg_761"/> making it appear that
                    the whole matter resulted from French initiative, thereby tending to counteract
                    the Weintal story.</p>
                <p>If this is done it would seem best to limit the part of the statement concerning
                    the relative contributions of the US and USSR to France itself rather than have
                    it cover “western Europe” as contemplated in the Dept’s original plan. The
                    inclusion of western Europe might also give the Communists here an opportunity
                    to point up their argument that we were sending much more grain to Germany than
                    to France.</p>
                <p>An alternative possibility would be to await Clayton’s return to Washington and
                    have the statement emanate from him. In my opinion, however, the time element
                    alone is sufficient to favor the first alternative.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
