<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="640" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d640">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">865.51/9–1147</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant
                                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-11">September 11,
                                        1947</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>Ambassador Tarchiani</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Armour, <gloss target="#t_AA1">A–A</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Dowling, <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>When the Ambassador called at his request this morning he said that
                                in a brief conversation with the Acting Secretary yesterday<note n="1" xml:id="d640fn1">No record of this conversation has been
                                    found.</note> Mr. Lovett had requested any suggestions which the
                                Ambassador might have regarding assistance for Italy. The Ambassador
                                said that unfortunately he had been unable to think of any concrete
                                measures which would not require Congressional action, although it
                                was clear by now that Italy would run out of dollars long before any
                                action which Congress might take. He said Italy would be able to
                                finance her requirements this month and it might be possible to pay
                                for October requirements, but there would be nothing at all left for
                                November <pb facs="0984" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/> imparts. He said
                                he had not received complete figures from Rome but his own estimate
                                was that within the near future Italy had in sight only some $37
                                million; this figure would have to be reduced proportionately if
                                there were any delay in final settlement of the Army accounts, from
                                which Italy expected to realize approximately $4 million, or in the
                                    <gloss target="#t_POWs1">POW</gloss> account totalling perhaps
                                $5 million. On the other hand, his estimate of Italy’s needs to the
                                end of December was $120 million. As he understood it the only
                                immediately available source of assistance was the relief program
                                for Italy which is generally expected to total about $120 million.
                                Of this amount, about $35 million had been committed in the present
                                quarter, leaving about $85 million for the balance of the program.
                                He understood further that it was contemplated that about half of
                                this amount would be spent in the final quarter of the year and the
                                rest in the first quarter of 1948. He hoped, however, we would give
                                consideration to stepping up shipments in the final quarter, in
                                anticipation that funds under the Marshall Plan would be available
                                for the first quarter of next year. He said the essential
                                commodities for Italy were, of course, wheat and coal; he realized
                                there were difficulties in procurement and transportation, but if
                                Italy’s requirements for these two items could be covered under the
                                relief program he felt that they would get along somehow.</p>
                            <p>I told Tarchiani that we would give consideration to his suggestion
                                and that we would see what could be done in this connection.</p>
                            <p>After thanking me, the Ambassador turned to the question of Italy’s
                                admission to the UN. He said that of course none of us knew what the
                                Soviet attitude on Italy’s application would be, now that the treaty
                                was coming into effect, but he feared the USSR would continue to
                                oppose Italy unless the other ex-enemy states were also admitted. He
                                added that he knew and sympathized with our attitude in this matter,
                                but that he hoped if we could admit some of the ex-enemy states
                                Italy could also get in. I said we had particularly grave doubts
                                that Albania, Bulgaria and Rumania were willing to carry out the
                                obligations of the Charter and that I did not see how we could vote
                                for all of the ex-enemy states. At the same time, Italy could count
                                on the same warm support for the Italian application which we had
                                already given in the Security Council. The Ambassador said that the
                                Italian Government was most grateful for this support and he knew we
                                would continue it.</p>
                            <p>Referring again to the coming into force of the Italian treaty on
                                September 15, Tarchiani said there were two matters to which he
                                hoped we would give special consideration. One was the delimitation
                                of the Italo-Yugoslav frontier. He said the Italian Government had
                                not accepted the Four Power Boundary Commission’s recommendations,
                                which he felt deviated from the treaty provisions and made <pb facs="0985" n="967" xml:id="pg_967"/> too many concessions to
                                Yugoslavia. The area involved was not great, but it meant a great
                                deal to the Italian people, and he hoped this unfavorable frontier
                                would not be imposed on Italy. The second matter was the possible
                                return to Italy of the US share of Italian naval vessels distributed
                                under the treaty. He said he understood we did not want to use these
                                ships, and he felt their return to Italy for scrapping would make a
                                tremendous impression on the Italian people. He said the scrap metal
                                was needed for Italian industries, and the return of the ships,
                                perhaps for some specific purpose like the production of
                                agricultural machinery, would be a gesture which would capture the
                                Italian imagination.</p>
                            <p>In conclusion the Ambassador said he hoped very much that any action
                                we might take in regard to these matters could be announced before
                                September 23 when debate began in the Constituent Assembly on the
                                motion of no confidence introduced by Nenni. He said De Gasperi
                                would surely be hard-pushed in the debate; the Communist-instigated
                                strikes were becoming increasingly grave; Togliatti had just
                                threatened the use of violence if necessary to overthrow the
                                Government; and every effort would be made to charge De Gasperi and
                                his pro-Western policy with responsibility for all of Italy’s ills.
                                He felt the vote would be extremely close, and further evidence of
                                American support and assistance might be the deciding factor.</p>
                            <p>I promised Tarchiani that I would look into all these questions
                                immediately, adding that as he knew we would be as helpful as
                                possible.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">orman</hi>] A[<hi rend="smallcaps">rmour</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>