<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of British Commonwealth
                    Affairs ( (Foster) ) to the Director of the Office of European Affairs (
                    (Hickerson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">842.5151/9–2747</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of British
                        Commonwealth Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foster</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-27">September 27,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Canadian Dollar Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The following is a summary of the developments of the past two weeks:</p>
                <p>On September 18 Mr. Clifford Clark (Acting Minister of Finance in the absence of
                    Abbott, who is still in London) visited Washington with the intention of talking
                    with you, Thorp, and Southard of the Treasury.<note n="1" xml:id="d77fn1"
                        >Willard L. Thorp, Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, and
                        Frank A. Southard, Director of the Office of International Finance, Treasury
                        Department.</note> He spent an hour or so with Southard in the morning, and
                    in the afternoon he met with Messrs. Ty Wood, Nitze, Jackson, Rosenson,<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d77fn2">C. Tyler Wood, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of
                        State for Economic Affairs; Paul H. Nitze, Deputy Director of the Office of
                        International Trade Policy; Wayne G. Jackson, Special Assistant to the
                        Director of the Office of European Affairs; and Alexander M. Rosenson,
                        Assistant Chief of the Division of Financial Affairs.</note> and myself. We
                    compared notes afterwards and found that the talks in State and Treasury were
                    very similar.</p>
                <p>I attach a copy of the memo relating to the State meeting,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d77fn3">Memorandum dated September 18, 1947, not printed.</note>
                    which you may wish to read. In brief, Clark (who was accompanied by Hume Wrong)
                    emphasized the gravity of the Canadian problem and said that his Government was
                    going to be compelled in the near future to apply import restrictions against
                    the radios, refrigerators, etc., from the U. S. He scarcely mentioned the loan
                    angle. He wanted to know whether we could give him any indication whether Canada
                    was being included in our framing of the Marshall plan (not in terms of direct
                    aid but as a partner in the reconstruction of the U. K. and western Europe). If
                    Canada was included in our thinking, and he appreciated that we couldn’t say
                    what Congress may do, his Government would apply the least drastic remedies to
                    the present emergency and would declare them to be temporary. But if Canada was
                    not included and if we felt that a “multilateral” trading world of comparative
                    free trade and comparatively interchangeable currencies was a thing of the past,
                    Canada would be obliged to apply very drastic and long-term remedies.</p>
                <pb facs="0143" n="125" xml:id="pg_125"/>
                <p>Mr. Ty Wood underlined to Mr. Clark and Ambassador Wrong that we were deeply
                    concerned by the Canadian problem and anxious to do what we could to assist; he
                    added, however, that there was no magic cure available to us in Washington. He
                    said that the <gloss target="#t_ITO1">ITO</gloss> and the Marshall plan would
                    simply have to be made to succeed but he said he thought it would be a mistake
                    for Canada to rely on either for any immediate solution of her problem. Even
                    under optimum conditions the effect of the <gloss target="#t_ITO1">ITO</gloss>
                    and the Marshall plan might not be felt for a long time, perhaps years.</p>
                <p>We feel that the meeting served two useful purposes. It brought us up to date on
                    details concerning the problem and Canadian thinking about its solution.
                    Secondly, it acquainted the Canadians with the fact that there is no easy remedy
                    available at present at this end. As to the loan, it would have to be
                    appropriated by Congress (which I suspect will be somewhat astonished to be
                    asked to lend $500,000,000 to Canada); and as to the Marshall plan, it is in a
                    very early stage. There isn’t much sign that Congress will give us in the
                    Marshall plan, even if it is adopted, any great degree of flexibility in placing
                    procurement in Canada or making US dollars available to the U. K. and western
                    Europe for purchases in Canada.</p>
                <p>On September 25 I talked with Hume Wrong for an hour about the problem. I attach
                    a copy of my memo of conversation,<note n="4" xml:id="d77fn4">Memorandum dated
                        September 25, 1947, not printed.</note> which I recommend you read if you
                    have time. This meeting served chiefly to set the record straight concerning the
                    word which Hume had sent us, after the Clark meeting on the 18th, that he and
                    Clark understood that “the next move was up to the U.S.”.</p>
                <p>Ray Atherton arrives in Washington on Monday morning, September 29, for a week’s
                    consultation. On Tuesday morning at 11.00 the following are meeting in Mr. Ty
                    Wood’s office to talk further about the problem: Wood, Atherton, Southard (of
                    the Treasury), Wayne Jackson, Nitze, Rosenson, and myself. I think you should be
                    there: you’d get the latest developments at first hand and I think the group
                    needs your wisdom. (Incidentally, Hume Wrong said, after the Clark meeting, “I
                    think we need to have Jack’s imagination brought to bear on the problem”.)</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew</hi> B. <hi rend="smallcaps">Foster</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. As you will note in my memo of conversation with Hume, he told me that
                        within a matter of weeks there will be a very high level approach, possibly
                        by the P. M. to the President, about the Canadian <pb facs="0144" n="126"
                            xml:id="pg_126"/> problem. No doubt the approach will relate to a loan
                        and to inclusion in the Marshall plan.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
