<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chancellor of the Exchequer ( (Dalton) ) to the Secretary of the Treasury
                    ( (Snyder))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">FW 841.51/7–2547</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chancellor of the Exchequer</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dalton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Secretary of the Treasury</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Snyder</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-23">23rd May,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear John</hi>: Thank you for your letter of the 7th
                        May<note n="1" xml:id="d9fn1">Not printed.</note> on the Sterling Balances
                    negotiations. We are pressing forward, and Gordon <pb facs="0034" n="16"
                        xml:id="pg_16"/> Munro will be keeping you informed of what we are doing and
                    what we have in mind.</p>
                <p>The broad picture is as follows. The two largest of our problems—India and
                    Egypt—will come to a head in June. The Egyptians should be arriving at the
                    beginning of the month, and the Indians in the second half. We shall be able to
                    handle Iraq, either over here or at Baghdad, towards the end of the month.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, we are continuing with other negotiations. We have completed
                    arrangements with some European countries—Portugal, Belgium, Holland and
                    Italy—and are proceeding with others, including Czecho-Slovakia, Norway,
                    Denmark, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland. The Argentine problem is settled, and we
                    have carried discussions with Brazil some distance, possibly within sight of a
                    conclusion. The Uruguayan Delegation arrives in a few days. Australia and New
                    Zealand have been very helpful with their willing cancellations, and we expect
                    to complete arrangements—less formal than would be appropriate to other holders
                    of balances—in due course. All our various arrangements will be within the
                    framework of the Loan Agreement.</p>
                <p>As regards the “segregation” of that part of the Sterling Balances of each
                    creditor which is not to be released for current transactions, I think the
                    technique must vary according to the capacity of the other party to control its
                    financial affairs. With some countries, an informal agreement that they will
                    maintain their balances at such and such a level should suffice; with others—and
                    these, I fear, include the largest holders of sterling—something more stringent
                    may prove to be inevitable. But, whatever the exact arrangements, they will have
                    the same effect: that what we agree to release for current purposes will be for
                    use in any currency area, while what is not released cannot be drawn upon for
                    current transactions at all. It is against our own interests to allow drawings
                    on the accumulated balances, for, in the end, this means using up current
                    productive effort in unrequited exports. If we fail to reach agreement with any
                    creditor, we shall probably have no alternative but to take the steps necessary
                    to segregate past accumulations while leaving future accumulations free.</p>
                <p>Like you, I should have liked to make permanent settlements between us and each
                    of our creditors, but it is not easy to see how we could commit ourselves at
                    this time to details of the rate of release after 1951. The rise in prices in
                    the United States, coupled with slow recovery in other parts of the world, has
                    left the future obscure. Given the tremendous demand for dollars in the world at
                    large, we can offer much less than we would have hoped in the way of releases in
                    the short run. On the other hand, the countries with whom we are negotiating
                    will insist, in these circumstances, on waiting for several years in the <pb
                        facs="0035" n="17" xml:id="pg_17"/> hope of securing better terms in any
                    final arrangements. I am sure that, in these conditions, it is wiser to make
                    provisional settlements for five years. Before the end of the period we shall,
                    of course, discuss further arrangements, which will be either for another period
                    of five years, or, if things go well, for longer.</p>
                <p>The inescapable fact is that all releases are, in the end, an added charge either
                    on our current production or on our dollar credit. The first is as yet
                    inadequate to our current needs, and the second is exhausting itself fast. We
                    shall have to be modest in what we attempt accordingly.</p>
                <p>With my warm personal regards,</p>
                <p>Yours very sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh Dalton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
