<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-04-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Campbell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">No. 15]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Stockholm,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-08"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your despatch of the 13th of February, No.
                            13, has been received.</p>
                        <p>I took occasion to communicate to Count Manderstrom the action of my
                            government on the subject of the Bergen international exhibition, with
                            which he expressed himself much gratified.</p>
                        <p>A letter from Mr. Wood, United States minister resident at Copenhagen, of
                            the 1st instant, and received by me on the 6th instant, informed me that
                            “confederate agents” were prowling around that city in search of a
                            vessel that would answer for piratical purposes, and that he (Mr. Wood)
                            understood that “Waddell, the captain of the late Florida,” who was
                            there, had said that he might go to Sweden, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>I immediately took the necessary steps to place the consuls of the United
                            States at the Swedish and Norwegian ports on their guard against the
                            supposed purposes of these rebel emissaries, and requested careful
                            watchfulness of their operations.</p>
                        <p>I enclose a copy of Mr. Wood’s note, (No. 1,) and of my reply, (No. 2,)
                            as well as a copy of a letter addressed by me to the consul at
                            Gothenburg, Mr. Thomas, on the subject, (No. 3.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0276" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/>
                        <p>Preparations for the resumption of commerce with the Baltic ports are now
                            being made. It is supposed the navigation will be free from ice after
                            the 15th or 20th instant. The winter has been one of unusual severity,
                            but the snow and ice are now fast disappearing.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>JAMES H. CAMPBELL.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 1.</seg></opener>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Wood</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Campbell</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir:</hi> Confederate agents have been
                                prowling around this city, and, I suppose, looking out for some
                                vessel that will do for a pirate, and which they would expect to get
                                out as a merchant vessel and arm at sea.</p>
                            <p>I have been informed that Waddell, the captain of the late Florida,
                                is here, and that he has dropped the remark that he might go to
                                Sweden; in other words, go where he could find such a ship as he
                                wanted.</p>
                            <p>I am not sufficiently acquainted with Swedish ports or Swedish
                                commerce to indicate what place he would go to, but have thought it
                                advisable to apprise you of what I have heard. As it is no longer as
                                easily as formerly to equip pirates in England, the confederates are
                                now, I think, turning their attention to the smaller maritime
                                powers.</p>
                            <p>I remain, very truly, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>BRADFORD R. WOOD.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Campbell,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Stockholm.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>P. S.—I should think Gothenburg a port, or one of the ports, most
                                    likely to be visited by the confederates. W.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 2.</seg></opener>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Campbell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Wood</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Stockholm,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-06"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Yours of the 1st instant was received
                                this morning, and I thank you for the information thus promptly
                                given. We have been out of the track of rebel operations here, and,
                                with the exception of a person calling himself William L. Preston,
                                C. S. A., who left this place about the time of my arrival, I have
                                not heard of any one within the jurisdiction of this legation who
                                might fairly be suspected as a spy or agent of the insurgents.</p>
                            <p>I can understand the value of your suggestions, and will immediately
                                take the necessary steps to place our consuls on the alert, and if,
                                or when, necessary, will call the attention of the Swedish and
                                Norwegian officials to the subject.</p>
                            <p>With thanks for your suggestions, and in the hope that we may meet in
                                Europe, I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient
                                servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>JAMES H. CAMPBELL.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bradford R. Wood,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minister Resident,
                                        Copenhagen.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 3.</seg></opener>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Campbell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Thomas, Jr</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Stockholm,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-06"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The following extracts are made from a
                                letter received this day from Hon. Bradford R. Wood, United States
                                minister resident, Copenhagen, and dated April 1, 1865, viz:</p>
                            <p>“Confederate agents have been prowling around this city, and, I
                                suppose, looking out for some vessel that will do for a pirate, and
                                which they would expect to get out as a merchant vessel and arm at
                                sea. I have been informed that Waddell, the captain of the late <pb facs="0277" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> Florida, is here, and that
                                he dropped the remark that he might go to Sweden; in other words, go
                                where he might find such a ship as he wanted. I am not sufficiently
                                acquainted with Swedish ports or Swedish commerce to indicate what
                                place he would go to, &amp;c. As it is no longer as easily as
                                formerly to equip pirates in England, the confederates are now, I
                                think, turning their attention to the smaller maritime powers,
                                &amp;c. I should think Gothenburg a port, or one of the ports, most
                                likely to be visited by the confederates.”</p>
                            <p>As the operations of the insurgent’s agents may extend to your
                                neighborhood, I have deemed it advisable to call your attention to
                                this information, and to request of you (that which I know the
                                interests of the United States will always receive at your hands
                                without any request of mine) especial care and watchfulness in this
                                regard. If necessary, my aid with the government officials here can
                                be invoked by telegraph or otherwise, as you may deem best. I have
                                written to the consuls of the United States at Bergen and Porsgrund
                                on this subject.</p>
                            <p>What is the prospect of emigration to the United States from your
                                part of Sweden for the approaching season? Be pleased to let me
                                know.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>JAMES H. CAMPBELL.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">William W. Thomas,</hi> Jr., Esq., <hi rend="italic">United States Consul, Gothenburg,
                                    Sweden.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>