<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hale to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-11-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-11-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="315"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Hale</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 46.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate General of the U. S. of
                                America</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cairo, Egypt,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 18, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> On the 16th instant I called on his excellency,
                    Cherif Pacha, minister for foreign affairs, having come from Alexandria for the
                    purpose on the prece ding evening.</p>
                <p>The minister courteously made excuses for his delay in answering my note of 20th
                    October, in which I had communicated to him the observations contained in your
                    instruction to me, No. 13, of the 21st September. He told me that he was ready
                    to give me an answer that would be in all respects satisfactory to my
                    government.</p>
                <p>I said that I was glad to hear this, and that if he could conveniently send me
                    his answer that day or the next, I could communicate its substance by telegraph
                    to Queenstown, in season to reach you, to be laid before the President before
                    the opening of Congress. He said that he would do so.</p>
                <p>We then dropped into a less formal conversation, when I was surprised to learn
                    that the Egyptian government had not abandoned or even scarcely suspended the
                    proposed expedition of negroes to Mexico. The minister expected that you would
                    be entirely satisfied to have the expedition go on, if you were assured that the
                    number of the force now in Mexico would not be increased, and <pb facs="0415"
                        n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/> that the soldiers were not slaves; and such was
                    the substance of the formal answer he was about to send me.</p>
                <p>As regards the first part of this answer, nothing else was ever proposed, and I
                    told the minister that you could not have understood that anything else was
                    proposed. His Highness had very clearly explained to me that the nine hundred
                    negroes were to be embarked to relieve the contingent sent out in January,
                    1863.; that I reported the proposition exactly in those words, although it was
                    observed that nine hundred was the number given to me, while four hundred and
                    fifty was the number stated to Mr. Thayer in 1863, and reported by him. No
                    remarks had been made even upon this discrepancy. I spoke of the expedition in
                    my despatch as a relief; you began your instruction by rehearsing the words of
                    my despatch in the usual manner, and that your observations must be taken as
                    based upon the distinct understanding that it was proposed to send out the
                    negroes to relieve the contingent already in service,</p>
                <p>The minister seemed to take it for granted that the compulsory service of the
                    negroes not only formed the whole objection to the affair in the eyes of the
                    people of the United States, but that if that objection were removed by
                    assurances on his part they would be entirely satisfied to see the expedition go
                    forward.</p>
                <p>I told the minister that I knew nothing of personal knowledge of the
                    circumstances of the embarcation of 1863, but I knew how it was described by Mr.
                    Thayer, and what was the general opinion not only in the United States but in
                    Alexandria, where the story of those days in January, 1863, when no black boas
                    (door-keeper) could be persuaded to open a door at night for fear of being
                    crimped, and when many black servants ran away to hide for a week in the desert,
                    while the embarcation for Mexico was going on, was still familiar in many
                    households; and I had supposed that there was no doubt of the furtive and secret
                    character of the proceeding.</p>
                <p>With regard to this last remark, the minister said, no doubt, the embarcation in
                    1863 was sudden and secret, but this was for a political reason, namely, that it
                    was necessary to keep the thing from the knowledge of the Porte until it was all
                    over; as the whole proceeding at that time was against the Sultan’s will, it was
                    arranged to have it finished before his remonstrance could arrive.</p>
                <p>To conclude the conversation, however, I told the minister that his Highness had
                    said to me expressly that he should not send the negroes except for the
                    engagement of his predecessor to the Emperor of the French; that appreciating
                    the position of his Highness, you had addressed your observations to the
                    governments at Paris and Constantinople as well as to his own, and that I knew
                    that the French government had been good enough, while assigning a special
                    reason and reserving its general abstract right, to give up the affair on its
                    part, after receiving your observations, and that I should be sorry if the
                    Egyptian government, after receiving the same observations, found no reason to
                    change the course that had formerly been proposed. I added that the announcement
                    made by Mr. Drouyn de Lhuys to Mr. Bigelow to this effect was made independently
                    of the matter of compulsory service, which had not been discussed between them
                    until after this previous point had been disposed of, and then only as a matter
                    of abstract interest; that Mr. Drouyn de Lhuys had expressly told Mr. Bigelow
                    that the inquiries he proposed to set on foot here with regard to the nature of
                    the service in the Egyptian army were to satisfy himself, and not as a matter of
                    official concern to his government.</p>
                <p>Cherif Pacha said this put an entirely new face on the affair, and could scarcely
                    credit the accuracy of my information. To satisfy him I sent to my hotel for the
                    copy which Mr. Bigelow had kindly transmitted to me of his despatch to you, No.
                    186, reporting his interview with the French minister. I read to Cherif Pacha
                    the principal parts of this despatch, and afterwards, at his request, furnished
                    him with a translation into French.</p>
                <p>In sending to Cherif Pacha this translation, I wrote a note to express what was
                        <pb facs="0416" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> already understood between us,
                    namely, that this was not precisely an official communication; that I was
                    waiting his answer to my official note of the 20th October, and that meanwhile I
                    was willing to add to his information upon the subject. I begged his particular
                    attention to the fact that the note of the 20th October conveyed your
                    observations upon understanding that the proposed expedition of negroes to
                    Mexico, was to replace the contingent now in service them. I said that whatever
                    reason might be assigned, the thing needed to tranquillize public opinion in the
                    United States would be to hear that his Highness had been good enough to declare
                    that he did not intend to renew the expedition of Egyptian soldiers to Mexico;
                    that a replacement would be considered as a renewal; that if he liked to make a
                    reserve of his rights in the manner pursued by the French minister, in saying
                    that the proposed expedition was not abandoned, but that in effect it would not
                    take place on account of domestic reasons, I should be satisfied with this, but
                    that of course a definitive abandonment would give us great pleasure; that I
                    believed France would make no objection to it; among our people in America it
                    would be regarded as a new proof of the friendship of his Highness, and
                    everywhere in the world it would be regarded as a proof of his noble wisdom in
                    the interests of humanity, since, without giving to the service of the Egyptian
                    negroes in Mexico the name of “slavery,” it must be admitted would not be an
                    agreeable thing for the soldiers, as his Highness himself had told me with all
                    possible frankness when expressing his anxiety to replace the men now in that
                    service by others.</p>
                <p>The substance of the preceding paragraph, and nearly in the equivalent words in
                    French, was written and sent to the minister, you will understand, with the view
                    of influencing his answer to the note of the 20th October. He kept my messenger
                    waiting a short time, however, and sent back by him his formal answer to that
                    note, a translation of which answer is hereto appended and marked A.</p>
                <p>As this formal answer to your observations will of course attract your particular
                    attention, I make no remark upon it.</p>
                <p>At the same time the messenger brought back a less formal note from the minister,
                    in which he acknowledged the receipt of my last note, saying that for the
                    present he could only refer me to our conversation of the morning, repeating
                    that it gave the subject, a new phase, of which the Egyptian government re
                    served for itself the examination, and that meanwhile he hastened to send me his
                    official answer to your observations.</p>
                <p>I believe that I have faithfully represented these communications, but for your
                    greater assurance I transmit herewith, marked B, C, D, and E, copies of the
                    originals of everything that has passed in writing, beginning with my note of
                    the 20th October, in which I endeavored to give exactly the sense of your
                    observations, continuing with the minister’s official answer, (of which the
                    translation is the piece marked A,) and concluding with our less formal
                    correspondence of the 16th instant, already described.</p>
                <p>The telegraph wire between Alexandria and Malta had just broken; but the steam
                    packet to the latter port leaves to-morrow, takes forward to Mr. Bigelow, in
                    Paris, a telegraphic message to the effect that the Egyptian government say the
                    insurrection is suppressed, and that the expedition of negroes may go forward. I
                    have also written to him fully.</p>
                <p>A French transport has arrived in the harbor of Alexandria with troops for
                    Cochin-China, who have been disembarked and have taken the railway for Suez.</p>
                <p>With regard to the question of the compulsory service of the soldiers in the
                    Egyptian army, and especially that of the blacks from the upper country, I
                    hardly know what I may say with propriety in an official communication. I have
                    reason to believe that Mr. Outrey, the agent and consul general here of France,
                    was annoyed at being called upon by Mr. Drouyn de Lhuys to make a report upon
                    this subject. Even to an entirely disinterested observer it might be difficult,
                    in a country where the civil government is absolute, to distinguish <pb
                        facs="0417" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> between compulsory service in the army
                    and military service everywhere; to distinguish between a levy in the Soudan and
                    the conscription in France. It would remain to weigh the evidence in such cases
                    as are reported to have occurred in filling the number of the contingent at
                    Alexandria in January, 1863. If the object desired is merely to satisfy the
                    private judgment of a candid observer, something might be learned from the
                    various books of modern travel in Egypt. The difficulties which embarrass the
                    subject when approached as a matter of discussion among governments are
                    illustrated by the fact—reported in my last despatch but one—of the frequent
                    release of negroes from slavery in Egypt by the interposition of the good
                    offices of the British consulates. The Egyptian government may point to these
                    instances as so many proofs in support of the assertion proudly made in the
                    minister’s answer to your observations, “Slavery no longer exists in Egypt;” for
                    whenever the consulates bring forward an instance of the contrary, the man is
                    immediately freed. Others would perhaps regard these instances as disproving the
                    proposition insisted on, or at least as illustrating that it is not of universal
                    application.</p>
                <p>I shall endeavor to collect the most authentic and also the most available
                    testimony within my reach, without loss of time, but should be glad of your
                    instructions as to the manner and degree in which it may be advisable to push
                    inquiries.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES HALE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">A.</note>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Affairs,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cairo,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Monsieur l’Agent et Consul Genéral:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have gladly received the despatch which you did me the honor to address me
                        under date of the 20th October last, for the purpose of presenting in the
                        name of your government the observations suggested to it by the expedition
                        by his Highness of a battalion of negroes, of which the departure has been
                        hitherto delayed by an insurrection in the Soudan, now suppressed, and who
                        are destined to replace in Mexico those who were sent thither in 1863.</p>
                    <p>If your government had not thought proper to make any remark previously on
                        this subject, you say this was because the government was too much occupied
                        with internal affairs, and also because it had not then decreed the
                        abolition of slavery. The government of his Highness, whose sympathies for
                        that of the republic of the United States cannot be doubted for a moment,
                        accordingly thinks it of the first importance to give explanations to the
                        latter, which I take pleasure in believing will reassure it completely with
                        regard to the bearing and the composition of the expedition in question. In
                        fact, the situation of 1863 has not been modified; there has been no change
                        to affect it. The Egyptian government, at the request of a friendly power,
                        thought itself competent to make certain engagements in which its neutrality
                        did not appear to be in any way compromised, and in which it was very far
                        from thinking that it would ever incur the disapproval of the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>The French government, in making a request for the replacement of the
                        contingent now in service by a new battalion, of which the composition
                        remains exactly the same, and his Highness the viceroy, in agreeing to the
                        request, do but obey the laws of the simplest humanity. It is three years,
                        in fact, that these men have been living far from their country, where most
                        of them have left their wives and children; home-sickness (la nostalgie) has
                        made more gaps in their ranks than the climate or the fire of the enemy. In
                        all countries of the world such considerations are thought worthy of regard,
                        and the Egyptian government would have had a bad appearance not to accept
                        their significance. Moreover, it would have been very difficult, not to say
                        impossible, to escape the consequence of an agreement which put at the
                        disposal of the French expedition to Mexico a certain number of men, strong
                        and well-fitted for military service. The honor of the flag, and the respect
                        due to its engagements then, united in requiring that the government of his
                        Highness should receive with favor a request which had in its eyes the
                        advantage of restoring, not only to their native country, but to their
                        separate homes, a certain number of these men, who were chosen originally
                        from the soldiers of the garrisons of Cairo and Alexandria, and who had a
                        right to their discharge by reason of the expiration of the period of
                        service due to the state.</p>
                    <pb facs="0418" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/>
                    <p>In the material point of view, then, we have merely to deal with a simple
                        substitution, and there is, in truth, no reason for anxiety at a situation
                        which remains the same that has existed for three years past.</p>
                    <p>In the moral point of view, the objection appears to me still less
                        well-founded. It is based on the fact that, at the date of the first
                        expedition, the United States had not decreed the abolition of slavery.</p>
                    <p>Thus, in the opinion of the cabinet of Washington, the Egyptian soldiers who
                        make part of the French expedition to Mexico are to be regarded as slaves,
                        and their stay there as contradicting the great measure of humanity which
                        has freed all their brethren in America.</p>
                    <p>Permit me, sir, to protest on my side against the expression of an error so
                        clear. Slavery no longer exists in Egypt. It was abolished there long before
                        it was abolished in the United States by the many sacrifices and glorious
                        efforts on the part of the defenders of the Union. The negroes in the
                        Egyptian territory are subjects of his Highness by the same title and with
                        the same rights as the other natives of the country. In serving under our
                        flag they obey a law of conscription equal for all. Regulations limit the
                        period of service due by each man to the country, and the length of this
                        period is proportioned to the number of the population.</p>
                    <p>This is not all. In virtue of a principle made applicable as long ago as the
                        reign of our illustrious Mehemet Ali, all slaves enrolled under the flag
                        become free in full right.</p>
                    <p>The good conduct of some of these soldiers since they have been in Mexico has
                        been pointed out by the general-in-chief of the expedition to the French
                        government, which has not hesitated to award to them crosses and medals of
                        honor; others have been proposed to the Egyptian government by the same
                        general-in-chief for similar distinctions, and even for promotion to the
                        grade of superior officers, and the Egyptian government has made haste to
                        recognize their merit.</p>
                    <p>I appeal to yourself, sir, is there a country in the world where soldiers who
                        were merely slaves would be treated with so much regard and would enjoy so
                        much consideration?</p>
                    <p>I rely, then, with all confidence on your co-operation to make known the
                        details, to transmit these loyal explanations to the government of the
                        United States, and to reassure it respecting the true condition of these
                        Egyptian negroes. I take pleasure in hoping that, better informed than
                        before, your government will be good enough to see nothing in this
                        expedition but the simple replacement of one battalion by another in
                        conformity with the terms of an understanding; a replacement of which the
                        necessity is demanded by the laws of humanity and the rules of justice; at
                        the same time that it is imposed upon his Highness by the benevolent
                        interest which he feels for all his subjects without distinction.</p>
                    <p>Be pleased to accept, sir, the assurance of my high consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi> CHERIF
                            PACHA.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">B.</note>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate General of the United
                                    States of America in Egypt,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Alexandria,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-10-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 20, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>YOUR EXCELLENCY: At an audience which his Highness, accorded me on the 25th
                        of August last, he was so good as to give me some explanations about the
                        circumstances under which the Egyptian government proposes to send nine
                        hundred negroes to Mexico to replace the troops of the same kind which were
                        sent there in the month of January, 1863.</p>
                    <p>Having thereupon made report to my government, without failing to set forth
                        the noble frankness with which his Highness expressed himself in giving me
                        on this subject all the details without reserve, I have just received
                        instructions from my government.</p>
                    <p>I must say to you that the previous expedition in 1863, although it may have
                        made room for many comments, was let pass by the government of the United
                        States of America without remark, because it was at that time very much
                        engaged with exceptionally complicated domestic affairs and with foreign
                        difficulties. But since that epoch the United States have abolished slavery.
                        Our attention is steadily fixed on the course of events in Mexico, a subject
                        which seriously affects the security of republican institutions on the
                        American continent, with which we are accustomed to connect the
                        so-much-desired ulterior consequences of the abolition of all compulsory
                        servitude, civil or military, in the western hemisphere.</p>
                    <p>I am therefore ordered, Mr. Minister, to bring the affair to your attention,
                        and to say to you that, in the opinion of my government, the repetition of
                        an expedition of Egyptian negroes to Mexico would not be regarded with
                        approval, nor even without profound inquietude by the United States.</p>
                    <p>I must also inform your excellency that instructions of the same character
                        have been sent to the diplomatic representatives of the United States at
                        Paris and at Constantinople.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to renew to your excellency the assurance of my high
                        consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="italic">Agent and Consul General,</hi> CHARLES HALE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Cherif Pacha,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0419" n="337" xml:id="pg_337"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">D.</note>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate General of the United
                                    States of America in Egypt,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Hotel des Ambassadeurs, Cairo,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency:</hi> In submitting to you the
                        translation, here enclosed, of a despatch from our minister at Paris,
                        addressed to the minister of foreign affairs at Washington, you will readily
                        understand that it is not precisely an official communication that I make to
                        you.</p>
                    <p>I await your answer to my official note of 20th October, written under
                        special instructions from my government; meantime I make known to you what
                        has passed.</p>
                    <p>You will understand that I have only made mention to my government of a new
                        expedition to replace the troops which are already in Mexico. The despatch
                        of the 20th of September, of which our minister at Paris in the beginning of
                        the letter here enclosed and also at the end under No. 1, was of the same
                        purport with that addressed at the same time to me, and which I communicated
                        to you under date of the 20th October. I pray you especially to take note of
                        the language of my government.</p>
                    <p>I should say to you that, whatever may be the reason, that which is necessary
                        to tranquillize public opinion with us would be to learn that his Highness
                        has been pleased to declare that he does not intend to renew the expedition
                        of Egyptian soldiers to Mexico. A replacing would be considered as a
                        renewal.</p>
                    <p>If you wish to make a reserve in respect of your rights in the manner of Mr.
                        Drouyn de Lhuys, by saying that the expedition is not abandoned, but that in
                        effect it will not take place in consequence of interior events in Egypt, I
                        would be satisfied, but naturally a definitive abandonment would give us
                        great pleasure. France, as I believe, would not make objections; with us in
                        America it would be considered as a fresh proof of the friendship of his
                        Highness, and by all the world it will be deemed a noble proof of his wisdom
                        in the interests of humanity.</p>
                    <p>Provided that the service of Egyptian negroes in Mexico is not slavery, it
                        may be admitted that it is not at all agreeable to the soldiers, as his
                        Highness told me with all frankness possible in expressing to me his wish to
                        change the men sent by others.</p>
                    <p>I seize this occasion to renew to you the assurance of my high
                        consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES HALE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">E.</note>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs, Cabinet of the
                                    Minister,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Cairo,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Consul</hi> GENERAL: I have just received your
                        despatch of the 16th, and the translation of the document therein referred
                        to.</p>
                    <p>For the present I can only refer to our conversation of this morning in
                        repeating that your despatch of to-day carries the question into a new
                        phase, which the government of his Majesty reserves to itself to examine.
                        Meanwhile I restrict myself to sending you my official answer to your
                        esteemed despatch of 20th October last.</p>
                    <p>Please accept, Mr. Consul General, the assurance of my high
                        consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHERIF PACHA.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hale,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Agent and Consul General of the United States of
                                America.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
