<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bigelow to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="367"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[With two enclosures.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Bigelow</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 79.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 18, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to enclose a copy and a
                    translation of a “note verbale,” received from his excellency the minister of
                    foreign affairs, in relation to the seizure of the United States mail at
                    Acapulco by the French authorities.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, with great respect, your very obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN BIGELOW.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure No. 2.—Translation.]</head>
                    <p>Last November Mr. Dayton communicated to the Emperor’s minister of foreign
                        affairs a despatch in which the United States consul at Acapulco complained
                        that the commander of the French forces in that city had ordered the seizure
                        of the mail addressed to that consul. Positive information since received on
                        the subject by the imperial government enables it to present this incident
                        in its true light. It is necessary to state, in the first place, the exact
                        position occupied by Mr. Ely, then consul of the United States, after the
                        French troops had taken possession of Acapulco. That agent, by abstaining
                        from any visit or official communication in writing asserting his quality to
                        Admiral Bonet upon the latter’s arrival, authorized the supposition that his
                        exequatur having been granted not by Mexico, but by the local government of
                        the state of Guerrero, he considered his mission to be interrupted by the
                        new state of things. Admiral Bonet, therefore, considered Mr. Ely as having
                        no longer any attributions beyond those of a purely commercial agent. Such
                        was also the opinion of the commander of the United States sloop
                        Narragansett, as evidenced in his search for a deserter from that vessel, as
                        well as the opinion of Admiral Bell himself. This view of the subject
                        appears to be also confirmed by the fact of the federal government giving
                        only the title of commercial agent to the person appointed since as the
                        successor of Mr. Ely. Here, now, are the facts concerning the seizure of the
                        United States mails as they occurred:</p>
                    <p>Acapulco, previous to its being taken possession of by the French forces, had
                        no regularly organized postal service. Letters from abroad were brought
                        there by the packets of the Panama Steamship Mail Company in three separate
                        bags. The one addressed to the company’s agent contained letters relative to
                        the affairs of that concern; the second, the mails intending to go on
                        farther; and the third, the correspondence for Acapulco and the interior of
                        Mexico. This latter bag, for want of a regular postal agent, was addressed
                        to the <hi rend="italic">American consul,</hi> where the letters were
                        delivered to the parties concerned and the postage collected. Complaints had
                        occurred about deficiencies in the system of delivery of private letters,
                        but, aside from that consideration, it was impossible to permit this state
                        of things to continue from the moment that Acapulco was to follow the system
                        adopted every where else by the Mexican government. Where taxes were to be
                        levied it evidently belonged to a Mexican administration only to fulfil that
                        office. The officer commanding at Acapulco had, therefore, decided on
                        appointing a temporary postmaster, and his choice for this office fell upon
                        the vice-consul of France, M. Dupuy. This gentleman, therefore, upon the,
                        arrival of the packet from San Francisco, on the 30th of September, caused
                        the three mail bags, previously mentioned, to be delivered to himself. The
                        one addressed to the <hi rend="italic">American consul</hi> was open, and
                        its contents proved that, as we have already stated, it was not a mail
                        addressed by the government of the United States to their consul at
                        Acapulco, but simply an ordinary letter bag. This decision, however, called
                        forth some opposition at the hands of the commander of the federal sloop
                        Cyane, who, whilst acknowledging that Mr. Ely no longer had any right to
                        demand that the bag addressed to the <hi rend="italic">American consul</hi>
                        should be delivered to him, asked that it should be given to himself, who,
                        as an officer of the United States navy, was the legal representative of his
                        government. After explanations on the subject had passed between the
                        commander of the Cyane and the commander of the French naval forces, these
                        two officers, equally desirous of maintaining the friendly relations
                        existing between the navies of the two countries, agreed that the bag should
                        be delivered to the post office of Acapulco, and there opened in the
                        presence of an officer of the United States sloop, who would thus ascertain
                        that it was only a public mail, and not an official correspondence of the
                        government of the United States.</p>
                    <p>This question had thus been disposed of in the most satisfactory manner, when
                        subsequent events prevented this arrangement being carried out. M. Dupuy,
                        the postmaster appointed, <pb facs="0473" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> having
                        seen fit to resign that office, and the evacuation of Acapulco having been
                        resolved upon, things were put back in their former position. This,
                        nevertheless, shows that the measures adopted at the time when the French
                        forces took possession of Acapulco were fully justified both by the
                        irregularity of the process of delivery of private correspondence and by the
                        absence of any real right of Mr. Ely to demand that the system should be
                        continued.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 12, 865.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
