<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Romero to  to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d561</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">561</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-06-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="561" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d561">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Romero</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexican Legation In The United
                                            States Of America, Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-06-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 12, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.</hi> Secretary: There has come into my hands
                                a memorandum which contains some considerations on the question
                                about Mexico, treated from the point of view of the laws of nations
                                in what regards the United States. Without expressing at present any
                                opinion respecting it, much less asking it from the government of
                                the United States, I confine myself to sending to you a copy of said
                                memorandum.</p>
                <p>I avail of this opportunity to renew to you, Mr. Secretary, the
                                assurance of my most distinguished consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. ROMERO.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Whatever were the causes which led to the war between France and
                                    Mexico, when it occurred it assumed the character of a war
                                    between two sovereign and independent nations. In <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a war the United States had no right
                                    to interfere, for, in accordance with established principles of
                                    international law, the federal government was in duty bound to
                                    observe a strict neutrality. But after the occupation of the
                                    city of Mexico by the French, their real policy and intentions
                                    were unmasked. New tactics were at once adopted, which changed
                                    the entire aspect of affairs.</p>
                    <p>Former grievances were lost sight of; claims for indemnities and
                                    spoliations ceased to be the order of the day. Assisted by a few
                                    leading and influential Mexicans, France set to work to remodel
                                    the political status of the country, and succeeded in organizing
                                    an imperial party, representing the minority, in opposition to
                                    the republican party, representing the majority. Hostilities
                                    ensued between the two, and <hi rend="italic">civil war</hi> was
                                    inaugurated. In his last annual message to Congress, President
                                    Lincoln, alluding to the situation of affairs in Mexico, took
                                    this view in declaring that <hi rend="italic">civil war</hi> was
                                    still raging in that country.</p>
                    <p>This change of policy on the part of France changed the position
                                    of the United States in reference to the Mexican question. The
                                    war assumed a new form, and, from one waged between two nations,
                                    degenerated into a struggle for supremacy between two parties.
                                    If the French considered themselves justified in maintaining by
                                    force of arms one of these parties, the United States had
                                    undoubtedly the right to give their support to the other.
                                    International law no longer compelled them to observe a
                                    neutrality.</p>
                    <p>What was the result of this state of things? Simply that the
                                    imperial party, supported by French bayonets, and countenanced
                                    by other European governments, who suffered the newly-proclaimed
                                    sovereign of Mexico to contract loans and enlist soldiers in
                                    their midst, obtained the ascendancy over an adversary who was
                                    fighting, and still continues to fight, alone, unaided even with
                                    the moral support of the United States.</p>
                    <p>The United States have always proclaimed themselves to be the
                                    protectors of their sister<pb facs="0686" n="604" xml:id="pg_604"/>republics on the American continent What
                                    hopes can the latter entertain of their future security when
                                    they see a great republic, of which they are the feeble
                                    imitators, assisting with indifference to the spectacle of a
                                    handful of foreign soldiers successfully progressing, on her
                                    very borders, in the work of erecting a government framed and
                                    fashioned on the European plan? What will be their reflections
                                    when they discover that the United States have nothing but words
                                    to offer to friends steadfast in their attachment from motives
                                    both of interest and sympathy?</p>
                    <p>If, through the instrumentality of the United States, a republic
                                    should be reared and fostered on the frontiers of France or of
                                    Russia, would these nations be indifferent to the event and
                                    accept the situation? Unquestionably not. For similar and more
                                    cogent reasons the United States cannot suffer the
                                    establishment, on the confines of their territory, of a monarchy
                                    created and maintained by foreign arms.</p>
                    <p>The United States have no more co-operated in safeguarding and
                                    perpetuating republican institutions in Mexico than the
                                    diminutive States of Central America, who have thought it
                                    sufficient to protest against this interference and encroachment
                                    on the part of European powers. But what may seem a matter of
                                    satisfaction to the pride of those states cannot be regarded in
                                    that light by so great and formidable a nation as the United
                                    States. The question at issue cannot remain in suspense; the
                                    United States must pursue one course or another—either to
                                    interfere actively in behalf of republican principles, and
                                    against the French occupation in Mexico, or to recognize
                                    Maximilian, and concede forever to European nations the right of
                                    an armed intervention in the domestic concerns of the republics
                                    on the American continent. Let the United States make this
                                    sacrifice, for they will then at least be spared, in the eyes of
                                    the world, the ridicule and mortification of not possessing the
                                    requisite energy to handle and settle a question of paramount
                                    interest to themselves, and in which the right is incontestably
                                    on their side.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
