<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Romero to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="565"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Romero</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexican Legation in the United States of America,
                                Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-07-23">23<hi rend="italic">d of
                                July,</hi> 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: In virtue of the recommendation which
                    you were pleased to make to me at the interview which we had yesterday at the
                    Department of State, to the effect that I should state to you in writing what I
                    verbally had the honor to represent to you, I now proceed to make to you the
                    following statement:</p>
                <p>You know very well with how much anxiety the government of Mexico has been
                    awaiting the termination of the civil war in the United States—since our fate
                    being identified to a certain extent with that of the Union, the success of the
                    latter insured our own, whilst its overthrow would have made our situation more
                    difficult. In fact, the French intervention in Mexico having been, as is already
                    universally admitted, nothing else than a part of the conspiracy which was
                    planned to subvert this government and to break up this country, nothing is more
                    natural than that the principal question in the United States, when once decided
                    in favor of republican institutions, the accessory one, which is being discussed
                    in Mexico, should be decided in the same sense. The success, therefore, of the
                    cause of the independence of Mexico is already beyond all doubt, even to the
                    eyes of the most determined enemies of the republic, and it has now become only
                    a question of time. The duty which the Mexican government has to shorten that
                    time as much as may be possible causes me to address this communication to
                    you.</p>
                <p>We had believed that when once the civil war had terminated here, which from its
                    magnitude and importance had absorbed the whole attention of the government of
                    the United States, without permitting it to take the measures necessary to
                    destroy those accessory to the rebellion which were developing themselves in
                    foreign countries, the same government would have to pursue one of these two
                    policies—either to take the steps it might deem proper in order that the French
                    should withdraw themselves from Mexico, or to follow the same policy of
                    neutrality observed up to this period, until peace is finally restored at home
                    and the federal authority is established in the southern States, thus giving
                    time to the Emperor of the French to the endthat, reconsidering his measures, he
                    may abandon an enterprise which is already without object, and which it is
                    utterly impossible to realize, and which, should he persist in it, will involve
                    him most certainly in future complications with the United States, which, when
                    once at peace, will not be able to remain an indifferent spectator of the
                    conquest by a European power of one of the principal regions of this continent
                    in their immediate vicinity.</p>
                <p>Upon the choice of these two policies I shall say nothing at this time, for I do
                    not propose in this note to solicit from this government the adoption of the one
                    or of the other. My object is solely to manifest that the time necessary <pb
                        facs="0721" n="639" xml:id="pg_639"/> having already elapsed to know which
                    of them has been adopted, we have believed that it is the second; and in this
                    belief, being unable to rely for the time being even upon the moral support of
                    the government to put an end to the war carried on against us by the Emperor of
                    the French, we deem it our duty to inform the government of the United States of
                    what we desire to do in this country in the fulfilment of our duties as
                    Mexicans.</p>
                <p>In the first place, I deem it my duty to represent to you that, although the
                    patriotism of the Mexican people is a sufficient guarantee to insure us success
                    over our invaders, and although we have in our country sufficient elements to
                    defend our independence—which elements have enabled us to resist during four
                    years the most persistent efforts of the first military nation of Europe, and
                    will enable us to prolong the contest to the point of compelling our enemies to
                    leave our country—our situation is such that the French might be enabled to
                    remain some years more in Mexico, if they persist in it and our condition does
                    not ameliorate.</p>
                <p>It is known that the people of Mexico is without arms. As arms are not
                    manufactured in the republic, we are compelled to use those which we may be
                    enabled to import. The circumstance that some of our ports are occupied and
                    others blockaded by the French, and, above all, the fact that this government
                    had prohibited, to our prejudice, the exportation of arms from the United
                    States, and that we could not obtain them in Europe, because almost all the
                    governments of that continent are hostile to our cause, has caused the
                    government of Mexico, from the commencement of the war, to find itself with a
                    small quantity of muskets, and these in so bad a condition that it is really
                    surprising how the resistance has been prolonged with implements so utterly
                    worthless.</p>
                <p>The principal, and almost exclusive, revenues of the Mexican government being
                    derived from the yield of maritime custom-houses of the republic, and the most
                    valuable of these being occupied or blockaded by the French, it follows that the
                    government of the republic has found itself deprived of its revenues in times
                    when it most required them to organize and sustain the armies which defend the
                    independence of the country.</p>
                <p>Our situation therefore is, to sum up, the following: with arms and means we can
                    terminate in a few months the war which France is waging against us; and without
                    these elements, we shall be obliged to limit ourselves to resisting the French,
                    who will be enabled to remain in Mexico for an indefinite period, with great
                    danger to the peace of this continent, until they find themselves compelled to
                    quit that country through weariness, if not expelled by the force of arms.</p>
                <p>You will understand, Mr. Secretary, that it is the duty of the Mexican government
                    to shorten the war, and to do all that is incumbent upon it to procure the
                    necessary elements to attain that result. The identity of interests existing
                    respecting this point between the United States and Mexico, and, above all, the
                    great sympathy which, with unparalleled unanimity, the people of the United
                    States have manifested, even in the most unfortunate days of the Union, for the
                    cause of the independence of Mexico, have led the Mexican government to believe
                    that, by rendering this sympathy effective, those elements might be derived from
                    it which are required to terminate immediately a war which otherwise might last
                    for years, and all this without compromitting in any manner the government of
                    the United States, and without causing it to deviate, by a single hair’s
                    breadth, from the duties incumbent upon it as a neutral power. Although in the
                    realization of this idea we propose to ourselves to treat with the citizens of
                    this country as individuals, without in any manner compromitting their
                    government, and although what we think of doing is entirely lawful and
                    compatible with the attitude occupied by the United States as a power neutral
                    towards France, we deem it proper to submit our plans to the government of the
                    United States, as a proof of our good faith, of our deference to this
                    government, and with <pb facs="0722" n="640" xml:id="pg_640"/> the view of
                    receiving assurances, if this be possible, that no embarrassment will be placed
                    in our way in the execution thereof, since a painful experience has taught us
                    the necessity of taking this step. Reserving, therefore, the consideration of
                    other matters, when circumstances shall require it, our wishes are limited for
                    the present to the two following points:</p>
                <p>1st. To negotiate a loan to the government of Mexico in this market, by disposing
                    of bonds which shall contain the guarantees which we consider sufficient to
                    induce speculators to purchase them, and which may make them acceptable to the
                    people of this country. It is indubitable that the duties of a neutral power do
                    not impose upon the United States that of preventing us from realizing our
                    bonds, since this does not constitute the intervention of this government in our
                    behalf. The market is as much, open to us as to our enemies. If the French
                    desire to negotiate a loan here upon the same basis as we—that is, as a private
                    speculation, with which the government has nothing to do—evidently there would
                    be no right to deny it the same. This same right is the one which we wish to
                    exercise now. Our deference towards the government of the United States has
                    reached the point that, notwithstanding we have had a pressing necessity for the
                    funds which such a loan could have furnished us, and that there was a time which
                    seemed most propitious for its realization, we preferred to await until the loan
                    with the United States, which the house of Messrs. Jay Cooke &amp; Co., of
                    Philadelphia, is now selling, should be realized, in order not to appear to be
                    acting in competition with the United States, and desirous of diverting the
                    funds of its citizens to exterior objects while they were needed by their own
                    government.</p>
                <p>2d. To purchase arms and munitions of war, and to be enabled to export them to
                    such places as may seem to us proper. After the order of the President of the 3d
                    of May last, which rescinded the prohibition to export arms from the United
                    States, and which has left in all their force the laws and traditions of this
                    country respecting the commerce of belligerents in articles contraband of war,
                    and, above all, after the precedent established by this government of permitting
                    the French officers who arrived in November, 1862, to purchase the means of
                    transportation for the invading army of Mexico, who purchased and exported the
                    articles they needed to wage war against my country, as your department
                    communicated to me in the note which it addressed to me upon this subject under
                    date of the 24th of November aforesaid, it does appear that there cannot be the
                    least cause that we should not be permitted now to do what the laws of this
                    country declare in every respect lawful, and what this government has permitted
                    to our enemies.</p>
                <p>I do not doubt that the government of the United States will appreciate the
                    sincerity of the motives which induce me to address it this note, and that it
                    will favor me with a reply which will be entirely satisfactory to my
                    government.</p>
                <p>I avail myself with pleasure of this opportunity to renew to you, Mr. Secretary,
                    the assurances of my most distinguished consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. ROMERO.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
