<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-11-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="588" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d588">
                            <head><persName type="from">The Minister of Foreign Affairs</persName>
                                to <persName type="to">the French Minister at
                                Washington</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-29"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 29, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. LE Marquis:</hi> I have had a conversation
                                recently with Mr. Bigelow, of which I think it well to give you the
                                substance. In that conversation the United States minister
                                enumerated the reasons the cabinet at Washington had for not
                                establishing diplomatic relations with the Mexican government. The
                                origin of that government, the antagonism between its form and the
                                republican institutions of the neighboring country, and the small
                                progress the emperor Maximilian would make in the affection and
                                confidence of his subjects, these are the three motives that oppose,
                                according to Mr. Bigelow, the relations we desire.</p>
                            <p>The representative of the federal government at the same time
                                criticised certain measures adopted in Mexico. He quoted to me
                                particularly the decree relative to the suppression of brigandage,
                                and one other concerning the introduction of blacks; then he
                                mentioned the sinister interpretations that might be given to the
                                honors accorded to the Iturbide family, and expressed to me the
                                unfavorable sentiments that all these resolutions would cause in the
                                American people.</p>
                            <p>Although the greater portion of this question was not new, I thought
                                I had better answer it. I will not return, I said to Mr. Bigelow, to
                                the causes that determined the Mexican expedition. These causes are
                                the same that carried the federal flag to Mexico some years ago. A
                                double question of interest and dignity forced us to resort to arms,
                                after uselessly exhausting all other means to have justice done to
                                our citizens. Finding neither reparations for the past nor
                                guarantees for the future in Mr. Jaurez’s administration, we were
                                happy to see the Mexican people assume a new government, and
                                faithful to the maxims of our public law we applauded that
                                manifestation of the national will. Our army has not exercised the
                                least force upon that great act, and the new government once
                                established, we have made ourselves an absolute law to respect its
                                independence.</p>
                            <p>The monarchical form, far from constituting an innovation, is rooted
                                in the traditions of the country, and the other system of government
                                did not assure the Mexican nation enough strength, comfort, and
                                stability to cause us to blame it for the resolution it has taken.
                                We do not dispute the greatness and prosperity that republican
                                institutions have given to the United States; but there is nothing
                                absolute in politics, and a government that suits one country may
                                not suit another. It is very certain that there was nothing but
                                disorder and anarchy in Mexico previous to the new rule. Was not the
                                cabinet at Washington the first to complain of that violent and
                                troubled situation? Was not its interest, like that of all other
                                powers, to see a more normal order of things, and more in harmony
                                with the conditions of vitality of modern societies, established in
                                that country? A monarchical form is certainly a menace to nobody. An
                                empire in Mexico is certainly not more incompatible with the dignity
                                of the United States than an empire in Brazil. There is, besides, in
                                this affair a principle that governs all others—the privilege of
                                every nation to choose its own political rule, and the United States
                                have certainly too just a sentiment of their own independence to
                                wish to control that of their neighbors.</p>
                            <p>As to the degree of confidence and affection that the Mexican nation
                                feels for its sovereign, the reports that reach us do not agree with
                                those received by the cabinet at Washington. I understand that the
                                new government is daily growing stronger; that Jaurez, whose term
                                has just expired, represents nothing, not even in the eyes of his
                                few followers; that constantly changing his residence, having
                                neither army nor finances nor administration, he is, in fact as well
                                as in law, clothed with no characters that constitute the chief of a
                                state. Can the emperor Maximilian, then, under these circumstances,
                                accord the rights of belligerents to bands still in the field? Did
                                not the federal government deny that quality to the confederates of
                                the south? And yet the confederacy had a vast territory, powers
                                obeyed everywhere, generals of rare talent, armies that the federal
                                troops could only conquer by patience and courage. The pretended
                                authority of Juarez, on the contrary, is but a fiction. Where is the
                                seat of his government? Who knows the names of his functionaries or
                                of his officers? What province or what city is subject to him? Where
                                are the regular traces of his administration? What remains of it but
                                undisciplined bands that live by robbery? If the remnants of the
                                southern armies were to form to-day bands to overrun the federal
                                territory, would the United States treat them as belligerents? In
                                such a situation there is no question of international law, the
                                question is internal, and the first duty of a government well
                                organized is to maintain order in the country.</p>
                            <pb facs="0781" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/>
                            <p>As to the Iturbide family, I have nothing to say to the reasons that
                                influenced the spontaneous decision of the emperor Maximilian. He
                                might have desired to raise the once illustrious name from
                                obscurity, and his resolution might have been inspired by a
                                sentiment of benevolence and respect for the historic recollections
                                of the Mexican nation. I will say, by the way, that it is untrue
                                that the rights of succession have been conferred upon young
                                Iturbide.</p>
                            <p>Moreover, if certain measures adopted in Mexico provoke the criticism
                                of the cabinet at Washington, they ought not to call us to account
                                for it. Autonomical and independent, the Mexican government is
                                responsible for its own acts. True, our troops are still in Mexico;
                                but the aid we lend to the emperor Maximilian constitutes in no
                                manner a bond of vassalism.</p>
                            <p>In giving you this summary of my conversation with Mr. Bigelow, I
                                desire, now that Congress is about to meet, to enable you to rectify
                                the erroneous opinions that might be conceived around you, and I
                                authorize you to make use of the present despatch in your
                                conversations with Mr. Seward and the political personages of the
                                Union.</p>
                            <p>Accept, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>DEOUYN DE LHUYS</signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>