<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Romero to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d598</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">598</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Munitions of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="598"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d598">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Romero</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Mexico In The United States Of
                                America</hi>, <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 14, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary:</hi> I have the honor of transmitting a copy
                    of a note from the consul of the Mexican republic in San Francisco, dated on the
                    17th of October last, which I received to-day, with the annexed documents.</p>
                <p>It appears from these that General McDowell, commanding the military department
                    of California, issued a General Order, No. 17, on the 11th of last October,
                    containing a declaration in regard to the exportation of arms that will
                    certainly cause a violation of the neutrality the United States wishes to
                    observe in the present war on Mexican territory. The order is contrary to the
                    laws of this country, which allow the export of arms and munitions of war for
                    belligerent nations, when the United States are neutral; and you sent me these
                    laws in your communication of the 24th of November, 1862, in reply to mine of
                    the same month, informing your department that several French officers had
                    visited New York and New Orleans for the purpose of purchasing articles
                    contraband of war for the French army invading Mexico. And, moreover, I have no
                    doubt that these laws or declarations are the only ones now in force, as
                    applicable to the exportation of arms from this country to Mexico, since the
                    revocation of the order prohibiting the exportation of arms from the United
                    States; for Mr. Hunter, in charge of the Department of State, told me so in the
                    President’s name, in his note of the 12th of May last.</p>
                <p>Now, the instructions given by the Secretary of the Treasury, Mr. Hamilton, the
                    4th of August, 1793, of which you sent me a copy with your note before
                    mentioned, authorize the <hi rend="italic">exportation</hi> of those articles,
                    and I understand <hi rend="italic">exportation</hi> to mean sending out of the
                    country, whether by land or sea. So, if any distinction is made in the
                    interpretation of this law to the injury of Mexico, I sincerely hope the
                    government of the United States will remove it, so as to preserve the <hi
                        rend="italic">bona fide</hi> neutrality it intends to maintain in this war,
                    of which the Mexican republic is now the stage.</p>
                <p>As General McDowell did not deem it proper to revoke his order on the
                    representations of the Mexican consul in San Francisco, I am compelled to appeal
                    to your excellency, and ask you to forward to that general the necessary
                    instructions for the preservation of the neutrality proclaimed by his government
                    in the department consigned to his command.</p>
                <p>This appeal to you is the more urgent, as the papers of to-day publish a
                    telegram, apparently from good authority, asserting that the United States
                    government will extend the effect of General McDowell’s order, intended only for
                    his department, along the entire frontier.</p>
                <p>I cannot for a moment believe that this is true; and I hope you will enable me to
                    give my government the necessary explanations to quiet apprehension <pb
                        facs="0790" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> in this particular, and not shake the
                    confidence it has in the honest intentions of the United States as a
                    neutral.</p>
                <p>I embrace this occasion of renewing to you, Mr. Secretary, the assurances of my
                    distinguished consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. ROMERO.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >&amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure No. 1.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of Mexico In San Francisco</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">San Francisco</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-10-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 17, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> After calling twice at General McDowell’s
                        office, I had the good fortune to meet him yesterday.</p>
                    <p>I told him his order of the 11th instant, published with evidences of
                        displeasure in the city papers, had attracted my attention; that the order
                        disturbed (violated) the strict neutrality proclaimed by the President of
                        the United States between belligerent parties in Mexico, as it favored the
                        French, now holding the Pacific ports.</p>
                    <p>General McDowell said, as he always has done, that he felt the profoundest
                        sympathy for Mexico; that he wanted the republic to triumph in this
                        struggle; but the neutrality laws compelled him to act in the manner he did.
                        He said I might complain to his superior. I then told him I thought it best
                        to apply to him first, before writing a note about the affair, and learn the
                        reasons he had for issuing the order in question; and afterwards I would
                        appeal to General Halleck, his superior, as he advised me.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with this understanding with General McDowell, who, during our
                        interview, was most polite and courteous, I addressed him yesterday the note
                        of which I send you a copy, and also <hi rend="smallcaps">a</hi> translation
                        of the order referred to; and I now await his reply to forward it to
                        you.</p>
                    <p>I protest my esteem and distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOSÉ A. GODOY, <hi rend="italic">Consul</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Citizen <hi rend="smallcaps">Matias Romero</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Envoy
                                Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of Mexico in
                                Washington</hi>,</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure No. 2.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of Mexico In San Francisco</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">San Francisco</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-10-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 16, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, consul of the Mexican republic in this port, has the honor
                        of calling be attention of General Irvin McDowell, commander-in-chief of the
                        department of California, to his order of the 11th instant, published in the
                        papers of this city. By that order the sending of arms and munitions of war
                        into México across the United States border is prohibited, in regard to the
                        neutrality towards the belligerents in Mexico.</p>
                    <p>As the exportation of arms is now allowed by the government in Washington,
                        that order seems to the undersigned to favor one of the parties—namely, the
                        French; for, as the ports on the Pacific are held by the invader of Mexico,
                        the constitutional government, the only one recognized by the United States,
                        has no other way than the frontier, which is now closed. Thus, general, the
                        strict neutrality, so often announced by the government at Washington,
                        ceases; and the consequence is, the usurping party, which the brave people
                        of this great republic are endeavoring to drive out, is favored.</p>
                    <p>The consul undersigned hopes General McDowell will please revoke his order of
                        the 11th instant, in conformity with the declaration of the President of the
                        United States, permitting the export of arms and munitions of war. This is
                        what the undersigned told General McDowell in the interview to-day.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned assures General McDowell of his esteem and distinguished
                        consideration.</p>
                    <p rend="right">JOSÉ A. GODOY.</p>
                    <p>General <hi rend="smallcaps">Irvin McDowell</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Commander-in-chief the Department of California</hi>,</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San Francisco</hi>,</placeName>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 16, 1865.</p>
                    <p>A true copy:</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOSÉ A. GODOY.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0791" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure No. 3.]</head>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">California neutrality in Mexican affairs.—A specimen of
                            British neutrality on the Pacific. —The United States authorities
                            conniving at the furnishing of arms to Maximilian.—They refuse to allow
                            any to pass the frontier to the liberal party, &amp;c.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Our San Francisco correspondence.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">San Francisco</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-10-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 13, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I have already informed you of some of the measures taken by the liberalists
                        of Mexico to supply themselves with arms from San Francisco. It would seem
                        that the proclamation of the withdrawal of the prohibition of the shipment
                        of arms to other countries by the United States government was to be
                        twisted, after all, so as to mean really nothing, the benefits being all
                        given to the French, who are allowed to carry away what they please, while
                        the Mexicans are, as usual, to have no chance to help themselves The western
                        coast being in the hands of the French, of course no more arms can be
                        introduced by the Mexicans by water, and the overland route was the only one
                        left them. The presence of Juarez at El Paso was favorable to their plan of
                        introducing arms through Arizona, but it would seem that the commander of
                        the department of California, to which the district of Arizona is attached,
                        has arrived at the conclusion that it is his duty to interfere and negative
                        the orders of the War Department, a course of action highly beneficial to
                        the French and ruinous to the Mexicans. His order, which I have been
                        permitted to copy from the official document, is as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="right">[General Orders No. 17.]</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Department of California</hi>,</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="italic">San Francisco, California, October</hi> 11, 1865.</p>
                    <p>It is made the duty of the officers commanding the districts of Arizona and
                        southern California—while keeping in view the recent orders allowing the
                        exportation of arms and munitions of war—to instruct the commanders on the
                        southern frontiers, within the department, to take the necessary measures to
                        preserve the neutrality of the United States with respect to the parties
                        engaged in the existing war in Mexico, and to suffer no armed parties to
                        pass the frontier from the United States, <hi rend="italic">or suffer any
                            arms or munitions of war to be sent over the frontier to either
                            belligerent.</hi> This is not to prevent individuals from passing with
                        arms for their personal protection.</p>
                    <p>By command of Major General McDowell.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>R. C. DRUM, <hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>The words of the order are copied <hi rend="italic">verbatim</hi>, the
                            italics only being mine.</p>
                        <p>It will be seen at once that this order strikes directly at Juarez and
                                <hi rend="italic">at no me else.</hi> Maximilian can, of course, get
                            all the supplies he wants by sea, and we have already had two of his
                            ally’s war steamers (the French frigate Victoire and armed steam
                            transport Rhine) fitted up and furnished throughout with everything
                            required for immediate service at the United States navy yard at Mare
                            island.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
