<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-03-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Sanford</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 250.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Brussels,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-03-20"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 20, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Important modifications have been lately
                            made, and are likely hereafter to be introduced, in various of our
                            departments of administration; and these, as time and experience shall
                            test them, will, doubtless, require further changes and adaptations.</p>
                        <p>It has occurred to me that much useful information in aid thereof might
                            be procured abroad expeditiously and without expense to the government
                            through its public agents in Europe; especially in matters connected
                            with the department of our finances, where a new revenue system has been
                            introduced, and where a knowledge of the machinery and workings of
                            similar branches of administration in Europe would be likely tobe
                            valuable. Their system of collection of internal revenue, and of
                            accountability of collectors and receivers in particular, perfected by
                            the experience of centuries of taxation, could not but be a profitable
                            study to us.</p>
                        <p>It would afford me real pleasure to furnish any facts on these subjects
                            likely to be useful at home; and I would suggest that the best method to
                            procure them would be by a series of questions on specific points where
                            information is needed.</p>
                        <p>I have at different times, looking forward to our future requirements in
                            this field, made reports upon the systems and workings of different
                            branches of administration abroad. In Ex. Doc. 68, 33d Congress, in the
                            same volume with my report upon the Penal Code of Europe, is an extended
                            paper of mine upon the administrative changes introduced in France by
                            the republic and the empire. My despatches Nos. 68 and 177 (the former
                            published in Diplomatic Correspondence of 1862) accompanied,
                            respectively, reports upon the revenue system of this country, and the
                            recruiting systems of this and other countries. I have also prepared for
                            a congressional committee a paper upon the legislation of European
                            states touching bankruptcy, and for another a paper upon the military
                                <pb facs="0159" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/> schools of this country, and
                            this experience has convinced me that much of the labor in preparing
                            such documents might be saved if attention could be directed to the
                            precise points upon which information is most needed. Hence the
                            suggestion which I have taken the liberty to make to you.</p>
                        <p>We have now nearly passed the phase of war, and of solicitude touching
                            the action or opinion of Europe with respect to it and its consequent
                            labors, and we are about entering upon the important one of
                            reorganization and consolidation; and it seems to me that our agents
                            abroad could materially aid in laying and strengthening the bases of the
                            modified administrative system which the wants and changes of the past
                            four years have rendered necessary.</p>
                        <p>If I can be of assistance in that work, the department has but to command
                            my services.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your most obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>H. S. SANFORD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c.,
                                &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>