<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Gresham to Mr.
                                Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-10-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="124" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Gresham</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-10-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 27,
                            1893</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge your dispatch
                        of the 30th ultimo, in which you state that, on Lord Rosebery’s return to
                        London from Balmoral, you will continue your efforts for adequate and
                        concurrent action on the award of the Paris Tribunal. You also say:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>To suspend wholly, even for a single year, the seal catch on the islands
                            might be highly prejudicial to the United States or their lessees, and,
                            as in the provisional or temporary arrangement of May, 1893, between
                            Russia and Great Britain, a limit of 30,000 seals on the Russian islands
                            was agreed to, it would seem a very reasonable figure to adopt for the
                            catch on the Pribilof Islands, whose product has been supposed to be
                            about double that of the Russian islands. I would respectfully ask for
                            an expression of your views on this subject, and how far we ought to go
                            in restricting the seal catch on these islands.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>I sent you yesterday copy of the contract which secures to the North American
                        Commercial Company the exclusive right to take seal on the Pribilof Islands,
                        thinking it advisable that you should know the precise relations between the
                        United States and that company. The President is not now prepared to say how
                        far we ought to go in limiting the seal catch should Great Britain make a
                        demand of that kind. You are well informed on the subject of the seal
                        industry and all matters relating to it, and we rely with confidence upon
                        your judgment in dealing with Lord Rosebery. If Great Britain firmly insists
                        that only a limited number of seals shall be taken on the islands, and you
                        must yield or fail in the effort to obtain a satisfactory understanding for
                        concurrent action, you can report the fact to me, and I will communicate it
                        to the President for his direction.</p>
                <p>I have no doubt you will be impressed by the reply of the Japanese minister
                        when I asked him, in an informal conversation, if his Government was willing
                        to give its adhesion to the regulations recommended by the arbitrators. You
                        have the substance of that conversation in my instructions of the 24th
                        instant. I must say that the position of Japan seems to be reasonable. An
                        agreement between the United States, Great Britain, Russia, and Japan, of
                        the character suggested by the minister of the latter country, for the
                        protection of the seal north of a line reaching from California to Japan,
                        along the thirty-fifth degree of north latitude, would likely be respected
                        by other powers. It is very important that the two Governments should come
                        to an understanding which will secure the desired result before the next
                        sealing season begins, and it is not doubted here that you are striving to
                        accomplish that end.</p>
                <pb facs="0134" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/>
                <p>The Russian minister told me a day or two ago that, when informed of the
                        means adopted by the United’ States and Great Britain to give practical
                        effect to the regulations, his Government would without delay determine
                        whether or not it could give its adhesion, as requested. It may be that
                        other powers will not be willing to be bound by the regulations recommended
                        by the tribunal without knowing what means will be employed by the two
                        Governments for their enforcement.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Q. Gresham.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
