<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-01-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="457" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d457">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Bolet Peraza</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the Republic of Venezuela</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-01-11"><hi rend="italic">January 11, 1892</hi></date>.
                            (Received January 11.)</dateline></opener>
                    <p>Sir: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your excellency’s note of
                        the 7th instant, wherein you are pleased to reiterate your mention of the
                        provisions contained in the tariff law of October 1, 1890 (section 3),
                        whereby the President of the United States was authorized to conclude with
                        countries that produce sugar, molasses, coffee, tea, and hides treaties of
                        reciprocity granting exemption from duties to those articles when imported
                        into the United States. At the same time your excellency was pleased to
                        notify me, in order that I might inform my Government, that the President of
                        the United States will, on the 15th day of March next, issue the
                        proclamation referred to in the aforesaid third section of the tariff law,
                        declaring subject to <pb facs="0507" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/> import duties
                        the aforesaid articles from countries which at that date shall not have
                        concluded any reciprocity treaty with the United States. According to the
                        desire expressed by your excellency I have transmitted to my Government the
                        contents of the note to which I have the honor to refer, so that it may be
                        filed among the papers relative to the negotiations on the subject which are
                        going on at Caracas with the representative of the United States.</p>
                    <p>With sentiments, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">N. Bolet peraza.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>