<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum on the currency question in Samoa and the
                                resignation of Baron Senfft von Pilsach. (. (Communicated by the German embassy, November 28.))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d473</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">473</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588" lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="473" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d473">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum on the currency question in Samoa and the
                                resignation of Baron Senfft von Pilsach</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">Communicated by the German embassy, November 28.</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office, Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>,<lb/>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-11-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 20, 1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">[Navigators Islands, November 28.—Confidential, 79; section
                            2.]</p>
                <p rend="center">No. 1.</p>
                <p>During the time the three representatives of the treaty powers were
                            administering provisionally the customs and taxes in Apia, a resolution
                            of the consular court of last year fixed as follows the relative values
                            of coins receivable under Article <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>,
                            paragraph 4, of the Samoan treaty, for the payment of customs duties and
                            taxes, as compared with the denominations “dollars” and “cents” therein
                            used, namely: 1<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. =4 dollars and 86 cents; 20
                            marks =4 dollars and 76 cents; and 7 dollars Chilean currency =5 dollars
                            American currency.</p>
                <p>On the 3d of June last the municipal council, on the motion of the
                            president, resolved, in view of simplifying the accounts, to ask the
                            Samoan Government to notify that the 1<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. and the
                            20-mark piece should be taken to be of the same value as 5 dollars of
                            the American currency, and to make English and Chilean coins alone
                            receivable for the payment of customs duties and taxes, with the
                            provision that Chilean silver coins should, on account of the
                            considerable fluctuations in their value, be so receivable only up to
                            November 15 of this year.</p>
                <p>The consular court, to which this resolution was communicated for
                            concurrence, was in favor of postponing a settlement of the matter. The
                            municipal council, nevertheless, submitted the resolution to the chief
                            justice for decision, in accordance with the Samoan treaty, and stated
                            in the note submitting it that the members of the council were not quite
                            unanimous on the question itself, but agreed that it was not to the
                            interest of the inhabitants that coins of different values should be
                            receivable.</p>
                <p>The chief justice was, at the same time, requested to prepare a measure
                            in this sense and to lay it before the King for sanction. Herr
                            Cedercrantz rejected the request, but suggested that the municipal
                            council should bring the resolution before the Government in the form
                            oil a petition. This was done on the 24th July, and Baron von Senfft
                            advised the King to confirm the resolution, adding the provision that
                            American silver should also be receivable for the payment of customs
                            duties and taxes. The King agreed, but wished for form’s sake to submit
                            the matter for the decision of the Feipule (native council), who, he had
                            no doubt, would make no objection.</p>
                <p>On the 27th July Baron Senfft received from the King the surprising
                            information that the Feipule had passed a resolution that, from the 15th
                            November of this year, <hi rend="italic">English and American gold and
                                silver coins</hi> should alone be received into the public
                            treasuries. Baron Senfft von Pilsach did not bring this resolution of
                            the Feipule to the knowledge of the municipal council, assuming that the
                            resolution in question was invalid, because he, as adviser of the King,
                            had had no opportunity of explaining to the King the consequences it
                            would have. At a meeting of the municipal council, which took place the
                            next day, the chairman, in reply to a question put to <pb facs="0529" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/> him on the subject by a member, stated
                            that no final settlement of the currency question had yet been arrived
                            at. Acting on the instigation of the German member of the municipal
                            council, Herr Grevesmühl, who was accounted an opponent of the chairman,
                            the King, with whom Herr Grevesmühl had had private communication, sent
                            to Baron von Senift on the 1st August a formal confirmation of the
                            resolution adopted by the Government on the 27th July, which Herr von
                            Pilsach again, and for the same motives as those given above, refrained
                            from communicating to the municipal council. On the representations of
                            Herr von Pilsach, who pointed out that, under Article <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi> of the treaty, the Government was not
                            justified in adopting such a resolution without the sanction of the
                            treaty powers, the King, Malietoa, declared himself ready to move the
                            Feipule to cancel it. At a meeting of the consular court, Baron von
                            Senfft gave an account of the circumstances of the case, and declared
                            that, in view of the provisions of Article <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>,
                            paragraph 4, of the Samoan treaty, the resolution adopted by the
                            Government, whereby German money was excluded, was invalid. The German
                            and English representatives concurred in this view but Mr. Blacklock,
                            the American consul, expressed no opinion.</p>
                <p>The Feipule did not cancel its resolution, notwithstanding Herr von
                            Senfft’s endeavors to induce it to do so. Malietoa informed the three
                            consuls of this fact by identical notes, and inquired at the same time
                            whether the conjecture of the chairman of the municipal council, that
                            the resolution was opposed to the provisions of the Samoan treaty, were
                            correct. The three consuls answered this note separately, and the German
                            consul alone stated that the resolution which the Government had adopted
                            was contrary to the provisions of the Samoan treaty. The English
                            consul’s answer avoided the point “that he was not at present prepared
                            to object to the same resolution,” and the American consul accepted the
                            resolution, “no reason to complain.” On the 12th of August the municipal
                            council resolved that the rates mentioned at the commencement of the
                            present paper, which had been established by the three consuls in 1890,
                            should again be put in force for payments into the municipal treasury,
                            but that no higher payment than $10 might be made in silver. The
                            consular court altered this resolution in the sense that German and
                            English silver should not be received at all, but that American and
                            Chilean silver should be received to an unlimited extent. The municipal
                            council declared against Baron von Senfft’s note, that they were
                            agreeable to this arrangement, and in a joint note of the 25th of August
                            the three consuls informed the King of this resolution. Baron von Senfit
                            considered this direct communication on the part of the consuls as an
                            encroachment on his rights, and on the 5th ultimo he placed in the
                            King’s hands his resignation of his post of chairman of the municipal
                            council, adding that he would continue to discharge his functions until
                            measures had been taken otherwise to provide for them.</p>
                <p>Such renunciation of his post by himself alone remains inoperative so
                            long as the authorities who appointed Baron von Senfft to the
                            chairmanship of the municipal council do not accept it. He was appointed
                            under an understanding with the treaty powers by the imperial
                            chancellor, and the imperial chancellor thinks it deisrable that, in the
                            interest of peace and good order in the Samoan Islands, Baron von Senfit
                            should remain at his post.</p>
                <p>In support of his resignation Baron von Senfft alleges that he can not
                            hope to do useful work at Apia now; that he no longer possesses the
                            confidence of the King, who has publicly passed him over and followed
                            the advice of irresponsible persons. He is convinced that this would not
                            have happened had he found in the representatives of the three treaty
                            powers the support he was entitled to expect.</p>
                <p>In opposing the resolution adopted by the Samoan Government, whereby
                            German currency wan excluded from being used to pay customs duties and
                            taxes, Baron von Senfft relied solely on the Samoan treaty (Article vi,
                            section 4). The Imperial Government claims no manner of advantage in
                            Samoa over the two other treaty powers, but they must decidedly oppose
                            any such diminution of the rights secured to them by treaty as would be
                            involved in the exclusion of German currency. The Imperial Government is
                            convinced that the loyal observance of the provisions of the Samoan
                            treaty by the representatives of the treaty powers will be successful in
                            restoring peace and good order in Samoa. But in order to obtain this end
                            it is, before all things, necessary that the representatives in question
                            should not work one against another, but that they should, on the
                            contrary, work together in the interests of peace, and should therefore
                            support Baron von Senfft.</p>
                <p>The latter’s conception of his position must be modified in two
                            directions. On the one hand, he is in error in denying to the consular
                            court, when unanimous, the right of access to Malietoa. On the other
                            hand, Baron von Pilsach must not judge of his position with Malietoa by
                            that of a minister with an European King, and resign when he thinks that
                            influence other than his own is prevailing. The chairman of the
                            municipal council must not forget that he owes his appointment to the
                            treaty powers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
