<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-11-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="776" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d776">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Baron <persName type="from">Saurma</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Imperial German Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-11-12"><hi rend="italic">November 12,
                                    1894</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: I have the honor, in
                            pursuance of instructions received, to invite your excellency’s
                            attention to the following matter:</p>
                        <p>In a memorial bearing date of September 10, 1894, Chief Justice Ide, of
                            Samoa, complained that he had not been invited to attend a conference
                            held August 23, 1894, between the consuls, the commanders of the war
                            vessels lying in the harbor, and the president of the municipality, in
                            which conference the subject of the interference of the war ships and
                            the measures to be adopted for the restoration of quiet and order on the
                            islands were discussed. Mr. Ide assumes that he is jointly responsible,
                            on the ground of the Samoa act, for the preservation of order in Samoa,
                            and that he must consequently claim the right to be present at
                            discussions of the kind in question. He makes a general complaint at the
                            same time that he has been neglected by the consuls in business matters.
                            The British consul especially, he says, renders the performance of the
                            duties of his office difficult, inasmuch as he frequently fails to show
                            proper consideration for him.</p>
                        <p>Presuming that your excellency has likewise received a copy of the chief
                            justice’s memorial, I have the honor to inquire what attitude the United
                            States Government proposes to assume with regard to Mr. Ide’s
                            complaints.</p>
                        <p>As to the view taken by the Imperial Government, it regards this case as
                            furnishing additional evidence that a many-headed administration of
                            affairs in Samoa is in the long run untenable, and that it must <pb facs="0741" n="735" xml:id="pg_735"/> lead to constant friction,
                            even supposing the officials thereto be guided by the most upright and
                            conciliatory feelings. It appears beyond a doubt from the chief
                            justice’s memorial that in the conduct of his office his intentions are
                            the best, but, on the other hand, it appears therefrom with equal
                            clearness that under present conditions a well-ordered administration of
                            affairs and a well-ordered situation will not be reached.</p>
                        <p>In the matter itself, and as regards the present point in dispute, the
                            Imperial Government is inclined to consider the view taken by the
                            consuls of the treaty powers as the right one. This view is shown by the
                            correspondence between the consuls and the chief justice, a copy of
                            which is herewith inclosed. A right of the chief justice to be present
                            at all political discussions between the representatives of the
                            Governments, including the Samoan Government, does not exist, and it is
                            the less possible to deduce any such right from the Samoa act, which
                            explicitly defines the competency of the chief justice, inasmuch as that
                            act makes no provision for such discussions. Leaving this out of the
                            question, however, it would, in the opinion of the Imperial Government,
                            be exceedingly hazardous on practical grounds to add a fifth to the four
                            political officials who are already in Samoa.</p>
                        <p>Should the United States Government agree with this view of the case it
                            might be well so to inform the chief justice.</p>
                        <p>With respect to the course pursued by the British consul, to which
                            reference is made in the chief justice memorial, the Imperial Government
                            has received the impression, both from the memorial and from other
                            sources, that that officer is less anxious to adjust existing
                            difficulties than are the German and American representatives.</p>
                        <p>The imperial ambassador in London has consequently been instructed to
                            bring the matter of again making it Mr. Cusack-Smith’s duty to maintain
                            a good understanding to the attention of the British Government.</p>
                        <p>Begging to be favored with a reply,</p>
                        <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Saurma.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 of November
                                    12.—Memorial.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Chief Justice Ide</gloss> to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Consuls</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Apia, Samoa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-08-24"><hi rend="italic">August 24, 1894</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: I am officially informed that a
                                meeting of the three consuls, the president, and the captains of the
                                English and German war ships stationed at Samoa was held at Mulinuu
                                on the 23d instant, for consideration of the situation and devising
                                remedies therefor, which meeting was in conference for several
                                hours. One of the officials in attendance came a long distance to
                                attend the meeting and no more time is required to give me notice of
                                such conference than to give the president notice. Having been
                                charged by the three treaty powers with important duties relating to
                                the punishment of crime and the promotion of good order in Samoa,
                                and having been held responsible in part for the securing of those
                                ends, and having functions to perform in strict pursuance of my
                                official duty which are materially affected by the course adopted at
                                such conferences, I hereby enter my protest against such conferences
                                being held without notice in advance to me and against the
                                determination of questions relating to the peace and good order of
                                Samoa without my having an opportunity to be present. No notice was
                                given me of the meeting above referred to.</p>
                            <pb facs="0742" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/>
                            <p>Before my acceptance of the position of chief justice I was
                                officially assured that I should receive the cordial support and
                                cooperation of the foreign officials in Samoa. I am unable to regard
                                the course above stated, which has occurred several times before, in
                                substance, as such cooperation. Matters have heretofore this year
                                been determined by the consular board without the slightest
                                conferene with me which have directly invaded my jurisdiction, in
                                the strictest judicial sense, and which have occasioned serious
                                embarrassment. If I should proceed directly in the line of the
                                treaty to decide the questions now pending in a sense under sections
                                4 and 6 of Article III and to recommend legislation upon the
                                questions of good order, under section 8, without conference, it
                                would be almost certain that my action would bring divided counsels
                                and conflicting procedure. The lines of authority between different
                                officials under the treaty are so obscurely defined that interfering
                                action is inevitable unless by mutual previous conference a common
                                course is arranged. It is needless to say that I can not regard that
                                as a conference which consists in previous determination of the
                                matter for consideration and then informing me by letter of such
                                determination. The situation is sufficiently difficult to require
                                the best wisdom of all in authority here acting in unison.</p>
                            <p>1 will only add that this is a matter which, in my judgment, might
                                and ought immediately to be arranged satisfactorily and pleasantly
                                here, without requiring application to the powers. I do not address
                                this letter to the president, because he has assured me that he
                                agrees with me in my position entirely. I shall, however, furnish a
                                copy of it to Captain Gibson, as senior officer of the men-of-war
                                now in Samoa in the interest of the treaty powers, but in my letter
                                to him inclosing the copy I make no comment or request for action or
                                reply.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Ide</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Chief Justice of Samoa.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 of November
                                12.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Consuls</gloss> to <gloss type="to">Chief Justice Ide</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Apia, Samoa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-09-05"><hi rend="italic">September 5, 1894</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your letter of the 24th ultimo, in
                                which you are pleased to enter your protest against such
                                conferences, as that referred to of the 23d, being held without
                                notice in advance to you and against the determination of questions
                                relating to the peace and good order in Samoa without your having an
                                opportunity to be present, was duly received, and we beg to inform
                                you that with regard to the meeting of the 23d ultimo, to which you
                                especially refer, we had no part in arranging it, but were ourselves
                                hastily invited to it, and therefore, if you were in fact entitled
                                to be of right present, which we do not concede, we are guiltless of
                                any real or implied omission or lack of consideration in the
                                matter.</p>
                            <p>We further beg leave to assure you that, so far as rests with the
                                undersigned, acting as a consular board, or as representing our
                                respective Governments, every assurance given you officially or
                                otherwise that you should receive the cordial support and
                                cooperation of the foreign officials in Samoa shall be, in the line
                                and scope of your authority, sincerely made good in the letter and
                                in spirit. We much regret that <pb facs="0743" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/> you are unable to regard what you term the
                                course stated, and which, as you correctly state, has occurred
                                several times before in substance, as such cooperation.</p>
                            <p>We must dissent from your declaration that matters have heretofore
                                this year been determined by the consular board, without the
                                slightest conference with you, which have directly invaded your
                                jurisdiction in the strict judicial sense, and which has occasioned
                                serious embarrassment.</p>
                            <p>The conference referred to of the 23d ultimo between the three
                                commanders of the men-of-war and the president, to which the
                                undersigned were invited, was called to consider— <list>
                                    <item>First. The request from the King that the war ships should
                                        cooperate with and take part in the operations of his army
                                        against the rebels in Aana in the same manner as they had
                                        done in Atua.</item>
                                    <item>Second. A complaint from the King that a part of the late
                                        rebels in Atua had broken the conditions of peace lately
                                        concluded with the commanders of the men-of-war.</item>
                                    <item>Third. A communication from the Tumua of Leulumoega (Aana)
                                        in regard to the action of the war ships, and lastly, a
                                        message from the people of Lufilufi (Atua) stating that the
                                        peace made with Atua was binding also by Samoan custom upon
                                        Aana.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>All these several matters were questions directly pertaining to the
                                conclusion of peace in one district and the prosecution of war in
                                the other.</p>
                            <p>After careful examination of every part of the Berlin general act, in
                                which the rights, powers, and jurisdiction of the chief justice are
                                inscribed, we are unable to perceive an on the part of the chief
                                justice to be present at such a conference, however agreeable it
                                might be that he should be present as a private gentleman on a like
                                or other occasion.</p>
                            <p>The line of precedent, we beg leave to suggest, since the formation
                                of the present Government is in support of the position here
                                assumed, and we can not admit that the friction which has been
                                experienced, and the difficulties so often encountered in the
                                administration of the internal affairs of this Kingdom, wherein, as,
                                you say, the lines of-authority between different officials are so
                                obscurely defined, would have been lessened or avoided by the
                                addition of yet another authority, whose jurisdiction in our opinion
                                is, in the midst of all the obscurity that may exist, clearly
                                defined and limited to another and more exalted field.</p>
                            <p>The supreme court, made up of but a single judge, is, under the
                                treaty, invested in some sense with perhaps the most unlimited
                                jurisdiction conferred upon any court in any country in connection
                                with the various nationalities and in the large number of
                                jurisdictions conferred upon it. We submit that each such
                                jurisdiction is of a legal character, if we may express it, and not
                                political.</p>
                            <p>We are aware that it is superfluous to remind you that the effort in
                                every country where the judiciary has been made an independent
                                department of the government has been to keep it separate and free
                                from political entanglement.</p>
                            <p>We do not believe that the three treaty powers, in the effort to
                                provide good government for a people essaying feeble steps in the
                                direction of higher civilization, would, disregarding all the
                                experience of time, have fixed upon them a system repudiated long
                                ago and conspicuously absent in their own constitutions. In our
                                opinion the only instance <pb facs="0744" n="738" xml:id="pg_738"/>
                                where an authority other than purely judicial is conferred upon the
                                chief justice is set forth in section 8, Article III:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The chief justice may recommend to the Government of Samoa the
                                    passage of any law which he shall consider just and expedient
                                    for the prevention and punishment of crime and for the promotion
                                    of good order in Samoa outside the municipal district, and for
                                    the collection of taxes without the district.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>The adviser of the Samoan Government in all other questions is the
                                president.</p>
                            <p>The possibility that a political question may ultimately come in a
                                legal form before the supreme court for adjudication is a
                                controlling reason why the chief justice should be so situated as to
                                deal with it impartially and free from any participation in its
                                origin.</p>
                            <p>In conclusion we beg to assure you, that whenever you wish to have a
                                conference with us we shall always, as heretofore, be glad and ready
                                to comply with your request; but we can not, as stated before,
                                acknowledge as justified by the treaty your claim to be present as
                                of right and heard at the meetings of the consular representatives
                                and the president when purely political affairs are under
                                consideration.</p>
                            <p>We have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">James H. Mulligan</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                            Consul-General</hi>.</item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">T. B. Cusack-Smith</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Her Britannic Majesty’s
                                            Consul</hi>.</item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Biermann</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Imperial German Consul.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>