<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. White to Mr. Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d785</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">785</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="785"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d785">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">White</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 997.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 19, 1893</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch, No. 994, of the 17th
                    instant, I have the honor to inclose herewith, for your information, an article
                    which appeared in the Times newspaper of yesterday relative to the affairs of
                    Samoa.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry White.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 997.]</seg>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[The Times, Thursday, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-18">May 18,
                            1893</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. Stevenson has not written, it would seem, too strongly about the state of
                        things in Samoa and the behavior of Baron Senfft von Pilsach and Chief
                        Justice Cedercrantz. Those who suspected that a master of historical romance
                        and a humorist of rare ingenuity had, on a slender basis of fact,
                        constructed a story of phantasy vying with the “Treasure Island” should read
                        the “Further correspondence respecting the affairs of Samoa,” just issued as
                        a blue book. In official documents, some of them under the hand of Baron
                        Senfft von Pilsach himself, he appears as absurd a personage as in the
                        letters from Mr. Stevenson, which we have from time to time published. Far
                        from being the inventor of imaginary grievances and grotesque dignitaries,
                        the latter is only the spokesman of a community, once amused, but long ago
                        indignant, at the antics of official comedians. Mr. Stevenson is not a
                        harsher critic of the reign of petty tyranny and licensed extravaganza at
                        Apia than our consul-general and the members of the municipal council. Under
                        the Berlin treaty, which gave it effect, three of the great powers control
                        Samoa; Mr. Otto Cedercrantz, <pb facs="0751" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> a
                        Swedish lawyer, was appointed chief justice, and a little later Baron Senfft
                        von Pilsach, a regierungs-assessor in the Prussian service, was nominated
                        president of the municipal council. Since these worthies set foot on the
                        islands peace has deserted them, and for about eighteen months almost every
                        mail must have brought our foreign office, the German chancery, and the
                        Secretary of State at Washington dispatches complaining of something done or
                        omitted by these officials. Mr. Stevenson may have made too much of a few
                        incidents, and failed to mention all condoning circumstances. He may have
                        credited the chief justice and the ex-regierungs-assessor with a vein of
                        comedy of which they were innocent. But in the official history is abundant
                        corroboration of the substance of his charges.</p>
                    <p>Shortly after the arrival of the chief justice he took the earliest
                        opportunity of snubbing the Samoan land commissioners, who exercise
                        important administrative and quasi-judicial duties in regard to land claims.
                        They can not incur expenditure without his approval. He did not answer their
                        letter of request with ordinary promptness, and in the end he declined to
                        sanction expenses which all the commissioners agreed were necessary, to the
                        serious obstruction of public business. In a crisis in the history of the
                        colony, when a revolt had broken out, he suddenly announced that he was
                        about to go to Fiji and Sydney, and to shut up the; supreme court for three
                        months—a course which he took, notwithstanding the protests of the consuls.
                        He did not improve matters by claiming personal exemption from the payment
                        of duties or taxes. In a little time we find him further embarrassing the
                        land commission by inhibiting it from settling disputed claims; and he
                        outdid his previous, performances by deciding that the import duties
                        belonged solely to the Samoan Government, and not, as had hitherto been
                        believed, to the municipality of Apia., thus reducing the latter at one
                        stroke to a state of insolvency. Both the English and German governments at
                        once recognized the injustice of the decision, which appears to have been in
                        flat contradiction to a previous opinion publicly expressed; but before they
                        could make known their opinion the chief justice had further distinguished
                        himself by announcing his intention of levying a fee of $5 on the
                        registration of each land title, the proceeds going to Dr. Hagberg, a
                        Swedish lawyer, appointed registrar by the chief justice. This was followed
                        up by a decision that registration of title to any estate should be
                        dependent on a preliminary survey of the land. Both these decisions Lord
                        Rosebery and the German foreign office declared to be <hi rend="italic"
                            >ultra vires</hi>. Evidently, Baron Senfft von Pilsach had made up his
                        mind not to be outdone in arbitrariness by the chief justice.</p>
                    <p>As early as August, 1891, our consul-general is writing to Lord Salisbury
                        that “the municipal president, in his capacity of adviser to the King, has
                        assumed the position of dictator to the Samoan Government.” He had
                        apparently come to Upolu with the notion that the Government could not
                        manage its affairs and that the business of an adviser was to give orders
                        and meddle as much as possible. Without consulting the municipal council he
                        instructed an architect to prepare plans and specifications for a costly
                        edifice and issued an advertisement inviting tenders for “capitol
                        buildings,” which, remarks our consul-general, “prove to be mainly a
                        dwelling house for Baron Senfft von Pilsach.” This pseudo Bismarck took very
                        high ground. He declared it to be a constitutional “necessity that no one
                        should be allowed to correspond with the King or the King permitted to reply
                        without the knowledge of and advice from the municipal president.” He
                        quarreled with the auditors of his accounts and persisted in maintaining, on
                        subtle, metaphysical grounds, that their duties did not include checking the
                        cash which he said he had in hand. He gave offense to the U. S. Government
                        by announcing <hi rend="italic">pro prio motu</hi> that the pound sterling
                        and the 20-mark gold piece were to be received at $5 U. S. currency, instead
                        of $4.76. He informed the consuls that he would no longer allow them to
                        inspect his financial reports to the King; and when the Government could
                        barely pay its way it bought up, at the baron’s suggestion, an opposition
                        newspaper, and then started a Royal Gazette to compete with and lessen the
                        value of that which had been bought. The result was what might be expected.
                        “The various officials,” our consul-general wrote last September to Lord
                        Rosebery, “are unable to draw their salaries, and there is no money even to
                        pay police. An order of the King’s upon the treasury to pay for a boat,
                        amounting to £100, has been returned by the president, who states that there
                        is no money in the treasury,” and he suggests that this collapse would have
                        been avoided if money had not been spent in building a dwelling house for
                        the baron and an expensive gaol never used, and in buying up a troublesome
                        local newspaper.</p>
                    <p>Before the arrival of the two officials whose vagaries form the staple of
                        Samoan history for the last two years the group of islands was far from
                        being well governed. Malietoa, the Sovereign, has an arbitrary turn, if we
                        may judge of his disposition from the tenor of one of his royal speeches,
                        which runs thus: “I have forbidden to all Samoans to play cricket by
                        ordinance made on the 20th June. * * *. I am of opinion that this (the game
                        of cricket) should be forbidden, else nobody would think of doing useful
                        work. From it results the shortness of food and the impossibility <pb
                            facs="0752" n="746" xml:id="pg_746"/> to think of ways and means to earn
                        money for paying taxes to the Government and for paying debts to the
                        merchants.” Chance gave Malietoa a chief justice and an adviser who hastened
                        to act with naive recklessness, and to treat a whole community as so many
                        naughty boys and its gravest affairs as lightly as a cricket match. Mr.
                        Stevenson has been only too completely justified by the story of
                        bureaucratic blindness, pompous inefficiency, and financial disaster told in
                        the official record. There are always elements of trouble and danger in
                        Samoa. The respect of the natives for the Government is small. Mataafa, the
                        plotting pretender to the Crown, sits hard by, as Mr. Stevenson has often
                        reminded us, and sees the blunders of high authorities do more for him than
                        he could ever hope from the spears of his followers; and the fear must be
                        that, if the official comedians remain much longer on the stage, their
                        concentrated folly may have a tragic ending.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
