<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="152" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">340.1115A/824: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-06">June 6,
                                    1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1113. Your 1520, June 6, noon. Arrangements are being made to have
                                the <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi> proceed direct to Ireland from
                                Bordeaux and Lisbon. You will be advised later of approximate date
                                of arrival.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi> will probably have available about
                                1000 accommodations for passengers from Galway counting emergency
                                accommodations. Ship will likely have 900 passengers aboard upon
                                leaving Lisbon. Bookings for departure from Galway will be made from
                                United States Lines Office, London. Lines will fix rates.</p>
                            <p>It has been our experience in the past that every vessel which we
                                have dispatched abroad for the purpose of returning Americans to the
                                United States has returned with unoccupied space. The Government
                                cannot continue the practice of dispatching such vessels for persons
                                who have been repeatedly warned since the outbreak of hostilities
                                that they should depart for the United States and who have not taken
                                advantage of the means which the Government has provided them at
                                considerable expense and at risk to the crews and ships in
                                traversing dangerous waters to repatriate them. This should be made
                                clear in your notification of the <hi rend="italic">Washington’s</hi> approaching arrival to Americans still in the
                                British Isles.</p>
                            <pb facs="0132" n="123" xml:id="pg_123"/>
                            <p>Use of loan authorization for <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                                approved.</p>
                            <p>American citizens inquiring at the Embassy regarding the possibility
                                of traveling on belligerent vessels should be informed that such
                                travel is against the law of the United States and permission will
                                not be granted for it.</p>
                            <p>You will warn each passenger as instructed in regard to the voyage of
                                S. S. <hi rend="italic">Roosevelt</hi> that they travel at their own
                                risk.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>