<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-16T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-16T08:00:00-05:00" n="349" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24 Raw Materials/1379:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-16T14:00:00+01:00">November 16, 1940—2 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 16—10:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3762. Department’s 3487, 15th.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Rubber Committee meeting postponed to Friday, November 22,
                                    which is about last date at which the action that is necessary
                                    now can be taken.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>There was a meeting yesterday at the Colonial Office at which
                                    the whole ground was gone over with the Dutch who are described
                                    in spite of the present political situation as being still in a
                                    position to block anything they do not like. There was agreement
                                    at the meeting (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to release the
                                    statutory extra 5 percent in the fourth quarter; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) to fix the quota at 95 percent for the
                                    first quarter; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) to contemplate a
                                    progressive reduction in the quota during 1941 from 95 to 85 to
                                    75 to 65 percent, which steps would be necessary to reach in a
                                    gradual and orderly fashion the figure of 60 percent which is
                                    deemed to be the logical one for 1942. Even with the extra
                                    100,000 tons to be purchased by the Rubber Reserve Company only
                                    16,000 tons would remain to be purchased by it in the fourth
                                    quarter of 1941, assuming the above quota figures.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The Dutch delegates were apparently not easy to convince as to
                                    the necessity for even such contemplated action in the first
                                    quarter, which they are described as disliking very much but
                                    which they are recommending to Batavia out of loyalty to their
                                    allies and which will probably be accepted by Batavia on that
                                    basis.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The proposals stated in (1) above were the result of a
                                    compromise between the British and the Dutch. The latter hated
                                    to be rushed and the British consented to defer the meeting
                                    until Friday as their part of the compromise.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The figure of 95 percent for the first quarter is stated by
                                    the Colonial Office to be the highest which in fact can be
                                    produced in <pb facs="0291" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/> view of
                                    the winter season as well as the highest with which the Dutch
                                    could be brought to agree.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>The Rubber Reserve Company’s and Viles’ proposals as
                                    communicated by the Department to the Embassy will be discussed
                                    with Clauson at 11 a.m. Monday<note n="42" xml:id="d349fn42">November 18.</note> and it is hoped that any comments the
                                    Department may wish to make upon this telegram reach the Embassy
                                    Monday morning.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>