<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="491" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d491">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">851.00/2199</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary
                                    of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-12-26">December 26,
                                        1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The French Ambassador called to see me this afternoon.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador said that he wished to give me a résumé of recent
                                events in France. He read to me excerpts from a telegram which he
                                had just received from M. Flandin, the Minister for Foreign Affairs.
                                In this telegram the Ambassador was informed that the dismissal by
                                Marshal Pétain of Laval had been due to the fact that Laval had been
                                assuming authority which was in derogation of Marshal Pétain’s own
                                authority as Chief of State, and had been proceeding towards a
                                policy of collaboration with Germany far in excess of what Marshal
                                Pétain approved or desired. The word “plot” was not specifically
                                mentioned by the Ambassador, but I drew the implication from his
                                remarks that Laval had entered into some kind of understanding with
                                the German authorities which, if carried out, would have reduced
                                Marshal Pétain to a figurehead without any power to act.</p>
                            <p>M. Flandin’s telegram went on to say that after Laval’s dismissal,
                                the German Ambassador in Paris, Herr Abetz, had immediately come to
                                Vichy and had made two demands, one that Marshal Pétain receive
                                Laval in order that the two might have a personal conference, and
                                the other that Laval be reinstated in the Pétain Government. The
                                Marshal had flatly refused even to discuss the second demand, but
                                had consented to receive Laval. The conversation between Pétain and
                                Laval, instead of improving relations between them, had caused a
                                complete breakdown in their personal relations. Laval had then gone
                                to Paris with Abetz. Three days later, De Brinon had returned to
                                Vichy from Paris and conveyed what was in essence an ultimatum to
                                Marshal Pétain from the German Government. Apparently the ultimatum
                                consisted of a demand that Laval be reinstated in the French
                                Government or else all cooperation between Germany and France
                                beneficial to the latter would be impossible. Marshal Pétain had
                                again refused to discuss the demands or the reinstatement of Laval
                                and had informed De Brinon for communication to the German
                                Government that if the Germans persisted in this attitude, the terms
                                of the armistice would be violated by them and the Pétain Government
                                would regain freedom of action, for whatever that might be worth.
                                That, the Ambassador said, was the situation at the moment, and it
                                    <pb facs="0439" n="430" xml:id="pg_430"/> was, of course, clear
                                that the Germans would not now take any steps towards releasing
                                French prisoners of war or relaxing the stringent barriers between
                                occupied and unoccupied France.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>