<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-12T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="522" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d522">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.8131/55: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-12T18:00:00+02:00">November 12, 1940—6 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 9:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>942. My telegram No. 919, November 8, 6 p.m.<note n="93" xml:id="d522fn93">Not printed.</note> Monick<note n="94" xml:id="d522fn94">Emmanuel Monick, Secretary General of French
                                    Morocco.</note> who called today to say good-bye told me that
                                his suggestion that the Marshal might desire to send a personal
                                representative to the United States fell on fertile soil. He said it
                                was given serious consideration in Government circles. It was,
                                however, firmly vetoed by Laval.<note n="95" xml:id="d522fn95">Pierre Laval, French Vice President of the Council of
                                    Ministers.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The latter he said explained that his son-in-law René de Chambrun is
                                now in Washington, that he goes frequently to the White House and
                                that he is in a position to keep the Government well informed of
                                what goes on in the United States. Monick went on to say that in
                                spite of the “low opinion” in which young de Chambrun is held here
                                the Marshal and others in the Government were impressed by Laval’s
                                picture of his ready access to the highest Government quarters in
                                Washington. He said he felt the only other procedure for bringing
                                    <pb facs="0461" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/> about a “better
                                understanding” between France and the United States would be for the
                                President to send a personal representative to Vichy “in the nature
                                of a Colonel House”.<note n="96" xml:id="d522fn96">Colonel Edward M.
                                    House, sent to Europe in January 1915 by President Wilson as his
                                    private and personal representative to seek peace between
                                    belligerents.</note> I interrupted to say that in my purely
                                personal opinion, given the present state of feeling in the United
                                States, the sending of any such personal emissary was entirely out
                                of the question. That it seemed to me, furthermore, that since
                                France was the country which felt itself misunderstood any
                                initiative should come from this side. I said that he had drawn a
                                picture for me of growing resistance within the Government to
                                Laval’s policies.</p>
                            <p>The fact, however, that Laval had been able to “veto” the suggestion
                                to send an emissary—which apparently even had the serious
                                consideration of the Marshal—seemed just one more bit of evidence of
                                the powerful position which he occupies here today.</p>
                            <p>In conclusion Monick said that he had not yet given up hope that some
                                personal friend of the Marshal would be found and sent soon. He
                                admitted that frankly he did not know of a man sufficiently in the
                                Marshal’s confidence to fill the bill. Apparently for one reason or
                                another the General Laure mentioned in my telegram 918 [<hi rend="italic">919</hi>] would not do.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>