<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in France ( (Matthews) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d560</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">560</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-11-16T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-11-16T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-16T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-16T10:00:00-05:00" n="560"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d560">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.34/164: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-16T17:00:00+02:00"
                            >November 16, 1940—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 10:11 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>964. For the Secretary and Under Secretary. Department’s 713, November 13, 5 [<hi
                        rend="italic">4</hi>] p.m. I was received alone by Marshal Pétain this
                    afternoon and presented to him as persuasively as possible our interest in
                    purchasing the <hi rend="italic">Jean Bart</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Richelieu</hi>. He listened with keen attention. When I had finished he
                    replied as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have given the most solemn assurances that the French Fleet, including
                            these two ships, shall never fall into Germany’s hands. I have given
                            those assurances to your Government; I have given them to the British
                            Government, and even to Churchill personally. I reiterate them now. They
                            will be used to defend French territory and possessions. They will never
                            be used against the British unless we are attacked by them. I cannot
                            sell those ships even if I wanted to. The terms of the armistice prevent
                            it and even if they did not the Germans would never permit it. We are
                            under their heel and powerless. If I were free I would gladly sell them
                            to you, on condition that they be returned to us after the war and thus
                            save them for France. Under present circumstances I must repeat I have
                            neither the right nor the possibility of selling them.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>He said this with great seriousness but with no sign either of surprise or
                    resentment at the suggestion. He then talked for half an hour of France’s
                    present situation which I am reporting in a separate telegram.<note n="41"
                        xml:id="d560fn41">See telegram No. 965, November 16, <ref target="#pg_411"
                            >p. 411</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
