<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by Mr. J. Rives Childs of the Division
                    of Near Eastern Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="679"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d679">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.8131/61</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by Mr. J. Rives Childs
                        of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-30">October 30,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Helm telephoned and read to me a telegram which he had just received from
                    London, reading substantially as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The United States Government were informed in the first instance of the
                            Moroccan deal in order that they might be given the opportunity, if they
                            chose, of participating in the proposed arrangement.</p>
                        <p>“The United Kingdom scheme is not progressing as we would have liked,
                            possibly owing to enemy influence with the Moroccan authorities.</p>
                        <p>“Under these circumstances the United States Government may wish to
                            suspend the taking of any measures looking to the consummation of the
                            proposed arrangement.</p>
                        <p>“The question is however still being pursued on our part, and if it
                            should appear that there may be any prospect for the consummation of the
                            United Kingdom arrangement we shall not fail to inform the United States
                            Government.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I informed Mr. Helm that in view of the latest international developments we had
                    rather anticipated receiving a communication of this character from him and that
                    the information he had given me would be conveyed to those interested.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
