<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="821" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d821">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24 Raw Materials/990</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                    State</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-05-18">May 18,
                                    1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The British Ambassador called at his request. He read from a
                                memorandum a statement by his Government to the effect that Italy is
                                stocked up on a considerable amount of important commodities, such
                                as toluyl, molybdenum, a number of other alloys, and still other
                                important commodities needed for war purposes; that the British
                                Government is of the opinion that this has been done for the benefit
                                of the Axis, especially for Italy, if and when she enters the war;
                                that today different cargoes of these and other commodities are
                                going forward from the United States to Italy. The plea of the
                                British Government is that, in view of the virtual certainty of
                                Italy going to war unless diverted in some way, this country should
                                by embargo or its equivalent let Rome understand that we could not
                                undertake to ship further to her the foregoing commodities, but that
                                we were reserving all of them for emergency purposes. I replied to
                                the Ambassador that I could not comment either pro or con with
                                respect to the matter, but would, along with my associates, give it
                                consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ull</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>