<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                    Affairs ( (Murray))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d839</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">839</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="839"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d839">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">346B.115 Standard Oil Co./21</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        Near Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-21">October 21,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. James A. Moffett, of the Standard Oil Company California, called on Mr.
                        Welles<note n="46" xml:id="d839fn46">Sumner Welles, Under Secretary of
                        State.</note> this morning to discuss the situation resulting from the
                    attack by Italian bombing planes on October 18 on properties of the Standard Oil
                    Company of California both in Bahrein as well as in El Hasa, on the mainland of
                    Arabia.</p>
                <p>Mr. Moffett had with him the attached telegrams<note n="47" xml:id="d839fn47">Not
                        printed.</note> received from the company’s representative in Arabia stating
                    definitely that both Arabia and Bahrein were attacked, but that damage was done
                    only on the Arabian side.</p>
                <p>Mr. Moffett said he realized that, owing to the status of Bahrein as a
                    British-protected state, this Government could not make any protest as a result
                    of the attack at that place. The situation was, however, <pb facs="0731" n="722"
                        xml:id="pg_722"/> entirely different in regard to the attack on the
                    company’s properties in Arabia proper and he very much hoped that we would find
                    it possible to make vigorous protest to the Italian Government in order that
                    there should be no repetition of this attack.</p>
                <p>Mr. Welles stated that if the information received from the company’s
                    representative in Arabia could be definitely depended upon the Department would
                    of course be prepared to take action. It would be desirable, however, for Mr.
                    Moffett to endeavor to obtain further details regarding the attack, and he
                    requested Mr. Moffett to take the necessary steps in that direction. Mr. Welles
                    promised, however, that the Department would in any case act this afternoon in
                    the event that further information had not been received by the company from
                    Arabia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
