<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="849" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d849">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">856B.01/2</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary
                                    of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-22">April 22,
                                    1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The Ambassador of Venezuela<note n="1" xml:id="d849fn1">Don Diógenes
                                    Escalante.</note> called to see me this afternoon. Dr. Escalante
                                told me that he was leaving Washington on April 24 and would sail
                                the following day from New York for Venezuela in order to attend the
                                session of the Venezuelan Senate of which he is a member.</p>
                            <p>I told the Ambassador that I would be grateful if he would talk over
                                with his Foreign Minister, Dr. Gil Borges, the problems which might
                                be suddenly raised with regard to the Dutch West Indies and Dutch
                                Guiana in the event of an invasion of Holland by Germany. I stated
                                that rumors had come to my attention which I had already transmitted
                                to Dr. Gil Borges to the effect that attempts might be made by
                                groups of Germans or other individuals operating from Venezuelan
                                territory to create acts of sabotage in the Dutch West Indies. I
                                added that if any further rumors of this character came to me I
                                would, of course, transmit them in the same way for the confidential
                                information of the Venezuelan Government. I said that it seemed to
                                me that in the event of an invasion of the Netherlands by Germany an
                                immediate consultation on the part of all of the American Republics
                                would be desirable so as to consider the steps of prevention which
                                might be taken in the interest of continental solidarity should the
                                local authorities in the Dutch West Indies and in Dutch Guiana find
                                themselves confronted with any concerted effort at sabotage or
                                insurrection and should the situation arising from such
                                possibilities create a condition where non-American activities would
                                endanger the peace of the western world.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador replied that he was in very hearty accord with these
                                ideas and that he felt sure that his own Government would be in
                                accord. He said that the rumors which had arisen alleging that <pb facs="0739" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/> the Government of
                                Venezuela itself might attempt to seize the islands were utterly
                                ludicrous and had originated from an article which had been
                                published in a newspaper in San Juan, Puerto Rico. The article had
                                later been circulated in certain Venezuelan cities in the form of
                                hand bills. He said that these hand bills undoubtedly had been
                                circulated by propagandists for the purpose of creating trouble and
                                he had no doubt that non-American money was behind this
                                circulation.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>