<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, hy the Assistant Secretary of State (
                    (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d855</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">855</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="855"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d855">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856B.01/18</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, hy the Assistant Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-05-11">May 11,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British Ambassador called at Woodley<note n="4" xml:id="d855fn4">Residence of
                        Assistant Secretary Berle.</note> last night, about 10:30 p.m., at his
                    request.</p>
                <p>He presented a note addressed to Secretary Hull, dated May 10th,<note n="4a"
                        xml:id="d855fn4a">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> relating to the concern of the United
                    Kingdom and of the Netherlands Government about the safety of Aruba and Curaçao,
                    and the oil refineries there, and to the decision that a small additional
                    British force should be landed in Curaçao.</p>
                <p>Prior to the visit of the Ambassador, McDermott<note n="5" xml:id="d855fn5"
                        >Michael J. McDermott, Chief of the Division of Current Information.</note>
                    had telephoned to me press reports that a French force had landed on Aruba from
                    the cruiser <hi rend="italic">Jeanne d’Arc</hi>. Surmising that this might be
                    the subject of Lord Lothian’s visit, I telephoned the White House.</p>
                <pb facs="0743" n="734" xml:id="pg_734"/>
                <p>The President said that in his view the position immediately to be taken should
                    be that we must insist that any forces landed must be so landed at the request
                    of the Dutch authorities, subject to the command of the Dutch authorities,
                    acting under the Dutch flag, and merely by way of temporary assistance. He
                    suggested that I communicate with McDermott, so that the morning papers should
                    not convey the impression that these landings amounted to a “taking over” of the
                    islands.</p>
                <p>When Lord Lothian handed me the British note, I stated that I had talked
                    informally to the President on the subject, and that indeed Lord Lothian was
                    familiar with the views of this Government, from his conversations held earlier
                    in the day with Secretary Hull. We had undertaken an obligation to “consult” in
                    the matter of the Dutch West Indies, should there be a “threatened change of
                    sovereignty”, as the Ambassador was aware from the proceedings of the Panama
                    consultation. On the other hand, I understood his communication to relate to a
                    temporary landing of forces solely for the assistance of the Dutch authorities,
                    carried out under Dutch command and under the Dutch flag, and not threatening in
                    any sense the Dutch control of the island. Lord Lothian observed that this was
                    his understanding, also.</p>
                <p>I likewise pointed out (as the President had suggested) that our reports seemed
                    to indicate that the Dutch authorities had the situation entirely in control.
                    They had interned some ninety-three Germans or German sympathizers working in or
                    near the oil refineries. They had likewise interned all Germans over the age of
                    sixteen. They had taken over the German ships in their harbors; although one had
                    resisted, and one German was killed, and the boat set on fire, the fire had been
                    put out and the resistance promptly put down. According to all reports, the
                    situation was well in hand.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Berle, Jr</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
