<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="903" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d903">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">840.51 Frozen Credits/755</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Rumanian Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Coste</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 3631/P–3–II–3a</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-17">October 17,
                                        1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to Your Excellency’s
                                note of October 12, 1940,<note n="20" xml:id="d903fn20">Not
                                    printed.</note> transmitting copies of Executive Order No. 8565
                                of October 10, 1940, I have the honor to inform you that I am
                                instructed by my Government to protest in its behalf against the
                                issuance of the above Executive Order, by which the provisions of
                                Executive Order No. 8389 of April 10, 1940, as amended, are extended
                                to Romania and Romanian nationals.</p>
                            <p>Considering that Executive Order No. 8565 does not contain any
                                reasons for the measures ordered thereby, the Romanian Government is
                                obliged to interpret it, in view of established precedents and of
                                statements, apparently semi-official, which appeared in the American
                                press on October 11, 1940, as a measure based on the assumption that
                                Romania is an occupied country.</p>
                            <p>The Romanian Government is unable to admit such an assumption and
                                declares most categorically that Romania is a free and independent
                                country.</p>
                            <p>The sending of a German military mission accompanied by military
                                units, for the purpose of instructing the Romanian army, had already
                                been negotiated by the previous Romanian Government.</p>
                            <p>This action on the part of the then Government being found agreeable,
                                the present Government continued these negotiations and is now
                                carrying out the agreement reached. Therefore, and since numerous
                                precedents are in existence, the Romanian Government can in no way
                                concur with the view that the presence in Romania of this mission
                                could be interpreted as a military occupation.</p>
                            <p>In behalf of my Government, therefore, I have the honor to ask for a
                                reconsideration of the entire matter, leading to the rescinding of
                                Executive Order No. 8565.</p>
                            <pb facs="0792" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/>
                            <p>Pending the favorable decision of the United States Government on
                                this request, I have the honor to inform you of the urgent character
                                of certain obligations, which my Government has to fulfill out of
                                funds deposited with the Chase National Bank by the National Bank of
                                Romania, and for which I request, on behalf of my Government, that
                                the Treasury be good enough to free immediately the following
                                necessary funds: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Two Million Seven Hundred Thirty Thousand Dollars for the
                                        payment of cotton imports from Iran, in fulfillment of an
                                        existing contract;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Seven Million Dollars for the import of raw materials from
                                        Turkey, in accordance with an agreement signed by the
                                        Bomanian and Turkish Governments in September 1940.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Four Hundred Thirty-Eight Thousand Dollars for the import
                                        of raw materials from Greece, in accordance with contracts
                                        now being executed.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Ninety-Five Thousand Dollars for salaries and expenses of
                                        Bomanian Legations in different countries during the current
                                        month.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Brutus Coste</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>