<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-20T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-20T16:00:00-05:00" n="960" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d960">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">852.48/785: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-20T22:00:00+01:00">November 20, 1940—10 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 20—9:37 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3803. I saw Lord Halifax<note n="41" xml:id="d960fn41">British
                                    Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> for a few minutes
                                yesterday afternoon and he mentioned the condition of starvation in
                                Spain which he regards with great anxiety due to its direct bearing
                                on Spanish relations with the Axis Powers. He referred to a telegram
                                which he had just sent to Washington instructing the British Chargé
                                d’Affaires to express the hope to the Department that we would not
                                insist on General Franco’s making a public declaration of
                                non-belligerency as a condition for receiving food supplies from the
                                United States. Lord Halifax said that it was quite impossible for
                                General Franco to make such a declaration and that the situation in
                                Spain was so critical that he hoped our point of view might be
                                modified. When I called to see Mr. Strang<note n="42" xml:id="d960fn42">William Strang, British Acting Assistant Under
                                    Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> at the Foreign
                                Office this afternoon he showed me this telegram as well as previous
                                telegrams from the British Ambassador at Madrid and one from Lord
                                Lothian to the British Chargé d’Affaires at Washington all of which
                                I understand have been repeated to Mr. Butler for communication to
                                the Department.</p>
                            <p>While I am aware of no facts in this connection not known to the
                                Department I feel that I should report the foregoing in view of the
                                very great importance which Lord Halifax attaches to an immediate
                                alleviation of the Spanish food situation.<note n="43" xml:id="d960fn43">In a message of November 23, 1940, to
                                    President Roosevelt, Prime Minister Churchill wrote: “Our
                                    accounts show that the situation in Spain is deteriorating and
                                    that the Peninsula is not far from starvation point. An offer by
                                    you to dole out food month by month so long as they keep out of
                                    the war might be decisive.” (852.48/11–2340. Photostatic copy
                                    obtained from the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N.
                                    Y.)</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>