<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-11T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-11T19:00:00-05:00" n="988" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d988">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">852.75 National Telephone Co./341:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-11T19:00:00-05:00">April
                                        11, 1940—7 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>41. Your 66, April 9, 6 p.m. You should immediately renew request for
                                interview with General Franco for the purpose of delivering to him
                                in person the communication in the form of an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> from this Government set forth in our no. 36
                                of April 2, 7 p.m. with the textual changes suggested in your no. 62
                                of April 4, 11 a.m.</p>
                            <pb facs="0879" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                            <p>As pointed out in our <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, assurances
                                were given by the Spanish Ambassador in Washington on July 28, 1939,
                                acting upon specific instructions from his Government, that the
                                Spanish Government intended to accord to American rights and
                                interests in Spain just and equitable treatment in accordance with
                                the principles of international law. In requesting this interview,
                                you should make clear to the Minister for Foreign Affairs that this
                                Government expects that the Chief of the Spanish State, as the
                                source of final authority, will exercise that authority to make
                                effective without further delay the assurances previously given with
                                respect to American rights and interests in Spain, which in the
                                present instance requires the restoration of its properties to the
                                control and management of the telephone company. You may add that
                                your Government cannot believe that the statements reported in your
                                telegram under reference represent the considered judgment of the
                                Spanish Government.</p>
                            <p>For your guidance we wish to stress the fact that the primary
                                consideration here involved is the restoration of the telephone
                                properties and operating rights to the American owners in accordance
                                with the terms of the contract with the Spanish State, and not the
                                status of particular American employees of the Spanish Telephone
                                Company. We fully agree with the opinion you express in this regard
                                in the final paragraph of your no. 54 of March 28, noon.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>