<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of United Nations Political and
                    Security Affairs ( (Wainhouse) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State for United
                    Nations Affairs ( (Hickerson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">262</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="262"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> Files, Lot 59 D 237, “Italian
                    Membership”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of United Nations
                        Political and Security Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wainhouse</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for United
                        Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-16">October 16,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Italian Membership</p>
                <p>The following is for your use in conversations with Guidotti on October 16
                    concerning the question of Italian membership:</p>
                <p>1. The Italian application has been vetoed by the Soviet Union four times—on
                    August 26, 1947; October 1, 1947; April 10, 1948; and September 13, 1949. The
                    Soviet Union has given as its reason for vetoing these applications the failure
                    of the Security Council to recommend simultaneous admission of Cominform
                    applicants.</p>
                <p>2. The United States has supported and will continue to support strongly the
                    admission of Italy. Together with the UK and France, we have recently reaffirmed
                    our “determination to make every effort to secure Italy’s membership in the
                    United Nations.” We have given serious consideration to all suggested courses of
                    action by which Italy’s admission might be achieved, including the recent
                    proposal of the Government of Italy.</p>
                <p>3. The Government of Italy, as pointed out in an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aide-Mémoire</hi> handed to the Secretary at Ottawa, maintains that since
                    the Soviet Union had never questioned Italy’s qualifications for membership, its
                    vetoes of Security Council recommendations to admit Italy are null <pb
                        facs="0383" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/> and void; and that the General
                    Assembly should therefore disregard the Soviet vetoes and consider action to
                    admit Italy. Aside from the practical consideration that the Soviet Union could
                    again raise the question of Italian membership in the Security Council and
                    advance alleged Charter grounds, we see basic Charter difficulties in the action
                    suggested. In an advisory opinion of March 3, 1950, the International Court of
                    Justice concluded that under the Charter, the General Assembly cannot admit a
                    state to membership when the Security Council has made no recommendation for
                    admission either because of the failure of a candidate to obtain the required
                    majority or because of the negative vote of a permanent member. Further, while
                    we certainly agree that the Soviet vetoes of Italy’s application have not been
                    based on Charter grounds, it does not follow, and the International Court of
                    Justice has never suggested, that an improper exercise of the veto right is,
                    because of its impropriety, null and void. Nor does it follow that the General
                    Assembly can take action implying that these vetoes are ineffective.</p>
                <p>4. Peru has requested the inclusion on the General Assembly agenda of an item
                    entitled: “Admission of New Members: Rights of States Candidates to Adduce Proof
                    to Show that They Satisfy the Requirements of Article 4 of the Charter.” This
                    proposal probably is similar to the plan Belaunde (Peru) has discussed with
                        <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> under which the General Assembly would
                    request that applicants be permitted to present to the Security Council proof of
                    their qualifications for membership. If there was then a threat of a veto, the
                    Assembly would request an advisory opinion from the International Court of
                    Justice as to the value of the proof. Assuming a favorable opinion by the Court,
                    the Security Council, in Belaunde’s opinion, would have to apply strictly the
                    sense of Article 4 and no member could veto the application.</p>
                <p>We see two basic difficulties in the plan. First, since an advisory opinion is
                    not binding, a permanent member could still veto. Second, we doubt whether the
                    Court would consider itself competent to determine whether an applicant is
                    qualified, since the Court itself has previously stated that of the factors to
                    be taken into account in considering conditions laid down in Article 4, “no
                    relevant political factor … connected with the conditions of admission is
                    excluded.”</p>
                <p>5. The Department of State is inclined to favor reconsideration by the Security
                    Council of Italy’s application as a special case while the General Assembly is
                    meeting in Paris, although it would not wish to take this action if Italy
                    opposed it. We would be prepared to support or sponsor reconsideration and
                    believe there may be an outside chance that the USSR would not veto if the case
                    is presented effectively. The <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> is
                    discussing this matter with the UK and France and has explained our views to
                    Guidotti. The latter has expressed the opinion <pb facs="0384" n="362"
                        xml:id="pg_362"/> that it would be a mistake to propose reconsideration of
                    Italy’s application by the Security Council since the USSR would probably veto
                    on Charter grounds and render the tactic suggested by the Italians or Belaunde
                    even more difficult. He stressed the “superiority” of the Assembly and urged
                    that the Assembly should recognize past Soviet vetoes as null and void. He also
                    expressed doubt as to the advisability of preliminary consultations with the
                    USSR, which Gross had suggested as a personal idea.</p>
                <p>6. If our efforts to obtain Italy’s admission fail, we would be prepared to vote
                    for an amendment to Article 86 to give Italy voting rights in the Trusteeship
                    Council if Italy desired it. However, such an amendment would probably be vetoed
                    by the Soviet Union. We would also favor an arrangement for participation by
                    Italy without voting rights in the main committees of the General Assembly if
                    desired by the Italians.</p>
                <p>7. We recommend that you inform Guidotti that we intend to do all we can to
                    obtain admission for Italy but explain the basic Charter difficulties in the
                    plans proposed by Italy and by Belaunde. We also recommend that you state that
                    we are inclined to believe that the only feasible course is Security Council
                    reconsideration of Italy’s application as a special case and that we would be
                    prepared to sponsor or support reconsideration and make the strongest possible
                    effort for a favorable recommendation unless Italy opposed the idea. If our
                    efforts to obtain membership for Italy should fail, we would be prepared to vote
                    for an amendment to Article 86 and would favor an arrangement for participation
                    by Italy without voting rights in the main Committees of the Assembly if these
                    measures should be desired by the Italians. We would appreciate Italy’s views on
                    these matters and will, of course, continue to consult closely with Italy in the
                    future.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
