<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. James N. Hyde, Adviser, United States
                    Delegation to the General Assembly</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d281</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">281</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="281"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d281">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. James N. Hyde, Adviser,
                        United States Delegation to the General Assembly</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-15">November 15,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Italian Membership</p>
                <p>Present: Count Guidotti, Italian Observer<lb/>Messrs. Vorys, Fisher, Nolting,
                    Hyde—US Delegation</p>
                <p>Guidotti called at our request and went over all the familiar ground in arguing
                    Italy’s case along the lines of the Italian <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    and de Gasperi letter.</p>
                <p>He denied, although none of us had suggested it that Italy feels that the
                    tripartite declaration commits us to an illegal course. In restating the entire
                    argument of the Italian <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, he stressed the
                    fact that no “juridical way” can be found to obtain Italy’s admission, that
                    action to circumvent the veto is necessary and he thought that such action had
                    been agreed to in the light of the fact the last Soviet veto was illegal.</p>
                <p>He went on to say that all that is necessary is a political decision and a
                    political will on the part of the US, UK and France and from this will flow the
                    necessary legal maneuvers which the Legal Advisers would then be instructed by
                    the Foreign Ministers to provide. He thought his reading of the tripartite
                    declaration was correct that it committed us to something more than the dead end
                    of another veto or a propaganda debate in the Assembly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Vorys commented that of course he understood that Italy wanted to come into
                    the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> by any legal method we could discover but
                    he felt Italy would not want to enter by the exercise of a power play in
                    disregard of the very Charter under which Italy wanted to undertake obligations.
                    Mr. Fisher commented that there is probably not so sharp a distinction between
                    the legal and political aspects in that some political courses are not possible
                    unless legal ways to accomplish them can be discovered. In other words, as Mr.
                    Vorys added, it does not follow that where there is a will there is a way.</p>
                <p>Guidotti went on to say that of course he was aware of what he termed the
                    Anglo-French draft resolution. He had told Broustra that Italy would approve it
                    and that he thought it was very good as far as it went in providing the frame
                    into which a picture would later be placed. As Guidotti put it, after the
                    application again goes to the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, is vetoed and
                    returned to the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>, he expected that the Assembly
                    would then itself take action on the application. He had been surprised and
                    disturbed when the French had told him on Nov 15 for the first time that the
                    idea of a resolution taking the case to the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> is
                    all that <pb facs="0417" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> was intended. This put the
                    procedure in a very different light. He had telegraphed his government for
                    instructions. He had recommended Italy’s acceptance none the less of such a
                    resolution, because he felt that Italy would have freedom of action in
                    considering next steps. He expects a reply by Monday, November 19.</p>
                <p>Mr. Vorys commented that he thought our thinking about a resolution sending the
                    application to the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> was that it was the picture
                    itself and not merely the frame. He added that it was rather a question of
                    whether this course is what Italy wants and would help her, not a question of
                    whether Italy would object or agree to it.</p>
                <p>In response to our questions, Guidotti reacted strongly that of and by itself
                    another trip to the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> would be extremely bad
                    from the Italian point of view in that it is bound to result in a veto, probably
                    based on the claim Italy is not peace loving because of her membership in <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. He felt this would depress the just hopes of
                    the Italian people which have been fed by the optimism of current newspaper
                    articles. For his part, unless his government thought that a lot of noise was
                    useful, he would prefer to see nothing done other than a general laudatory
                    debate on Italy in the Assembly rather than undertaking this useless action.</p>
                <p>Assuming, however, that we were to persist in this course, he pointed out that in
                    the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> it would be possible for the President to
                    rule that this is a procedural issue and in so doing he would act in accordance
                    with the findings of the Interim Committee and thus avoid a Soviet veto. Hyde
                    pointed out that neither the <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> nor the <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> had ever taken the position that a <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> vote on membership is procedural. Guidotti also
                    felt that the double veto technique might be used to support this tactic in the
                    Council.</p>
                <p>Then he went on to state the Italian thesis that since the 1949 Soviet veto is
                    illegal, the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> might by a vote take Italy into
                    the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on the ground that there exists a
                    recommendation of the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, the Soviet negative
                    vote being illegal. Mr. Vorys commented that he had very great difficulty with
                    the concept of overlooking the need for a <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    recommendation in the light of the two advisory opinions of the Court,
                    particularly the 1950 one. He suggested that Italy would not want to put herself
                    in the position of coming into the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> by a device
                    which might be challenged as sound Charter interpretation. He asserted that we
                    all have the strongest political will to see Italy a member. In this connection,
                    speaking personally, Mr. Vorys wondered whether the Assembly might put to the
                        <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> for an advisory opinion the question of
                    whether the Soviet vote in 1949 is a veto or an illegal vote in violation of the
                    rule contained in the 1948 opinion of the Court. He thought this possibly might
                    lay a foundation for improving Italy’s position and even a negative decision by
                    the Court would not do any particular <pb facs="0418" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/>
                    harm. Guidotti replied that he had never thought of this idea but off hand he
                    was opposed to it and thought that it would be the final nail in the coffin.</p>
                <p>Having pursued this line to the end, Guidotti then suggested that the <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> might recommend every present and future
                    applicant in sight and by a selective process let each applicant argue its case
                    before the Assembly on the theory that the satellites could not possibly get a ⅔
                    vote. He added that he could see no moral difficulty with this, because some
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> members are just as bad as some of the
                    applicants. He had advised his government against urging this course, however,
                    because he thought it would be politically impossible for the US. Mr. Vorys was
                    glad Guidotti had urged his government against this course, because he could not
                    see how we could possibly agree and it was hard for him to understand how Italy
                    could want to enter the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in the same category
                    as various gangster states.</p>
                <p>We then raised the possibility of participation without a vote in all the main
                    committees and subcommittees of the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. Mr.
                    Nolting recalled that this question had been mentioned by the Secretary to
                    Ambassador Quaroni earlier in the day. Guidotti’s reaction was definite and
                    negative. He stated he could reject the idea without consulting his government
                    further; it involved second class citizenship in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>; it had been thoroughly discussed in Washington and his own
                    experience in the Trusteeship Council showed that a state could have no prestige
                    without a vote. He saw no useful purpose in preparing the suggestion in writing
                    to be transmitted to the Foreign Office as Quaroni had suggested.</p>
                <p>That brought him to the conclusion that he was very disappointed in what we had
                    to offer, considering the language of the tripartite declaration and the
                    statement in the acknowledgment of de Gasperi’s letter that the State Department
                    appreciates the political problem present and the necessity for finding a
                    solution. He added that he felt he saw strong sentiment in the <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> not to allow the situation of “veto, veto, veto”
                    to continue. Is it right, he inquired, for an ally in <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> to be separated from the majority of the other <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members and prevented in the foreseeable
                    future from any hope of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> admission? He had
                    stated that the realization of this would be very difficult for his government
                    but when Mr. Vorys asked a few questions about what the Italian domestic
                    political problem was on this issue, Guidotti did not go into detail. As he left
                    he said that he would be more discouraged but for the fact that the Italian
                    position had been thoroughly rejected previously. We made it clear that our own
                    thinking is all in the direction of trying to find a way to solve the problem,
                    acting within the Charter and in accordance with Italy’s views.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
