<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="358" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Plenary Position
                                    Paper</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                                    <lb/> US/A/3429</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-01-09">January 9, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Complaint of Aggressive Acts of the United
                                    States and Its Interference in the Domestic Affairs of Other
                                    Countries, As Instanced by the Appropriation of 100 Million
                                    Dollars to Finance the Recruitment of Persons and the
                                    Organization of Armed Groups in the Soviet Union, Poland,
                                    Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria, Albania and a Number
                                    of Other Democratic Countries, as Well as Outside the Territory
                                    of Those Countries: Report of the First Committee</hi>
                                (A/2030)</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">1. united states position</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The First Committee has not recommended any resolution to the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> for adoption. The Assembly will have
                                before it, however, a Soviet resolution which was rejected by the
                                First Committee and has been reintroduced in the plenary
                                    (A/2031).<note n="1" xml:id="d358fn1">The text was the same as
                                    that submitted by the Soviet Union to the First Committee on
                                    December 19 and substantially transmitted in Paris telegram
                                        <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 745, December 19,
                                        <ref target="#pg_484">p. 484</ref>.</note> The United States
                                should <pb facs="0509" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/> vote against this
                                resolution which (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) condemns the United
                                States Mutual Security Act as an act of aggression and as
                                interference in the internal affairs of other states; and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) recommends that the United States
                                Government take steps to repeal this Act.</p>
                            <p>The United States should abstain on the question whether there should
                                be plenary debate of the First Committee report (Rule 67). If there
                                is debate the United States should make a statement along the lines
                                of <hi rend="italic">Annex A</hi> attached; if there is no debate
                                the United States, in explanation of vote, should make a statement
                                along the lines of <hi rend="italic">Annex B</hi> attached.<note n="2" xml:id="d358fn2">Neither Annex is printed, but see
                                    footnote 3, below.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">2. history in committee</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>After 4 meetings of debate the First Committee rejected Soviet
                                resolution (identical to that indicated above) by 39 votes to 5,
                                with 11 abstentions (Afghanistan, Burma, Egypt, Guatemala, India,
                                Indonesia, Iran, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Syria, and Yemen). Since
                                the Soviet resolution was the only proposal introduced under this
                                agenda item, the First Committee did not recommend any resolution to
                                the Assembly for adoption.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">3. possible developments in plenary</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is unlikely that the required number of states (one-third) will
                                desire plenary debate of the First Committee report. In this event,
                                however, the Soviet states can be expected, in explanations of vote,
                                to renew their attacks against the United States. As indicated
                                above, the United States, in explanation of vote, should make a
                                statement along the lines of <hi rend="italic">Annex B</hi>
                                    attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d358fn3">
                                    <p>On January 11 the General Assembly considered the new Soviet
                                        item and after some discussion rejected the Soviet draft
                                        resolution 42–5–11 (Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Yemen,
                                        Afghanistan, Burma, Egypt, Guatemala, India, Indonesia,
                                        Iran). For the proceedings, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (VI), <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>, pp.
                                        306 ff.</p>
                                    <p>Congressman Mansfield made a lengthy statement in explanation
                                        of the United States position, describing the Soviet charges
                                        as propaganda aimed not just at the Mutual Security Act, but
                                        as “part of a general assault launched by the delegation of
                                        the Soviet Union at the beginning of this session against
                                        the United Nations collective security system and the
                                        regional collective security systems which strengthen it.”
                                            (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 309)</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>