<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">376</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-23T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-23T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general">Human rights violations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-23T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-23T15:00:00-05:00" n="376"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">320/11–2351: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-23T21:00:00+01:00"
                            >November 23, 1951—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 331. Subj: Yugoslav item. Fol is present
                    status Yugo draft resolution:</p>
                <p>Draft resolution was circulated confidentially to friendly <gloss
                        target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s by Yugos yesterday. Is identical with text
                    transmitted in <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 297, Nov 21, except for
                    elimination of bracketed [<hi rend="italic">numbered?</hi>] para 4 and revision
                    of sentence “recommends to the govts concerned that they” to “recommends that
                    the govts concerned”. <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> will note that prior
                    to receipt of <gloss target="#t_Gadel2">Gadel</gloss> 216, Nov 21, <gloss
                        target="#t_GADel1">GADel</gloss> already had successfully suggested to Yugos
                    that their draft resolution be addressed in effect to Yugo as well as Cominform
                    states.</p>
                <p>Previous to receipt of <gloss target="#t_Gadel2">Gadel</gloss> 216 Cooper and
                    staff last night strongly urged Bebler that Yugo draft contain additional
                    recommendation as fols:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Recommends further to the govts concerned that if the international tension
                        in the area does not subside; they request the sub-commission of the peace
                        observation commission, provided fol in the resolution (VI) to arrange for
                        observation and reporting on the situation along the frontiers between Yugo
                        on the one hand, and Hungary, Bulgaria, Rumania and Albania on the
                        other”.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>In explaining this suggestion, Cooper argued that US believes it wld be
                    inconsistent for Yugos, after raising their complaint against. Cominform states
                    not to take advantage of existing <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> machinery
                    designed to meet situation. Cooper also said that some use of <gloss
                        target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> doubtless wld seem quite logical to number of
                        <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s which just previously had approved
                    establishment Balkan subcommission under Greek item in same comite.</p>
                <pb facs="0539" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/>
                <p>Bebler last night appeared unenthusiastic, but undertook to discuss suggestion
                    with his <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>. He observed that Yugo may not be
                    willing propose such recommendation in its own resolution and that if it has to
                    come it wld be better submitted in form of amendment from some other <gloss
                        target="#t_del1">del</gloss>. He inferred that in such case Yugo wld find it
                    hard to vote against it. He also commented that while US suggestion doubtless
                    has merit from logical point of view, still he wonders whether any use of <gloss
                        target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> in Yugo at this time wld be politically
                    wise.</p>
                <p>Bebler told Cory this a. m. that Yugo <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss> earlier
                    today had decided adversely on latest US suggestion and hopes US will not press
                    it either itself or through other <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s, either
                    as addition to present untabled draft or as amendment in comites. He said that
                    Yugo feels such recommendation, if incorporated now in draft resolution, wld
                    attract intensive Soviet attack on general grounds that such use of <gloss
                        target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> wld constitute unnecessary “imperialist”
                    meddling in Balkans. He added that with this in mind his <gloss target="#t_del1"
                        >del</gloss> hopes to avoid any mention of <gloss target="#t_POC1"
                        >POC</gloss> in its own speeches but that, of course, if questions are
                    raised regarding Yugo opinion on use of <gloss target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> Yugo
                        <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss> wld have to express itself. He said also
                    he hopes that if any <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss> intends to recommend
                    use of <gloss target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> under Yugo item it will consult in
                    advance with Yugo <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>, in which case Yugo wld
                    attempt to dissuade.</p>
                <p>Cory replied that we will of course promptly transmit Bebler’s remarks to US
                        <gloss target="#t_GADel1">GADel</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_Dept1"
                        >Dept</gloss>, but that to be perfectly frank he felt it only fair to state
                    that US still believes limited use of <gloss target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> wld be
                    desirable altho, of course, final decision necessarily rests with Yugo. He added
                    that there obviously can be no assurance Yugo and other interested <gloss
                        target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s wld be successful, even if they try, in
                    dissuading other states from presenting an amendment which wld be pertinent and
                    helpful to Yugo draft resolution.</p>
                <p>First reaction by Barnes<note n="1" xml:id="d376fn1">R. C. Barnes, Adviser,
                        United Kingdom Delegation to the General Assembly.</note> (<gloss
                        target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> [<gloss target="#t_UKDel1">
                        <hi rend="italic">UKDel</hi>
                    </gloss>]) to suggested addition was adverse but he agreed US wld go along if
                    Yugo accepts it. Ordonneau (Fr) was non-commital.</p>
                <p>Speaking of his conversations with other <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s re
                    Yugo item, Dr. Bebler last night said that of 20 <gloss target="#t_del1"
                        >del</gloss>s which he has so far consulted 19 <gloss target="#t_del1"
                        >del</gloss>s seem favorably disposed toward item and believe that Yugo
                    draft resolution is sufficiently mild to merit their support. One exception was
                    India which, Bebler said, was non-commital. He added that Pakistan, which
                    abstained on vote to include item in agenda in general comite; showed more
                    positive interest than before.</p>
                <p>It is very likely some other <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss> will propose ref
                    to <gloss target="#t_POC1">POC</gloss> in some form during debate which will
                    open Nov 26. In such case we shall support appropriate amendment. If no such
                    proposal made we shall review situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0540" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/>
                <p>Re para 2, <gloss target="#t_Gadel2">Gadel</gloss> 216, we propose refer human
                    rights violations in speech by <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Sent <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 331, rptd info Belgrade 84.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
