<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="418" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d418">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. J. Jefferson
                                    Jones, III, Adviser, United States Delegation to the Trusteeship
                                    Council</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">US/T/140 <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                            York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-17">July 17, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: The Ewe Question</p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>Mr. Awni Khalidy, Iraqi Delegation</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. J. Jefferson Jones, III, United States
                                        Delegation</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>Mr. Khalidy stopped me just outside the Trusteeship Council chamber
                                to discuss the Ewe question. He reiterated his reservations to
                                Council action along the lines the United States had in mind. He
                                went into considerable lengths in his argument that the United
                                States should support a resolution along the lines of the draft
                                which he had given us. He said that he would be perfectly willing to
                                give the administering authorities another chance and to authorize
                                them to submit to the Council definitive proposals for settlement of
                                the question at the next session of the Council. He also said that
                                unless the administering authorities were confronted with a Council
                                demand for action, they would let the question drag on
                                interminably.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Khalidy said that he would like to bring to the attention of the
                                United States Delegation his firm view that, unless some definitive
                                progress was made toward solving this problem, there would be an
                                “eruption of violence” in the Ewe areas. He referred to the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> news article of recent date
                                regarding rioting in the Gold Coast and French Togoland and said
                                this was merely a foretaste of what would happen unless concrete
                                steps were taken at once to work towards a settlement of the
                                problem.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Khalidy said that he thought that the United States was deeply
                                concerned in the problem for two reasons: (1) In case of another
                                world war, it was likely that the Mediterranean Sea would be closed
                                to the free world in the same way that it was during the last war.
                                If this proved to be true, western Africa would become vital to the
                                Western nations in their communications with the East. Consequently,
                                it behooves us to attempt to win the sympathetic understanding of
                                those peoples who would probably control that area of Africa within
                                the next several years. (2) Unless progress was made in solving the
                                Ewe problem, there would inevitably be a tendency on the part of the
                                Ewe people to fall under the domination of more extremist elements,
                                particularly the Communists. Mr. Khalidy thought that for this
                                reason, if for no other, the United States would wish to follow a
                                policy which would retain the friendship of the Ewes.</p>
                            <p>In my reply to Mr. Khalidy, I advanced again the reasons which form
                                the basis of the United States attitude with respect to Trusteeship
                                    <pb facs="0624" n="602" xml:id="pg_602"/> Council consideration
                                of the Ewe problem. I took advantage of the occasion to ask Mr.
                                Khalidy to clarify the statement which he had previously made to me
                                with respect to the possibility that he might be able to vote for
                                the United States resolution rather than abstain. He replied that if
                                the United States resolution, as finally presented, contained a
                                sufficient number of his ideas, he might be able to vote for the
                                resolution as a whole although abstain on certain paragraphs. I
                                pointed out the difficulty in the way of amalgamating the views of
                                the two delegations in one resolution, and particularly the fact
                                that such a resolution would “go in two directions at once”. I said,
                                however, that we should be glad, of course, to give consideration to
                                his suggestion.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>