<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="452" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>John D. Hickerson, Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations
                                Affairs, was to head the United States group at the bilateral talks
                                on colonial policy in London and Paris, October 1951, but was
                                prevented from attending just before departure. Mr. William Sanders,
                                Special Assistant to Assistant Secretary Hickerson, was designated
                                to replace Hickerson. Other members of the group were Mr. Ward P.
                                Allen, Adviser on United Nations Affairs, Bureau of European
                                Affairs, and Mr. O. Benjamin Gerig, Director of the Office of
                                Dependent Area Affairs. Detailed from their respective Embassies
                                were Miss Margaret Joy Tibbetts (for the London talks) and Mr. John
                                E. Utter (for the Paris talks). Gerig proceeded to London from
                                Geneva where he was attending <pb facs="0673" n="651" xml:id="pg_651"/> the meeting of the Special Committee on
                                Information Transmitted under Article 73 (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)
                                of the Charter of the United Nations.</p>
                            <p>The talks with the British at London were held from October 10
                                (afternoon) to October 12 (morning). The principal officers engaged
                                on the British side were, from the Foreign Office, Messrs. Paul
                                Mason, Superintending Under Secretary, and C. C. Parrott, Head of
                                the United Nations (Political) Department; from the Commonwealth
                                Relations Office, Mr. Neil Pritchard, Superintending Under
                                Secretary; and from the Colonial Office, Messrs. John Martin and
                                Andrew Cohen, Assistant Under Secretaries of State. Messrs. P. C.
                                Hope and D. I. Dunnett also attended from the Foreign Office; and
                                there was a supporting element of eight officers from the
                                Commonwealth Relations and Colonial Offices. Mr. J. K. Thompson,
                                Colonial Attaché at the British Embassy, Washington, was also
                                present. Mr. Ernest Davies, Parliamentary Under Secretary of State,
                                Foreign Office, opened the conference and presided the first
                                day.</p>
                            <p>The colonial policy talks with the French Government were held in
                                Paris on October 15 and 16. M. Leon Pignon, Representative of France
                                on the United Nations Trusteeship Council, presided. Delegates
                                attending from the French Foreign Ministry were: M. André Naudy
                                (Ministry Delegate to the United Nations), M. Jean-Daniel Jurgensen
                                (Africa Division), M. Pierre Salade (Far Eastern Department) and M.
                                Jules (?) Charles-Roux (Caribbean Department). M. Kresser
                                represented the Ministry of Overseas France.</p>
                            <p>A summary report on the London and Paris talks by William Sanders,
                                dated December 7, 1951, is printed <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>. The
                                United States Minutes for the British talks (in brief form and not
                                “agreed” minutes) are located in Department of State file
                                741.022/10–1851, under cover of London despatch 1826, October 18,
                                1951. The United States Minutes for the French talks are located in
                                Department of State Office Lot File 62 D 228 (ODA Files), “Colonial
                                Policy Talks UK and France–1951”, as part of Tab A of the Sanders
                                Report of December 7. (Tab A also included a set of the minutes of
                                the British talks.)</p>
                            <p>The London Embassy despatch forwarding the London minutes (No. 1826,
                                October 18) emphasized that the British participants regarded the
                                discussions to be of very considerable value. It was noted that the
                                Colonial Office participants had been most frank. The Foreign Office
                                had reiterated its belief to the Embassy that only through such
                                conversations could the Colonial Office be assured of the value of a
                                less legalistic and more flexible approach to dependent area
                                questions in the United Nations. The London Embassy stated that
                                “unquestionably” the morale of the Colonial Office had been raised
                                “by the evidence of a friendly United States interest in these
                                problems.” (741.022/10–1851)</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>