<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-07T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-07T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recDV1FNGQhoilizZ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90000897"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconstitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-07T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-07T15:00:00-05:00" n="477"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d477">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">320/12–751: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-07T21:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 7, 1951—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 551. Subject: South West Africa. Joint
                    resolution South West Africa handed in today sponsored by Cuba, Den, Ecuador,
                    Egypt, Iraq, Philippines, Thailand, and US. Text same as that submitted in
                        US/A/C.4/212<note n="1" xml:id="d477fn1">Dated December 1, <ref
                            target="#pg_696">p. 696</ref>.</note> except small verbal changes first
                    two paras, substitution “regrets” for “deplores” in para 14 and alteration of
                    para 17 to provide for reconstitution new <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Comite
                    unnamed blank states because Den insisted getting off comite.</p>
                <p>Reconstitution new comite therefore offers possibility US also discontinue serve,
                    although strong pressure being brought to continue. <gloss target="#t_Dept1"
                        >Dept</gloss>’s reaction this point wld be appreciated. Appears likely res
                    will be adopted huge majority.<note n="2" xml:id="d477fn2">
                        <p>On December 8 Ambassador Sayre told the Fourth Committee that the draft
                            resolution “was the culmination of the Committee’s sincere efforts
                            throughout the years to find a just and practicable solution to the
                            thorny question of South West Africa. …</p>
                        <p>“It was greatly to be regretted that those efforts had failed. All the
                            Committee could do was to support the opinion of the International Court
                            of Justice and to hope that the Government of the Union of South Africa
                            would give effect to that opinion. It was essential to maintain the rule
                            of law and reason in international affairs. A just solution in respect
                            of South West Africa would bring greater peace and harmony not only to
                            Africa but also to the world as a whole. The people and Government of
                            the Union of South Africa believed in the rule of law and had
                            contributed much to its maintenance. … He therefore felt that a solemn
                            appeal should be made to the Government of the Union of South Africa to
                            reconsider its position and to resume negotiations on the basis of the
                            proposals of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on South West
                            Africa. … The joint draft resolution was couched in reasonable, though
                            firm terms, and he trusted that it would win unanimous support.” (<gloss
                                target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (VI), <hi rend="italic">Fourth
                                Committee</hi>, p. 131.)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
