<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Fourth Meeting of the International Security Affairs
                    Committee, Held in the Department of State, 11:00 a.m., February 16,
                    1951</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d637</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">637</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-02-16T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-02-16T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-16T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-16T11:00:00-05:00" n="637"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d637">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> Files, Lot 53 D 443</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Fourth Meeting of the International Security
                        Affairs Committee, Held in the Department of State, 11:00 a.m., February 16,
                        1951</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1951-02-16T11:00:00-05:00">February 16, 1951, 11:00 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <lb/>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> M–4</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow a list of those present (18) and a discussion of previous
                    minutes.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Grant Aid to Latin America</hi>
                </p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cabot</hi> said that the Department of State is not
                    prepared at this time to make a decision with respect to the proposed grant aid
                    program for Latin America because it is felt that more information as to the
                    nature of and justification for the program are needed in State before such an
                    important policy decision can be made. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cabot</hi>
                    <pb facs="1022" n="1000" xml:id="pg_1000"/> listed some of the considerations
                    which enter into his own thinking on this question: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>This is a very important question of policy and not merely a problem
                            of the dollar amount involved. A decision to extend even the modest
                            amount of grant aid proposed will subject us to persuasive pressures to
                            increase the amount to unforeseeable proportions over the next few
                            years.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>According to the State Department estimates denial of this grant aid
                            would make it unlikely that the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> could
                            raise Latin American forces for foreign duty under the <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, whether in Korea or elsewhere.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The increasing shortage of war materials, and the low priority we have
                            given Latin America as a claimant on available war materials, make it
                            clear that the Latin American countries would not receive shipments of
                            any consequence for 12 or 18 months, even under a grant aid
                            program.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is anticipated that the flow of dollars to Latin America will
                            increase considerably during <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1952 as a
                            result of our stepped-up defense effort, so it is not clear why the
                            Latinos should not buy what arms they require.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is open to question whether the Congress would support such a grant
                            aid program, and it is possible that its inclusion in the 1952
                            legislation might weaken our total case.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cabot</hi> stated that it was not clear to him what we
                    could reasonably expect to gain in terms of U.S. security through this proposed
                    program, since we could only promise aid and would not be able to deliver within
                    the next year or year and a half.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cabot</hi> stated that it would be most helpful for
                    the Department of State to have answers, even though not specific and not
                    complete, to the questions raised by Mr. Ohly<note n="1" xml:id="d637fn1">John
                        H. Ohly, Acting Assistant Director, International Security Affairs.</note>
                    with respect to the proposed program (paragraph IV, page 5, of <gloss
                        target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–5).<note n="2" xml:id="d637fn2">Dated
                        February 15, <ref target="#pg_985">p. 985</ref>.</note> He concluded by
                    saying that since the Department of State is not in a position to make a
                    decision on this question at the present time he suggested that the Department
                    of Defense undertake to provide him with as much of the needed information as
                    possible so that the question could be decided in <gloss target="#t_ISAC1"
                        >ISAC</gloss> at a future meeting. He mentioned that Mr. Nitze is meeting
                    with elements of the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> early next week and
                    that in these talks he might be able to get the kind of information which the
                    Department of State requires for a decision on this matter.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="smallcaps">General Burns</hi> stated that he had hoped that the
                    information supplied by General Bolte at the previous meeting would answer most
                    of the State Department’s questions. However, Defense will provide as much
                    information as it can in reply to the questions in Paragraph IV of <gloss
                        target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–5. He pointed out that this grant aid
                    proposal has only recently been approved in the Department of Defense and that
                    there are no detailed plans developed in support of it. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Gordon</hi> pointed <pb facs="1023" n="1001" xml:id="pg_1001"/> out that
                    since an early decision on this question is required to meet the needs of the
                    Foreign Ministers Meeting (March 26) and the Congressional Presentation (April
                    2) a firm decision should be reached by March 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        White</hi> stated that although Mr. Miller realized it was not possible for
                    him to have this decision before leaving on his trip, he wants to be consulted
                    before a final decision is taken, and if it is felt that a decision must be
                    reached before Mr. Miller returns to Washington (between March 10 and 12) it
                    will be necessary to consult him by cable.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Halaby</hi> pointed out that at this stage the grant
                    aid question is largely between Defense and State, and that although <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and the other member agencies have a less
                    direct interest, it should be up to State and Defense to work out an agreed line
                    and merely keep the other agencies informed of developments. While agreeing
                    generally with Mr. Halaby, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Gordon</hi> and <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hebbard</hi> asked that they be kept up to date on
                    ‘State-Defense discussions. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Cabot</hi> stated that he
                    would work this out with General Burns and would tentatively schedule the
                    question for final decision at the <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> meeting
                    on February 23.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Gordon</hi> stated his understanding that a decision
                    by State on the grant aid question is not conditioned upon full and complete
                    answers by Defense to the formidable list of questions posed in paragraph IV of
                        <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–5. He pointed out that we should not
                    expect that a new program such as the one proposed can be supported by as
                    detailed a programming job as we can reasonably expect in connection with the
                    European <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Cabot</hi> agreed with this observation and emphasized that he only wants a
                    clear picture of what this program is intended to achieve in order to decide
                    whether it warrants the major policy decision required.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Halaby</hi> stated that there should be an estimate
                    of the financial and economic capabilities of the Latin American countries to be
                    affected by the proposed program in order that the economic impact may be
                    assessed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hebbard</hi> stated that he would undertake
                    to get at least a rough estimate on the financial capabilities of these
                    countries. He noted, however, that Treasury appreciates that a strong dollar
                    position of a Latin American country is only one element which would affect a
                    decision on the question of extending grant aid.</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>, addressing the document <gloss
                        target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–5, said that <gloss target="#t_ARA1"
                        >ARA</gloss> could not approve it because they did not think it possible
                    adequately to set forth the pro’s and con’s on the question until there is more
                    complete information available. Apart from this fact, he stated his reservations
                    on the area approach taken by this paper, pointing out that each Latin American
                    country presents a different problem and that a more selective approach is
                    sounder. He stated that two of the questions listed in paragraph IV of the paper
                    particularly interest him, namely, <pb facs="1024" n="1002" xml:id="pg_1002"/>
                    for what purposes do we contemplate making Latin American troops available; and
                    from what countries would they be drawn. In conclusion, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        White</hi> urged that the financial condition of a Latin American country
                    not be taken as the controlling element in a decision on whether or not to
                    extend grant aid, since psychological, political, and strategic factors are also
                    major consideration.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of matters unrelated to the question of a military grant
                    aid program for Latin America.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
