<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of Defense ( (Foster) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d653</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">653</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="653"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d653">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">720.5–MSP/12–1751</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foster</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-17">December 17,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I am forwarding to you for your
                    information a copy of my letter to the President dated 5 December 1951 regarding
                    the Title IV Mutual Security Program. In this letter I have recommended that the
                    President make a finding to the effect that United States defense plans
                    establish a need for the participation in missions important to the defense of
                    the Western Hemisphere of certain designated Latin American countries. I further
                    recommended that because of this requirement, the President find that military
                    assistance may be furnished these countries in accordance with the provisions of
                    Section 401 of the Mutual Security Act of 1951. This letter was coordinated with
                    your Department.</p>
                <p>You will note that the list of countries and the forces each is to be requested
                    to make available reflects the recommendation regarding Ecuador made by you in
                    your letter to me dated 9 November 1951.<note n="1" xml:id="d653fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1027">p. 1027</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1055" n="1033" xml:id="pg_1033"/>
                <p>Furthermore in addition to the tabulated countries and their force contributions,
                    I have recommended to the President that Venezuela be included tentatively in
                    the list of countries eligible to receive military grant aid. This action again
                    reflects another of the recommendations contained in your letter referred to
                    above. In the case of this latter country, I consider that every effort should
                    be made to secure the full participation of Venezuela in the Mutual Security
                    Program by means of reimbursable aid; however, if in the course of future
                    conversations or negotiations it appears from a political point of view that
                    Venezuela’s omission from the list of countries to receive military grant aid
                    may threaten the defense and continued flow of Venezuela’s strategic materials,
                    this consideration would be overriding. In such an event, the eligibility of
                    Venezuela to receive grant aid will have been established in the finding by the
                    President.</p>
                <p>With further reference to your letter of 9 November 1951, I agree that Brazil
                    should be granted a high priority if any reallocation of funds which may be
                    required as a result of failure of one or more of the other governments to
                    qualify for inclusion in this year’s program. However, the amount of military
                    grant aid to be given to Brazil should be in consonance with Brazil’s
                    willingness to accept hemisphere defense tasks, and also her ability to absorb
                    efficiently and utilize effectively such materiel assistance. Further any
                    reallocation of funds among the Latin American countries must be effected so as
                    to insure the balanced progress of the total program.</p>
                <p>On notification of the President’s action with reference to the recommended
                    findings, I understand that you are prepared to issue the necessary instructions
                    to the diplomatic missions in the countries to be approached with a view to
                    ascertaining whether the governments of these countries are willing to enter
                    upon negotiations for the conclusions of the required agreements.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Foster</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-05">December 5,
                                1951</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: Section 401 of the Mutual
                        Security Act of 1951 authorized the appropriation of $38,150,000 for the
                        purpose of furnishing grant military assistance to the other American
                        Republics. The Congress, in the Mutual Security Appropriation Act, 1952,
                        made such an appropriation. However, the furnishing of such assistance is
                        contingent upon compliance with the relevant general provisions of the
                        Mutual Defense Assistance Act of 1949, as amended, and upon several <pb
                            facs="1056" n="1034" xml:id="pg_1034"/> special provisions of the Mutual
                        Security Act of 1951. Among the latter is this requirement: “That such
                        assistance may be furnished only in accordance with defense plans which are
                        found by the President to require the recipient country to participate in
                        missions important to the defense of the Western Hemisphere.”</p>
                    <p>The Department of Defense has for a number of years been giving careful study
                        to the roles which the various Latin American countries might play in
                        support of Western Hemisphere defense. This study has resulted in the
                        conclusion that in addition to maintaining the minimum armed forces required
                        to preserve internal security (including the performance of such tasks as
                        protection against enemy clandestine operations or raids; protection of
                        sources, and of installations required in the production or distribution, of
                        strategic materials; safeguarding vital lines of communication; and insuring
                        the local security of bases and other military installations), selected
                        Latin American countries could, provided that they were furnished adequate
                        equipment and training, supply forces capable of executing certain specific
                        and essential common defense missions within this hemisphere. These
                        missions, if not performed by the selected countries, would necessitate the
                        diversion of substantial United States forces to the area in time of war.
                        The specific missions are based on a current United States war plan, but the
                        general concept of this plan is in consonance with the Common Defense Scheme
                        which was prepared multilaterally by the Inter-American Defense Board and
                        will also be reflected in the defense plan currently being developed by the
                        Board. Ten Latin American governments and the United States have approved
                        the Common Defense Scheme and formal approval of this document, or of the
                        defense plan, by each of the proposed countries will be a prerequisite to
                        receipt of military grant aid under this Program.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with the war plan, each of the Latin American countries
                        concerned will be asked to provide specific forces to perform hemisphere
                        defense missions. These forces will generally be employed
                        extra-territorially and the details regarding the units to be provided by
                        each country will be contained in the military understandings which,
                        together with the bilateral agreements required by the Mutual Security Act
                        of 1951, will be negotiated with each country. It is considered highly
                        desirable from a military standpoint that the several Latin American
                        governments indicated in Tab (A), provided they can be assisted by adequate
                        military grant aid, make forces of the general types and sizes shown
                        available for the performance of hemisphere defense missions in accordance
                        with the war plan.</p>
                    <p>In advance of negotiations, it is of course not possible to know within any
                        accuracy the extent to which individual governments are prepared to agree to
                        provide specific forces of the types indicated to <pb facs="1057" n="1035"
                            xml:id="pg_1035"/> perform hemisphere defense missions. Consequently,
                        the details with respect to the precise units which would be furnished by
                        each country will need to be negotiated with each government and
                        incorporated in the military understanding.</p>
                    <p>The Department of Defense has therefore recommended that the several
                        governments indicated in Tab (A) be approached and that, upon agreement
                        between the United States and the Latin American nations concerned, programs
                        be initiated to supply grant military assistance for the purpose of
                        supporting the forces to be provided by each. The Department of Defense has
                        further recommended that in the event that satisfactory agreements cannot be
                        concluded with one of the nations, the following course of action be
                        followed: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In the case of army forces, one of the other countries shown on
                                the list would be asked to provide the additional forces required.
                                The decision as to which nation to substitute would depend on the
                                type of forces to be furnished.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In the case of navy forces, one of the other nations listed would
                                be asked to supply the deficiency.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In the case of air forces, the following countries, in the order
                                of priority indicated, would be approached: (<hi rend="italic"
                                    >a</hi>) Argentina; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Dominican
                                Republic; and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Bolivia.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In requesting the concurrence of the Secretary of State from a political
                        standpoint in the foregoing list of proposed recipient nations, I pointed
                        out that the decision to include Argentina in the Mutual Security Program
                        was made only after an extensive study and was based primarily on military
                        considerations. I further indicated that in view of the current political
                        situation in Argentina, the Secretary of State might wish to delay
                        negotiations with that country until a more appropriate time.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary of State has concurred in the foregoing proposals with respect
                        to the countries to be approached subject, however, to a specific
                        recommendation with regard to including Venezuela as a recipient of grant
                        aid.</p>
                    <p>Venezuela was not included in the original list because, in the course of
                        military staff conversations earlier this year, Venezuelan military
                        authorities stated that the Venezuelan government would purchase any of the
                        equipment which might be required for its defense forces. The Secretary of
                        State has recommended that Venezuela be included tentatively in the list of
                        countries proposed as recipients of grant aid pending verification of the
                        ability and willingness of the Venezuelan government to pay its own way in
                        procuring the equipment required by those forces which it should support in
                        order to carry out vital hemisphere defense missions. In order to secure the
                        continued flow of strategic materials to the United States and in view of
                        the possibility <pb facs="1058" n="1036" xml:id="pg_1036"/> that political
                        considerations may become overriding as a result of future conversations, I
                        concur in the recommendation of the Secretary of State to include Venezuela
                        tentatively in the list of countries eligible to receive military grant
                        aid.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary of State in addition to making the above recommendation, agreed
                        that the political situation in Argentina was currently of such a nature
                        that negotiations with that country on this subject should be delayed until
                        a more appropriate time.</p>
                    <p>In view of the importance of proceeding to implement the aforementioned plans
                        and our desire to initiate diplomatic-military negotiations with the
                        proposed recipient governments at the earliest practicable date, it is
                        recommended that you now make a finding to the effect that United States
                        defense plans establish a need for the participation in missions important
                        to the defense of the Western Hemisphere of the proposed recipient countries
                        indicated in Tab (A), with the addition of Venezuela tentatively. It is
                        further recommended that you find that, because of the above, military
                        assistance may be furnished these countries in accordance with the
                        provisions of Section 401 of the Mutual Security Act of 1951.</p>
                    <p>The Department of State concurs in this recommendation, and I am transmitting
                        this letter through the Director for Mutual Security<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d653fn2">W. Averell Harriman assumed the office of Director for
                            Mutual Security on October 31, 1951.</note> so that he may indicate his
                        concurrence or comments. In the event that you make the finding recommended,
                        it is proposed immediately to approach the several countries indicated (with
                        the exception, for the reasons hereinabove set forth, of Argentina and
                        possibly Venezuela) with a view to initiating negotiations.</p>
                    <p>With great respect, I am</p>
                    <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi> A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1059" n="1037" xml:id="pg_1037"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Tab A]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Department of Defense list of countries and the forces which each is
                        expected to contribute (with the support of military grant aid) is indicated
                        below: <table cols="4" rows="11">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Country</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Army</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Navy</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Air Force</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Argentina</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">2 AAA Gun Bns.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Brazil</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">
                                    <gloss target="#t_RCT1">RCT</gloss> w/Sv Spt.<lb/>1 AAA Gun
                                    Bn.</cell>
                                <cell>2 Light Cruisers<lb/>5 Destroyers<lb/>8 Patrol Craft<lb/>5
                                    Mine Craft<lb/>2 Ren. Sqdns. (Air)</cell>
                                <cell>3 Fighter Sqdns.<lb/>4 Light Bomb. Sqdns.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Chile</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 Ren. Bn.</cell>
                                <cell>2 Light Cruisers<lb/>13 Patrol Craft</cell>
                                <cell>1 Fighter Sqdn.<lb/>2 Light Bomb. Sqdns.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Colombia</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 AAA AW Bn.</cell>
                                <cell>4 Patrol Craft</cell>
                                <cell>1 Fighter Sqdn.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Cuba</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 Transport Sqdn.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Ecuador</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 AAA AW Bn.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 Fighter Sqdn.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Mexico</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 AAA Gun Bn.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 Fighter Sqdn.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Peru</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 AAA AW Bn.</cell>
                                <cell>6 Patrol Craft</cell>
                                <cell>2 Fighter Sqdns.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Uruguay</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#top">1 AAA AW Bn.</cell>
                                <cell>2 Patrol Craft<lb/>1 Ren. Sqdn. (Air)</cell>
                                <cell>1 Fighter Sqdn.<lb/>1 Light Bomb. Sqdn.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Air Force Alternate countries: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Argentina</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Dominican Republic<note n="3" xml:id="d653fn3">For
                                                documentation pertaining to the effort of the
                                                Department of State to have the Department of
                                                Defense upgrade the priority assigned to the
                                                Dominican Republic vis-a-vis the military grant aid
                                                program for Latin America, see <ref
                                                  target="#pg_1367">pp. 1367</ref> ff.</note>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Bolivia</item>
                                    </list>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
