<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="705" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d705">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Rio de Janeiro Embassy Files, Lot 61 F
                                30, Folder 523.1</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mills</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Officer in Charge of Brazilian Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kidder</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">official—informal</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-21">May 21,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Randy</hi>: I received this morning your
                                Confidential letter of May 15, 1951,<note n="1" xml:id="d705fn1">Neither the letter nor its enclosures are printed.</note>
                                enclosing Ed Moline’s memorandum of May 3 to Ivan White on “Brazil’s
                                Proposed Petroleum Development Program” and a memorandum of the same
                                date entitled “Brazil’s Petroleum Demand and Program for Petroleum
                                Development” prepared by Ortiz of <gloss target="#t_PED1">PED</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>Without doubt you have seen the Ambassador’s Top Secret telegram 1503
                                of May 21<note n="2" xml:id="d705fn2">Not printed.</note> for the
                                attention of Assistant Secretary Miller. It stresses the political
                                importance which the Brazilians attach to receiving from us the
                                equipment for both prospecting and refining which they have on
                                order.</p>
                            <p>No one in the Department needs to be told of the nationalistic fervor
                                surrounding the petroleum problem in almost every country which has
                                hopes of developing self sufficiency in this field. Brazil, as you
                                well know, is no exception.</p>
                            <pb facs="1221" n="1199" xml:id="pg_1199"/>
                            <p>I make this well known observation merely as a reminder that many
                                things of great importance to us may be influenced greatly by the
                                way in which we handle the Brazilian request for assistance in
                                purchasing petroleum equipment with their own resources. It is not
                                unlikely that there are persons both inside and outside the
                                Department arguing with sincerity that we should insist that Brazil
                                accept the participation of private capital in both refining and
                                exploration on the terms which such private capital has to date been
                                willing to offer and to force such acceptance we should ration
                                equipment releases.</p>
                            <p>From the Ortiz memorandum I judge that <gloss target="#t_PED1">PED</gloss> can make a case for the equipment either way on
                                defense grounds. The nub of the matter as we see it, however, lies
                                in the last sentence which reads as follows:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“To encourage the continuance and intensification of this
                                    alliance sympathetic consideration should be given to Brazil’s
                                    economic development programs, particularly in so far as they
                                    can be integrated into the over-all Western Hemisphere defense
                                    effort.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>The program which is dearest to the Brazilian heart is the petroleum
                                program, both refining and exploration. If we do not wish the
                                alliance to go sour in other fields, we should be slow to use the
                                screws of “short supply” to prevent Brazil from obtaining
                                equipment.</p>
                            <p>I think you are the one person in the Department who, because of your
                                fairly recent residence here, fully realizes the emotional dynamite
                                in this question and what damage could be done to the overall
                                relationship if the Brazilians become convinced we are “welshing” on
                                what they undoubtedly consider a commitment to help them buy
                                petroleum equipment with their own money.<note n="3" xml:id="d705fn3">In a letter to Ambassador Johnson, dated July
                                    5, 1951, Mr. Kidder stated in part the following: “Procuring
                                    petroleum equipment for the Brazilians is a tough, uphill fight
                                    in which we so far have the support and the good will of people
                                    in the Petroleum Policy Staff, in the Petroleum Administration
                                    for Defense, and in the Office of International Trade. The
                                    three-man group studying petroleum refinery equipment is working
                                    hard and is in close touch with the representatives in New York
                                    of the National Petroleum Council and with the American firms
                                    working for the Council. Progress is being made but it is
                                    impossible to come out with a flat approval of all of Brazil’s
                                    requests for equipment. The situation is becoming increasingly
                                    tighter … and refinery equipment must go to places where it will
                                    produce optimum results. Brazil’s case can be argued on several
                                    grounds but, when analyzed alongside other requirements for
                                    petroleum equipment, its case boils down to the paramount
                                    political considerations about which you and Shelly have
                                    written. We have made the strongest possible case based on those
                                    considerations.” (832.2547/6–2551)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Sincerely,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sheldon</hi> T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mills</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>