<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Ward P. Alien, Member, United States Party
                    on Colonial Policy Talks With the French</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="96"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">320/10–1551</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Ward P. Alien, Member,
                        United States Party on Colonial Policy Talks With the French</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d96fn1">This and the Allen memorandum of conversation,
                        October 17, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>, were carried back to Washington on
                        October 18 by the head of the U.S. party, William Sanders.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-15">October 15,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Moroccan Case in the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                </p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">M. Maurice Schumann, Secretary of State for
                            Foreign Affairs;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">M. Pignon, French Delegate to Trusteeship
                            Council;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">M. Broustra, Director of Conference Section
                                (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>);</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">M. Naudy, Conference Section (<gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>);</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">M. Wolfrom, Assistant Director, Conference
                            Section (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>);</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. William Sanders, Department of State;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Benjamin Gerig, Department of State;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. John Utter, U.S. Embassy, Paris;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Ward P. Allen, Department of State.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>M. Schumann took the occasion of an informal conversation with the above group to
                    raise the question and reiterated the French position as follows:</p>
                <p>1. As soon as the question of admitting the item to the agenda arises in the
                    General Committee, the French will make a major stand on the <pb facs="0163"
                        n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> question of jurisdiction under Article 2,
                    paragraph 7, claiming that the Assembly is completely incompetent to deal with
                    the matter. They will, however (and M. Schumann gave us to understand this would
                    be in the General Committee) take advantage of the opportunity to explain in
                    some detail the French record in Morocco. However, they will force the question
                    to a vote on the jurisdictional issue.</p>
                <p>2. M. Schumann seemed quite optimistic that the matter can be kept off the
                    agenda, provided the US, UK and French present “a solid front”. He stated that
                    several of the Arab States themselves (specifically Iraq and Saudi-Arabia) had
                    previously informed the French that they were opposed to submitting the item,
                    and were highly unenthusiastic about any <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    consideration, realizing that there is really no constructive action the <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> could take. They did, however, state that if the
                    matter did arise, they would, of course, have to go along. As to the Latin
                    Americans, M. Schumann referred to Brazil’s recent refusal of Egypt’s request to
                    mediate in the matter as indicative of Latin indifference and he therefore felt
                    confident that there would be general support among the Latin American
                    Delegations for opposing admission of the item.</p>
                <p>We sought to temper somewhat this optimism on the question of admission to the
                    agenda, pointing out the traditional attitude of the Latin Americans both
                    towards freedom of discussion in the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and
                    towards colonial problems generally, as well as the fact that the reaction of
                    Brazil is not always an accurate barometer of that of the other 19. Making clear
                    we were not prepared to comment on the U.S. position, we nevertheless gave no
                    ground for belief that the U.S. would be able to join the French in opposing
                    admission of the item.</p>
                <p>3. If, nevertheless, the item should be admitted, M. Schumann initially stated
                    that the French would probably not participate in any discussion in Committee I.
                    In response to a direct question on this point, however, he replied that at that
                    time, the French Government (which had not yet reached a decision) would “have
                    to consider the question of their participation in the discussion”.</p>
                <p>There was general agreement among those present that, if admitted, it would be
                    desirable to place the item as low on the Committee agenda as possible.</p>
                <p>4. In the course of the discussion it was noted that Egypt in its complaint
                    placed great emphasis on the violation of Human Rights in Morocco. On this
                    aspect the French freely admitted the right of Committee IV to consider the
                    matter, in view of the fact that under Chapter 11 of the Charter France has
                    accepted the responsibility for promoting human rights in Morocco as a
                    non-self-governing-territory and reports upon this problem regularly to the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. M. Schumann nevertheless maintained that
                    Committee I has no right to discuss even this aspect of the Moroccan question
                    since it would then be placed in <pb facs="0164" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> a
                    political context. The U.S. representatives mentioned that, legal position
                    aside, from a practical point of view, Committee I or the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                        Hoc</hi> Committee<note n="2" xml:id="d96fn2">The General Assembly’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Political and Security
                        Affairs.</note> might be a more favorable forum than Committee IV for this
                    type of discussion since the Heads of Delegations who sit in Committee I are apt
                    to be more responsive to over-all political factors and less likely to take
                    positions without instructions from or consultations with their governments. It
                    was generally agreed that the raising of the specific case of violation of human
                    rights in Morocco in Committee IV might introduce a new precent [<hi
                        rend="italic">precedent</hi>] which might create future difficulties.</p>
                <p>5. Throughout the discussion the French representative sought to place the
                    problem of Morocco in the context of its importance as part of the problem of
                    defense of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> area. He pointed out the
                    vulnerability of U.S. to attack in the course of any discussion because of the
                    existence of U.S. bases there, and thus emphasized the desirability of a
                    completely united front on this whole question between the U.S. and France.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
