<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-01-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="11" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">EAC Files, Lot 52M 64, File
                            “215—France”</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the <gloss type="from">Counselor of the American Delegation</gloss> to the
                                European Advisory Commission</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kennan</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-01-15">January 15, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Sir William Strang’ phoned me about one o’clock today.</p>
                        <p>He said that they had had news from Washington to the effect that
                            Bovenschen had been getting on very nicely in his conversations, and
                            that there had been some talk there about the French agreement. It had
                            been suggested—he thought by Mr. McCloy<note n="38" xml:id="d11fn38">John J. McCloy, Assistant Secretary of War.</note> —that they
                            should first make sure that Monnet<note n="39" xml:id="d11fn39">Jean
                                Monnet, Commissioner of Armaments, Supplies and Reconstruction in
                                the French Committee of National Liberation.</note> was qualified to
                            discuss the French agreement on behalf of the National Committee, and
                            that when this was confirmed the paper should first be cleared before
                            the Advisory Commission as soon as possible, prior to talks with
                            Monnet.</p>
                        <p>He said that the British Joint Chiefs had just approached the Foreign
                            Office and suggested that conversations with Monnet be started at once,
                            subject to confirmation of the latter’s competency. The Foreign Office
                            had replied that the Russians had said they had <pb facs="0030" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> certain observations to make on this document and
                            that it would be better for this reason to bring it first before the
                            Advisory Commission. It was his idea that when the paper was produced
                            before the Commission, we would say to the Russians in effect: “We have
                            been talking together about this matter and wish to talk to the French
                            about it. We would like to know any views you may have, before entering
                            into our discussions with the French.” The Commission could then take
                            note of Russian observations, and could ask that they be communicated to
                            our Governments, to be borne in mind in the talks with Monnet.</p>
                        <p>He did not consider that the document itself would have to be discussed
                            in detail by the Commission. “We don’t regard the EAC as a body which
                            can go into detail on civil affairs”, he said.</p>
                        <p>He understood that our Government had already received confirmation of
                            Monnet’s competence to discuss this matter. The British Government had
                            also wired asking for such confirmation, and expected to receive it at
                            any time.</p>
                        <p>They proposed, therefore, to raise the matter in the EAC, unless Mr.
                            Winant wished to do so himself.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>G[<hi rend="smallcaps">eorge</hi>] F. K[<hi rend="smallcaps">ennan</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>