<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="345" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d345">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War/2412</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Soviet Embassy</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On March 19, the British Ambassador, Mr. Kerr, sent a letter to Mr. V. M.
                        Molotov, People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs and, on behalf of the
                        British Government, informed him that the British Government gave
                        consideration to the question of application of the <pb facs="0601" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/> principle of unconditional surrender in regard to
                        European countries—satellites of Germany, in the light, as it was said in
                        the letter, of the new situation developed as a result of the terms which
                        were proposed by the Soviet Government to Finland and which, as it is known,
                        do not contain a demand of unconditional surrender and provide negotiations
                        on certain questions.</p>
                    <p>The letter contains a summary as to how the British Government interprets the
                        formula “unconditional surrender” and points out in detail the disadvantages
                        which may arise for the Allies in the case of strict application of this
                        principle in regard to the European satellite countries and expresses the
                        thought that, on the contrary, non-application of this principle may in
                        certain cases be advantageous for the Allies, the policy of whom should be
                        that of withdrawing small countries from the war, as it is said in the
                        letter, as soon as possible.</p>
                    <p>The letter further says that while it is desirable to insist on unconditional
                        surrender in the case of Germany, it is not necessary that the same formula
                        is to be applied as obligatory to small European countries.</p>
                    <p>Having in view that the principle of the unconditional surrender in regard to
                        all Axis countries with whom correspondingly are in a state of war the
                        Soviet, British and American governments was confirmed at the Moscow
                        Conference, the British Government in the above-mentioned letter asks
                        “whether the Soviet Government, on its part, agrees that all the three
                        governments be freed from the Moscow decision as far as the small European
                        Axis countries are concerned, in regard to their propaganda in these
                        countries, as well as in connection with any peace moves, which these
                        countries may undertake, in order that in the future the three governments,
                        as far as these countries are concerned, were free to decide, in the light
                        of existing circumstances and, after consultation with each other, whether
                        to insist or not to insist on the unconditional surrender.”</p>
                    <p>At the end of the letter the Soviet Government was asked to give a speedy
                        reply in view of the fact that serious appeals for peace from the Rumanian,
                        Hungarian and Bulgarian governments may be received. It was also stated in
                        the letter that a similar request was being made to the United States
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>On March 29, the Soviet Government gave the following reply to Ambassador
                        Kerr’s letter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“In connection with your letter of March 19, in regard to the
                                application of unconditional surrender to European
                                countries—satellites of Hitlerite Germany, the Soviet Government
                                informs, that, as it was already clear from the Soviet peace terms
                                to Finland, the Soviet Government considers it possible, under
                                certain circumstances, not to apply the principles of unconditional
                                surrender to the satellites of Germany to what [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] and the British Government agreed.</p>
                            <pb facs="0602" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/>
                            <p>The Soviet Government considers that the demand of unconditional
                                surrender from European satellite countries under certain
                                circumstances may yield not a positive but a negative effect,
                                helping not to weaken but to strengthen the bonds of satellite
                                countries with Germany and thereby delaying the process of
                                disintegration of these bonds. Besides, the principal task of the
                                Allied governments in regard to the countries—satellites of Germany,
                                especially under the present conditions, must be that of assisting
                                the rupture between these countries and the Hitlerite Government and
                                their going over to the side of the Allies for the purpose of
                                hastening the defeat of Germany. Proceeding from the above-mentioned
                                considerations, the Soviet Government regards favorably the proposal
                                of the British Government that, in modification of the decisions of
                                the Moscow Conference, the three Allied governments, in each
                                separate case, could make decisions after having consulted each
                                other, whether they should insist on the unconditional surrender in
                                regard to a particular satellite country, or, instead of that, to
                                put forward moderate concrete terms of agreement between this
                                country and the Allied countries.</p>
                            <p>As to the question of applying the principle of unconditional
                                surrender to Germany, the Soviet Government considers that this
                                principle should not be subjected to any doubt and that it should be
                                preserved in regard to Germany to the full extent.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Soviet Government, until making final decision regarding the proposal of
                        the British Government, would like also to know opinion of the American
                        Government on this question. The Soviet Government would appreciate a speedy
                        reply from the Government of the United States.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-31">March 31,
                                1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>