<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Extract From the Personal Diary of the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Stettinius))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d424</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">424</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="424"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot File 60–D 224, Box 59: Stettinius Diary</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Extract From the Personal Diary of the <gloss type="from"
                            >Under Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stettinius</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="14" xml:id="d424fn14">The personal diary of Edward R.
                        Stettinius, Jr., covering the Dumbarton Oaks Conversations, was based on
                        personal conversations, correspondence, telegrams, minutes of meetings, and
                        other documents; vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> covers the period August
                        20 to September 7, 1944, and vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, September 8
                        to October 7, 1944.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fourth Day, Thursday</hi>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1944-08-24">August 24, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">12:30 Meeting at the White House</hi>.</p>
                <p>Messrs. Hackworth, Dunn, Pasvolsky and Bowman accompanied me. We started our
                    discussion with the President at 12:45 and left at 1:10. The memorandum on the
                    seven open points<note n="15" xml:id="d424fn15">See footnote 3, <ref
                            target="#pg_717">p. 717</ref>.</note> which I had left with the
                    President the day before was on his desk, when we entered. We gathered around
                    his desk but did not take seats. The following resulted from the meeting.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The President approved our proposal that at this stage the Executive
                        Council should not be given the right to impose the terms of settlement of a
                        dispute but that its function should be to promote peaceful settlement, to
                        make recommendations to the parties and to settle disputes only on the
                        request of the parties.</item>
                    <pb facs="0745" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>On the voting question, as to whether great powers parties to a dispute
                        should be allowed to vote, there was only a brief discussion but the
                        President approved our position that voting under such circumstances should
                        not be permitted, and making a statement that our people would understand
                        the principle that a man should not sit in judgment on his own case.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The President approved our recommendation that we stand for a two-year
                        term for non-permanent members of the Council.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>There was considerable discussion on the question of including France as a
                        permanent member of the Council. The President felt we should not be too
                        explicit on this point as difficulty might arise over the word “recognize”.
                        It was decided that we should accept some provision which would provide for
                        a permanent place for France when she has a permanent government. We also
                        discussed the case of Brazil and the President finally expressed the view
                        that he thought we should raise the question of an additional permanent seat
                        in general terms but that we should not insist on it at this time. He
                        thought in this connection that we might make informal references to Brazil
                        in the discussion.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>With only brief discussion the President approved our recommendation that
                        we should accept a two-third rather than a majority vote in the Council
                        except on minor decisions.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The President agreed with our position that the proposals should not
                        contain provisions for withdrawal and suspension. He seemed to feel that
                        such provision would tend to weaken the organization and that the matter
                        should be left to further experience.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>On <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> judges the President approved our
                        position after a very brief discussion. (Our recommendation was that we
                        should make it clear that we feel the principle of <hi rend="italic">ad
                            hoc</hi> judges is unwholesome but that we should not press the matter
                        because we ourselves would always have a judge on the court.)</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>There was then some discussion of the name of the organization, its
                        headquarters, and also of the seat for the world court. It developed that
                        the President favors the name “The United Nations” and that he feels
                        strongly that Geneva should not be the headquarters. He expressed the
                        opinion that the permanent secretariat would require some fixed seat but
                        that the Council and the Assembly could hold its sessions at different
                        places, pointing to the experience on Pan-American conferences in this
                        regard. He mentioned the Azores and Hawaii as possible places of meeting
                        where ideal climates could be found. He referred to the Pentagon and Empire
                        State Buildings as places where the permanent secretariat could be housed
                        and did not seem to feel there would be too much difficulty in holding
                        meetings in different places with the secretariat not located in the same
                        city. He made inquiry as to the ownership of the World Court Building <pb
                            facs="0746" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/> at The Hague, which we were unable
                        to answer specifically, but we could tell him that it had proved to be
                        adequate. The President expressed the opinion that the history of the Court
                        was good. Opinion toward it was favorable and he felt that continued
                        association of the court with The Hague would be desirable.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>We discussed about the economic and social functions of the organization
                        and the Soviet position that they should be entirely separate from the
                        international security organization stating that the Soviets laid great
                        emphasis upon the ineffective debates in the Assembly of the League and the
                        apparent confusion of purposes in that body. After discussion the President
                        expressed the conviction that the Assembly should have adequate functions
                        with respect to economic and social problems but he felt the actual
                        provisions written into the proposals might be in general terms.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>After leaving the President the group went with me immediately to my
                        office where I placed a call to Mr. Hull and I informed him in some detail
                        of the outcome of the conversation with the President. When we came to the
                        question of Brazil the Secretary indicated that he himself at several times,
                        had supported the idea of a permanent seat for Brazil. Mr. Hull reported
                        that the Senatorial group was coming in for a discussion with him tomorrow
                        and asked that we get together adequate material for him. I arranged to have
                        Pasvolsky prepare an appropriate memorandum and to hand it to Mr. Hull
                        personally in the evening, with such oral explanation as might be
                        advisable.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
