<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-06T08:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-06T08:30:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EAC/8–144</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">American Minutes of an Informal Meeting of the
                                European Advisory Commission</hi><note n="40" xml:id="d43fn40">Meeting held at Lancaster House on Thursday, July 6, 1944, at 3:30
                                p.m. These minutes were prepared by Brig. Gen. Vincent Meyer,
                                Ambassador Winant’s Chief Military Adviser, and were transmitted to
                                the Department as an enclosure to despatch 17219, August 1, 1944,
                                from London (not printed).</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>London</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-06T15:30:00+02:00">July 6, 1944, 3:30 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William</hi>—I reported to Mr. Eden yesterday
                            about the question of consultation with the other Allied Nations and in
                            particular I reported to him the confidence of my U.S. colleague that we
                            could finish discussion of the protocols and draft letter<note n="41" xml:id="d43fn41">A draft letter of invitation to these Governments
                                in connection with the surrender of Germany had been prepared by the
                                British delegation and circulated to the United States and Soviet
                                Representatives at the end of June. The draft letter, not printed,
                                was discussed and revised at an informal meeting of the European
                                Advisory Commission held on July 10. At an informal meeting of the
                                Commission on July 24 it was agreed to send the letter to the nine
                                Allied European Governments on July 25, simultaneously with the
                                sending of the Instrument of Surrender for Germany and the
                                accompanying report from the Commission to the Governments of the
                                United States, the United Kingdom, and the Soviet Union. For text of
                                the Surrender Instrument and the Report, see <ref target="#pg_256">pp. 256</ref> and <ref target="#pg_254">254</ref>,
                                respectively. For text of the letter to the European Allied
                                Governments, see <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> to the other
                            Allied European Nations by the end of next week. I also said Mr. Gousev
                            had expressed his willingness to examine the text of the proposed
                            communication to the Allied Governments. Mr. Eden replied that he was
                            glad to hear this and that he hopes we shall be able to make good and
                            finish off this stage of the discussion by the end of next week. <pb facs="0073" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/> He will make no declaration to
                            the Allied European Nations in the meantime. He hopes we will do as well
                            as we expect to do.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>