<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Extracts From the Personal Diary of the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Stettinius))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d449</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">449</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="449"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 60–D 224, Box 59: Stettinius Diary</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Extracts From the Personal Diary of the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Stettinius</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sixteenth Day, Thursday</hi>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-07">September 7,
                        1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Luncheon Meeting with Gromyko and Cadogan</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At lunch today I had another long and intimate conversation with Gromyko and
                    Cadogan. I suggested that I thought the time had arrived when we should begin to
                    formulate a definite agreement on the method of approving the Dumbarton document
                    and presenting it to the United Nations in calling together the United Nations
                    conference. I told them I was expressing my own personal views in an informal
                    way and that I hoped that when they took this up with their Governments they
                    were qualified in that way and mate it clear that I was not expressing official
                    views of my Government.</p>
                <p>They seemed interested and asked me to present my personal views in detail. I
                    said I thought we should take steps to have our four Governments approve the
                    document before we disbanded Dumbarton Oaks and that it should be agreed that at
                    the conclusion of these talks the document would be presented to the other
                    United Nations. I added that I hoped this could be done by the end of September
                    and that simultaneously with the presentation, an invitation to the United
                    Nations conference could be extended to the other countries for a date some time
                    before November 1, probably around October 25. I said <pb facs="0793" n="779"
                        xml:id="pg_779"/> I thought the invitations should make clear that we
                    propose that the Dumbarton document should be used as the basis of discussion at
                    the full dress conference. I further suggested that the conference should be
                    held at some suitable convenient place in the central part of the United States.
                    (I did not mention French Lick or any other specific place to them.) This last
                    suggestion as to location brought forth a considerable amount of good-natured
                    repartee back and forth. For instance, Cadogan said “Well, the climate in
                    England in October is the best of all”. He added that we had started in Moscow,
                    continued in Washington and should end up in London. Gromyko interjected the
                    statement that the climate in Moscow in October was much better than it was in
                    London in that month. I explained the matter further in general terms and I
                    think they understood the political advantage of having the meeting in the
                    interior of the United States at the time suggested. Gromyko specifically
                    indicated that he thought his Government would be impressed with that feature. I
                    again made clear that I was speaking personally and not in the names of Mr. Hull
                    or the President.</p>
                <p>They then asked me a number of questions. Cadogan asked about the size of the
                    delegation I had in mind. I said I thought that we would require a delegation of
                    from ten to twelve people in order to meet our special requirements. He said
                    that they might have three delegates plus experts but that he could understand
                    why we would need a larger group. Cadogan agreed that when we finished our work
                    it would be practically impossible to hold the document from the other United
                    Nations and from the public for long but indicated that if it were made public
                    by the end of September it would undoubtedly cause a debate in Parliament at
                    that time even though it was not then being submitted to Parliament for official
                    ratification. He was not apprehensive that this would prejudice approval but
                    thought we should know we would be running that risk. In answer to his inquiry I
                    said this would not concern us. Gromyko inquired at what level the conference
                    would be held and I said I assumed it would be at the level of Foreign Ministers
                    and that Mr. Hull would be the chairman of our delegation. Cadogan added that he
                    was certain Eden would wish to come. Cadogan estimated that such a conference
                    would consume approximately three weeks. Gromyko expressed the opinion that this
                    schedule would allow too short a time for the other United Nations to study the
                    question but Cadogan disagreed. Gromyko did not express an opinion as to whether
                    Molotov would be prepared to attend a meeting of this type and I did not ask
                    him.</p>
                <p>We then had a long discussion on the general progress of the Conversations viewed
                    in the light of this morning’s Joint Steering Committee meeting. Gromyko seemed
                    discouraged. He told me privately <pb facs="0794" n="780" xml:id="pg_780"/> that
                    he was ready to act on all matters. He put it this way, “I am 99% sure I could
                    clean up everything except the voting procedure and this is a serious matter
                    with us”. Cadogan and I both stressed to him that a document with this matter
                    unsettled would be weak and Cadogan added that he thought in the event it was
                    unsettled Eden would insist on the inclusion of a footnote making the British
                    position on the question dear. This disturbed Gromyko. I explained to him that
                    we would have trouble ourselves on this matter with the Latin American
                    countries. After some little talk, Gromyko seemingly came around to the position
                    that it was necessary to settle the voting question at this time and not refer
                    it to a general United Nations conference.</p>
                <p>I then asked whether he felt there was a possibility of agreement at this meeting
                    on the economic and social council and he replied that he felt it should be
                    settled at Dumbarton.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Arranging for Gromyko’s Bedroom Conference with the
                        President</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After reaching my apartment late in the afternoon, I continued to mull over the
                    present situation and came more and more to the conclusion that the voting
                    question was the crux of the problem and that we had now reached the stage where
                    we should call out our biggest and last remaining gun. It seems obvious to me
                    that the success or failure of the conference depends upon this one point. I
                    then telephoned Mr. Hull and after reporting to him in detail on the
                    developments of the day, told him I had reached the conclusion that bold action
                    was now in order on the major open point. I reviewed various possibilities of
                    bring[ing] this to a climax, such as Hull phoning Molotov, the President sending
                    a wire to Stalin, our requesting Harriman to see Molotov, or the President
                    sending for Gromyko for a private talk. Mr. Hull immediately responded that he
                    felt the most effective step would be to have the President see Gromyko, but
                    warned that in presenting the matter to Gromyko, I should do it in a rather
                    personal way, asking if he would be willing to discuss the matter with the
                    President and not put it on the basis of the President sending for him. (My
                    later talk with Gromyko carried out the Secretary’s instructions to the last
                    letter. I obtained Gromyko’s full concurrence and his willingness to talk to the
                    President.)</p>
                <p>I then explained the whole plan to Dunn who gave it his full approval and
                    encouraged me to carry it out promptly. I then called Harry Hopkins but could
                    not reach him. He called me back in about ten minutes. I outlined to him the
                    developments of the day and told him the plan I had in mind. He thought that in
                    addition to the President talking to Gromyko that he should also send a cable to
                        <pb facs="0795" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> Stalin. I asked Hopkins if he
                    could arrange the meeting at the White House and he said he would immediately go
                    to the President’s office and tell him that there was a matter of great urgency
                    which I wished to talk to him about on the phone. The President called me in
                    about five minutes. We had a long conversation. I reported to him in detail on
                    developments at the Joint Steering Committee meeting. I told him I was convinced
                    that we could settle the remaining open items, such as the economic and social
                    council question, and the international air force question, except that the
                    Soviets were being stubborn and apparently were not willing to yield on any of
                    these other points until the voting procedure issue was settled. I said that in
                    my opinion once this matter was disposed of, I was confident that we could wind
                    up everything else with flying colors in a few hours time. I told him I thought
                    the time had arrived to use our big gun on this question and ran over with him
                    the several alternatives which I had discussed with Mr. Hull. After considerable
                    discussion, he said, “Why not call in Gromyko?”, and then added that he had a
                    press conference at 10:30 in the morning but could see him at noon. I told him
                    that it was important that it be done between 5 o’clock this afternoon and 10
                    o’clock in the morning. The President said that he could not do it tonight but
                    if Gromyko would not be offended, he would be glad to receive him in his bedroom
                    tomorrow morning. I said I thought the Ambassador would be immensely impressed.
                    He then asked me to bring him in at 9:30 in the morning. I asked him if he felt
                    it would be best for me to be present. We left open the question of the
                    President’s sending a wire to Stalin.</p>
                <p>I then telephoned Gromyko immediately on the White House wire and told him I had
                    just finished reporting to the President on the day’s developments at Dumbarton,
                    and that the President had expressed a desire to talk with him on the question
                    of voting, which he felt was of over-riding importance. I then asked him whether
                    he would be willing to call on the President in order that he might have an
                    opportunity of receiving directly from the President his views on this question.
                    Gromyko immediately replied that he would, of course, be delighted, that he
                    would be happy to see the President, and that he knew he was a busy man and he
                    hated to take his time. After I told him that it would take only a few minutes
                    he said that he would be very pleased to meet me at 9:30 in the morning for his
                    meeting in the President’s bedroom.</p>
                <p>I then called Mr. Hull and told him of the arrangements which I had worked out.
                    Mr. Hull inquired, and I assured him that I had made it clear to Gromyko that we
                    did not want him to do this unless he were willing. I told Mr. Hull that in
                    addition to this meeting I thought the President should also send Marshal Stalin
                    a wire. He <pb facs="0796" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"/> agreed in principle. I then
                    called Harry Hopkins and thanked him for arranging so promptly for the President
                    to call me. I told him it had worked out very well and that I was bringing the
                    Ambassador to see the President in his bedroom at 9:30 in the morning. Hopkins
                    emphasized again the importance which he attached to sending a wire to Stalin,
                    in addition, and suggested that I should have a draft of a wire in my pocket to
                    show the President after he had finished talking to Gromyko. He also suggested
                    that it would be wise for me to remind the President to tell Gromyko that he was
                    planning to cable Stalin on the question. I then phoned Chip Bohlen and after
                    telling him of the arrangements, asked him to prepare the appropriate wire to
                    Stalin for me to have ready in the morning. Bohlen thought the entire plan was
                    excellent. I then told Dunn of all of these developments and asked him to tell
                    Pasvolsky.</p>
                <p>I then called Sir Alexander and explained the whole plan to him and told him that
                    I thought it would be best for him not to tell anyone except Lord Halifax until
                    we could determine how it worked out. Sir Alexander told me that he was wiring
                    London suggesting that their Ambassador in Moscow be instructed that the real
                    significance of the voting procedure question is that Gromyko does not
                    understand the issue and that he probably has not presented the facts to Moscow
                    accurately, although Sir Alexander was not entirely clear apparently that Clark
                    Kerr was being instructed to call at the Soviet Foreign Office and attempt to
                    give them an accurate explanation of the voting issue.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
