<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="534" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d534">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.42/23</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stettinius</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-02-14">February 14, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>On February 9, 1944<note n="3" xml:id="d534fn3">Memorandum by President
                            Roosevelt, not printed.</note> you transmitted to me and requested my
                        recommendation on the attached memorandum dated January 22, 1944,<note n="4" xml:id="d534fn4">Not printed.</note> addressed to you by the Secretary
                        of the Smithsonian Institution, the Archivist of the United States and the
                        Librarian of Congress suggesting that this Government, in conjunction with
                        the principal Allied governments, make provision for the establishment of an
                        international commission to take constructive and effective measures for the
                        intellectual rehabilitation of Europe.</p>
                    <p>This Department’s Division of Science, Education and Art (formerly the
                        Division of Cultural Relations) has been and is giving this important
                        subject active attention. As the memorandum in question recognizes, an
                        adequate program in this field will require the active cooperative
                        participation of various governmental and private agencies in this country
                        and the establishment of effective international facilities for
                        inter-governmental cooperation.</p>
                    <p>To these ends we propose to take the following steps in the immediate future: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Appoint an outstanding leader from the field of intellectual and
                                educational organizations as Chief of the Department’s Division of
                                Science, Education and Art. The plan is to appoint a man who
                                ordinarily could not be attracted to this position, requesting him
                                to undertake the job as a temporary public service for the purpose
                                of reappraising our cultural relations program and realigning it for
                                most effective operations in the light of future conditions and
                                needs. This man would also be expected to select and groom a highly
                                qualified successor to take over the permanent position in the
                                Department. Dr. Waldo Leland, Director of the American Council of
                                Learned Societies, appears to be the best qualified man who might be
                                available for this assignment at this time.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Make a public statement of the Department’s and this Government’s
                                general policies in respect to these matters in order that there may
                                be a clear policy basis on which private and governmental agencies
                                here may develop cooperative programs and the inter-governmental
                                facilities may be created. Attached hereto is a proposed statement
                                which, with any changes you may care to suggest, will be issued by
                                the Department.<note n="5" xml:id="d534fn5">For text of statement
                                    issued by the Department on March 31, 1944, see Department of
                                    State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, April 1, 1944, p.
                                    299.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Submit proposals to the British Government and the other
                                governments having members or observers in the existing Conference
                                of Allied Ministers of Education in London for the transformation of
                                the present conference into an United Nations Advisory Commission
                                    <pb facs="0981" n="967" xml:id="pg_967"/> for Educational and
                                Cultural Reconstruction. To date we have not participated in the
                                existing Conference, but have sent observers. We propose to suggest
                                to these governments that the Commission be organized in London not
                                later than this April as a temporary body with investigatory and
                                advisory powers, each member having one vote, with a program to
                                study and formulate recommendations for action on the following
                                immediate and critical problems: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>aiding in the material rebuilding of national educational
                                        systems.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>aiding in the reestablishment of technical and university
                                        education, especially for the training of educational and
                                        other professional personnel by furnishing books,
                                        periodicals, scientific apparatus, etc.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>aiding, within the scope of its functions, in recovering
                                        objects and materials looted by Axis countries from historic
                                        monuments, art galleries, archives, and libraries, and aid
                                        in restoring them to their rightful owners.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>If these three proposed steps have your approval, we shall go forward on
                        these lines immediately.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi> R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius,
                                Jr.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>