<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="61" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EAC/9–1944</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Delegation of the French
                                    Committee of National Liberation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="98" xml:id="d61fn98">Handed to the Secretary of State on
                                September 19, 1944. The Department informed Ambassador Winant of
                                this communication in its telegram 8037 to London, October 2, 1944,
                                7 p.m., and added: “It is suggested that you endeavor through your
                                colleagues on the Commission to ascertain the views of their
                                Governments on the French request. If they ask for your views, you
                                may say that final decision has not been reached but that matter is
                                receiving sympathetic consideration.” (740.00119 E.A.C.
                                9–1944)</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-19">September 19, 1944</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Following the note addressed on July 25<note n="99" xml:id="d61fn99">See
                                    <ref target="#pg_63">p. 63</ref>.</note> by the President of the
                            European Advisory Commission to the French Chargé d’Affaires in London,
                            the Provisional Government of the French Republic has already had the
                            opportunity to emphasize the vital interest it takes in the discussions
                            which are being held at present between the American, British, and
                            Soviet Governments concerning the armistice conditions with Germany and,
                            more generally, the essential importance that France attaches to all
                            questions pertaining to the German problem.</p>
                        <p>The Provisional Government of the French Republic has now settled in its
                            normal seat in the French capital, wherefrom the Allied armies have
                            chased the enemy with the participation of the French people. Until free
                            elections become possible, it is backed by the unanimous and
                            enthusiastic adhesion of the liberated population.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, the Provisional Government has the duty to call the attention
                            of the Governments of Washington, London, and Moscow to a question which
                            requires an immediate solution in view of the present accelerated pace
                            of military operations. While the problem of the German capitulation is
                            one of vital importance to France, the other questions which will arise
                            from the collapse of the Reich cannot leave her unconcerned,
                            particularly: the restoration of the countries invaded by Germany, the
                            eventual setting of new frontiers, and, generally speaking, the
                            reestablishment of fruitful and peaceful relations between the states of
                            continental Europe—all questions which <pb facs="0102" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/> will have to be dealt with by the European Advisory
                            Commission during the following weeks.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, the Provisional Government of the French Republic has the
                            honor to request the American, British, and Soviet Governments to be
                            admitted to sit on the Commission so as to allow France to take her part
                            in the task of the reconstruction and reorganization of Europe. It
                            trusts that this request will meet the views of those Governments and
                            will be pleased to send a representative to the Commission as soon as it
                            receives an invitation to do so.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>