<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-17T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-17T03:00:00-05:00" n="628" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d628">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00115 European War 1939/10084:
                        Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                            the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Bern</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-17T09:00:00+01:00">June 17,
                                1944—9 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received 8:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>3871. Your 1181, April 7; 1221, April 10; 1846, May 27; and 1921, June
                            5;<note n="81" xml:id="d628fn81">Telegram 1921 not printed.</note> my
                        2297, April 13; and your 1400, April 22.<note n="82" xml:id="d628fn82">Telegram 1400 not printed.</note> Translation material part Foreign
                        Office <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> June 13 follows.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Since outbreak war passports of Latin American countries (Honduras,
                            Costa Rica, Nicaragua, Guatemala, Ecuador, El Salvador, Venezuela,
                            Haiti, Paraguay) have circulated among Jews residing in German occupied
                            territories and especially Poland. These passports were issued by
                            Consulates of various countries mentioned in Portugal, Sweden,
                            Switzerland, New York, Japan and perhaps Poland. When such passports of
                            countries whose interests Switzerland protects in Germany expired and
                            when Swiss Legation Berlin was asked by bearers to renew them
                            instructions were requested of interested Governments. In general latter
                            refused authorize extension those passports which they did not
                            recognize. German authorities were not informed of this fact but Swiss
                            Legation Berlin was henceforth deprived of possibility according
                            protection of these people.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>A rather large number of these passports are Paraguayan. Paraguay
                            being represented in Germany by Spain it seems that Spanish Embassy
                            Berlin received from Paraguayan Government a list of limited number of
                            persons who alone should benefit from Spain’s protection. Federal
                            Political Department does not know whether Spanish Government
                            subsequently received instructions rectifying this situation in
                            conformity with statement of Paraguayan Government <pb facs="1086" n="1072" xml:id="pg_1072"/> mentioned second paragraph American
                            Legation’s memorandum April 10 (your 1181).</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>A certain number of bearers Latin American passports generally Eastern
                            European origin secured admission to American civilian internment camps
                            which are under control Ministry Foreign Affairs Berlin such camps being
                            administered by analogy in accordance with POW Convention. These persons
                            thus virtually became candidates for an exchange of civilians between
                            Germany and American countries. On other hand those who stayed in Poland
                            remained under regulations governing other eastern Jews. Recently a
                            census was taken of internees at Vittel and Compiegne and a group of
                            Jews were removed from these, camps. This seems to have involved in
                            certain cases bearers of Latin American passports whose validity was
                            questioned.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>At time contents American Legation’s April 14 notice (your 1221) was
                            delivered German Government, German police had already removed from
                            Vittel and Compiegne Jews who had not been able establish American
                            nationality. From verbal statements made to Swiss Legation Berlin by
                            official of German Foreign Office it appeared latter seemed glad of
                            opportunity while there was still time to support United States
                            recognition of any one claiming ties with a Latin American country as
                            exchangeable. German Foreign Office would be ready consider in future as
                            eligible exchange all Jews bearing Latin American identity documents
                            interned in these camps as well as those elsewhere known to German
                            Foreign Office against Germans in United States who desire return to
                            Germany.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>It would therefore seem logical to admit that desiring to establish as
                            large a basis as possible for foreseen exchanges German Foreign Office
                            will do all possible to exempt from deportation Jews bearing Latin
                            American passports provided these Jews will be effectively covered in an
                            exchange agreement.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>According Swiss Legation Berlin there are still said to be in Poland
                            bearers of Latin American passports who until now have neither been
                            interned nor considered for exchange. It seems that best protection they
                            could be given would be for interested Governments officially to
                            recognize all Latin American passports held by Jews in Germany or German
                            occupied territories and so to declare formally through protecting
                            power. Of countries whose interests Switzerland protects in Germany
                            until [<hi rend="italic">only</hi>] Venezuela and El Salvador have
                            recently made such declarations through intermediary of Federal
                            Political Department. Honduras, Costa Rica, Ecuador, Guatemala and
                                Nicaragua<note n="83" xml:id="d628fn83">Telegram 2316 of July 6,
                                1944, midnight, transmitted to Bern a paraphrased portion of a
                                Nicaraguan communication of April 22 to the Swiss Foreign Office
                                requesting the Swiss to ask the German Government for application to
                                all internees in concentration camps who were bearers of Nicaraguan
                                passports of international conventions covering prisoners of war
                                (740.00115 E.W. 39/10084).</note> have not as yet individually
                            confirmed attitude which should result from steps taken by Department of
                            State with various Latin American countries mentioned second paragraph
                            American Legation’s memorandum April 10.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Without implying any guarantee foregoing permits hope that German
                            Foreign Office concurs with views of State Department. <pb facs="1087" n="1073" xml:id="pg_1073"/> Concrete proposal leading to exchange of
                            lists contained in recent communication to German Government and
                            submitted by American Legation to Federal Political Department May 31
                            (Department’s 1846, May 27) should constitute a basis for practical
                            discussion in this matter.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Federal Political Department must, however, submit following to
                            attention Legation: arrangements under consideration will be effective
                            only to extent that number of persons holding passports and other
                            identity documents issued in names of Latin American Republics
                            corresponds to that of German citizens whose repatriation may be
                            considered. It has come, however, to attention of Federal Political
                            Department that recently again documents of this type are said to have
                            been issued by hundreds.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>Information relative to success of steps undertaken with Spanish
                            Government referred to in paragraph 2 of above note by American Embassy
                            Madrid would be appreciated.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Finally essentially precarious status which one hopes to assure Jewish
                            bearers of Latin American passports could be compromised by any
                            publicity whatsoever given to action now being taken.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Harrison</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>