<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Switzerland ( (Harrison))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d671</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">671</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-22T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-22T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-22T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-22T19:00:00-05:00" n="671"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d671">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/8–2244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-22T20:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 22, 1944—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2888. Refer Department’s 2737 August 9 WRB 112.<note n="63" xml:id="d671fn63">Not
                        printed.</note> For Harrison and McClelland. Communication has been received
                    from IGC substantiating reports of deportations of holders of Latin American
                    documents from civilian internment camps subsequent to May 11.<note n="64"
                        xml:id="d671fn64">According to telegram 5109 of August 8 from Bern, a sharp
                        protest against these actions was lodged through the Swiss Government, but
                        the Germans denied the right of the Swiss to intervene for the protection of
                        persons who were allegedly not nationals of the countries under Swiss
                        protection (840.48 Refugees/8–844).</note> lists of names and full details
                    have been supplied. Such deportations took place about May 16 and July 18 from
                    Vittel. Internees at Vittel were informed erroneously by Camp Commandant that
                    transport was to be sent to Bergen-Belsen. They were also advised by the
                    Commandant that neither Latin American documents nor Palestine certificates
                    would have validity in the eyes of the German authorities unless an exchange
                    actually took place to South America or to Palestine.</p>
                <p>Please request Swiss Government to inform German Foreign Office that if facts are
                    substantially as reported to it this Government protests against this action as
                    a violation of the assurances previously given by Germany to Switzerland,
                    reported in your 4223 of July 3. Please also request Swiss Government to press
                    for the immediate return of all deportees to civilian internment camps and to
                    secure renewed assurances that such removals from civilian internment camps will
                    not be repeated. It is requested moreover, that the German authorities be
                    advised that failure to return those removed from Vittel subsequent to May 11 to
                    civilian internment camps where refugees are held for exchange will not only be
                    considered as a violation of assurances previously given but further that all
                    interested <pb facs="1146" n="1132" xml:id="pg_1132"/> governments will have no
                    alternative but to consider that those deported, claimants to the protection of
                    these governments, have been disposed of contrary to the rules of humanity and
                    international practice. Further in this connection use may be made of the
                    argument contained in paragraph 3 of Department’s 2490 of July 21.</p>
                <p>In view of the fact that the German assurances that there would be no further
                    removals of Latin American document holders from civilian internment camps after
                    May 11 were given to the Swiss Government, it is not only hoped that the Swiss
                    Government will find it possible to transmit the above protest but that it may
                    also support it in its own name.</p>
                <p>This is WRB Bern cable 127.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
