<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Switzerland ( (Harrison))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-23T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-23T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVMjpePTbXrmHOO" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-23T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-23T21:00:00-05:00" n="674"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/8–544: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-23T22:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 23, 1944—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2900. The following for McClelland is WRB 129 and refers to your 4604 of July 19
                    and 5040 of August 5.</p>
                <p>1. Please express to the Foreign Office the appreciation of this Government for
                    the information contained in your 4604 and 5040, in addition to taking action
                    requested in Department’s 2715 of August 7.<note n="67" xml:id="d674fn67">Not
                        printed; Minister Harrison was instructed to transmit to Intercross on
                        August 11 the text of the reply sent to him in Department’s telegram 2657 of
                        August 2, midnight, <ref target="#pg_1114">p. 1114</ref> (840.48
                        Refugees/6–1344).</note> You may make available to appropriate officials of
                    the Foreign Office the text of the reply given on August 11 by this Government
                    to Intercross in accordance with Department’s 2657 of August 2 and 2715 of
                    August 7, in order that the Swiss Government may be fully informed of the
                    attitude of this Government.</p>
                <p>Although this Government has noted the communication reported in your 5040, it
                    does not accept the reasoning contained therein and reserves the right to return
                    at a later date to the purported facts <pb facs="1148" n="1134" xml:id="pg_1134"
                    /> related therein. Please request the Swiss Foreign Office so to inform the
                    Hungarian authorities. They should be informed further that the Hungarian
                    Government’s assurances are too limited in character to be satisfactory. The
                    United States Government therefore reiterates its public warning that there will
                    be brought to justice all those who share the responsibility for the persecution
                    of Jews and other minorities. They should also be informed that the deportation
                    of any category of Jews is included in the foregoing and that there must be
                    extended to all categories of Jews as a minimum permission freely to emigrate
                    and Red Cross supervision of treatment and living conditions.</p>
                <p>2. Communications and reports regarding Hungarian Government’s offer relating to
                    treatment of Jews show wide discrepancies. Position this Government based for
                    obvious reasons on version sent through Swiss Foreign Office and contained in
                    your 4604. It proposes to maintain this position, but nevertheless is anxious to
                    ascertain precise nature of offer and attitude of Hungarians. It is requested,
                    therefore, that without departing from above stated position of this Government,
                    you make discreet and informal inquiries concerning following principal
                    uncertainties from such sources as are available to you.</p>
                <p>Is there definite stoppage deportations of all categories? If suspended only, for
                    what categories and for how long?</p>
                <p>Is it possible to expect continuance of stoppage of deportations and other forms
                    of actual danger to life even in the absence of actual sizeable emigration of
                    Jews from Hungary during hostilities? If so, to what extent?</p>
                <p>To what extent are Jews over ten years of age permitted to emigrate to countries
                    other than Palestine?</p>
                <p>Might emigration be conducted so as to prevent breakup of families? (Related to
                    question of separation from parents of children under ten.)</p>
                <p>Will Jews in Hungary be permitted and, in fact and aside from Intercross action,
                    enabled to obtain food and other necessities through ordinary commercial
                    channels? If so, to what exent?</p>
                <p>In view of Hungarian internal situation to what extent can Hungarian promises be
                    counted on as being made effective and continuing for the duration?</p>
                <p>Answers to any of the above questions should be submitted as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>It appears here, in light of current political and military situation, that main
                    emphasis should now be placed on inducing appropriate Hungarian circles to
                    maintain and strengthen the recently reported <pb facs="1149" n="1135"
                        xml:id="pg_1135"/> relaxation of Jewish regime in Hungary and to apply such
                    relaxations to all categories of Jews therein. Assistance in clandestine escapes
                    of groups and individuals seems less important now than prevention of
                    deportations and assurance of tolerable living conditions for all Jews in
                    Hungary. Kindly report any information and developments thereon.</p>
                <p>The broad program envisaged above and in Department’s 2657 might be jeopardized
                    by narrow scope of approach suggested by 230<note n="68" xml:id="d674fn68"
                        >Telegram 6040, July 29, 5 p.m., from London, sent to Bern as No. 230, <ref
                            target="#pg_1108">p. 1108</ref>.</note> from London Embassy. It is not
                    thought advisable therefore that you limit your <hi rend="italic">démarches</hi>
                    to items covered in London’s 230, namely children under ten and the supply
                    problem. Naturally however you are authorized to give the assurance, in line
                    with 230 from London, concerning availability of supplies for Hungarian refugees
                    through blockade.</p>
                <p>Repeated to London.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
