<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-07T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-07T17:00:00-05:00" n="686" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d686">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/9–744: Circular
                        telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>)<note n="93" xml:id="d686fn93">Repeated
                            on the same date to Stockholm, Lisbon, Caserta, London, and Bern.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-07T18:00:00-04:00">September 7,
                                1944—6 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The following WRB cable no. 106 is for Hirschmann. Several requests have
                        already been received by the War Refugee Board for financial assistance in
                        the relief of refugees in areas liberated by the Allied military forces.</p>
                    <p>For your information and guidance War Refugee Board activities are to be
                        strictly limited to the rescue and relief of the victims of enemy oppression
                        who are in imminent danger of death, that is, who are still in
                        enemy-occupied territory. Refugee problems in liberated areas are not
                        regarded as being within the Board’s functions. Accordingly, if you receive
                        requests limited to the relief and assistance of refugees in areas liberated
                        from the Germans, you should refer such <pb facs="1163" n="1149" xml:id="pg_1149"/> problems to UNRRA, the appropriate military
                        authorities, the Intergovernmental Committee on Refugees, private refugee
                        organizations, or other national or international groups which are
                        authorized to deal with matters of this nature.</p>
                    <p>The foregoing shall not be construed to limit the activities of the Board
                        dealing with arrangements for the removal of refugees in liberated areas
                        whose presence serves to discourage or prevent the rescue of additional
                        refugees from enemy-occupied areas.</p>
                    <p>This message has been repeated to the other WRB Special Representatives
                        abroad.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>