<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-30T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-30T02:00:00-05:00" n="744" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d744">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">703.5451/9–3044: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Acting American Representative to the French Committee
                            of National Liberation at Paris</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="65" xml:id="d744fn65">A Mission at Paris was reestablished on
                            September 8, and Jefferson Caffery was assigned as U. S. representative
                            to the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> French Authority on September 21,
                            1944.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-30T09:00:00+02:00">September 30,
                                1944—9 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received October 1—8:37 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>121. The questions raised in Department’s 37, September 25, 9 p.m. are
                        answered to a large extent by my 96, September 27, 4 p.m.,<note n="66" xml:id="d744fn66">Neither printed; in telegram 37 to London, for Selden
                            Chapin (who was assigned as Counselor of Mission at Paris on September
                            1), request was made for information regarding the Mission’s assumption
                            of functions with respect to United States nationals and their property
                            (whereabouts, welfare, financial assistance, messages and funds)
                            (703.5451/9–2544). In telegram 96, September 27, from Paris, Mr. Chapin
                            reported that, because of his hopelessly inadequate staff, it was
                            impossible to consider taking over from the Swiss the representation of
                            American interests for the time being (124.51/9–2744).</note> which
                        crossed the Department’s telegram.</p>
                    <pb facs="1222" n="1208" xml:id="pg_1208"/>
                    <p>As the Department is aware we are already acting on all whereabouts, welfare
                        and property inquiries referred to the Mission by the Department in addition
                        to a limited number of inquiries originating here. We are not prepared,
                        however, to handle any financial matters for American citizens or others
                        until our disbursing section is fully installed.</p>
                    <p>The Swiss continue to handle all financial matters and ordinary welfare and
                        protection cases as in the past and it will not be feasible to take over any
                        of these functions until as pointed out in my telegram referred to we are
                        adequately staffed. For the time being our activities must be limited to the
                        Paris area due to existing difficulties of transportation and telegraphic
                        and postal communication. As Consulates are opened in other parts of the
                        country they can presumably assume such functions although in cases of
                        extreme urgency it might be possible even before that time for this Mission
                        to send a representative beyond the Paris area or to elicit the cooperation
                        of the military authorities although neither course is recommended.</p>
                    <p>The Department may wish to announce publicly at this time<note n="67" xml:id="d744fn67">See Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 8, 1944, p. 391.</note> that the Mission is
                        prepared to receive welfare and whereabouts inquiries emphasizing in the
                        announcement that a delay may be anticipated due to shortage of personnel
                        presently available to the Mission.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chapin</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>