<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary in Charge of the Mission at Algiers ( (Lawton) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d779</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">779</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-11T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-11T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-11T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-11T10:00:00-05:00" n="779"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d779">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751R.62114/7–1144: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary in Charge of the Mission at Algiers</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lawton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-11T17:00:00+02:00"
                            >July 11, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 11:22 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2355. Your telegram No. 2161, July 10, 8 p.m. Owing to engagements Massigli, I
                    saw his principal assistant Chauvel this afternoon <pb facs="1253" n="1239"
                        xml:id="pg_1239"/> and made representations as instructed leaving <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> with him. Chauvel referred to Duff Cooper’s
                    note described in my telegram No. 2287, July 6, 8 p.m., and said answer which
                    Massigli had made thereto set forth position of FCNL and could therefore be
                    considered reply to our representations. That reply was received last night by
                    Duff Cooper who has furnished me copy. Following is summary thereof:</p>
                <p>Nothing could be further from intention of French military or civil authorities
                    than violation of agreement placing FFI under SHAEF strategic command which is
                    considered most useful safeguard against arbitrary action of German Command;
                    French Command gave no orders in case in question; then follows recital
                    extremely brutal measures taken by German Command against activity of FFI in
                    executing hostages of both sexes and all ages as well as burning villages;
                    following these executions initiative was taken by local FFI commander to shoot
                    6 German prisoners which resulted in French authorities finding themselves in
                    anomalous position of either getting [<hi rend="italic">giving</hi>] their
                    approval to these acts or of repudiating Frenchmen engaged in merciless struggle
                    against the enemy. Note continues that contrary to fears expressed reprisals
                    taken and publicity given to it has not provoked an extension of German
                    atrocities; then there is quoted three instances where Germans have subsequently
                    moderated their threatened harsh treatment of French hostages. In conclusion
                    note states French Committee fully aware of dangers which might result from such
                    action on part of FFI and expresses earnest desire to find general formula which
                    could furnish appropriate guarantee. In this spirit, French Committee attaches
                    great importance to Anglo-American conversations which have in view publication
                    of common declaration sustaining French position and contributing to protection
                    of the lives of FFI. Annex attached to note contains list of brutalities
                    committed against French civilian population by Germans between May 21 and July
                    9.</p>
                <p>In discussing above communication, Chauvel emphasized great importance of an
                    agreement between Washington, London and Algiers for united policy and issuance
                    of public statement thereon. He expressed hope that State Department would take
                    immediate steps to further that end.</p>
                <p>Duff Cooper tells me that Massigli assured him in conversation that Committee
                    were unanimously opposed to policy of reprisals; that everything possible would
                    be done to discourage any repetition of the incident in question; that he felt
                    confident it was not likely to happen again.</p>
                <pb facs="1254" n="1240" xml:id="pg_1240"/>
                <p>Local Canadian representative under instructions from Ottawa has also made
                    representations to French authorities supporting British note.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lawton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
