<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-10-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-10-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" subject="war-criminals">War criminals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-10-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-10-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="881"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d881">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 EW/10–344</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Ref: 152/153/44</p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has received a
                    formal letter from the Chairman of the United Nations War Crimes Commission
                    stating that the work of the Commission in dealing with war crimes committed by
                    Italians is hampered by the lack of information from Italian sources. The
                    Chairman asks whether the Italian Government can be obliged to afford access to
                    military archives, records and information catalogue, and whether the Commission
                    may be informed as to the quarter to which those who are responsible for the
                    preparation of charges against war criminals should address themselves in order
                    to obtain the information they want.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In Mr. Eden’s view, the Allied Commission in Italy would seem to be the
                        appropriate body to assist the War Crimes Commission in this matter. He
                        thinks that if the War Crimes Commission’s requirements in particular cases
                        were communicated to the Allied Commission either through the Combined
                        Chiefs of Staff and Supreme Allied Commander Mediterranean, or, since the
                        War Crimes Commission is located in London, through His Majesty’s Government
                        and the British Resident Minister Central Mediterranean (Mr. Macmillan), the
                        Allied Commission could no doubt ensure the Italian Government’s compliance
                        with the War Crimes Commission’s requirements.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Mr. Eden is seeking the views of Mr. Macmillan and of Sir Noel
                            Charles<note n="1" xml:id="d881fn1">British Representative on the
                            Advisory Council for Italy.</note> on the above point and, subject to
                        their views, considers <pb facs="1391" n="1377" xml:id="pg_1377"/> that it
                        would be desirable for this matter to be raised in the Advisory Council for
                        Italy simultaneously with the question of the War Crimes Commission’s
                        competence for dealing with German crimes against Italians.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Mr. Eden suggests that, if the United States Government agree, appropriate
                        instructions might be sent to the United States representative on the
                        Advisory Council.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-10-03">October 3,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
