<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Sweden ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d919</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">919</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-30T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-30T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" subject="war-criminals">War criminals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-30T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="919"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d919">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 EW/8–3044: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-30T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 30, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 31—1:57 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3389. This afternoon I saw Foreign Minister Gunther at my request to discuss with
                    him subject matter of Department’s 1688, August 23, 7 p.m.<note n="15"
                        xml:id="d919fn15">See footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_1410">p.
                        1410</ref>.</note> Mr. Boheman<note n="16" xml:id="d919fn16">B. C. Boheman,
                        Secretary General, Swedish Foreign Office.</note> was also present and I
                    went into the matter thoroughly.</p>
                <p>Obvious deduction from Mr. Gunther’s immediate reaction is that this question is
                    one which has already received careful study by the Foreign Office and the
                    Swedish Government. Mr. Gunther stated that this question had been on agenda for
                    discussion at Cabinet meeting last Friday but that owing to pressure of other
                    business it had not been reached. He said that it would be taken up at the
                    meeting this Friday and that he personally believed that the Government’s
                    decision would be to issue a declaration that Sweden would not give asylum to
                    war criminals. I found no disposition on the part either of the Foreign Minister
                    or Mr. Boheman to argue the case or any indication that they were not in entire
                    agreement with our views. Mr. Gunther pointed out, however, that Sweden will be
                    presented, particularly in the case of persons coming from Norway, with very
                    real difficulties as hundreds of Norwegians are now able to enter Sweden
                    unobserved, it being impossible to patrol so extensive a frontier. It must be
                    taken for granted that war criminals will likewise take advantage of the same
                    opportunities. It is possible that such an individual might be in Sweden several
                    weeks before he is discovered. Boheman also said that it is probable that some
                    criminal refugees from Germany may <pb facs="1429" n="1415" xml:id="pg_1415"/>
                    be landed in this country by plane or paraehute unknown to the authorities. In
                    the informal discussion which followed I admitted that it would be impossible to
                    prevent all cases of that kind but that I hoped the Swedish Government would not
                    then in any case accept such a situation as a <hi rend="italic">fait
                        accompli</hi> but would take immediate steps to detain the person and said
                    in this connection that the Allies would undoubtedly expect that any such
                    individuals be delivered if required. Such cases would in all probability be
                    criminals of a minor character and not the outstanding Axis leaders or their
                    principal vassals. Of this latter category Mr. Gunther left no doubt in my mind
                    that the Swedish Government will not give them asylum. He is also aware that the
                    problem may arise at any moment and that the policy is therefore one for urgent
                    determination. Mr. Gunther himself said that public opinion in this country not
                    to speak of the Government is entirely hostile to any reception of war criminals
                    and he added that no prominent Axis or quisling who would fall into this
                    category could expect to remain alive for a day if he came to Sweden and
                    attempted to move around in the normal way. Although Mr. Gunther said that he
                    was speaking as I was informally and could not make any official statement until
                    after the Government had made its decision, his reaction and the statements he
                    made were so entirely satisfactory that I have no reasonable doubt that he was
                    expressing a view which has already been determined upon in the Government. I
                    thanked him and said that I was confident that this informal response would be
                    appreciated by my Government. He promised to send for me as soon as the
                    Government has determined its official action. (See my 3312, August 26, 1
                        p.m.).<note n="17" xml:id="d919fn17">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
