<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1904-08-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1904-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="312" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-08-02"><hi rend="italic">August 2,
                                1904</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1420.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm my cable of
                            June 3, 1904.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>Upon the receipt of your instruction setting forth your views, which came
                            to hand on the 19th of June, I addressed a note to His Majesty’s
                            secretary of state for foreign affairs communicating the substance of
                            the same to him and stating that I should be glad to receive and
                            transmit to you the views of His Majesty’s Government on the same
                            question as soon as his lordship should have formulated them, of which
                            note I inclose a copy.</p>
                        <p>On Saturday last I received from Lord Lansdowne a note in reply, setting
                            forth the views of His Majesty’s Government on the same subject, which
                            you will perceive are in substantial concurrence with your own.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>You will observe that a considerable time elapsed between the date of my
                            note to him of June 24 and his reply, which bears date July 19, but this
                            arose from no hesitation or doubt in his mind or in that of his
                            Government upon the subject treated of, but as he told me at our last
                            interview his note was prepared very promptly after the receipt of mine,
                            but its delivery to me was accidentally delayed.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph H.
                            Choate.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to
                                    Lord <persName type="to">Lansdowne</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-06-24"><hi rend="italic">June 24,
                                        1904</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: Referring to our recent
                                interviews, in which you expressed a desire to know the views of my
                                Government as to the order issued by the Russian Government on the
                                28th of February last, making “every kind of fuel, such as coal,
                                naphtha, alcohol, and other similar materials, <hi rend="italic">unconditionally contraband,”</hi> I am now able to state them,
                                as follows:</p>
                            <p>These articles enter into great consumption in the arts of peace, to
                                which they are vitally necessary. They are usually treated not as
                                “absolutely contraband of war,” like articles that are intended
                                primarily for military purposes in time of war, such as ordnance,
                                arms, ammunition, etc., but rather as “conditionally contraband,”
                                that is to say, articles that may be used for or converted to the
                                purposes of war or peace according to circumstances. They may rather
                                be classed with provisions and food stuffs, of ordinarily innocent
                                use, but which may become absolutely contraband of war when actually
                                and especially destined for the military and naval forces of the
                                enemy.</p>
                            <p>In the war between the United States and Spain the Navy Department,
                                General Orders, No. 492, issued June 29, 1898, declared, in article
                                19, as follows: “The term contraband of war comprehends only
                                articles having a belligerent destination.” Among articles
                                absolutely contraband it declared ordnance, machine guns, and other
                                articles of military or naval warfare. It declared as conditionally
                                contraband “coal, when destined for a naval station, a port of call,
                                or a ship or ships of the enemy.” It likewise declared provisions to
                                be conditionally contraband “when destined for the enemy’s ship or
                                ships, or for a place that is besieged.”</p>
                            <p>The above rules as to articles absolutely or conditionally contraband
                                of war were adopted in the Naval War Code, promulgated by the Navy
                                Department, June 27, 1900.</p>
                            <pb facs="0423" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/>
                            <p>While it appears from the documents mentioned that rice, food stuffs,
                                horses, beasts of burden and other animals which may be used in time
                                of war are declared to be contraband of war only when they are
                                transported for account of or in destination to the enemy, yet all
                                kinds of fuel, such as coal, naphtha, alcohol, are classified along
                                with arms, ammunition, and other articles intended for warfare on
                                land or sea.</p>
                            <p>The test in determining whether articles <hi rend="italic">ancipitis
                                    usus</hi> are contraband of war is their destination for the
                                military uses of a belligerent. Mr. Dana, in his Notes to Wheaton’s
                                International Law, says: “The chief circumstance of inquiry would
                                naturally be the port of destination. If that is a naval arsenal or
                                a port in which vessels of war are usually fitted out, or in which a
                                fleet is lying, or a garrison town, or a place from which a military
                                expedition is fitting out, the presumption of military use would be
                                raised, more or less strongly according to circumstances.”</p>
                            <p>In the wars of 1859 and 1870 coal was declared by France not to be
                                contraband. During the latter war Great Britain held that the
                                character of coal depended upon its destination, and refused to
                                permit vessels to sail with it to the French fleet in the North Sea.
                                Where coal or other fuel is shipped to a port of a belligerent, with
                                no presumption against its pacific use, to condemn it as absolutely
                                contraband would seem to be an extreme measure.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Hall, International Law, says: “During the West African
                                conference in 1884 Russia took occasion to dissent vigorously from
                                the inclusion of coal among articles, contraband of war, and
                                declared that she would categorically refuse her consent to any
                                articles in any treaty, convention, or instrument whatever which
                                would imply its recognition as such.”</p>
                            <p>We are also informed that it is intended to treat raw cotton as
                                contraband of war. While it is true that raw cotton could be made up
                                into clothing for the military uses of a belligerent, a military use
                                for the supply of an army or garrison might possibly be made of food
                                stuffs of every description which might be shipped from neutral
                                ports to the nonblockaded ports of a belligerent. The principle
                                under consideration might, therefore, be extended so as to apply to
                                every article of human use, which might be declared contraband of
                                war simply because it might ultimately become in any degree useful
                                to a belligerent for military purposes.</p>
                            <p>Coal and other fuel and cotton are employed for a great many innocent
                                purposes. Many nations are dependent on them for the conduct of
                                inoffensive industries, and no sufficient presumption of an intended
                                warlike use seems to be afforded by the mere fact of their
                                destination to a belligerent port. The recognition in principle of
                                the treatment of coal and other fuel and raw cotton as absolutely
                                contraband of war might ultimately lead to a total inhibition of the
                                sale by neutrals to the people of belligerent states of all articles
                                which could be finally converted to military uses. Such an extension
                                of the principle, by treating coal and all other fuel and raw cotton
                                as absolutely contraband of war, simply because they are shipped by
                                a neutral to a nonblockaded port of a belligerent, would not appear
                                to be in accord with the reasonable and lawful rights of a neutral
                                commerce.</p>
                            <p>I shall be glad to receive and transmit to my Government the views of
                                His Majesty’s Government on the same question as soon as your
                                lordship shall have formulated them.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph H.
                                Choate.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Lord <persName type="from">Lansdowne</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Choate</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-07-29"><hi rend="italic">July 29, 1904</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to
                                acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 24th ultimo, containing
                                the views of the United States Government with regard to the Russian
                                regulations of the 28th February last, in which every kind of fuel,
                                such as coal, naphtha, alcohol, and other similar materials is
                                declared to be absolutely and unconditionally contraband, of
                                war.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to inform Your Excellency, in reply to your request
                                to be furnished with the views of His Majesty’s Government on this
                                subject, that the views of the United States Government, as
                                expressed in Your Excellency’s note, are generally in accord with
                                those which have been held and acted upon from time to time by His
                                Majesty’s Government With reference, however, to <pb facs="0424" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/> the statement made in paragraph 7 as
                                to the attitude of Great Britain in 1870 in regard to coal, I would
                                observe that Her late Majesty’s Government refused in that year to
                                permit vessels to sail with coal to the French fleet, not merely
                                because they held that the character of the coal depended on its
                                destination, but because they held that steamers engaged to take out
                                cargoes of coal to the French fleet in the North Sea would be in
                                reality acting as storeships to that fleet.</p>
                            <p>It is, however, right that I should add that in the altered
                                conditions of modern maritime warfare, and the ever-increasing
                                importance of the part played therein by coal, His Majesty’s
                                Government propose to submit the whole question to careful and
                                exhaustive examination at an early date, with the object of
                                determining whether, and in what respects, the British rules, as
                                hitherto acted upon, are in need of revision.</p>
                            <p>In these circumstances His Majesty’s Government do not propose to
                                make any formal protest at the present stage against the Russian
                                declaration in so far as the question of coal is concerned. They
                                have, however, already entered a protest against the treatment of
                                food stuffs as absolutely contraband, and they have pointed out that
                                they observe with great concern that rice and provisions will be
                                treated as unconditionally contraband, a step which they regard as
                                inconsistent with the law and practice of nations.</p>
                            <p>In that protest it was stated that His Majesty’s Government do not
                                contest that in particular circumstances provisions may acquire a
                                contraband character, as, for instance, if they should be consigned
                                direct to the army or fleet of a belligerent, or to a port where
                                such fleet may be lying, or if facts should exist raising the
                                presumption that they are about to be employed in victualing the
                                fleet or forces of the enemy. In such cases it is not denied that
                                the other belligerent would be entitled to seize the provisions as
                                contraband of war, on the ground that they would afford material
                                assistance toward the carrying on of warlike operations.</p>
                            <p>They could not, however, admit that if such provisions were consigned
                                to the port of a belligerent (even though it should be a port of
                                naval equipment) they must, on that ground alone, be of necessity
                                regarded as contraband of war.</p>
                            <p>In the view of His Majesty’s Government the test appeared to be
                                whether there are circumstances relating to any particular cargo to
                                show that it is destined for military or naval use.</p>
                            <p>His Majesty’s Government further pointed out that the decision of the
                                prize court of the captor in such matters, in order to be binding on
                                neutral States, must be in accordance with recognized rules and
                                principles of international law and procedure.</p>
                            <p>They therefore felt themselves bound to reserve their rights by
                                protesting at once against the doctrine that it is for the
                                belligerent to decide that certain articles, or classes of articles,
                                are, as a matter of course, and without reference to the
                                considerations above referred to, to be dealt with as contraband of
                                war regardless of the well-established rights of neutrals; nor would
                                they consider themselves bound to recognize as valid the decision of
                                any prize court which violated these rights, or was otherwise not in
                                conformity with the recognized principles of international law.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lansdowne.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>