<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1904-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1904-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.—Paraphrase.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-05-27"><hi rend="italic">May 27,
                                1904</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>(Mr. Choate states that he is informed by the British foreign office that
                            the British minister at Tangier reports on the request of the American
                            consul-general at Tangier the conditions for the release of Perdicaris
                            and Varley insisted upon by the brigand as follows: <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>The release of a large number of Moorish prisoners.</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>The dismissal of the governor of Tangier.</item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>The recall to Fez of the Government troops which had been sent
                                    out to keep order.</item>
                                <label>IV.</label>
                                <item>The payment of a ransom of £11,000, this amount to be obtained
                                    by the sale of the properties of the governors of Tangier and
                                    Fez. Money obtained from any other source will be refused by
                                    Raisuli.</item>
                                <label>V.</label>
                                <item>Two small districts to be ceded absolutely to Raisuli by the
                                    Sultan.</item>
                                <label>VI.</label>
                                <item>Demand for the arrest and imprisonment of two Sheikhs and the
                                    two sons of one of them.</item>
                                <label>VII.</label>
                                <item>Free ingress and egress to and from town markets for turbulent
                                    tribesmen, among whom Raisuli now is.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Raisuli would, in order to save time, accept our guaranty that the Sultan
                            will fulfill the conditions imposed. He will probably add to the above
                            conditions immunity for the past. In rejecting our counter proposals he
                            declares that negotiations to reduce the conditions will be useless, as
                            he has stated his minimum terms. Our proposal for free pardon upon
                            immediate release of the captives and abandonment of above conditions
                            remains unanswered, and we do not expect that it will be accepted.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Gummeré, the consul-general of the United States at Tangier, would
                            appreciate the communication of the above terms to his Government, as he
                            has no safe means of sending them.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>