<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1904-04-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1904-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Storer</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-04-21"><hi rend="italic">April 21,
                                1904</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 119.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the law
                            governing emigration from Hungary has been passed at Budapest with
                            certain additions and amendments to the text, of which I transmitted a
                            translation in the month of May, 1903. As yet I have not been able to
                            obtain a full official copy, but newspaper comments, both of praise and
                            of hostile criticism, show that there is a diversity of opinion as to
                            the necessity and advisability of the law. Last night the Emperor took
                            occasion to speak to me on the subject, and expressed his belief that
                            the provisions and aims of this law had not been fully understood, and
                            that this fact was the only cause of the criticisms which the law was
                            receiving on both sides the Atlantic. He added that the explanations to
                            be offered would, he was confident, clear up any objections, as the
                            principles and intentions of the law were those that had for long been
                            understood and accepted. These explanations, I take it, will be made to
                            the Department through the Austro-Hungarian embassy at Washington.</p>
                        <p>As soon as I am able to have before me an official copy of the law as
                            promulgated I will report thereon fully to the Department.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bellamy Storer.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>