<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Ambassador in Greece (
                        MacVeagh
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-24T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="170" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/10–2346: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Greece</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-24T19:00:00-05:00">October 24, 1946—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1385. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss> 1441 Oct 23.<note n="16" xml:id="d170fn16">Not printed.</note> Although your excellent clarification
                    US views to Tsaldaris included reference to Greek territorial claims you may
                    take opportunity further to stress this aspect Greek problem with Tsaldaris or
                    other Govt officials or King if you think advisable in connection declared Greek
                    intention present territorial claims to <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> in
                    New York. US vote against Bulgarian frontier revision in Bulgarian Territorial
                    Commission and Peace Conference<note n="17" xml:id="d170fn17">See the United
                        States Delegation Journal account of the Fifteenth Meeting of the Political
                        and Territorial Commission for Bulgaria, October 1, and the Verbatim Record
                        of the Forty-Second Plenary Meeting, October 11, <ref target="frus1946v03#pg_610">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp.
                            610</ref> and <ref target="frus1946v03#pg_796">796</ref>.</note> makes
                    clear our position on that question. In fairness Greek Govt should realize in
                    advance that US can not support Greek desire for revision Albanian frontier.
                    Although US has sympathetic understanding Greek arguments for territorial
                    adjustments and realizes failure to achieve national claims is bitter pill,
                    indeed, we feel that in interest more important long-range aim of Balkan peace
                    and stability US must favor retention 1939 boundaries. However, we would
                    strongly support Greece in event any effort made to change those boundaries.</p>
                <p>It would appear to be to eventual advantage of Greece to accept territorial
                    integrity of its neighbors several of which are now exploiting <pb facs="0258" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/> against Greece what they characterize as
                    increasingly aggressive attitude of Greek Govt in its endeavors to enlarge
                    territory at their expense.</p>
                <p>Although it has always been US belief that international differences should be
                    given fullest hearing in appropriate international bodies Greek Govt must
                    certainly be aware that continued attempts to advance these claims in and out of
                    season can only create difficulties for Greece and for those nations who want to
                    assist her in present dangerous situation. If in spite unfavorable atmosphere
                    and likelihood frontier claims being rejected Greek Govt still feels it must
                    present these claims to <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, US Govt strongly
                    hopes Greek officials and politicians are prepared to accept in good faith and
                    goodwill any decision on her territorial claims even though it may be
                    unfavorable to Greece and that they should be further prepared to exert all
                    possible influence within their country to have such decision accepted with a
                    minimum of dissatisfaction and rancor towards other nations.</p>
                <p>Foregoing views being expressed to Greek Amb here.<note n="18" xml:id="d170fn18">On October 25 (memorandum of conversation not printed).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Athens 1385. Rptd London 7347, Paris 5714, Moscow 1888, Sofia 348, Tirana
                    195.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
