<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Head of the Delegation of the Soviet Union at the United Nations (
                    (Vyshinsky) ) to the President of the Security Council ( (Makin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d224</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">224</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="224"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d224">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Head of the Delegation of the Soviet Union at the United
                        Nations</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Vyshinsky</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the President of the Security Council</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Makin</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="48" type="source" xml:id="d224fn48">Reprinted from <gloss
                            target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser., supp.
                            No. 1</hi>, p. 17.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-24">24 January
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The delegation of the Soviet Union, acting on behalf of the Soviet Government,
                    considers it necessary, in connexion with the appeal of the Iranian delegation
                    addressed to the Security Council, to make the following statement:</p>
                <p>1. The allegation made by the Iranian delegation of interference by the Soviet
                    Union, through its officials and through its armed forces, <pb facs="0322"
                        n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/> in the internal affairs of Iran is not in
                    accordance with the facts and is devoid of any foundation. In this particular
                    case, the Iranian delegation repeats the statement made by the Iranian
                    Government to the Soviet Government in November 1945.<note n="49"
                        xml:id="d224fn49">For summary of note of November 17, 1945, from the Iranian
                        Ministry for Foreign Affairs to the Soviet Embassy in Iran, see telegram
                        959, November 19, 1945, from Tehran, <ref target="frus1945v08#pg_431">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>, p. 431</ref>. The text of the note is
                        printed in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st
                            ser., supp. No. 1</hi>, p. 50.</note> This statement, however, was
                    categorically refuted by the Soviet Embassy in Iran in its Note of 26
                        November.<note n="50" xml:id="d224fn50">For last paragraph of Soviet note,
                        the key section in the Soviet reply, see telegram 1040, December 2, 1945,
                        from Tehran, <ref target="frus1945v08#pg_470">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>, p. 470</ref>. The full text is printed
                        in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                        <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser., supp. No. 1</hi>, p. 55.</note> It
                    should also be noted that in its reply of 1 December 1945,<note n="51"
                        xml:id="d224fn51">For text, see telegram 1054, December 3, 1945, <ref
                            target="frus1945v08#pg_473">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>, p. 473</ref>, or <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                            >SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser., supp. No. 1</hi>, p.
                        58.</note> the Iranian Government not only failed to disprove the facts
                    referred to in the Soviet Note of 26 November, but also expressed, as is stated
                    in the above-mentioned Iranian Note, “its satisfaction that, as is confirmed by
                    the Embassy’s reply, the interference of Soviet officials in the internal
                    affairs of the northern districts of Iran is not in accordance with the facts”.
                    Moreover, in the same note, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Iran “expresses
                    its satisfaction at the fact that, as has been pointed out, the Soviet officials
                    fully respect the Tri-Partite Agreement<note n="52" xml:id="d224fn52">The Treaty
                        of Alliance between the United Kingdom, the Soviet Union, and Iran, signed
                        at Tehran on January 29, 1942; for text, see Department of State <hi
                            rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 21, 1942, p. 249.</note> and the
                    Declaration signed and published in Tehran by the leaders of the three great
                        Powers,<note n="53" xml:id="d224fn53">The Declaration regarding Iran,
                        December 1, 1943, <ref target="frus1943v04#pg_413">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 413</ref>.</note> Allies of Iran.”</p>
                <p>These facts are sufficiently convincing evidence of the inaccuracy and
                    groundlessness of the statement of the Iranian delegation regarding the alleged
                    interference on the part of the Soviet Union in the internal affairs of
                    Iran.</p>
                <p>2. Equally in contradiction to the facts is the statement of the Iranian
                    delegation that the Iranian Government has made unsuccessful attempts to enter
                    into negotiations with the Soviet Government on this question. This statement of
                    the Iranian delegation is refuted by the above-mentioned facts, since the
                    Iranian Government not only attempted to negotiate but entered into negotiations
                    with the Soviet Government on this question, as is evident from the Iranian Note
                    of 1 December, referred to above.</p>
                <p>3. The Soviet delegation considers it necessary to point out that the Iranian
                    Government is trying to use the presence of foreign troops in Iran in order to
                    represent this fact as a violation of Iranian sovereignty and as a cause of the
                    events which are taking place in Iranian <pb facs="0323" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"
                    /> Azerbaijan. As a matter of fact, the presence of Soviet troops on the
                    territory of Iran is quite legitimate inasmuch as this right was granted to the
                    Soviet Government by the Soviet-Iranian Treaty of 26 February 1921<note n="54"
                        xml:id="d224fn54">Treaty of Friendship between the Russian Socialist
                        Federated Soviet Republic and Persia, signed at Moscow; for text, see League
                        of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 384.</note>
                    and the Soviet-British-Iranian Treaty of 1942. The events in Iranian Azerbaijan
                    have no connexion with the presence there of Soviet troops, as the indisputable
                    and entirely objective facts bear witness. These events are of an exclusively
                    Iranian and internal nature.</p>
                <p>As is known, what is happening in northern Iran is connected with the aspirations
                    of the population of northern Iran for national autonomy within the limits of
                    the Iranian State, and with the achievement of the wishes of the local
                    population, which is nothing unusual for a democratic State.</p>
                <p>4. At the same time, the Soviet delegation cannot but draw attention to the fact
                    that propaganda hostile to the Soviet Union has of late been growing stronger in
                    Iran with the manifest toleration of the Iranian Government. This propaganda in
                    no way differs from the fascist propaganda which was carried on against the
                    Soviet Union at the time of Riza Shah.</p>
                <p>The anti-democratic and pogrom activity, hostile to the Soviet Union, on the part
                    of the reactionary forces in Iran which are supported by certain influential
                    Iranian groups drawn from the ruling circles and the police authorities, creates
                    for the Azerbaijan Soviet Socialist Republic and for Baku a danger of organized
                    hostile actions, diversions and so forth.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Government considers, however, that questions of this kind, which
                    affect the relations between two neighbouring States, the USSR and Iran, can and
                    should be settled by means of bilateral negotiations between the Soviet
                    Government and the Iranian Government. The Soviet Government did not and does
                    not refuse to accept this method of settling such questions arising between
                    Allied Governments.</p>
                <p>5. In view of these facts, and taking into consideration that in this I
                    particular case the conditions envisaged by Articles 34 and 35 of the Charter of
                    the United Nations are lacking, the Soviet delegation regards the appeal of the
                    Iranian delegation to the Security Council as devoid of any foundation and is
                    categorically opposed to the consideration of the above-mentioned appeal of the
                    Iranian delegation by the Security Council.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Vyshinsky</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0324" n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[The Iranian and Soviet letters of January 19 and 24 were brought formally to
                        the notice of the Security Council at its meeting on January 25. Two major
                        issues were discussed at this meeting: The question of the inclusion of the
                        Iranian matter on the agenda of the Council and the question of Iran’s right
                        as a member of the United Nations to be invited to the Council’s table.</p>
                    <p>The Iranian question was placed on the agenda with no objection. At this
                        point, Mr. Vyshinsky stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“There is one point I would like to clarify: that is the inclusion of
                                the Iranian question in the Security Council’s agenda. Does this
                                mean consideration of the substance of the question or discussion as
                                to whether it should come before the Council at all?</p>
                            <p>If this item is placed on the agenda so that we may discuss whether
                                the question should be considered, then I have no objection to its
                                inclusion on the agenda for the next meeting. … The Soviet
                                delegation … has put forward reasons proving that the statement of
                                the Iranian Government should not be considered by the Security
                                Council.</p>
                            <p>It therefore seems to me that we should, in the first place,
                                thoroughly discuss this matter, and, as the Chairman suggests, the
                                Soviet delegation should in any case have the opportunity at the
                                next meeting of putting forward its reasons why this question should
                                not be considered by the Security Council.” (United Nations, <gloss
                                    target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser.,
                                    No. 1, p. 16.</hi>)</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The President of the Council replied: “… I should like to say that the
                        inclusion of the item in this agenda does give an opportunity for the
                        Council to have a discusion, and that the USSR could, at the initial stage
                        of that discussion, make such proposal as it might think proper. The
                        inclusion would not deny to the USSR representative the opportunity of being
                        able to move in whatever direction he might wish.” (<hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid.</hi>)</p>
                    <p>In reply to a question by Mr. Bevin, the President of the Council stated
                        further: “… It is for the Council itself to determine the procedure that it
                        wishes to adopt in regard to this matter, that is, whether it wishes to
                        proceed to a discussion or to take any other action it might wish.” (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 20)</p>
                    <p>Regarding the second issue, Mr. Stettinius stated: “… I wish to make very
                        clear that the United States Government believes that any Member country of
                        the United Nations which makes a complaint has a right to be heard at this
                        table.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 18.) A motion by the Egyptian
                        representative to this effect was adopted without a vote.</p>
                    <p>For the official record of the proceedings of the Security Council on January
                        25, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 15–20.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
