<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Iran ( (Murray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-03-22T05:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-22T05:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recEKBMJ0utJPbJXo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-22T05:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-22T05:30:00-05:00" n="274"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24691/3–2246: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-22T14:00:00+03:30"
                            >March 22, 1946—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 24—12:49 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>383. National Bank Governor Ebtehaj called on me late evening March 21 to report
                    that new Soviet Ambassador Sadchikov had seen <gloss target="#t_PriMin1"
                        >PriMin</gloss> afternoon of March 20 only few hours after reaching Tehran
                    and had suggested that Soviets might withdraw troops from Iran if Shah and
                        <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> would sign letter to him assuring
                    Russia that arrangements would be made for joint Irano-Soviet exploitation of
                    north Iranian oil. Ebtehaj said he had not learned this from Qavam but from
                    intermediate source in whom he had absolute confidence. He feared Qavam might be
                    tempted by offer and be tricked into some agreement which would leave loophole
                    for Russians to run out on their part of bargain. He was, therefore, anxious for
                    me to see <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> before latter saw Shah at
                    lunch today.</p>
                <pb facs="0382" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/>
                <p>I had two and half hour conversation with <gloss target="#t_PriMin1"
                        >PriMin</gloss> this morning which he asked be kept completely confidential.
                    (I again assured him that leak on Soviet Chargé’s threat<note n="32"
                        xml:id="d274fn32">See telegram 343, March 15, 1 p.m., from Tehran, <ref
                            target="#pg_356">p. 356</ref>.</note> had not come from American
                    source.) To induce him to talk I opened by telling Qavam of Gromyko’s letter to
                    Lie requesting postponement of Security Council meeting and of President’s
                    public statement that meeting would not be postponed. I also reminded him of
                    Stettinius’ statement at London <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting that
                    US Govt considered withdrawal of foreign troops from any country which requested
                    it should not be subject to any conditions.<note n="33" xml:id="d274fn33">See,
                        for example, the statement made by Mr. Stettinius at the Twenty-First
                        Meeting of the Security Council on February 15, 1946, <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                            >SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser., No. 1</hi>, p.
                        301.</note> I stressed importance of this position.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> did not explicitly confirm Ebtehaj
                    version of his talk with Sadchikov but from his remarks I am sure that account
                    was substantially correct.</p>
                <p>According to Qavam Sadchikov expressed himself as having been surprised and upset
                    on learning at Baku of Iranian appeal to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    saying he had thought it had been understood that he was coming to Tehran to
                    continue Moscow negotiations. <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> replied
                    by reminding Sadchikov of him [<hi rend="italic">his</hi>] protest filed at
                    Moscow against continued occupation of Iran and of changes he (Qavam) had
                    insisted on making in proposed communiqué in order to show that negotiations
                    were not to be continued Tehran. He thought he had made it clear that presence
                    Soviet troops in Iran after March 2 tied his hands so far as negotiations were
                    concerned. Sadchikov said Stalin felt it was regrettable that during Moscow
                    talks Iran had made no single gesture favorable to USSR, especially with respect
                    to oil. <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> answered by saying he had not
                    rejected any Soviet proposals, since law did not permit him consider proposals
                    regarding oil. He further said that if Soviet Govt pressed him to do anything
                    against law his only course would be to resign. New <gloss target="#t_PriMin1"
                        >PriMin</gloss> could hardly be more favorably disposed to USSR than he.</p>
                <p>Qavam then asked me hypothetical question which confirms my belief in Ebtehaj
                    story. He said (in effect): What would you do in my place if Soviet Ambassador
                    should offer to effect withdrawal of Soviet troops in exchange for an
                    understanding regarding exploitation of oil in northern Iran? I said I could
                    only speak personally but felt he should be extremely careful about any sort of
                    written agreement or exchange of letters exclusively involving Iran and USSR. He
                    had already had experience in which Soviets had broken pledged word embodied in
                    formal treaty and should have even less reason to depend on any less formal,
                    bilateral, understanding. However, if he could induce Russians to commit
                    themselves before <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> to withdraw <pb facs="0383"
                        n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/> by certain date he would have more binding
                    assurance. I also suggested it would be well for him to leave way open for
                    Soviets to save face if he could do so while safeguarding Iranian interests.</p>
                <p>See, for example, the statement made by Mr. Stettinius at the Twenty-First
                    Meeting of the Security Council on February 15, 1946, <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">1st yr., 1st ser., No. 1</hi>, p. 301.</p>
                <p>Essence of Qavam’s thinking as it developed in course of conversation was: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>He fears that if <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> censures USSR and
                            asks withdrawal of troops Russians will vent their wrath on himself and
                            on Iran, which could be harrassed in many ways by Soviet Govt, and that
                                <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss> could not provide adequate
                            protection.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>He considers that from viewpoint of practical politics understanding
                            with USSR on northern Iranian oil is long overdue. He asserted that
                            Soviet complaints that Iran had discrimmated in favor of Britain by
                            granting <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss>
                            <note n="34" xml:id="d274fn34">Anglo-Iranian Oil Company.</note>
                            concession were hard to meet in light of fact controlling interest in
                                <gloss target="#t_AIOC1">AIOC</gloss> is held by British Govt. He
                            believes any future Majlis will approve concession to Soviets and that
                            such concession is inevitable.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>He believes he can get around law prohibiting oil negotiations by
                            arranging for a joint Irano-Soviet Company with the two Govts snaring
                            control. He admits even such company would ultimately need Majlis’
                            approval for its operations but is confident this can be obtained.
                            Meanwhile during period before new Majlis assembles, he asserts approval
                            can be granted by Cabinet decree subject to later Majlis confirmation.
                            (I would hesitate to pass on correctness of his legal position in this
                            reasoning, which seems to me open to grave doubt. However he might be
                            able to carry it off in circumstances.)</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>He is considering preparation of an agreement in very general terms
                            which would provide in principle for joint Irano-Soviet oil exploitation
                            as inducement for Soviets to withdraw troops. He would draft this very
                            carefully to make troop withdrawal a condition precedent. He added this
                            agreement might be expanded to include subjects other than oil.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> was to lunch today with Shah and
                    Hosein Pirnia (Motamen-Ol-Molk) an outstanding elder statesman and patriot. He
                    was to see Sadchikov again at 5:00 this afternoon. Unless Shah dissuaded him I
                    believe he planned to suggest to Sadchikov some sort of arrangement such as that
                    indicated above, to be conditioned on Soviet pledge to <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> that troops would be withdrawn by specified date not more than 6
                    weeks distant.</p>
                <p>Sent Department as 383; repeated Moscow 191; London 72.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
