<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-27T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-27T14:00:00-05:00" n="377" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">121.5491/6–2146: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent   most immediate</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-27T15:00:00-04:00">June 27,
                                    1946—3 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>559. Would appreciate your confirmation of report in <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> Tehran despatch Jun 22 that Emb had
                            protested to Iranian Govt incident reported Tabriz 198, Jun 21,<note n="71" xml:id="d377fn71">Not printed; Mr. Rossow reported that the
                                previous day the Military Attaché, the Military Attaché for Air, the
                                Assistant Military Attaché, and a fourth member of their party were
                                arrested and held under armed guard at the Tabriz airport for 7
                                hours on the pretext that they had landed without authority. The
                                Military Attaché had been assured previously by the Iranian Foreign
                                Office that clearance had been arranged. Despite Mr. Rossow’s “most
                                vigorous representations”, the officers were not permitted to leave
                                the airport until at 5 p.m. the Acting Governor General of
                                Azerbaijan consented to bring the officers to Tabriz where they were
                                held under armed guard at the telegraph office. Finally they were
                                released on condition that they would depart the following day if
                                landing permission were not granted. Mr. Rossow summed up the manner
                                of the local officials as “hostile, disrespectful and insulting to
                                the prestige of the United States”. The Chief of Political Police
                                informed the Consulate on the morning of June 21 that landing
                                permission had been granted and expressed his hope that “we would
                                not harbor rancor” since the matter was an error of the Central
                                Government. (121.5491/6–2146)</note> (repeated Tehran as 190.) Dept
                            greatly disturbed over incident, which appears to represent endeavor by
                            Azerbaijan to apply arbitrary totalitarian methods used by Sov forces
                            when stationed in Iran, and feels that strong protest to Iranian Govt is
                            called for. Iranian Govt should be requested to investigate incident,
                            indicate what action if any is contemplated against persons involved,
                            and what steps will be taken to prevent recurrence. These views were
                            expressed by Dept official in conversation with Iranian Amb who promised
                            to bring them to attention of <gloss target="#t_ForMin1">ForMin</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Sent to Tehran, repeated to Tabriz, Moscow and London.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>