<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-13T08:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-13T08:30:00-05:00" n="384" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/8–1346: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-13T17:00:00+03:30">August 13,
                                    1946—5 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received August 13—3:58 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1116. Following my conference with Qavam today regarding Helmand River
                            matter he asked me to stay for very serious talk concerning political
                            situation. He said he expected delegation from Azerbaijan headed by
                            Governor General Djavid to arrive in Tehran in few days. He said he was
                            determined to find out immediately whether Tabriz government wanted
                            Azerbaijan to be part of Iran or not.<note n="79" xml:id="d384fn79">In
                                telegram 1104, August 10, 1946, 5 p.m., from Tehran, the Ambassador
                                had reported that negotiations between the Iranian Government and
                                the Azerbaijani authorities regarding the status of Azerbaijani
                                regular and volunteer forces had broken down and that relations
                                between the two governments had seriously deteriorated
                                (891.00/8–1046).</note> He said he would be very firm, and that if
                            negotiations broke down he might have to use force to bring Azerbaijan
                            back into Iranian nation, much as he hesitated to shed Iranian blood. He
                            said his principal worry was that in case of resort to force he feared
                            USSR would supply Azerbaijan with guns, tanks, airplanes, money and men
                            in civilian clothes who would pose as volunteers. He asked what I
                            thought UN would be able to do to help Iran.</p>
                        <p>I said that as he was of course aware USSR had veto in Security Council
                            over substantive action by that body. Moreover, UN had no security
                            forces or armaments available. Nevertheless I believed that in case of
                            flagrant support by USSR of separatist movement in Iran and in case Iran
                            placed matter strongly and unreservedly before Security Council, I could
                            not believe that those nations which were determined to make UN a
                            forceful organization capable of defending small nations from
                            aggression, would sit by idly and admit that organization was incapable
                            of any assistance in case of this kind. I referred to speeches by
                            President Truman and Secretary Byrnes calling on members of UN to
                            believe in UN and to base their policies on it as only hope for better
                            organized world in future. I said I thought some means would be found to
                            aid nations which did so.</p>
                        <pb facs="0524" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/>
                        <p>I suggested to Qavam that if negotiations with Azerbaijan broke off, he
                            should make it abundantly clear to world that rupture came because
                            Tabriz Government was not willing for Azerbaijan to become part of Iran
                            again. This would make it clear that he was fighting for Iran’s
                            integrity. He could cite plenty of evidence that Azerbaijan group have
                            failed even to abide by more than generous agreement Qavam gave them in
                            June.</p>
                        <p>Qavam was in most determined mood I have found him since my arrival here.
                            He said he knew that Azerbaijan group and probably Soviet press would
                            denounce him as Fascist and reactionary, but he was prepared for all
                            that. He said reason he had been so overly conciliatory to Azerbaijan
                            and Tudeh up to present was his lack of confidence in Iranian Army but
                            he had that confidence now. If USSR would remain neutral he did not fear
                            results.</p>
                        <p>If Qavam appeals to Security Council again, I believe he will do so
                            wholeheartedly and unreservedly. I hope Council will be able to show its
                            ability to function in what may be real test.<note n="80" xml:id="d384fn80">In telegram 1117, August 13, 6 p.m., Ambassador
                                Allen reported a conversation with Prime Minister Qavam during which
                                he expressed the hope that the latter might visit the United States
                                in September since it was especially appropriate for the Prime
                                Minister of the first member of the United Nations to present a
                                substantive case to the Security Council to head his country’s
                                delegation to the General Assembly (891.002/8–1346). In telegram
                                692, August 16, 6 p.m., the Department expressed its concurrence
                                with the Ambassador’s views regarding Iran’s relations with the UN
                                and Qavam’s attendance at the General Assembly
                                (891.00/8–1346).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Department 1116; repeated Paris, London and Moscow.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>