<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-01-10T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-10T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-10T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-10T23:00:00-05:00" n="48"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.51/1–946: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-10T23:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 10, 1946—11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>309. For Hawkins and Taylor.<note n="4" xml:id="d48fn4">Harry C. Hawkins,
                        Counselor for Economic Affairs in the United Kingdom, and William H. Taylor,
                        Treasury Representative in the United Kingdom, who were American
                        participants in British-Greek discussions on the Greek economic and
                        financial situation; see telegram 11089, December 27, 1945, to London, <ref
                            target="frus1945v08#pg_297">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>, p. 297</ref>.</note> Following is
                    proposed draft on Greek Currency Committee proposal submitted to but not yet
                    cleared by Sec Vinson.<note n="5" xml:id="d48fn5">Fred M. Vinson, Secretary of
                        the Treasury.</note> Do not consider this draft as approved or act on
                    instructions contained herein until you receive telephone confirmation by State
                    Department approximately Friday noon Wash time. Any changes in draft will be
                    communicated to you at that time.<note n="6" xml:id="d48fn6">In telegram 339,
                        January 11, 1946, 8 p.m., the Department informed London that President
                        Truman, at discussions the same afternoon with Messrs. Acheson and Vinson,
                        had expressed grave concern as to the possibility of success of the
                        committee device and the extent of United States involvement through
                        participation by an American on the Committee. Nevertheless he had approved
                        proceeding on the basis set forth in telegram 309. (868.51/1–746)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Dept and Treas have given most careful consideration to Brit views on Greek
                    situation set forth in <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss>s 273, Jan 9 and
                    119, Jan 4<note n="7" xml:id="d48fn7">Neither printed.</note> (repeated to
                    Athens as 8 and 4 respectively) to views of Emb contained in Athens’ 1497, Jan
                        1<note n="8" xml:id="d48fn8">
                        <ref target="frus1945v08#pg_298">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">viii</hi>, p. 298</ref>.</note> (repeated to you as
                        <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 128 Jan 5) and in Athens despatch
                    2002, Dec 15,<note n="9" xml:id="d48fn9">
                        <ref target="frus1945v08#pg_284">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 284</ref>.</note> and to Greek views
                    reported in <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 173, Jan 7<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d48fn10">Not printed.</note> (apparently not repeated to Athens). As
                    result of this consideration following views have been developed.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We are convinced that monetary measures alone cannot solve Greek problem
                        but agree that comprehensive program of economic and administrative
                        rehabilitation cannot be successfully implemented without some degree of
                        currency stability.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We believe that proposed Currency Committee has serious shortcomings but
                        recognize that it may have stabilizing effect which may assist initiation of
                        comprehensive program mentioned above. We believe this is matter of judgment
                        which in last analysis Greek Government must decide. Apart from matter of
                        its technical effectiveness Currency Committee proposal is open to serious
                        question from US viewpoint because: (1) US representation on Committee would
                        result in degree of US participation in internal affairs of friendly foreign
                        nation far in excess of that to which US Govt has heretofore been willing to
                        agree, (2) There is danger that an American, even if appointed in private
                        capacity, may be regarded by Greeks as representing US Govt, (3) possibility
                        that Committee will fail in effectively stabilizing <pb facs="0102" n="90"
                            xml:id="pg_90"/> Greek currency can not be overlooked in which event US
                        Govt might share onus of such failure and become subject to attack in Greek
                        politics. Despite these misgivings we are prepared to agree to participation
                        of an American in proposed Currency Committee if Greek Govt proposes its
                        establishment and if Greek Govt clearly understands that U. S. Govt assumes
                        no responsibility for operations of currency committee or for determination
                        of exchange rates and is in no way committed to additional financial support
                        on account either of decisions made by currency committee or participation
                        of American individual therein. This decision is made because we believe
                        that present situation justifies adoption of extraordinary measures,
                        particularly since they appear to constitute only feasible immediate
                        remedy.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>This Govt notes possibility that Brit Govt may be willing to pay into
                        proposed Greek currency reserve account sum not exceeding £ 5 million which
                        should contribute to flexibility necessary to successful operation of
                        scheme. U. S. Govt cannot commit itself at this time to pay equal sum into
                        currency reserve account. Such proposal can only be considered on its merits
                        when need for funds arises.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Final approval was given Jan 9 to $25 million <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1"
                            >Eximbank</gloss> loan to Greece. Greek Ambassador will be informed late
                        afternoon Jan 11. Note to Greeks will be released in press Jan 12.<note
                            n="11" xml:id="d48fn11">For text, see Department of State <hi
                                rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 20, 1946, p. 78.</note> In view
                        of fact that Greeks here were already aware consideration of loan had
                        reached final stages it was not deemed appropriate to postpone announcement
                        further.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Any U. S. Govt expert advisors who may be requested by Greeks to aid in
                        formulation of economic rehabilitation program will act in exclusively
                        advisory capacity under terms of reference which will clearly indicate that
                        such advisors will have no authority to commit U. S. in any way with respect
                        to additional loans to Greece.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>We are not completely clear as to procedure for implementing Currency
                        Committee proposal and manner in which decisions respecting such matters as
                        exchange rate, amount of note issue and of currency reserve, etc., will be
                        made. We presume these questions will be determined later and we will be
                        given advance opportunity to examine proposals.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>You are requested to inform Brit at earliest opportunity of U.S. position
                        as outlined above so necessary steps can be taken to ascertain Greek
                        reaction to Currency Committee proposal and implement project. Copies of
                        this telegram have been provided to Brit Emb and Treas Delegation,
                        Washington. For your info Dept informally advised Brit Emb here Jan 7 of
                        Depot’s initial reaction on <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss>
                        loan and Currency Committee, indicating Dept felt there would be difficulty
                        in postponing announcement of loan but Dept would not advance objection to
                        appointment of American on Currency Committee on understanding U.S. and Brit
                        members were not appointed as representatives of their respective
                        Govts.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
