<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Egypt (
                        Tuck
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d581</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">581</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-10-01T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-01T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-01T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-01T10:00:00-05:00" n="581" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d581">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.77/10–146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Tuck</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">most immediate</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-01T17:00:00+02:00">October 1, 1946—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 2—noon]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1641. For Loy Henderson.<note n="25" xml:id="d581fn25">Director of the Office of
                        Near Eastern and African Affairs.</note> General Giles, Regional Director
                        <gloss target="#t_TWA1">TWA</gloss>, has requested me to transmit the
                    following Top Secret message which King Ibn Saud has asked him to deliver
                    urgently to President Truman.</p>
                <p>In consenting to forward this message which I consider important, I wish to make
                    it clear that it is not my intention to poach on the preserves of our Minister
                    to Saudi Arabia. Giles has assured me that he would have given the message
                    immediately to Childs at Jidda but for the fact that the latter was absent in
                    the Yemen.<note n="26" xml:id="d581fn26">Minister Childs had left Jidda to
                        present his letters of credence to the Imam of the Yemen; see despatch 69,
                        September 17, from Jidda, <ref target="#pg_925">p. 925</ref>.</note> The
                    gist of the passage as given verbally by King Ibn Saud to Giles at Riyadh on
                    September 28, 1946 is as follows:</p>
                <p>The King first informed Giles that the message he wished delivered to President
                    Truman was of the utmost secrecy and urgency and that not even Prince Faisal or
                    his Saudi Arabian Minister in Washington were aware of it. The King said that he
                    had pledged his word to his people to build a railway from the east coast of
                    Saudi Arabia to Riyadh<note n="27" xml:id="d581fn27">The Saudi Arabian Minister
                        of Finance had left Jidda en route to the United States on July 29. On
                        August 6, Minister Childs had advised the Department in airgram A–86, 1946,
                        that one of the principal purposes of this visit was understood to be the
                        raising of a loan of $50,000,000 to finance construction of a railway from
                        Damman to Riyadh. (890F.51/8–646) Abdullah Suleiman discussed the question
                        of the railroad with President Truman on August 14 (Memorandum of
                        Conversation by R. D. Muir, Acting Chief of Protocol, filed under
                        890F.002/8–1446) and with Acting Secretary of State Acheson on October 10
                        (Memorandum of Conversation by Mr. Sanger, filed under
                        890F.77/10–1046).</note> which he wished his people to operate. This railway
                    would serve to bring into the country oil equipment and supplies and would aid
                    in developing the hinterland. The King said that a road alone would not serve
                    the country effectively as motor transport was constantly in need of repair and
                    is therefore of limited use. He added that he intended to fulfill this pledge to
                    his people at whatever cost and he looked for assistance to President Truman and
                    the American people as his only true friends. The King said that British
                    interests were both selfish and restrictive in character and that he believed
                    that the British were secretly friendly to the Jews. The King expressed to Giles
                    his great hope and faith in the US and declared that he would always remain our
                    friend although on occasion his pronouncements in regard to the Palestine
                        question<note n="28" xml:id="d581fn28">For documentation on this question,
                        see <ref target="#pg_576">pp. 576</ref> ff.</note> might indicate
                    otherwise.</p>
                <pb facs="0761" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/>
                <p>King Ibn Saud stated that he would exhaust every means at his disposal in the
                    hope of obtaining American assistance for this proposed railway construction
                    project but if American help was not forthcoming, he would not hesitate to seek
                    British assistance which he believed the British would gladly offer. Failing
                    either American or British help, he would be obliged to seek recourse to some
                    other powerful nation (presumably Russia).</p>
                <p>The King concluded the interview by reiterating his firm intention to build this
                    railway which he said would be the “crowning glory” of his reign.</p>
                <p>This message has not been repeated to Jidda.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
