<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Secretariat Files: NSC 22
                            folder</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Paul H.
                                    Nitze</persName>, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Economic Affairs</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">Thorp</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-03">August 3, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Comments and recommendation concerning National
                            Security Council paper circulated at request of the Secretary of the
                            Army for discussion at the next meeting of the National Security Council
                            concerning the current critical situation in China and outlining
                            alternative courses of U. S. action.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Comments</hi></p>
                        <p>While the attached memorandum<note n="94" xml:id="d111fn94">See note by
                                Rear Admiral Sidney W. Souers to the National Security Council, July
                                26, <ref target="#pg_118">p. 118</ref>.</note> primarily raises
                            questions for decision on political and military grounds, the following
                            comments are offered with respect to the analysis of the current
                            situation in China, the critical questions which face the U. S.
                            Government and the suggested courses of action. <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Since promulgation by the National Government of its ten-point
                                    program of domestic self-help measures on January 28, 1948,<note n="95" xml:id="d111fn95">See statement from the Chinese
                                        Embassy, <ref target="#pg_7">p. 7</ref>.</note> the economic
                                    situation in China has deteriorated at an accelerated pace. The
                                    National Government has not in fact taken action to show that it
                                    will or can come to grips with the basic problems of budgetary
                                    and balance-of-payments deficits. The capacity of the government
                                    to initiate and cary through necessary reforms is declining as
                                    the military situation and prospects worsen, as rumors of
                                    defection and separatist movements increase, and as confidence
                                    in the present Nanking regime falls lower and lower.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Some constructive steps have been taken with U. S. assistance,
                                    for example, the inauguration of rice rationing in principal
                                    urban <pb facs="0140" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/> centers has
                                    proved a stabilizing factor and has undoubtedly contributed to
                                    maintenance of public order. It is too early to write off the
                                    possibility of any further constructive steps in connection with
                                    the present China Aid Program and this Program must be ably
                                    staffed and energetically carried thru by the United States. As
                                    matters now stand, however, it appears that at best the present
                                    aid program can only slow down the rate of deterioration in a
                                    worsening situation. There is no real basis for foreseeing
                                    improvement in economic and political prospects in China unless
                                    and until a Chinese Government itself can and will carry through
                                    energetically a program of rural and fiscal reforms.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The Chinese Government has now drawn down its official foreign
                                    dollar holdings until little remains uncommitted beyond minimum
                                    working balances of $25 to $35 million (officially-held gold in
                                    China amounts to approximately $84 million and official holdings
                                    of silver in China are around $28 million). Unless China can
                                    rapidly take steps to increase her exports and acquire for
                                    official use the dollars from foreign overseas remittances, the
                                    end of the present U. S. aid program in April 1949 will find her
                                    with foreign exchange assets completely depleted, and without
                                    means for acquiring the necessary amounts of imports of military
                                    supplies, raw materials, fuel and foodstuffs.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Even on the assumption that the present regime retains some
                                    degree of authority in Nanking during the next six months, the
                                    dependence of that regime on continuance of U. S. assistance
                                    will be completely apparent, and a decision will have to be
                                    reached in this Government at the latest by next February or
                                    March as to whether to continue to support the present Nanking
                                    regime. This decision may be required even sooner should there
                                    occur a collapse in the authority of the present regime from
                                    military reverses, from its currency becoming worthless, or
                                    because of separatist movements. It would be a decision vastly
                                    more difficult and far-reaching in its implications should the
                                    present regime remove itself from Nanking and still claim to
                                    function as the Government of Nationalist China.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>In our view, even in the present serious situation which
                                    appears to be shaping up to a crisis, this Government stands
                                    committed to support in coming months, as much as possible, the
                                    present National Government of China. It should, however, be
                                    made finally and unmistakably clear to the leader of that
                                    Government that U. S. aid cannot in itself save a situation in
                                    which the Nationalist Government itself cannot or will not take
                                    the measures of self-help necessary to utilize that aid
                                    effectively, and to command the support of the Chinese people.
                                    No pledge of further U. S. aid should be made, except as it is
                                    contingent upon the record which the present regime makes in
                                    utilizing aid presently going forward.</item>
                                <pb facs="0141" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>As long as the U. S. recognizes the present National
                                    Government of China, in our view, it must deal through that
                                    Government and not by-pass Nanking to deal with individual
                                    military leaders or separatist groups. If it is the view of the
                                    U. S. Government that larger amounts of U. S. economic or
                                    military aid should go to areas or commanders now neglected by
                                    the Nationalist Government, it is appropriate to exert the
                                    strongest pressure on the Nationalist Government to have this
                                    done.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>In the event of a collapse in the authority of the present
                                    regime in China, this Government should take all steps which
                                    circumstances permit to support new leadership pledged to
                                    maintain and develop an independent, non-Communist National
                                    Government. This would not only be consistent with our
                                    objectives and policies in the past, but it appears the course
                                    by which this Government can most effectively help to maintain
                                    China’s position in the family of nations, her role in the
                                    United Nations and other international bodies, the maintenance
                                    of her legal commitments from the standpoint of peace treaties,
                                    commercial treaties and other international obligations.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi></p>
                        <p>It is recommended that this Government should as a matter of urgent
                            priority consider in the National Security Council possible courses of
                            action in the event of collapse in the authority of the present regime
                            in China, particularly with respect to its attitude towards support of
                            other non-Communist regimes which may be established in various parts of
                            China, and to the steps which it proposes to take under various
                            foreseeable circumstances for protection of U. S. lives, property, and
                            commercial interests in China.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>