<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="118" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Nanking Embassy Files, Lot F73—800
                            Nationalist-Communist (1948)</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister-Counselor of Embassy in China</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Clark</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-27">August 27, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Walt</hi>: Admiral Badger’s Top Secret message
                            No. 240715Z to the Chief of Naval Operations under date of August
                                24,<note n="2" xml:id="d118fn2"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_169">p. 169</ref>.</note> brings to a milestone my
                            strenuous efforts to assure compliance with the Secretary’s directive to
                            the effect that to make specific recommendations for the use of “other
                            aid” would involve responsibility on our part and possible subsequent
                            involvement which the Secretary was unwilling for us to risk. I have
                            argued with Badger and with the Ambassador until I am blue in the face
                            that we were not authorized to make any specific recommendations on the
                            expenditures of “other aid” and that to importune the Gimo or others to
                            meet the professed requirements of Fu Tso-yi or of the Garrison
                            Commander at Tsingtao would involve a responsibility which might later
                            become embarrassing. I have even gone so far as to reiterate <hi rend="italic">ad nauseum</hi> that if Fu Tso-yi received so much
                            support as result of our representations that he felt he could declare
                            his independence and decide to go it alone, we would have to blush with
                            shame and try to make our peace with the Gimo.</p>
                        <p>I am afraid my arguments which I have tried to keep on an unprejudiced
                            basis have been to no avail. As I have previously intimated, Admiral
                            Badger is desperate at the thought that he might eventually have to
                            evacuate Tsingtao and is moving heaven and earth trying to find some way
                            to avoid that possibility. As you know, the Ambassador’s heart is most
                            deeply involved in Yenching and consequently in the stability of North
                            China, and, as much as I love him and admire him, I am compelled to
                            admit that when he thinks of that situation his judgment is influenced
                            by his desire at almost any cost to avoid Communist dominance of the
                            Peiping–Tientsin area. By the nature of things, therefore, I have had
                            two strikes against me in my efforts to assure strict compliance with
                            the Secretary’s directives.</p>
                        <p>I had thought that I had been able to convince the Ambassador that we
                            could not assume the responsibility of suggesting to the Gimo any
                            specific allotment to North China and that the most we could do was to
                            point out to him information reaching us regarding the seriousness of
                            the danger to North China, the vast implications of the possibility that
                            we might have to evacuate Tsingtao, and, while at the same time
                            admitting our lack of knowledge of his overall commitments and
                            requirements, express our hope that he would do his utmost to see that
                            those areas were not permitted to fall to the Communists.</p>
                        <pb facs="0150" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/>
                        <p>I thought I had convinced the Ambassador and, in fact, his exposition of
                            those ideas to Lapham<note n="3" xml:id="d118fn3">Roger D. Lapham, Chief
                                of the China Mission of the Economic Cooperation
                                Administration.</note> was so sound I was convinced he had grasped
                            the significance of the Secretary’s policy. I knew I had not convinced
                            Admiral Badger and that he was going to continue to try to find some way
                            to make Tsingtao secure. Nevertheless it was a surprise to me, when they
                            both returned from a weekend spent at Ruling as the guests of the
                            Generalissimo and Mme. Chiang, to find that in some way the Gimo had
                            suddenly decided on the expenditure from “other aid” of around
                            $20,000,000 to meet the needs of Fu Tso-yi and those of the Garrison
                            Commander at Tsingtao. Vice Minister of National Defense Cheng Kai-min
                            had been designated by the Gimo as the one who should make known to
                            General Barr the needs in this regard, and after General Barr’s
                            agreement had been secured, the Gimo promised to instruct Wellington Koo
                            to make the necessary requisitions in Washington. Cheng Kai-min did, in
                            fact, present to General Barr a list of requirements of Fu Tso-yi to
                            equip seven armies and of the Tsingtao Garrison Commander to equip three
                            divisions. I understand that the Shangtung division is equivalent to one
                            of Fu’s armies.</p>
                        <p>Badger then came up to Nanking and after a conference with the
                            Ambassador, Barr and me, it was agreed that such things as 105 mm.
                            howitzers and heavy machine guns on Fu’s request, and flame throwers,
                            would be eliminated and that Fu would be equipped for only four rather
                            than seven armies. Badger undertook to endeavor, through the Navy
                            Department, to secure free transportation of this equipment in Navy
                            bottoms which he said were coming to the Orient empty. Also, although
                            Badger denied that he ever said so, he certainly left with the Chinese
                            the impression that there was a possibility they would be able to
                            acquire this equipment either as surplus or at procurement cost—this in
                            spite of my understanding of the ECA Act and the President’s directive
                            which would require that supplies acquired under 404–<hi rend="italic">b</hi> of the Act be paid for at replacement cost.</p>
                        <p>Barr has all along opposed this idea in principle and has further taken
                            the position that the Chinese Government, with the Gimo’s approval, had
                            already set up its priorities for acquisitions under “other aid” and a
                            couple of months or more ago instituted the procedures to acquire what
                            they needed, all of which would be thrown into a tailspin by any such
                            new priority demands at this late date. Nevertheless, in his desire not
                            to be obstructive and in view of the fact that the Gimo had apparently
                            already taken the decision, he raised no objection and went back to
                            Cheng Kai-min with the revised proposal.</p>
                        <p>According to Barr, Cheng Kai-min was adamant that Fu Tso-yi’s seven
                            armies should be supplied and that the heavy machine guns <pb facs="0151" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> should be included and equally
                            adamant that there should be ammunition for an estimated six months’
                            need. Barr figures these demands as at present formulated as totaling
                            around $41,000,000 if Badger is unable to come through with free
                            transportation or to arrange for making the supplies available at
                            procurement costs. In other words, about $1,000,000 more than remains of
                            the “other aid” for the entire army supply was to be expended solely for
                            Fu Tso-yi and Tsingtao. There would be nothing left for spare parts and
                            matériel needed in the arsenals and for many other vital needs under
                            Barr’s original arrangement. There seemed to be something wrong
                            somewhere, yet the Gimo had given his authorization and there was every
                            reason to believe that the matter would go on through.</p>
                        <p>At this stage Barr went back to see Cheng Kai-min with Ho Ying-chin and
                            took with him a draft of the cable which the Gimo was to send to
                            Wellington Koo. Covering the draft cable was a memorandum containing a
                            clear statement that the request for seven armies for Fu and three
                            divisions for Tsingtao would completely exhaust the army portion of
                            “other aid”, and a strong recommendation that in view of this fact they
                            agree to only four armies for Fu. It may have been this memorandum, or
                            it may have been something else, but in any event at this stage both
                            General Ho Ying-chin and Cheng Kai-min suddenly took the strong position
                            that they had been led to believe all along that this matériel going to
                            Fu Tso-yi and Tsingtao was not, repeat not, coming out of “other aid”,
                            but was to be acquired on some sort of barter basis in which Fu Tso-yi
                            and Tsingtao would supply the materials, the sale of which would sooner
                            or later provide foreign exchange with which the United States Armed
                            Services could be reimbursed.</p>
                        <p>I do not know, of course, what transpired in the conversations at Kuling
                            and the Ambassador is most emphatic that he had gone to great lengths
                            explaining to the Gimo that the $125,000,000 would have to be used
                            before any consideration could be given to other sources of money to pay
                            for munitions. Nevertheless, you will recall the efforts earlier this
                            year of Fu to obtain arms and ammunition through barter. At that time,
                            through Barr, we were able to arrange for the Chinese Government to send
                            Central Trust representatives into Fu’s territory to ascertain whether
                            he had materials which could be sold to bring in foreign exchange, but
                            the result was negligible. Fu either did not have the materials he
                            claimed or was unwilling to let the Central Trust representatives see
                            them.</p>
                        <p>There the matter stands for the moment. Badger is coming back to Nanking
                            next Monday and there will be another meeting with Ho Ying-chin and
                            Cheng Kai-min. I do not know what will come out of that meeting yet I
                            have been convinced all along that the <pb facs="0152" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> Chinese had no intention of letting Fu Tso-yi have
                            all the arms and ammunition listed, particularly if the money to be used
                            in payment was coming from the National Government till. It may be,
                            however, that Badger can arrange for the shipment of some supplies in
                            Navy bottoms which are coming to the Orient otherwise empty, and if so,
                            I should think such action would come within what the Secretary would
                            call feasible.</p>
                        <p>I thought you should have this background in view of the telegrams which
                            may be coming in on the subject, and should anything develop in Monday’s
                            meeting I shall write you further.</p>
                        <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lewis Clark</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>