<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="130" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.50 Recovery/9–748</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Minister-Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Clark</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-04">October 4, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Lewis</hi>: Your letter of September 7 was
                            delayed in reaching me and in the meantime events have somewhat made my
                            reply an obvious one.</p>
                        <p>By now you will have received the Department’s telegram stating that
                            payment has been authorized from the $125 million grants for
                            approximately $38 million for ordnance supplies for Fu Tso-yi and
                            Shantung. This authorization was in response to a request received <pb facs="0186" n="176" xml:id="pg_176"/> from the Chinese Military
                            Procurement Mission in which it was stated specifically that the
                            supplies were to be shipped direct to Tsingtao. It will interest you to
                            know that, in contrast to some of the previous requests for payment
                            under “other aid”, this request was made up of such immediately useful
                            items as rifles, machine guns, mortars, howitzers, pistols and
                            ammunition for these weapons and would appear more nearly to approximate
                            what the doctor ordered.</p>
                        <p>Where all of these supplies are to come from has yet to be determined by
                            the Army, which is handling the procurement, but it is expected that the
                            first portion of this shipment will not arrive in China before December
                            1. As you know, shipment to Tsingtao will be handled by the Navy at no
                            expense to the Chinese. The Department has pointed out to the Military
                            Establishment, however, the advisability of considering means other than
                            U. S. Naval vessels for transshipment from Tsingtao to Taku, although it
                            was stated that there would be no objection to having American military
                            observers accompany the shipment to insure its reaching Fu’s
                            command.</p>
                        <p>We are now well aware of the propensity of Admiral Badger for whipping
                            off telegrams indicating unreserved concurrence by the Ambassador,
                            General Barr, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, where such may not, in fact,
                            be the case, and his messages are therefore accepted by the Department
                            as representing principally the opinion of Admiral Badger until the
                            Embassy and the AAG have been heard from. Your continuing efforts to
                            keep an eye on Badger’s messages and to inform the Department where
                            divergence of opinion exists will be very helpful in this regard.</p>
                        <p>As ever,</p>
                        <closer><signed>W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Walton
                            Butterworth</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>