<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Butterworth) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4e0e83c862cd00b" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="east-asia-and-pacific">United States policy toward China</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="144"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Secretariat Files: NSC 22</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-03">November 3,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: NSC Paper on United States Policy Toward China<note
                        n="30" xml:id="d144fn30">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In his telegram (Deptel no. 1180 of August 13<note n="31" xml:id="d144fn31">
                        <ref target="frus1948v07#pg_416">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>,
                            416</ref>.</note>—Tab A) to Ambassador Stuart, the Secretary stated that
                    it was not likely that the situation would make it possible for us at this
                    juncture to formulate any rigid plans for our future policy in China. He further
                    said that developments in China were obviously entering into a period of extreme
                    flux and confusion in which it would be impossible with surety to perceive
                    clearly far in advance the pattern of things to come and in which this
                    Government plainly must preserve a maximum freedom of action. The Secretary
                    reiterated these views in his recent telegram to Ambassador Stuart on United
                    States policy toward China.<note n="32" xml:id="d144fn32">See telegram No. 1490,
                        October 26, noon, <ref target="frus1948v07#pg_512">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >vii</hi>, p. 512</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the light of the above-described statements, the NSC paper appears to plot
                    very rigidly and specifically the courses of action we should take in the
                    immediate future. For example, it states as in (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) below:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Now and for the foreseeable future, the United States should seek to
                            prevent China from becoming an adjunct of Soviet politico-military
                            power. In pursuing this aim the United States should: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Furnish limited political, economic and military assistance to
                                    those elements which at any particular time appear most likely
                                    to resist domination of China by the Communists.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0198" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/>
                <p>This recommendation, which does not appear to take into consideration the
                    possible effectiveness of resistance by anti-Communist elements in China, is
                    repeated in two other instances in the NSC paper in slightly varying form. One
                    recommendation suggests that the United States should immediately make plans and
                    preparations to exploit probable developments through support of the remaining
                    anti-Communist forces in the event of a National Government collapse or the
                    formation of a coalition with the Communists. The other recommendation suggests
                    that the United States furnish assistance to such anti-Communist regional
                    regimes as hold out promise of helping prevent Communist domination of China in
                    the event of the National Government’s collapse or its coalition with the
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>In this general connection, Ambassador Stuart stated in his telegram no. 2003 of
                    October 26<note n="33" xml:id="d144fn33">
                        <ref target="frus1948v07#pg_518">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p.
                            518</ref>.</note> (Tab B): <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Any direct military aid to resistance groups on theory that we are
                            fighting Communism all over the world would seem to me unwise. It could
                            only delay their ultimate liquidation and would meanwhile arouse
                            increased anti-American sentiment and expose our nationals in coalition
                            territory to danger. Transportation and other difficulties in reaching
                            these resistance leaders and ensuring proper use of our supplies would
                            be enormous. But chief objection would perhaps be that this is one of
                            negative or vacillating courses which we should at all costs avoid.</p>
                        <p>“It would seem to me no less undesirable to make any premature
                            announcements as to our intentions or our general opinion of Communism
                            that would endanger our existing national interests in China or
                            embarrass us in future. Whatever influence we may want to exert will be
                            increased if our attitude toward new regime is undefined and
                            flexible.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is certainly true that we should, as stated in the NSC paper, seek to prevent
                    China from becoming an adjunct of Soviet politico-military power and the only
                    question is one of the tactics to be followed. While plans and preparations
                    should be made against all eventualities, we should not expect that the United
                    States will be able during the immediate future to exert a decisive influence on
                    developments throughout the whole of China. The above-described courses of
                    action recommended in the NSC paper seem desirable, but they should be subject
                    to approval in the light primarily of our national interests and the then
                    existing circumstances. The fact that a faction in China is anti-Communist is
                    not in itself sufficient. While it may be desirable to support one or more
                    anti-Communist factions should the National Government collapse, we should take
                    particular care to avoid so committing ourselves to a course of action or of
                    becoming so deeply involved in the Chinese scene that we succeed only in
                    prolonging an unsuccessful <pb facs="0199" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> civil war
                    and in thus further weakening the position of anti-Communist elements in China
                    which might eventually provide the basis for effective indigenous resistance to
                    complete Communist domination of that country. Unsuccessful efforts to support
                    remaining anti-Communist elements would be costly in terms of U. S. prestige and
                    expenditure of further U. S. funds.</p>
                <p>In summary, it seems desirable that the recommended courses of action following a
                    possible collapse of the National Government be clearly qualified by
                    considerations of our national interests and the circumstances existing at that
                    time.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. W[<hi rend="smallcaps">alton</hi>] B[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >utterworth</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
