<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary of
                        State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d255</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">255</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-12-27T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="255" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/12–2748</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary of
                        State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-12-27">December 27,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table rend="width: 50%" rendition="#center-block">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Present:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Lovett</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Madame Chiang</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>General Carter</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Madame Chiang called on me in the Secretary’s office at 3 p.m. today at her
                    request. She said that she had been waiting almost four weeks for decisions of
                    this Government, under the impression that General Marshall had the final word.
                    Her conversations with President Truman and me had seemed to corroborate this.
                    She had seen General Marshall this morning at 11:30 and he had explained that he
                    had not been officiating for three weeks and was not aware of current events
                    either here or in China. She repeated her conversation with the General
                    substantially along the lines of the attached memorandum<note n="45" xml:id="d255fn45">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_302">p. 302</ref>.</note>
                    dictated by General Marshall after his interview. (Also see Carter’s memorandum
                    of subsequent events, also attached<note n="46" xml:id="d255fn46">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>). She showed me the message she had
                    received this morning from the Generalissimo (attached),<note n="47" xml:id="d255fn47">Not printed.</note> and went into some detail supporting
                    the Generalissimo’s position as explained in his cable.</p>
                <p>I took occasion to explain to the Madame that under no conditions could the
                    United States be placed in the position of deciding for the Generalissimo
                    whether or not he would step aside, that this was a decision for the
                    Generalissimo alone to make and was purely and simply a Chinese problem, that
                    nothing we might say or do or not say or not do should have any bearing on the
                    decision. I re-emphasized this point to make it quite clear to the Madame that
                    we were not involved in any way in this particular problem.</p>
                <p>A lengthy discussion ensued as to whether or not the President’s letter to the
                    Generalissimo would serve the purpose of a statement requested <pb facs="0316" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/> by the Chinese. Madame quite obviously did not
                    want this letter released, but said she would again query the Generalissimo on
                    the matter. I explained to her the reasons why we could not appropriately issue
                    a new statement at this time and explained that both the President and General
                    Marshall have already made this clear to her.</p>
                <p>She then handed me the three point paper attached,<note n="48" xml:id="d255fn48">Not printed. The three points in this paper were a request for a statement
                        from the United States Government that it would give such moral and material
                        support as was possible to China in its struggle against Communism; that a
                        representative of high rank should go to China to assist in organizing and
                        training the Chinese Army, and to coordinate American policy with the aid
                        program in Europe; and that some way should be found to continue to supply
                        military equipment until Congress should pass a resolution to continue aid
                        to China.</note> stating that General Marshall had asked her to put in
                    writing quite clearly exactly what she wanted. I answered the three requests by
                    referring specifically to those portions of the President’s message which
                    answered them.</p>
                <p>At the end of an hour and 20 minutes the Madame left with the following
                    agreements: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>She would get the Generalissimo’s latest reaction to release, either
                            here or in China, of the President’s letter.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>I would discuss with the President the advisability of releasing the
                            letter here and again take up the question of a new statement.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>I would discuss with the President once more Madame Chiang’s urgent
                            plea for a high ranking military adviser to go to China.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I furnished Madame a copy of the President’s letter to the Generalissimo and
                    directed General Carter to furnish her excerpts from press conferences of the
                    last month.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R[<hi rend="smallcaps">obert</hi>] A. L[<hi rend="smallcaps">ovett</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
