<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs ( (Butterworth) ) to the
                    Minister-Coumelor of Embassy in China ( (Clark))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="273"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/10–2548</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Minister-Coumelor of Embassy in China</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clark</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-25">October 25,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Lewis</hi>: The Tsingtao situation continues a
                    pressing problem in the solution of which it is exceedingly difficult to obtain
                    agreement <pb facs="0340" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/> among the concerned agencies
                    of the Government, In order that you may be <hi rend="italic">au courant</hi> of
                    developments here in regard to this problem, I am enclosing copies of the
                    following documents: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Letter from the Acting Secretary to the Executive Secretary of the
                            National Security Council dated October 14, 1948;<note n="41"
                                xml:id="d273fn41">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_326">p.
                                326</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Memorandum from the Director of the Joint Staff to the Acting
                            Secretary dated October 19<note n="42" xml:id="d273fn42">Not
                                printed.</note> enclosing a copy of a memorandum for the Joint
                            Chiefs of Staff;</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Memorandum from the Acting Secretary dated October 19<note n="43"
                                xml:id="d273fn43">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> in reply to the memorandum
                            listed immediately above.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>As you will note from the enclosure listed under (2), the President, following a
                    conversation with Messrs. Hoffman<note n="44" xml:id="d273fn44">Paul G. Hoffman,
                        Administrator of the Economic Cooperation Administration.</note> and
                        Lapham,<note n="45" xml:id="d273fn45">Roger D. Lapham, Chief, China Mission,
                        Economic Cooperation Administration.</note> sent a memorandum on October 18
                    to the Secretary of Defense suggesting that withdrawal from Tsingtao not take
                    place at this time and that aid to North China be expedited, The Acting
                    Secretary’s letter to the NSC was, of course, written before the President’s
                    memorandum to Secretary Forrestal. However, after reviewing the letter we
                    believe the steps recommended therein to be consonant with the President’s
                    memorandum. At yesterday’s meeting of the NSC it was agreed to defer
                    consideration of the letter until the meeting on November 4.</p>
                <p>We have also taken the view, as you will note from the enclosure listed under
                    (3), that the existing directive from the JCS to Admiral Badger instructing him
                    to evacuate U. S. forces in the event of a Communist attack and should the
                    situation so require is not in conflict with the President’s memorandum. We have
                    not been informed yet of the action, if any, taken by the JCS at their meeting
                    on October 20.</p>
                <p>It is evident from the foregoing that the Tsingtao problem is still very much up
                    in the air. Our immediate objective is to have Admiral Badger’s command placed
                    on a mobile basis by evacuating Navy and Marine dependents and liquidating,
                    insofar as possible, shore installations. We consider this a preliminary step
                    necessary either to meet an emergency or to carry out whatever policy decision
                    may be made regarding the retention of U. S. forces in Tsingtao.</p>
                <p>As ever,</p>
                <closer>[<signed>W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Walton Butterworth</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P. S. Since writing the foregoing, we have been informed that the JCS on
                        October 23 cancelled the directive to Admiral Badger mentioned in the
                        penultimate paragraph above and (1) authorized him to use his forces for the
                        protection of United States interests and for <pb facs="0341" n="331"
                            xml:id="pg_331"/> the maintenance of order in connection therewith,
                        within the Tsingtao perimeter, (2) instructed him to be prepared for prompt
                        evacuation of dependents, U. S. nationals and other nationals from Tsingtao
                        when in his judgment the situation so requires, (3) instructed him to be
                        prepared to evacuate U. S. Forces on orders of the JCS and (4) requested him
                        to keep the appropriate authorities informed of any change in the situation
                        and of any action taken pursuant to the directive.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
