<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Cabot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d371</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">371</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-11-12T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-11-12T02:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-12T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-12T02:00:00-05:00" n="371" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d371">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5151/11–1248: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-12T15:00:00+08:00">November 12, 1948—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 12—8:59 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2395. For State and Treasury from Casaday. ReContel 2287 to Department, repeated
                    Nanking as 1731, November 2.</p>
                <pb facs="0441" n="431" xml:id="pg_431"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Formal confirmation our understanding never received from Central Bank
                        owing partly Cabinet crisis and continued illness both Governor O. K. Yui
                        and Acting Governor S. Y. Liu. However, on basis verbal confirmation given
                        Merchant and Casaday by S. Y. Liu just before he became ill, we had been
                        negotiating special rates for Army, Navy and State Department posts and
                        actual purchases and remission of funds have taken place as follows:</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows account of specific exchange rates obtained and related
                    comments.]</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>On November 11 Consulate General Shanghai and all outposts received
                        authorization from Embassy to be exercised at discretion local head of post,
                        to acquire local currency requirements by sale US currency or drafts on best
                        terms available or to pay individual, including alien staff, in US currency.
                        Casaday instructed urgently inform S. Y. Liu or other responsible Central
                        Bank official this decision. Since S. Y. Liu still sick, Casaday verbally
                        informed Albert Shao afternoon November 11 who said he would inform S. Y.
                        Liu at once.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>Shao apparently not surprised nor displeased at news. He said in fact such
                        arrangement probably less embarrassing to Central Bank than prior
                        arrangement which had caused Central Bank to become besieged with requests
                        for “special” deals by other organizations, especially various United
                        Nations groups, missionary organizations and other foreign Consulates and
                        Embassies. Albert Shao said the Central Bank could truthfully say it did not
                        have special deal with anybody and could disclaim any knowledge how American
                        Government agencies acquiring their funds. He also said that in event
                        individuals were paid in US currency perhaps Central Bank should take some
                        step stop recent arrests of US agency employees or to secure their quick
                        release if arrested.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>However, Albert Shao said nothing about new official rate of 20 to 1
                        announced later last night and carried in press this morning. Under new
                        regulations no longer illegal for people possess gold, silver and foreign
                        currencies although still illegal to “deal” in same. (Summary new
                        regulations being forwarded separately.<note n="6" xml:id="d371fn6">See
                            telegram No. 2394, <ref target="#pg_428">p. 428</ref>.</note>) Possibly
                        Shao supposed US Government agencies would automatically support new
                        official rate as we have done in similar circumstances in past but he said
                        nothing about it and tone of conversation was otherwise.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Consulate General and Embassy assuming in absence instructions from
                        Department to contrary, authorization granted in Embtel 1070 to Shanghai
                        November 10<note n="7" xml:id="d371fn7">Not found in Department
                            files.</note> and Embcirtel same date<note n="8" xml:id="d371fn8">Not
                            printed.</note> still holds good. <hi rend="italic">A priori</hi> no
                        reason to suppose new rate, which definitely unrealistic at <pb facs="0442" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/> outset, will measurably reduce present chaos
                        or for long retard process economic deterioration. Consequently, feel
                        discretion given posts in this matter no less essential merely because of
                        new official rate 2 days ago when authorization granted.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Uncertain whether verbal notification of authorization to make local
                        arrangements given Central Bank yesterday by Casaday will be viewed by
                        Central Bank as automatic abrogation of our October 29 understanding.
                        Casaday assumes his notification likely to be so viewed by Central Bank
                        which would mean Army, Navy and USEFC stuck with 20 to 1. Decided not press
                        Central Bank today for its views on this matter nor on question in item
                        number 3 above.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Understand Army, Navy requesting authority from Washington to make own
                        arrangements locally similar that just issued by Embassy to State Department
                        posts. No such possibility for USEFC, however, and seems likely we must
                        endeavor continue or reestablish some specially negotiated arrangement for
                        that organization.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Sent Department 2395, repeated Nanking 1814. [Casaday.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
