<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-15T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-15T12:00:00-05:00" n="432" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d432">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.50 Recovery/5–1348: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-15T13:00:00-04:00">May 15, 1948—1
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>738. Dept fully agrees observations Embtel 843 May 10 and assumes Emb
                            satisfied agreement along lines Deptel 695 May 7<note n="59" xml:id="d432fn59">Not printed.</note> can be negotiated beginning
                            June 1 without undue difficulty to allow signature prior July 3.
                            Adequate time negotiation China agreement must be allowed. Majority
                            European drafts were presented yesterday for negotiation. Procedure
                            indicated Embtel 864 May 13 would appear provide only 2 weeks
                            negotiation if ratification requiring 2 weeks must be obtained by Jul 3
                            to make agreement effective by that date. Efforts being made to reach
                            prompt US govt agreement China draft and text will be sent Emb<note n="60" xml:id="d432fn60">See telegram No. 774, May 24, 8 p.m., <ref target="#pg_524">p. 524</ref>.</note> immediately thereafter in
                            accordance comment Art 11, Embtel 850, May 11.<note n="61" xml:id="d432fn61">Not printed; this telegram indicated the
                                desirability of placing a draft agreement in the hands of the
                                Chinese in the reasonably near future because of the time required
                                for translating and checking the Chinese text (893.50
                                Recovery/5–1148).</note> Request Emb’s further comments re time
                            factor.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, Dept suggests Emb initiate corollary discussions if not
                            already undertaken, giving special emphasis objectives mentioned <pb facs="0530" n="520" xml:id="pg_520"/> second para Deptel 694 May 7
                            with highest level ChiGovt officials, preferably including Premier,
                            Chang Kia-ngau,<note n="62" xml:id="d432fn62">Governor of the Central
                                Bank of China.</note> FonMin and other responsible officials at
                            appropriate stages discussion. Ambassador should emphasize to Gimo, when
                            appropriate, significance discussions and importance Chinese informal
                            and formal undertakings and concrete implementations thereof from point
                            of view U.S., and should ensure Gimo informed more important points
                            discussion and Chinese undertakings. Would it not be desirable also keep
                            in touch Li Tsungjen<note n="63" xml:id="d432fn63">Vice-President-elect
                                of the Republic of China.</note> for same purpose?</p>
                        <p>Following comments re Section II Embtel 669, Apr 14: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Dept believes opening Hankow foreign shipping, even
                                    temporarily, should be emphasized as in Chinese economic self
                                    interest. However, if Chinese unwilling to go whole hog, Emb
                                    should certainly press for permission U. S. aid cargoes unload
                                    river ports and carry export cargo from such ports of discharge
                                    as necessary efficient implementation aid program and as test
                                    case general issue.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Unnecessary. Protocol already signed.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Unnecessary, in view adequate commitment this regard obtained
                                    minutes negotiation commercial treaty, in GATT and ITO,<note n="64" xml:id="d432fn64">International Trade
                                        Organization.</note> and proposed Art. IV agreement Deptel
                                    695, May 7.<note n="65" xml:id="d432fn65">Not
                                    printed.</note></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Dept’s tentative view is that FonMin’s note of Nov. 27,
                                        1947<note n="66" xml:id="d432fn66">Not printed; for summary
                                        of note, see Embassy’s telegram No. 2325, December 2, 1947,
                                        3 p.m., <ref target="frus1947v07#pg_1382"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p. 1382</ref>.</note>
                                    this subject covers matter adequately if Chinese intentions as
                                    stated note carried out. Dept may make additional comment this
                                    regard after further consideration here.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Dept believes emphasis this field should follow lines
                                    indicated below. Reference “maximum freedom in commercial
                                    interchanges” raises a number of unresolved problems and appears
                                    indicate U. S. favors relaxation Chinese trade and exchange
                                    controls which, in view continuing emergency, cannot, in
                                    general, be considered practical possibility.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In addition point 1 above, following points intended indicate general
                            scope and occasional substance corollary discussions, subject Emb’s
                            discretion. Dept believes Emb in better position elaborate subjects
                            appropriate for discussion. Emb should encourage Chinese set forth their
                            own proposals and indicate concrete application in first instance,
                            reserving Emb’s comments for emphasis or addition when significant
                            points neglected by Chinese. In general, Dept believes Emb should stress
                            general character problems and measures required, but should treat
                            concrete and specific application as matter for Chinese judgment and
                            responsibility, at same time pressing for informal Chinese undertakings
                            of specific character. Dept has not included <pb facs="0531" n="521" xml:id="pg_521"/> reference below to certain suggestions dealt with
                            by Chinese technical mission here, discussion of which might be taken by
                            Chinese to imply assistance not now anticipated by U. S., such as
                            currency reform or control over private assets in U. S. Question
                            undertaking re assets in U. S. should be avoided pending further study
                            here. Also, reconstruction projects should not be included corollary
                            discussion regarding self-help measures since projects are dependent
                            primarily upon U. S. aid and will receive appropriate attention in due
                            course.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Government Expenditures</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Establishment of budgetary control and standardization accounting,
                                based on short-term projections, in hands of central fiscal
                                authority with power to make allocations for all expenditures and
                                with sufficient political strength to resist demands for unnecessary
                                expenditures.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Elimination of non-productive expenditures not essential to
                                efficient civil administration and prosecution of war, such as
                                padded army rolls, troops garrisoned in sheltered areas, Kmt<note n="67" xml:id="d432fn67">Kuomintang (Nationalist Party).</note>
                                activities and other purposes for which Emb can find supporting
                                examples.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Govt Receipts</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Emphasis on administrative improvements taxation.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Expand measures to protect tax revenue from currency depreciation,
                                such as use multiplication factors, ad valorem taxes and taxation at
                                source.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Expedite sale of Govt assets which could be operated more
                                appropriately and efficiently by private enterprise.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Civil and Military
                                Administration</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Adoption or continuation of realistic cost of living index as
                                standard for ensuring more adequate pay for civil employees and
                                soldiers.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Drastic and impartial weeding out of civil and military officials
                                guilty of gross inefficiency or corruption.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Conscientious reduction of civil and military rolls to eliminate
                                unnecessary employees, combining this with arrangements for
                                retraining severed employees to fit into projects or other
                                productive activity.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Coordination and elimination of duplication in civil and military
                                agencies.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Distribution of staple
                                commodities</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Emphasis, where practicable in Emb’s views, on improved administration
                            of, or extension of, distribution controls. Explain essentiality of
                            applying controls or incentives to maintain and expand flow of consumer
                            goods into rural areas as incentive production and movement agricultural
                            goods for urban consumption and export.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Banking and credit</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Adjustment of banking system in order: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>to give Central Bank complete control of banking and credit
                                        <pb facs="0532" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/> policy for purpose
                                    of checking speculation and ensuring more adequate credit for
                                    essential productive economic activity.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>to establish clearer demarcation between functions of
                                    government and private banks and to prevent favoritism to
                                    government banks.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>to eliminate uneconomic banking operations, such as the
                                    Central Cooperative Bank.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">6. <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Improvement</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Emphasis on implementation of recommendations of Joint U. S.–China
                            Agricultural Mission, with special reference land reform policy, where
                            desirable in judgment Emb.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">7. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Trade and its
                            Controls</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Emphasis on: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Administrative improvements in import and exchange controls,
                                    including coordination throughout China of control
                                    procedures.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>More realistic exchange rate policies.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Adequate credit for production and marketing of export
                                    goods.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Improvement in quality and standardization of export
                                    goods.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">8. <hi rend="italic">Encouragement to private
                                enterprise</hi>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Clarification, by action as well as by statement, of fields open
                                to private enterprise without governmental intrusion.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Elimination of special privilege in foreign trade and domestic
                                enterprise if Emb feels it can appropriately press this
                                point.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>