<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d692</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">692</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="692" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d692">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">846G.79693/6–3048</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 288</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-30">June 30,
                            1948</date>.<lb/>[Received July 14.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Ambassador has the honor to enclose for the information of the Department of
                    State a copy of a memorandum of conversation which took place on June 24, 1948
                    between Mr. Quentin Roosevelt of the China Aviation Corporation and Mr. Jarvis,
                    the Civil Air Attaché, on the subject of United States air carrier movement of
                    Shanghai–Hong Kong traffic. The Department will observe that Minister of
                    Communications Yu Ta-wei informed Messrs. Roosevelt and Bond of Pan American
                    Airways that he felt that China was “licked” on the Shanghai–Hong Kong question,
                    and that China would likely not take any further action in the matter until the
                    present agreement expired.</p>
                <p>The Embassy would like to suggest that this memorandum not be discussed with Pan
                    American Airways in order to insure that source will in future feel that such
                    matters can be freely discussed with Embassy.</p>
                <pb facs="0809" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Civil Air Attaché in
                            China</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jarvis</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-24">June 24,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. Roosevelt during the course of a conversation on another matter,
                        volunteered that he and Mr. Bond of Pan American Airways had called on
                        Minister of Communications Yu Ta-wei, and during the course of their
                        discussion with him, he mentioned the “Shanghai–Hong Kong consultation with
                        the Americans.” According to Mr. Roosevelt, Minister Yui stated that, during
                        the course of the discussions prior to the conclusion of the Sino-United
                        States air agreement, an understanding had been reached between the Chinese
                        negotiators and Col. Powell of the U. S. under which the U. S. agreed to
                        refrain from the movement of Shanghai–Hong Kong traffic. Minister Yu
                        informed Mr. Roosevelt that in the event he was responsible for any further
                        treaty negotiations with the Americans, he intended to have a battery of one
                        hundred lawyers available to check each word in the document.</p>
                    <p>Apparently Minister Yu then asked Messrs. Roosevelt and Bond whether there
                        was a possibility that some arrangement could be made whereby, through an
                        exchange of letters between carriers, Pan American Airways would voluntarily
                        refrain from movement of traffic on this segment of its route. According to
                        Mr. Roosevelt, he and Mr. Bond informed Minister Yu that the matter did not
                        rest with Pan American, but was one which had to be discussed solely between
                        the two Governments. Mr. Roosevelt indicated that he and Mr. Bond then
                        informed Minister Yu that Pan American Airways was not actively promoting
                        competition for CNAC on this route and had in fact positively refrained from
                        such activity. Mr. Jarvis gathered the impression that Messrs. Eoosevelt and
                        Bond left with Minister Yu the thought that PAA would voluntarily refrain
                        from movement of this traffic if the U. S. Government would not
                        intervene.</p>
                    <p>At this point, Mr. Roosevelt queried Mr. Jarvis as to the possible reaction
                        of the U. S. Government in the event PAA suggested that it, by an exchange
                        of letters, agree to refrain from the carriage of this traffic and at the
                        same time pointed out the insignificant amount of traffic handled by PAA on
                        this segment due to foreign exchange difficulties. Mr. Jarvis informed him
                        that he was sure that the U. S. Government would not agree to such a
                        suggestion; that the U. S. position vis-à-vis the Shanghai-Hong Kong
                        question was firm. Mr. Jarvis went on to say that not only the rights of PAA
                        were involved in this case, but also those of such other U. S. carriers as
                        might be certificated to operate on this route.</p>
                    <pb facs="0810" n="800" xml:id="pg_800"/>
                    <p>Mr. Roosevelt then mentioned that Minister Yu had informed him that he did
                        not wish to put any pressure on the CNAC request to operate to Tokyo, nor
                        did he wish Col. C. Y. Liu, of CNAC, to do so, as in the event he decided to
                        take further action on the Shanghai–Hong Kong question, he did not wish the
                        Americans to be in a position to point to the fact that CNAC had been
                        permitted to go through Tokyo in justification U. S. operation into Hong
                        Kong. Mr. Jarvis informed Mr. Roosevelt that no attempt had been made to
                        “tie-up” Tokyo with the Shanghai–Hong Kong question, as the U. S. believed
                        that the Shanghai–Hong Kong case would stand on its merits.</p>
                    <p>At the close of the discussion, Mr. Roosevelt said that Minister Yu stated
                        that he felt China was “licked” on the Shanghai–Hong Kong question and that
                        China would likely not take any further action on the matter until the
                        present agreement expired.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
