<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Geo. H. Yeaman to to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1870</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1870-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1870-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1870-08-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1870-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">No. 15.</note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Geo. H. Yeaman</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Fish</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 253.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic"> Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-08-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 5, 1870</date>. (Received August 24,
                        1870.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Touching the subject of the neutrality of Denmark
                    in the present contest between Prussia and France, two events have lately
                    occurred of some interest. This government has forbidden the further exportation
                    of horses, an order which the government is entirely competent to make, simply
                    as a regulation of commerce; but which is done notoriously in view of the
                    possible exigencies of the present situation.</p>
                <p>The other fact is the arrival at this capital, a few days ago, of the Marquis de
                    Cadore, late French minister at Munich, which capital he quitted when Bavaria so
                    promptly espoused the cause of Germany, and who, it is generally stated and
                    credited, comes here as an envoy extraordinary on special mission to this
                    government.</p>
                <p>Of course, such a visit at this juncture excites very great interest and
                    curiosity in political and diplomatic circles. But very little, indeed nothing,
                    has as yet transpired as to the object of his visit. There can be no reasonable
                    doubt that he left Paris for an important purpose, and, probably, with definite
                    instructions. But from all that can be learned here he seems to have said and
                    done so little as to give rise to the suggestion that, upon arriving here, he
                    found the programme altered or modified. The Danish declaration of neutrality
                    could scarcely have been officially, perhaps not publicly, known at Paris when
                    he left; he traveled all the way from Cherbourg by sea, and by the time he
                    arrived <pb facs="0097" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/> here, the publication by Count
                    Bismarck of the diplomatic proposals of France so seriously affecting Belgium,
                    and even the “Duchy” question pending between Denmark and Prussia, may have
                    suggested to the cabinet of Paris that an earnest and successful effort by
                    France to drag Denmark into the war might cost too much in the form of other and
                    adverse complications. It might draw both England and Belgium into the war, and
                    give still greater cause of dissatisfaction to Russia. Of course, as an
                    explanation of the Marquis Cadore’s apparent inactivity, this is all
                    speculation; but it has a certain air of plausibility about it. While I deem it
                    quite certain that he came here for a definite and important purpose, I have
                    reason to doubt whether he is formally and officially accredited to this
                    government, and I know that up to yesterday evening he was not so regarded by
                    it, and had not established official relations with it. The subject has become
                    an interesting and important puzzle to the diplomatic corps, and the more so as
                    most of my colleagues are actively pressing upon this government the wishes of
                    their own governments that Denmark should remain neutral. There is somewhat less
                    confidence felt that this attitude will be preserved than there was at the date
                    of my last advices upon that subject.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. H. YEAMAN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
