<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1870</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1870-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1870-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recSGyPwUYTaLPhEi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038182"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Consular service</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="reci0GubnZFV3spJe" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011003316"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Infant</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107724"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Protestants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1870-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1870-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="272"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">No. 273.</note>
                <note rend="inline">NATURALIZATION LAW.</note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Fish</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 333.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic"> London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-05-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 14, 1870</date>. (Received May
                        26.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> * * * I beg to refer you to * * * the
                    naturalization bill which has just received the royal assent, and a copy of
                    which accompanies this dispatch.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">An Act</hi> to amend the law relating to the legal
                        condition of aliens and British subjects, [12th May, 1870.]</head>
                    <p>Whereas it is expedient to amend the law relating to the legal condition of
                        aliens and British subjects:</p>
                    <p>Be it enacted by the Queen’s most excellent Majesty, by and with the advice
                        and consent of the lords spiritual and temporal, and commons, in this
                        present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>First. This act may be cited for all purposes as “The Naturalization Act,
                        1870.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0469" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">status of aliens in the united kingdom.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Second. Real and personal property of every description maybe taken,
                        acquired, held, and disposed of by an alien in the same manner in all
                        respects as by a natural-born British subject; and a title to real and
                        personal property of every description may be derived through, from, or in
                        succession to an alien, in the same manner in all respects as through, from,
                        or in succession to a natural-bom British subject: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Provided</hi>, 1. That, this section shall not confer any right on an
                        alien to hold real property situate out of the united kingdom, and shall not
                        qualify an alien for any office or for any municipal, parliamentary, or
                        other franchise. 2. That this section shall not entitle an alien to any
                        right or privilege as a British subject, except such rights and privileges
                        in respect of property as are hereby expressly given to him. 3. That this
                        section shall not affect any estate or interest in real or personal property
                        to which any person has or may become entitled, either mediately or
                        immediately, in possession or expectancy, in pursuance of any disposition
                        made before the passing of this act, or in pursuance of any devolution by
                        law on the death of any person dying before the passing of this act.</p>
                    <p>Third. Where her Majesty has entered into a convention with any foreign state
                        to the effect that the subjects or citizens of that state who have been
                        naturalized as British subjects may divest themselves of their status as
                        such subjects, it shall be lawful for her Majesty, by order in council, to
                        declare that such convention has been entered into by her Majesty; and from
                        and after the date of such order in council, any person being originally a
                        subject or citizen of the state referred to in such order, who has been
                        naturalized as a British subject, may, within such limit of time as may be
                        provided in the convention, make a declaration of alienage, and from and
                        after the date of his so making such declaration such person shall be
                        regarded as an alien, and as a subject of the state to which he originally
                        belonged, as aforesaid.</p>
                    <p>A declaration of alienage may be made as follows, that is to say: If the
                        declarant be in the United Kingdom, in the presence of any justice of the
                        peace; if elsewhere in her Majesty’s dominions, in the presence of any judge
                        of any court of civil or criminal jurisdiction, of any justice of the peace,
                        or of any other officer for the time being authorized by law in the place in
                        which the declarant is to administer an oath for any judicial or other legal
                        purpose. If out of her Majesty’s dominions, in the presence of any officer
                        in the diplomatic or consular service of her Majesty.</p>
                    <p>Fourth. Any person who by reason of his having been bom within the dominions
                        of her Majesty is a natural-born subject, but who also at the time of his
                        birth became, under the law of any foreign state, a subject of such state,
                        and is still such subject, may, if of full age and not under any disability,
                        make a declaration of alienage in-manner aforesaid, and from and after the
                        making of such declaration of alienage such person shall cease to be a
                        British subject. Any person who is born out of her Majesty’s dominions of a
                        father being a British subject may, if of full age, and not under any
                        disability, make a declaration of alienage in manner aforesaid, and from and
                        after the making of such declaration shall cease to be a British
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>Fifth. From and after the passing of this act, an alien shall not be entitled
                        to be tried by a jury <hi rend="italic">de medietate linguœ,</hi> but shall
                        be triable in the same manner as if he were a natural-born subject.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">expatriation.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Sixth. Any British subject who has at any time before, or may at any time
                        after the passing of this act, when in any foreign state and not under any
                        disability voluntarily become naturalized in such state, shall from and
                        after the time of his so having become naturalized in such foreign state, be
                        deemed to have ceased to be a British subject and be regarded as an alien:
                            <hi rend="italic">Provided</hi>, 1. That where any British subject has,
                        before the passing of this act, voluntarily become naturalized in a foreign
                        state, and yet is desirous of remaining a British subject, he may, at any
                        time within two years after the passing of this act, make a declaration that
                        he is desirous of remaining a British subject, and upon such declaration
                        hereinafter referred to as a declaration of British nationality being made,
                        and upon his taking the oath of allegiance, the declarant shall be deemed to
                        be and to have been continually a British subject; with this qualification,
                        that he shall not, when within the limits of the foreign state in which he
                        has been naturalized, be deemed to be a British subject, unless he has
                        ceased to be a subject of that state in pursuance of the laws thereof, or in
                        pursuance of a treaty to that effect. 2. A declaration of British
                        nationality may be made, and the oath of allegiance be taken as follows,
                        that is to say, if the declarant be in the United Kingdom in the presence of
                        a justice of the peace; if elsewhere in her Majesty’s dominions, in the
                        presence of any judge of any court of civil or criminal jurisdiction, of any
                        justice of the peace, or of any other officer for the time being authorized
                        by law in the place in which the declarant is to administer an oath for any
                        judicial or other legal purpose. If out of her Majesty’s dominions, in the
                        presence of any officer in the diplomatic or consular service of her
                        Majesty.</p>
                    <pb facs="0470" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">naturalization and resumption of british
                            nationality.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Seventh. An alien who, within such limited time before making the application
                        hereinafter mentioned as may be allowed by one of her Majesty’s principal
                        secretaries of state, either by general order or on any special occasion,
                        has resided in the United Kingdom for a term of not less than five years, or
                        has been in the service of the Crown for a term of not less than five years,
                        and intends, when naturalized, either to reside in the United Kingdom, or to
                        serve under the crown, may apply to one of her Majesty’s principal
                        secretaries of state for a certificate of naturalization.</p>
                    <p>The applicant shall adduce in support of his application such evidence of his
                        residence or service, and intention to reside or serve, as such secretary of
                        state may require. The said secretary of state, if satisfied with the
                        evidence adduced, shall take the case of the applicant into consideration,
                        and may, with or without assigning any reason, give or withhold a
                        certificate as he thinks most conducive to the public good, and no appeal
                        shall lie from his decision, but such certificate shall not take effect
                        until the applicant has taken the oath of allegiance.</p>
                    <p>An alien to whom a certificate of naturalization is granted shall, in the
                        United Kingdom, be entitled to all political and other rights, powers, and
                        privileges, and be subject to all obligations to which a natural-born
                        British subject is entitled or subject in the United Kingdom, with this
                        qualification, that he shall not, when within the limits of the foreign
                        state of which he was a subject previously to obtaining his certificate of
                        naturalization, be deemed to be a British subject unless he has ceased to be
                        a subject of that state in pursuance of the laws thereof, or in pursuance of
                        a treaty to that effect.</p>
                    <p>The said secretary of state may, in manner aforesaid, grant a special
                        certificate of naturalization to any person with respect to whose
                        nationality as a British subject a doubt exists, and he may specify in such
                        certificate that the grant thereof is made for the purpose of quieting
                        doubts as to the right of such person to be a British subject, and the grant
                        of such special certificate shall not be deemed to be any admission that the
                        person to whom it was granted was not previously a British subject.</p>
                    <p>An alien who has been naturalized previously to the passing of this act may
                        apply to the secretary of state for a certificate of naturalization under
                        this act, and it shall be lawful for the said secretary of state to grant
                        such certificate to such naturalized alien upon the same terms and subject
                        to the same conditions in and upon which such certificate might have been
                        granted if such alien had not been previously naturalized in the United
                        Kingdom.</p>
                    <p>Eighth. A natural-born British subject who has become an alien in pursuance
                        of this act, and is in this act referred to as a statutory alien may, on
                        performing the same conditions and adducing the same evidence as is required
                        in the case of an alien applying for a certificate of nationality, apply to
                        one of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state for a certificate
                        hereinafter referred to as a certificate of readmission to British
                        nationality, readmitting him to the status of a British subject. The said
                        secretary of state shall have the same discretion as to the giving or
                        withholding of the certificate as in the case of a certificate of
                        naturalization, and an oath of alligiance shall in like manner be required
                        previously to the issuing of the certificate.</p>
                    <p>A statutory alien to whom a certificate of readmission to British nationality
                        has been granted shall, from the date of the certificate of readmission, but
                        not in respect of any previous transaction, resume his position as a British
                        subject; with this qualification, that within the limits of the foreign
                        state of which he became a subject, he shall not be deemed to be a British
                        subject, unless he has ceased to be a subject of that foreign state
                        according to the laws thereof, or in pursuance of a treaty to that
                        effect.</p>
                    <p>The jurisdiction by this act conferred on the secretary of state in the
                        United Kingdom in respect of the grant of a certificate of readmission to
                        British nationality, in the case of any statutory alien being in any British
                        possession, may be exercised by the governor of such possession; and
                        residence in such possession shall, in the case of such person, be deemed
                        equivalent to residence in the United Kingdom.</p>
                    <p>Ninth. The oath in this act referred to as the oath of allegiance shall be in
                        the form following, that is to say:</p>
                    <p>“I, — — ——, do swear that I will be faithful and bear true allegiance to her
                        Majesty Queen Victoria, her heirs, and successors, according to law. So help
                        me God.”</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">national status of married women and infant
                            children.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Tenth. The following enactments shall be made with respect to the national
                        status of women and children: 1. A married woman shall be deemed to be a
                        subject of the state of which her husband is for the time being a subject.
                        2. A widow being a natural-born British subject, who has become an alien by
                        or in consequence of her marriage, shall be deemed to be a statutory alien,
                        and may as such at any time during widowhood obtain a certificate of
                        readmission to British nationality in manner provided by this act. 3. Where
                        the father being a British subject, or the mother being a British subject
                        and a widow, becomes an alien in pursuance of this act, every child of <pb
                            facs="0471" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/> such father or mother who, during
                        infancy, has become resident in the country where the father or mother is
                        naturalized, and has. according to the laws of such country, become
                        naturalized therein, shall be deemed to be a subject of the state of which
                        the father or mother has become a subject, and not a British subject. 4.
                        Where the father, or the mother being a widow, has obtained a certificate of
                        readmission to British nationality, every child of such father or mother
                        who, during infancy, has become resident in the British dominions with such
                        father or mother, shall be deemed to have resumed the position of a British
                        subject to all intents. 5. Where the father, or the mother being a widow,
                        has obtained a certificate of naturalization in the United Kingdom, every
                        child of such father or mother who. during infancy, has become resident with
                        such father or mother in any part of the United Kingdom, shall be deemed to
                        be a naturalized British subject.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">supplemental provisions.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Eleventh. One of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state may, by
                        regulation, provide for the following matters: 1. The form and registration
                        of declarations of British nationality. 2. The form and registration of
                        certificates of naturalization in the United Kingdom. 3. The form and
                        registration of certificates of readmission to British nationality. 4. The
                        form and registration of declarations of alienage. 5. The registration by
                        officers in the diplomatic or consular service of her Majesty of the births
                        and deaths of British subjects who may be born or die out of her Majesty’s
                        dominions, and of the marriages of persons married at any of her Majesty’s
                        embassies or legations. 6. The transmission to the United Kingdom for the
                        purpose of registration or safe-keeping, or of being produced as evidence,
                        of any declarations or certificates made in pursuance of this act out of the
                        United Kingdom, or of any copies of such declarations or certificates, also
                        of copies of entries contained in any register kept out of the United
                        Kingdom in pursuance of or for the purpose of carrying into effect the
                        provisions of this act. 7. With the consent of the treasury the imposition
                        and application of fees in respect of any registration authorized to be made
                        by this act, and in respect of the making any declaration or the grant of
                        any certificate authorized to be made or granted by this act.</p>
                    <p>The said secretary of state, by a further regulation, may repeal, alter, or
                        add to any regulation previously made by him in pursuance of this
                        section.</p>
                    <p>Any regulation made by the said secretary of state in pursuance of this
                        section shall be deemed to be within the powers conferred by this act, and
                        shall be of the same force as if it had been enacted in this act, but shall
                        not, so far as respects the imposition of fees, be in force in any British
                        possession, and shall not, so far as respects any other matter, be in force
                        in any British possession in which any act or ordinance to the contrary of
                        or inconsistent with any such direction may for the time being be in
                        force.</p>
                    <p>Twelfth. The following regulations shall be made with respect to evidence
                        under this act: 1. Any declaration authorized to be made under this act may
                        be proved in any legal proceeding by the production of the original
                        declaration, or of any copy thereof certified to be a true copy by one of
                        her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state, or by any person authorized by
                        regulations of one of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state to give
                        certified copies of such declaration, and the production of such declaration
                        or copy shall be evidence of the person therein named as declarant having
                        made the same at the date in the said declaration mentioned. 2<hi
                            rend="italic">.</hi> A certificate of naturalization may be proved in
                        any legal proceeding by the production of the original certificate, or of
                        any copy thereof certified to be a true copy by one of her Majesty’s
                        principal secretaries of State, or by any person authorized by regulations
                        of one of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state to give certified
                        copies of such certificate. 3. A certificate of readmission to British
                        nationality may be proved in any legal proceeding by the production of the
                        original certificate, or of any copy thereof certified to be a true copy by
                        one of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of state, or by any person
                        authorized by regulations of one of her Majesty’s principal secretaries of
                        state to give certified copies of such certificate. 4. Entries in any
                        register authorized to be made in pursuance of this act shall be proved by
                        such copies, and certified in such manner as may be directed by one of her
                        Majesty’s principal secretaries of state, and the copies of such entries
                        shall be evidence of any matters by this act or by any regulation of the
                        said secretary of state authorized to be inserted in the register. 5. The
                        documentary evidence act, 1868, shall apply to any regulation made by a
                        secretary of state, in pursuance of, or for the purpose of carrying into
                        effect any of the provisions of this act.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">miscellaneous.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Thirteenth. Nothing in this act contained shall affect the grant of letters
                        of denization by her Majesty.</p>
                    <p>Fourteenth. Nothing in this act contained shall qualify an alien to be the
                        owner of a British ship.</p>
                    <pb facs="0472" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                    <p>Fifteenth. Where any British subject has in pursuance of this act become an
                        alien, he shall not thereby be discharged from any liability in respect of
                        any acts done before the date of his so becoming an alien.</p>
                    <p>Sixteenth. All laws, statutes, and ordinances which may be duly made by the
                        legislature of any British possession for imparting to any person the
                        privileges, or any of the privileges, of naturalization, to be enjoyed by
                        such person within the limits of such possession, shall within such limits
                        have the authority of law, but shall be subject to be confirmed or
                        disallowed by her Majesty in the same manner, and subject to the same rules
                        in and subject to which her Majesty has power to confirm or disallow any
                        other laws, statutes, or ordinances in that possession.</p>
                    <p>Seventeenth. In this act, if not inconsistent with the context or
                        subject-matter thereof “disability” shall mean the status of being an
                        infant, lunatic, idiot, or married woman. “British possession” shall mean
                        any colony, plantation, island, territory, or settlement within her
                        Majesty’s dominions, and not within the United Kingdom, and all territories
                        and places under one legislature are deemed to be one British possession for
                        the purposes of this act. “The governor of any British possession” shall
                        include any person exercising the chief authority in such possession.
                        “Officer in the diplomatic service of her Majesty” shall mean any
                        ambassador, minister, or chargé d’affaires, or secretary of legation, or any
                        person appointed by such ambassador, minister, charge d’affaires, or
                        secretary of legation to execute any duties imposed by this act on an
                        officer in the diplomatic service of her Majesty. “Officer in the consular
                        service of her Majesty” shall mean and include consul-general, consul,
                        vice-consul, and consular agent, and any person for the time being
                        discharging the duties of consul-general, consul, vice-consul, and consular
                        agent.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">repeal of acts mentioned in schedule.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Eighteenth. The several acts set forth in the first and second parts of the
                        schedule annexed hereto shall be wholly repealed, and the acts set forth in
                        the third part of the said schedule shall be repealed to the extent therein
                        mentioned: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi> That the repeal enacted in this
                        act shall pot affect, 1. Any right acquired or thing done before the passing
                        of this act. 2. Any liability accruing before the passing of this act. 3.
                        Any penalty, forfeiture, or other punishment incurred or to be incurred in
                        respect of any offense committed before the passing of this act. 4. The
                        institution of any investigation or legal proceeding, or any other remedy
                        for ascertaining or enforcing any such liability, penalty, forfeiture, or
                        punishment as aforesaid.</p>
                    <p rend="center">SCHEDULE.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Note.—</hi>Reference is made to the repeal of the
                        “whole act” where portions have been repealed before, in order to preclude
                        henceforth the necessity of looking back to previous acts.</p>
                    <p>This schedule, so far as respects acts prior to the reign of George the
                        Second, other than acts of the Irish Parliament, refers to the edition
                        prepared under the direction of the record commission, intituled “The
                        Statutes of the Realm; printed by command of his Majesty King George the
                        Third, in pursuance of an address of the House of Commons of Great Britain.
                        From original records and authentic manuscripts.”</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">PART I.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">acts wholly repealed, other than acts of the irish
                            parliament.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>An act that all such as are to be naturalized or restored in blood shall
                        first receive the sacrament of the Lord’s Supper, and the oath of
                        allegiance, and the oath of supremacy. (7 Jas. 1, c. 2.)</p>
                    <p>An act to enable his Majesty’s natural-born subjects to inherit the estate of
                        their ancestors, either lineal or collateral, notwithstanding their father
                        or mother were aliens. (11 Will. 3, c. 6.<note n="*" xml:id="d272fn1">11
                            &amp; 12 Wm. 3. (Ruff.)</note>)</p>
                    <p>An act for naturalizing such foreign Protestants and others therein
                        mentioned, as are settled or shall settle in any of his Majesty’s colonies
                        in America. (13 Geo. 2, c. 7.)</p>
                    <p>An act to extend the provisions of an act made in the thirteenth year of his
                        present Majesty’s reign, intituled “An act for naturalizing foreign
                        Protestants and others therein mentioned, as are settled or shall settle in
                        any of his Majesty’s colonies in America, to other foreign Protestants who
                        conscientiously scruple the taking of an oath.” (20 Geo. 2, c. 44.)</p>
                    <p>An act to explain two acts of Parliament; one of the thirteenth year of the
                        reign of his late Majesty, “for naturalizing such foreign Protestants and
                        others as are settled or shall settle in any of his Majesty’s colonies in
                        America; and the other of the second <pb facs="0473" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"
                        /> year of the reign of his present Majesty, “for naturalizing such foreign
                        Protestants as have served or shall serve as officers or soldiers in his
                        Majesty’s royal American regiment, or as engineers in America.” (13 Geo. 3,
                        c. 25.)</p>
                    <p>An act to prevent certain inconveniences that may happen by hills of
                        naturalization. (14 Geo. 3, c. 84.)</p>
                    <p>An act to declare his Majesty’s natural-born subjects inheritable to the
                        estates of their ancestors, whether lineal or collateral, in that part of
                        Great Britain called Scotland, notwithstanding their father or mother were
                        aliens. (16 Geo. 3, c. 52.)</p>
                    <p>An act to alter and amend an act passed in the seventh year of the reign of
                        his Majesty King James the First, intituled “An act that all such as are to
                        be naturalized or restored in blood shall first receive the sacrament of the
                        Lord’s Supper, and the oath of allegiance, and the oath of supremacy.” (6
                        Geo. 4, c. 67.)</p>
                    <p>An act to amend the laws relating to aliens. (7 and 8 Vict., c. 66,)</p>
                    <p>An act for the naturalization of aliens. (10 and 11 Vict., c. 83.)</p>
                    <p rend="center">PART II.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">acts of the irish parliament wholly repealed.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>An act for encouraging Protestant strangers and others to inhabit and plant
                        in the kingdom of Ireland. (14 and 15 Chas. 2, c. 13.)</p>
                    <p>An act for naturalizing of all Protestant strangers in this kingdom. (2 Anne,
                        c. 14.)</p>
                    <p>An act for naturalizing such foreign merchants, traders, artificers,
                        artisans, manufacturers, workmen, seamen, farmers, and others as shall
                        settle in this kingdom. (19 and 20 Geo. 3, c. 29.)</p>
                    <p>An act for extending the provisions of an act passed in this kingdom in the
                        nineteenth and twentieth years of his Majesty’s reign, intituled “An act for
                        naturalizing such foreign merchants, traders, artificers, artisans,
                        manufacturers, workmen, seamen, fanners, and others as shall settle in this
                        kingdom.” (23 and 24 Geo. 3, c. 38.)</p>
                    <p>An act to explain and amend an act intituled “An act for naturalizing such
                        foreign merchants, traders, artificers, artisans, manufacturers, workmen,
                        seamen, farmers, and others who shall settle in this kingdom.” (36 Geo. 3,
                        c. 48.)</p>
                    <p rend="center">PART III.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">acts partially repealed.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>An act for reviving, continuing, and amending several statutes made in this
                        kingdom heretofore temporary. (4 Geo. I, c. 9; act of Irish Parliament.)
                        Extent of repeal: So far as it makes perpetual the act of 2 Anne, c. 14.</p>
                    <p>An act for consolidating and amending the laws relative to jurors and juries.
                        (6 Geo. IV, c. 50.) Extent of repeal: The whole of section 47.</p>
                    <p>An act consolidating and amending the laws relating to jurors and juries in
                        Ireland. (3 and 4 Will. IV, c. 91.) Extent of repeal: The whole of section
                        37.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
