<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Henry M. Brent to to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1870</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">297</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1870-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1870-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="debt" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1870-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1870-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="297"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d297">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">No. 299.</note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Henry M. Brent</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Fish</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 238.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic"> Lima</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-09-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 29, 1870</date>. (Received Oct.
                        28.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith the copy and
                    translation of a note from his excellency the minister of foreign affairs
                    relative to the immunities to be accorded to hearers of dispatches.</p>
                <p>I made answer to his excellency that I would transmit the document to the
                    Department and await instructions.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>H. M. BRENT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Señor Loayza</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. H.
                            M. Brent</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 47.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-09-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 23, 1870.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I regret having to commence my official
                        intercourse with you in referring to an affair which has taken an unpleasant
                        character, and in which the doctrine sustained by your legation cannot be
                        admitted by my government without establishing precedents of very important
                        consequences. It is understood that I refer to the departure of the American
                        citizen, Mr. W. D. Farrand, violating the judicial orders of detention
                        issued against him, at the request of persons to whom he was under certain
                        responsibilities. Since the violation of these orders, issued in conformity
                        with Peruvian laws and by competent authority, was an accomplished fact, and
                        since the government of Peru could not be silent on such an important point,
                        without admitting the theory sustained by General Hovey, it was found
                        necessary to address to this high functionary the note of protest, with
                        which you are perfectly conversant. I thought that this would terminate the
                        discussion initiated by the American minister, in which this department has
                        sustained, and does sustain, that the appointment of a person as bearer of
                        dispatches is not sufficient to withdraw him from the jurisdiction of the
                        tribunals of the country where he has resided as a private individual, and
                        as such entered into various undertakings of a business character; but,
                        nevertheless, the general addressed me the note which I received on the 19th
                        instant a few hours before he made his official farewell. I find it
                        indispensable to take notice of that dispatch regarding the matter under its
                        true merits, and placing the question of international right in its correct
                        limits, proving thus again that my government has, in this disagreeable
                        affair, observed the proper circumspection, and has adhered perfectly to the
                        principles of the great law of nations.</p>
                    <p>Following the plan established by his excellency General Hovey, I will first
                        remark the facts preceding the departure of Colonel Farrand, to afterward
                        enter into the question of the privileges of bearers of dispatches.</p>
                    <p>When, by the first dispatch of his excellency on the 13th instant, I learned
                        of the appointment of Colonel Farrand as bearer of dispatches to Washington,
                        and of the existance of certain orders of detention against him, I was
                        pained at not being able to accede to the request contained in that
                        dispatch, that Farrand might not be impeded from leaving in the steamer
                        sailing for Panama on the next morning 5 since it was impossible to
                        establish an unjustifiable exception, and violate the laws to which the
                        person detained was liable, the government thus contributing to weaken the
                        respectable orders of the judicial power, and causing the interested parties
                        in the detention to lose their rights by a gubernatorial act, at once
                        illegal and unjustifiable.</p>
                    <p>Such were the considerations that governed me in replying to General Hovey on
                        the same day, a reply which was delivered to him by Dr. Elmore, the chief
                        clerk of this <pb facs="0552" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/> department, who
                        likewise brought to me at 12 o’clock on the same night the answer of the
                        American legation. Without awaiting the result of the discussion, his
                        excellency General Hovey departed for Callao in the first train on the
                        morning of the 14th, and going on board the steamer Peru, the scene with
                        which you are acquainted took place. It is said that the letter of the
                        official mayor, transcribed in his excellency’s dispatch which I now reply
                        to, was considered as an easy method devised by me to avoid the controversy,
                        and that it was not supposed after this semi-official announcement that any
                        difficulty would occur.</p>
                    <p>I must be permitted to recall to your honor that when a diplomatic discussion
                        is being carried on in writing, it cannot be considered as terminated by
                        private notes, not even bearing the signatures of the debating ministers,
                        but only that of an employé of the department of the chief clerk; especially
                        as the said employé did not state in his letter that the note was by the
                        order or the request of the minister. On the other hand, from the tenor of
                        this document, to which an importance is given it that is not merited, it
                        appears that the minister who now addresses you insisted in denying the
                        request, and this must be noted, since this department cannot refuse the
                        request of the minister of a friendly power, to afterward concede it in an
                        anti-diplomatic and indecorous manner. Since the minister of foreign affairs
                        cannot and does not accept the responsibility of the acts of others, this
                        point may be considered as fixed. But since the legation has given such
                        importance to this letter, the same must be allowed to a document of the
                        same nature, addressed to me by the official mayor on the same night,
                        thinking he might not find me, and which he delivered to me in my house. In
                        this he says: “The general accompanies Farrand to Callao to-morrow, and says
                        that a very grave international question will take place if the authorities
                        of Peru detain, in such circumstances, an officer of the United States.”</p>
                    <p>It therefore appears that the decision of his excellency to accompany Farrand
                        was not the result of the letter from the official mayor, but had been
                        formed from the morning of the 13th. This cannot be denied, unless it is
                        agreed that the private letters of which I have spoken have not the
                        semi-official character, which, if given to the first, must also be conceded
                        to the last.</p>
                    <p>A number of quotations are made in the dispatch, which I have the honor of
                        answering from noted writers, respecting the immunities, inviolability of
                        the person and dispatches and papers of the messenger. These are hardly to
                        the point, since I do not pretend to sustain that messengers while in the
                        country to which they are sent, or in a third nation through which they must
                        pass, can be detained. The present question is of a distinct character. It
                        is whether an individual domiciled in a country in which as a private
                        citizen he has made business transactions and contracted certain
                        responsibilities can escape these by being named bearer of dispatches by a
                        diplomatic agent. The question now fairly put is not sustainable by the
                        theory invoked in favor of Farrand, and certainly no authority will be found
                        to assert the immunity of the messenger simply from having received that,
                        character, and against whom, before his entrance upon his duty, the orders
                        of arrest were issued. It cannot be otherwise, since, if the doctrine upheld
                        by the legation of the United States is admitted, it follows by clear logic
                        that a diplomatic agent naming as messenger some person against whom legal
                        writs were pending, or who from certain responsibilities was prohibited from
                        leaving the country where they were contracted, was authorized to protect
                        with his flag such a person even if before his entrance on duty the grave
                        impediment against the messenger was known. Your honor will agree with me
                        that such a theory, absurd and wholly untenable, and even supposing, as it
                        must be supposed, that at the time of naming the messenger the minister was
                        unaware of the obstacles existing, once cognizant of them the person should
                        be left to justice, and another person named to discharge the commission,
                        thus reconciling the exigencies of the diplomatic service with those not
                        less to be respected, of the due administration of justice.</p>
                    <p>I have been very far from affirming in any of my communications that a
                        messenger sent by a legation, an embassador, or a minister, should not leave
                        the state from which he carries the dispatches. I have affirmed, calling
                        upon the authority of Baron Martens, that the messenger is inviolable in the
                        state to which he is sent, or in the territory of a third, through which he
                        may pass to perform his duty, and that Martens, in not stating the case of
                        the messenger being detained in the territory from which he is sent, clearly
                        insinuates that the messenger may be there detained, if there are motives
                        for so doing, since it is easy to replace him; since his responsibilities
                        should not be ignored, contracted in the place of his residence, and since
                        establishing a contrary theory, diplomatic agents would have the additional
                        privilege of withdrawing from the courts of the country where they are
                        accredited, any person subject to civil or criminal responsibilities, only
                        by alleging the person was being sent as bearer of important dispatches.
                        This necessary rectification made, the argument referred to is
                        destroyed.</p>
                    <p>But even supposing that the Baron de Martens had made no distinction in this
                        matter, it would always be impossible to sustain that a commission as bearer
                        of dispatches would free a person from the action of the courts of the
                        country where he resides, and <pb facs="0553" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> from
                        the liabilities he had there contracted. Bearers of dispatches cannot
                        pretend to the same immunities as the higher members of the diplomatic
                        corps; and if the Baron de Werch, plenipotentiary of the Landgrave of Hesse
                        Cassel in France, was detained in Paris because he had not paid his
                        creditors, and was not allowed to leave that capital until the Landgrave had
                        assumed the responsibility of his debts, what would take place with respect
                        to persons not having such rank in the diplomatic family? The question needs
                        no reply.</p>
                    <p>The difference of opinion on the point in discussion does not alter the good
                        understanding between the two governments, nor the harmony and personal
                        consideration between the two ministers who have been engaged in the
                        question, which I think is now concluded.</p>
                    <p>I must observe to your honor that in mentioning the delay in receiving the
                        note I have just answered, it was only to fix that delay on record, and not
                        to give the matter any undeserved importance.</p>
                    <p>I beg to assure your honor of my highest consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. J. LOAYZA.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi> M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Brent,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires of the United States.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
