<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="218" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/7–1444</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Vice President <persName type="from">Wallace</persName> to
                            President <persName type="to">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>
                        </hi><note n="47" xml:id="d218fn47">Copy transmitted by Vice President
                            Wallace to the Chief of the Division of Chinese Affairs; date of receipt
                            in Department not indicated.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chengtu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-27">June 27,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear President Chiang</hi>: Since taking leave of
                        you I have given much serious thought to our conversations in your home and
                        to the situation in China as it has been revealed to me during my visit in
                            <pb facs="0247" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> Chungking, Kunming, and
                        Kweilin. The situation which confronts us—Americans as well as Chinese—is
                        extremely critical; but it is not hopeless if quick positive action is taken
                        to bring into play new forces and a new spirit. I believe this action should
                        take the form of a radical new approach to the problem of Chinese-American
                        collaboration. I have in mind not only military collaboration but
                        collaboration in determining the methods on a political level of employing
                        the military potential at our disposal, and collaboration in breathing a new
                        spirit into the fight from China against the Japanese. Drastic measures may
                        be needed to meet a drastic situation.</p>
                    <p>I believe in China and I believe that the Chinese people whom you serve have
                        the courage to fight to the finish if they are shown the way and given the
                        encouragement that comes from a realization of the value of what they are
                        fighting for.</p>
                    <p>Immediately upon my return to Washington I shall take up with President
                        Roosevelt your suggestion that he should send to Chungking a personal
                        representative who could work with you, plan with you, and effect that
                        dynamic collaboration of which I have spoken.</p>
                    <p>I believe that it would be easier for President Roosevelt to make his
                        decision, and easier to complete the necessary preliminary arrangements with
                        the speed which the situation requires, if you could send to Washington
                        immediately a man in whom you repose complete confidence and whom you could
                        empower to discuss the problem personally with the President and concur, on
                        your behalf, in all decisions arrived at.</p>
                    <p>In this connection, you will recall that I suggested to you during one of our
                        conversations in Chungking the advantages that might result if you could
                        spare Dr. T. V. Soong from Chungking long enough for a quick visit to
                        Washington.</p>
                    <p>I consider the matters discussed in this letter on the eve of my departure
                        from China to be urgent and trust that you will give my suggestions the most
                        serious consideration.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi> A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>