<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-27T23:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-27T23:30:00-05:00" n="220" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6–2844: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Officer in Chargé at New Delhi</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Merrell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="49" xml:id="d220fn49">Copy submitted to President Roosevelt by
                            the Secretary of State on June 28.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-28T11:00:00+06:30">June 28,
                                1944—11 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received June 28—4:20 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>471. Following for President from Wallace (Message No. 1).</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Reference your message, delivered to me by Ambassador Gauss noon of
                            June 23,<note n="50" xml:id="d220fn50">Not found in Department
                                files.</note> with regard to United States Army observer group
                            proceeding to North China (including Communist controlled areas) to
                            obtain vital military intelligence. Prior to receipt of message,
                                G–mo<note n="51" xml:id="d220fn51">Generalissimo Chiang
                                Kai-shek.</note> had indicated to me very positively his assent to
                            the dispatch of group as soon as it could be organized. Accompanied by
                            General Ferris,<note n="52" xml:id="d220fn52">Brig. Gen. Benjamin G.
                                Ferris, Acting Chief of Staff, U. S. Army Forces in China, Burma,
                                and India.</note> I again discussed the matter in detail with the
                            G–mo on the afternoon of 20th [<hi rend="italic">23d</hi>],<note n="53" xml:id="d220fn53">See Department of State, <hi rend="italic">United
                                    States Relations With China</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>, Government Printing Office, 1949), pp.
                                555–558.</note> and we obtained what I hope will prove to be his
                            full cooperation for the early despatch and effective operation of the
                            group.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Discussion between Government and Communist representatives is taking
                            place in Chungking but the G–mo’s attitude toward the problem is so
                            imbued with prejudice that I perceive little prospect of a satisfactory
                            long-term settlement. G–mo assures me that only “political” measures
                            will be employed.</item>
                        <pb facs="0249" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>G–mo indicated desire for improved relations with USSR and desires
                            that we assist in bringing about meeting of Sino-Soviet representatives.
                            I emphasized importance of reaching understanding.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>I have found economic, political, and military situations in China
                            extremely discouraging. Chinese morale is low and demoralization is a
                            possibility with resultant disintegration of central authority. There is
                            little that we can do about the economic situation. The Chinese appear
                            incapable of coping with it but a general collapse does not seem
                            imminent. The political situation is unstable and tense with rising lack
                            of confidence in the G–mo and his reactionary entourage. Of the military
                            situation I can only say that it might be worse. In Hunan it is
                            critical. Although potentialities and plan exist for stiffening Chinese
                            defenses out of Hengyang, there is serious threat of severance of East
                            China from West with consequent effect on morale in remaining Free
                            China.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The G–mo seems bewildered regarding economic situation; unsure
                            regarding political situation; and, while expressing confidence in his
                            army, is obviously distressed regarding military developments. He
                            attributes recent and current reverses to low morale due to economic
                            difficulties. He is convinced that all-out Burma offensive early this
                            year would have strengthened Chinese will to resistance and prevented
                            military reverses. He assures me that Chinese will continue to resist up
                            to their ability but he displays discouragement rather than
                            optimism.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>I consider vital our need for a more vigorous and better coordinated
                            American representation in China—in Chungking. Our effort in China, in
                            its military and related political aspects, requires more positive
                            direction, and closer cooperation from the Chinese, if this area is to
                            be employed as an effective base of operations against the Japanese. (I
                            am dispatching immediately a separate telegram<note n="54" xml:id="d220fn54">Telegram No. 472, June 28, noon, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> on this subject).</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Merrell</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>