<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="250" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">033.1193 Nelson, Donald M./1–1245</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Donald M. Nelson</persName> to
                            President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                        </hi><note n="44" xml:id="d250fn44">Copy transmitted to Secretary of State
                            Stettinius by Mr. Nelson in his letter of January 12, 1945. In his
                            letter of acknowledgment of January 15, 1945, Acting Secretary of State
                            Grew congratulated Mr. Nelson “on the constructive work already
                            accomplished and the favorable outlook that you have created for an
                            important potential improvement in China’s war effort, increased war
                            production and eventual industrial development.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-20">December 20, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: This is my report to you on
                        my work in China this autumn. As I cabled you from Chungking on November 22,
                        the situation there has undergone marked improvement, particularly with
                        respect to the cooperation between the Generalissimo and our military
                        forces. It is clear, however, that China is passing through her greatest
                        crisis of the war. Most of our military authorities in China believe that if
                        the Japanese are able to press their drive through Kweiyang, they will
                        direct their next thrust against Kunming, rather than Chungking. If Kunming
                        were to fall, it is generally agreed that China would cease to be an active
                        belligerent. Under those conditions, there is no doubt in my mind that at
                        least an additional year and possibly several additional years of warfare,
                        with an expenditure of many American lives, would be required to beat Japan
                        and liberate China.</p>
                    <p>Fortunately, the Generalissimo is working energetically with General
                            Wedemeyer<note n="45" xml:id="d250fn45">General Wedemeyer succeeded
                            General Stilwell in command of U. S. Army Forces in China.</note> to
                        halt the Japanese advance. If they are successful—and I think they will
                        be—steady progress from defensive to offensive warfare should follow in the
                        China theatre.</p>
                    <p>My main effort in China to date has been concentrated on measures of
                        immediate benefit to the war effort. During my visit to Chungking in
                        September, I was disturbed by the widespread postwar thinking in official
                        circles, and by a relative lack of constructive war effort. This situation,
                        I am glad to report, has been largely corrected. China’s government is now
                        throwing its weight into the job of winning the war. In my many talks with
                        Chinese leaders in November, postwar questions were put aside by mutual
                        agreement. With your approval, I shall reserve postwar discussions in China
                        until the Chinese war effort is further advanced.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Findings on China’s War Effort</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>China’s ability to wage war, as I found it in my September visit to
                        Chungking, was deteriorating rapidly. General Wedemeyer has no doubt
                        reported the tragic defects in the leadership, training, equipment, <pb facs="0302" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/> and supply of the Chinese armies.
                        The long persistence of these defects was due in large part to the attitude
                        of the Ministry of War, which clung to traditional practices in the face of
                        imminent disaster.</p>
                    <p>Prior to the cabinet changes in November, this attitude was characteristic of
                        most of the Generalissimo’s cabinet. The chief officials surrounding him
                        rested on the assumption that the United States would defeat Japan, and that
                        China could do little to help. Attempts to bring about cooperation between
                        the National Government and socalled Communist China were sternly resisted
                        by certain key ministers. Although these ultra-conservative officials were
                        obedient to the Generalissimo, their influence upon him was profound. Most
                        of the news that reached him was filtered through their offices.</p>
                    <p>While the Chinese government persisted in a stand-pat military and political
                        policy, her war economy steadily disintegrated and production declined.
                        Chinese arsenals have been operating in the midst of war on only 55% of
                        capacity. Operating rates of most other industries have been even lower. The
                        steel industry has been operating at less than 20% of capacity.</p>
                    <p>Another factor undermining China’s war effort has been her vicious price
                        inflation. It has made hoarding profitable and production unprofitable. To
                        meet swiftly rising costs of raw materials and labor, factories were forced
                        to raise prices, and China’s war procurement agencies were unable to meet
                        those prices. The bad price situation has been further aggravated by
                        uneconomical production practices in key industries.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, the Chinese Ministry to [<hi rend="italic">of</hi>] Finance and the
                        four government banks had established an excessively “tight” policy. Funds
                        allocated for Ordnance Procurement were insufficient to keep arsenals and
                        other war plants operating at full capacity. The government banks had
                        established interest rates of over 40% per annum, together with certain
                        outmoded practices which made it virtually impossible for war industries to
                        borrow.</p>
                    <p>On another side, China’s feeble war production effort was handicapped by her
                        unbelievable transportation difficulties. As you know, there are only 6,000
                        trucks in China and those old and in bad condition. Free China is also
                        desperately short of planes, liquid fuel, usable rolling stock for the
                        country’s few small and unconnected railroads, and spare parts.</p>
                    <p>The economic war effort of the nation was poorly planned and entirely
                        uncoordinated. Chinese Ordnance procurement officers made little use of
                        plants owned by other agencies of the government and by private sources.
                        Government departments had no mechanism for cooperation with each other or
                        with private industry in the war effort. Procurement was piecemeal.
                        Statements of requirements by government <pb facs="0303" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/> departments were non-existent or completely
                        unrealistic. No system of priorities existed, nor any mechanism to subsidize
                        high cost production of essential materials such as iron and steel.</p>
                    <p>Along with the military and economic vitality of the nation, the morale of
                        the Chinese people was being drained away. In September, I found the
                        civilians of China wavering between resigned reliance on the United States
                        to defeat Japan, and bleak pessimism. Their will to victory withered for
                        lack of strong moral leadership. In the educated, salaried middle class,
                        which has been nearly ruined by the inflation, resentment of hoarding and
                        speculation by the wealthy, and of official corruption had been steadily
                        growing.</p>
                    <p>In recent years, leaders of the country, from the Generalissimo down, have
                        been unable effectively to rally the people to the war effort. It must be
                        kept in mind, too, that the civilians of China receive little war news,
                        largely because of lack of communication. For the most part, they have no
                        feeling of participation in the war. The lack of an army postal system and
                        prevailing illiteracy virtually prevent communication between civilians and
                        soldiers.</p>
                    <p>Although the Generalissimo is highly respected and widely regarded as the one
                        man capable of holding China together, there are many rumors of disaffection
                        among powerful provincial leaders. For example, the allegiance of the
                        Governor of important Yunnan Province, General Lung, is reported to hang by
                        a thread. Such rumors, whether true or not, depress morale.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Action Taken</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It was clear to General Hurley and to me, as we faced the situation in
                        September, that if China was not to drop out of the war as a belligerent,
                        she had to move rapidly. Swift action by the Generalissimo was the goal of
                        the talks which we had with him in September. Such action obviously required
                        the closest cooperation with the representatives of this country. Your
                        appointment of General Wedemeyer to the command of the China Theatre, your
                        subsequent appointment of General Hurley as Ambassador, and the arrival of
                        the American war production mission in China, laid the groundwork for a
                        number of significant measures, since put into effect: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Active steps were taken to check the Japanese
                                    advance</hi>. The diversion of Chinese troops from the border of
                                Yenan Province to the fighting zone in Kweichow suggests a shift in
                                attitude of the National Government toward the Communists; while the
                                movement of Chinese troops from Burma to Kweichow was the work of
                                the newly established military command in China. The latter
                                development was made possible only by close cooperation among the
                                Chinese, Americans, and British. In talks which I held at General
                                Wedemeyer’s request with <pb facs="0304" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/>
                                ranking American and British commanders in Calcutta and Ceylon, I
                                found a healthy understanding of the Chinese military situation, and
                                a willingness to make far-reaching changes in campaign plans, so as
                                to give full cooperation to General Wedemeyer. Of great importance
                                also is the fact that the Chinese Service of Supply has now been put
                                under the command of General Wedemeyer.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chinese War Production Board was established
                                    and is functioning</hi>. In September, I obtained the
                                enthusiastic agreement of the Generalissimo to create an agency in
                                the Chinese government to plan and coordinate Chinese war production
                                and related economic activities. Following your approval in our
                                Washington conversation of November 2, I returned to China with a
                                small group of men who have had long experience in American war
                                production. Our first step was to work with a group of Chinese
                                officials headed by Dr. Wong Wen-Hao, Minister of Economics, to
                                draft the basic law for a Chinese War Production Board. This law,
                                which grants very wide powers, was immediately approved by the
                                Generalissimo, and has since been passed by the Executive and
                                Legislative Yuans. We worked closely with Dr. Wong on organization
                                and policy, participated in working up firm ordnance requirements
                                for the Chinese Army, and aided in winning cooperation for the
                                Chinese War Production Board from all Ministries of the Chinese
                                government and from leading financial and industrial groups.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>For the first time, the Chinese economic war effort is now
                                coordinated. Two members of the staff of the American War Production
                                Board have remained in Chungking to act as my deputies in further
                                advising the Chinese War Production Board on problems of policy and
                                operation. Excellent arrangements also have been made for close
                                liaison between the Chinese War Production Board and U. S. Army
                                Ordnance, represented in Chungking by officers of high
                                ability.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">An American technical production mission has begun
                                    work in China</hi>. By arrangement with the Foreign Economic
                                Administration, on my return to China in November, I brought with me
                                six American production specialists, five of whom are experts in
                                steel production, one in alcohol production. These highly qualified
                                men immediately began to visit Chinese industry and to study
                                production methods there. They will work with Chinese plant managers
                                and government officials over a period of three months with a view
                                to increasing output, improving quality, and reducing costs.
                                Attention was focused at once on measures to obtain immediate
                                increased production of entrenching tools, small arms, trench
                                mortars and ammunition needed by the Chinese Armies.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">War production requirements have been
                                    financed</hi>. The four Chinese government banks have contracted
                                to lend 10 billion CNC <pb facs="0305" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/> to
                                the Chinese War Production Board to finance essential production.
                                The urgent need for additional working capital in many Chinese
                                industries also made it necessary that China’s government banks
                                reduce interest rates for war production to a point where management
                                would once more find it possible to borrow capital and borrow it
                                quickly. With the approval of the Generalissimo I put the issue
                                before the newly appointed Minister of Finance and participated in
                                negotiations among the Chinese War Production Board, the Ministry of
                                Finance, and the four government banks. The bankers agreed to reduce
                                interest rates on loans for war production purposes to 20% per
                                annum, or less than half the previous customary rate. The time
                                necessary to negotiate a loan has been reduced from four or five
                                months to a few days. Complicated red tape in granting and servicing
                                loans has been sharply cut.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Additional transportation facilities have been
                                    allocated to China</hi>. On October 19, after my return to the
                                United States from my first visit to China, I recommended and you
                                approved the production of 10,000 additional trucks for China, now
                                scheduled for production in 1945. At the same time you approved my
                                negotiating with General Arnold<note n="46" xml:id="d250fn46">Gen.
                                    Henry H. Arnold, Commanding General, U. S. Army Air
                                    Forces.</note> for 30 C–46 cargo planes for use of the Chinese
                                National Aviation Company; and General Arnold agreed to this
                                proposal, deliveries to begin in January or February 1945.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Shifts were made in the Chinese Cabinet with a
                                    view to strengthening the war effort</hi>. On November 27, the
                                Generalissimo announced a number of important cabinet changes, in
                                which new ministers were appointed for War, Finance, Education, and
                                Information. While these changes by no means mark a new era in the
                                government, yet they certainly represent a step toward a more
                                aggressive war policy. Following on the heels of the cabinet
                                reorganization, and closely related to it, came important changes in
                                the Chinese system of military supply and far closer cooperation
                                between the Chinese and American High Command. Conversations between
                                the National Government and Communist leaders looking toward war
                                cooperation were also benefited.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Moves have been made to bolster Chinese civilian
                                    morale</hi>. The establishment of the Chinese War Production
                                Board and the arrival of the technical mission had an immediate
                                effect on the morale of the Chinese civilian. These were the first
                                constructive economic achievements which the country had seen for a
                                long while. During November, I discussed the morale problem with the
                                Generalissimo, and he stated that he would personally assume
                                responsibility for strengthening morale. With the same purpose, I
                                accepted an invitation to address the Presidium and Resident Members
                                of the People’s Political <pb facs="0306" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                                Council in Chungking—China’s nearest approach to a representative
                                legislative body. Taking the need for cooperation within China as my
                                theme, I also talked before the China-American Institute of Cultural
                                Relations, as well as to leaders of Chinese industry and finance.
                                Before I left Chungking, I attended a joint meeting of the Chinese
                                War Production Board, the Ministry of Information, and the American
                                    OWI,<note n="47" xml:id="d250fn47">Office of War
                                    Information.</note> to discuss the possibility of reaching
                                Chinese workers with inspirational and educational material. A
                                cabled report from Chungking states that such material is beginning
                                to be actively used in factories.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Results</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Kweiyang–Kunming–Chungking triangle, with its great agricultural wealth,
                        and the possibility of driving the Americans out of China, may prove an
                        irresistible temptation to the Japanese. Apparently, they have men and
                        supplies available, should they decide on another offensive aimed at
                        Kweiyang. In that event, the crisis would arise again. The morale of the
                        Chinese armies in Kweichow, even as now reinforced, is still a doubtful
                        factor. Fortunately, the recent close cooperation between the Chinese and
                        American military may make a profound difference in the near future. On the
                        whole, time is now working for the Chinese—a new development.</p>
                    <p>In addition to the improvement in the military situation, we can look for
                        far-reaching gains on the economic front, as a result of action taken this
                        autumn in China. The 1945 schedule of the Chinese WPB for production of
                        entrenching tools and trench mortar shells is double the program previously
                        prepared by China’s Ordnance Department, and increased production rates will
                        be felt within the next few weeks on the fighting fronts of China. Alcohol
                        schedules are similarly double rates planned prior to the arrival of our
                        mission. By spring of 1945, I expect the rate of China’s total war
                        production should be at least double the November rate.</p>
                    <p>The expected opening of the Ledo–Burma road in February for one-way traffic,
                        and the opening of the Calcutta–Kunming pipeline—which will be the longest
                        in the world—will greatly strengthen the supply situation. The Ledo–Burma
                        road should carry about 30,000 tons, and the pipeline should deliver some
                        17,000 tons per month when they are operating smoothly. In November ATC and
                            CNAC<note n="47a" xml:id="d250fn47a">Air Transport Command (U. S.) and
                            China National Aviation Corporation.</note> flew over the Hump 37,000
                        tons of cargo—a record figure. Indications are that next summer we should be
                        getting into Kunming around 75,000 tons per month of cargo from all sources.
                        This compares with 25,000 tons in September 1944.</p>
                    <pb facs="0307" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/>
                    <p>Increased and coordinated production, plus improved transportation will make
                        itself felt in an accession of strength to the entire Chinese economy.
                        Better distribution of regional and local production, and less scarcity of
                        manufactured products will be forces operating to check the inflation. Over
                        a period of time, technological improvement in an expanding economy will
                        mean greater productivity of industrial workers, higher real wage levels,
                        larger purchasing power and tax returns, and more government funds with
                        which to tackle urgent problems such as increasing per capita agricultural
                        output in China.</p>
                    <p>The feeling that China’s economy is being strengthened and that the country’s
                        productive ability is growing will do more than any amount of propaganda to
                        raise the morale of the Chinese people and hearten them for a sustained and
                        intensified war effort. Growing confidence in the national future will make
                        for greater governmental effectiveness and stability, as will experience
                        gained in war production planning, which is teaching the advantages and
                        techniques of cooperation.</p>
                    <p>The government should also benefit from its closer relations with industry.
                        At the same time, the heightened status of Chinese industry under the War
                        Production Board will tend to exert a liberalizing influence. Under that
                        influence, there is more likelihood that moderate elements in the Kuomintang
                        will continue to gain power, adding to the chances of genuine cooperation
                        between the national government and the Communists. Such cooperation, if
                        attainable, will be of historical importance both in speeding the progress
                        of the war and in strengthening the bases of the peace.</p>
                    <p>The success of China’s venture in planned war production, if properly
                        followed up through American government and business channels, will make for
                        close postwar economic relations between China and the United States. China
                        has the capacity and the desire to develop herself industrially with
                        American aid. If that aid is realistically planned, and if financial
                        arrangements are put on a sound business basis, China should soon after the
                        war begin to replace Japan as the leading industrial nation of the Orient.
                        In that event, a market of enormous size should progressively open up for
                        American export industries. I believe, too, that with American guidance,
                        China’s development can be turned into peaceful and democratic channels,
                        eliminating much of the fear of war which has for so long shaped political
                        attitudes in the Orient and South Pacific.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The creative work in aiding China to organize her economy effectively for war
                        is virtually completed. From this time forward, our <pb facs="0308" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/> job will be to sustain and advise the Chinese War
                        Production Board on a day to day basis. Arrangements have been made to this
                        end, and continuous reports will keep me in close touch with the situation.
                        With a view to creating the most favorable background for my deputies in
                        China, I have tentatively accepted, subject to your approval, an invitation
                        from the Generalissimo to become High Economic Advisor to the Chinese
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>After leaving China on December 4, I stopped at Pearl Harbor to acquaint
                        Admiral Nimitz<note n="48" xml:id="d250fn48">Adm. Chester W. Nimitz, U. S.
                            Navy, Commander in Chief, U. S. Pacific Fleet and Pacific area.</note>
                        with the existing Chinese situation. In the course of our conversation, I
                        found that the information which had reached the Admiral through usual
                        channels did not accord with the facts as General Hurley and I had learned
                        them. Accordingly, I suggested to Admiral Nimitz that arrangements be made
                        with General Hurley to transmit to him and to General MacArthur<note n="49" xml:id="d250fn49">Gen. Douglas MacArthur, Supreme Commander, Allied
                            Forces, Southwest Pacific.</note> regular reports on the Chinese
                        situation, as viewed by General Hurley and General Wedemeyer.</p>
                    <p>In the same conversation with Admiral Nimitz, we discussed the importance of
                        Chinese waterways for military transport, especially in the event of a
                        coastal invasion of China. Proper use of the waterways for war purposes
                        would undoubtedly require special river boats and equipment, and the Admiral
                        was deeply interested in this aspect of the matter.</p>
                    <p>If the Chinese war effort progresses well, I believe that the spring of 1945
                        would be a good time to begin work on a postwar program of Chinese-American
                        economic cooperation. <hi rend="italic">I recommended that at that time, the
                            military situation permitting, a seven-man American mission be appointed
                            to go to China to work with the Chinese Government in planning the
                            progressive expansion of Chinese-American trade on a realistic business
                            basis</hi>. In my judgment, this Commission should comprise businessmen
                        of wide experience, high standing, and awareness of America’s stake in
                        expanding foreign trade. To obtain the kind of aid implicit in such a
                        mission, the Chinese Government, I feel sure, would make strenuous efforts
                        to meet all prerequisite conditions.</p>
                    <p>In the interest of healthy diplomatic relations, I believe it would be
                        advisable to keep the governments of Russia, Great Britain, Australia, and
                        New Zealand informed of the measures we have taken and may hereafter take,
                        in aiding China to develop her economy. During my return trip from China, I
                        stopped at Canberra and at Wellington to talk with members of the Australian
                        and New Zealand Governments, both on the Chinese situation, and on postwar
                        trade problems. <pb facs="0309" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> Together with Mr.
                        Nelson Johnson, your Minister to Australia, I also visited Prime Minister
                        Curtin at Melbourne, where he is convalescing in a hospital from a recent
                        serious illness, and discussed with him the American and Australian
                        positions in postwar foreign trade.</p>
                    <p>I found the views of Prime Minister Curtin and of Dr. Evatt, the Australian
                        Minister for External Affairs, particularly satisfying from an American
                        standpoint. Prime Minister Fraser of New Zealand and Mr. Nash, the Minister
                        of Finance, were also sympathetic to the expansionist viewpoint on foreign
                        trade. I believe that both governments felt pleased at having been given
                        direct information on developments in China; and they show keen interest in
                        the considerably enlarged potentialities of postwar trade between their
                        countries and the United States.</p>
                    <p>As reports reach me on the progress of Chinese war production, I shall, of
                        course, keep you informed of salient points.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Donald M. Nelson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>