<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-02-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="291" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/15290</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 2219</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-02-23">February 23,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received March 6.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Embassy’s
                        telegram No. 258, February 8, 3 p.m. and despatch No. 2207 of February 21,
                        1944 in regard to the possibility of negotiation of Kuomintang–Communist
                        differences and to despatch No. 2216 of February 23, 1944, in regard to the
                        discussion at a press conference of the Central Government blockade of the
                        Communist-controlled areas. There is now enclosed a copy of a memorandum of
                        February 21, 1944,<note n="75" xml:id="d291fn75">Not printed.</note>
                        reporting an interview granted by the Communist representative at Chungking
                        to foreign newspaper correspondents on February 16.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. Following the government press
                            conference on February 16, a group of foreign newspaper correspondents
                            called on Mr. Tung Pi-wu, Communist representative at Chungking, to
                            obtain his reaction to the statements made by the Government spokesmen
                            and information concerning the Communist aims in the forthcoming
                            Kuomintang–Communist negotiations. Mr. Tung listed four possible aims of
                            the Communist Party in the negotiations: (1) to obtain treatment with
                            respect to military supplies and pay for the Communist armies equal to
                            that accorded other Chinese forces fighting against <pb facs="0367" n="353" xml:id="pg_353"/> Japan; (2) to obtain the lifting of the
                            blockade of the Communist-controlled Shensi–Kansu–Ninghsia Border
                            Region; (3) to obtain recognition of the legality of the
                            Shensi–Kansu–Ninghsia and Shansi–Chahar–Hopei Border Regions; and (4) to
                            obtain recognition of the legality of the Communist Party. Informed by a
                            correspondent that the Central Government denied the existence of the
                            blockade, Mr. Tung suggested to the correspondents that they go and see
                            for themselves whether such a blockade existed and added that the
                            foreign newspaper correspondents would be most welcome at Yenan. <hi rend="italic">End of Summary.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>Mr. Tung, the chief Communist representative at Chungking since the departure
                        of General Chou En-lai for Yenan in June 1943 and also a member of the
                        People’s Political Council, informed the correspondents at the beginning of
                        the interview that he could not make any statement to them but that he would
                        be willing for them to print his replies to any questions they might wish to
                        ask. Reports of this interview written by the correspondents for forwarding
                        to their respective newspapers have been handed by the Chinese censors to
                        General Ho Ying-chin, Chief of Staff and Minister of War, for approval and
                        it is not yet known how much of this interview will be passed for
                        transmission abroad.</p>
                    <p>In connection with the question of the Central Government blockade of the
                        Communist areas and of the shipment of medical supplies to that region
                        (Embassy’s despatch No. 2188 of February 18), informed sources state that
                        the Central Government has now given its approval to the shipment of two
                        truckloads of medical supplies to the Shensi Border Region. Apparently the
                        publicity given to Madame Sun Yat-sen’s message to an American publication
                        (Embassy’s despatch No. 2217 of February 23) and the questions asked by
                        foreign newspaper correspondents at the press conference on February 16 have
                        resulted in the Central Government’s taking belated action to permit the
                        passage of medical supplies furnished by relief organizations.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>C. E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>