<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="34" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/15338</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Second Secretary of Embassy in
                            China</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Service</hi>)<note n="98" xml:id="d34fn98">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Ambassador in China in his
                            despatch No. 2351, March 23; received April 13.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-20">March 20, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">To: Assistant Chief of Staff, G–2.</p>
                    <p>The following is supposed to be the gist of remarks made by the Generalissimo
                        at the latest meeting of his “inner council”. The source has been good in
                        the past. Suggested rating B–3.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The British feel that they lost out badly at both Cairo and Teheran.
                            They are therefore trying to recoup their position. British-American and
                            British-Soviet relations are not likely to be improved or cooperation
                            made better.</item>
                        <pb facs="0052" n="38" xml:id="pg_38"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Japan, facing the certainty of increasing pressure from America and
                            Britain, is sure to carry out a large scale campaign to put China out of
                            the war. They will hope to accomplish this by (1) the opening of the
                            Canton–Hankow railway, and (2) the capture of Chungking. The Japanese
                            will hope that by thus eliminating China and entrenching themselves in
                            China, they can so prolong the war that Britain and America will tire
                            and agree to a negotiated peace. This Japanese drive will come this
                            year.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>China can meet this drive but the greatest danger is of economic
                            collapse. The budget for the present year, increased largely by huge
                            expenditures on airfield construction for the American Army, will equal
                            the total of the national budget for the past six years. (Kung is quoted
                            by several other sources as saying that it takes CN$1,000,000 to feed 8
                            American soldiers for a year.) Great as these expenditures for the
                            American Army are, we should not grudge them. For if China is lost, and
                            America has to beat Japan from other bases, the additional cost to the
                            American taxpayers will be billions of American dollars. But the
                            economic situation is very serious and means must be found for dealing
                            with it. This year will be China’s toughest.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The importation of American currency for the American troops is not an
                            important factor in the situation. And since these troops are risking
                            their lives in fighting for China, it would be improper for us to make
                            objection. (Dr. Kung has also been reported to have expressed similar
                            opinions.)</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The press trip to Yenan will leave in the near future. It is planned
                            that they will have an opportunity of seeing the real conditions in the
                            Communist area and of comparing them with our reconstruction activities
                            in other parts of the Northwest. For this reason the trip will take
                            several months. It is hoped that this will have some effect in meeting
                            foreign criticism.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>We must attempt to settle the Communist problem by political means. I
                            asked Chou En-lai and Chu Teh<note n="99" xml:id="d34fn99">Communist
                                leaders.</note> to come to Chungking to discuss matters. Now it
                            appears that only Lin Pai-hsu is coming first. It is not likely that the
                            Communists will agree to give up their separate government and army. But
                            we must continue our efforts. It is hoped that a branch of Central News
                            can be established at Yenan.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>American public opinion toward China is becoming increasingly
                            critical. (The same source stated that the texts of numerous critical
                            articles in publications such as <hi rend="italic">Amerasia</hi> had
                            recently been sent from the U. S. These are circulated to some high
                            government officials but are not published.) We must do everything
                            possible to improve American opinion. If we have a failing, we must
                            correct it.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>According to the informant, the meeting ended with the Generalissimo
                            asking: “What exactly is wrong with China that the Americans do not
                            like?” No one tried to make an answer.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>China is in a mess. No military action on a significant scale is in sight.
                        The economic crisis continues to drift and worsen. Internal unrest is active
                        and growing. Relations with all her allies are estranged.</p>
                    <pb facs="0053" n="39" xml:id="pg_39"/>
                    <p>China (the Gov’t) is still Chiang Kai-shek. Although we may have to deal with
                        others—H. H. Kung or Ho Ying-chin<note n="1" xml:id="d34fn1">Chinese
                            Minister of War.</note>—we must recognize them as substantially only
                        yes-men.</p>
                    <p>We are, it is true, partially to blame for adding to China’s economic
                        problems. But for the sorry situation as a whole Chiang, and only Chiang is
                        responsible.</p>
                    <p>That under these serious circumstances Chiang should be acting as he is seems
                        incredible. Instead of all-out cooperation to win the war, we meet with
                        “active non-cooperation”. Military commitments are not being fulfilled.
                        Construction projects are delayed. Vital financial negotiations make little
                        progress. The simple request for observers to obtain military intelligence
                        from Communist North China is refused.</p>
                    <p>Yet Chiang knows that we are going to win this war, and that his destiny is
                        linked to us. He is completely dependent on the United States—in foreign
                        relations, militarily and economically. Even his internal position would be
                        endangered if American support were withdrawn.</p>
                    <p>The answer to the apparent enigma lies in Chiang’s background and
                        limitations, and in our failings in dealing with him.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p>Thus the recurrent alarms of new Japanese threats, the cries of imminent
                        economic collapse (unfortunately with a foundation of truth, but about which
                        he does nothing constructive), and the repeated demands for loans and other
                        aid on an unreasonable scale.</p>
                    <p>Thus also the difficulty in dealing with Chiang and in getting delivery on
                        promises. The words of the Ambassador carry little weight—because the State
                        Department has not taken a strong policy and because it does not, in any
                        event, speak for the White House. He does not fear General Stilwell—because
                        the General cannot demonstrate the unqualified backing of the War
                        Department, or the White House.</p>
                    <p>Chiang will cooperate if the United States, upon which he is dependent, makes
                        up its mind exactly what it wants from him and then gets hard-boiled about
                        it. Until the President determines our policy, decides our requirements, and
                        makes these clearly and unmistakably known to Chiang, Chiang will continue
                        in his present ways.</p>
                    <p>The President can do this directly or through fully authorized and completely
                        supported representatives. These might be the Ambassador and General
                        Stilwell acting in close concert.</p>
                    <p>This may mean taking an active part in Chinese affairs. But unless we do it,
                        China will not be of much use as an ally. And, in doing it, we may save
                        China.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Service</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>