<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-18T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-18T05:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/15380: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-18T17:00:00+07:00">May 18, 1944—5
                                p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received May 19—7:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>865. Press correspondents departed May 17 by plane to Paochi en route Sian
                        and Communist areas. Party included only three regular full-time foreign
                            correspondents<note n="44" xml:id="d346fn44">Harrison Forman, American,
                            representing the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald Tribune</hi>, the
                            United Press, and the London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>; Guenther
                            Stein, naturalized Briton of German origin, representing the <hi rend="italic">Christian Science Monitor</hi>, the Associated Press,
                            and the London <hi rend="italic">News-Chronicle;</hi> and Israel
                            Epstein, without nationality, representing <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>,
                            the <hi rend="italic">New York Times, Allied Labor News</hi>, and the
                            Sydney <hi rend="italic">Morning Herald.</hi>
                        </note> (excluding Tass representative) to cover for American and British
                        newspapers and American news agencies. Reuters not represented. Votaw
                        (Embassy’s 622–A<note n="45" xml:id="d346fn45">Telegram No. 622, April 7, 2
                            p.m., <ref target="#pg_395">p. 395</ref>.</note>) even [<hi rend="italic">is?</hi>] taking trip reportedly as representative <hi rend="italic">Baltimore Sun.</hi><note n="46" xml:id="d346fn46">Father
                            Shanahan, American, representing Catholic publications in the United
                            States, was also a member of the party.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Invitations May 12 from Information Minister to correspondents stated
                        Government wished party to remain North Shensi at least 3 months to enable
                        “complete understanding of conditions there”. In reply to correspondent’s
                        request regarding censorship (Embassy’s 837, May 12), Minister stated
                        existing rules would apply to military affairs; Communist statements on
                        policy would be passed provided accompanied by Kmt<note n="46a" xml:id="d346fn46a">Kuomintang.</note> rebuttal and if not prejudicial to
                        settlement Kmt-Communist differences. No reply to request for immediate
                        check on material deleted by censors Chungking. Lin Pai-hsu and Secretary
                        arrived Chungking May 17 by plane together with Wang Shih-chieh and General
                        Chang Chih-chung. Lin told American correspondent at airport, [that] Chou
                        En-lai would come to Chungking soon and group five Communist representatives
                        left Paochi by truck on 17th en route Chungking.</p>
                    <p>Some days ago Embassy informally approached Wu Teh-chen, Secretary-General,
                        to arrange for Service [to] join party. He replied that as Government has
                        refused similar requests from other diplomatic missions ours could not be
                        granted.</p>
                    <p>Editorial in <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi> recently pointed to Honan
                        defeat and increased need for unity between two parties and some Chinese
                        observers feel that Honan situation will serve to put pressure on Central
                        Government to adopt more conciliatory attitude. Continuation of discussions
                        between Kmt [and] Communist representatives at <pb facs="0439" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> Chungking is another encouraging sign but recent
                        indications of intensified private anti-Communist and anti-Soviet propaganda
                        do not point to any genuine desire on the part of Kmt to reach fundamental
                        solution. This anti-Communist propaganda seems to be “officially” as [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] adhered to by Lin Yutang<note n="47" xml:id="d346fn47">Chinese author and lecturer.</note> and Wei Tao-ming
                        in United States and observed here by recent publication in party press of
                        alleged Communist attack on Chungking troops, off the record circulation by
                        Central News at Kunming of report Communists had begun attack on Sian and
                        recent distribution to all CEC members of violently anti-Communist
                        documents. Much of this may be attributed to bitter anti-Communist element
                        in Kmt. Whatever action is taken at CEC session scheduled May 20 will depend
                        chiefly on Gmo and at best is not expected to provide more than temporary
                        solution.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>