<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">410</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-15T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-15T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-15T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-15T23:00:00-05:00" n="410"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8–1644: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-16T11:00:00+07:00"
                            >August 16, 1944—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 19—9:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1416. Timberman reports to HQ under date August 15 he and Ringwalt (our 1409,
                    August 15) had “conference” of 1 hour with Marshal Li Chi-shen substantially as
                    follows.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Li was informed by Ringwalt of ‘Embassy’s hands off policy’. In answer to
                        question of United States backing by [<hi rend="italic">of?</hi>] Li, I said
                        I could not answer as this was question for decision in Washington. I said
                        my presence here was solely in connection with military situation. Li said
                        Chinese people are discouraged by corruption in administration and by
                        Chungking’s neglect of the army and that movement was intended only to serve
                        needs of Chinese people; that 60% of taxes collected in area by Central
                        Government with no local benefits and that there was no desire to fight in
                        the army and that Tenth Army fought only at Hengyang. Li said Chungking
                        afraid to fight, Generalissimo had forbidden recruiting army up to strength
                        and during past year some 40% had disbanded under pretext of cutting down
                        expenses. Li said “that he himself controlled all troops this area through
                        loyal leaders and he would re-arm them, feed them and recruit them to
                        strength. In regard to west China communications he was vague but stated he
                        could use better administration and improve them. He sees no reason for
                        armed conflict as soldiers he desires would not be in opposition to his
                        movement. He said he intended to carry out his plans irrespective of Jap
                        moves but thought that Japs would not move further south and if they attempt
                        further offensive it will be aimed at Chungking or Kunming. Ringwalt
                        requested that we be kept informed of developments in view of our interest
                        in rapid defeat of Japs.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Timberman commented that he believed Li’s main purpose was concerned with
                    southeastern China only but movement might spread elsewhere because of general
                    discontent: that he was refreshed by Li’s enthusiasm and candor; and that while
                    Li did not indicate when he would move openly Ringwalt concurred in feeling this
                    would occur within 30 days.</p>
                <p>2. Ringwalt reports same date through Army as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Irrespective whether aid is rendered by United States or dissident
                            leaders elsewhere in this country, leaders will proceed with South <pb
                                facs="0524" n="510" xml:id="pg_510"/> China plans according to head
                            of committee and Kukong will possibly be seat. The ‘powers’ of Kwangsi,
                            Kwangtung, Fukien and Hunan will ‘absolutely’ support movement. It was
                            reiterated movement not to set up permanent dissident government but
                            that present Chungking Government will end with resignation of
                            Generalissimo and cause establishment democratic, capable regime for
                            real prosecution war and good of China. Pai Chung-hsi [is] said [to
                            have] left for Chungking to confer with Generalissimo. Political rather
                            than military considerations have dictated solidarity operations this
                            idea principally by 79 Army according to Z Force officers. Units
                            returning from front are well equipped and in good physical
                            condition”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
