<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Chinese Afairs (
                    (Vincent))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d442</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">442</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="442"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d442">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8–144</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Chinese Afairs</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">Vincent</hi>)<note n="82" xml:id="d442fn82">Addressed to
                        the Secretary of State and the Under Secretary of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-19">September 19,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>While the majority of the Chinese people continue to place their faith in the
                    leadership of Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek, there has been a marked decline in
                    his prestige during the past year.</p>
                <p>The attached despatch (no. 58, August 1, 1944)<note n="82a" xml:id="d442fn82a">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_493">p. 493</ref>.</note> from
                    Kunming discusses the changed attitude towards Chiang of Chinese liberals at
                    Kunming, which is believed to be symptomatic of liberal sentiment throughout
                    China. Within the past year liberal Chinese have come to regard the
                    Generalissimo as too static, stubborn, and shortsighted to undertake vitally
                    needed democratic, military and economic reforms. Most Chinese liberals now take
                    the view that, in spite of the urgent need for reforms in the Chinese
                    Government, the Generalissimo will not be persuaded to effect them; that
                    progressive elements within the Government can exert no influence; and that the
                    Generalissimo, on the strength of his firmly established authority and the
                    certainty of allied victory over Japan, will “ride out” the war in power and,
                    with his clique of second-rate men, direct the building of future China. You may
                    care to read through the first three paragraphs of the despatch.</p>
                <p>The attitude displayed by these “intellectual” liberals is as much an indictment
                    of themselves as of Chiang. They are ineffectual because they complain but do
                    nothing. They seem incapable either of producing strong leadership or of seeking
                    such leadership around which to unite. This, in a measure, accounts for their
                    extreme pessimism. Their estimate of Chiang’s character is substantially correct
                    but he may be capable, on grounds of expediency, to effect some governmental
                    changes, and, if he is not, it is very unlikely that he will be able to retain
                    his leadership once the war is over.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
