<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Second Secretary of Embassy in China ( (Davies))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="505"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/1–1049</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Second Secretary of Embassy in China</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">Davies</hi>)</head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">British Views on the China Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. John Keswick, Counselor of the British Embassy and Political Liaison Officer
                    to the Supreme Allied Commander, South East Asia, invited me to lunch on
                    November 16 primarily to question me, I believe, regarding conditions in
                    Communist China and the possibility of a <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>
                    between the Central Government and the Communists. I kept the conversation to
                    generalities.</p>
                <p>Mr. Keswick revealed in his conversation some points of view which are worth
                    recording. He exhibited no concern over the expansion of the Chinese Communists
                    in North China, seeming to take it pretty much for granted.</p>
                <p>He engaged in speculation over the Generalissimo’s ability to unify China. Chiang
                    had proved himself in the past, Keswick observed, to be a wiley hard-headed
                    politician. If he had not become inflexible, <pb facs="0715" n="701"
                        xml:id="pg_701"/> and if he was surrounded by accurate information, he
                    should be able to save the situation. Mr. Keswick wondered, however, whether
                    this was still the case. Furthermore, if a coalition were formed and the
                    Government reformed, many rice bowls would be broken. In other words, many of
                    Chiang’s closest advisers must be strongly opposed to any coalition with the
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>A possible solution which Keswick suggested was a government for Kuomintang China
                    in which the Generalissimo would occupy the position of the late Lin Sen and the
                    actual control would be in the hands of Sun Fo, T. V. Soong and Pai Chung-hsi.
                    Dr. Soong, however, had proved to be “disappointing”, Keswick remarked. Keswick
                    displayed no strong conviction or enthusiasm regarding this solution. In fact,
                    his attitude on the whole political situation was one of slightly perplexed
                    resignation.</p>
                <p>I asked him what British policy was. Keswick replied that it was to stay out of
                    involvement in the present Chinese political scene. He said that the British
                    felt that there was nothing that they could do at this stage to help the
                    situation; that they proposed to wait and see.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Davies</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-17">November 17,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
