<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-16T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-16T18:00:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Stettinius Mission/99a:
                        Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-16T19:00:00-04:00">May 16, 1944—7
                                p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>662. In interviews with Chinese Ambassador Koo<note n="55" xml:id="d67fn55">V. K. Wellington Koo.</note> in London on April 18 and 25, Under
                        Secretary Stettinius outlined the general course of his discussions with the
                            British.<note n="56" xml:id="d67fn56">A statement issued to the press on
                            April 29 jointly by the Under Secretary of State and the British Foreign
                            Secretary indicated that Mr. Stettinius had been visiting in London
                            during the past three weeks for informal and exploratory exchanges of
                            views and that opportunities had been taken to keep the Soviet and
                            Chinese Governments informed as to the course of the discussions.</note>
                        The Under Secretary also told Mr. Koo that an official of the British
                        Foreign Office had stated that the Chinese Embassy would be furnished a
                        written statement in regard to the American-British conversations.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Koo inquired whether the questions of India and of Far Eastern
                        territories (doubtless with Hong Kong in mind) had been discussed with the
                        British; the Under Secretary replied that they had not.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wei had a long interview with the Under Secretary today in which he was
                        informed of the London discussions.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>