<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="752" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d752">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">711.932/11</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in Ghina</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 551</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-08">March 8, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the final paragraph of the
                        Department’s 192, February 8, 10 p.m., there is enclosed copy of a
                        memorandum dated November 2, 1943<note n="5" xml:id="d752fn5">
                            <ref target="frus1943China#pg_714">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, China, p.
                            714</ref>.</note> in regard to informal conversations between Mr.
                        Stanley K. Hornbeck<note n="6" xml:id="d752fn6">Director of the Office of
                            Far Eastern Affairs; Adviser on Political Relations. August 1937 to
                            January 1944.</note> and officers of the Far Eastern Department of the
                        British Foreign Office which took place in London on <pb facs="1024" n="1010" xml:id="pg_1010"/> the subject of the negotiation of new
                        commercial treaties with China. There are also enclosed copies of memoranda
                        of conversations<note n="7" xml:id="d752fn7">See memoranda of conversations
                            by Mr. Hamilton on February 26, 1943; by Mr. Willoughby on May 7, 1943;
                            by Mr. Hornbeck on March 10, 1943; and oral statement of the Department
                            on May 6, 1943, <ref target="frus1943China#pg_710">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, China, pp.
                            710</ref>, <ref target="frus1943China#pg_712">712</ref>, <ref target="frus1943China#pg_769">769</ref>, and <ref target="frus1943China#pg_711">711</ref>, respectively.</note> held
                        during 1943 with Dr. T. V. Soong<note n="8" xml:id="d752fn8">Chinese
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> and with officers of the British
                        Embassy on the same subject which may be of interest to you.</p>
                    <p>As indicated in the first paragraph of the reference telegram, the Department
                        shares the views expressed in your 84, January 13, 10 a.m. and 99, January
                        15, 2 p.m.,<note n="9" xml:id="d752fn9">For telegram No. 99, see <ref target="#pg_1042">p. 1042</ref>.</note> and has noted from these and
                        other reports submitted by you that Chinese thinking on the subject of
                        future commercial relations with the United States and other foreign
                        countries has not yet definitely crystallized. Your suggestion that the
                        draft of our new commercial treaty, if presented to the Chinese, might
                        result in the drawing up of legislation along liberal lines is therefore of
                        especial interest. The Department hopes that you will do whatever may be
                        possible by informal conversations with leading Chinese officials to
                        convince them of the desirability of adopting liberal commercial policies
                        with respect to foreign trade.</p>
                    <p>As indicated in the reference telegram, work on the drafting of the treaty is
                        progressing but the drafting of a number of articles, particularly those
                        relating to the acquisition of land and other immovable property and to the
                        rights of corporations, present difficult problems. In connection with the
                        problem of the acquisition of land and other immovable property, the
                        Department would appreciate an expression of opinion by you in regard to the
                        intent and meaning of the right granted by the Chinese Government in recent
                        treaties concluded with Great Britain, Norway and Belgium<note n="10" xml:id="d752fn10">The three treaties deal with the termination of
                            extraterritorial rights of these countries in China and were signed at
                            Chungking in 1943. The British treaty was signed January 11, League of
                            Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ccv</hi>, p. 69; the
                            Norwegian treaty, November 10, <hi rend="italic">Overenskomster med
                                Fremmede Stater … 1940–1945</hi>, p. 107, or <hi rend="italic">The
                                Chinese Year Book</hi>, 1944–45, p. 526; and the Belgian treaty,
                            October 20, United Nations Treaty Series, vol. 14, p. 375.</note> to
                        “acquire and hold real property”. Is it your understanding that this
                        language does, in fact, grant to the nationals of the countries mentioned
                        the right to own real property on the same terms as Chinese nationals or is
                        it contemplated that foreign nationals may acquire and hold real property
                        subject to special and restrictive laws and regulations? The Department
                        hopes to receive your detailed comments on the draft after you have received
                        a copy thereof and have had an opportunity to study it, but in the meantime
                        would appreciate your views in regard to the specific question of the
                        acquisition of real property mentioned above.</p>
                    <pb facs="1025" n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/>
                    <p>Drafting of the consular provisions has been almost completed and it is
                        expected that a copy of these articles will be transmitted to you for your
                        comments at an early date. However, no final decision has been reached in
                        regard to the question of including these articles in a separate consular
                        convention. The Department is inclined to the view that a separate consular
                        convention would be preferable but certain technical difficulties might
                        arise in connection with the termination of the old treaties and agreements
                        with China unless the commercial treaty and the consular convention were
                        signed and ratified simultaneously.</p>
                    <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                    <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>