<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>17. Paper Prepared by the Division of Research for USSR and Eastern Europe,
                    Office of Intelligence Research</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="17"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                <head>17. Paper Prepared by the Division of Research for USSR and Eastern Europe,
                    Office of Intelligence Research<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d17fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, 761.00/1–156. Secret. Attached to the
                        source text was a brief memorandum of transmittal from Klessen to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HF1">Howe</persName>, January 11.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-01-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 11, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">THE SOVIET LEADERSHIP SITUATION AND THE <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss> PAPER OF 12/30/55 ENTITLED “SPECULATIONS ON SOVIET LEADERSHIP
                        SITUATION”<note n="2" xml:id="d17fn2">A copy of the paper, sent to Klessen
                        under cover of a memorandum of January 5 from <persName corresp="#p_HF1"
                            >Howe</persName> requesting his division’s comments, is <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.</hi> In the memorandum <persName corresp="#p_HF1"
                            >Howe</persName> noted that the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                        paper seemed “to present three different hypotheses and marshalls the
                        arguments behind each without making a selection.” Attached to the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> paper was a note dated December 30 from
                        Amory to <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Howe</persName>, in which Amory said he
                        was “sticking with the third hypothesis for the time being.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Most recent evidence supports the view that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> is the dominant figure in the Soviet hierarchy. He
                    has become the most important spokesman of the Soviet regime on both domestic
                    and foreign questions. It is likely that the hand of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> is behind a number of the shifts of local Party
                    officials which have occurred since the July announcement of the forthcoming
                    Party Congress, but not all officials affected can be directly linked to him. It
                    is possible that these local changes are designed to achieve two related
                    objectives: (1) they may serve to strengthen <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s influence throughout the system of territorial
                    Party organs and effect a “packing” of delegations to the congress with his
                    adherents, and (2) the shifts also raise a number of Party officials to
                    positions where they would be logical nominees for membership in the Central
                    Committee or other bodies to be elected at the congress. The rise of
                    Khrushchevism influence does not mean, however, that “collective leadership” has
                    lost all significance. “Collective leadership” never involved, and of course
                    does not now involve, the equal sharing of power at the top level. Appreciation
                    of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s superior position should
                    not lead, therefore, to the conclusion that he has secured, or is about to
                    secure, a STALIN-type prominence.</p>
                <p>1. The <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> paper <hi rend="italic">Speculations
                        on the Soviet Leadership Situation</hi> presents arguments for a series of
                    three hypotheses. The first, the approaching impregnability of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, is the most convincing of the
                    three, but appears, nevertheless, to be overdrawn. The other two, positing a
                    coalescence of anti-<persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> forces or
                    arguing for a continued effectiveness of collective leadership, are weakly
                    supported; in the case of the latter, over-weakly.</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="39" xml:id="pg_39"/>
                <p>2. The conclusion that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                    position “will become practically impregnable” after the 20th Party Congress
                    (February 1956) is supported by some dubious arguments. Leadership changes are
                    not as uniformly indicative of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                    >Khrushchev</persName>’s sway as the paper implies. The authors seem to have
                    overlooked the appointment to the Party’s Presidium last July of Suslov, whose
                    ties to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> are very tenuous.
                    Likewise, <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s influence is not
                    too evident in the appointment in 1955 of new deputy chairmen of the Council of
                    Ministers/Two of the new deputy chairmen cannot be directly linked with
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, nor can <persName
                        corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName>, Pervukhin, and Saburov, who were
                    elevated to First Deputy Chairmen. Even some of the recently-appointed
                    Secretaries of the <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s immediate lieutenants, cannot be
                    classified in any definite way as <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> protégés. The fact that <persName corresp="#p_MGM1"
                        >Malenkov</persName> still holds a position in the government and that there
                    was a long delay in the appointment of Matskevich as Minister of Agriculture
                    could also be interpreted as indicating resistance to <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s influence.</p>
                <p>Much of the argumentation on this topic is based on very capricious speculation.
                    Thus, the authors describe Yegorov and Konstantinov as <persName
                        corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> men, although the evidence for the
                    proposition is most inconclusive. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    is hastily dismissed as a deviationist. The formulation used by <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> for which he was forced to admit his
                    error was an incidental reference buried in a full dress foreign affairs
                        speech.<note n="3" xml:id="d17fn3">The party journal <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kommunist</hi> on October 8, 1955, published a letter of September 16
                        from <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, in which he recanted
                        comments he had made in his February 8, 1955, report to the Supreme Soviet
                        about the foundations of a socialist society having already been built in
                        the Soviet Union.</note> If it was considered at all serious ideologically
                    it seems that some attempt would have been made before October to correct it,
                    yet the speech was still being published in pamphlet form in minority languages
                    as late as September. The main reasons for the rebuff to <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> seems to be suggested by the timing of
                    the letter just prior to the Geneva Foreign Minister’s Conference. It appears
                    that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName> wished to emphasize their final
                    authority in the field of foreign policy. Soviet comment at the time suggested
                    that the censure was also related to the rapprochement with Yugoslavia, which
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> reportedly opposed.</p>
                <p>3. Reasoning and evidence buttressing the second and third hypotheses are
                    extremely weak. The proposition on anti-<persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> moves is introduced by three most doubtful points:
                    the so-called <persName corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> promotion to First
                    Deputy Chairman of the Council of Ministers, the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pravda-Izvestiya</hi> conflict over the corn program, and the appointment
                    of a “<persName corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> man,” i.e. Konstantinov,
                        <pb facs="0070" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> as agit-prop chief. The paper refers
                    to five possibly dissatisfied groups in the population. There is very little
                    evidence of this dissatisfaction, and in some cases even of the group’s
                    existence. The argument for dissatisfaction within the army element seems to
                    oppose the argument given earlier suggesting that the army will be faithful to
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>.</p>
                <p>The arguments presented to support the collective leadership hypothesis, the
                    third, do not stand up very well and in some cases might be used to prove the
                    opposite point. What is called “the best ammunition” is <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s and <persName corresp="#p_BNA1"
                        >Bulganin</persName>’s willingness to travel abroad for five weeks. Their
                    willingness to travel abroad so long could also be interpreted as reflecting
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s complete confidence in
                    the security of his position. The contention that <persName corresp="#p_MAI1"
                        >Mikoyan</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName> are
                    friends or “cronies” of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> does
                    not necessarily have anything to do with the existence of collective
                    leadership.</p>
                <p>4. The authors show a certain naivete and amateurishness in their handling of
                    evidence on the leadership question. This is exemplified in the reference to
                        <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kaganovich</persName> speaking “as one fully in
                    accord with current policies” at the October anniversary celebration, to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName> acting “as if he fully
                    approves the current state of affairs,” to <persName corresp="#p_BNA1"
                        >Bulganin</persName> as “content to play a supporting role,” and to
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName> as “prominently associated
                    with policies of the regime.” These postures and declarations are perfectly
                    standard and prove nothing about leadership struggles or harmony.</p>
                <p>The treatment of the military in the first part seems to be an especially bad
                    example of misuse of fact. The contention is made that the officer corps is
                    probably in a better position under <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName>
                    than it was under <persName corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName>. Apparently
                    this is based on the elevation of a number of general officers and marshals to
                    higher ranks in 1955. The authors seem to forget that there were a number of
                    promotions when <persName corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> was Chairman of
                    the Council of Ministers; that the call-up and discharge procedure was put on a
                    more regular basis in 1953; and that other privileges were granted and efforts
                    made to raise the prestige of the military before <persName corresp="#p_MGM1"
                        >Malenkov</persName> was ousted. It should be recalled, also, that
                        <persName>Marshal Zhukov</persName> was promoted to a top military position
                    and subsequently elected to the Party Central Committee in the period of
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> ascendancy. The purported
                    satisfaction of the military in 1955 over their budget is unconvincing. Although
                    the publicly-announced amount increased in 1955 over 1954, there is great
                    uncertainty as to the actual total.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
