<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-09-26T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-09-26T14:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                        <head>198. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United
                                Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 120.154/9–2656. Top Secret;
                                Limited Distribution. Repeated to Paris, Athens, and
                            Ankara.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-09-26T20:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">September 26,
                                        1956—8 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1692. Paris for <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName> only. Athens and
                            Ankara principal officers only. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> met yesterday evening with <persName corresp="#p_LSJSB1">Lloyd</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LBA1">Lennox-Boyd</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NSHA1">Nutting</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PCBP1">Peake</persName> (British Ambassador to Greece) and
                                <persName>Young</persName> (Head Southern Department). Agreed cover
                            was call on <persName corresp="#p_NSHA1">Nutting</persName> to discuss
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> affairs.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> briefly explained mission
                            and then raised question of whether in light of Suez situation, Her
                            Majesty’s Government anxious for early solution of Cyprus or whether it
                            was considered in British interest to hold line on island and proceed in
                            unhurried <pb facs="0439" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> manner with
                            Radcliffe constitution. There was no direct answer to this question,
                            which probably indicates that relation Cyprus and Suez had not been
                            thought through.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LSJSB1">Lloyd</persName> mentioned British query to
                            Department concerning our attitude inscription of Cyprus item by Greece
                            on provisional agenda General Assembly. It was explained that one
                            objective our suggested informal examination of situation was to
                            determine U.S. position in U.N. Speaking direct to <persName corresp="#p_LSJSB1">Lloyd</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NSHA1">Nutting</persName> said he thought it essential that British
                            complaint against Greece should be inscribed before final date of
                            provisional agenda October 12. <persName corresp="#p_LSJSB1">Lloyd</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LBA1">Lennox-Boyd</persName> seemed to agree and although British may
                            delay until near deadline, there seems no doubt they will submit their
                            complaint. They feel their case against Greece is a strong one and that
                            there is a possibility that its inscription may result in a negotiated
                            removal of it and the Greek item or the postponement of both to the tail
                            end of the agenda.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LBA1">Lennox-Boyd</persName> reported that
                            Radcliffe had departed for Cyprus and would return in about a week. He
                            expected that within 4 or 5 weeks from now Radcliffe would submit his
                            draft constitution to Her Majesty’s Government. If the government
                            approved the draft, he was willing to show it to the Greek Government
                            before promulgation. In response to questions, he stated that personally
                            he would be willing to accept Greek comments, and if there was real
                            evidence of good faith by Greece, he would be willing to allow
                            non-substantive changes if by so doing Greece’s ability to influence the
                            Ethnarchy would be strengthened. Although he could not predict what
                            Radcliffe’s recommendations would be, he felt certain that his draft
                            constitution would be a truly liberal one.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LBA1">Lennox-Boyd</persName> then volunteered his
                            position with respect to <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>: it was never intended that the exile would be
                            permanent; if the Archbishop would denounce terrorism now and for the
                            future, he would be allowed to return to Cyprus, but only after the new
                            constitution was in force and working; if even after constitution in
                            force and working, he still failed to denounce terrorism he would
                            nevertheless be released, free to go where he chose, except he would be
                            barred from Cyprus.</p>
                        <p>The Colonial Secretary then said he saw some possibility of a settlement
                            if Greece would completely separate self-government and
                            self-determination, settling now for the former, and if Turks could be
                            convinced that self-government was not an open door to
                            self-determination and that minority really protected.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> pointed out that from what
                                <persName corresp="#p_KC1">Karamanlis</persName> and Averoff have
                            told our representatives in Athens, the appeal to the U.S. to mediate
                            remarks by Averoff to Committee of 3 in Paris and to Senator <persName corresp="#p_GWF1">George</persName> and him, it was our opinion that
                            Greek Government <pb facs="0440" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> is very
                            anxious for settlement, fears its political position and feels that when
                            circumstances right it can influence Cypriots. <persName corresp="#p_PCBP1">Peake</persName> opinioned that <persName corresp="#p_KC1">Karamanlis</persName> is in no great danger of
                            being ousted and that talk of losing power and painting black picture of
                            what might succeed him was designed to “make our flesh creep”. No one
                            expressed agreement with this view.</p>
                        <p>There then followed general discussion of how Greek sincerity and
                            influence with Cypriots might be tested. <persName corresp="#p_KSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName> suggested that they might be asked to send
                            word secretly to Bishop of Kitium that leading Cypriots respond to
                            Radcliffe’s invitation to consult on constitution.</p>
                        <p>The meeting lasted an hour and of course there was much more general
                            conversation of the complex subject under discussion. It ended with
                                <persName corresp="#p_LSJSB1">Lloyd</persName> saying that they
                            would discuss the matter, think it over and communicate with us as soon
                            as possible.</p>
                        <p>The meeting was cordial, serious and our desire to be helpful was clearly
                                appreciated.<note n="2" xml:id="d198fn2">In telegram 1254, October
                                5, for <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> and principal
                                officers only, the Department made a number of comments on telegram
                                1692 that were intended for possible use in discussions with the
                                British. Among its comments, the Department noted that if the United
                                Kingdom was determined to inscribe the item regarding Greece’s
                                intervention in the Cyprus problem, it might be best to make the
                                item of a general character without naming Greece. With respect to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>, the Department
                                added, any proposals must be ultimately acceptable to the Greek
                                Cypriots whose representatives insist that there can be no progress
                                without the Archbishop. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                120.1540/9–2656)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AWW1"><hi rend="strong">Aldrich</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>