<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="29" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                        <head>29. Intelligence Report Prepared by the Division of Research for USSR
                            and Eastern Europe, Office of Intelligence Research<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d29fn1">Source: Department of State, PPS
                                Files: Lot 66 D 487, USSR. Confidential. Attached to the source text
                                was a memorandum of transmittal from <persName corresp="#p_AWPJ1">Armstrong</persName> to the Acting Secretary of State, March
                                14, in which <persName corresp="#p_AWPJ1">Armstrong</persName> wrote
                                that the 49-page report, “while fairly long, is interesting reading
                                and covers many points of significance to US policy makers.” A note
                                on the source text indicates that the report was based on
                                information available through March 5.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">IR–7205</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-03-06"><hi rend="italic">March 6,
                                1956</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">THE TWENTIETH CONGRESS OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF THE SOVIET
                            UNION</p>
                        <p rend="center">Abstract</p>
                        <p>The first public criticism of STALIN by his successors stands out as the
                            highlight and main innovation of the Twentieth Congress of the Communist
                            Party of the Soviet Union (February 14 to 25). Otherwise, the conclave
                            served largely as an authoritative occasion for the Soviet rulers to
                            confirm and formalize their current policies.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Criticism of STALIN.</hi> In the nearly three years
                            since his death, STALIN’s stature has been progressively reduced. The
                            new regime shrank the symbol of STALIN largely by withholding adulation
                            from him and concentrating it entirely on Lenin. The Congress has now
                            marked a further distinctive step as the rulers took to open attack.
                            Their criticism centered chiefly on the ill-effects of one-man rule,
                            with its glorification of an all-wise leader. Beyond this, however,
                            while they neither completely buried STALIN nor brought into question
                            his basic state policies, they ranged critically over many fields,
                            including economic development, ideology, law and foreign affairs.</p>
                        <p>The Soviet rulers are rewriting history and rehabilitating some of
                            STALIN’s victims; how much further they will go remains to be seen.
                            Clearly to find clay feet on the infallible demi-god whose rule for
                            three decades encompassed all facets of Soviet life will have widespread
                            effects—but effects whose manifestations will depend upon a whole
                            complex of related factors.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Collective Rule.</hi> The attack on one-man rule served
                            to underscore the virtue claimed for collective leadership which,
                            formally enshrined as a guiding principle, has thus become an obstacle
                            to concentration of overwhelming power in the hands of one individual.
                            That the present ruling group is stable appears from the absence of
                            changes among full members of the Party Presidium. New and younger blood
                            has been brought to the top circle by the candidate members, expanded to
                            six.</p>
                        <pb facs="0094" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                        <p>Inclusion in the latter group of <persName>Marshal Zhukov</persName>, the
                            first professional military chief to reach Presidium level, appears to
                            represent both recognition of him personally and appreciation of the
                            military ingredient in policy-making rather than an indication that the
                            armed forces are growing to be a distinct political force.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> received no special
                            build-up at the Congress, but his leadership within the ruling group was
                            strengthened by the number of new Presidium candidate members and new
                            members of the Central Committee who have had past links with him.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs.</hi> In foreign affairs the Soviet
                            rulers claimed major successes for their current policy and announced
                            they would pursue it with greater vigor. They set forth as the
                            underlying basis of their policy the thesis that peaceful coexistence is
                            “the only alternative” to nuclear war, and they indicated that the USSR
                            will energetically champion coexistence as an activist program aimed at
                            undermining Western defense efforts. They called for the development of
                            friendly relations throughout the world, and especially with the
                            underdeveloped countries. Although this policy was to apply also to the
                            major Western powers, it was not meant to imply concessions on major
                            East-West issues. Their goal was evidently to remove apprehensions of a
                            Soviet threat and instead to imbue the USSR with an air of
                            respectability, normalcy, and tolerance.</p>
                        <p>To further this impression, the Soviet rulers readjusted their
                            ideological stance: they stressed the preventability rather than the
                            inevitability of war and, without renouncing violence, they sanctioned
                            for foreign Communists a “non-violent” acquisition of power by
                            parliamentary means. They sought both to assure non-Communists that the
                            USSR is not wedded to violence and to reassure Communists that a period
                            of coexistence would not undercut their struggle for the promised
                            ultimate victory of Communism nor jeopardize the prospect of winning
                            it.</p>
                        <p>Any improvement in state-to-state relations between Communists and
                            non-Communists would involve no ideological reconciliation. The speakers
                            confidently predicted the inevitable world triumph of Communism on the
                            grounds that Soviet military power would protect the Soviet base; that
                            continuing Soviet economic successes would inspire others to take the
                            Communist path; and that a majority of mankind, although representing
                            different views, was already joining together in “one mighty stream”
                            that would wash out the underpinnings of historically-doomed
                            capitalism.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Domestic Innovations.</hi> Traditional emphasis on
                            enforced industrialization and on the maintenance of high level
                            armaments continued at the Congress. It approved the Sixth Five-Year
                            Plan, announced in January, adding a provision for shortening the
                            work-week to 40–41 hours before 1960. A breakdown of investment figures
                            for 1956–60 <pb facs="0095" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/> showed a marked
                            similarity, with some deviation in favor of agriculture, to the pattern
                            implemented in 1951–55.</p>
                        <p>The leaders showed some concern over living standards and promised to
                            bring up the level of the lowest-paid workers and pensioners while
                            retaining the present policy of a sharply differentiated income
                            structure. Another innovation was the proposal to establish fee-charging
                            boarding schools. Although justified in part as a way of meeting the
                            problem of children who lack adequate parental supervision, these
                            schools will probably be select elitetraining institutions.</p>
                        <p>The importance of these developments on the internal scene was less than
                            the implications of the attack on STALIN, which opens the way to a
                            re-evaluation of all sectors of Soviet life. In this sense the Congress
                            could turn out to be, in <persName corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName>’s words, “the most important Congress” in Soviet
                            Communist Party history since Lenin’s time.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>