<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>312. Despatch From the Embassy in Greece to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec12oVQ7f61LEbi0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Domestic politics</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="312"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                <head>312. Despatch From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Greece</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d312fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.81/11–457. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 308</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-11-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 4, 1957</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Greece’s Disengagement from United States Policy</item>
                </list>
                <p>In recent weeks and months the Embassy has reported to the Department a series of
                    increasingly frequent instances wherein Greece and the United States have found
                    themselves, primarily in the political and psychological spheres, at odds on
                    major and minor matters of policy. For several weeks officers of the Embassy
                    have studied these instances in their contexts and believe that they are of
                    sufficient importance to constitute a trend which, … for lack of a better label,
                    may be described as a “disengagement” on the part of Greece from the essentially
                    “American” policy which she has followed since the end of the Second World
                    War.</p>
                <p>This recently accelerated disengagement has become manifest in three fields: (1)
                    in Greek domestic politics and the Greek national psychology; (2) in matters
                    affecting the Middle East; and (3) in Greece’s attitude toward Communists,
                    Communism and the Communist Bloc of states.</p>
                <p>It should be said at the outset that this despatch is considered to be chiefly an
                    analysis of a trend which the Embassy considers to be of major importance to
                    United States and Western interests in this <pb facs="0628" n="598"
                        xml:id="pg_598"/> part of the world; it is not intended to be a balanced
                    report of the entire picture of Greece and her domestic and foreign policies of
                    the moment. Furthermore, in order to identify for the Department in the clearest
                    and briefest manner possible the factors which constitute this now recognizable
                    trend, no attempt has been made to provide bulky documentation to substantiate
                    the thesis. However, few items will be mentioned in this despatch which are not
                    already to be found in the Department’s files among previous telegrams and
                    reports submitted to Washington by the Embassy and by other United States
                    agencies operating in Greece. Here it is our purpose to tie together all the
                    factors of this trend primarily to identify and assess them, so that having once
                    been recognized they may be dealt with by the Embassy and the Department.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary and Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Greece today remains formally and officially tied to the United States and her
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Allies and will continue to be so tied
                    for the foreseeable future. The United States is—and for some time to come will
                    probably remain—the paramount foreign power in this country, as it has for the
                    past ten years. But we are passing through a period when our influence and
                    prestige among the Greek people and with the Greek Government are undergoing a
                    reassessment and readjustment in a changed world situation. We can no longer be
                    as certain as we have been in the past that we shall have Greece’s support in
                    foreign policy matters that are critical to us. In the Middle East our policies
                    and our actions in the past few years, with very few exceptions, have been the
                    contrary of what Greece has considered to be her own best interests. In the
                    Cyprus issue most of all we have failed in Greek eyes to support the Greek
                    position, and to the Greeks there is no more important problem in this decade.
                    Toward the Soviet Union and the Eastern Bloc Greece’s attitude has undergone an
                    accelerated process of softening in the past year and a half and she less
                    frequently asks for or accepts our advice in her dealings with the Bloc. She
                    feels that we have ignored what she considers to be her special position in the
                    Middle East and that we have supported more strongly her ancient enemy, Turkey,
                    instead. The other reasons for this drift toward divergence and disengagement
                    are manifold; some are of a minor and transitory nature, but others are deep,
                    permanent, even normal and natural, and will be difficult to correct. Unless
                    they are corrected, however, there is a distinct possibility that Greece will
                    find herself ultimately in the neutral bloc or in a “non-bloc” alignment where,
                    we have reason to fear, a growing number of Greeks today already feel themselves
                    psychologically.</p>
                <pb facs="0629" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/>
                <p>[Here follow sections entitled: “Domestic Scene”; “Greece, the US and the Middle
                    East”; and “Attitude Toward the Communist Bloc”.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The General Perspective</hi>
                </p>
                <p>By the nature of its subject this despatch has had to paint a rather dark picture
                    of the current state of Greek-American relations. While it treats admittedly of
                    only one side of the whole story it is a side which, until recent weeks, had
                    been of very small significance and which was not an important factor in our
                    relations with Greece. The trend toward disengagement—or, as Liberal Leader
                        <persName corresp="#p_PG1">George Papandreou</persName> has phrased it,
                    “psychological dis-association”—of Greece from American policy has recently
                    become a fact, recognized and deplored by the Embassy as well as by responsible
                    figures in public life in Greece. We are certain from remarks made by the Prime
                    Minister to the Ambassador that no one deplores this drift more than <persName
                        corresp="#p_KC1">Constantine Karamanlis</persName>, himself, who assures us
                    that regardless of the prominence of the present trend Greece will remain loyal
                    to her <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> commitments. Similar sentiments
                    have been expressed to us privately by other high Government personages and by
                    members of the Opposition as well. Unfortunately the latter will undoubtedly
                    proceed as usual in the current session of Parliament to berate the Government
                    publicly for being “American lackeys”. Politics in Greece is like that. The
                    unfortunate thing about this whole matter is that no one in public life, with
                    the exception of the King, has expressed any strong feelings of late that Greece
                    must resist a drift away from her <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ties and
                    toward a softening attitude on Communism.</p>
                <p>On the economic side, the Embassy feels that there do not exist the same grounds
                    for concern as on the political. Greece’s volume of trade is 90 percent with the
                    Free World and cannot be easily or abruptly changed. The economic ministers of
                    the present Government are realistically aware of Greece’s continuing dependence
                    on the West as a market for her exports and as a source for the investment
                    capital which she needs. Also realistically (and privately) they are willing to
                    face up to a gradual tapering off of American economic aid, knowing that less
                    aid is in itself a measure of Greece’s growing economic prosperity, as its
                    capacity to absorb US surpluses decreases. Their sense of duty to their country
                    will, however, require them to protest loudly at any mention of decreased
                    assistance.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Indeed a similar report could be compiled containing counter-indications to many
                    of the factors treated in this despatch. Nevertheless, <pb facs="0630" n="600"
                        xml:id="pg_600"/> it is hoped that the Department will give careful and
                    thoughtful study to the contents of the present despatch, which represents the
                    serious and well considered view of the Embassy that we have reached a new stage
                    in Greek-American relations in which many of our decade-old assumptions and
                    rules-of-thumb are no longer valid. During the current process of Greek
                    readjustment every move on our part which affects Greece assumes a double
                    importance.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PJK1">
                            <hi rend="strong">JK Penfield</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
