<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>322. Telegram From the Embassy in Turkey to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-04-01T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-04-01T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyb5QQsNI4WeVPs" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military capabilities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-04-01T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-04-01T09:00:00-05:00" n="322"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d322">
                <head>322. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Turkey</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d322fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 682.87/4–155. Secret; Priority.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-04-01T16:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 1, 1955—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1173. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1170, April 1.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d322fn2">In telegram 1170, the Embassy in Ankara reported the
                        substance of a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_NBM1">Nuri
                            Birgi</persName> to discuss developments in the Middle East. <persName
                            corresp="#p_Birgi1">Birgi</persName>, who had called on <persName
                            corresp="#p_MA1">Menderes</persName>’ instructions, indicated that the
                        Prime Minister believed that the “weight of maneuvers and attacks” against
                        the Northern Tier defense concept was coming not only from the Arabs, but
                        from the French and the Israelis. The attacks, <persName corresp="#p_Birgi1"
                            >Birgi</persName> continued, “are really getting to be too much for
                        Turco-Iraqis shoulders alone.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</note> There
                    is so much sleight-of-hand going on in <gloss target="#t_MID1">Mid</gloss>-East
                    at present, it is hard to keep the eye on the ball. Frankly, I feel our Turkish
                    friends have demonstrated they have rather clearer eye-sight than some of the
                    rest of us. I cannot avoid feeling we are letting them down badly—and against
                    our own interest. “Northern Tier” is our concept, and in my mind, a sound
                    one—not likely to add great material strength to free world military <pb
                        facs="0660" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> capabilities in the near future, but
                    contributing (as one can judge by Moscow’s violent opposition) an immediately
                    powerful deterrent. I fear that such assurances as were given the Egyptian
                    Ambassador in Washington (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> [<hi
                        rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                    </hi>] 1230, March 30<note n="3" xml:id="d322fn3">In telegram 1230, March 29,
                        the Department informed the Egyptian Ambassador that the United States was
                        not trying to prevent an Egyptian pact with the Syrians and the Saudis,
                        although it indicated that the American people would favor a Turco-Iraqi
                        pact directed against a “communist menace”, rather than a
                        Syrian-Saudi-Egyptian pact, which might have “other objectives”. The
                        Department also suggested that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                        might wish to consider a defense arrangement that might include Turkey and
                        Iraq. <persName>Warren</persName> was also informed that the United States
                        favored the preservation of the status quo regarding the adherence of
                        additional Arab States to the Turco-Iraqi pact. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.,</hi> 682.87/3–3055)</note>) seriously undercuts the position we
                    have encouraged the Turks to take by our support of the Turco-Pakistani and
                    Turco-Iraqi pacts;<note n="4" xml:id="d322fn4">On April 2, 1954, Pakistan and
                        Turkey concluded an Agreement for Friendly Cooperation; for text, see <hi
                            rend="italic">AFP: Basic Documents, 1950–1955,</hi> p. 1253. On February
                        24, 1955, Turkey, Iraq, and Pakistan concluded a Pact of Mutual Cooperation.
                        For text of the accord, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> p. 1257.</note>
                    and that it may prolong the life of a Syrian Government hostile to us, encourage
                    the Egyptians in a neutralist, if not actively anti-western course, and long
                    delay the construction of a Middle East barricade deterring Soviet designs. I
                    hope the desk will give prompt consideration to the Prime Minister’s
                    observations reported in reference telegram and give me a positive reply for
                        him.<note n="5" xml:id="d322fn5">In telegram 1252, April 2, the Department
                        asked <persName>Warren</persName> to assure the Turkish Government that the
                        United States “strongly supports” the Turco-Iraqi Pact, but that it
                        continued to doubt the desirability of applying pressure on Iran to join the
                        pact. Nor did the Department feel that the time was right for US adherence
                        to the pact. (Department of State, Central Files, 682.87/4–155)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Warren</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
