<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>81. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in the
                    Philippines</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-10-29T17:23:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-10-29T17:23:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-10-29T17:23:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-10-29T17:23:00-05:00" n="81"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                <head>81. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Philippines</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d81fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 761.00/10–2957. Secret; Priority. <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1"
                            >Roger</persName> Channel. Drafted by Cumming and cleared in substance
                        with <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-10-29T17:23:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 29, 1957—5:23 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1376. For <persName corresp="#p_BCEC1">Bohlen</persName> from Cumming. Fully
                    realize your absorption Philippine elections and physical remoteness Soviet
                    scene. Many <pb facs="0203" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> here would be grateful
                    however receive your interpretation current internal Soviet crisis. May well be
                    even prior your receipt this message Soviets will have made authoritative
                    release which would provide most useful material for interpretation which at
                    present difficult even with all the sources available Washington. Following
                    summary available facts may be of interest to you even if you have not time to
                    give us your reactions no matter how tentative: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName> returned 26 October from
                            three-week trip Yugoslavia and Albania. That morning <gloss
                                target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> gave him full title Minister of
                            Defense; in afternoon <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> dropped
                            Minister of Defense title in reporting his departure from Albania.
                            Announcement release from Defense post made by <gloss target="#t_TASS1"
                                >TASS</gloss> evening hours Moscow that day.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>At midday arrival Moscow <persName corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName>
                            received by military, press and Foreign Office personnel as well as
                            Albanian and Yugoslav diplomatic representative. No top Party members
                            present.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, <persName
                                corresp="#p_BNA1">Bulganin</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName> arrived one hour late at
                            Iranian reception early evening same day.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Indications are Central Committee in session since about 28
                            Oct.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Foreign communist correspondents Moscow indicated in despatches that
                                <gloss target="#t_IDEA1">idea</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName> promotion (namely release
                            from Defense duties for broader political duties) should be discarded
                            and that feeling perplexity prevailed Moscow. Boffa, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Unita</hi> correspondent Moscow advised no reliable briefing
                            available.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Evening 28 October CBS correspondent Schorr suggested through Soviet
                            censorship that issue broader than merely struggle between <persName
                                corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName>; conflict concerned internal
                            rather than foreign issues; that most Western speculation was wide of
                            mark; that outcome would have extremely farreaching implications; and
                            that tipoff would come in appearance of portraits of Soviet Presidium
                            members in preparation for Fortieth Anniversary “whoever they may be at
                            that time.” (These have not yet appeared.)</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>One factor current situation may be old issue Army-Party relationship
                            military and party press recent months indicate see-saw battle this
                            issue.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial 28th and other Soviet press
                            items emphasize Party supremacy in all matters; Party leadership to
                            victory World War II. <hi rend="italic">Red Star</hi> stresses Party
                            control and cites fable of officer Velikii Luki whose head turned by
                            overpraise, considered himself above reproach and led by conceit to
                            severe Party punishment.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Reliable … source reports news seriously shocked and disturbed members
                            Soviet Officer corps. Other reliable … info reports replacement of
                            Shtemenko who had been Chief GRU since some time in summer 1956 by
                            Shalin who was previous GRU chief. <pb facs="0204" n="174"
                                xml:id="pg_174"/> Thus, seems possible decision remove <persName
                                corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName>, reassign Rokossovsky and remove
                            Shtemenko all made 22 Oct.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Announcement Rokossovsky’s assignment command Trans-Caucasus military
                            district first appeared Tblisi local press 23 October replayed Moscow
                            press 25 October.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>AP and <gloss target="#t_UP1">UP</gloss> despatches datelined Moscow
                            have just arrived reporting <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                                >Khrushchev</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BNA1"
                                >Bulganin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MAI1"
                                >Mikoyan</persName> with other unnamed Presidium members
                            unexpectedly showed up at Turkish Embassy reception tonight. <persName
                                corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> told reporters <persName
                                corresp="#p_ZGK1">Zhukov</persName> would be given a new position
                            “according to his experience and qualifications” but no decision yet
                            made. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> said reports
                            that Central Committee in Session were made up by correspondents. Also
                            said his presence at Turkish party could be interpreted as peace
                            gesture.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>If you care to make any comments they should be sent through <persName
                                corresp="#p_MSRM1">Roger</persName> channel.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
