<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="215" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d215">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">865.85/482</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-17">April 17, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging"> Argentine Ambassador, Sr. Don Felipe A.
                                    Espil;</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Colombian Ambassador, Sr. Dr. Gabriel
                                    Turbay;</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Brazilian Ambassador, Mr. Carlos
                                    Martins;</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mexican Ambassador, Sr. Dr. Don Francisco
                                    Castillo Nájera;</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Chilean Chargé d’Affaires, Sr. Don
                                    Guillermo Gazitúa;</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Under Secretary, Mr. Welles.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>I saw this afternoon the Argentine, Colombian, Brazilian, and Mexican
                            Ambassadors, and the Counselor of the Chilean Embassy in the absence of
                            the Ambassador.</p>
                        <pb facs="0199" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/>
                        <p>I gave them copies of the draft resolution which this Government intends
                            to offer at the next extraordinary meeting of the inter-American
                            Economic and Financial Advisory Committee, and advised them that the
                            full text was being communicated to all of the American Governments in
                            order that this Government might receive the views and suggestions of
                            the other Governments of this Hemisphere.</p>
                        <p>I impressed upon them all my belief that in the interest of continental
                            solidarity it was most desirable that this very important problem be
                            settled by unanimous agreement at the earliest possible moment and said
                            that I trusted this could be achieved before the meeting on April 22. I
                            said that if the matter dragged on in open discussions of a
                            controversial character, Axis propagandists would of course avail
                            themselves with glee of such an opportunity, and I felt sure the result
                            would be highly detrimental to every one of the American countries. I
                            said I believed that the draft offered for their consideration
                            harmonized with the various conflicting viewpoints and I earnestly hoped
                            it would receive the approval of their Governments.</p>
                        <p>All of the Ambassadors expressed their own personal approval of the
                            draft, but the Argentine and Brazilian Ambassadors said they felt the
                            real difficulty from the standpoint of their Governments was to find out
                            whether the British Government would withdraw its present objection to
                            the utilization by their countries of these ships.</p>
                        <p>I said that obviously it was the purpose of this Government to use the
                            ships in its own ports in such a way as to promote the interests of
                            inter-American trade and the interest of assistance to Great Britain, to
                            which, of course, we were completely committed. I said that under these
                            conditions it seemed to me probable that the British Government would
                            adopt a reasonable and friendly attitude in the matter and that it
                            seemed to me more than likely that the British Government would
                            negotiate a satisfactory agreement on this point with each of the
                            Governments concerned. I said that this Government, of course, would
                            make every endeavor to have a satisfactory solution of this point
                            reached.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>