<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of the Navy ( (Knox) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec3fxRcXXIdLOFDO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006620"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naval operations</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00111 A.R./1447</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Knox</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-19">September 19,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The staff agreements that we now have with
                    various American Republics provide that their harbors, ports, bases and
                    facilities will become available to the Armed Forces of the United States only
                    in case they are involved in repelling non-American aggression, either by
                    invitation of the country attacked or by a special inter-American agreement.</p>
                <p>There are no general agreements permitting the Armed Forces of the United States
                    to use the harbors or port facilities of any of the American Republics under
                    present conditions without special arrangements in each case.</p>
                <p>The strategical situation is such that our Naval Forces now engaged in operations
                    defending the Western Hemisphere should be permitted to use the port facilities
                    of a number of the American Republics, with the least possible formality.</p>
                <p>At the request of the Navy Department, arrangements have been made with Brazil to
                    use the port facilities of Recife and Bahia. Negotiations are now pending for
                    using the port facilities of Natal, Maceio, Guayaquil, Callao, Valparaiso,
                    Antofagasta, and an anchorage in the Galapágos Islands. As our Naval operations
                    increase in intensity, it will be most important to have available the
                    facilities of many other ports of the American Republics, both on the Atlantic
                    and Pacific Coasts.</p>
                <p>It is suggested that broad agreements for the use of the desired ports and
                    harbors, under present international conditions, might be arranged by means of a
                    liberal interpretation of the Declaration of Uruguay, recently announced by the
                    Uruguayan Government.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/>
                <p>The original Declaration of June 18, 1917 was as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“That no American country, which in defense of its own rights, should
                            find itself in a state of war with nations of other continents, will be
                            treated as a belligerent; and that existing decrees which may be in
                            contravention to this resolution shall be null and of no effect.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>As a clarification of this Declaration, The United States Minister in Uruguay
                    sent a despatch to the Secretary of State, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Uruguayan Minister for Foreign Affairs authorizes me to say to
                            Department of State that all ships of the American Navy, of any kind
                            whatsoever, may now and henceforth visit the ports of Uruguay, for any
                            purpose whatsoever, where they will be received as friend, and not as
                            belligerent, and without restrictions.”<note n="16" xml:id="d28fn1">
                                <ref target="frus1917Supp01v01#pg_300">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917, supp. 1, p.
                                    300</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is understood that a number of the other American Republics have recently
                    adhered to the Declaration of Uruguay, but under what conditions is not
                    known.</p>
                <p>In the opinion of the Navy Department, it is highly important that a definite
                    understanding be reached with all the American Republics, regarding the
                    Declaration of Uruguay and, if possible, secure the following: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Adherence of all American Republics to the Declaration of
                            Uruguay.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>All to give the same liberal interpretation as expressed by Uruguay in
                            1917.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Permission for United States Naval Forces to use their port facilities
                            now, as well as in case of our becoming a belligerent, by simple
                            notification of entry, and without restriction as to time limits of the
                            visits.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank Knox</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
