<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Armour) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-10-02T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-10-02T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-02T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-02T16:00:00-05:00" n="370"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d370">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">835.796/186: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-02T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >October 2, 1941—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7:28 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1070. Department’s 721, September 30, midnight. The Embassy feels that there is
                    little or no opportunity of Air France’s permit being revoked by the Argentine
                    Government at this time. This opinion is shared by Bradley, president of local
                    company for Pan American Airways, who is well acquainted with Argentina’s air
                    transportation situation. However Bradley expresses the personal opinion that
                    Air France planes should not be allowed to operate under French registry if the
                    line does not actually connect with France. It is doubtful whether the increased
                    Panagra services between Buenos Aires and Santiago would be sufficient argument
                    to induce Argentina to revoke Air France permit and it is felt that the RFC
                    project should not be mentioned at this time. Furthermore, it is believed that
                    Argentina would like to have as many air services as possible of different
                    nationalities as evidenced by fact that it countenances Lati.</p>
                <p>As mentioned in Embassy’s 1052, September 29, general manager of YPF denied
                    possibility of contract with Lati for 100,000 liters monthly but admitted Lati
                    was receiving small normal quantities for Argentine requirements. Last night a
                    member of the Embassy staff informally discussed this matter with another
                    official of YPF named Benassar who disclaimed knowledge of even the small
                    monthly sales by YPF to Lati. There seems to be no doubt that YPF is selling
                    Lati approximately 10,000 liters a month which possibly bears out a suspicion
                    that one section of YPF does not know what another section is doing. Benassar
                    did say that an application had just come across his desk for 100,000 liters of
                    aviation gasoline to be shipped to a firm in Porto Alegre whose name he did not
                    recall. He said he would recommend rejection of the application and that he
                    could count on the support of virtually all YPF officials.</p>
                <p>While it now appears unlikely that YPF will continue with any negotiations it
                    might have had under consideration for sale of 100,000 liters monthly to Lati
                    there are several factors which are still questionable. In the first place I am
                    not certain whether my representations <pb facs="0358" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/>
                    to the Foreign Office on this matter have been transmitted in full force to YPF.
                    It is also possible that high Argentine officials might look with approval on
                    negotiations with Lati. There is also the apparent lack of coordination within
                    YPF itself.</p>
                <p>Consequently I feel that the only way we are going to get definite information is
                    by asking the Argentine Government for a statement as to its policy concerning a
                    difference of opinion vis-à-vis Lati. I believe such an inquiry would be more
                    effective if it were made by the Department to Espil.<note n="60"
                        xml:id="d370fn1">Felipe A. Espil, Argentine Ambassador in the United
                        States.</note> At the same time and while I appreciate the position outlined
                    in telegram No. 1299 of September 17, 8 p.m., from the Embassy at Rio de Janeiro
                    to the Department,<note n="61" xml:id="d370fn2">Not printed.</note> I feel that
                    we should be prepared to justify our position in asking Argentina not to sell to
                    Lati when Intava is selling to both Condor and Lati in Brazil and Condor in
                    Argentina.</p>
                <p>Paraphrase to Rio de Janeiro by courier.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Armour</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
