<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Brazil ( (Burdett) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d498</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">498</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="498"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d498">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/5353/7</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Burdett</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 4149</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-28">January 28,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Embassy’s
                    despatch No. 4100 of January 16, 1941 (File No. 830),<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d498fn1">Not printed.</note> concerning the staff conversations held
                    between representatives of the Brazilian and United States Navies.</p>
                <p>A note was sent to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on January 13, 1941, and a
                    copy transmitted to the Department with the abovementioned despatch. This note
                    requested information on the action taken on the agreements reached in the staff
                    conversations. I have called several times at the Foreign Office in an endeavor
                    to expedite a reply to this note.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, Captain A. T. Beauregard, United States Navy, Chief of the
                    United States Naval Mission to Brazil, has conferred with the Minister of
                    Marine. Captain Beauregard has handed to the Embassy a memorandum concerning
                    this conference. Copies are transmitted herewith. It is requested that a copy be
                    sent to the Navy Department.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Burdett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0502" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the United States Naval Mission
                            to Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Beauregard</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chargé in Brazil</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Burdett</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <p>On January 27, 1941 in an interview with the Minister of Marine that official
                        showed the Chief of Naval Mission the substance of his reply to a question
                        from the Foreign Office as to what was being done to make ready for
                        execution the provisions of the Staff Conversations, which in effect was
                        mainly as follows:— <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Studies and plans were being developed in all the subjects
                                mentioned in the Staff Conversations.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Inability to receive war material at any early date from the
                                United States retarded the development of preparedness.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The Minister of Marine, himself, planned to visit the North of
                                Brazil on a cruiser to determine the material required for the
                                development of facilities and defenses at Belem and at Natal, and
                                for the militarization of Fernando Noronha and Trinidad.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The Foreign Office was urged to use diplomatic means to secure
                                promise of release and delivery of needed war material from the
                                United States.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>An officer had been sent to the United States to cooperate in the
                                preparation of codes and ciphers for Pan-American use.
                                (Note:—Lieut-Comdr. Harper of the Naval Mission has already prepared
                                a cipher based on the International Signal Code which is available
                                for sudden emergency use).</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Chief of Naval Mission impressed upon the Minister of Marine the
                        following opinions:— <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Brazil was not as seriously alarmed over the world situation as
                                perhaps she should be.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Brazil seemed more concerned over future economic independence
                                than immediate preparedness.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>If Brazil were suddenly attacked, the defenses should be such as
                                to hold out until reenforcements from the United States could
                                arrive.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Reenforcements arriving should have safe and protected anchorages
                                to which to proceed.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Captains of the Ports did not at present possess even armed tugs
                                with which to enforce any regulations.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Information was to the effect that nothing had been done toward
                                manufacture or acquisition of submarine nets.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The development of Brazilian-made torpedoes would probably take
                                several years and the destroyers now being built might upon
                                completion find themselves without torpedoes. The Minister stated
                                that he did not like Bliss torpedoes, and that even if he did, only
                                old Marks could be supplied and not the latest models.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The Brazilian Ministry of Marine should keep the United States
                                Government constantly informed of the revised items it desired to
                                obtain by purchase, because changed conditions might at any time
                                make certain material suddenly available.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0503" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/>
                    <p>The Minister of Marine was asked if a copy of the Naval Staff
                            Conversations<note n="7" xml:id="d498fn2">These Naval Staff
                            Conversations, carried on by the Chief of the Brazilian Naval General
                            Staff, Vice Admiral José Machado de Castro Silva, and the Chief of the
                            United States Naval Mission, Captain A. T. Beauregard, resulted in a
                            statement of “Understanding and Agreement” in which (1) the necessity
                            was recognized of keeping open Brazilian ports and airfields in case of
                            attack until reinforcements could arrive from the United States; (2) the
                            United States agreed to assist with armed forces in meeting any attack
                            from a non-American state or from a Fifth Column; (3) the United States
                            promised to aid in procuring armaments and training personnel; (4) both
                            parties agreed to the desirability of full exchange of information, of
                            developing a suitable code and cipher, and of building up intelligence
                            services; (5) when necessary, Brazil agreed to place at the disposition
                            of United States naval forces, naval and air bases, anchorages, and port
                            facilities, and agreed to allow “advance discreet operations” in the
                            Natal area. The approval of the Navy Department of this understanding
                            was indicated on November 14, 1940. (882.24/256½)</note> had been given
                        to the President of Brazil.<note n="8" xml:id="d498fn3">Getulio
                            Vargas.</note> He replied in the negative but stated that they had been
                        explained to him. It was suggested that if the President would approve the
                        bases of those conversations and indicate that he was willing to allocate
                        funds for their execution, the Minister of Marine would be in a position to
                        go ahead at once on many items. The Minister of Marine stated that he would
                        consult with the Foreign Minister toward securing <hi rend="italic"
                            >governmental</hi> approval of the principles embodied in the Staff
                        Conversations, which if obtained, should give an impetus to activities of
                        preparation.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Beauregard</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
