<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-05-24T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-05-24T18:00:00-05:00" n="557" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d557">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M)/2099: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-05-24T19:00:00-04:00">May 24, 1941—7
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>339. Your telegram no. 525 of May 23 has been discussed with the Federal
                            Loan Agency. The Agency had always understood from <pb facs="0556" n="546" xml:id="pg_546"/> the beginning of the negotiations that the
                            work of purchasing from the Brazilian producers and of assembling and
                            checking the various materials at concentration points, which presumably
                            would be Brazilian ports, be carried on by the Bank of Brazil or other
                            agency set up by the Brazilian Government. In fact the Federal Loan
                            Agency was advised of the appointment of Mr. Filho<note n="5" xml:id="d557fn1">Francisco Alves dos Santos Filho, Exchange Director
                                of the Bank of Brazil.</note> to organize this department of the
                            bank of Brazil.</p>
                        <p>The Federal Loan Agency is nevertheless willing to take over a large
                            share of this work. It now proposes to send Mr. Leonard J. Buck to Rio
                            de Janeiro. Mr. Buck will arrive there next Wednesday. His duties will
                            be to buy the materials listed in no. 325 at the prices therein
                            mentioned. He will buy only from the large wholesalers or exporters who
                            will make deliveries at concentration points, presumably Brazilian
                            ports. When the materials are ready for delivery, they will be received
                            and checked by Buck and Danforth. Arrangements have already been made
                            with the National City Bank to make payment against invoices and
                            documents approved by Buck and Danforth. Buck will hire such experts as
                            may be necessary to assist in all this work. This includes industrial
                            diamond experts and such other specialists as may be required.</p>
                        <p>Since Buck will arrive Wednesday, it is believed that all the necessary
                            arrangements can be made promptly upon his arrival to enable the
                            issuance by the Brazilian Government of the regulations prohibiting
                            exports except in accordance with the agreement. It seems therefore not
                            necessary to adopt any preliminary methods such as are suggested in your
                            telegram.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>