<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Chile ( (Bowers) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d603</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">603</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-08-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-08-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="minerals-and-metals" lcsh-match="no_match">Metals</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Good Neighbor Policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-08-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-08-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="603"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d603">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Chile/7</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1779</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-08-25">August 25,
                            1941</date>.<lb/>[Received September 2.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report in connection with the
                    proposed purchase of certain Chilean concentrates and ores by the Metals Reserve
                    Company that Mr. Thomas J. Williams, mentioned in the Department’s <pb
                        facs="0595" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> Telegram No. 249 of August 7, 6
                        p.m.,<note n="74" xml:id="d603fn1">Not printed; Mr. Williams was a
                        representative of the Metals Reserve Co.</note> arrived in Santiago on
                    August 18. He immediately called at the Embassy and on the following morning was
                    introduced to Mr. R. P. Miller, the Metals Reserve Company’s special
                    representative in Chile and the special representative in this country of the
                    Federal Loan Agency, to serve in the absence of Mr. Horace Graham.</p>
                <p>After Messrs. Williams and Miller had conferred with me regarding the general
                    aspects of the plan of the Metals Reserve Company and had studied, in
                    conjunction with my Commercial Attaché, all the detailed information on the
                    subject in the Embassy’s possession, I presented them at 1 p.m. Friday, August
                    22, to Foreign Minister Rossetti. At the same time I handed him my Note No. 603,
                    of which a copy is enclosed,<note n="75" xml:id="d603fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    advising that the Metals Reserve Company now was ready to discuss the
                    acquisition of the exportable surpluses of certain Chilean concentrates and ores
                    and that the special representative of the Company, Mr. Miller, was authorized
                    to negotiate a purchase agreement in collaboration with the Embassy. Mr. Miller
                    also handed the Foreign Minister a letter in the same tenor. A copy of Mr.
                    Miller’s letter is also enclosed.<note n="75" xml:id="d603fn3">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Williams outlined the essential points of the Metals Reserve Company’s plan
                    to Rossetti who immediately endorsed it and expressed the hope that there would
                    be no delay in reaching an agreement to which end he promised his complete
                    cooperation. The Foreign Minister declared that it was his desire to go along in
                    every way with the United States in promoting hemispheric solidarity but
                    difficulties were being experienced in Congress where the opposition was
                    charging the Government with neglecting the national interest. The prompt
                    conclusion of a satisfactory purchase agreement with Metals Reserve, he said,
                    would greatly strengthen his and the Government’s position in Congress and would
                    facilitate obtaining favorable consideration of other important measures
                    involving continental defense and economic cooperation. He explained that the
                    United States had not received the measure of credit, to which it was entitled,
                    for the aid it already had extended Chile largely because such aid had benefited
                    the “vociferous little fellows” only in an indirect way. An agreement with the
                    Metals Reserve Company, he declared, would drive home the fact that the United
                    States was interested in their welfare and was genuinely desirous of helping
                    Chile.</p>
                <p>As proof of his wish to go ahead at once with negotiations, Rossetti appointed a
                    committee composed of the President of the Miners’ Bank, the Subsecretary of
                    Commerce, the Vice President of the Fomento Corporation, the Vice President of
                    the Mining Society and a <pb facs="0596" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/>
                    representative of the Ministry of Fomento to meet with Messrs. Williams and
                    Miller at six p.m. Friday afternoon. The meeting, presided over by Rossetti
                    himself, was carried on in an atmosphere of mutual frankness and cordiality
                    according to the special representatives of the Metals Reserve Company. At the
                    express suggestion of the Foreign Minister, who declared that he did not wish to
                    give the meeting too much of an official character, no representative of the
                    Embassy attended. However, a report of the meeting is contained in the enclosed
                    copy of Mr. Miller’s letter No. 2 to the Vice President of the Metals Reserve
                        Company.<note n="76" xml:id="d603fn4">G. Temple Bridgman; letter of August
                        23 not printed.</note> There also is enclosed for the information of the
                    Department copies of Mr. Miller’s letters numbers 1 and 3 to the Metals Reserve
                        Company<note n="77" xml:id="d603fn5">Not printed.</note> wherein he sets
                    forth in detail his estimate of the situation and his views on the prospects of
                    negotiating an over-all agreement for the purchase of the concentrates and
                    ores.</p>
                <p>The Chilean reaction to the Metals Reserve’s proposal will be summed up in a
                    memorandum the Committee has promised to submit to Mr. Miller. While it is too
                    early to venture an opinion as to the ultimate outcome of the negotiations I
                    believe, with Mr. Miller, that to obtain an over-all agreement it may be
                    necessary for Metals Reserve to <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>agree to taking deliveries in Chile instead of f.o.b. steamer Chilean
                            ports,</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>offer slightly better prices for some ores and concentrates,
                            particularly those of copper,</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>purchase the Chilean gold ores</item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>offer contracts for a period longer than one year.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Refusal to make concessions along these lines might jeopardize the negotiations
                    which, if they are not carried to a successful conclusion, could have
                    unfortunate political repercussions here and lead to the questioning of the
                    sincerity of the whole good neighbor policy.</p>
                <p>To surround the negotiations with as favorable an atmosphere as possible,
                    Rossetti tendered a luncheon on Saturday, August 23, to Messrs. Williams and
                    Miller, there being present on the occasion the members of the Chilean
                    Commission, influential members of Congress and individuals prominent in the
                    mining industry. Both the meeting with the Commission on Friday and the luncheon
                    the following day were given wide publicity in the local papers. The principal
                    press articles, clippings of which are enclosed, were inspired by the Foreign
                    Minister who was quoted by the <hi rend="italic">Diario Ilustrado</hi> as having
                    said: “it is the firm purpose of the Government to obtain, by all the means at
                    its command, the stability and prosperity of the small mining industry, assuring
                    it prices which will permit the development of its maximum productive
                    capacity.”</p>
                <pb facs="0597" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                <p>Mr. Williams returned to Buenos Aires yesterday, leaving Mr. Miller to continue
                    with the negotiations in collaboration with the Embassy. His presence here was
                    most helpful in starting the negotiations. Both he and Mr. Miller made an
                    excellent impression on all with whom they came in contact and it is my
                    observation that the Metals Reserve Company has in these men two very capable
                    and competent representatives.</p>
                <p>The Department will be kept fully informed of all phases of the negotiations.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bowers</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
