<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-04T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-04T16:00:00-05:00" n="606" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d606">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Chile/8:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-04T17:00:00-04:00">September 4, 1941—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 10:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>422. Reference my despatch No. 1779, August 25. The Chilean Commission
                            appointed by Rossetti has submitted to Miller an informal unsigned
                            memorandum outlining its views regarding the basis for an over-all
                            agreement with Metals Reserve. According to the Commission the agreement
                            should: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Cover all minerals produced including gold ore and
                                    concentrates, and any probable increases over previous
                                    production of manganese, zinc, cobalt and mercury.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>That prices should not be less than those ruling in the market
                                    and should be established for production placed Chilean ports
                                    with payments 90% against delivery.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>That the length of the agreement should be for not less than 3
                                    years.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>That long term loans should be made available for the
                                    development of new production of copper and manganese.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>That priority and export licenses be granted for the Paipote
                                    smelter materials.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>That Chile be able to count on obtaining steel, repair parts
                                    and other materials essential to the mining industry.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Our reaction is that any agreement with Metals Reserve should be
                            conditioned on a satisfactory solution of the copper tax problem but if
                            it is believed desirable that we proceed with negotiations then it would
                            be helpful to receive from Metals Reserve final prices for all mineral
                            products including antimony and zinc, also authority to discuss an
                            agreement up to 18 months if necessary but refusing any commitments with
                            respect to points 4, 5 and 6.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Bowers</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>