<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-17T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-17T19:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851G.00/7–1747: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Consulate General</gloss> at Saigon</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-17T20:00:00-04:00">July 17,
                                    1947—8 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>122. Request your and Hanoi’s appraisal implications relation US
                            objectives stable Southeast Asia friendly to democratic West in event
                            French should be forced deal present Vietnam Govt and this Govt <pb facs="0132" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> should eventually emerge as
                            controlling power three Annamese provinces. Refer particularly the
                            following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Whether influence Communists in present coalition Govt and
                                    behind-scenes Communists like Dang Xuan Khu and Ha Ba Cang would
                                    be sufficient put Vietnam in Soviet camp.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Position Ho respect above. Whether your opinion evidence
                                    increasing opposition to Ho by militants tends substantiate
                                    repeated reports his abandonment Party line and to corroborate
                                    reported letter to Chiang Kai Shek in which Ho excused past
                                    Communists connections on grounds nowhere else turn, and stated
                                    only interest now independence his country. (Impression here Ho
                                    publicly attempting walk chalked line between nationalism and
                                    Communism effort retain backing both forces.)</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Whether intellectuals backing Vietnam realize what Communism
                                    means as international political force distinct its economic
                                    aspects and whether nationalists among them feel they can cope
                                    in future with Communist leaders Vietnam.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Whether, with removal solidifying effect French pressure,
                                    coherent Govt likely be extended over Vietnam representing real
                                    interests Annamese and allowing reasonably free political
                                    expression or whether coalition would break in factions which
                                    would settle differences by terrorism and armed force, resulting
                                    chronic disorders or eventual police state under one-party
                                    rule.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Sensitivity Vietnamese to US opinion and importance this
                                    factor future orientation Vietnam Govt. While French Communists
                                    exploit every show of US interest developments Indochina to warn
                                    of US intervention, Vietnamese apparently welcome this
                                    interest.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Effect on Laotians and Cambodians should Soviet-oriented
                                    Vietnam emerge.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dept fully realizes paucity solid <gloss target="#t_Info1">info</gloss>
                            on which base appraisal.</p>
                        <p>Sent Saigon 122. Repeated Hanoi 66. Repeated Paris for <gloss target="#t_Info1">info</gloss> 2649.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>