<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-16T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-16T12:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851G.00/12–1647: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-16T18:00:00+01:00">December
                                    16, 1947—6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>5398. Following is Foreign Office version of meetings on December 6 and 7
                            between Bollaert and Bao Dai. Additional reports will follow.</p>
                        <p>Bollaert and Bao Dai reached agreement in principle on future status of
                            Vietnam (Embtel 5282, December 9<note n="21" xml:id="d163fn21">Not
                                printed.</note>). At outset Bao Dai demanded as prerequisite to any
                            understanding guarantee that French will not negotiate with Ho Chi-minh
                            at any time and make public announcement to this effect. <pb facs="0165" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> Under agreement Bao Dai is to return to
                                <gloss target="#t_FIC1">FIC</gloss> and establish new government.
                            Vietnam, which will include Tonkin, Annam and Cochin-China, is to be
                            granted independence within French Union; foreign relations are to be
                            conducted by France with Vietnamese being incorporated in French Foreign
                            Service. Vietnam will have independent army which will, however, be
                            “available for defense of any part of French Union”. There will be
                            common customs and integration of transportation and communication
                            systems.</p>
                        <p>Details of agreement presently being studied by French Government and no
                            public statements will be made until Bollaert returns to Indochina and
                            Bao Dai government established. Foreign Office source sees as principal
                            difficulties the formula for return of Bao Dai to <gloss target="#t_FIC1">FIC</gloss> without being branded as French
                            “stooge” and formation of representative and effective government.
                            Source adds that inclusion of Cochin-China (because of its
                            constitutional status as a “Crown Colony”) in Vietnam will require act
                            of Parliament and expects that this bill would be subject of attack by
                            Communists. Latter who up to now have actively campaigned for union of
                            “three <gloss target="#t_ky1">Ky</gloss>s” as part of their all-out
                            campaign of support for Ho Chi-minh would doubtless reverse themselves
                            on this issue if uncompromising anti-Ho statement as demanded by Bao Dai
                            is made.</p>
                        <p>Department pass to Saigon as Paris 37.<note n="22" xml:id="d163fn22">Also
                                to be repeated by Saigon to Hanoi.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>