<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="282" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d282">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">894.5018/12–1847</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Frank G.
                                    Wisner</persName>, Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of State
                                for Occupied Areas, to the <gloss type="to">State-Army-Navy-Air
                                    Force Coordinating Committee</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-18">December 18, 1947</date>.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>There is enclosed a draft directive<note n="6" xml:id="d282fn6">Not
                                printed. The Joint Chiefs of Staff sent the directive as <hi rend="smallcaps">War</hi> 92777 on December 19, Serial No.
                                88.</note> prepared on the basis of a policy decision approved at
                            the eighty-third meeting of the Far Eastern Commission on December 11,
                                1947,<note n="7" xml:id="d282fn7">
                                <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>–248/9, printed in <hi rend="italic">The Far Eastern Commission</hi>, p. 41.</note>
                            under the provisions of paragraph II, A, 1, of its terms of
                            reference.</p>
                        <p>It is requested that the enclosed directive be forwarded to the Joint
                            Chiefs of Staff for transmission to General MacArthur for his guidance
                            in accordance with paragraph III, 1, of the terms of reference of the
                            Far Eastern Commission. It is assumed that if the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                            have any question regarding the draft directive they will refer the
                            matter to the Department of State for clarification before transmitting
                            a directive on the subject.</p>
                        <p>It is also requested that the statement of the U.S. representative on
                            November 20, 1947,<note n="6" xml:id="d282fn8">Not printed. The Joint
                                Chiefs of Staff sent the directive as <hi rend="smallcaps">War</hi>
                                92777 on December 19, Serial No. 88.</note> and the statements of
                            the U.S., Chinese, and New Zealand representatives at the time of the
                            adoption of the policy decision, December 11, 1947, be transmitted to
                            the Supreme Commander for his information.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary-General of the Far Eastern Commission has requested that
                            the Joint Chiefs of Staff, in transmitting the enclosed draft directive
                            to the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, inform him that in
                            adopting the policy decision regarding the supply of food for civilian
                            consumption in Japan the Commission agreed that it should be released to
                            the press after being received by the Supreme Commander. Therefore, in
                            accordance with normal procedure, acknowledgment of the receipt of the
                            directive is requested.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank G. Wisner</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="0347" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Annex 1]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Statements by the United States and Chinese
                                    Representatives, Far Eastern Commission, December 11, 1947</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>The United States representative asked that the following statement
                                be recorded in the minutes of the Commission at the time of adoption
                                of this policy.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The United States approves the policy statement on food
                                    contained in <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 248/4 on the
                                    understanding that: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>As a first step in implementation of paragraph 3 of
                                            this policy the Supreme Commander will present his
                                            requirements for food imports to the United States
                                            Government as requested by current directives classified
                                            separately as to: <list>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Requirements essential to the safety of the
                                                  occupation forces.</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Additional requirements necessary to meet the
                                                  objectives of the occupation.</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>In order to make it possible for the United States
                                            Government to ‘take all steps within its power to assist
                                            this policy to be carried into effect’ the Supreme
                                            Commander for the Allied Powers will forward to the
                                            United States Government all necessary data as to
                                            Japanese indigenous resources, measures being taken to
                                            increase production and provide equitable distribution
                                            of such resources, dietary standards necessary to
                                            prevent disease and unrest such as would endanger the
                                            safety of the occupation forces and other required
                                            information.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>The United States Government will determine, on the
                                            basis of information submitted by the Supreme Commander
                                            for the Allied Powers and other information available to
                                            it, and after consultation with appropriate
                                            international bodies, the imports other than those
                                            needed for the safety of the occupation forces which
                                            would not have the effect of giving preferential
                                            treatment to the Japanese.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>The United States Government will then inform the
                                            Supreme Commander of its views as to the maximum imports
                                            which would not provide preferential treatment for the
                                            Japanese.”</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>The Chinese representative made the following statement of
                                understanding which he asked be recorded in the minutes.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is the understanding of the Chinese Delegation that paragraph
                                    2 <hi rend="italic">a</hi> should not be interpreted to prevent
                                    removal as reparations of Japanese fertilizer plants and
                                    facilities, or to predetermine the ultimate capacity of such
                                    industry to be retained in Japan.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>In reference to the above Chinese statement, the United States
                                representative asked that the following statement of understanding
                                also be recorded in the minutes.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The United States Government does not acquiesce in any statement
                                    which implies that fertilizer plants may be used for
                                    reparations.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0348" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Annex 2]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Statement by the New Zealand Representative, Far
                                    Eastern Commission, December 11, 1947</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>“Mr. Chairman, may I be permitted to make some statements on the
                                general aspect of this paper now that it is going to be passed? This
                                is not the first occasion on which the Far Eastern Commission has
                                been called upon to consider the question of food supplies for
                                Japan. The Commission will recall the very keen interest which my
                                Government, and particularly my Minister, Sir Carl Berendsen, has
                                taken in the matter in its earlier stages, and I don’t have any
                                desire at all to recapitulate any part of the difficult and
                                prolonged discussions which we have had on this paper extending
                                almost for over a year—well over a year.</p>
                            <p>“I am instructed by my Government to support the present paper as
                                being the best obtainable under the circumstances, but I should like
                                to comment on one or two of the general aspects involved.</p>
                            <p>“Of course, we realize that it is entirely natural and understandable
                                that an occupying power holding such a predominant place in Japan as
                                does the United States should earnestly desire to avoid any
                                unnecessary complication of its difficult and delicate task. It is
                                also true that it is difficult to build a democratic country out of
                                a hungry people. These things are plain and undeniable.</p>
                            <p>“But there is another principle involved. If there is to be hardship,
                                and if at a time like this when there is not food enough to go
                                around, anyone has to go short, then clearly, as we see it, the
                                shortage and the suffering should fall upon the aggressors and not
                                upon their victims. There does not seem to be any reason whatever,
                                in logic or in equity, why, for example, the people of China, or
                                Malaya or the Philippines or India or Burma, or, indeed, any of the
                                peoples of the world who are suffering from hunger as a direct
                                result of Japanese aggression, should be allowed to go short of food
                                in a time of desperate need while the Japanese, the substantial
                                cause of their miseries, are supplied with food in greater
                                proportion. The paper before us acknowledges this general principle,
                                the validity of which, of course, is unquestionable, but the paper
                                provides an important exception, in that the Japanese may be
                                permitted to receive more food than their former victims if such
                                extra food is necessary to prevent such starvation and widespread
                                disease and civil unrest as will endanger the safety of the
                                occupation forces. This is an exception, sir, which may become both
                                unjust and dangerous.</p>
                            <p>“It may become unjust because it can lead to a violation of that
                                general principle I have referred to, and it may become dangerous
                                    <pb facs="0349" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> because it leaves the
                                way open for the Japanese, by deliberately fomenting internal
                                disorder, to induce <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> and the
                                United States Government to allow more food. But, of course, in the
                                proper discharge of the Commission’s responsibilities, it is clear
                                to all of us that such an exception must be inserted in the policy
                                paper. In the circumstances we couldn’t possibly do otherwise, but I
                                do suggest that we should act with our eyes open. It is, therefore,
                                obviously the duty of all concerned to minimize both the possibility
                                of injustice and of danger, and to take all necessary steps to
                                insure that the amount of actual food required by this exception is
                                as small as possible. The Japanese food problem is only one part of
                                a world-wide problem, as is recognized in the statement of the
                                United States Member in the document recently filed, <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 248/4, and the more the Japanese
                                can be got to see it in this light, and together with their own part
                                in the history of its development, the less is there likely to be
                                unrest and the more cooperative will the Japanese become and the
                                lower will the level of food required to prevent danger to the
                                occupation forces also be. In a previous food paper before the
                                Commission, that is, <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 026/12,
                                there was a very significant paragraph which doesn’t appear in the
                                present paper, and I should like, with your permission, sir, to
                                quote that paragraph. The paragraph reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>‘The Supreme Commander should make it clear to the Japanese
                                        people that: <list>
                                            <item>‘(1) Many countries are suffering from a dire
                                                shortage of foodstuffs largely due to Japanese
                                                aggression and in many of the countries devastated
                                                by the Japanese the diet of the people is inferior
                                                to that of the Japanese.</item>
                                            <item>‘(2) The Supreme Commander assumes no obligations
                                                to maintain, or to have maintained, any particular
                                                standard of living in Japan, and</item>
                                            <item>‘(3) The Supreme Commander assumes no
                                                responsibility to the Japanese people to import
                                                foodstuffs to meet any deficit arising from the
                                                failure of the Japanese Government and people to
                                                assure the just and impartial distribution of their
                                                indigenous foodstuffs.</item>
                                            <item>‘(4) The standard of living will depend upon the
                                                thoroughness with which Japan rids itself of all
                                                militaristic ambitions, redirects the use of its
                                                human and natural resources wholly and solely for
                                                purposes of peaceful living, administers adequate
                                                economic and financial controls and cooperates with
                                                the occupying forces and the governments they
                                                represent.’</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>“Now, sir, in the course of the food discussions, which, of course,
                                were very prolonged in the Commission and in the committee, the New
                                Zealand Delegation fully understood the reasons for most of the
                                arguments which were adduced by the United States, although, of <pb facs="0350" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/> course, on occasions we
                                contested their validity, but we never did understand the reason for
                                the flat United States rejection of subparagraph (1) in the abstract
                                of the paragraph which I have just read. That is the subparagraph
                                which suggests that the Supreme Commander should make it clear to
                                the Japanese people that many countries are suffering from shortage
                                of food stuffs largely due to Japanese aggression. The remainder of
                                the paragraph that I quoted was fully accepted by the United States
                                Delegation. Now my Government attaches great importance to this
                                matter being understood in its correct perspective, and being so
                                understood by the Japanese, and it has at times felt doubtful
                                whether this was the situation or even whether <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> was doing what could be done in
                                this respect. And the attitude of the United States upon that
                                subparagraph (1)1 have referred to didn’t help very much to remove
                                the doubts. But it does not appear that comparatively recently
                                something has been done to put the matter to the Japanese in the
                                proper light. I refer to the two papers that have been filed in the
                                    Commission—<gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 248/5 and
                                248/6—and I refer also to a press report to the effect that the
                                Japanese miners have been informed that they were getting twice as
                                much food as the European miners but that they were only producing
                                one-fourth as much coal. Now that is the sort of thing which ought
                                to be told to the Japanese, but here again in the statements that
                                were made by <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> officers at their
                                press conference, the two statements that are filed as of record in
                                the Commission, I note that the <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> officers gave a reasonably good picture of the
                                world food situation but there was no significant mention of the one
                                big fact which must be brought home to the Japanese—that their own
                                carrier [career?] of wanton aggression throughout the food-producing
                                lands of Southeast Asia has been and still is a major cause of the
                                world shortage of rice. We should like to see this fact hammered
                                home to the Japanese until every man, woman and child in Japan had
                                at least some appreciation of the grave extent of Japan’s own
                                responsibility in this matter. I repeat that the information at our
                                disposal may not be complete, but in any case I would suggest to the
                                United States Representative that possibly his Government might
                                profitably look again at the whole paragraph that I have referred
                                to, that is, the paragraph that was in the previous document, and
                                carefully consider the advisability of implementing it so as to
                                attain the two objectives: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The maximum possible cooperation from the Japanese,
                                        and</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The reduction in the amount food required to keep safe the
                                        occupation forces.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>