<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-05-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control Japan/5–1247</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                    State</gloss> to the United States Member of the Far Eastern
                                Commission</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">McCoy</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-05-13">May 13, 1947</date>.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In accordance with paragraph<note n="86" xml:id="d329fn86">Number of
                                paragraph not inserted in file copy.</note> of the Memorandum of
                            April 8, 1947, forwarding to the U.S. Member of the Far Eastern
                            Commission <pb facs="0408" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 236/43,<note n="87" xml:id="d329fn87">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_382">p.
                                382</ref>.</note> the negotiating instructions referred to in that
                            paragraph are hereby transmitted.</p>
                        <p>The United States Member is requested to expedite the negotiation of this
                            United States policy in the Far Eastern Commission as a matter of the
                            utmost urgency. In view of the length of time which the Commission has
                            already devoted to the Level of Industry and the detailed discussions
                            thereon which have taken place, it is hoped that every effort will now
                            be made to complete this matter by obtaining a policy decision on this
                            paper within three weeks.</p>
                        <p>Three amendments to this paper have now been agreed to in <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss>. You are requested to introduce
                            these in the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> as U.S. amendments to
                                <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 218. They are as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Substitute for para. 1 <hi rend="italic">g</hi> of the
                                    enclosure to <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 218 the
                                    following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Aluminum and Magnesium</hi>
                                        </p>
                                        <p>(Definition: “Plants and establishments primarily engaged
                                            in the production of alumina, primary or secondary
                                            aluminum and magnesium and in the rolling, extruding,
                                            drawing, forging and casting of aluminum and magnesium
                                            and their alloys.”)</p>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>All facilities for the production of magnesium
                                                should be made available for claim.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>All facilities in excess of 25,000 metric tons per
                                                year aluminum reducing capacity should be made
                                                available for claim.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>All facilities primarily engaged in the rolling,
                                                extruding, drawing, forging, and casting of aluminum
                                                and magnesium and their alloys should be made
                                                available for claim.”</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>) At the end of the first sentence of
                                    para. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.(1) add the following words:
                                    “including the Ryukyus”;</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>) After the first sentence insert the
                                    following: “During the period of the occupation <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> may also retain additional
                                    fertilizer capacity necessary to meet essential fertilizer
                                    imports for Southern Korea.”</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>As a new paragraph 3. to the Enclosure of <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 218, add the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“In addition to the facilities to remain in Japan, as
                                            provided in this paper, <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> may retain temporarily any items
                                            deemed essential to the needs of the occupation.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In order to secure prompt agreement by the Commission, the U.S. Member is
                            authorized to accept such limited and minor changes as would not
                            materially affect the over-all level of retention as provided in the
                            Conclusions of <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 236/43.</p>
                        <p>Only two additional matters require immediate <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> action in connection with <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> 236/43 (<gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 218).
                            These are the Selections paper, <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>–041/7,
                            and the Industrial Disarmament paper, <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>
                            <pb facs="0409" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> 084/11. Instructions on this
                            latter document have been recently transmitted to you.</p>
                        <p>In order to clarify the procedures whereby Japanese facilities will be
                            selected for reparations it is necessary that <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> approval be obtained to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>–041/7, “The Selection of Plants for Reparations
                            Removals, Destruction or Retention in Japan”. Existing instructions to
                            you on this paper appear adequate for purposes of final negotiation.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>