<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-07-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="347" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 P.W./7–2347</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Cleon O. Swayzee of the Division of
                                International Labor, Social, and Health Affairs</hi><note n="22" xml:id="d347fn22">Addressed to General Hilldring; Arthur R.
                                Ringwalt, Chief of the Division of Chinese Affairs; Edwin M. Martin,
                                Chief of the Division of Japanese and Korean Economic Affairs; Hugh
                                Borton, Chief of the Division of Northeast Asian Affairs; and
                                Melville H. Walker, Assistant Chief of the Division of Investment
                                and Economic Development.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-07-23">July 23, 1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Comments Respecting the Draft <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> Paper which Deals with the Problems
                            of the Utilization of Japanese Technical Personnel by Claimant Countries
                            in the Installation and Operation of Industrial Facilities Removed from
                            Japan on Reparations Account.</p>
                        <p>The proposed U.S. policy in dealing with the above-named problem, as laid
                            out in the draft <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> paper, would
                            permit the recruiting of a “reasonable” number of Japanese technicians
                            by reparation claimant countries under a number of safeguards to be set
                            up by <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> designed to protect them
                            from involuntary employment. The reparation claimant countries would be
                            responsible only for transportation and “subsistence” during the period
                            of the contract, while the Japanese government would be responsible for
                            the workers’ remuneration “in excess of subsistence”. The latter
                            payments would be made in yen to the account (or the dependents) of the
                            individual Japanese so employed and would be debited to the reparations
                            accounts of the reparation claimant countries.</p>
                        <p>This Division has two general comments regarding the proposals embodied
                            in this paper: <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item> While we recognize the validity of the various arguments put
                                    forward in support of this program, such as the necessity for
                                    the industrially undeveloped claimant countries to secure the
                                    use of skilled technicians, and that the amount of reparations
                                    that these countries will receive from Japan is likely to be
                                    relatively little at the best; we still believe that certain
                                    aspects of the program as outlined has serious disadvantages
                                    from the U.S. point of view: <list>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>We believe as a matter of principle that it is
                                            undesirable to recruit labor for service abroad as
                                            reparation because we believe such arrangements
                                            considerably increase the risks that are always present
                                            in recruiting <pb facs="0433" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                                            labor for service abroad, namely those of involuntary
                                            servitude and the exploitation of labor. Largely because
                                            of this danger American labor has gone on record as
                                            opposing the use of manpower as reparations, and would
                                            undoubtedly protest if our Government agreed to a plan
                                            calling for the same. Moreover, if we give assent to a
                                            labor reparations program, however carefully we might
                                            attempt to safeguard the rights of labor, our action
                                            would be subject to misrepresentation and distortion
                                            abroad, and consequently our future position in dealing
                                            with international issues involving moral considerations
                                            would be weakened.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>This policy differs radically from the one that we
                                            have been following in Europe. Thus on March 19, 1947 an
                                            outgoing telegram for the Political Adviser in Berlin
                                            (No. 603)<note n="23" xml:id="d347fn23">
                                                <ref target="frus1947v02#pg_1105">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1105</ref>.</note>
                                            which cleared through <gloss target="#t_AH1">A–H</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CE1">CE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ILH1">ILH</gloss>
                                            stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“We have considered proposal stated in <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 482 Feb 27<note n="24" xml:id="d347fn24">
                                                  <ref target="frus1947v02#pg_1104">
                                                  <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                                  1104</ref>.</note> relative to recruitment of
                                                  labor in Germany for work abroad for purposes of
                                                  reerecting plants allocated member countries IARA
                                                  as reparation.</p>
                                                <p>“We are opposed in principle to use of German
                                                  labor abroad as form of reparation. …</p>
                                                <p>“However we are agreed in principle that
                                                  recruitment of German technicians be permitted for
                                                  purpose assisting in reerection of plants removed
                                                  as reparation. Such recruitment should be
                                                  conditioned upon following requirements in
                                                  addition those you listed: First, recruitment be
                                                  on voluntary basis. Second, that technicians be
                                                  permitted leave Germany only on temporary
                                                  assignments limited to period necessary to
                                                  accomplish reerection of the plants, and that
                                                  arrangements be made to ensure their return.
                                                  Third, arrangements for remittances of earnings to
                                                  Germany be accomplished. …”</p>
                                            </quote>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>In view of the foregoing considerations we recommend that this
                                    Government: (1) oppose any proposal that Japanese workers be
                                    recruited for labor abroad on reparation account; and (2)
                                    support, as a substitute, the idea of voluntary recruitment in
                                    keeping with the general provisions of the third paragraph of
                                    the Department’s telegram to Berlin.</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item> We are considerably concerned over the possibility that
                                    Japanese workers recruited for service abroad at this time and
                                    for the purpose indicated, whether on reparations account or by
                                    voluntary recruitment, might in fact become subject to
                                    involuntary labor. However carefully the work contract required
                                    by <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> might be drawn up, once
                                    the workers were in the reparations claimant country, unless
                                    some special safeguarding plan were adopted, they would be
                                    entirely subject to control of the authorities of that country.
                                    This would follow because they would have no Consul to appeal to
                                    in case the terms of their contracts were not lived up to, and
                                    would be unable in all probability <pb facs="0434" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> to finance a return trip to their own
                                    country (certainly unable if “subsistence” only is paid directly
                                    to them as under the payments for reparation account plan) or to
                                    secure the needed travel permits or tickets.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>Therefore, we believe that the safeguards set out in the draft
                                        <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> paper should be
                                    altered to include the following provisions: <list>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>The contract be drawn for a fixed period, not to
                                            exceed one year, but subject to renewal in case both
                                            parties agree.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Either party should be permitted to terminate the
                                            contract at any time by giving one month’s notice. In
                                            order to protect the employing country from capricious
                                            actions by Japanese employees, we would favor including
                                            in the contract a wage-withholding plan which would
                                            place at least some portion of the cost of the
                                            repatriation of workers who wished to return home before
                                            their contracts expired upon the workers
                                            themselves.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>The setting-up of some system of inspection to ensure
                                            that the Japanese workers are given the treatment called
                                            for in their contracts; and especially that they are not
                                            being detained against their wills. Possibly we should
                                            insist that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, until
                                            such time as the Japanese Government resumes control of
                                            her foreign relations, be given authority to send or
                                            delegate representatives periodically to inspect the
                                            conditions of the men so recruited. In practice this
                                            should not prove too difficult as it could be done by
                                            the regular U.S. diplomatic corps in the countries in
                                            question. Another possible method of protection might be
                                            that of arranging periodic inspection by International
                                            Labor Office representatives who would report to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> directly.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In order to expedite action on this problem we are drawing up specific
                            suggestions for the amendment of the draft <gloss target="#t_SWNCC1">SWNCC</gloss> paper and will forward these to you for consideration
                            by the China Committee<note n="25" xml:id="d347fn25">Mr. Ringwalt was
                                Chairman of the Committee.</note> at an early meeting.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cleon O. Swayzee</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>