<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. John A. Bailey, Administrative Officer of
                        the Division of Occupied-Area Economic Affairs
                    Addressed to Dr. Warren Kelchner, of the Division
                        of International Conferences. The memorandum was drafted by Rufus Burr Smith
                        who had originally headed the reparations mission in Japan.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d364</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">364</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="364" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d364">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 PW/11–2647</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. John A. Bailey, Administrative Officer of
                        the Division of Occupied-Area Economic Affairs</hi>
                    <note n="55" xml:id="d364fn55">Addressed to Dr. Warren Kelchner, of the Division
                        of International Conferences. The memorandum was drafted by Rufus Burr Smith
                        who had originally headed the reparations mission in Japan.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-11-26">November 26,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Review of U.S. Reparations, Restitution and Restoration
                    Delegation to date.</p>
                <p>The function of the U.S. Reparations, Restitution and Restoration Delegation to
                    Japan is to represent the interests of the U.S. Government <pb facs="0457" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> in the following major fields: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the distribution of reparations from Japan, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the restitution to claimants of property looted from their
                    territory by Japan, and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the restoration of property
                    owned by U.S. citizens to its rightful owner.</p>
                <p>A separate U.S. mission to accomplish these purposes is necessary because the
                    American forces under General MacArthur are in Japan as an Allied Occupation
                    Force, representing the interests of all allied powers, and not the direct
                    interest of the U.S. Government as such. As a consequence, General MacArthur has
                    invited the United Nations with paramount Far Eastern interests, who compose the
                    Far Eastern Commission, namely, Australia, China, France, India, The
                    Netherlands, Canada, New Zealand, The Philippines, UK, USSR, and the U.S. to
                    appoint official missions to perform the above mentioned general functions in
                    Japan. All eleven countries have accepted the invitation and now have missions
                    actively operating in Japan. These missions act both as spokesman and claimant
                    for their respective governments and as advisors to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> in the development of mutually acceptable procedures for the
                    solution of these problems. Jointly the eleven missions form the Reparations
                    Technical Advisory Commission to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> and will
                    shortly be organized into a similar agency concerned with problems of
                    restitution and restoration.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Accomplishments:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The accomplishments of the first 6 months of the operation of the mission may be
                    summarized under the following heads: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Reparations</hi>. The U.S. mission has participated
                            actively in the organization of the Reparations Technical Advisory
                            Committee in Tokyo. This eleven nation inter-allied body, in
                            consultation with <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, has been
                            responsible for the development of specific procedures which will govern
                            the selection and distribution of reparations facilities in Japan. The
                            U.S. member, both because of the position of the U.S. in the
                            administration of Japan and because of his personal acquaintance with
                            the activities of the Far Eastern Commission and its basic policies
                            governing Japan, has exerted a considerable influence upon the policies
                            of the <gloss target="#t_RTAC1">RTAC</gloss>. In addition, the U.S.
                            member, for the foregoing reasons, has frequently been able to negotiate
                            points of conflict between other nations and <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> with mutual benefit to both parties and considerable
                            benefit to U.S. foreign relations in this field. During this period
                            basic procedures have been adopted, the first allocation of reparations
                            under the advance transfer reparations program of the U.S. has been made
                            and additional removals of facilities will begin in the near future. The
                            first actual reparations from Japan, consisting of some 20 thousand
                            machine tools, have recently been allocated and are now being packaged
                            for removal. While the U.S. is not <pb facs="0458" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> a recipient of any of these advance reparations,
                            the prompt receipt and use of them by such nations as the Philippines,
                            China, <gloss target="#t_NEI1">N.E.I.</gloss> and Malay–Burma, is of
                            direct concern to the basic policies of the U.S. Government in assisting
                            in the rapid post-war recovery of these areas and in lessening
                            consequent requirements for U.S. dollar assistance.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Restitution</hi>. The direct concern of the U.S. in
                            the restoration of looted property has been minor, since very little
                            American territory has been actually occupied by the Japanese. The
                            principal activities of the U.S. delegation in this field has been
                            concerned with the revision of existing policies and procedures, in
                            consultation with <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> and the
                            Department of State, in order to expedite the restitution of property
                            owned by other countries. An example of the work of the mission in this
                            field has been the success of the Chief of the Delegation in obtaining
                                <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> approval of a broad revision
                            of basic policy under consideration by the Far Eastern
                            Commission.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Restoration</hi>. The most direct U.S. interest of the
                            activities of the delegation is in the prompt restoration of U.S. owned
                            property in Japan to its rightful owners. The U.S. delegation has
                            invited all major U.S. interests with property in Japan to send
                            representatives, as technical aides to the delegation, for the purpose
                            of inspecting their properties, recommending steps necessary for their
                            adequate protection while under the custodianship of <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, and formulating a decision as to the
                            time and conditions under which they desire a return of that property.
                            To date, some 15 representatives of such American concerns as I.T. &amp;
                            T., Ford Motor Company, Singer Sewing Machine, Otis Elevator, Libby
                            Owens Ford, and Socony Vacuum Oil Company have availed themselves of
                            this opportunity. The U.S. delegation has also been actively concerned
                            in developing, with <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, detailed
                            policies and procedures for the actual restoration of this property, for
                            its exemption from Japanese war-time tax burdens, and its treatment
                            under Japanese corporate re-organization policies.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In addition to the foregoing official functions, it should be recognized that the
                    U.S. delegation is the only fully independent representative of the State
                    Department in Tokyo and as such it has been of great service to the Department
                    in consulting with <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> on various proposed
                    U.S. economic policies requiring <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> approval
                    and also in reporting to the Department developments within Japan which would
                    effect basic policies under consideration in the Department, or in the Far
                    Eastern Commission.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Future Activities:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The activities of the past six months have been largely preparatory to a greatly
                    increased flow of reparations, of restituted looted property and the actual
                    restoration of U.S. property in Japan, all of which, <pb facs="0459" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> it is anticipated, will reach a peak with the next 6
                    months. The best estimate of the Department of the duration of the activities of
                    the mission, with regard to these matters, is that it will require a further
                    period of 2 years for completion. This estimate is based upon the policies
                    adopted by the Far Eastern Commission for the removals of restorations work and
                    identification of looted property.</p>
                <p>The foregoing discussion of the functions of the delegation indicates clearly the
                    technical nature of the problems involved. It has also been the experience of
                    the delegation during the past 6 months that the technical competence of its
                    personnel and their intimate acquaintance with the policies of the Far Eastern
                    Commission has been of major significance in their negotiations with other
                    delegations in Tokyo. When the delegation was originally formed, it was staffed
                    by personnel temporarily detailed to it from their regular assignments dealing
                    with these same matters in the Department in Washington. At that time it was
                    hoped that it would be possible to employ an eminently qualified person, either
                    in or out of the government, to become permanent Chief of the Delegation.
                    However, over a period of 6 months it has not been found possible to obtain a
                    person from outside sources with the requisite technical knowledge and
                    experience. It has, therefore, been necessary to ask Mr. Charles L. Hodge, who
                    has been serving as Chief of the delegation on a detail basis from <gloss target="#t_OE1">OE</gloss>, if he would be willing to serve as permanent
                    Chief of the Delegation. He has agreed to accept the position providing the
                    Department would grant him reemployment rights, allow him to maintain his Civil
                    Service Status, and provided his family could join him for the duration of his
                    stay. He also expressed the need for a qualified technical assistant if he was
                    to do the job expected of him by the Department.<note n="56" xml:id="d364fn56">In despatch 1482, December 29, the Acting Political Adviser in Japan
                        reported on the operations of the Reparations and Restitution delegations in
                        Japan and submitted a list of the personnel of 11 delegations. The
                        Reparations Technical Advisory Committee had held 16 meetings since June 2,
                        and a Restitution Advisory Committee was being planned.
                        (800.515/12–2947)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
