<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Douglas) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="369"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 P.W. (Peace)/3–2047</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 66</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-20">March 20,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Foreign Office Comment on General Mac Arthur’s Advocacy
                    of Treaty with Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a copy of a
                    self-explanatory memorandum of a conversation held between a Foreign Office
                    official and an officer of the Embassy on the above-cited subject on March 19,
                    1947.</p>
                <p>I also enclose a copy of the text of an item which appeared in the March 19, 1947
                    issue of the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi> (independent) on the
                    subject of General Mac Arthur’s pronouncement.<note n="72" xml:id="d369fn72">Not
                        reprinted; it indicated approval of General MacArthur’s call for an early
                        peace settlement and his proposal to end the economic blockade and to
                        restore free trading with Japan (740.0011 PW (Peace)/3–2047).</note> There
                    is very good reason to believe that that item was written after its author had
                    canvassed the situation at the Foreign Office, and that it correctly reflects
                    Foreign Office thought on the subject of Japan.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett F. Drumright</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">First Secretary of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the First Secretary of
                            Embassy in the United Kingdom</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Drumright</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-03-19">March 19,
                                1947</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Foreign Office Comment on General MacArthur’s
                        Advocacy of Treaty with Japan.</p>
                    <p>In the course of an informal conversation this afternoon at the Foreign
                        Office, Mr. Drumright inquired what views were held in the Foreign Office on
                        the statement made by General MacArthur to foreign correspondents at Tokyo
                        on March 17, 1947.</p>
                    <p>Mr. MacDermot<note n="73" xml:id="d369fn73">D. F. MacDermot, Head of the
                            Japan and Pacific Department of the British Foreign Office.</note> said
                        that General MacArthur’s views on the future of Japan had not come as a
                        surprise to the Foreign Office, since <pb facs="0465" n="451"
                            xml:id="pg_451"/> about a week prior to his interview with the press
                        General MacArthur had imparted them in a general way to Mr. Gascoigne, the
                        chief British diplomatic representative in Tokyo.</p>
                    <p>Mr. MacDermot said that the Foreign Office shared General MacArthur’s views
                        that an early settlement of issues about Japan is desirable. He went on to
                        say that the Foreign Office is in favor of the conclusion of a general
                        treaty with Japan, but that before such a treaty is arranged the Foreign
                        Office considers that a disarmament and demilitarization treaty along the
                        lines suggested by Mr. Byrnes in 1946<note n="74" xml:id="d369fn74">For
                            draft released by the Department on June 21, 1946, see Department of
                            State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 30, 1946, p. 1113.</note>
                        should be concluded among the interested powers.</p>
                    <p>Though generally approving of General MacArthur’s statement, Mr. MacDermot
                        said that the Foreign Office was “piqued” over his remark that “Japan was
                        still blockaded by the allied powers.” Mr. MacDermot went on to say that
                        Great Britain was not responsible for the economic blockade of Japan and had
                        never wanted it. For several months, as a matter of fact, Britain had been
                        calling for the opening of Japan to private trade, and he (Mr. MacDermot)
                        was glad to see that more and more steps were being taken to open Japan to
                        private trade.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Drumright inquired whether the Foreign Office had issued or contemplated
                        issuing a statement in regard to General MacArthur’s pronouncement. Mr.
                        MacDermot replied that the Foreign Office had not issued a formal statement
                        but that after consultation the news department of the Foreign Office had
                        “briefed” certain correspondents on its thoughts on the matter.</p>
                    <p>Before closing the conversation, Mr. Drumright referred to the currecent
                        clamor in Britain for the demobilization of British troops and asked in this
                        relation whether there might be further withdrawal of British troops from
                        Japan. While Mr. MacDermot did return a categorical reply to this question,
                        it appeared from the tenor of his remarks that the British Government may
                        now have under consideration the withdrawal of further British contingents
                        from Japan. In this connection, Mr. MacDermot referred to a recent
                        pronouncement of the Indian Government on the return of all Indian troops to
                        India and remarked that this undoubtedly presaged the recall of Indian
                        troops from Japan.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett F. Drumright</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
