<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Repeated in telegram 105, August 26, 7 p.m., to
                        Petropolis, Brazil, for the U.S. delegation, headed by the Secretary of
                        State, to the Inter-American Conference for the Maintenance of Peace and
                        Security, held August 15–September 2, 1947.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d403</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">403</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-08-21T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-08-21T22:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-21T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-21T22:00:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 PW (Peace)/8–2247: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="33" xml:id="d403fn33">Repeated in telegram 105, August 26, 7 p.m., to
                        Petropolis, Brazil, for the U.S. delegation, headed by the Secretary of
                        State, to the Inter-American Conference for the Maintenance of Peace and
                        Security, held August 15–September 2, 1947.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-22T12:00:00+09:00">August 22, 1947—noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1770. I was summoned by the Foreign Minister yesterday evening (August 21) and
                    handed a letter addressed by him to you which he asked to have transmitted
                    through our facilities, indicating that he did not wish to rely on the security
                    of the Chinese Embassy in Washington.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister made it plain that he was much concerned over the attitude
                    of the Soviets and the consequences of Soviet refusal to go along with the
                    American peace proposal. He said that the Chinese Government wished to avoid
                    offending the Soviets, especially because of the bearing of the matter on the
                    problem of Dairen.<note n="34" xml:id="d403fn34">For documentation on the status
                        of Dairen, see <ref target="frus1947v07">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> He said that he felt sure that the Soviets would use a peace
                    treaty negotiated without their participation as an excuse for intrenching
                    themselves even deeper and for refusing any form of cooperation with China with
                    respect to Dairen.</p>
                <p>Following is text of letter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Dear General Marshall: I would not write to you personally were it not
                            for the fact that the matter I am going to discuss in this letter is
                            particularly important and merits your immediate attention.</p>
                        <p>Shortly after the contents of the verbal statement made by General
                            Hilldring on July 11 were received, the Chinese Government informed the
                            State Department through its Ambassador in Washington of its views
                            regarding the proposed conference on peace with Japan. It will be
                            recalled that in that reply the Chinese Government stated, among other
                            things, that it would have to re-examine the matter in the event of
                            Soviet Russia refusing to participate in the conference on the terms
                            suggested by the United States and that the Chinese Government would
                            like to know what further steps the American Government would take in
                            case such a contingency arose.</p>
                        <pb facs="0511" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/>
                        <p>Since then the Soviet Government has made its reply, from which it is
                            clear that the stand taken by the Soviet Government in the matter is
                            radically different from that of the American Government and that unless
                            some modification of the original American proposal is conceded, it is
                            scarcely possible to expect her attendance at the proposed conference.
                            It is the opinion of my Government that the purpose of this conference
                            being to seek the creation of greater stability in the Far East and thus
                            to reap the fruit of real peace, no effort should be spared in securing
                            the Soviet Government’s participation, so as to prevent her from
                            pursuing independent lines of action. The policy of my Government in
                            this matter will be based primarily on this consideration.</p>
                        <p>With a view to reconciling the divergent views and seeking a formula
                            under which participation by all the interested powers would be
                            possible, the Chinese Government thinks that the Foreign Ministers of
                            the United States, the United Kingdom, the USSR and China should get
                            together at the time of the forthcoming meeting of the General Assembly
                            of the United Nations and engage in an exchange of views on the
                            organization and procedure of the conference on peace with Japan in the
                            hope that some agreement may be reached and an all-inclusive conference
                            brought about. I shall appreciate it very much if you will give your
                            careful consideration to this suggestion and let me have the favor of an
                            early reply.</p>
                        <p>I am looking forward to the pleasure of meeting you again in September
                            when the General Assembly of the United Nations meets.</p>
                        <p>With kindest personal regards, yours very sincerely, (Signed) Wang
                            Shih-chieh.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
