<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Political Adviser in Korea ( (Langdon))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d467</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">467</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="467"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d467">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 P. W./2–347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Political Adviser in Korea</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Langdon</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 50</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-02-03">February 3,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary of State encloses for reply, a letter from Mr. Soon Ju Chey
                    concerning the treatment of former Japanese industrial facilities in Korea under
                    the reparations program.<note n="19" xml:id="d467fn19">Letter dated November 27,
                        1946, not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary of State transmits herewith the following information for use in
                    replying to Mr. Chey’s letter:</p>
                <p>The negotiations for a settlement of Japanese reparations issues will be carried
                    out on a governmental level by the countries represented on the Far Eastern
                    Commission. As part of its responsibility for Southern Korea, the United States
                    Government is prepared, as it has previously announced, to use a portion of such
                    allocation of Japanese industrial assets as may be made to it through
                    inter-Allied agreement, to secure industrial equipment from Japan for
                    installation in Southern Korea. In addition, it is the United States position
                    that all industrial facilities in Korea which were formerly owned by the
                    Japanese shall be excluded from the Japanese reparations settlement and shall
                    remain the property of the Korean people.</p>
                <p>The United States Government will adopt and will endeavor to obtain agreement by
                    the other nations participating in the Far Eastern Commission to any
                    recommendations contained in the report of Ambassador Pauley<note n="20"
                        xml:id="d467fn20">Department of State, Far Eastern Series No. 25: <hi
                            rend="italic">Report on Japanese Reparations to the President of the
                            United States, November 1945 to April 1946, by Edwin W. Pauley, Personal
                            Representative of the President on Reparations</hi> (Washington,
                        Government Printing Office, 1948).</note> which will contribute to the
                    well-being of the Korean people.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
