<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                        State for Occupied Areas (Saltzman)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d617</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">617</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-09-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-09-23T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-09-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-09-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="617" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d617">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/9–2347</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                        State for Occupied Areas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Saltzman</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-09-23">September 23,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Col. B. C. Limb, Chairman of the “Korean Commission”</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Robert T. Oliver</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Saltzman, Assistant Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Penfield, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Colonel Limb and Mr. Oliver called on Mr. Saltzman by appointment. They expressed
                    great pleasure over the reference of Korea to the General Assembly and conveyed
                    to Mr. Saltzman the gratitude of the “Korean people”. They then proceeded to
                    raise the following matters: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>They referred to the passage of an election law by the Interim
                            Legislature some months ago, said they could not understand why General
                            Hodge has delayed appointing an election commission (which would be the
                            first step toward holding elections), and strongly urged that no time be
                            lost in expediting the holding of an election in South Korea. I was
                            noncommittal in my comments on this subject.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>As an argument for early elections, Messrs. Limb and Oliver described
                            at some length the undesirable situation affecting former Japanese-owned
                            property, which they said constitutes 90% of the productive facilities
                            of South Korea. All of this property is held in trust by the military
                            government which operates it as trustee for a future Korean Government.
                            As a result, no one is willing to make basic policy decisions on the
                            conduct and operation of the property and due to this cause alone, they
                            intimated, Korean production is but a fraction of its pre-war volume. I
                            asked Messrs. Limb and Oliver one or two questions on this matter and
                            promised to look into it further.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Messrs. Limb and Oliver next asked whether an exchange rate could not
                            be fixed for Korean <hi rend="italic">won</hi>. They said that various
                            Korean groups wished to send representatives abroad and that many Korean
                            students wanted to study in American universities but that these very
                            desirable activities were greatly restricted because it is impossible to
                            change Korean currency into US dollars. They suggested that it might be
                            possible to arrange some remittance procedure through the military
                            government, even if the fixing of a general commercial exchange rate was
                            impractical. It was agreed that Mr. Oliver would discuss this matter
                            further with Mr. Hilliard.<note n="18" xml:id="d617fn18">Charles C.
                                Hilliard, assistant for financial policy in General Saltzman’s
                                office.</note>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="0826" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Finally, Colonel Limb explained that he and Miss Louisa Yim had been
                            appointed representatives of the Korean people by the National
                            Representative Assembly which, although unofficial, is representative of
                            all Korean political factions except the Communists. He asked my
                            assistance in arranging for some sort of official or semiofficial status
                            in the UN for him and Miss Yim. I explained that in as much as their
                            credentials came from an unofficial body, it would be very difficult to
                            try to give them an official status and that, furthermore, it was our
                            feeling that the problem now being in the hands of the UN, it would be
                            inappropriate for the US to take the initiative in attempting to arrange
                            for the hearing of Korean witnesses. I added that the UN would
                            undoubtedly want to take Korean views into consideration but that it
                            might, for instance, wish to send a committee out to Korea to get its
                            information on the spot. Messrs. Limb and Oliver appeared to appreciate
                            our position in this matter.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Saltzman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
