<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Soviet Minister for Foreign Affairs (
                        Molotov
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Transmitted to the Acting Secretary of State by
                        the Soviet Chargé (Tarassenko) in his note 210, October 10. The text was
                        published in Moscow on October 12.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d634</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">634</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-10-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="634" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d634">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Korea)/10–1047</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Soviet Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Molotov</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="37" xml:id="d634fn37">Transmitted to the Acting Secretary of State by
                        the Soviet Chargé (Tarassenko) in his note 210, October 10. The text was
                        published in Moscow on October 12.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Marshall</hi>: The position taken by the US
                    delegation in the Joint Soviet-American Commission at Seoul provides evidence
                    that the USA Delegation does not wish to continue the work of the Joint
                    Commission with a view to reaching, on the basis of an exact observance of the
                    Moscow Agreement on Korea, agreed decisions on questions connected with the
                    establishment of a provisional Korean democratic government.</p>
                <p>In violation of the Moscow Agreement on Korea and the understanding reached
                    between the Governments of the USSR and the USA in May 1947 concerning the
                    conditions for resuming the work of the Joint Commission, the USA Delegation
                    insists that not only democratic parties and groups in northern and southern
                    Korea which have signed the declaration of support for the aims of the Moscow
                    Agreement and are loyally carrying out the conditions of this declaration, but
                    also such reactionary groups which, having signed this agreement, are carrying
                    on a struggle against the Moscow Agreement and are continuing to comprise the
                    so-called “Anti-trusteeship Committee”, which contradicts the above-mentioned
                    understanding between the Governments of the USSR and the USA, shall take part
                    in the formation of the Korean Government. The Soviet Delegation, consistently
                    defending the principles of the Moscow Agreement, obviously cannot agree with
                    this.</p>
                <p>The position of the USA Delegation has made impossible the formation of a
                    provisional Korean democratic government in accordance with the Moscow
                    Agreement, which hinders the re-establishment of Korea as a united democratic
                    state.</p>
                <p>In view of the situation which had been created the Government of the USSR
                    instructed the Soviet Delegation to introduce in the Joint Commission at Seoul a
                    new proposal, namely: To give to the Koreans <pb facs="0842" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/> the possibility of forming a government themselves,
                    without aid and participation on the part of the United States of America and
                    the Soviet Union, on condition that American and Soviet troops be withdrawn from
                    Korea. If the Government of the USA should agree to the proposal for the
                    withdrawal from Korea of all foreign troops at the beginning of 1948, the Soviet
                    troops would be ready to leave Korea simultaneously with the American
                    troops.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the fact that this proposal was introduced by the Soviet
                    Delegation at the session of the Joint Commission on September 26, the USA
                    Delegation has unfortunately not replied to date, which cannot fail to delay the
                    solution of the Korean question.</p>
                <p>With reference to the consideration of the Korean question at the session of the
                    General Assembly of the United Nations Organization, which was proposed in Mr.
                    Lovett’s letter of September 17, the position of the Soviet Government on this
                    question, as you know, has already been set forth by the Soviet Delegation to
                    the General Assembly.<note n="38" xml:id="d634fn38">See citations in bracketed
                        note, <ref target="#pg_792">p. 792</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Copies of this letter are being sent by me to the Governments of Great Britain
                    and China.</p>
                <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-10-09">October 9,
                            1947</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
