<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Foote) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d756</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">756</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-06-20T09:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-06-20T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-06-20T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-06-20T09:30:00-05:00" n="756"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d756">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856E.01/6–2047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foote</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-06-20T22:00:00+07:30"
                            >June 20, 1947—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>241. My telegram 239, June 19. Called on Sjahrir today for amendments <gloss
                        target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> reply Dutch note May 27. Instead amendments
                    to <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> reply, received only copy radio address
                    by Sjahrir last night. Highlights thereof follow:</p>
                <p>Following signing Linggadjati, feelings distrust increased and any step or move
                    of either party added to distrust by other. After Dutch note May 27 and
                    Republican’s reply clouded sky became dark. People now discussing possibility of
                    war. Some see <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> reply as rejection in
                    concealed manner designed force Dutch surrender, accepting even force if
                    necessary as consequence of Republican policy. Spirit of Republican reply is
                    sincere desire achieve quick practical solution. Wording of Republican reply
                    could perhaps be better so that increasing suspicion be prevented but <gloss
                        target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> reply clearly stated there no hidden meanings
                    concealing malice or desire for disaster. Republican note is reflection feelings
                    views Republican Government. No new discussions yet occurred so cannot be said
                    what solution can be accepted by all parties but mutual suspicions constantly
                    increasing and atmosphere deteriorating. Real object of Republicans is avoid
                    being forced into degrading situation where have to choose between war and
                    straight out surrender by Republicans. We propose materialize forthwith
                    cooperation meant at Linggadjati and we agree with establishment interim
                    government. What we suggest re composition interim government and position of
                    Crown does not exclude that during first period of interim government
                    representative of Crown may occupy position <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi>. We
                    expect interim government approach nearer what we picture in counter note and
                    interim government finally be dissolved in sovereign government of <gloss
                        target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>. Negotiations reformation interim government to
                    be held with representatives of east <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> and
                    Borneo and this should be done quickly and interim government established by
                    middle July. This ends Sjahrir’s statement.</p>
                <p>Two points should be emphasized: This statement is personal one by Sjahrir and
                    not made in consultation with government at Djocja and, from talks with Sjahrir
                    yesterday and today, Republic has no intention to recede from its bid to
                    dominate all <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> and future <gloss
                        target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>. British Consulate General had separate talk
                    with Sjahrir and appears optimistic re situation but regret I do not share his
                    optimism. Talks today with head <gloss target="#t_FEO1">FEO</gloss> Netherlands
                    Minister Foreign Affairs show Dutch attach little or no importance to Sjahrir’s
                    statement. Atmosphere is tense awaiting decision from Cabinet at Hague.</p>
                <pb facs="0970" n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/>
                <p>In meantime heads of Governments West Borneo and East Indonesia have stated
                    publicly after conversations with Sjahrir and other <gloss target="#t_Indo1"
                        >Indo</gloss> officials their opposition to plans outlined in Republican’s
                    note.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Foote</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
