<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-08-04T22:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-08-04T22:30:00-05:00" n="814" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d814">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">856E.00/8–547: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Foote</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-08-05T11:00:00+07:30">August 5,
                                    1947—11 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>307. In radio broadcast last night Soekarno, as CinC of Republic Armed
                            Forces, gave cease fire order effective at 12 midnite. After reviewing
                            events since July 20, Soekarno said Security Council “appealed to us to
                            cease hostilities”.</p>
                        <p>At ten p.m. last night Sjarifoeddin broadcasted via radio Djocjakarta to
                            effect Republic considers itself no longer bound by Linggadjati
                            Agreement. He stated Dutch violated agreement when they established
                            autonomous states of Banka, Billiton and Riouw. He added Republic wishes
                            solve conflict by peaceful means but that it wishes arbitration by
                            international commission. He said truce means Republic’s fighting youth
                            be released, reinstatement of Republic officials and withdrawal of
                            troops to original demarcation lines. Sjarifoeddin pointed out there
                            still many fighting organizations in action and it will be difficult
                            contact them.</p>
                        <p>General opinion prevails among local Americans, Dutch, moderate
                            Indonesians and others that cease fire order issued by Soekarno will not
                            and cannot be enforced. This opinion based on experience which shows
                            that similar orders issued by <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                            civil authorities have never been carried out by Indonesian military and
                            private fighting clubs.</p>
                        <p>Department please pass London and The Hague.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foote</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>