<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1947-12-03T21:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-12-03T21:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033350"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Textiles</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-03T21:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-03T21:30:00-05:00" n="871"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d871">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/12–447: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-04T10:00:00+07:30"
                            >December 4, 1947—10 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>503. Following are highlights views expressed by Vredenburch during 3-hour talk
                    with Scott and Ogburn December 1: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Re possibility shipment food and textiles to Republican areas and
                            implementation May 1947 Netherlands-<gloss target="#t_Indo1"
                                >Indo</gloss> agreement (Graham telegram 44, December 1<note n="53"
                                xml:id="d871fn53">See telegram 496, December 1, from Batavia, <ref
                                    target="#pg_1076">p. 1076</ref>.</note>), it fantastic expect
                            Dutch cooperation view continued <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                            destruction mills and use trucks by <gloss target="#t_Indo1"
                                >Indo</gloss>s for military purposes. Sabotage and insulting
                            Republican propaganda unabated despite activities <gloss
                                target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> which this case even used as vehicle
                            for such propaganda.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>No improvement situation possible until agreement reached paragraph
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>
                            proposals for implementing cease-fire (Graham telegram 31, November
                                19<note n="54" xml:id="d871fn54">Telegram 467, November 19, from
                                Batavia, not printed.</note>), demarcation lines established, and
                            forces both parties withdrawn from behind lines. (This connection
                            parties still deadlocked paragraph <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, <gloss
                                target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s accepting <gloss target="#t_GOC1"
                                >GOC</gloss> text, Netherlands maintaining prohibition alteration
                            troop positions can apply only forward elements, permitting continuation
                            mopping up rear areas. Vredenburch’s apparent conviction these matters
                            contain key whole problem suggests possibility Dutch working for
                            demarcation lines confining Republicans to central Java which would
                            become permanent arrangement).</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Republican ability or desire control looters any conditions highly
                            doubtful and its word worthless. Too many Djocja politicians out for
                            graft and “everybody in Djocja is in Government.” Republican intention
                            is foment chaos and wreck <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> as means
                            obtaining <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> arbitration of dispute.
                            Republic is totalitarian state denying freedom speech and employing
                            methods terrorism.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Republic only one of many groups working for independence. Plans
                            federal <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> slowly taking shape. Areas
                            states would be determined accordance democratic procedures articles 3
                            and 4 Linggadjati with Republicans probably confined central Java. No
                            possibility liberated areas would vote Republican in plebiscites which
                            already projected. Plan autonomous west Java already far advanced by
                            Abdul Kadir, with early plebiscite likely. Defections from Republicans
                            in Java and Sumatra increasing with populations many localities
                            requesting Dutch protection, and might soon snowball such extent as
                            completely change present situation. It was pointed out to Vredenburch
                            that Dutch views of Republic and plans for federation appeared
                            extraordinarily similar French views Viet Nam and plans federation. <pb
                                facs="1092" n="1078" xml:id="pg_1078"/> He was asked what factors
                            here would prevent duplication disastrous Indochina situation; namely,
                            devastation country and inability metropolitan power either hold on
                            without serious drain its resources or let go without risking wholesale
                            reprisals against elements drawn to its side. Vredenburch replied would
                            refer [<hi rend="italic">prefer?</hi>] question answered by person
                            better informed than he.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Linggadjati Agreement “terrible mistake”. Was approved by Netherlands
                            representatives only because Netherlands Government insisted on
                            agreement any price. Dutch now intend “program based principles
                            underlying Linggadjati”. Linggadjati misled majority <gloss
                                target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> members into assuming Republic and
                            Netherlands were parties dispute. Real parties are Republican <gloss
                                target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s and non-Republican <gloss
                                target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s. This connection, Netherlands had
                            not recognized <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> authority Republican
                            Government any time but only that it exercised <hi rend="italic">de
                                facto</hi> authority at one time in Java, Madura, and
                            Sumatra.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Settlement Netherlands-Republican dispute present conditions
                            impossible. Even under favorable conditions, settlement details would
                            require services <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> 6 months or more.
                            View obvious inability present US member remain more than 2, seem most
                            desirable senior foreign service officer be appointed succeed
                            him.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
