<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Batavia (
                        Livengood
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Repeated by the Department to The Hague in
                        telegram 608, December 23, 6 p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1947v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d879</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">879</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1947-12-19T21:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1947-12-19T21:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-19T21:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-19T21:30:00-05:00" n="879" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d879">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/12–2047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="67" xml:id="d879fn67">Repeated by the Department to The Hague in
                        telegram 608, December 23, 6 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-20T10:00:00+07:30">December 20, 1947—10 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>555. From Graham No. 67. Further to mytel 64, December 18.<note n="68" xml:id="d879fn68">Telegram 549, December 18, not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>As already reported, discussions parties proceeding basis paragraph by
                        paragraph analysis Linggadjati (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                        35, December 11,<note n="69" xml:id="d879fn69">Telegram 359, December 11,
                                <ref target="#pg_1081">p. 1081</ref>.</note>
                        <pb facs="1100" n="1086" xml:id="pg_1086"/> paragraphs 5 and 6). Plan is
                        result USDel position in <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> which based
                        conviction that bringing parties within framework Linggadjati offers only
                        hope solution dispute. However, as Department aware, Dutch by various
                        elucidations have backed out of all provisions agreement giving any basis
                        Republic claims solid status. Believe by end month, areas
                        Netherlands-Republic disagreement will be fully and precisely
                        defined.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Primary area will probably concern
                                basis on which territory states to be delineated including also
                                basis for any subdivision of three component states <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> named in Linggadjati. Will relate
                                directly clauses Linggadjati appearing give assurance of territorial
                                integrity Republic, Borneo and East Indonesia decide by democratic
                                process it will have different status. Nature cooperation between
                                Netherlands and Republic in formation <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>, as provided article 2, as so related this
                                question.</item>
                            <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) If agreement reached this subject,
                                secondary area will probably relate basis determination of relative
                                strength of representation various states in federal bodies, for
                                example, whether Republic if it includes Java, Sumatra, Madura would
                                completely dominate <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> on basis its
                                enormous population or be rendered impotent by small states.</item>
                            <item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) If agreement reached this subject,
                                third area will probably comprise degree sovereignty <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> upon its establishment and nature
                                and duration interim arrangements.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Question precise legal status Republic would probably disappear if
                        agreement reached these areas. According present indications, however, no
                        such agreement possible. Failing such agreement, USDel believes <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> should ask parties whether they wish it
                        propose terms agreement. (This point will be elaborated in subsequent
                        telegram.) Rejection by Netherlands either of this proposal, or, if proposal
                        accepted, of terms suggested (on which probably only two members <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> could agree), seems certain in light
                        current developments and attitude Netherlands delegate. USDel would then
                        propose full report to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> setting forth
                        irreducible areas disagreement and await instructions.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Re assistance Department might render either immediately through approach
                        Netherlands or ultimately in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, USDel
                        considers there basically only two realistic solutions <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> dispute and that efforts US should be
                        directed toward realization one of these solutions.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Continued in following telegram. [Graham.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
