<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1947-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="909" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d909">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.9631/12–3147</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Philippines</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">O’Neal</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1418</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Manila</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1947-12-31">December 31,
                                1947</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the
                            office of President Roxas released the following statement to the press
                            on December 19, 1947, concerning the trade agreement between the United
                            States and the Philippines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The President has expressed great satisfaction this afternoon
                                    when he read the statement made by President Truman at a press
                                    conference in Washington yesterday, giving assurances that the
                                    preferential trade agreement between the Philippines and the
                                    United States would not in any way be altered by any decisions
                                    which might be made at the <gloss target="#t_ITO1">ITO</gloss>
                                    conference in Havana.<note n="42" xml:id="d909fn42">See <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                            United States, Harry Truman, 1947</hi> (Washington,
                                        Government Printing Office, 1963), p. 514, document No.
                                        236.</note> It would be recalled that President Roxas
                                    protested vigorously against attempt in connection with the
                                        <gloss target="#t_ITO1">ITO</gloss> Charter to modify the
                                    trade preferences between the Philippines and the United States
                                    for the duration of the trade agreement, and that he had
                                    instructed Secretary Abello, who is now head of the Philippine
                                    delegation in Havana not to sign any agreement which might in
                                    any way disturb our preferential trade with the United States or
                                    prejudice the interests of the Philippines.</p>
                                <p>“The President expressed appreciation of the attitude of
                                    President Truman and remarked that he is grateful to Ambassador
                                    O’Neal with whom he and the Vice-President had conferred on this
                                    subject for his cooperation in bringing this matter to the
                                    attention of the President of the United States.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>At the same time, the Department of Foreign Affairs released the
                            following telegram which it received on December 18, 1947, from the
                            Philippine Embassy in Washington: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“2129 <gloss target="#t_reurad1">Reurad</gloss> 4286 President
                                    Truman at press conference today flatly denied UniStates has any
                                    intention abandoning its treaty under <pb facs="1140" n="1126" xml:id="pg_1126"/> which Philippines gets certain
                                    preferential treatment from UniStates. President declared there
                                    is not a word of truth in any report that the Administration has
                                    in mind abandoning this treaty. He added it would not abandon
                                    the treaty as long as he was President.</p>
                                <p>“State Department transmitted Ambassador O’Neal’s message
                                    American Delegation Havana. Before Truman made statement
                                    reaction of Division Commercial Policy Department informally
                                    expressed to us was that on basis of Draft Charter approved
                                    Geneva there should be no ground for apprehension in this regard
                                    as under article 16 paragraph 2 subparagraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi> preferences granted Philippines pursuant trade
                                    agreement will not be eliminated. They suggest there might be
                                    misunderstanding on interpretation. We have arranged for
                                    conference tomorrow between Embassy representatives and State
                                    Department experts on the subject. Will inform you further.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>On the occasion of a subsequent informal meeting with President Roxas he
                            assured me personally of his appreciation of the prompt and definite
                            action taken by our Government in this regard.</p>
                        <p>Press comments on the subject have been reported in Embassy despatch No.
                            1397 dated December 22, 1948.<note n="43" xml:id="d909fn43">Not
                                printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Emmet O’Neal</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>