<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Friday, May 9, at 11:25 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-05-09T05:25:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-05-09T05:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-09T05:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-09T05:25:00-05:00" n="52"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.03401/2</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">CF–2</note>
                <head>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Friday, May 9, at 11:25 a.m.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-05-09T11:25:00+01:00">May 9, 1919, 11:25 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>President Wilson.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Clemenceau.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Rt Hon. D. Lloyd George, M. P.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>H. B. M. Orlando.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <table cols="3" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Sir Maurice Hankey, K. C. B.</cell>
                        <cell role="brace" rows="2">}</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretaries.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Count Aldrovandi.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3">Prof P. J. Mantoux.—<hi rend="italic">Interpreter.</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>(Mr. Hurst was introduced.)<note n="1" xml:id="d52fn1">Cecil James Barrington
                        Hurst, Legal Adviser to the British Foreign Office and member of the
                        Drafting Committee.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="margin">Guarantees. Provision for Reoccupation of Terrritory in Case
                        of Necessity</seg>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> pointed out that the text of Article
                    430 of the Treaty of Peace differs from the instructions on the subject which
                    were given to the Drafting Committee. The instructions to the Drafting Committee
                    were as follows:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In case either during or after this 15 years’ delay, the Inter-Allied
                            Commission of Reparations recognise that Germany refuse to execute the
                            whole or part of the conditions agreed upon by her according to the
                            present Treaty, the international re-occupation of part or the whole of
                            the areas defined by Article 2 will take place immediately.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Article 430 of the Treaty reads as follows:— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In case either during the occupation or after the expiration of the 15
                            years referred to ahove, the Reparation Commission finds that Germany
                            has failed to observe the whole or part of her obligations under the
                            present Treaty, the whole or part of the areas specified in Article 429
                            will be re-occupied immediately by the Allied and Associated
                            forces.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The essential difference between the two texts, President Wilson pointed out, is
                    that in the Article in the Peace Treaty the words “Germany has failed to
                    observe” have been substituted for the original words “Germany refuse to
                    execute”.</p>
                <pb facs="0530" n="520" xml:id="pg_520"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hurst</hi> pointed out that the change was a very small
                    one. It was an Article in regard to which no action would take place for at
                    least five years, and then it would only affect a relatively small area of
                    territory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> pointed out that there was
                    considerable difference between refusal and failure to execute the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> pointed out a further difference,
                    namely, that the original draft, though loosely worded, was only intended to
                    apply to Reparation, whereas Article 430 applied to the whole Treaty. The
                    Reparation Commission had nothing to do with anything but Reparation. He agreed,
                    however, that the original text was partly misleading.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hurst</hi> said that this would entail the modification
                    of Article 430, and no doubt an opportunity would arise during the negotiations
                    with the Germans. The alteration would be to Germany’s advantage, so that
                    Germany was not likely to object. He undertook to arrange for a Meeting of the
                    Drafting Committee in the afternoon, and to present a fresh draft by the
                    following morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> asked whether the word “may” should
                    not be substituted for “will” in the last line.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> asked what the original text was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hurst</hi> said it was “will”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said he would prefer to adhere to the
                    original text, owing to the effect of a change on the French people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hurst</hi> said the difficulty could be surmounted by
                    using the future tense in the French text.</p>
                <p>(It was agreed that the Drafting Committee should prepare a fresh draft of
                    Article 430 to be presented to the Supreme Council of the Principal Allied and
                    Associated Powers on the following morning.)</p>
                <p>(Mr. Hurst withdrew.)</p>
                <p>(It was agreed in the afternoon to discuss the action to be taken in the event of
                    a failure on the part of the Germans to sign the Treaty of Peace.)</p>
                <p>(Sir Maurice Hankey was instructed to circulate a memorandum by Marshal
                        Foch.<note n="2" xml:id="d52fn2">See appendix I to CF–4, <ref
                            target="#pg_532">p. 532</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>He circulated at the Meeting the memorandum by the Allied Admirals on the Naval
                    action to be taken.)<note n="3" xml:id="d52fn3">See appendix II to CF–4, <ref
                            target="#pg_533">p. 533</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Villa Majestic, Paris</hi>, May 9, 1919.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
