<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Wednesday, May 14, 1919, at 11:45 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-05-14T05:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-05-14T05:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Demarche</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-14T05:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-14T05:45:00-05:00" n="64"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.03401/12</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">CF–12</note>
                <head>Notes of a Meeting Held at President Wilson’s House in the Place des
                    Etats-Unis, Paris, on Wednesday, May 14, 1919, at 11:45 a.m.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-05-14T11:45:00+01:00">May 14, 1919, 11:45 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>President Wilson.</item>
                                    <item>Mr. McCormick.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Clemenceau.</item>
                                    <item>M. Clementel.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Rt. Hon. D. Lloyd George, M. P.</item>
                                    <item>The Rt. Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, M. P.</item>
                                    <item>Lt. Commander Arnold Forster.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Orlando.</item>
                                    <item>M. Crespi</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <table cols="2" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell rows="2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi>—</cell>
                        <cell>Count Aldrovandi.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Sir Maurice Hankey.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Interpreter</hi>—</cell>
                        <cell>M. Mantoux.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Proposals With Regard to the Blockade of Germany</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord R. Cecil</hi> stated that there were two subjects
                    for consideration; viz., (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) A Public announcement
                    indicating the present position of the Blockade of Germany and stating that it
                    would be raised in the event of signature of the Peace Treaty (Annex 1), (<hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>) a plan of the measures to be taken in the event of its
                    being decided to re-impose the blockade. (Annex 2.) In referring to this plan
                    Lord Robert Cecil drew attention to the proposal in the last paragraph that the
                    Governments of the neutral countries contiguous to Germany should now be invited
                    to consent to prohibit trade with Germany if called upon to do so. This would
                    make it possible to exercise a more immediate and more effective pressure on
                    Germany, if such pressure should become necessary.</p>
                <p>2. Statement with regard to the present position of the blockade (Annex 1).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> drew attention to the words in the
                    first sentence of the statement “as soon as the German representatives have
                    signed the Treaty of Peace.” He suggested that after the signature of the treaty
                    the German assembly might repudiate it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> asked whether it would be necessary to
                    wait for the approval of the Treaty by the Allied Parliaments, before raising
                    the blockade. It was agreed that this would be unnecessary.</p>
                <pb facs="0610" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> proposed that the words quoted above
                    should be amended to read:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“as soon as Germany has formally accepted the Treaty of Peace.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It was agreed that the Statement should be published, subject to this
                    amendment.</p>
                <p>3. Measures to be taken in the event of reimposition of the blockade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> stated that this was not the time to
                    discuss whether we should or should not reimpose the blockade in the event of
                    Germany refusing to sign the Peace Treaty. In his judgment the most suitable
                    means of pressure would be some kind of military occupation rather than blockade
                    measures which would tend to reduce her population to starvation and despair. To
                    have our armies in an area thus starved would not be an edifying spectacle.
                    Blockade would be more terrible than military occupation and presents many
                    inhumane features; if it were reimposed it would presently become distasteful to
                    the world The President expressed grave doubts whether the blockade should be
                    reimposed unless no other course were open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> was of opinion that in any case the
                    application of the blockade would only be necessary for a fortnight or three
                    weeks. An excuse was wanted in Germany for signing the Peace Treaty. The fear of
                    the reimposition of the blockade would provide such an excuse. Haase,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d64fn1">Hugo Haase, leader of the Independent Socialist Party of
                        Germany.</note> for example is afraid of the blockade. There is a pressure
                    in Germany against signing the Treaty, which is a very painful Treaty to
                    sign.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lloyd George</hi> expressed himself as all in favour of
                    a military occupation as a demonstration but not as the only means of pressure.
                    Some parts of Germany would not mind a military occupation. After only a
                    fortnight of the reimposed blockade there would be a general cry to
                        Scheidemann<note n="2" xml:id="d64fn2">Philip Scheidemann, President of the
                        Ministry of the German Republic.</note> of “Sign, Sign”.</p>
                <p>4. On the question of the declaration of a formal blockade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord R. Cecil</hi> drew attention to the statement of the
                    British Admiralty as to objections to such a declaration; he understood that the
                    Admiralty view was that the ships now in commission were insufficient for the
                    maintenance of a strictly “effective” blockade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> said that the United States had never
                    admitted the legality of the existing form of blockade. The Admiralty caveat was
                    thus a little inacceptable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord R. Cecil</hi> said that whether the blockade was
                    absolutely effective or not did not matter, what mattered was the general
                    stoppage of trade.</p>
                <pb facs="0611" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">President Wilson</hi> added that there was a difference
                    between blockade breaking and blockade running. Under the conditions indicated
                    by the Admiralty there might be cases of blockade running: but a definite breach
                    of blockade, such as would render it legally ineffective, would require a naval
                    force which Germany does not now possess.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that if blockade measures have to be reimposed a formal blockade
                    should be declared. No definite decision was arrived at as to whether blockade
                    measures should or should not be taken in the event of Germany refusing to sign
                    the Peace Treaty: but it was understood that such preparations would now be made
                    as would render it possible to give effect to the blockade measures proposed, in
                    the event of its being necessary to take such action.</p>
                <p>In particular it was agreed that the Demarche to Neutral Governments referred to
                    by Lord E. Cecil (see general note at end of Annex 2) should be made now.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord R. Cecil</hi> referred to the possibility of
                    exercising economic pressure on countries, which were appealing to the Allies
                    for assistance and supplies, and were at the same time fighting with their
                    neighbours in defiance of the wishes of the Council.</p>
                <p>He cited the case of Poland which is at present engaged in operations against the
                    Ukraine. He referred also to the food supplies withheld by Serbia in the
                    Banat.</p>
                <p>He suggested that the Council might on occasion think it desirable to notify the
                    Supreme Economic Council that economic pressure should be applied in such
                    cases.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that this should be done and that the Supreme Economic Council
                    should be free to take such action as seemed to them desirable in such
                    cases.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex I]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">supreme economic council</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Public Announcement Indicating the Present
                            Position With Regard to the Blockade of Germany</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The Supreme Council of the Principal Allied and Associated Governments have
                        authorised the following statement as to the present position of the
                        blockade against Germany. Arrangements have been made to remove the blockade
                        against Germany immediately and completely as soon as Germany has formally
                        accepted the Treaty of Peace.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime the following temporary relaxations have already been made
                        for the duration of the Armistice.</p>
                    <pb facs="0612" n="602" xml:id="pg_602"/>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Foodstuffs.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The import of foodstuffs into Germany is now free within the limits of a
                        monthly ration of 300,000 tons of cereals and 70,000 tons of fats.
                        Foodstuffs within the ration may be exported to Germany without formality
                        from any country which is prepared to allow the export to her. Fish imported
                        from the neutral countries contiguous to Germany does not count within the
                        ration. Since March 25th, 1919, the quantity of foodstuffs shipped to
                        Germany by the Associ-ated and Allied Governments has amounted to about
                        550,000 tons, of which about 250,000 tons have been actually delivered. In
                        effect Germany is now free to import all the food for which she can pay.</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Exports.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Exports of gold, silver, securities and war material are prohibited, and
                        other exports over land frontiers are free. As regards oversea exports the
                        Allied Governments have retained certain rights of pre-emption over coal and
                        dye-stuffs and certain other commodities. Other articles can be exported
                        freely to any country prepared to accept them.</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Black Lists.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>All black lists of firms and persons in neutral countries have been
                        withdrawn, and all disabilities attaching to trade and communications with
                        such firms and persons have ceased to operate.</p>
                    <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Communications.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Commercial correspondence with regard to the export and import trade of the
                        character indicated above is permitted, subject to certain regulations which
                        have been accepted by the German Government, and to the Enemy Trading Laws
                        of the Belligerent countries.</p>
                    <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Fishing Area.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The area open to German fishing craft has been largely extended. A quantity
                        of net thread, etc., for repair of nets has been allowed to proceed from
                        Holland in accordance with a request of the German Government.</p>
                    <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Exports from the Allied and Associated Countries to the
                            countries contiguous to Germany</hi>.</p>
                    <p>There is a free list of articles which may now be exported without licence or
                        other formality. In the case of other articles (except where a control has
                        been retained for domestic reasons) the rules as to the obtaining of
                        licenses and guarantees have already been largely relaxed. Export will be
                        further freed from formalities, if a general guarantee is given by the
                        Governments of the neutral countries concerned that they will prevent
                        re-export of such imported articles to Germany without the consent of the
                        Associated Governments.</p>
                    <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Raw Materials.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Permission has been given for the import of raw materials urgently required
                        for use in the German coal mines. Arrangements are being <pb facs="0613"
                            n="603" xml:id="pg_603"/> made for the early shipment of these supplies,
                        subject to the necessary finance being forthcoming.</p>
                    <p>The principal difficulty with regard to the import of raw material is the
                        financial one. In order to obviate this difficulty as far as possible the
                        Supreme Economic Council has approved a plan whereby Germany may be
                        permitted to import rations of raw materials for the urgent needs of the
                        coal mining and other essential industries, in so far as these requirements
                        can be met from German-owned stocks in neutral countries.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-05-12">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">May</hi> 12, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex II</head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">supreme economic council</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Plan of Measures To Be Taken in the Event of
                            Its Being Decided To Reimpose the Blockade</hi>]</p>
                    <p>“In accordance with the instructions given by the Supreme Economic Council at
                        its meeting on May 5th, the Superior Blockade Council and the Military and
                        Naval experts consulting with the Council, submit to the Council of Four the
                        following report:</p>
                    <p>In case the German Government should refuse to accept the preliminaries of
                        peace, the following measures should be immediately taken if the Associated
                        Governments should decide to have recourse to means of economic
                        coercion:</p>
                    <p>(A) <hi rend="italic">Declaration of formal blockade.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Declaration of a formal blockade of the whole of the coast line in the
                        occupation of the Germans, both in the Baltic and in the North Sea.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary’s Note</hi>: Since the adoption of the
                            foregoing recommendation, information has been received from the British
                            Admiralty, that they have strong objections to the declaration of a
                            formal blockade, and consider that the re-establishment of the system of
                            blockade in force before the armistice would be sufficient to accomplish
                            the object in view, especially as more complete naval supervision of any
                            permitted sea traffic between the Nprthern Neutrals and Germany is now
                            possible.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>(B) <hi rend="italic">Danish, Dutch and Swiss Land Frontiers.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Consideration was given to the question as to whether the communications upon
                        the Danish, Dutch or Swiss Frontiers on the German side could be cut by the
                        Allied troops. The Sub-Committee appreciate the fact that, if all or any of
                        these operations could be carried out, the efficiency of the Blockade would
                        be greatly strengthened but they feel that these questions lie outside their
                        province.</p>
                    <pb facs="0614" n="604" xml:id="pg_604"/>
                    <p>(C) <hi rend="italic">Rhine.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The maintenance of a completely effective control upon traffic between the
                        banks of the Rhine.</p>
                    <p>(D) <hi rend="italic">Bavarian Frontier of Germany.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Inter-Allied Commission now in Vienna will take effective measures to
                        prevent exports and imports between Austria and Germany.</p>
                    <p>(E) <hi rend="italic">Czecho-Slovak Frontier of Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Polish Frontier of Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Requests to the Governments of Czecho-Slovakia and Poland effectively to
                        prevent any trade with Germany.</p>
                    <p>The Sub-Committee appreciate the supreme importance of Dantzig and the
                        Dantzig Polish Railway for the revictualling of Poland but they were advised
                        by the Representatives of the General Staffs that the occupation of Dantzig
                        and the control of the railway would entail Naval and Military measures of
                        such importance that they cannot be considered at short notice.</p>
                    <p>(F) <hi rend="italic">Renewal to the fullest extent of Measures previously in
                            force in the case of Neutrals in their relation to Germany.</hi>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The Re-imposition of the <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>Censorship.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>Black Lists.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>Rations.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Reconsideration of the present Free List.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Withdrawal of all concessions made to the Germans under the
                                Brussels Agreement so far as these concessions represent relaxations
                                of previous blockade policy.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary’s Note</hi>: Concessions not
                                        related to the Blockade were not considered by the Council
                                        to come within the province of this report.)</p>
                                </quote>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">General Note</hi>: It would greatly increase the
                        effectiveness of the Blockade if the Neutral Governments of the countries
                        with whom agreements are now in force (Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Holland and
                        Switzerland) should consent forthwith to prohibit if called upon by the
                        Associated Governments to do so, all exportation, re-exportation or transit
                        of goods from or across their respective countries to or from Germany,
                        except with the consent of the Associated Governments.”</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
