<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/2456</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Translation of Opinion in the Mexican Petroleum
                                Company’s Suit for “Amparo” as Announced by the Supreme Court of
                                Justice of Mexico, November 17, 1927</hi><note n="18" xml:id="d188fn18"><p>This translation was enclosed in a letter of
                                    Dec. 14, 1927, from Mr. Guy Stevens, director of the Association
                                    of Producers of Petroleum in Mexico, to the Under Secretary of
                                    State. A previous translation prepared by the Association in
                                    Mexico was transmitted with the Spanish text by the Ambassador
                                    in Mexico in despatch No. 115, Nov. 22, 1927; not printed (file
                                    No. 812.6363/2438).</p>
                                <p>In despatch No. 148, Dec. 5, 1927, the Chargé in Mexico informed
                                    the Department that the formal opinion was signed on Dec. 2,
                                    1927 (file No. 812.6363/2448).</p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Mexico, Federal
                                    District</placeName>. Decision of the full Court, of <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-11-17">November 17,
                                1927</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Having taken under review the case arising from the suit of <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> (the Spanish word <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> means literally shelter, hence protection; and the
                            protection sought in a suit for <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> is similar
                            to that sought in the United States in a suit for injunction) brought by
                            the attorney-in-fact of the Mexican Petroleum Company of California
                            against acts of the Department of Industry, Commerce and Labor and the
                            agent of said Department in charge of the Technical Petroleum Agency in
                            Tampico, State of Tamaulipas, and alleging violation of articles 4, 14,
                            16, 22 and 27 of the Federal Constitution; and upon an examination of
                            the record the following being disclosed (<hi rend="italic">resultando</hi>):</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Statement of the Case</hi></p>
                        <p>First: By a writing dated January 26 of the current year and presented on
                            the following day, Carlos Palomar, as attorney-in-fact of the Mexican
                            Petroleum Company of California, a capacity which he proved by means of
                            an authenticated copy of his power of attorney <pb facs="0300" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> exhibited with his complaint, sought <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> against acts of the authorities before
                            mentioned, which he said consisted of the issuance of official
                            communications Nos. 1090, 1091 and 1093 dated January 11 of the same
                            year, addressed by the Chief of the Technical Petroleum Agency in
                            Tampico to the representative of the aforesaid Company, notifying him
                            that, because of non-compliance with the requirement contained in the
                            Regulatory Law of Art. 27 of the Constitution in the branch of petroleum
                            (i. e. The Petroleum Law promulgated December 31, 1925), making it
                            necessary to ask for confirmation of subsoil rights acquired prior to
                            May 1, 1917, the said Agency, acting upon express instructions from the
                            Department of Industry revokes the permits granted by official
                            communications Nos. 82, of Jan. 3 of the current year, 11 of the same
                            date, and 21, likewise of the same date, to drill wells: “Mendez No.
                            27”, “Chijol No. 63” and “Dicha No. 104”, respectively, in lands of the
                            former Hacienda de Chapacao, Municipality of Panuco, State of Veracruz.
                            These acts are considered as violative of the guarantees established in
                            the Constitutional articles before mentioned, and, to support its
                            complaint, the complainant company sets forth the following
                            allegations:</p>
                        <p>That in the city of Mexico, in the month of January of last year (i. e.
                            1926) it sought <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> against the provisions of
                            articles 2, 4, 14 and 15 of the Regulatory Law of Art. 27 of the
                            Constitution in the branch of petroleum, in so far as those provisions
                            deprived said company of the rights to explore and exploit the
                            oil-bearing subsoil acquired prior to May 1, 1917; that the District
                            Judge dismissed the complaint as not having a legal basis (<hi rend="italic">improcedente</hi>), the Supreme Court having confirmed
                            this decision; that the complainant company considered that the said
                            provisions modified to its prejudice, in respect to its properties and
                            rights, a legal status existing before May 1, 1917, the date on which
                            Art. 27 of the Constitution became effective; that the Supreme Court
                            took the contrary view declaring that the law did not at that time
                            deprive (the complainant) of its rights and possessions, adding that
                            articles 14 and 15 of the Regulatory Law, in designating in connection
                            with Art. 12 the period of one year within which it would be possible,
                            if possible at all, to ask for confirmation of the rights, showed
                            conclusively that the legal provisions cited were not immediately
                            obligatory in character, stating in conclusion that, as yet, no specific
                            act of enforcement could be pointed out; that such a specific act having
                            now taken place, the (present) suit of <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> was
                            being brought on the following grounds:</p>
                        <p>Prior to May 1, 1917, the complainant, a foreign company organized under
                            the laws of the State of California, U. S. A., domiciled in the Republic
                            of Mexico and qualified to do business therein by <pb facs="0301" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> reason of having complied with the legal
                            requirements, acquired in the State of Veracruz various lots of land
                            that form part of the former Hacienda de “Tampalache, Chila y sus
                            Llanos”, known also by the name of Chapacao, acquisitions which it has
                            been exploiting for petroleum, and which date back for more than 25
                            years, as do also the operations undertaken; that the Department of
                            Industry recognized in the fullest manner its rights by official
                            communications of September 2, 1926 and October 16 of the same year;
                            that said recognitions were granted after examination of the title
                            documents proving its rights, of which (title documents) photostatic
                            copies are attached (hereto),<note n="19" xml:id="d188fn19">Not attached
                                to translation.</note> and the right reserved to present the
                            originals if it should be necessary; that the fundamental object of the
                            Company is the exploitation of petroleum, wherefore, in acquiring the
                            various tracts, it did so with the definite purpose of extracting and
                            utilizing the petroleum, a purpose which is corroborated by positive
                            acts of exploitation which it has been performing for twenty-five years;
                            that the official communications by which the drilling permits are
                            cancelled, attack its rights in violation of the individual guarantees
                            invoked, <list>
                                <item>because article 2 of the Petroleum Law declares in absolute
                                    terms that only with the express authorization of the Federal
                                    Executive, granted in accordance with the provisions of the law
                                    and its regulations,<note n="20" xml:id="d188fn20">For text of
                                        petroleum law, see <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi>,
                                        Dec. 31, 1925. For text of the regulations, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Apr. 8, 1926.</note> may the
                                    operations required in the petroleum industry be
                                    conducted;</item>
                                <item>because Art. 4 declares that only Mexicans, companies
                                    organized in conformity with Mexican laws and alien individuals
                                    (the latter under specified conditions) may obtain petroleum
                                    concessions, thus excluding foreign companies such as the
                                    complainant;</item>
                                <item>because Art. 14 provides that there shall be confirmed by
                                    means of concessions granted in conformity with said law, the
                                    rights derived from lands upon which exploitation operations had
                                    been begun prior to May 1, 1917, to the exclusion of any other
                                    (lands), subject to the understanding that the life of such
                                    confirmations may not exceed fifty years computed from the time
                                    the exploitation operations were begun;</item>
                                <item>because Art. 15, according to which the period of one year is
                                    granted for applying for concessions of confirmation, fixes the
                                    penalty that, if this is not done, the respective rights shall
                                    be considered as renounced, and shall have no effect whatever
                                    against the Federal Government.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In the points of law set forth in the complaint it is said specifically
                            that, as regards the lands which complainant acquired in fee (<hi rend="italic">en pleno dominio</hi>) prior to May 1, 1917, its
                            rights over the subsoil <pb facs="0302" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/> are
                            merged (<hi rend="italic">se confunden</hi>) with those over the surface
                            which, according to general law (<hi rend="italic">derecho común</hi>)
                            such as existed prior to the date named, formed a whole with the
                            underlying strata, without other limitations than those established by
                            the Mining Laws, in accordance with the provisions of Art. 731 of the
                            Civil Code,—the discussion as to whether coal, petroleum and other
                            mineral fuels did or did not belong to the owner of the land having been
                            definitely settled by the Mining Code of 1884, which declared in article
                            10 that those substances were of the exclusive ownership of the owner of
                            the soil, which was also declared by the Mining Law of November 25,
                            1909, and the acquisition made by the Mexican Petroleum Company having
                            been under the protection of those laws, the company’s rights to the
                            subsoil, as regards the tracts obtained prior to the effective date of
                            the Constitution, are of indefinite duration as is the right of
                            ownership itself. Wherefore, since the Petroleum Law does not accord
                            recognition to those rights in articles 2, 4, 14 and 15, the individual
                            guarantees before mentioned are violated to its (i. e. the
                            complainant’s) prejudice, <list>
                                <item>because its rights to exploit the subsoil cannot be derived
                                    from a future concession or from a permit or authorization which
                                    the Executive may grant to it, but are born from the titles
                                    themselves;</item>
                                <item>because it is excluded, as a foreign company, from the right
                                    of exploiting the subsoil, since it cannot obtain a concession,
                                    nor have its rights confirmed;</item>
                                <item>because, even supposing that a concession could be granted to
                                    it, that (concession) could refer only and exclusively to lands
                                    on which exploitation operations were begun prior to May 1,
                                    1917, thereby excluding those lands on which it had performed no
                                    operations;</item>
                                <item>because the right to exploit the subsoil is limited as to
                                    time, without taking into consideration the fact that, with
                                    respect to tracts held in fee (<hi rend="italic">poseidos a
                                        titulo de dorminio</hi>), that right is of unlimited (<hi rend="italic">indefinido</hi>) duration;</item>
                                <item>and, finally, because it is established as a condition for
                                    obtaining concessions that these be applied for within the
                                    period of one year, under penalty of loss of all rights now
                                    existing, or what amounts to the same thing, that the titles of
                                    acquisition be cancelled, every right definitely lost, and the
                                    interests of the company confiscated.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The violations specified in the complaint are seven in number: <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 4 of the Constitution, in that Art. 15 of the
                                    Petroleum Law deprives the complainant company of the
                                    accumulation of capital bound up with the subsoil which the said
                                    article confiscates, taking from the Company mentioned the
                                    products of its labor and the fruit of its efforts,</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 14 of the Constitution, in that Art. 27 of the
                                    Constitution is applied retroactively since the Petroleum Law
                                    fails to <pb facs="0303" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> recognize the
                                    significance, as established in unequivocal terms by the Supreme
                                    Court in five decisions (i. e. The Texas Company and other <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> cases decided in 1921 and
                                        1922),<note n="21" xml:id="d188fn21">See <ref target="frus1921v02#pg_461"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                                Relations</hi>, 1921, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 461</ref> ff.; <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_680"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                                            680</ref>; and Estados Unidos Mexicanos, <hi rend="italic">Semanario Judicial de la Federacion</hi>
                                        (México, Antigua Imprenta de Murguía, 1922), quinta época,
                                        tomo x, p. 1308.</note> of that provision (i. e. Article
                                    27), as it relates to the particular case which gives rise to
                                    the <hi rend="italic">amparo;</hi></item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>Art. 14, also, in that the official communications of
                                    revocation deprive the Mexican Petroleum Company of its
                                    properties, possessions and rights, without due process of law
                                        (<hi rend="italic">sin que haya mediado juicio</hi>), and
                                    without compliance with the other requirements set forth in Par.
                                    2 of the said article, since by applying to it Art. 15 of the
                                    Petroleum Law, the right which the Company holds over the
                                    subsoil of its lands is disregarded, (thus) despoiling it of the
                                    right to exploit them, acquired by virtue of former laws;</item>
                                <label>IV.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 16 of the Constitution, in that, without legal
                                    justification, the responsible authorities are disturbing the
                                    complainant company in its possessions, obstructing it in the
                                    exercise of its rights and depriving it of them;</item>
                                <label>V.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 22 of the Constitution, in that Art. 15 (of the
                                    Law) punishes with the penalty of confiscation any one who, as
                                    in the case of the complainant, may not have consented to
                                    receive new titles in exchange for its old titles to the
                                    subsoil, for on the supposition that the exchange of titles
                                    could have been made, as it cannot in this case since the
                                    Company is a foreign one, the confiscation is absolute and
                                    inevitable;</item>
                                <label>VI.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 27 of the Constitution, in that retroactive
                                    effects are given to Articles 14 and 15 of the Petroleum Law,
                                    whereas neither in letter nor in spirit, according to the
                                    declaration of the Supreme Court (i. e. in The Texas Company
                                    case), does Art. 27 of the Constitution have that attribute, as
                                    regards rights to the oil-bearing subsoil acquired prior to May
                                    1, 1917; and</item>
                                <label>VII.</label>
                                <item>That of Art. 27, in the sense that no one may be despoiled of
                                    his properties, save by expropriation for reasons of public
                                    utility and by means of compensation.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Second. The complaint having been admitted by the District Judge of Villa
                            Cuauhtemoc before whom it was presented, the Department of Industry,
                            Commerce and Labor set up: <list>
                                <item>that the drilling permits granted were expressly and
                                    distinctly provisional in nature, that is to say, precarious,
                                    subject to the provisions of the Petroleum Law, so that they did
                                    not imply any recognition of subsoil rights, and still less did
                                    they themselves confer such recognition, wherefore, if the
                                    company did not comply with the fundamental condition upon which
                                    the subsistence of those permits depended, that is to say, if it
                                    did not comply with the provisions of Articles 14 and 15 of the
                                    said Petroleum Law, renouncing voluntarily the rights which it
                                    may have held in the subsoil, it cannot now claim that its
                                    rights were violated by the ordering of the cancellation of the
                                    permits;</item>
                                <item>that as regards the application of certain articles of the
                                    said Petroleum Law, it should be pointed out that a law is being
                                    dealt <pb facs="0304" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> with which in
                                    general terms considers that the bona fide rights, the
                                    confirmation of which was not applied for within the specified
                                    period, are renounced, but so long as it is not proved that such
                                    rights exist and that the Petroleum Law results in harm or
                                    injury to them, there is no ground for the <hi rend="italic">amparo;</hi></item>
                                <item>that the jurisprudence invoked does not declare that the
                                    persons under consideration have rights which were legally
                                    acquired and must be respected, but establishes only that their
                                    rights be respected if and when they are proved;</item>
                                <item>and that, as a matter of fact, the ruling by the President of
                                    the Republic which ordered that such companies as had not
                                    applied for confirmation of the rights which they claimed to
                                    hold, should be brought to the attention of the Attorney General
                                    of the Nation in order that he might bring action to vindicate
                                        (<hi rend="italic">revindicar</hi>) the subsoil rights of
                                    the Nation, gives the Companies an opportunity to prove their
                                    rights and that the Petroleum Law undertakes to despoil them
                                    thereof; and it will be against such final judgment as may be
                                    rendered in that case that <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> may be
                                    brought for the violation of such constitutional guarantees as
                                    may be violated and particularly that contained in Article 14,
                                    but in the present <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> proceeding it
                                    is impossible to prove that acquired rights are legally
                                    involved, and therefore it is not possible to decide that those
                                    rights are being taken away.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The Petroleum Agency in Tampico failed to submit its brief; and the
                            hearing having been held at which the complainant company put in
                            evidence various certified copies of the documents by virtue of which it
                            claims to have acquired its rights, and testimony to show that it had
                            performed petroleum exploration and exploitation operations prior to May
                            1, 1917, the District Judge, in disagreement with the view of the
                            District Attorney, granted the <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi>, on the
                            ground that the Mexican Petroleum Company has been deprived of its
                            rights to explore and exploit the subsoil of Chapacao, without any court
                            proceedings having intervened as required by law, and in violation of
                            Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution, since nationalization of
                            petroleum, according to Art. 27 of the Federal Constitution, should be
                            carried into effect against private individuals through the Judicial
                            Tribunals.</p>
                        <p>Third. The Department of Industry, its Agency in Tampico, the District
                            Attorney and the complainant company appealed. The first two alleged the
                            same errors (<hi rend="italic">agravios</hi>), saying: <list>
                                <item>that there is a contradiction between that part of the
                                    decision in which the court announces its judgment and that part
                                    which contains the reasoning on which the judgment is based,
                                    since (the Court) grants the <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi>, and
                                    at the same time declares that neither Art. 27 of the
                                    Constitution nor the provisions of the Petroleum Law violate any
                                    individual guarantees because it is not the authorities that
                                    apply said laws retroactively, but the legislator;</item>
                                <pb facs="0305" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/>
                                <item>that the said decision is contrary to the letter and spirit of
                                    Art. 27 already mentioned, and the Petroleum Law, inasmuch as
                                    the complainant can only be the owner of petroleum which it may
                                    cause to flow or which may flow naturally (into its possession),
                                    but not of that which in a merely potential sense it may be able
                                    to obtain, for this latter has not as yet been acquired;</item>
                                <item>that the decision overlooks the relevancy of Art. 15 of the
                                    Petroleum Law, which in express terms provides that all rights,
                                    the confirmation of which may not have been applied for, shall
                                    be considered as renounced;</item>
                                <item>that Point Six in the opinion is based upon an erroneous
                                    interpretation of Art. 27 of the Constitution, inasmuch as the
                                    cancellation of the permits does not imply the doing of any
                                    affirmative act on the part of the Department, but purely and
                                    simply a compliance with Art. 15 already mentioned; and</item>
                                <item>that the Judge ignored the clause which specifically states
                                    that the permits are of a provisional nature and subject to the
                                    Petroleum Law.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The District Attorney says: <list>
                                <item>that there is a contradiction between the third and sixth
                                    points in the opinion;</item>
                                <item>that the judgment is in conflict with others rendered by the
                                    same Court in similar cases;</item>
                                <item>that the right to drill has not become part of the estate of
                                    the complainant company in such a way as to make its withdrawal
                                    dependent upon any legal proceedings, for rights that impose
                                    obligations (<hi rend="italic">perentorios</hi>) and are
                                    conditional, granted as an act of favor (<hi rend="italic">a
                                        titulo de gracia</hi>), for the utilization of natural
                                    resources, are of no effect whatever when there has been a
                                    failure to comply with the conditions set out in the title under
                                    which the favor was obtained; and</item>
                                <item>that while a real and perpetual right over the subsoil is
                                    assumed as if such a right had been proved, that is something
                                    which has not been proved.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The complainant company agreed with the judgment, and appealed only in
                            order that the Supreme Court might confirm the granting of the <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi>, taking the ground,— <list>
                                <item>that it is prohibited from exploiting the oil deposits, in
                                    violation of Art. 4 of the Constitution;</item>
                                <item>that it is not true that Par. IV of Art. 27 of the
                                    Constitution is retroactive, either in letter or in spirit,
                                    because the Supreme Court has established jurisprudence (to the
                                    contrary);</item>
                                <item>neither is it true, as the decision asserts, that the
                                    cancellation of the permits is not a penalty or a
                                    confiscation;</item>
                                <pb facs="0306" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/>
                                <item/>
                                <item>that the violation of Art. 27 of the Constitution as it
                                    relates to expropriation was not taken into account, since it is
                                    held that deprivation of rights could be made legally, by
                                    resorting to the judicial authorities and following the
                                    procedure set out in Art. 27;and</item>
                                <item>that the proofs submitted to show the right of ownership, and
                                    the use of that right, were disregarded.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Fourth: The records came to this Supreme Court of Justice, and the appeal
                            having been admitted, they were brought to the attention of the parties
                            and the file was sent to the Attorney General for him to formulate his
                            brief, which he did, to the effect that the judgment under review be
                            reversed, and the <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> denied, taking the
                            ground that as the permits granted were of a provisional nature and
                            subject to the provisions of the Law Regulatory of Art. 27 of the
                            Constitution in the branch of petroleum, those permits could be revoked
                            if the Company failed to (submit to) the provisions of the law; and
                            since it failed voluntarily to apply for confirmation of the rights it
                            claims to hold, the revocation was in accordance with law, no judicial
                            proceeding being necessary, because said formality is unnecessary in
                            revoking administrative permits.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Opinion of the Court</hi></p>
                        <p>The opinion of the Court is as follows (<hi rend="italic">considerando</hi>):</p>
                        <p>First:—The errors alleged by those designated as the responsible
                            authorities, are so closely related to those set up by the District
                            Attorney, that the study of the former includes the latter, so that
                            there is no need of making special mention of either. Therefore, with
                            the exception of the error relating to the existence of the rights which
                            the complainant company claims to hold not having been proved, an error
                            which was alleged by the District Attorney and will be dealt with in a
                            later part of this opinion, the other errors, as has been said before,
                            will all be analyzed together.</p>
                        <p>Second:—It is objected that the part of the decision containing the
                            judgment of the Court is inconsistent with some of its reasoning,
                            because notwithstanding it is maintained in the Court’s reasoning that
                            it was the legislator and not the responsible authorities who gave
                            retroactive effects to the law, wherefore, in applying it (i. e. the
                            law), there is no violation of guarantees in this respect, nevertheless
                            an <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> is granted. The error does not exist;
                            for even admitting the correctness of this premise, it would not in
                            itself be a sufficient cause for reversing the judgment, unless the
                            reasoning directly governed the judgment part; and quite on the
                            contrary, it appears from the decision that the reason for which the <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> was granted was not the retroactivity
                            which the complainant company <pb facs="0307" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/>
                            alleges to be a feature of the Petroleum Law, but the fact that the
                            Judge took the point of view,—a point of view which the Supreme Court
                            does not undertake to analyze,—that there had been deprivation of rights
                            without due process of law as required by articles 14, 16 and 27 of the
                            Constitution.</p>
                        <p>It is asserted also that the decision recognizes that the existence of a
                            potential right, namely, the right of the company to exploit the
                            subsoil, is violated. It is not true that there are involved here rights
                            merely in expectancy; for in addition to the fact that the District
                            Judge has referred only to the rights to explore and exploit which had
                            been granted to the complainant, the said rights exist by virtue of the
                            operations which the said (complainant) has conducted under the
                            respective permits, under the protection of former general provisions
                            (of law), and not merely potentially; and because of that fact (i. e.
                            the actual conduct of operations), there is, to say the least, no simple
                            expectancy involved here, and all the more since the said Petroleum Law,
                            the application of which is under consideration, recognizes in an
                            express manner (both the) possible and real existence of those rights by
                            enumerating them in article 14, and does not withhold recognition of
                            said rights for an alleged failure to exercise the same or utilize them.
                            The Department of Industry, when it maintains the contrary in its
                            corresponding error, goes so far as to put itself in conflict with the
                            very Petroleum Law with the enforcement of which it is charged.</p>
                        <p>The contention made to the effect that the rights of the Company
                            respecting which no confirmation was applied for, should be considered
                            as legally renounced, in accordance with the provisions of article 15 of
                            the Petroleum Law, is not tenable. In fact, the law allows a period of
                            one year in which to present the application for confirmation of rights,
                            and that period could not have run as against the complainant company,
                            because if that confirmation cannot be granted for more than fifty
                            years, as provided in the final paragraph of fraction 2 of article 14 of
                            the Law, and if this limitation implies a partial restriction or partial
                            loss of the rights which its titles, granted prior to May 1, 1917, may
                            confer (upon the Company), it is evident that said application could not
                            have been made by the complainant without curtailment of something which
                            belongs to its estate, so long as such application would imply
                            submission to the aforesaid limitation. And if it is indisputable that
                            the confirmation of a right is the express recognition of the same, the
                            restricting of it in the manner provided in said article 14 is to
                            modify, and not to confirm, said right. Consequently, if the complainant
                            company was not able to apply for the confirmation of its pre-existing
                            rights, except with the limitation of them as to time, it is beyond
                            doubt that it was imperative that this restriction should first
                            disappear and, <pb facs="0308" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> by the same
                            token, the period of one year specified in this connection by article
                            15, could not have elapsed, there existing the impossibility mentioned;
                            and as the Department of Industry and Commerce, contrary to the concepts
                            expressed above, revoked the permits which it had granted to the
                            complainant company, on the ground that the said period had expired,
                            without taking into consideration the unconstitutionality of the limit
                            of fifty years, a condition attaching to the confirmation, it is
                            indisputable that the protested ruling violates in this respect the
                            guarantees afforded the complainant by articles 14, 16 and 27 of the
                            Federal Constitution.</p>
                        <p>Finally, it is said that the Judge failed to consider the clause
                            contained in the revoked permits, relative to the provisional nature of
                            the same, and (stipulating) that they shall be subject to the provisions
                            of the Petroleum Law. In this connection it is to be observed that the
                            decision does deal with this question,—the statement of the error being
                            therefore incorrect; but even though this alone would be sufficient for
                            dismissing it (i. e. the point raised in this assignment of error), it
                            is well to point out that the revoked permits, although they were of a
                            provisional nature, were granted upon the fundamental consideration that
                            the applicant company had rights which it could allege, and of the kind
                            covered by Article 14 of the Petroleum Law, and as yet there has been no
                            legal examination of those rights that makes it possible to assert that
                            they do not exist as set forth in said Article 14. Moreover, compliance
                            with the Petroleum Law, however free, spontaneous and open we may assume
                            it to be, can refer only to those provisions which are constitutional;
                            for, otherwise, it would be necessary to accept the absurdity that
                            personal guarantees may be renounced, something which it is settled law
                            cannot be done, constituting as they do a basic precept of our
                            Constitutional Law.</p>
                        <p>Third:—The District Attorney asserts that the rights which the
                            complainant company claims to hold were not proved, and that, as the
                            decision of the District Judge goes upon the theory that they were, this
                            constitutes an error. At the hearing the Mexican Petroleum Company
                            exhibited various certified copies referring to the acquisition of
                            different lots of land for petroleum exploitation purposes, and
                            furthermore, produced testimony proving the regular operations carried
                            out in said land, which is sufficient ground for holding it (the
                            Company) injured for the purposes of <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi>,
                            since it is not in this proceeding involving constitutional questions
                            that alleged property rights should be discussed, and still less those
                            of the complainant company refused recognition out of hand, inasmuch as
                            precisely such an examination of rights must (<hi rend="italic">deberá</hi>) be made when the application for confirmation is
                            presented to the Department of Industry and Commerce. <pb facs="0309" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> Consequently, if the Company has not had
                            the opportunity of having the rights relied upon examined, the error
                            assigned by the District Attorney is not to be admitted.</p>
                        <p>Fourth:—The errors alleged by the responsible authorities and the
                            District Attorney having been analyzed, it is necessary to enter upon a
                            study of the violations claimed in the demand for <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi>, with the exception of that relating to the limitation
                            as to time contained in Article 14, which has already been dealt with in
                            earlier parts of this opinion. The complainant company maintains that
                            the provision which imposes the obligation of applying for confirmation,
                            constitutes in itself a violation (of its constitutional rights), since
                            such confirmation cannot be accorded except in the form of a new
                            concession which the said Company believes it is not called upon to
                            apply for, because it is in the enjoyment of the rights in question by
                            virtue of its titles and the perfectly valid authorization issued before
                            the Petroleum Law (went into effect). Legally, this error cannot be
                            upheld, because the Department of Industry, Commerce and Labor violates
                            no guarantee whatsoever in requiring that confirmation of the rights be
                            applied for, since Article 14 of the Petroleum Law refers only to the
                            recognition of acquired rights without any substantial alteration; so
                            that, the requirement of confirmation is only a formality (<hi rend="italic">modalidad</hi>) imposed by the Legislator upon the use
                            and exercise of the said rights for reasons of a public nature, and for
                            the very purpose of safeguarding them. If such rights were confirmed by
                            operation of the law and no report (<hi rend="italic">manifestación</hi>) had to be made, it would be extremely difficult and
                            impossible in many cases to determine whether the specified rights
                            continued to exist in their original form (<hi rend="italic">estado</hi>) or had changed for any reason.</p>
                        <p>There are procedures similar to this in our legislation, and off hand we
                            might mention the provisions of the Law relating to Waters of Federal
                            Jurisdiction, requiring confirmation of rights for the use and
                            utilization of said waters which until then had been under local
                            jurisdiction and by the new law came under federal jurisdiction; but
                            providing that such confirmation should be made under the procedure
                            established therein, which required the water user to apply to the
                            Department of Fomento, in order to obtain confirmation of his rights, as
                            a means employed by the Legislator to secure knowledge regarding the
                            utilization of public waters, the existing number of water users, and
                            their location and boundaries, and thus be in a position to exercise the
                            supervision and (perform) the other duties which the laws impose upon
                            the authorities, to do which they would not be qualified if uninformed
                            of the facts before mentioned; and similarly the Department of Industry,
                            Commerce and Labor must have some means of getting before it the various
                            holders of titles to petroleum <pb facs="0310" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/>
                            lands and be able to know the condition and the extent of their rights,
                            confirming them without any cost in accordance with the provisions of
                            Paragraph I of Article 14, by means of an act of recognition (<hi rend="italic">mediante un reconocimiento</hi>), which is nothing but
                            the use of a formula for expressing (<hi rend="italic">expresión
                                formulista</hi>) the confirmation of rights already acquired to
                            which the very Petroleum Law refers. Consequently, the rights of the
                            complainant company are not at all affected by a confirmation which does
                            not modify them, but which recognizes them, provided that the
                            requirements laid down by fractions 1 and 2 of Article 14 of the said
                            Law, and the obligations set out in its (the Company’s) respective
                            titles, are complied with.</p>
                        <p>Fifth:—To go further, there is no doubt in anybody’s mind that petroleum
                            and its derivatives constitute one of the resources most coveted and
                            sought after by industry and commerce, and that the zones in which they
                            are produced are of limited and small area. Within an area which is
                            often small there are mingled and developed many and varied industries;
                            surface and underground transportation, industries of extracting and
                            treating petroleum, and operations of exploration and exploitation. All
                            these activities, instead of developing harmoniously, frequently come in
                            contact, clash and enter into conflict, leading to interference and
                            encroachments, which it is the unavoidable duty of the Public Power to
                            prevent and regulate; and it is not humanly or reasonably possible to
                            regulate this activity without having an exact knowledge of it, without
                            knowing and harmonizing the conflicting interests, and the plan and
                            conditions of their development; and the initial and primary road to
                            this understanding is confirmatory registration which neither injures
                            nor modifies substantially the rights, but tends merely to authenticate
                            and make certain of them, thus enabling the Public Power to coordinate
                            them in a wise and peaceable manner. The large concentration of human
                            beings within the restricted area of centers of population has produced
                            the common phenomenon observable in all large cities, of the land being
                            utilized to the last millimeter for the erection of large buildings,
                            formidable structures in which are sheltered hundreds and thousands of
                            people, and notwithstanding the undeniable rights of the owner of the
                            building to utilize his property and the rights of the tenants to enjoy
                            the inviolability of their homes without being molested, the public
                            authority establishes supervision within them,—police, sanitary and of
                            other kinds, without that being considered by anybody as a transgression
                            or a violation of the home or property; and in an analogous situation,
                            the Legislator undoubtedly had a similar object in view regarding the
                            petroleum zones, in which the crowding of persons, of activities, or
                            interests openly or latently in conflict, makes it his duty to take
                            opportune measures of social foresight <pb facs="0311" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/> looking toward better living conditions, aside
                            from the fact that the essential purpose of issuing confirmatory
                            concessions is to give to the State (the power of) regulation and
                            supervision (<hi rend="italic">interventión</hi>) which Article 27 of
                            the Constitution recognizes in it.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Judgment of the Court</hi></p>
                        <p>By reason of what has been stated, and upon the basis of Articles 103,
                            fraction 1, and 107, fraction 9, of the Federal Constitution and Article
                            86 and other pertinent ones of the Regulatory Law of <hi rend="italic">Amparo</hi>, it is resolved: <list>
                                <item>First:—The judgment pronounced by the District Judge in the
                                        <hi rend="italic">amparo</hi> proceedings to which this
                                    record refers, is confirmed in the following terms:</item>
                                <item>Second:—The Justice of the Union protects and defends the
                                    Mexican Petroleum Company of California against the acts of
                                    which it complains and which consist in the revocation of the
                                    permits granted by the Department of Industry, Commerce and
                                    Labor to drill wells: “Mendez No. 27”, “Chikol No. 63” and
                                    “Dicha No. 104”, in lands of the former Hacienda de Chapacao,
                                    Municipality of Panuco, State of Veracruz, basing such
                                    revocation on Articles 14 and 15 of the Petroleum Law, the
                                    organic law of Article 27 of the Federal Constitution, and
                                    imposing the penalty established by said Article 15.</item>
                                <item>Third:—Let notice be given . . . . . . .</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>