<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-01-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.12/897</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a
                                Conversation With the Chilean Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Cruchaga</hi>), <hi rend="italic">January 21, 1927</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1927-01-21">January 21, 1927</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg></opener>
                        <p>He then told me that he had heard from Mexico that my suggestion about
                            arbitration was very satisfactory and said that he thought that the
                            Mexican Ambassador and I could agree on an arbitration in a very short
                            time. I told him that according to my information the Mexican Government
                            was continuing its confiscatory acts; that they were daily cancelling
                            permits to drill for oil on properties owned by American citizens and
                            that, of course, we could not permit any such confiscatory proceedings
                            to go on. He said that he might suggest to the Mexican Government that
                            they stop their confiscatory <pb facs="0330" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/>
                            proceedings pending negotiation. I told him I did not care to have him
                            make any suggestions; that the Mexican Government was going ahead with
                            full knowledge of our position; that they understood it fully from my
                            notes to that Government; that their attitude did not seem to be
                            conciliatory at all. I declined to permit him to make any suggestions to
                            the Mexican Government on the subject.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>