<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Greek Legation to the Departments of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="21"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.51 War Credits/479⅞</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Greek Legation</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Departments of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>In order that the capacity for payment be fully appreciated, it must be borne in
                    mind that Greece has been at war continuously since September 1912 until April
                    1923. This war resulted in an internal disturbance which aggravated the economic
                    situation of the country. The war expenditures and refugee needs are estimated
                    by experts at 63,400,000,000 pounds Sterling, from which only 26,000,000 will be
                    covered through external loans, and the balance from Greece’s own resources. As
                    a result of the defeat in Asia Minor, the war material was entirely destroyed
                    and the replacement strictly imposed for the elementary defense of the country
                    has cost more than 3,400,000,000 Drachmas. And despite the compulsory
                    consolidation of the interest bearing notes by the Dictatorial Government, there
                    remains still a floating debt for the payment of the most urgent part of which
                    the League of Nations has considered as indispensable the sum of 3,000,000
                    pounds.</p>
                <p>The deficit of the year 1927–1928 estimated on the basis of the results of the
                    financial exercise of the previous year and the additional obligations, has been
                    figured at 2,600,000,000 Drachmas. Superhuman efforts are being made in order to
                    cover this deficit and create a steady balance, through the realization of
                    economies, mainly in the expenditures in the War and Navy Departments and
                    through the increase of the existing taxes. The taxation burdens, however, have
                    attained such large proportions that they have exceeded the resistance of the
                    people as is evidenced from the decrease noted in the tax revenues. In fact,
                    despite, the heavy new taxation, the revenues of the first semester amounted to
                    3,645,000,000 Drachmas, against the estimated revenues of 8,829,000,000; that
                    is, a deficit of revenues for the first semester of 770,000,000 and for the
                    whole year of 1,540,000,000. This deficit must be reduced by superhuman efforts
                    in order to improve the revenues of the second semester. However, it is evident
                    that the resistance of the people is exhausted and that any further increase of
                    taxes is excluded since the results are directly the opposite of those
                    anticipated.</p>
                <p>Upon the new exercise will be imposed additional expenditures pertaining mainly
                    to the public debt of 634,000,000 Drachmas, of which 258,000,000 will be used
                    for the loan to be contracted for the settlement of refugees and the
                    consolidation of 138,000,000 Drachmas for the public Ottoman Debt; 91,500,000
                    for the assistance of the State railways; relative to the service of the loans
                    contracted during the Dictatorship; 30,000,000 for the loan relative to the
                    fulfillment of the Greco-Bulgarian agreement on the exchange of populations;
                    32,000,000 for the loan relative to the indemnities to be paid to those who
                    abandoned their properties in Turkey and 50,000,000 for increasing the amount
                        <pb facs="0116" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> already used for the payment of the
                    debt to the National Bank of Greece.</p>
                <p>The above figures do not include the new burdens which will have to be carried as
                    a result of the debt settlement with the United States and France.</p>
                <p>It is quite clear that since any new imposition of taxes is excluded, the only
                    remaining means to increase the revenues is the reinforcement of the national
                    economy, through the full settlement of the refugees and the development and
                    construction of new productive works. For the full settlement of the refugees,
                    it will be required according to the lowest estimate a sum of 5,000,000 pounds
                    (which personally the Minister of Finance considers insufficient), part of which
                    will be met by the loan of $3,000,000 approved by the League of Nations.</p>
                <p>It must be pointed out that since the arrival of the refugees despite the
                    compulsory expropriation of all large properties, there is a shortage of
                    tillable land which, to a certain extent, has lessened the desire for work by
                    those refugees already established and furthermore seriously affected the
                    establishment of the rural refugee population still remaining in the cities.
                    Therefore, it is necessary to complete the net of roads and the draining and
                    anti-flood works upon the completion of which Greece will be entitled to expect
                    an improvement of the economical situation.</p>
                <p>It can be easily understood that after so many hardships and following the
                    national catastrophe which deprived Greece of Thrace and Asia Minor and caused,
                    in addition to the loss of all war material, the death of 60,000 men and the
                    influx of one and a half million refugees, the economic situation of Greece
                    became precarious and the capacity for payment was reduced to the minimum. It is
                    only due to the great frugality, the industrious character and vitality of the
                    Greek people that the country withstood complete annihilation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-11-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 5, 1927</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
