<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-07-20T14:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-07-20T14:45:00-05:00" n="456" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d456">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/4940: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Eberhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-07-20T14:00:00-05:45"><hi rend="italic">July 20,
                                        1927—2 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received July 21—11
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>175. The Department’s 112, July 18, 5 p.m. Sandino is reported to be an
                            erratic Nicaraguan about 30 years of age with wild Communist ideas
                            acquired largely in Mexico where he spent several years prior to his
                            return to Nicaragua about a year ago via the Coco River plentifully
                            supplied with arms which he gave to followers in northern Nicaragua or
                            concealed there, meantime working at the Butters American mine in San
                            Albino till he finally joined Moncada this spring. Refusing to lay down
                            arms with other Moncada generals he returned to northern Nicaragua where
                            he has since roamed at will with a few followers committing most every
                            known depredation and acts of outlawry. Following his confiscation of
                            the American mine referred to in my telegram number 161, June 30, 2
                            p.m., the number of his admiring followers increased and he repeatedly
                            wrote insultingly to Captain Hatfield, commander of the garrison at
                            Ocotal, offering his men all loot and plunder they might find and also
                            to join them drinking “Yankee blood” the day soon to be when they would
                            take that town. One o’clock Saturday morning July 16th, Sandino led 300
                            or 400 men, plentifully armed with rifles, machine guns and bombs made
                            from powder confiscated from the American mine, in an attack on 39
                            marines and 48 Nicaragua constabulary garrisoned at Ocotal, the latter
                            well supplied with small arms but with only two machine guns. The fight
                            continued till middle of the afternoon with a loss to Sandino of more
                            than 200 men when our airplanes arrived and with bombs and machine
                            gunfire routed the attacker[s] who fled in disorder, Sandino with
                            them.</p>
                        <p>It should be remembered that for weeks, General Feland had given Sandino
                            every opportunity to surrender or leave the country and had brought upon
                            himself much blame for not having dealt with the bandit more severely.
                            Furthermore, Feland had ordered his men to make no advances against
                            Sandino and only to fire on the enemy if they should be attacked.
                            Sandino apparently considered this course of the Americans as a sign of
                            weakness; preached Communism, Mexican brotherly love and cooperation,
                            and death to the Americans, until the rabble of the whole north country
                            joined him in his plan to massacre Americans there and to set up his own
                            government at Ciudad Sandino, the name to which El Jicaro the capital of
                            the department had been changed by him. He has met with complete
                            disaster and while some persons think [he will] collect as much cash as
                            possible <pb facs="0544" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/> and leave for
                            Honduras or return to Mexico it is quite possible that in his fanaticism
                            he will continue his outlawry though quite unlikely on any large scale
                            any time soon.</p>
                        <p>Throughout the whole affair the forebearance and self-restraint exercised
                            by our troops under most exasperating provocation should call for
                            nothing but commendation from all good Americans just as their
                            magnificent stand against such heavy odds in the actual fight should
                            fill any American with pride.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Eberhardt</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>