<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-02-10T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-02-10T14:00:00-05:00" n="742" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d742">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.672/558: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The High Commissioner in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bristol</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase<note n="26" xml:id="d742fn26">Quotations not paraphrased.</note>]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Angora</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-02-10T21:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">February 10,
                                        1927—9 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received February 11—9:15
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>11. My telegram No. 9, dated February 7, 6 p.m. This evening I met Tewfik
                            Rouschdy Bey. He did not present a draft text himself, but [accepted?]
                            in principle my draft with the suggestion that the following changes be
                            made:</p>
                        <p>Article 1. In the first sentence change “reestablish” to read
                            “establish”. Modification recommended.</p>
                        <p>Article 2, paragraph (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>). In the first sentence,
                            beginning with the word “ratified” and ending with the word “Congress”,
                            change to read, “ratified by the United States Senate and the Grand
                            National Assembly of Turkey on or before June 1, 1928”. Add as a
                            concluding sentence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="flushleft">“It being understood that in the event the
                                    Turkish-American treaty is ratified before June 1, 1928, article
                                    31, thereof, shall be modified to read that the nonpermanent
                                    articles of that treaty will expire on the same date as
                                    corresponding articles of the allied treaties of Lausanne.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The modifications recommended in paragraph (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                            were unimportant changes in wording.</p>
                        <p>Article 3 is to be discussed and made the subject of a separate note to
                            be signed and to go into effect concurrently with this note. The
                            separate note would provide for the preservation of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> for 1 year from the date of signing.
                            At the end of this term the note would automatically continue for a
                            further period of 3 months unless in the interim the Lausanne Treaty
                            should have been ratified, or unless by mutual agreement the note should
                            have been modified, or unless one of the contracting parties should have
                            been asked for a reconsideration of its provisions. The Foreign Minister
                            desires this change because such a provision requires the approval of
                            the Grand National Assembly, whereas the other provisions of this note
                            do not need to be submitted to the plenary session.</p>
                        <pb facs="0894" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/>
                        <p>Article 4 is to be changed commencing with the thirty-ninth word of the
                            first sentence, “article”, and continuing through to complete the
                            article <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="flushleft">“the principles enumerated in articles 1 and 2
                                    of this note together with the essential provisions of the
                                    Turkish-American treaty signed at Lausanne August 6, 1923, and
                                    its annexes shall [constitute?] the basis for the law [<hi rend="italic">treatment?</hi>] which on condition of
                                    reciprocity shall be accorded nationals of Turkey in the United
                                    States and nationals of the United States in Turkey.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Modification is recommended.</p>
                        <p>In place of our article 5, which we did not discuss, I recommend the
                            following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The present agreement shall become effective on the day of
                                    signature.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>For the preamble of this note I recommend the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Excellency: I have the honor to make the following statement of
                                    my understanding [of the] agreement reached through recent
                                    conversations at Angora on behalf of the Government of the
                                    United States and the Government of Turkey with reference to the
                                    regularization of relations between the United States and
                                    Turkey.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>February 12 we shall meet to agree on the final text which I shall
                            immediately telegraph to the Department. In the meantime it is
                            recommended (1) that the Department approve the text as amended; (2)
                            that I be [authorized?] to sign the French translation of this text; (3)
                            that the Department immediately telegraph full powers for I think we
                            should act quickly.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bristol</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>