<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Uruguay ( (Grant-Smith) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1927v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d767</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">767</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-09-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-09-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="767"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d767">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.332/1</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-09-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 6, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received September 30.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 287</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s instruction
                    No. 54 of August 6, 1926,<note n="1" xml:id="d767fn1">Not printed; this
                        instruction was substantially the same, <hi rend="italic">mutatis
                            mutandis</hi>, as instruction No. 905, Aug. 28, 1926, to the Minister in
                        Colombia, <ref target="frus1926v02#pg_1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1926, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1</ref>.</note> I have the honor to
                    report that in conversation this afternoon with Sr. Saralegui, Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs a. i., referring to the study I had been making recently of the
                    treaty making powers of the Uruguayan Government, I said casually that it was
                    surprising that no Treaty of Commerce and Consular Rights existed between our
                    respective Governments. He replied that Uruguay now had no treaties of commerce
                    with any country and, on my mentioning those with France and England, he said
                    that they had all been denounced after the War. To my inquiry as to how Uruguay
                    got on, he replied that her commercial relations with other countries were
                    regulated entirely by International Law on the basis of the most-favored-nation
                    treatment and pointed out that the Uruguayan Tariff was the same for all.</p>
                <p>I observed that it was precisely the policy of unconditional most-favored-nation
                    treatment that the United States was trying to forward; that we had recently
                    negotiated a treaty with Germany on that basis<note n="2" xml:id="d767fn2">See
                            <ref target="frus1923v02#pg_22">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            pp. 22</ref> ff.</note> and that he would readily understand that
                    Germany would not have entered into an agreement which would not have been
                    advantageous to her interests, to which he readily assented. I mentioned that I
                    had been interested to learn by the press telegrams that a similar treaty had
                    just been concluded between the United States and Hungary<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d767fn3">See <ref target="frus1925v02#pg_341">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            pp. 341</ref> ff.</note> and went on to say that I was convinced that in
                    the adoption of the policy of the “wide open door” small nations would find the
                    best guarantee for their independence. That, for example, in case a neighbor or
                    other strong power should at any <pb facs="0916" n="814" xml:id="pg_814"/> time
                    manoeuvre a country into a difficult position, it might be difficult to avoid
                    the concession of special privileges, especially might that come about in the
                    condition in which Uruguay at present found herself, without any commercial
                    treaties. On the other hand, such a possibility would be avoided if she had a
                    treaty containing broad provisions such as those contained in our treaty with
                    Germany.</p>
                <p>I observed that the old spirit of monopoly was still abroad; that the desire to
                    canalize commerce to their own exclusive advantage was still entertained by some
                    nations. I said that in that connection, I had been especially interested by a
                    case in the colonial history of this part of the world. He would recall that
                    during that period, the Spanish had held a monopoly for the commerce with South
                    America, had canalized it over the Isthmus and down the Pacific Coast to Peru,
                    whence it had had to cross the Andes and so down to Buenos Aires. Legitimate
                    trade could then be carried on only by that circuitous and costly route, whereas
                    all traffic direct by sea with the River Plate was treated as contraband.</p>
                <p>Sr. Saralegui evinced interest and inquired why I did not submit a draft of such
                    an agreement, to which I replied that first I would prefer that he should
                    examine our treaty with Germany, which I would have translated into Spanish,
                    when he could see just what it contained, a suggestion which he appeared to
                    receive with satisfaction. I added that we had no such treaties with nations in
                    this part of the world and that I was not unnaturally desirous that such a
                    treaty should be negotiated during my incumbency of this Legation.</p>
                <p>It will be my endeavor to induce Sr. Saralegui to repeat his suggestion in
                    writing and although he may do so there would be no prospect of substantial
                    progress with negotiations being made until after the November elections. It
                    will be, however, advantageous if we can bring them about before the return from
                    Europe of Dr. Blanco because Sr. Saralegui, being the permanent Undersecretary,
                    will presumably stop on at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs whatever the result
                    of the elections may be and would be likely to take more interest in such a
                    treaty if the negotiations are initialed by him. Should I be fortunate enough to
                    receive a written request I shall advise the Department by telegraph and would
                    be glad if a draft would be forwarded to me with as little delay as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">U. Grant-Smith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
