<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-14T06:09:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-14T06:09:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                    <head>123. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State and the
                        Embassy in Bahrain<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d123fn1">Source:
                            National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                            Foreign Policy Files, D750170–0050. Confidential. Repeated to London,
                            Jidda, Kuwait, <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CNO_1">CNO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>,
                                <gloss target="#t_CINCUSNAVEUR_1">CINCUSNAVEUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_COMIDEASTFOR_1">COMIDEASTFOR</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_USCINCEUR_1">USCINCEUR</gloss>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-05-14T11:09:00+00:00">May 14, 1975,
                                1109Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>4508. Subj: Shah’s Statement on Foreign Forces in Gulf. Ref: Manama
                            0545.<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2">In telegram 545 from Manama, May 8,
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TJW_1">Twinam</persName> requested
                            comment on the Shah’s reported criticism of the U.S. naval presence in
                            Bahrain. (Ibid., D750162–0190)</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> Although <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss>
                        rhetoric may be evolving to more neutral or independent posture as Iran and
                        Arab states move to improved and more active relationships, we do not
                        believe there will be any real change in Iran’s desire for close ties with
                        U.S. and <gloss target="#t_USN_1">USN</gloss> in Gulf. Never<pb facs="0413" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/>theless, we believe <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> should recognize changing Iranian public stance and give
                        careful consideration to proposed naval activities or use of Iranian
                        facilities which might appear to conflict with that stance. <hi rend="italic">End summary.</hi></p>
                    <p>1. As reported in Wireless File of May 5, Shah told London <hi rend="italic">Observer</hi> that he wanted “any permanent American military presence
                        removed from the Persian Gulf area, including the American naval base in
                        Bahrain.” At same time, Shah said, “he expects Iraq to agree to a similar
                        exclusion of Soviet bases in the Gulf.” This is a more explicit description
                        of <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> position on Gulf security than has
                        normally been presented—i.e., that Iran believed security should be in hands
                        of littoral states and that these states should not depend on super power
                            support.<note n="3" xml:id="d123fn3">For the Shah’s earlier views of the
                            U.S. naval presence in the Gulf, see <ref target="frus1969-76ve04#d104"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, volume
                                E–4, Documents on Iran and Iraq, 1969–1972, Documents 104</ref>,
                                <ref target="frus1969-76ve04#d159">159</ref>, and <ref target="frus1969-76ve04#d160">160</ref>.</note> Iranians regularly
                        add that as long as littoral states are unable to assure own security it is
                        inevitable that they will have to look to outsiders and as long as one super
                        power (<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>) is present in Gulf or Indian
                        Ocean, <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> wants other (U.S.) to remain in
                        order to keep a strategic balance. New element in <hi rend="italic">Observer</hi> article is specific mention of removal of American
                        presence at Bahrain. As noted above Shah hedged this position by saying Iraq
                        would have to agree to exclusion of Soviet bases in Gulf. Story has not been
                        played by local press, suggesting either that paper’s quotation of Shah is
                        not sanctioned as <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> policy position or
                        that <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> does not want to highlight the
                        issue on the eve of Shah’s visit to Washington. It is, of course, possible
                        that reporter misquoted or misinterpreted the Shah.</p>
                    <p>2. Whatever the explanation for the statement, in wake of Iran–Iraq Accord
                        and mutual Iranian-Arab efforts to strengthen ties, we believe we may
                        anticipate some similar movement in Iranian rhetoric towards Arab viewpoints
                        and vice versa. We understand that both sides are not allowing nomenclature
                        for Gulf to stand in way of expressions of cooperation—while neither,
                        however, is yielding its respective position on Persian or Arab designation.
                        Although <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> will be cautious in its
                        evolving relations with Iraqis and other Arabs, it is possible that <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> may find itself engaged in Gulf summitry
                        or negotiations for non-aggression pacts or other such diplomatic business.
                        Certainly the flow of Arab visitors to Tehran shows no sign of abating and
                            <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> seems to find process useful, not
                        the least for internatl political reasons.</p>
                    <p>3. We do not believe these changes in Iranian rhetoric or diplomatic
                        manifestations will bring any basic change over the near term in substance
                        of Iranian position on realities in Gulf, particularly <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss>’s perceived value of U.S. Navy in this
                        region. Iran is committed to devel<pb facs="0414" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/>opment of a blue water navy and is depending heavily on <gloss target="#t_USN_1">USN</gloss> for assistance in that endeavor. Shah has
                        remarked on several occasions that he personally appreciates the ready and
                        effective cooperation of the <gloss target="#t_USN_1">USN</gloss>. We doubt
                        that he would take inconsistent and unfriendly step of actively pushing for
                            <gloss target="#t_COMIDEASTFOR_1">COMIDEASTFOR</gloss> to leave Bahrain
                        and the Gulf, but he is trying to carry water on both shoulders. Therefore,
                        Shah might be reluctant now to send emissary to Bahrain to support presence
                        of <gloss target="#t_COMIDEASTFOR_1">COMIDEASTFOR</gloss> as he did last
                        year or to otherwise oppose its departure if demanded by other major
                        littoral states.</p>
                    <p>4. In these changing circumstances, we believe that we should be sensitive to
                        Shah’s public position on Gulf security, and give very careful consideration
                        to the frequency, duration and public exposure of ship visits and joint
                        exercises. Also, P–3 operations at Bandar Abbas should be examined for their
                        continuing utility and appropriateness. This more complicated matter will be
                        subject of a forthcoming message.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed corresp="#p_MJC_1">
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJC_1">Miklos</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>