<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>13. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="13"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d13">
                <head>13. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d13fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 602,
                        Country Files—Middle East, Iran, Vol. IV, September 1971–April 1973. Secret.
                        Sent for information. A stamped notation on the memorandum indicates the
                        President saw it. All brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-04-26">April 26, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Shah on Sadat’s Situation</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName> has sent through our
                    private channel a brief report on his chat with the Shah after he presented
                    credentials April 5.<note n="2" xml:id="d13fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName> sent the report in backchannel
                        message 61 to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, April 6.
                        (Ibid., Box 425, Backchannel Files, 1973, Middle East/Africa) See also <ref
                            target="#d12">Document 12</ref>.</note> In part of that conversation,
                    the Shah asked him to inform you that Egyptian Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_ZMH_1">Zayyat</persName> during a recent visit to Tehran asked
                    the Shah to urge you to arrange some kind of settlement between Egypt and
                    Israel. According to the Shah, <persName corresp="#p_ZMH_1">Zayyat</persName>
                    made these points:</p>
                <p>—Egypt will accept the Rogers Plan.<note n="3" xml:id="d13fn3">On December 9,
                        1969, Secretary of State Rogers outlined what became known as the Rogers
                        Plan for Arab-Israeli peace in an address before the 1969 Galaxy Conference
                        on Adult Education. Among its provisions, the plan called for a peace
                        agreement between the parties, the establishment of demilitarized zones, and
                        Israeli withdrawal from Arab territories occupied in the 1967 war. The text
                        of Rogers’s address is in the Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bulletin,</hi> January 5, 1970, pp. 7–11.</note> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Comment:</hi> This is not new.]</p>
                <p>—Sadat is in a precarious domestic situation; new leaders might take over the
                    Egyptian army at almost any time. [<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> When the Shah
                    pressed, <persName corresp="#p_ZMH_1">Zayyat</persName> was vague about the
                    exact source of the threat. Nevertheless the Shah was struck by <persName
                        corresp="#p_ZMH_1">Zayyat</persName>’s pleading tone.]</p>
                <p>The Shah sympathizes with Egypt’s plight, although he realizes that “if Egypt can
                    ever reassert herself, she will go right back to trying to organize the
                    leadership of the Arab world.”</p>
                <p>The Shah hinted that if we wanted his help as a go-between—he also has a
                    relationship with Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG_2">Meir</persName>—he could be
                    persuaded.</p>
                <p>The Shah said he sensed in <persName corresp="#p_ZMH_1">Zayyat</persName>’s
                    attitude almost irresistible domestic pressure in Egypt to resume some type of
                    hostilities against Israel. With a large army on active duty plus the costs of
                    maintaining it, the Egyptian leadership is feeling increasingly impelled to “do
                    something.” The Shah advised emphatically against trying to cross the Canal,
                    although he did not argue strongly against some kind of demonstration.</p>
                <pb facs="0086" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/>
                <p>Once again, it is difficult to distinguish the degree of genuine pressure on
                    Sadat from the degree of showmanship put on for our benefit. We are now getting
                    this same message through a number of side channels. At the very least, this is
                    a well orchestrated campaign. There seems little question that Sadat is
                    disappointed that he did not in his view improve his position through <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>’s visit, but he also seems to recognize
                    the disadvantages of military action.</p>
                <p>We shall keep in mind the thought of a possible role for the Shah.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
