<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-06-16T09:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-06-16T09:25:00-05:00" n="134" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                    <head>134. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d134fn1">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Memoranda of
                            Conversations, Box 12. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.
                            The meeting was held in the Secretary’s office at the White House. All
                            brackets are in the original.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1975-06-16T10:25:00-04:00" to="1975-06-16T10:50:00-04:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">June 16, 1975, 10:25–10:50 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                            Secretary of State and Assistant to the President for National Security
                            Affairs</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Alan Greenspan</persName>, Chairman,
                            Council of Economic Advisers</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Charles W. Robinson</persName>, Under
                            Secretary of State for Economic Affairs</item>
                        <item>Lt. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>,
                            Deputy Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Bilateral Oil Agreement with Iran</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0447" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: The President wanted me to
                        discuss something we have been discussing with Iran. This is for you only
                        and is highly sensitive.</p>
                    <p>When I saw the Shah in March, he complained his liftings were falling and he
                        had 500,000 barrels a day excess.<note n="2" xml:id="d134fn2"><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> apparently misspoke; he is
                            referring to the meeting with the Shah on May 16. See <ref target="#d127">Document 127</ref>.</note> I said that under specific
                        conditions we might take it off their hands. <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Chuck [Robinson]</persName> has discussed it further with them and they
                        have now gone up to 700,000 barrels a day. They would sell to us for
                        Treasury notes with a forgiveness period. The notes could be redeemed for
                        the purchase of American goods.<note n="3" xml:id="d134fn3">In a memorandum
                            to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, June 13, <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> reported the Shah’s
                            willingness to consider non-negotiable Treasury notes without interest
                            for the first year, as an extra discount off the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> official price, but also his
                            insistence that this be kept confidential by handling it in a side
                            letter. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>, 59,
                            Records of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>,
                            1973–1977, Lot 91D414, Box 15) A memorandum of a longer discussion of
                            the bilateral oil deal among <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName>, June 14, is in the
                            Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, Kissinger Papers, Box CL–152,
                            Iran, Chronological File, 1 June–31 July 1975.</note></p>
                    <p>I am interested in this idea because, number one, it breaks the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> front because it shifts the surplus.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: It would have to be at
                        Saudi expense, and they wouldn’t like it. How long would it be for?</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It’s up to us. Second, it
                        would make it harder to raise the prices. Third, it’s insurance against
                        another embargo. Fourth, it puts pressure on the suppliers.</p>
                    <p>There are two possible schemes. The first one is that we pay the market price
                        for oil. The other is to sell at current prices plus an adjustment tied to
                        the wholesale price index.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: That breaks the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> price structure.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If they give us a
                        forgiveness feature, one year gives us $1 dollar discount.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: If we could keep Iran at
                        full production it puts severe pressure on the Saudis. We would want to
                        insure that Iran would not cut back elsewhere.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: They could but that
                        obviously is not their scheme. They want to keep their revenue up.</p>
                    <p>The basic scheme is a barter. If they contract way out for oil, they need the
                        assurance that the price will go up in line with other goods they would buy.
                        By either scheme—the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> price, or the
                        current price plus the wholesale price index (so long as it didn’t go above
                            <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss>). We would give them Treasury
                        notes without interest for the first year and that are non-negotiable for
                        the first year. So for the first year we would have $2 billion in our
                        hands.</p>
                    <pb facs="0448" n="405" xml:id="pg_405"/>
                    <p>This will take imagination and a change in how we operate.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: So in effect you have $2
                        billion in escrow. So if they broke the deal or entered an embargo, we have
                        the $2 billion.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: We get a discount. We will
                        have to establish a specific arrangement, which can go far to break <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss>.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: When this gets out . . .
                        the only real issue is price. It would be crucial that the price not
                        escalate beyond the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> price.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: I think I got that, but I
                        haven’t nailed that down yet.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: It seems obvious that if
                        you look at 1978 at these prices, the Saudis are the only ones who will not
                        be a net borrower. The others are committing funds at such a rate. The
                        700,000 barrels by itself won’t do it. But as a symbol . . . The Saudi
                        reaction will be important.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Will the companies give us
                        trouble because the Saudis will be upset?</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: The idea properly packaged
                        seems very attractive. Let me think about it. An essential ingredient is not
                        to let the price go above the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> price.
                        I will think on the negative elements, but I am intrigued.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: There are two alternatives:
                        a government purchase to be auctioned off, or we could buy it for the Navy
                        reserve and so on.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: We can buy it for the
                        stockpile. We are talking about a $1 billion stockpile, but we don’t have
                        the Salt Dome capacity. Maybe you can solve the company problem by having
                        them take the oil.</p>
                    <p>The notes would have to be non-negotiable. Have you looked at the different
                        interest rates?</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: It is about $1 a barrel at
                        the current interest rates. I am thinking of a five-year maturity with no
                        interest if they don’t use it for equipment.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Another option is to lower
                        the interest rate and have no forgiveness. How will it look to our IEA
                        partners? It really helps them.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: But we must be careful how
                        we do it.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: It will have a devastating
                        impact on <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss>. So you want the maximum
                        apparent price concession.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: Iran insists that the
                        non-negotiable aspect be covered by a side letter, as well as the price not
                        going above <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss>.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I know we would like the
                        greatest apparent price differential . . . the side letters will look . . .
                        the Saudis will be very upset.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: If you then have the same
                        deal with the Saudis, I would not favor it. Because then <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> becomes Saudi.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That is a separate issue.
                        Let the Saudis worry about that.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>: It would be politically
                        difficult to say we do it with Iran but won’t for the Saudis.</p>
                    <pb facs="0449" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>: Let me think it through.
                        The critical thing is what happens in 1980, with Iran and with or without
                        the Saudis. We may need a total strategy before we move.<note n="4" xml:id="d134fn4"><persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName> sent
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> a “think piece” by
                                <persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName> on the Iranian oil
                            deal in backchannel message <gloss target="#t_Tohak_1">Tohak</gloss> 10,
                            June 18. (Ibid.) In a discussion with <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> on June 23, <persName corresp="#p_ZF_1">Zarb</persName> warned that the deal could lead to a government
                            purchasing authority, or even a nationalized oil industry. <persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName> added that the Saudis had the
                            production flexibility to preserve the cartel. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> replied that the plan would
                            not break <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> decisively; it was
                            “just a nibble” to gain leverage with the oil producers. Regardless,
                                <persName corresp="#p_ZF_1">Zarb</persName> believed that they
                            should proceed with the deal, and <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> added that, if they did so, the price that the
                            United States paid to Iran could not “ever exceed the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> price.” As <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> observed later, both the
                            administration and the Shah were reluctant to go through Congress.
                            (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records of
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, 1973–1977,
                            Lot 91D414, Box 15)</note></p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I think we should pick up
                        what we can and develop a total strategy after Iran is signed up.<note n="5" xml:id="d134fn5">Telegram 148283 to Tehran, June 24, transmitted a
                            message from <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> to the
                            Shah asking him to receive <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> on June 30 to discuss the deal further. (Ibid.,
                            Central Foreign Policy Files, P840178–1979) On July 5, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> explained the details of the
                            5-year deal to <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>, noting:
                                “<persName corresp="#p_ZF_1">Zarb</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName> are afraid that if <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> buys the oil, it would lead to a
                            government purchasing agency. <persName corresp="#p_GA_2">Greenspan</persName> is worried about whether you should give the
                            Saudis the same deal.” He added: “I would give them the same deal for
                            the same amount but ask for a better deal if they want more. I would
                            wait to see if the Saudis came to us. This would end the charges of
                            cuddling the Shah and the money would be spent only in the United
                            States.” (Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Memoranda of
                            Conversations, Box 12)</note></p>
                    <p>[The meeting ended]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>