<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-01-03T01:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-01-03T01:55:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                    <head>201. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d201fn1">Source: Department of State, INR/IL
                            Historical Files, Roger Channel, TS, Tehran I, 1963–1978. Secret;
                            Immediate; Roger Channel; Special Handling.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-01-03T06:55:00+00:00">January 3,
                                1977, 0655Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>1. Eyes Only for Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>. Subj: <gloss target="#t_SAVAK_1">SAVAK</gloss>
                        Activities. Ref: (A) State 313328, (B) State 314119.<note n="2" xml:id="d201fn2">Telegram 313328 is <ref target="#d199">Document
                                199</ref>. In telegram 314119 to Tehran, December 31, 1976, the
                            Department altered the wording of telegram 313328. The first sentence of
                            paragraph 2 was changed to read: “Although these <gloss target="#t_FBI_1">FBI</gloss> reports are ambiguous, the Secretary
                            believed that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>
                            should again be alerted to <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>’s
                            genuine concern over operations of foreign security/intelligence
                            organizations in the United States.” The third sentence of paragraph 5
                            was amended: “In view of the particularly close and mutually beneficial
                            relationship between our two countries we want to avoid problems on such
                            matters and believe that a continuing dialogue will be helpful.”
                            (Department of State, INR/IL Historical Files, Roger Channel, TS, Tehran
                            I, 1963–1978)</note></p>
                    <p>1. Conveyed exact language of para 5 <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> (A) as amended by para 1(B) <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> (B) to Minister of Court <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> evening December 31. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> expressed appreciation for clarification of what
                        transpired between you and <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>,
                        particularly noting with relief that <gloss target="#t_PNG_1">PNG</gloss>
                        action had not been raised or considered by US which was contrary to what
                            <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName> had reported. Also filled
                            <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> in on general background as
                        described <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> (A) leading up to your
                        meeting with <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> was not at all pleased to hear that
                        CBS “60 Minutes” planned a program on <gloss target="#t_SAVAK_1">SAVAK</gloss>’s actions in the US. He said this was “very bad” but then
                        commented that “I suppose there is nothing you (<gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>) can do about it.” He said that he had been opposed to the
                        last Mike Wallace interview with the Shah but that <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName> had persuaded the Shah that it was a
                        good idea after having talked with Wallace for several hours before making
                        his recommendation.<note n="3" xml:id="d201fn3">See <ref target="#d196fn3">footnote 3, Document 196</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>2. Evening of January 2 <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> summoned
                        me to his residence to tell me that he had related our December 31
                        conversation to the Shah. He said that the Shah was satisfied with our
                        explanation but that the Shah had then gone on to say that if this matter
                        became an issue he would not be able to overlook the presence of “70 of your
                        people who are carrying out activities contrary to Iranian law.” As a matter
                        of fact, <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> added, “We would not be
                        able to overlook the presence of others whom we do not know about
                        officially.” He asked that I make clear the seriousness with which the Shah
                        regards this matter in my report to Washington.</p>
                    <p>3. Leave to your judgment the question of the accuracy of <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>’s reporting (<persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName> said he must have misunderstood) but
                        suggest you <pb facs="0638" n="595" xml:id="pg_595"/> may wish to consider
                        dual approach in Washington and here on subjects of such sensitivity in the
                        future. <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName> seems to have gotten
                        this one wrong as he has other matters in the past and perhaps unnecessarily
                        exercised our friends here.</p>
                    <p>4. Since this matter could conceivably be raised by the <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> with the Station Chief here, I felt it
                        wise to fill him in on the exchanges I have had with <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Alam</persName>, asking that he keep it to himself for
                        the time being. You may wish to consider letting his people know in
                        Washington.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed corresp="#p_MJC_1">
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJC_1">Miklos</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>