<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-06-05T18:27:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-06-05T18:27:00-05:00" n="252" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                    <head>252. Telegram From the Mission at the United Nations to the Department of
                            State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d252fn1">Source: Library of
                            Congress, Manuscript Division, Kissinger Papers, Box CL–154, Iraq, 10
                            March 1974–11 January 1977. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>; Cherokee.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-06-05T23:27:00+00:00">June 5, 1974,
                                2327Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>2065. Subj: Iraqi-US Relations. For the Secretary From <gloss target="#t_Amb_1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_SJA_1">Scali</persName>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> Iraqi <gloss target="#t_Amb_1">Amb</gloss>
                        El-Shibib, replying to your confidential comments to him at <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> luncheon Apr 15,<note n="2" xml:id="d252fn2">No record of the luncheon has been found.</note> said he authorized
                        assure you that Iraq (1) wants continue secret high-level dialogue; (2) will
                        reciprocate any positive <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> action; (3)
                        desires increased pragmatic businesslike economic relations with US firms
                        and (4) will not seek to block or conspire against Egyptian-Syrian peace
                        moves even despite adverse Iraqi propaganda. <hi rend="italic">End
                            summary.</hi></p>
                    <p>1. El-Shibib met with me alone at <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>
                        Mission to relay what he termed “not startling info but our sincere
                        readiness to begin serious dialogue” in answer to your initiative April 15
                        when you sat beside him at SYG luncheon. El-Shibib said his govt
                        particularly interested in and appreciative of your assurance that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> not interested in encouraging separatist
                        movement in Iraq. This is viewed by his govt as a very positive and helpful
                        attitude on part of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. However, he said
                            <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> cld reinforce this positive
                        attitude by encouraging Iran, which Iraq believes had exceedingly close ties
                        with <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, to follow up easing of border
                        difficulties by serious, meaningful negotiations for permanent settlement of
                        problem. Unless <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> puts some pressure on
                        Iran, Tehran govt will feel it has leeway to create continuing problems even
                        though Iraq is encouraged by your comment that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> is not encouraging Barzani rebel movement.</p>
                    <p>2. In answer to your question about Iraqi relations with <gloss target="#t_Sov_1">Sov</gloss> Govt, Iraqi Govt wants you to know it is
                        not client of anyone and has not closed its doors to any state. El-Shibib
                        noted that Iraq has restored rela<pb facs="0741" n="698" xml:id="pg_698"/>tions with all <gloss target="#t_WE_1">WE</gloss> govts, including <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and West Germany, and that its policy is to
                        cooperate economically with all nations. El-Shibib said American companies
                        are beginning to do “good business with Iraq.” Specifically, he noted that
                        an American firm had been given the biggest contract to develop deep-water
                        port in south Iraq and that three American companies are among seven foreign
                        firms invited to submit bids for gas liquifying project. Economically, no
                        doors are closed to the US. Iraq is deeply interested in practical,
                        pragmatic cooperation with <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and hopes to
                        be able to increase such economic relations.</p>
                    <p>3. El-Shibib said his govt recognizes that important political differences
                        will continue with <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> in <gloss target="#t_ME_1">ME</gloss> area with little prospect that either side
                        can convince the other of justice of its case in near future. But perhaps by
                        establishing a dialogue, <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and Iraq can
                        limit their differences. Iraq is very willing to do this.</p>
                    <p>4. Whenever there is a positive sign of action from <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, he said, it will be reciprocated by the Iraqi side just as
                        positively. He cautioned, however, against expecting dramatic developments
                        quickly because any sudden changes would be counter-productive in too short
                        a period of time. El-Shibib said negative Iraqi radio and press reaction to
                        Syrian-Israeli disengagement agreement should not be looked on as overly
                        important. Iraq must adopt such an ideological position in view of its
                        traditional attitude but, he said, Iraq will not overthrow or seek to
                        conspire against governments seeking to cooperate with <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. The Iraqi Govt’s attitude should not be
                        viewed as being as negative as its propaganda. Further, whatever “negative”
                        positions Iraq advances diplomatically shld not be overblown in the <gloss target="#t_ME_1">ME</gloss> context. El-Shibib mentioned Iraqi-Iranian
                        relations three times. His main point was that Tehran cld be pressed by the
                            <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> to be far more reasonable. If
                        Iran’s attitude became more cooperative as a follow-up to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_SC_1">SC</gloss> border compromise, Iraq wld note this as
                        a positive result. In this connection, he acknowledged that US had already
                        played a helpful role in negotiating a compromise via <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_SC_1">SC</gloss> to ease border tensions.<note n="3" xml:id="d252fn3">In <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Security Council
                            Resolution 348, adopted unanimously on May 28, Iran and Iraq agreed to
                            withdraw their armed forces from the border and resume negotiations for
                            a peaceful settlement of all bilateral issues. See <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of the United Nations, 1974,</hi> pp. 252–256.</note></p>
                    <p>5. The time appears at hand, El-Shibib said, for Iraq and Iran to move
                        farther and arrive at an equitable settlement of longstanding differences.
                        El-Shibib said he wld not forget your comment about how US and Mexico’s
                        border was a peaceful one because it had been agreed to with the objective
                        of making it fair for both sides.</p>
                    <p>6. In answer to his comments, I noted <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                        had already played leading role in encouraging Iran to compromise its
                        differences with <pb facs="0742" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/> Iraq. Iraqi Govt
                        shld not expect Iran to listen obediently every time <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> advised particular course because, as cld
                        be seen from recent Iranian economic moves, Iran frequently takes positions
                        it believes in its own national interests regardless of views of friends.
                        However, I said that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> believed it to be
                        in best interest of region for Iraq–Iran Govts to follow up <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> compromise with active negots to settle
                        outstanding issues. Actions as well as words of Iraqi Govt will be watched
                        in weeks ahead to form our own judgment about whether actual Iraqi policy
                        less negative than propaganda which at times of incendiary nature. <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> fully recognizes, I said, that propaganda
                        level is no reliable index to what true govt position is in <gloss target="#t_ME_1">ME</gloss> particularly.</p>
                    <p>7. Accordingly, I told him I would relay his views to you, with confident
                        belief you would wish to continue highest-level dialogue. I cautioned
                        against any leaks to any govt or media of discussions saying <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> would regard this as sign Iraq not really
                        interested. On US side, I said you would wish to confine those knowing of
                        dialogue only to President and me to guarantee maximum candor, flexibility
                        and results satisfactory to both sides.</p>
                    <p>8. El-Shibib said he was sure his govt wanted to keep talks confined to Prime
                        Min, Fon Min, and him only. He said he wld be returning to Baghdad Monday or
                            Tuesday<note n="4" xml:id="d252fn4">June 10 or 11.</note> and would be
                        happy to relay any additional message and would be prepared to wait few days
                        if necessary to hear from you.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed corresp="#p_SJA_1">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJA_1">Scali</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>