<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>276. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Iran (Helms) to the
                    President’s Deputy Assistant for National Security Affairs () to the President’s
                    Deputy Assistant for National Security Affairs (Scowcroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-03-08T10:54:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-03-08T10:54:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries">OPEC</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-03-08T10:54:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-03-08T10:54:00-05:00" n="276"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                <head>276. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Iran (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>) to the President’s Deputy Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1"
                        >Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d276fn1">Source:
                        Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Backchannel Messages, Box 4,
                        Mideast/Africa, Incoming 3/75. Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-03-08T15:54:00+00:00">March 8, 1975, 1554Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>96. Reference: Tehran 095 081015Z.<note n="2" xml:id="d276fn2">
                        <ref target="#d275">Document 275</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Please pass the following message to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> from me as a supplement to referent telegram: <hi
                        rend="italic">Begin text:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At audience this afternoon Shah asked that I send you this message from him. It
                    is put in quotation marks as a reasonable approximation of what he said: “When I
                    returned home after meeting with you in Zurich,<note n="3" xml:id="d276fn3">See
                            <ref target="#d103">Document 103</ref>.</note> I received a message from
                    General Barzani saying that it was becoming impossible to carry on fighting
                    under existing circumstances, that his people would be massacred unless
                    something could be done. He declared that the Kurdish forces must have more
                    sophisticated weapons and more Iranian military support or that the Kurds be
                    permitted to declare their independence like Cyprus did. I did not see how we
                    could increase our military commitment without going to open war with the
                    Iraqis. Then on March 2 I saw <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Ashraf
                        Marwan</persName> (this was the day after I received Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>) who had just come from Baghdad. He
                    repeated message I had received through others, i.e. that <persName
                        corresp="#p_HST_1">Saddam Hussein</persName> was ready to pull Iraq out of
                    Soviet orbit if Iran would take away the [garble—military struggle?] which was
                    forcing them into the arms of the Soviets. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2"
                        >Marwan</persName> expressed the view that he was almost certain that Saddam
                    would pull away from Soviets as promised. In Algiers Boumedienne pushed hard and
                    showed great interest in bringing me together with Saddam. The first meeting was
                    unproductive. Saddam mouthed the same things the Iraqis have been saying for ten
                    years, and I so told Boumedienne. At the second meeting there was a big change.
                    The main results have been published. On the Kurds I got two promises from
                    Saddam; one, that Barzani and his people would have one week to decide whether
                    they wanted to stay in Iraq or come to Iran where they will have a haven, a
                    decent life, and be able to withdraw without bloodshed.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d276fn4">According to backchannel message 97 to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, March 9, <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName> noted that Barzani was in Tehran and
                        had been informed of Saddam’s promise, but had yet to notify the Shah of his
                        decision. (Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Backchannel Messages,
                        Box 4, Mideast/Africa, Incoming 3/75)</note> They will be given till the end
                    of the month for their withdrawal. (My earlier message said ‘two weeks’ and the
                        <pb facs="0793" n="750" xml:id="pg_750"/> Shah may mean the end of the
                    Iranian month on March 20.) The second promise was that the security services of
                    the two countries would work together, briefing each other on which Kurds were
                    good and which were bad (read Communist). This will, I hope, prevent the
                    establishment of Communist Kurds in Barzani’s territory. All this, mind you, was
                    agreed in front of Boumedienne and he approved it all. How it will work out, I
                    obviously do not know. But I felt that I had to take a chance since otherwise
                    the Kurdish cause would be hopeless in the relatively near future and I might be
                    accused of having destroyed a chance for getting the Iraqis out of the Soviet
                    orbit. In any event Boumedienne was jubilant and all the participants at the
                        <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> conference seemed equally
                    pleased.”</p>
                <p>The Shah mentioned that the Iraqis have already ordered troops into action
                    against the Kurds since these agreements were made. He said he had brought this
                    to the attention of Boumedienne as a violation of the understandings. He had had
                    no word as to what effect his remonstrance had had on the Iraqis. (Other matters
                    covered in the audience will be filed in regular State Department channels
                        Sunday.)<note n="5" xml:id="d276fn5">Telegrams 2209, 2216, and 2237 from
                        Tehran, March 9. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy Files, D750082–1028, D750082–1004, and
                        D750082–1131)</note> Warm regards.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
