<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>301. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-11-03T00:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-11-03T00:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-11-03T00:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-11-03T00:20:00-05:00" n="301"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                <head>301. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d301fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                        P840084–0158. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>;
                        Cherokee.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-11-03T05:20:00+00:00">November 3, 1975,
                        0520Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>10655. For the Secretary from the Ambassador. Subj: Congressional Testimony on
                    Kurds. Ref: Tehran 10459.<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">In 1975, the House of
                        Representatives established the House Select Committee on Intelligence,
                        known as the Pike Committee, to investigate possible abuses by the
                        Intelligence Community. The investigation covered <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                            >CIA</gloss> covert operations, including that in support of the Kurds,
                        and high-level officials, notably <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1"
                            >Helms</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>,
                        testified before it. In telegram 10459 from Tehran, October 28, <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName> urged <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> to review the record of his testimony before the
                        Pike Committee to prepare for the Secretary’s own appearance. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName> also noted that the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> documentation held by the Committee was
                        voluminous and inquired as to which communications channels remained secure
                        if backchannel communications had been revealed. (Ibid.,
                        P840084–0133)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. At audience for Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fulbright</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d301fn3">Former Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">J.
                            William Fulbright</persName> visited Tehran as a representative of the
                        Institute of International Education November 1–4.</note> which was held
                    late afternoon November 2 immediately after Shah’s arrival from Ankara, took
                    occasion to mention that CBS News had carried story on November 1 which inter
                    alia mentioned <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operation to support Iraqi
                    Kurds with “tens of millions of dollars worth of Soviet arms.”<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d301fn4">Telegram 260094 to Tehran, November 3, advised the Embassy
                        that the story of U.S. assistance to the Kurds had also appeared on the
                        front page of <hi rend="italic">The Washington Post.</hi> In addition, the
                            <hi rend="italic">Christian Science Monitor</hi> had reported that
                        Barzani was in the United States for medical treatment as a guest of the
                            <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName> had visited him in the hospital. The
                        telegram stated that there would be no official comment on the allegations.
                        (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                        Policy Files, D750381–0723)</note> Shah reacted with a smile rather than a
                    frown and commented, “Yes, that story was the first thing my government
                    mentioned to me when I alighted at the airport a few minutes ago.” He did not
                    pursue the matter and neither did I, but I have no doubt I will hear more about
                    it when there is no third party present. Leaks such as this Schorr story right
                    out of the Pike Committee only serve to persuade the Shah that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> is incapable of keeping confidences or
                    secrets.</p>
                <p>2. Recognize how painfully aware you are of damage these leaks do,<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d301fn5">Telegram 1115 from Baghdad, November 4, noted that the
                        Baghdad dailies had reported the story but blamed <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> and downplayed the Iranian role,
                        apparently indicating that the government did not wish the story to disturb
                        U.S.-Iraqi relations or Iraqi-Iranian détente. (Ibid., D750382–0334)</note>
                    but felt I should mention foregoing for the record and whatever ammunition it
                    may give you in supporting your own position to keep Department cables away from
                    Congressional committees. Incidentally, Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1"
                        >Fulbright</persName> threw up his hands when I asked what could be done <pb
                        facs="0854" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/> to stop the hemorrhaging. He indicated
                    that he knew of nothing and opined that it would simply have to run its course,
                    much as he disapproved of what Congress was doing.</p>
                <p>3. Set forth below is what [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] what alerted me to the leak. It is certainly what Pike
                    Committee believes or at least what members told me they believe when I appeared
                    before them on October 23. <hi rend="italic">Begin text.</hi> Daniel Schorr of
                    CBS News on 6:30 broadcast 1 November stated that the Pike Committee had
                    uncovered a <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operation which delivered “tens
                    of millions of dollars worth of Soviet and Chinese Communist arms” to the Iraqi
                    Kurds. Schorr said that the operation was conceived during the <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> visit to Tehran in June 1972. Apparently
                    the Shah requested that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> provide this
                    material and <persName corresp="#p_CJB_1">John Connally</persName> was sent to
                    Tehran later that year in July to inform the Shah of the President’s
                        approval.<note n="6" xml:id="d301fn6">See <ref target="frus1969-76ve04#d209">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, volume E–4,
                            Documents on Iran and Iraq, 1969–1972, Documents 209</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1969-76ve04#d211">211</ref>.</note> Schorr said that <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> opposed the operation. Aid to the Kurds ceased
                    after the Iran-Iraqi agreement of 6 March 1975. The Pike Committee stated that
                    this action was illegal because the authorization came directly from the
                    President and not via the National Security Council. On 1 November 75 Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> refused to make details of
                    the operation public. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> officially denied
                    comment, according to Schorr, who said however unofficial <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> sources claim the President had the right to
                    run such an operation directly. <hi rend="italic">End of text.</hi>
                    <note n="7" xml:id="d301fn7">In <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> columns,
                        February 5 and 12, 1976, William Safire condemned the President for ending
                        the Kurdish operation and betraying the Kurds, based on further leaks from
                        the Pike Committee report.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_HRM_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
