<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-10-30T07:43:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-10-30T07:43:00-05:00" n="41" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                    <head>41. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Iran (<persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>) to the President’s Deputy Assistant
                        for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d41fn1">Source:
                            National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 425, Backchannel Files,
                            1973, Middle East/Africa. Secret; Sensitive; Immediate.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-10-30T12:43:00+00:00">October 30,
                                1973, 1243Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>110. Refs: A. Jidda <gloss target="#t_Embtel_1">Embtel</gloss> 4745, B. Jidda
                            <gloss target="#t_Embtel_1">Embtel</gloss> 4708.<note n="2" xml:id="d41fn2">Telegram 4745 from Jidda, October 29, transmitted Saudi
                            Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SSO_1">Saqqaf</persName>’s
                            message that good relations with the United States could not be restored
                            until a just solution to the Middle East conflict was reached, and that
                            his government’s resolution to use oil as a political instrument was
                            firm. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                            Foreign Policy Files, P750018–0141) Telegram 4708 from Jidda, October
                            25, transmitted Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJE_1">Akins</persName>’s view that Saudi oil pressure would not cease until
                            an acceptable settlement, including the disposition of Jerusalem,
                            emerged. (Ibid., P750018–0154)</note></p>
                    <p>1. What follows is an effort to wrap up for Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> before he begins his swing
                        through this area<note n="3" xml:id="d41fn3">Telegram 212612 to Tehran,
                            October 27, sent <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s
                            message to the Shah advising him of his plan to visit Tehran on November
                            9 for consultations on settling the Arab-Israeli dispute. (Ibid., Nixon
                            Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box
                            603, Country Files—Middle East, Iran, Vol. V, May–December 1973) From
                            November 5 to 9, the Secretary also visited Morocco, Egypt, Jordan,
                            Saudi Arabia, and Pakistan.</note> my views on the current state of mind
                        hereabouts. There is nothing novel in what I have to say, but I thought the
                        effort might be marginally useful to him.</p>
                    <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_SSO_1">Saqqaf</persName>’s remarks to Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_AJE_1">Akins</persName> reported <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> (A) and Jidda Country Team message
                            (<gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> (B)) indicate Saudi
                        Government is disposed to maintain solidarity with other Arab governments
                        and keep pressure on the United States to influence Israel to accept the
                        Arab interpretation of <gloss target="#t_SC_1">SC</gloss> Resolution
                        242.</p>
                    <p>3. From our soundings in the Gulf, from among local Arab diplomats, senior
                        Iranian officials who advise the Shah, and from remarks made on various
                        occasions since last May by the Shah himself, we believe that <persName corresp="#p_SSO_1">Saqqaf</persName>’s warning and the Jidda Country
                        Team assessment should be taken seriously indeed.</p>
                    <p>4. We are in an unprecedented situation in which Saudi Arabia took the lead
                        in underwriting economically the military initiatives of Egypt and Syria and
                        in securing the financial and political participation of other conservative
                        states in the united action. The ultimate failure of the Arab military
                        effort has made even more dramatic and important the potential power of the
                        Arab economic effort and in this Saudi Arabia is the key to success or
                        failure. Faysal surely must enjoy the increased power and prestige of his
                        new position. He is also deeply attached to the idea of a special status for
                        Jerusalem, as Jidda has pointed out.</p>
                    <pb facs="0194" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/>
                    <p>5. It has been traditional on the basis of past experience to say that
                        because of competing interests, the Arabs would not stand together to use
                        the oil weapon effectively against the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                        and its allies. Now, however, we have come into a new situation where old
                        pressures for oil revenue no longer apply. Saudi Arabia and Kuwait have
                        sufficient financial reserves to wait us out. And Europe and Japan have
                        sufficient self-interest to deal directly with the producers, cutting out
                        the American companies as middlemen, if this seems to them necessary to
                        insure a steady flow of oil to their countries.</p>
                    <p>6. Saudi Arabia so far has applied only the mildest of measures to put
                        pressure on the United States: the 10 per cent cut-back in production and an
                        embargo on exports to the USA.<note n="4" xml:id="d41fn4">On October 17, the
                            Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries warned of a cut-back
                            in oil production or a total embargo, and on October 19, Saudi Arabia
                            announced it would impose an oil embargo on the United States in
                            retaliation for aid to Israel. Other Gulf oil producers soon followed
                            the Saudi lead. Documentation on the U.S. and Western response to the
                            embargo is in <ref target="frus1969-76v36"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, volume XXXVI, Energy Crisis,
                                1969–1974</ref>.</note> She has also, we suppose, applied a second
                        informal pressure by not moving forward on new contracts with American
                        firms. We do not know to what extent the SAG may have begun transfers of
                        dollar reserves and investments. But I do believe we should be constantly
                        aware of the possibility that other Saudi pressure options will be taken if
                        we do not appear to be using our influence to secure adherence to <gloss target="#t_SC_1">SC</gloss> 242. These options would be further cut-back
                        in oil production; denial of overflight rights; closing of the U.S. Military
                        Training Mission; nationalization of Aramco; withdrawal of Saudi funds from
                        U.S. accounts and U.S. investments; a break in diplomatic relations; and
                        expulsion of Americans from the country. If these measures were taken in
                        consort with Kuwait, Qatar and Abu Dhabi, the impact upon our interests
                        would be serious indeed.</p>
                    <p>7. Faysal used to be inhibited from considering such radical measures because
                        the loss of his American alliance would have made him vulnerable to external
                        aggression from Egypt or Iraq and vulnerable to internal subversion by
                        nationalist and “progressive” forces. Today his prestige is so improved, he
                        probably would feel safe in adopting such measures against us. Each measure
                        would actually tend to increase his popularity and strengthen his
                        regime.</p>
                    <p>8. Long before the present crisis, as the Secretary will remember, the Shah
                        in conversations in Washington and with me here made it clear that he
                        thought the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> should adopt policies which
                        would restore its appearance of balance between the Arabs and Israel. His
                        own government has repeatedly stated its support of <gloss target="#t_SC_1">SC</gloss> 242, with the interpretation that evacuation of occupied
                        territories means just about all territories.</p>
                    <pb facs="0195" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/>
                    <p>9. Since the opening of hostilities, Iran has reaffirmed that position. In
                        response to popular sentiment, Iran has flown medical supplies to the Arabs,
                        has made preparations to accept Arab wounded for treatment, has loaned
                        C–130’s to Saudi Arabia and has authorized a moderate tilt by Iranian media
                        in favor of the Arabs. This has occurred despite the fact that the Shah and
                        the Iranian establishment have had, and continue secretly to have, very
                        close cooperative relations with Israel.<note n="5" xml:id="d41fn5">According to a November 2 paper prepared in <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> that <persName corresp="#p_CRS_1">Cline</persName> sent
                            to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> in advance of his
                            trip, the Shah “regards Israel as a profitable channel for Iranian oil
                            and as an ally against Arab radicalism.” Acknowledging the Shah’s
                            actions on behalf of the Arab war effort, the paper noted that the Shah
                            “simultaneously suppressed domestic expressions of support for the Arab
                            cause and continued to ship oil to Israel (around the Cape.)” (National
                            Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73,
                            ORG 7 S)</note> The reason is that the Shah and his advisors have come
                        to believe that the balance of forces has changed sufficiently that overt
                        identification with Israel would not be politically viable, even though they
                        are pleased that the Arabs were not militarily victorious.</p>
                    <p>10. From the perspective of Tehran it looks to us as if the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and Israel must this time hammer out a
                        solution which a conservative Arab leader like Faysal and a moderate
                        nationalist like Sadat can and will accept. You have heard this before, I
                        know. This time, however, sober Americans feel that the Arab states are in a
                        position where they can and will use the oft-threatened oil weapon.<note n="6" xml:id="d41fn6">In telegram 7285 from Tehran, October 15, the
                            Embassy forwarded at the Shah’s instruction an interview he had given to
                            an Egyptian newspaper that “was specifically designed to eradicate among
                            Arab leaders the conception that the use of oil as a weapon would have
                            any effect upon the United States in the short term.” (Ibid., Central
                            Foreign Policy Files, [no film number])</note></p>
                    <p>11. Warm regards.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>