<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-27T18:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-12-26T05:00:00-05:00" n="134" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                        <head>134. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>At the 416th meeting of the National Security Council on August 6,
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> discussed
                            developments in Afghanistan during his survey of significant world
                            developments affecting U.S. security: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Noting that Afghanistan was included in the South Asia paper,
                                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> said the
                                    situation in this country was very difficult from the point of
                                    view of preventing Soviet penetration and loss of Afghan
                                    independence. He displayed a map showing Soviet and U.S.
                                    projects in Afghanistan, the inaccessibility of the country and
                                    the road being built by the Soviets toward the Pakistan border.
                                    Soviet assistance to Afghanistan in relation to the population,
                                    size and resources of the country is quite large. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> was providing Afghanistan
                                    with $25 million worth of arms, including jet aircraft and light
                                    and heavy weapons. In addition Soviet Military Advisers are, for
                                    the first time, working in the Afghanistan Defense Ministry
                                    disguised as instructors. The Soviets have also provided $260
                                    million in economic aid to Afghanistan, including a $100 million
                                    loan. Five hundred Soviet technicians are supervising
                                    construction of a new road and the Soviets are also helping to
                                    build airports. Afghanistan has insisted that Soviet assistance
                                    should be in the form of grants rather than loans. The Soviets
                                    have assented, contrary to their usual practice of providing
                                    loans instead of grants.</p>
                                <p>“Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said the
                                    Soviet willingness to consent to grants rather than loans
                                    indicated the flexibility of the Soviet foreign economic aid
                                    campaign. Moreover, in an economic agreement recently concluded
                                    with Afghanistan, the Soviets agreed to accept payment in Afghan
                                    currency at a very high rate of exchange for transit charges
                                    incurred through the shipment of Afghan goods across the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Afghanistan, however, is
                                    keeping the door to the West open a little, thereby leaving the
                                    U.S. an opportunity to exploit the Afghan interest in education.
                                    The U.S. should also attempt to allay the tensions between
                                    Afghanistan and Pakistan resulting from the Pushtoonistan issue.
                                    However, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>
                                    felt that the U.S. should not try to match Soviet assistance to
                                    Afghanistan dollar for dollar.” (Memorandum of discussion by
                                    Marion W. Boggs; Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p></quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The South Asia paper in question, which was discussed later at this
                            meeting, is <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5909, “U.S. Policy
                            Toward South Asia”; see <ref target="#d4">Document 4</ref>. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5909 is printed as <ref target="#d6">Document 6</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>