<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                        <head>188. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d188fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                                Files. Secret. According to a note on the cover sheet, the following
                                intelligence organizations participated in the preparation of this
                                estimate: the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and the
                                intelligence organizations of the Departments of State, Army, Navy,
                                Air Force, and The Joint Staff. All members of the U.S. Intelligence
                                Board concurred with the estimate on December 9, with the exception
                                of the representatives of the Atomic Energy Commission and the
                                Federal Bureau of Investigation. Those representatives abstained
                                since the subject being considered was outside their
                                jurisdiction.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 54–2–58</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-12-09"><hi rend="italic">December 9,
                                    1958.</hi></date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">THE OUTLOOK FOR POLITICAL STABILITY IN CEYLON<note n="2" xml:id="d188fn2">Supplements <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                                54–58, “The Outlook for Ceylon,” dated 18 March 1958. [Footnote in
                                the source text. <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 54–58 is
                                printed as <ref target="#d182">Document 182</ref>.]</note></p>
                        <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                        <p>To estimate the outlook for political stability in Ceylon over the next
                            few years.</p>
                        <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Internal stability in Ceylon has deteriorated sharply under the
                                present regime due to mounting political and economic problems and
                                the weak leadership of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> and his shaky socialist-neutralist
                                coalition government. The outlook over the next few years is for
                                little if any political or economic improvement, more strikes, and
                                probably further rioting between the majority Sinhalese and minority
                                Tamil communities. (Paras. 4–8)</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Despite general lack of confidence in <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>’s leadership, there is no ready
                                alternative to him within the present Parliament. However, we
                                believe that the Bandaranike government will probably become
                                increasingly vulnerable and that there is an even chance it will be
                                voted out of office by Parliament before the end of its <pb facs="0426" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/> full term in 1961.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> might,
                                moreover, be forced out either by the Governor General acting in an
                                emergency situation or by a coup staged by military, police, and
                                conservative elements.<note n="3" xml:id="d188fn3">On November 24,
                                    the Embassy in Ceylon reported rumors of a plot to establish a
                                    dictatorial government in Ceylon and liquidate leftists,
                                    particularly <persName>Philip Gunawardena</persName>. The coup
                                    allegedly had been planned for November 20. (Telegram 436 from
                                    Colombo, November 24; Department of State, Central Files,
                                    746E.00/11–2458) Rumors and parliamentary charges about this
                                    matter continued into December; documentation is <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 746E.00.</note> We believe that
                                there will be no significant change in foreign policy under any
                                likely successor government. (Paras. 9–11, 14)</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Communist influence in Ceylon will probably continue to increase
                                despite the strong rivalry which exists between the three communist
                                groups. We do not believe, however, that these communist groups,
                                separately or together, will be able within the next few years to
                                seize control of the government by extra-legal means—chiefly because
                                of their small size and the almost certain opposition of the
                                Governor General and the security forces to such a move. Nor do we
                                believe it likely that any grouping of communists will win the next
                                general election or dominate new government. However, “Trotskyite”
                                leader, <persName corresp="#p_PNM1">N. M. Perera</persName> who
                                controls important elements of organized labor and is widely
                                respected even in non-communist circles may be able to achieve an
                                important place for himself and his party in a new government.
                                (Para. 12)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Ceylon has experienced a progressive deterioration in internal
                                stability under the government of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>. Serious economic
                                difficulties have contributed to a decline in public confidence in
                                the government. Long-standing tension between the majority Sinhalese
                                community and the large Tamil minority has increased. The division
                                of political forces among a number of erratic and highly competitive
                                parties, including three rival communist parties, has complicated
                                the island’s troubles.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The island’s economy has been badly weakened by inadequate food
                                production, rising costs, growing unemployment, and an unusually
                                high rate of population increase (about three percent annually).
                                Foreign exchange reserves have been reduced as the result of rising
                                imports and falling export earnings. The government’s economic
                                development program has been poorly formulated and prosecuted.
                                Threats of nationalization of key activities have resulted in a loss
                                of confidence among Ceylonese and foreign businessmen.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>In this situation, the weakness of the government is a major
                                critical factor. The government is a coalition of divergent
                                interests whose political and economic outlook ranges all the way
                                from conservative <pb facs="0427" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/>
                                socialism to Marxist communism and which continues to be split
                                within itself on major domestic policy issues. <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> has proven himself a
                                weak and vacillating leader. Labor unrest and general disrespect for
                                law and order have increased. The traditional political neutrality
                                of the police and the armed services, which include diverse racial
                                and religious groups, is probably now uncertain. The government’s
                                strongly pro-Sinhalese orientation has been a major factor in the
                                rise of communal tension which culminated in May 1958 in bloody and
                                widespread rioting between Sinhalese and Tamils.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>In the face of <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>’s ineffectiveness in controlling the
                                rioting, Governor General <persName corresp="#p_GSOE1">Goonetilleke</persName> picked up the reins of leadership,
                                declared a state of emergency, and apparently directed personally
                                the widespread use of the security forces to restore order. The
                                state of emergency has been maintained by the <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> government, although
                                the Governor General has played a less active political role in
                                recent months. As relative calm has been restored, less and less use
                                has been made of the emergency powers.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The outlook is for continued discontent and further turbulence.
                                Little if any significant economic progress can be anticipated.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> shows little
                                promise of ever giving the island strong leadership. The morale of
                                the security services, already weakened by political interference
                                and probably by the communal tension, is likely to continue to
                                decline. We believe that this is particularly true of the police.
                                Continued labor unrest is probable and the leaders of the communist
                                parties will probably call further strikes in order to advance their
                                political fortunes. Such strikes might become widespread. While the
                                Sinhalese by virtue of their numbers clearly dominate the island,
                                demands by Sinhalese extremists for further privileges and by Tamils
                                for recognition of their interests will continue. We believe that
                                severe and widespread communal rioting may erupt again at any time,
                                especially after the state of emergency lapses, and might also
                                involve violence against indigenous Christians and
                                Westerners.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Despite general lack of confidence in <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>’s leadership, there is no ready
                                alternative to him in sight in the present Parliament. The
                                conservative opposition in Parliament is small and lacks leadership,
                                although the United National Party (<gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>) has apparently regained some popular support in
                                recent months. The leftist opposition in Parliament, although
                                stronger than the conservatives, is also relatively small and
                                lacking in cohesion. Although the government has lost some strength
                                in Parliament, it continues to hold a small majority. However, the
                                government will probably become increasingly vulnerable under
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>’s weak
                                leadership. Despite the desire of the major elements in the
                                government coalition to stay in power, festering differences among
                                them may lead to the government’s downfall. On balance, we believe
                                there is an even chance that <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>
                                <pb facs="0428" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> will be voted out of
                                office by Parliament before the end of his full term in 1961. In
                                that event, there would probably be a call for new elections.
                                Furthermore, if <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>,
                                who has been reported in ill health, should die in office or be
                                obliged to retire, the present coalition would probably not
                                survive.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>At the same time Bandaranike may be removed from office by some
                                other means before his term is over. If another major crisis
                                develops, and if <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>
                                again fails to respond to the situation, the Governor General might
                                choose to assume power himself. In such an eventuality, the Governor
                                General would probably seek to maintain a constitutional facade for
                                his actions, and would probably have the support of the security
                                forces and the civil service. He could probably provide effective
                                government for the country at least for a short time. However,
                                popular opposition to authoritarian rule and the small size and
                                relatively limited capabilities of the Ceylonese police and military
                                services would create strong pressures to restore some kind of
                                representative government fairly promptly.<note n="4" xml:id="d188fn4">Ceylonese security forces include 8,000 police
                                    and 7,600 armed forces personnel (6,000 regular and 1,600
                                    reserves now on active duty) with about 3,700 reserves currently
                                    demobilized. Ceylon’s population is about nine million.
                                    [Footnote in the source text.]</note></item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>There is a lesser chance that a group of leaders from among
                                conservative elements and the military and police might attempt a
                                takeover of the government without the leadership or support of the
                                Governor General. Such a group might succeed in seizing power, but
                                we do not believe that it would be able to maintain control of the
                                country for very long. If a coup of this kind failed, the position
                                of conservative elements would be badly damaged. In any event, the
                                loyalties of the armed forces and police would be put to a severe
                                test and significant numbers might withhold their support.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Communist influence in Ceylon will probably continue to increase
                                despite the strong rivalry which exists between the three communist
                                groups: the orthodox Communist Party, the “Trotskyite” party (<gloss target="#t_LSSP1">LSSP</gloss>) of <persName corresp="#p_PNM1">N. M. Perera</persName>, and the “independent” communist party
                                    (<gloss target="#t_VLSSPMEP1">VLSSP</gloss>) of <persName>Philip
                                    Gunawardena</persName> which is part of <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName>’s coalition. We do not
                                believe, however, that these communist groups, separately or
                                together, will be able within the next few years to seize control of
                                the government by extra-legal means—chiefly because of their small
                                size and the almost certain opposition of the Governor General and
                                the security forces to such a move. Nor do we believe it likely that
                                any grouping of communists will win the next general election or
                                dominate a new government. However, <persName corresp="#p_PNM1">N.
                                    M. Perera</persName> who controls important elements of
                                organized labor and is widely respected even in non-communist
                                circles may be able to achieve an important place for himself and
                                his party in a new government.</item>
                            <pb facs="0429" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/>
                            <label>13.</label>
                            <item>It appears unlikely that <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> will be able to remain as prime
                                minister beyond the next election. His demonstrated lack of
                                leadership, the generally poor government provided by his coalition,
                                and unfavorable economic developments make it unlikely that he will
                                be again able to organize a winning coalition. Popular support will
                                probably gravitate to the right and the left. While it now appears
                                that the <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_LSSP1">LSSP</gloss> will be the largest gainers, we
                                do not believe that any of the presently existing parties is likely
                                to get a majority. The result will probably be another coalition
                                government.</item>
                            <label>14.</label>
                            <item>The <persName corresp="#p_BMS1">Bandaranaike</persName> government
                                has won widespread support for its neutralist foreign policy. As
                                long as it remains in office, it will almost certainly continue to
                                follow this policy, and to adopt positions much the same as those of
                                India on international issues. The government has received or
                                accepted commitments of more than $100 million in foreign assistance
                                since it came to power. Of this, almost $60 million has come from
                                the Bloc and $43 million from the West. It will almost certainly
                                continue to seek as much foreign aid as it can get “without strings”
                                from both sides. It is unlikely that there would be any significant
                                change in foreign policy if a conservative regime were to come to
                                power, either by a coup or victory in the elections, but such a
                                government would in private probably be more sympathetic toward the
                                West.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>