<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>199. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    India</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-01-10T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-01-10T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recoRXZiW0XKZ4ec4" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Development loan</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recEmfen6T5wplQqD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Title II</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-01-10T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-10T21:00:00-05:00" n="199"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                <head>199. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                    <note n="2" type="source" xml:id="d199fn2">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 891.10/1–1058. Confidential; Priority. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_TWV1">William V. Turnage</persName>, Deputy Director of the
                        Office of International Financial and Development Affairs; cleared with
                            <gloss target="#t_SOA1">SOA</gloss>, the Export-Import Bank, and the
                        Treasury Department; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                            >Dillon</persName>. Paragraph 7 was cleared with the Department of
                        Agriculture.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-01-10T21:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 10, 1958—9 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1750. Ambassador authorized communicate following message on US assistance for
                    India to Prime Minister. The <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> sections are
                    for Embassy’s background information and use as guidance in discussion with
                        <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>. Embassy requested report promptly
                    Indian reaction.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Recognizing India’s need for additional resources to assist its economic
                        development, the US Government is prepared to discuss with Indian
                        representatives the implementation of a loan program contributing to current
                        India requirement. The loan program proposed by the US, utilizing presently
                        available funds, consists of <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss>
                        loans and Development Loan Fund credits.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In order to proceed with working out the details of this program, it is
                        hoped that the Indian Government will send to Washington qualified experts
                        empowered to engage in staff-level discussions on the technical aspects of
                        these programs. The discussions will concentrate primarily on implementation
                        of proposed <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> lending.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Eximbank</hi>
                        </gloss>: <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> is prepared to
                        consider a line of credit of $150 million to finance capital equipment and
                        services for priority projects in both public and private sectors which
                        would offer possibilities of early impact on the economy. In accord with its
                        basic policy, the use of the Bank’s resources would be limited to financing
                        goods of US origin.</item>
                    <pb facs="0448" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss>
                        </hi>: The Development Loan Fund is prepared to consider the extension of
                        credits, from funds available in the current fiscal year, to the extent of
                        about $75 million in connection with other high priority projects of the
                        Indian program for which financing from <gloss target="#t_EximBank1"
                            >Eximbank</gloss> or from other sources is not available. Additional
                        credits will be considered when and if new funds are appropriated by the
                        Congress for the Development Loan Fund. Development Loan Fund credits would
                        not necessarily be limited to the financing of goods of US origin.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In view of the increased Indian needs for capital goods of all types, it
                        is believed that such a loan program can make a significant contribution
                        towards meeting India’s capital goods import requirements over the next 15
                        to 18 months. It is desirable that Indian experts coming to Washington be
                        prepared to discuss the Indian import program in detail, providing such
                        information as the total size of the import program by years, its commodity
                        composition by capital goods category (e.g., electrical equipment, transport
                        equipment, machinery, etc.), commitments already entered into by country,
                        possible items for <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> financing
                        from US sources, and Indian contracting procedures. Since it is recognized
                        that presently available funds are limited, it is considered important that
                        Indian representatives be prepared to indicate those projects of program
                        considered of first importance. Following these discussions the <gloss
                            target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> and Development Loan Fund would
                        be prepared to send a mission to India to work out further details of the
                        credits. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. We believe it is desirable
                        that proposed credits be used for the type of projects which would make an
                        impact upon Indian public opinion. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                        >FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Also exploring possibility converting 1951 Wheat Loan<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d199fn3">reference is to the India Emergency Food Aid Act of
                            1951, approved by the President on June 15, 1951. (65 Stat. 71)</note>
                        to provide for repayment in local currency. <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                            >FYI</gloss>. This would require <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>
                        approval and consultation with Congressional leaders also deemed
                        appropriate. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In addition foregoing financial assistance, intensive work being done here
                        on means meeting immediate grain shortage. Embtels 1739<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d199fn4">Dated January 6. (Department of State, Central Files,
                            891.49/1–658)</note> and previous being carefully considered but (for
                        reason given below) primary means at present contemplated are (a) amendment
                        of present PL 480 Agreement<note n="5" xml:id="d199fn5">Agricultural Trade
                            Development and Assistance Act of 1954, approved by the President on
                            July 10, 1954. (68 Stat. 454) The then most recent <gloss
                                target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480 agreement with India was signed at
                            New Delhi on August 29, 1956. (7 UST 2803)</note> to substitute wheat
                        for substantial portion remaining cotton and (b) barter transactions of
                        substantial size involving various minerals. Appears total quantities wheat
                        which could be so provided would be sufficient, added to latest 400,000 tons
                        from Canada, <pb facs="0449" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> to meet needs to June
                        30 or somewhat later. Title I program<note n="6" xml:id="d199fn6">Reference
                            is to Title I of <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 480.</note> out of
                        FY59 funds will be considered when extended PL 480 authorization for next
                        fiscal year is passed by Congress. Arrangements for cotton-wheat shift being
                        worked out here as matter urgency, including preparation text exchange of
                        notes to take place New Delhi. Expect to discuss barter possibilities with
                        Indian representatives next week. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. For
                        domestic policy reasons it is considered important to conclude barter deal
                        if possible. Since <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> has not raised
                        question replacement cotton under (a), we prefer not discuss that question
                        now. To meet grain emergency, resort might also be had to other means,
                        including use Title II, if absolutely necessary, but not until above primary
                        means have been exhausted. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In view of the fact that the details for this proposed program cannot be
                        finalized before discussions are held with Indian representatives, it is the
                        desire of the US Government that publicity deal only with the broad
                        composition of the loan program. There is no objection, however, if the
                        Indian Government desires, to the release of information to the effect that
                        “the United States Government, desirous of assisting the Indian Government
                        to meet its current economic problem, has invited Indian representatives to
                        Washington to discuss the details of a loan program from currently available
                        funds totaling about $225 million from <gloss target="#t_EximBank1"
                            >Eximbank</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> sources. The
                        Indian Government has accepted this invitation. In addition, the US
                        Government is considering on an urgent basis additional measures to assist
                        India in meeting its immediate grain shortage.” <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                            >FYI</gloss>. We prefer that the decision on the desirability of a
                        publicity release be made by the Indians. Advise <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                            >GOI</gloss> reaction and content and timing if release planned to
                        permit simultaneous release here. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                            >FYI</gloss>.<note n="7" xml:id="d199fn7">In telegram 1816 from New
                            Delhi, January 14, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                                >Bunker</persName> informed the Department that Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_NBK1">Nehru</persName> was “pleased and
                            gratified” by the information on U.S. aid. (Department of State, Central
                            Files, 891.10/1–1458) A press release announcing the aid program was
                            issued on January 16 in both New Delhi and Washington. (Telegram 1774 to
                            New Delhi, January 14; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                            891.10/1–1458)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
