<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-02-11T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-02-11T22:00:00-05:00" n="513" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d513">
                        <head>513. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d513fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 792.5–MSP/2–1259. Secret. Also sent to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for POLAD.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Bangkok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-02-12T10:00:00+07:00"><hi rend="italic">February 12,
                                        1959—10 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>2042. Department telegram 1711.<note n="2" xml:id="d513fn2">Telegram
                                1711, February 4, informed the Embassy that no jet airplanes were
                                included in the fiscal year 1960 military assistance for Thailand.
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 792.5–MSP/2–459)</note><gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss>, particularly Marshal Chalermkiat,
                            will be bitter over failure provide jet planes FY 1960. Chalermkiat will
                            lose no opportunity express his feelings to <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> and anyone else in RP who will listen. However,
                            believe <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> and others will be
                            disposed judge nonscheduling jets in context total US aid program. If
                            Thai believe total aid FY 1960 inadequate, failure provide jets will
                            serve as additional irritant.</p>
                        <p>This connection Embassy noted one year ago (Embassy telegram 2048,
                            January 16, 1958)<note n="3" xml:id="d513fn3">Not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 792.5/1–1658)</note> that Thai
                            operated propeller-driven fighter-bombers becoming increasingly
                            difficult maintain and need replacement. At such time as replacement
                            effected, believe adverse political reaction here would be very strong
                            unless jets are supplied. Thais well-aware US furnishing F–86 and even
                            more modern aircraft to other Asian allies.</p>
                        <p>Re timing replacements, Embassy wishes make following observations:</p>
                        <p>Program refinement instructions to JUSMAG from DOD give as objectives
                            proposed FY 1960 program: maintenance of effectiveness of <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>-supported forces, replacement of
                            overage or nonsupportable equipment and provision of limited force
                            improvement which is of special political or strategic significance.
                            (See also paragraph 53, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Operations
                            Plan for Thailand, January 9, 1959.)<note n="4" xml:id="d513fn4">Not
                                printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Files: Lot 62 D 430, Thailand)</note> Continued
                            equipping of two of three <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>
                            fighter-bomber squadrons of <gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> with
                            F–8–F propeller-driven aircraft is certainly not consistent with these
                            objectives. Furthermore, as F–8–F aircraft are on life-of-type support
                            at present time, their phase-out is insured within 12 months. In effect,
                            failure to supply additional more modern aircraft to <gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> in FY 1960 or before will, leave them
                            with only one active fighter-bomber squadron as present F–8–F equipped
                            squadrons become inactive. This likewise hardly consistent with <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-approved force objective of three
                            effective, combat-ready fighter-bomber squadrons.</p>
                        <pb facs="1099" n="1067" xml:id="pg_1067"/>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> was advised in Washington and again
                            during visit to Thailand of Deputy Assistant Secretary Defense (ISA) in
                            November, that unless utilization of its jet aircraft improved
                            materially Thailand could expect receive no more jet aircraft. JUSMAG
                            advises that average monthly aircraft utilization for 1957 was 226 hours
                            and for 1958, 301 hours. More significant is effort made in past five
                            months presumably in response to the warnings. Utilization of jets in
                            September 286, October 385, November 572, December 636 and January 500
                            hours. Failure to program jet aircraft in FY 1960 will certainly look to
                            Thais like breach of faith, as they expect as corollary to improved
                            utilization which they have now shown, provision of some jets to replace
                            their obsolete conventional aircraft.</p>
                        <p>Further and most important, unless jets are programmed in FY 1960, JUSMAG
                            will be without any leverage to press for better training and
                            utilization. Deliveries can be withheld until performance is assured
                            only if jets are in the program. Programming however does not insure
                            that they will be delivered.</p>
                        <p>While <gloss target="#t_RTN1">RTN</gloss> would presumably be happy
                            accept minesweeper, doubt that any Thai military would regard this as
                            adequate substitute for jet squadron. Provision destroyer escort FY 1959
                            will also help offset impact failure provide jets but will of course not
                            make <gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> any happier. Would also
                            soften blow if we could indicate US still planning furnish jets as
                            replacement for F–8F–s at some future time. While Embassy of course not
                            in position make judgment as to type aircraft <gloss target="#t_RTAF1">RTAF</gloss> should have in future we feel that desire to have
                            reasonably capable air arm is entirely understandable and justified. In
                            this connection, Thais well-aware <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> does not guarantee automatic and immediate US air
                            support.</p>
                        <p>Also, believe it important bear in mind Thailand’s unique position in
                            area as member <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> and supporter US
                            foreign policy objectives and understandable sensitivity over very small
                            magnitude US aid as compared with other countries in area. To maintain
                            Thailand’s exceptionally cooperative attitude toward US requires
                            nurturing on our part and responsiveness to proper and reasonable Thai
                            expectations. Chief JUSMAG concurs in foregoing.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JUA1"><hi rend="strong">Johnson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>