<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>562. Telegram From the Embassy in Thailand to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d562</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">562</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-11-05T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-11-05T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="rechJJ62r5nmf4KiI" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural exchanges</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-11-05T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-11-05T02:00:00-05:00" n="562"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d562">
                <head>562. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d562fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.92/11–560. Secret. Repeated to Vientiane, Phnom Penh, Saigon, and
                        Moscow.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bangkok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-11-05T14:00:00+07:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 5, 1960—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>809. Reference: Embtels 789 and 797 (latter paraphrased in our telegram repeated
                    to Moscow 2).<note n="2" xml:id="d562fn2">
                        <p>Telegram 789, November 3, informed the Department of front-page coverage
                            in the Thai English language press concerning reports by Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName>’s Assistant Luang Vichit
                            Vadakarn of the call by the new Soviet Ambassador on <persName
                                corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> on October 31. Luang Vichit said
                            that the Ambassador proposed commercial, technical, scientific, and
                            cultural relations with Thailand to which the Prime Minister replied
                            that Thailand would be glad to agree but asked that the Soviets not
                            propound their political ideology or carry out subversive activity in
                            the country. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 661.92/11–360)</p>
                        <p>Telegram 797, November 4, provided more reporting on press coverage
                            concerning the possibility of closer Thai-Soviet relations, and quoted
                            from press interviews with <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName>
                            in which he emphasized that he and the Soviet Ambassador had talked
                            about increased trade as a way to promote closer ties, although
                                <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> emphasized Thai dislike
                            for Communist ideology. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                            661.92/11–460)</p>
                    </note> Statements by Prime Minister and Luang Wichit on closer relations with
                    and possible acceptance of aid from Soviets are rather transparent tactics
                    designed give US dramatic warning that Thailand serious about (1) their
                    dissatisfaction with US attitude on Lao situation and their feeling US and
                        <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> actions to meet dangers to Thailand
                    inadequate, and (2) long-standing complaint that “neutrals” not only receive
                    more aid, which committed nation like <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss>
                    foregoes, but also are better treated by US than committed nation. At present I
                    do not believe that government will implement Prime Minister’s general
                    statements to any significant extent. Interesting to note in support of view
                    this done for US benefit that World editor Berrigan told Embassy officer here of
                    call from Public Relations Department calling special attention to Soviet
                    Ambassador’s “offer” and Thailand response, thus assuring that it would get big
                    splash in English-language press.</p>
                <p>Of course even if only tactical move on part of Thailand it dangerous one.
                    Left-wing and nuetralist elements here which have been effectively silenced for
                    past two years sure to be encouraged by statements government even willing to
                    consider prospect of accepting aid from and conducting student and cultural
                    exchanges with Soviets. Soviets could follow up with highly attractive offer
                    which would strengthen hand of left-wing elements here even though government
                    might refuse accept and perhaps never intended accept offer. Anti-Commie
                    elements will find government’s attitude confusing. <pb facs="1184" n="1152"
                        xml:id="pg_1152"/> Therefore even though government intends no shift in its
                    tough line toward domestic leftist elements it may find it has in fact
                    encouraged them and made them more difficult to control.</p>
                <p>In terms of reasons Thailand chose to take this step, Embtel 744 (which being
                    repeated Moscow) emphasized factors arising out of present Lao situation which
                    have created discontent among Thais.<note n="3" xml:id="d562fn3">Telegram 744
                        from Bangkok, October 26, conveyed <persName corresp="#p_JUA1"
                            >Johnson</persName>’s view that, in spite of Thai unhappiness and
                        dissatisfaction with U.S. policy in Laos and with French and British
                        unwillingness to consider a stronger <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                        role in Laos, Thailand’s policy of close adherence to the United States
                        would not change in the absence of further adverse developments. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 692.00/10–2660)</note> Long before Laos
                    situation arose, as Embassy often pointed out, many Thais were disturbed by way
                    “neutrals” treated in US programs relative to <gloss target="#t_RTG1"
                        >RTG</gloss>. Thais have watched Cambodia most closely this respect, and
                    such cases as Pakistan moves toward obtaining Soviet assistance and recent
                    announcement US aid program to Guinea no doubt have had some impact. These cases
                    provide ammunition for group in government (e.g. nationalists like Foreign
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_KT1">Thanat</persName> and Luang Wichit and
                    probably also left-wingers Generals Net and Amphorn) who appear believe <gloss
                        target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> should move toward neutralism at least to
                    extent pressuring US for greater aid by what they would call “blackmail” if done
                    by Cambodia, for example. Lao situation has played into hands this group by
                    creating sense frustration among “men of action” such as <persName
                        corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> and apparently made it possible for them
                    to convince <persName corresp="#p_TS1">Sarit</persName> of wisdom making these
                    statements.</p>
                <p>In order keep incident in perspective, would like point out that new Soviet
                    Ambassador was making routine courtesy call on Prime Minister which latter could
                    not have refused accept.</p>
                <p>I propose, for time being, to take no action and to shrug off any leading
                    questions from <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> officials in order avoid
                    playing into their hands.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
