<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>570. Telegram From the Embassy in Thailand to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d570</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">570</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-11-18T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-11-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-11-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-11-18T06:00:00-05:00" n="570"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d570">
                <head>570. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d570fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.92/11–1860. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bangkok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-11-18T18:00:00+07:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 18, 1960—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>875. Embtels 848 and 856.<note n="2" xml:id="d570fn2">
                        <ref target="#d565">Documents 565</ref> and <ref target="#d568"
                        >568</ref>.</note> Yesterday Foreign Minister asked again discuss subject
                    with me. Gave me new Thai draft of “agreement” to effect that neither Thai nor
                    US Government would take “measures or actions” in regard to Laos “without
                    concurrence of other party.” In reply my queries Foreign Minister said that as
                    far as Thailand concerned would include such actions as trade policies with
                    respect Laos, returning fire of Lao forces, etc. On part US would expect include
                    such items as procedures payment Phoumi forces, etc. I said that while
                    appreciating willingness Thailand limit its freedom of action to such extent,
                    did not feel <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> could do so. Of course <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> fully recognized Thai interest in Laos and in
                    fact our actions there might well have serious repercussions on Thailand.
                    Therefore we could and would as we had in past consult with Thailand but had to
                    retain freedom of action in our day-to-day operations in Laos and relations with
                    Lao authorities. However recognized such actions as US placing US forces in Laos
                    or Thailand placing Thai forces there entirely different order of importance as
                    by such action either could involve other in hostilities. Therefore utmost
                    importance there be full consultation and maximum degree agreement on such
                    actions.</p>
                <p>Although Department’s reaction to draft aide-mémoire Embtel 856 not yet received
                    I showed draft to <persName corresp="#p_KT1">Thanat</persName> and discussed
                    with him stressing it purely my own draft and not cleared by Washington. After
                    long discussion he agreed accept as basis for further discussion by him with
                    Prime Minister with amendment of second sentence last para to read: “In order
                    that their efforts to this end should have maximum effect, it is agreed that
                    they will consult together and coordinate their efforts and actions to the
                    fullest possible extent.”</p>
                <p>Would appreciate soonest Department’s comments on draft as amended above for
                    guidance discussion with Foreign Minister after he has seen Prime Minister.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
