<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>66. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (Rountree) to the ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recfrz0b94d87k9th" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-engineering" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092968" lcsh-match="exact">Engineering</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="66"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                <head>66. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1" type="from"
                    >Rountree</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d66fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 690D.91322/4–2859. Secret. Drafted by Kennedy and <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHW1">Spielman</persName> on April 27 and concurred in by
                            <gloss target="#t_WMSC1">W/MSC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_H1"
                            >H</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-04-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 28, 1959</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Your meeting with Mr. <persName>Eugene Black</persName> with Respect to
                        the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> Proposal for Settlement of the
                        Indus Waters Dispute</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Eugene Black</persName>, President of the International Bank for
                    Reconstruction and Development, will be proceeding to New Delhi and Karachi to
                    discuss with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NBK1">Nehru</persName> and
                    President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> the Bank’s proposal for
                    settling the Indus Waters Dispute (Tab A).<note n="2" xml:id="d66fn2">Reference
                        is to an <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> memorandum of March 26,
                        attached to the source text but not printed.</note> The purpose of his call
                    on you is to obtain some indication of the Department’s attitude with respect to
                    the Bank’s Plan. In particular, recalling what Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ISWAB1"
                        >Iliff</persName> said to you when he saw you before your departure for the
                        <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> meeting, Mr.
                        <persName>Black</persName> will be desirous of obtaining some “sympathetic
                        noises.”<note n="3" xml:id="d66fn3">No record of this conversation has been
                        found.</note> The date and time of his appointment with you is not yet
                    fixed.</p>
                <p>The Bank proposal consists of three parts: (1) the preliminary engineering
                    proposal, (2) the proposed financial arrangements and (3) a proposed
                    International Water Agreement.</p>
                <p>Briefly, the engineering proposal provides that India would have exclusive use,
                    after a suitable lapse of time, of the waters of the three Eastern Rivers and
                    Pakistan the use of the waters of the Western Rivers. The proposed financial
                    arrangements (which Bank representatives have called illustrative) provide for
                    financing of replacement works which would enable Pakistan to procure her water
                    requirements formerly supplied by India, from the three Western Rivers, and
                    would also provide for a certain amount of new development. The total cost of
                    the Plan, estimated to amount to $985 million, would be provided as follows:
                    from the United States new dollar loans repayable in local currency and PL 480
                    rupees—$606 million; United Kingdom, Australia and Canada in free foreign
                    exchange grant to Pakistan—$70 million; India in payment to Pakistan in free
                    foreign exchange—$200 million; <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>—$109
                    million. Of this total $501 million <pb facs="0196" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/>
                    represents the cost for works in Pakistan necessary to replace the waters which
                    India will take and the balance of $484 million of new development.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That you express your appreciation of the Bank’s efforts and say the Plan
                        appears to be a very sound one.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>That you refer to your understanding that the Bank’s financial plan is
                        illustrative and indicate that there seemed to be some elements worth
                        exploring. Points which might be made include: (a) India’s $200 million
                        contribution might be made in Indian rupees as a line of credit for Indian
                        products which Pakistan might procure instead of in free foreign exchange,
                        (b) the Commonwealth countries’ contribution of $70 million might be
                        increased and used to meet foreign exchange costs of construction projects
                        instead of paying for the importation of goods to produce Pakistan rupees
                        and (c) other countries of the Free World, for example, Germany, Japan and
                        Italy might be encouraged to share in the foreign exchange
                        contributions.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>That you make the “sympathetic noise” which it is understood Mr.
                            <persName>Black</persName> wishes before he goes to New Delhi and
                        Karachi by saying that you personally were very sympathetic to the proposal,
                        that you hope that Mr. <persName>Black</persName> will succeed in his
                        mission and that you would be prepared to discuss with other high officers
                        in the Government and with Congressional leaders the request to Congress for
                        providing the United States’ share of the necessary funds. Such a request,
                        of course, would depend on several factors including agreement between India
                        and Pakistan and contributions from other countries.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
