<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-01T16:32:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-01T16:32:00-05:00" n="156" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d156">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/339: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Goold</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                            Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-01T17:00:00-04:32"><hi rend="italic">December
                                            1, 1918, 5 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received December 2, 6.37 a.m.</hi>]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs informed me yesterday afternoon that
                                it was the intention of the Bolivian Government to send a special
                                embassy to Washington for the purpose of congratulating the
                                Government of the United States upon the outcome of the war and for
                                the purpose of presenting the case of Bolivia for the acquisition of
                                a port. He stated that the case of Bolivia was precisely like that
                                of Servia; that it was necessary for the country to occupy a
                                position that would enable it to communicate and carry on commerce
                                with the outside world without having to obtain the consent <pb facs="0228" n="126" xml:id="pg_126"/> of another country. He
                                stated that there was a very considerable body of opinion in Chile
                                in favor of the cession of Arica to Bolivia, and he claimed that a
                                similar body of opinion existed in Peru, but that it was less
                                articulate in Peru because of the Peruvian grievance against Chile
                                on the subject of Arica. He pointed out that with Bolivia placed
                                between Chile and Peru, the peace of this continent would be more
                                secure than it has been for decades. He stated that the Bolivian
                                Government is anxious to have the United States take the initiative
                                in the settlement of the problem, either by making specific
                                suggestions for the settlement to the countries involved, or by
                                calling a conference of the three to be held under the presidency of
                                the Secretary of State or other officer to [be designated?] by the
                                President of the United States or by any other method deemed
                                suitable by the Secretary [<hi rend="italic">United States</hi>]. If
                                under the rules to be adopted by the Congress of Versailles, nations
                                other than those which have actually participated in the war are to
                                be allowed to send representatives, it is the intention of the
                                Bolivian Government to send delegates to said Congress, which
                                delegates will bring to its attention the problem herein referred
                                to, unless the United States has in the meantime taken steps looking
                                toward its settlement. The Bolivian Government would prefer to have
                                the proceedings for the settlement initiated and presided over by
                                the United States.</p>
                            <p>I would like to know definitely whether the President is going to
                                Versailles, and if so, when, and something concerning the probable
                                duration of his absence from the United States, so that it can
                                determine the destination and date of departure of the embassy
                                herein before referred to.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Goold</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>