<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the British Appointed Ambassador ( (Grey))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-11-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-11-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-11-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-11-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="500"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/2533</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        British Appointed Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grey</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-11-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 11, 1919</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                    receipt of the note (No. 812) of the 8th instant in which Your Excellency, in
                    reference to communications made to you in behalf of this Department on the
                    subject of loans to China, conveys an expression of the satisfaction of the
                    British Minister for Foreign Affairs that the independent loan by the Chicago
                    Continental and Commercial Trust and Savings Bank has been abandoned and that
                    the United States Government is prepared to adopt the proposal put forward by
                    the British Government for an immediate advance by the Four Powers without
                    prejudice.</p>
                <p>I have taken pleasure in communicating to the American Group the terms of this
                    proposal as embodied in your note, with an expression of this Government’s hope
                    that the Group may find it feasible to arrange for cooperation with the several
                    other national groups upon the terms so indicated; and in the confidence that
                    such cooperation may be arranged I am directing the American Ambassadors in
                    Paris and Tokyo to support the proposals of the British Government.</p>
                <p>I venture to hope that this adoption by the American Government of the proposals
                    made by the British Government may make it possible to effect without undue
                    delay a combination of the financial interests concerned, if only for the
                    temporary and limited purpose of affording to the Chinese Government the means
                    of meeting its <pb facs="0641" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/> present financial
                    crisis and averting the necessity of its taking such steps as would essentially
                    alter the <hi rend="italic">status quo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is enclosed herewith for your information a copy of the telegram in which I
                    am advising the Japanese Government, through the American Embassy at Tokyo, of
                    the action taken by this Government in response to the suggestion of the British
                        Government.<note n="45" xml:id="d500fn45">Telegram of Nov. 11, 5 p.m., <ref
                            target="#pg_535">p. 535</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
