<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The French Ambassador ( (Jusserand) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d521</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">521</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-12-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="521"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d521">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/2595</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-12-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 22, 1919</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: It appears from reports that
                    have reached my Government that American bankers have taken up the matter of a
                    30 million loan to China that had been dropped by the Abbott group. It is said
                    that the revenues derived from alcohol and tobacco would be taken as security
                    for the loan and that a reorganization thereof would be entrusted to an
                    international department under American management. It is even said that the
                    contract may have already been signed.</p>
                <p>My Government wishes me to remind Your Excellency of our views on the subject
                    which may be summed up as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>As the American Government undoubtedly knows, we wish, on account of
                            the international interest that attaches to the arrangement, that the
                            advances and loans to China be in the exclusive charge of the
                            institutions in the Consortium partnership.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The influence possessed in Peking by the United States Government
                            should, we believe, make it easy for the American Minister to China to
                            induce the Chinese Government to ignore offers from institutions that do
                            not belong to the Consortium.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It cannot be denied that the taxes on alcohol and tobacco constitute,
                            in any event, the first mortgage of the loan floated in 1913 [<hi
                                rend="italic">1914?</hi>] by the Industrial Bank.<note n="62"
                                xml:id="d521fn62">See <ref target="frus1916#pg_143">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1916, pp.
                                    143</ref>–<ref target="frus1916#pg_144">144</ref>.</note> It
                            therefore seems to us that our countrymen have a right to ask when the
                            internal revenue service is reorganized to have a part commensurate to
                            their interests and, in particular, the administrative direction of the
                            service, assigned to them.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic realized, as fully as Your
                    Excellency, the advantages of an active Franco American <pb facs="0654" n="552"
                        xml:id="pg_552"/> collaboration in the Far East. He therefore believes it
                    would be beneficial, in the process of reorganization, to assign to American
                    specialists the technical management, mainly because of the experience gained by
                    the American Tobacco Company’s representative in China.</p>
                <p>In my Government’s opinion the above suggested arrangement would be practical and
                    equitable, as taking into consideration the various interests involved. From a
                    practical standpoint the American Government will doubtless take the position
                    that the prohibition law recently enacted in the United States would make it
                    preferable to entrust a Frenchman rather than an American with the executive
                    collection of taxes on two staples, one of which is alcohol.</p>
                <p>Be pleased [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
