<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="674" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/1</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-09"><hi rend="italic">August 9,
                                        1918</hi>.</date><lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received September
                                        18</hi>.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 2184</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to a
                                communication, under date of July 16th last, with which Mr. Charles
                                Denby, special assistant to the Department of State, enclosed a
                                memorandum embodying a suggestion that the foreign courts of all
                                nationalities conducted under the system of extraterritoriality in
                                China be abolished, and that China be urged to establish courts of
                                her own with jurisdiction over cases in which foreigners are
                                parties.</p>
                            <p>I venture to comment that this suggestion, although perhaps not
                                realizable in the immediate future, would nevertheless seem to
                                indicate a stage of development towards which Chinese and foreign
                                residents alike should find it advantageous to strive. While it is
                                true that the present administration of justice in China is not such
                                as would warrant the inclusion of foreigners under its jurisdiction;
                                and while it is further unfortunately true that the Chinese are in
                                general apathetic and unresponsive to any suggestion of improvement,
                                it may nevertheless be urged that this apathy is itself the result
                                of the hopelessness with which they regard any possibility of
                                obtaining the right to be entrusted with any responsible share in
                                the administration of their laws where foreigners are concerned; I
                                believe it is the fact that, in the case of this and of certain of
                                the other limitations upon their sovereignty, imposed by the older
                                treaties, the feeling of even the more ambitious Chinese is that the
                                attitude of foreign nations, and particularly of Japan, has been
                                such <pb facs="0777" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> as to warrant no hope
                                that a betterment of conditions through the efforts of China would
                                receive the sympathy and cooperation of the powers.</p>
                            <p>If this belief be correct, there is at least an explanation, if not a
                                justification, of the rather short-sighted view which the Chinese
                                are too generally inclined to take towards the international
                                obligations thus imposed upon them—the view that such restrictions
                                upon their freedom of action should not only be jealously guarded
                                with a view to preventing any undue enlargement of the privileges
                                already conceded, but should whenever possible and by all available
                                means be contested, evaded, and rendered nugatory. It is at least to
                                be hoped that the proposal by our Government of a plan devised to
                                allow them a fuller share of responsibility in dealing with foreign
                                interests would encourage in the Chinese the broader and more
                                far-sighted view, that only by deserving it can they entitle
                                themselves to the enjoyment of fuller rights than have hitherto been
                                allowed them. It was, of course, by a patient devotion to this ideal
                                that Japan rid itself of extraterritoriality.</p>
                            <p>More recently, and under circumstances that, though less conspicuous,
                                are perhaps even more remarkable by reason of the comparative
                                smallness of the state concerned, Siam has in its more important
                                international relations (i. e., with Great Britain and France)
                                almost completely done away with the restrictions of
                                extraterritoriality. As the Department is aware, this result has
                                been accomplished largely through the influence of two American
                                advisers, the late Mr. Edward Strobel, and Mr. Jens I. Westengard,
                                who, under conditions which in many respects were analogous to those
                                now prevailing in China, were able to bring the Siamese Government
                                to the realization that by scrupulous observance of all the
                                obligations imposed upon them, and by sedulous improvement of their
                                legislation and judicial administration, they would eventually put
                                themselves in a position to claim the sympathy and assistance of the
                                powers with which their relations had hitherto been continually
                                irritated by the attempt of Siam to minimize those obligations. The
                                result was that save for certain safeguards, which are scarcely
                                onerous to the Siamese, the jurisdiction over subjects of Great
                                Britain and of France has been almost wholly rendered over to Siam,
                                under a system not fundamentally different from that which Mr. Denby
                                suggests as eventually possible in the case of China.</p>
                            <p>Although fully realizing the preoccupation of the Department, and
                                feeling some hesitancy in urging consideration of a matter which may
                                for the present be deemed somewhat academic, I venture to urge that
                                the matter is one which is at least worthy of consideration; and I
                                venture further to suggest that if this view is in any degree shared
                                    <pb facs="0778" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/> by the Department, it
                                would be advisable to consult Mr. Westengard (whose address is
                                understood to be the Harvard Law School, Cambridge, Mass.) with a
                                view to ascertaining his judgment upon a proposal which so closely
                                resembles the plan which he brought to a successful realization in
                                Siam.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. V. A.
                                MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Special Assistant to the Department of
                                        State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Denby</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-16"><hi rend="italic">July 16, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I enclose herewith
                                    a memorandum making a suggestion of a somewhat radical character
                                    in regard to the exercise of extraterritorial jurisdiction in
                                    this country. I beg you to give this matter your sympathetic
                                    attention as it is of vital interest to us here, and one of the
                                    great steps we can take to complete the post war program for the
                                    United States. This idea is my own, if [<hi rend="italic">is?</hi>] entirely original in its present form and I want
                                    the American Government to have the benefit of it, and to this
                                    end I urgently recommend that you take it up at once with the
                                    Chinese Minister at Washington in a tentative way in order that
                                    to America may attach the credit and advantage of having first
                                    approached the Chinese Government in this sense.</p>
                                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles
                                    Denby</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of the <gloss type="from">Special
                                            Assistant</gloss> to the Department of State</hi>
                                        (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Denby</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <p>The time has not yet arrived to abolish extraterritoriality in
                                    China. Extraterritoriality as applied to citizens of the United
                                    States was established by the Treaty of Wang-Hea, signed in
                                        1844,<note n="5" xml:id="d674fn5">For text of treaty, see
                                        Malloy, <hi rend="italic">Treaties</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 196 ff.</note> Article[s]
                                    XXI and XXV of which read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXI</hi></p>
                                        <p>“Subjects of China who may be guilty of any criminal act
                                            towards citizens of the United States shall be arrested
                                            and punished by the Chinese authorities according to the
                                            laws of China, and citizens of the United States who may
                                            commit any crime in China shall <pb facs="0779" n="677" xml:id="pg_677"/> be subject to be tried and
                                            punished only by the Consul or other public functionary
                                            of the United States thereto authorized according to the
                                            laws of the United States; and in order to the
                                            prevention of all controversy and disaffection, justice
                                            shall be equitably and impartially administered on both
                                            sides.”</p>
                                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXV</hi></p>
                                        <p>“All questions in regard to rights, whether of property
                                            or person, arising between citizens of the United States
                                            in China shall be subject to the jurisdiction of, and
                                            regulated by the authorities of their own Government;
                                            and all controversies occurring in China between the
                                            citizens of the United States and the subjects of any
                                            other Government shall be regulated by the Treaties
                                            existing between the United States and such
                                            Government[s] respectively, without interference on the
                                            part of China”.</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>By the American Commercial Treaty signed at Shanghai in 1903<note n="6" xml:id="d674fn6"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, pp. 201
                                        ff.</note> provision was made to abolish extraterritoriality
                                    at some proper time. Article XV of this Treaty reads as follows:
                                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The Government of China having expressed a strong desire
                                            to reform its judicial system and to bring it into
                                            accord with that of Western nations, the United States
                                            agrees to give every assistance to such reform and will
                                            also be prepared to relinquish extraterritorial rights
                                            when satisfied that the state of the Chinese laws, the
                                            arrangements for their administration, and other
                                            considerations warrant it in so doing.”</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>It is evident that China has not yet established her right under
                                    our Shanghai Treaties to call upon us to abolish
                                    extraterritoriality, but there are growing evidences that
                                    extraterritoriality, as at present administered, is a barrier to
                                    our relations with China, and is a handicap to the Chinese
                                    themselves in their attempt to establish autonomous government
                                    free from foreign control. The extraterritorial provisions in
                                    the treaties which the foreign powers have imposed upon China
                                    were intended to protect the foreigner from the entire conflict
                                    between their ideas of legal administration and our own; above
                                    all to protect the foreigner from the possible animus of Chinese
                                    authorities against a litigant because of his nationality.
                                    Undoubtedly this purpose has been served and without this system
                                    foreign residence in China would have been impossible. The
                                    advantages of the system are manifest; the disadvantages were
                                    not foreseen at the time that treaties were put into effect. In
                                    the early days of the commercial intercourse of foreigners with
                                    the Chinese the foreign merchant’s life was his own, he was
                                    quite content with his own little world, with his race course
                                    and his club. He conducted his business in a commercial house to
                                    which the Chinese <pb facs="0780" n="678" xml:id="pg_678"/>
                                    customers in general had a limited access, and he conducted his
                                    business through his compradore, which person was his link with
                                    the Chinese world. He felt no necessity to learn the Chinese
                                    language, nor, in fact, to familiarize himself with the market
                                    with which he was dealing. To compensate himself for this
                                    deficiency, however, he had the protection of his own laws and
                                    the sanctity of his own national concession in some treaty port.
                                    The requirements, however, of modern business in China have
                                    changed all this. The young men of the great foreign firms, such
                                    as the British-American Tobacco Company, the Standard Oil
                                    Company and others find it necessary to go widely throughout the
                                    country. They are, in fact, breaking down the barriers which
                                    were heretofore highly prized by the foreign merchants and we
                                    now find these barriers which protected us from Chinese ill
                                    treatment in fact obstacles in the way of our intercourse with
                                    them. We do not get at the market nor do we get at the people.
                                    The missionaries have long outgrown this and in their
                                    intercourse with the Chinese the treaty port concession has lost
                                    its value. They have learned the Chinese language, they have
                                    mixed freely with the people; they have secured through treaty
                                    the right to secure land elsewhere than at treaty ports, and
                                    have, in fact, occupied the anomalous position of Foreigners
                                    resident throughout the Republic remote from any court that
                                    could bring them to trial for their misdeeds or for the
                                    settlement of their civil controversies. This is a lesson to the
                                    foreign interests in general that extraterritoriality while a
                                    protection is at the same time a distinct limitation on the
                                    activities of foreigners in this country. The Japanese have not
                                    been slow in finding this out. They reason with justice that if
                                    they can keep the foreign world chained to the principle of
                                    extraterritoriality, Chinese tariff and economic subjection they
                                    thus limit the foreign activity and leave it free to the
                                    Japanese to place themselves outside these restrictions. By
                                    reason of racial and linguistic similarity the Japanese have, in
                                    fact, readier access to the Chinese people than the foreigner
                                    can ever hope to have. They are profiting thereby to enter the
                                    markets of China freely and as it goes on there will be less and
                                    less doubt that they are gainers by what we have considered our
                                    own protective measures.</p>
                                <p>It is not probable that conditions in China at the present time
                                    would justify the abolition of extraterritoriality and the
                                    committing of foreigners and their rights to Chinese courts;
                                    something, however, can be done towards this end. It might be
                                    indicated to the Chinese Government that the United States
                                    contemplated with some concern the time when extraterritoriality
                                    could be abolished; that the United States Government recognized
                                    that the Chinese could never learn to administer justice in
                                    cases where foreigners were <pb facs="0781" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/> involved without some experience in that
                                    administration, and that the United States Government proposed
                                    to lay before China some plan by which a gradual abolition of
                                    extraterritoriality could be accomplished.</p>
                                <p>We have in China at this date large interests such as the Foreign
                                    Maritime Customs, the Salt Gabelle, with its collection of
                                    enormous revenue, the railways with their semiforeign
                                    administration, all of which are conducted upon the (principle
                                    that the Chinese is to be used as far as possible but that his
                                    activities are to be controlled by supervising foreign
                                    administration.</p>
                                <p>It is, therefore, proposed by the undersigned that the United
                                    States Government approach the Chinese Government with the
                                    proposition that a Ministry of Justice shall be established with
                                    a prominent jurist at the head of the same; that this Ministry
                                    should be charged with the duty of establishing local courts
                                    throughout the Chinese Republic; that the appointees of these
                                    courts should be in some cases foreigners with Chinese, and in
                                    some cases Chinese alone; that in all cases during the operation
                                    of this plan an appeal should lie from the Courts of first
                                    instance to a superior court which foreign officials would
                                    control. In this way all the Consular Courts with their natural
                                    bias in favor of their own nationalities could be abolished. We
                                    would inspire in the Chinese some sentiment of self-respect, and
                                    above all we could train them in their relations with foreigners
                                    so that eventually they would be able to conduct not only their
                                    own legal procedure but other functions of their government in
                                    their relations with foreigners.</p>
                                <p>The machinery of such an organization would not be complicated as
                                    compared with the Customs Service, the railways and the Salt
                                    Administration. It would not be necessary in the first instance
                                    to establish a great number of courts; the system could be
                                    allowed to grow, the sites of the Courts, the methods of
                                    procedure, etc. could be modified by experience and there is
                                    much reason to believe that in the course of a few years such a
                                    reliable machinery of justice could be built up as to justify us
                                    in turning the whole system over to the Chinese themselves.</p>
                                <p>In view of the fact that the Power which first offered to China
                                    some such plan as above outlined will receive its warm
                                    gratitude, it is recommended that the Minister of China at
                                    Washington be at once approached along these lines; that the
                                    above project be more carefully elaborated and that in time a
                                    convention be made with China to put it into effect. The
                                    advantages of the system are so manifest that no determined
                                    opposition need be feared from other Treaty Powers. The United
                                    States, England and France are all recognizing the restrictions
                                    they are under in their relations with <pb facs="0782" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/> the Chinese by reason of their
                                    extraterritoriality. Commerce would profit by the innovation.
                                    China would be more widely thrown open to foreign intercourse,
                                    educational and missionary establishments would gather a new
                                    impetus and our political influence over the Chinese would be
                                    greatly widened. This seems the proper time to introduce this
                                    reformation. There will be much adjustment after the war, and
                                    this project might well be one feature thereof, free from any
                                    taint of selfishness or commercial gain. This idea is submitted
                                    now so as to gain for it a place in the affairs of China which
                                    will become subjects of post war negotiation. Now is the time to
                                    lay it before the Chinese and to secure their provisional
                                    acceptance of it.</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-16"><hi rend="italic">July 16, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>