<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Colombia ( (Philip) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d753</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">753</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-10-29T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-10-29T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-10-29T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-10-29T12:00:00-05:00" n="753"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d753">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.21/512: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-10-29T12:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 29, 1919, noon.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received November 2, 6.40 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>160. Referring to Department’s October 13, 10 p.m. and October 14, 6 p.m.<note
                        n="36" xml:id="d753fn1">Latter telegram not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The treaty situation as I view it after careful consideration is briefly as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>Our Government, having obtained the consent of the Colombia[n] Government to
                    extensive alterations in the text of treaty of 1914, has refused action on that
                    pact until Colombia shall agree to a second treaty to guarantee the ownership of
                    non-metalliferous subsoil deposits to American holders of real property in
                    Colombia; the <pb facs="0856" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> Colombian Government is
                    most anxious to see a settlement of the treaty of 1914 and wishes to meet the
                    second requirement by our Government if that can be accomplished without
                    incurring revolution as a result of such an effort upon the suspicions of an
                    extraordinar[il]y sensitive population as well as upon those of its political
                    opponents.</p>
                <p>I am definitely assured that the President and a majority of the Cabinet as at
                    present constituted are in favor of private ownership of subsoil rights to
                    non-metalliferous deposits. However, I am authoritatively informed that a
                    majority in Congress favors the contrary, or national ownership. The Chamber has
                    completed its discussions of the petroleum law and is expected to vote and send
                    it to Senate probably within a few days. The President, the Minister of Foreign
                    Affairs, and others tell me they believe the law will be a very advantageous one
                    for foreign interests. Two striking features it will embody are as follows: 1,
                    the public oil lands will be acquired by contract and not by denomination [<hi
                        rend="italic">denunciation</hi>], and 2, owners of private lands who develop
                    the subsoil deposits in their lands within twenty years after the legislation,
                    will own such deposits in perpetuity; if such deposits are not developed within
                    that time they will become the property of the nation. I beg an immediate
                    consideration of the latter point by the Department with a view to early
                    instructions [regarding] any change suggested, if such legislation is not in
                    harmony with the Department’s desires or views, as it might be possible for me
                    to bring about some modification in the Senate respecting it. The evident aim of
                    the Colombian Congress is to enact legislation which will encourage capital and
                    at the same time force prompt development of resources, thus preventing the
                    holding up of these for development in the remote future.</p>
                <p>The most uncertain element as regards the petroleum situation is the nature of
                    the decision which will be handed down by the Supreme Court relative to the
                    constitutionality of the Executive decree of June 20 last.<note n="36"
                        xml:id="d753fn2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_765">p. 765</ref>.</note> If
                    this opinion should favor nationalization, it seems to me the Department’s
                    attitude regarding an agreement would be untenable; if the decision declares the
                    decree unconstitutional, as is expected, such an agreement as required might
                    probably be obtainable, though the sentiment of the country is against it
                    especially as a condition upon the treaty of 1914. It is not known when the
                    Supreme Court’s decision will be handed down, but presumably the proposed
                    petroleum legislation will be equally applicable whether it is against or for
                    nationalization.</p>
                <p>During a recent talk with the President, he repeated that he believes the
                    suggested agreement would be comparatively feasible if the <pb facs="0857"
                        n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/> treaty of 1914 were first ratified. But he is
                    strongly in favor of an arrangement by means of an exchange of notes or
                    declarations embodying an interpretation of the text of the treaty of 1846. This
                    procedure he believes would be entirely binding and could be carried out now as
                    it would not necessitate congressional action. The Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    informed me that he received a cable from the Minister at Washington concerning
                    proposed agreement but he did not enter into the details. …</p>
                <p>The Colombian Government is in a very difficult position regarding the treaty
                    negotiations with our Government and its embarrassment has been increased by the
                    Roncador complication<note n="37" xml:id="d753fn3">See <ref target="#pg_795">pp.
                            795</ref> ff.</note> which has inflamed public opinion here against the
                    United States.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
