<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>178. Letter From President Johnson to Chairman to Chairman Kosygin</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic arms</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recFUiQttKOsl6yXD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009928"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Strategic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="178"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                <head>178. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="from"
                        >Johnson</persName> to Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KAN1" type="to"
                        >Kosygin</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d178fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Rostow Files, <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>,
                        Box 10. Secret. The source text, which the President had cleared on January
                        14, was submitted for the President’s signature under cover of a January 23
                        memorandum from Rostow to the President.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-01-21">January 21, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Mr. Chairman:</p>
                <p>I have asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> to return to
                    the Soviet Union as my Ambassador<note n="2" xml:id="d178fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Llewellyn Thompson</persName> was appointed to
                        his second ambassadorship to the Soviet Union on October 13, 1966, and
                        presented his credentials on January 23, 1967.</note> because of the great
                    importance I attach to the improvement of relations between our two countries. I
                    have full confidence in him, and I hope that you and your colleagues will feel
                    as free to discuss our mutual problems with him as you would with me if we were
                    able to sit down together. I am, of course, always available to your Ambassador
                    here through the channel we have established, or directly whenever
                        necessary.<note n="3" xml:id="d178fn3">The special “channel” refers to a
                        direct line of communication first established in 1963 between <persName
                            corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> and President Kennedy through
                        which views on pressing issues were exchanged. Periodically during President
                            <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s administration, he
                        revived this channel to communicate directly with Chairman <persName
                            corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>. These communications were labeled
                        “Pen Pal Correspondence.”</note> I have arranged for Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> to have a channel of communication
                    which will be open only to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                    and myself.</p>
                <p>I have directed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> as a
                    matter of first priority to discuss with you and the appropriate members of your
                    Government the possibilities of reaching an understanding between us which would
                    curb the strategic arms race. I think you must realize that following the
                    deployment by you of an anti-ballistic missile system I face great pressures
                    from the Members of the Congress and from public opinion not only to deploy
                    defensive systems in this country, but also to increase greatly our capabilities
                    to penetrate any defensive systems which you might establish.</p>
                <p>If we should feel compelled to make such major increases in our strategic weapons
                    capabilities, I have no doubt that you would in turn <pb facs="0468" n="432"
                        xml:id="pg_432"/> feel under compulsion to do likewise. We would thus have
                    incurred on both sides colossal costs without substantially enhancing the
                    security of our own people or contributing to the prospects for a stable peace
                    in the world.</p>
                <p>I was accordingly glad to receive your message from Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d178fn4">See <ref target="#d174">Document 174</ref>.</note>
                    indicating that the Soviet Government is likewise concerned about this question.
                    We have no inflexible views as to how to proceed and would welcome yours.
                    Perhaps after Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> has
                    made an initial exploration of this matter with your Government, it may prove
                    desirable to have some of our highest authorities meet in Geneva or another
                    mutually agreeable place to carry the matter forward. Similarly, we have no
                    inflexible views as to the nature of an understanding between us. Our objective
                    should be a mutually acceptable and stable balance of forces, verifiable to the
                    maximum extent possible by our national means. I trust you will agree that this
                    is a question not only of the greatest importance but of considerable
                    urgency.</p>
                <p>May I express the hope that in the coming year peace will return to this troubled
                    world, and that we may find ways to cooperate in dealing with the problems that
                    face mankind today and for which our two countries, by their very size and
                    importance, carry a heavy responsibility.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lyndon B. Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
