<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>186. Oral Statement Delivered to the Ambassador to the Soviet Union
                    (Thompson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Missile defense</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="186"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                <head>186. Oral Statement Delivered to the Ambassador to the Soviet Union (<persName
                        corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d186fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File,
                        Intelligence File, Arms Control Messages Exchanged Between President
                            <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and Chairman, <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Vol. 1. No classification
                        marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-02-28"
                            >February 28, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">ORAL STATEMENT MADE TO AMBASSADOR THOMPSON FEBRUARY 28, 1967, RE:
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">KOSYGIN</persName>’S MESSAGE TO THE PRESIDENT OF
                    FEBRUARY 27, 1967<note n="2" xml:id="d186fn2">See <ref target="#d185">Document
                            185</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We note with satisfaction the agreement of the US Government with the opinion of
                    the Soviet side that the question concerning achievement of a mutual
                    understanding on anti-missile defense systems should be considered
                    simultaneously with the solution of the question of offensive nuclear delivery
                    means. Such a combined approach is in this case the only correct one, since it
                    would permit a real discussion of the broad objectives concerning both
                    containment of the arms race and disarmament.</p>
                <p>However, as can be understood from your statement, the American side proceeds
                    from the premise that as a point of departure for consideration of these
                    problems it is necessary to recognize the present strategic situation as “most
                    stable” and to seek to preserve it for the future. Unfortunately, <pb
                        facs="0488" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/> in real life such “stability” by no
                    means precludes the risk of nuclear conflict. This is especially true in the
                    present situation which is characterized by the existence of dangerous hotbeds
                    of international tension. A buildup of the means of nuclear attack which is
                    being carried out in the US and the militant mood of certain US allies which is
                    finding support among influential American circles further exacerbate the
                    tenseness of the situation.</p>
                <p>The presently existing strategic situation, which you call stable, has another
                    dangerous aspect. As a matter of fact, one can speak of the concept of
                    “stability” at any given moment only in very relative terms, as of a combination
                    and interaction of many factors which are understood differently by the parties.
                    Such “stability” creates in practice a situation where one party in providing
                    for its security is compelled, in response to the accelerated production and
                    accumulation of offensive strategic rocket-nuclear means by the other party, to
                    take steps for strengthening its defense capabilities, while the other party in
                    turn sees in this reason for moving to a new and higher level in the armaments
                    race spiral.</p>
                <p>We believe it necessary to find a way out of this vicious circle. This in our
                    view can be done only if we seek equally to ensure the security of each side
                    rather than attempt to solidify such a correlation of forces as this or that
                    party regards at a given moment to be advantageous to it. Such an approach, in
                    our view, would meet the interests not only of our countries but also of other
                    nations, and it would meet the interests of the world at large.</p>
                <p>It seems to us that the best way towards nuclear disarmament which would take
                    into account the considerations expressed above would be to destroy all
                    offensive weapons and, in any event, to reduce to a minimum the arsenals of
                    means for a rocket-nuclear attack, leaving—and then only temporarily—only
                    strictly limited amounts of such means. In such a case apparently no great
                    difficulties would arise for the solution of the anti-missile defense problem
                    either.</p>
                <p>In our view, it is important first of all to reach some common understanding with
                    regard to the approach itself to the solution of this problem, after which one
                    could move to a discussion of more specific questions.</p>
                <p>We would be prepared to consider any additional considerations which the American
                    side might wish to express on this matter. In this connection, we do not exclude
                    holding in the future, if it proves necessary, a special meeting or meetings of
                    our appropriate representatives for more detailed discussions of this entire
                    problem.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
