<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-02-28T08:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-02-28T08:45:00-05:00" n="187" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                    <head>187. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet
                            Union</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d187fn1">Source: Department of State, Pen
                            Pal Correspondence: Lot 77 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 163, Special
                                US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> File, Pen Pal Series, 1963.
                            Top Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-02-28T13:45:00+00:00">February 28, 1967,
                            1345Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>3682. Ref: Moscow 3674,<note n="2" xml:id="d187fn2">Telegram 3674, February
                            28, is the translation of <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>’s letter to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> (<ref target="#d185">Document 185</ref>). A copy
                            of the telegram is in Department of State, Pen Pal Correspondence: Lot
                            77 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 163, Special US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> File, Pen Pal Series, 1963.</note>,
                            3675,<note n="3" xml:id="d187fn3">Telegram 3675, February 28, is the
                            translation of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s oral
                            statement delivered in connection with <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>’s letter to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> (<ref target="#d186">Document
                                186</ref>). A copy of the telegram is in Department of State, Pen
                            Pal Correspondence: Lot 77 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 163, Special
                                US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> File, Pen Pal Series,
                            1963.</note> 3676.<note n="4" xml:id="d187fn4">In telegram 3676,
                            February 28, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>
                            noted that “at nine-thirty this morning <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> handed me <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>’s reply to President’s letter on <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>s and made some oral remarks.” In this
                            same telegram, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> inquired about the possibility of a Department
                            of State or White House response to <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s statement and he asked for press guidance. A
                            copy of the telegram is ibid.</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I interpret <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>’s letter
                            and <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s statement as effort
                            to establish good negotiating position rather than intention avoid
                            serious discussion. Although not spelled out, implicit in <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s remarks is Soviet
                            unwillingness to freeze present strategic balance which we have publicly
                            boasted is in our favor. This, however, is difficult for Soviets to
                            admit.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Possible approach to solution would be agreement by which Soviet would
                            maintain present <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> deployment around
                            Moscow, agree not to complete or activate other <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> launchers, and Soviets would be allowed to complete or
                            harden agreed number of additional launchers which number would still be
                            less than ours in view of their Moscow <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> deployment, larger territory and greater dispersal
                            their targets, large size some of their warheads, etc. Both sides would
                            be free to improve quality of their missiles. Since Soviets doubtless
                            have a number of missiles in their production pipeline, our agreement
                            for increase on their part would have some practical appeal. The
                            alternative of some decrease in our missiles would make it easier for
                            them to justify abstention from <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                            deployment and would have greater appeal to world opinion. If we decide
                            insist on deactivization Moscow complex they will probably demand parity
                            in number of launchers.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Best way to proceed to rapid agreement would be for us to present
                            concrete proposal but I realize this is difficult in view of uncertainty
                            about their present deployment <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>s.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>While would be useful to have expert assistance here, each step in
                            negotiation at this stage will have to be considered at top level here
                            which will be time consuming and I doubt if presence of expert yet
                            justified.</item>
                        <pb facs="0490" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>I trust that any public statement on our part will be confined to
                            announcement receipt of reply to President’s letter and fact that
                            discussions taking place in Moscow with no indication of position
                            taken.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Thompson</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>