<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>264. Paper Prepared by the Interagency Working Group</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d264</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">264</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="reckP3QiieAZd7kwE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003001255"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Launchers</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011308"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ballistic missiles</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recqaxqBsfTYVWHfR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034367"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cruise missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="264"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d264">
                <head>264. Paper Prepared by the Interagency Working Group<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d264fn1">Source: Johnson Library, <persName corresp="#p_CCM2"
                            >Clifford</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_KAN1"
                            >Kosygin</persName>-Talks with Soviet Union (2), Box 22. Top Secret;
                            <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. According to a memorandum from
                            <persName corresp="#p_FAS2">Fisher</persName> to the Executive Committee
                        of the Committee of Principals, July 31 (reproduced in Seaborg, Journal,
                        Vol. 26, pp. 341-342), this paper is a revision of an earlier draft sent to
                        the Executive Committee of the Committee of Principals on July 26. A copy of
                        the July 26 draft is in Johnson Library, <persName corresp="#p_CCM2"
                            >Clifford</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_KAN1"
                            >Kosygin</persName>-Talks with Soviet Union (2), Box 22. A revision of
                        the July 26 paper, marked “<gloss target="#t_ACDA1"
                        >ACDA</gloss>-2956/Rev.2,” dated July 30, and containing proposed
                        last-minute changes by <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>, is attached to a
                        memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SJP2">Shaw</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_G1">G</gloss>/PM) to <persName corresp="#p_BCE2"
                            >Bohlen</persName>, July 31, with recommendations on the positions
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName> should take on these
                        proposed changes at the interagency working group meeting that afternoon.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, DEF 12)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-07-31">July 31, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">STRATEGIC MISSILE TALKS PROPOSAL</p>
                <p>The elements of a U.S. proposal for the proposed U.S.-<gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> strategic missile talks are outlined below. This proposal
                    should be viewed as an entity since that is the basis on which it has been
                    evaluated.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">I. Fixed Land-Based <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>
                        Launchers</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The proposal would require cessation of the initiation of construction of any
                    additional strategic offensive land-based missile launchers as of September 1,
                    1968. The Soviet Union would be permitted to complete the launchers which it is
                    constructing as of that date. Beyond that date, however, it would not be allowed
                    to initiate further deployment of fixed <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>
                    launchers. Under no circumstances would either side be permitted to deploy more
                    than 1,200 <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss> launchers. Building of
                    additional silos, enlarging of existing silos, changing basic external
                    configuration of silos and other <pb facs="0696" n="660" xml:id="pg_660"/>
                    launchers, and the relocation of launchers would be prohibited. No additional
                    restrictions would be imposed upon technological improvements of launchers or
                    missiles already deployed including increasing the hardness of existing silos
                    and deployment of <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>’s, or the retrofitting
                    of existing launchers with new missiles.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">II. Fixed Land-Based IRBM/<gloss target="#t_MRBM1"
                            >MRBM</gloss> Launchers</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Further construction of fixed land-based launchers for IRBM/<gloss
                        target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss> (ranges greater than 1,000 km) would be
                    prohibited. The retrofitting of existing IRBM/<gloss target="#t_MRBM1"
                        >MRBM</gloss> launchers to accommodate <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>
                    missiles would be prohibited. The installation of <gloss target="#t_ICBM1"
                        >ICBM</gloss> missiles on IRBM/<gloss target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss>
                    launchers would be prohibited as would the conversion of IRBM/<gloss
                        target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss> missiles to <gloss target="#t_ICBM1"
                        >ICBM</gloss> missiles. Building of additional silos, enlarging of existing
                    silos, changing basic external configuration of silos and other launchers and
                    the relocation of launchers would be prohibited. No additional restrictions
                    would be imposed upon technological improvements of launchers or missiles
                    already deployed or the retrofitting of existing launchers with new missiles of
                    intermediate or medium range.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">III. Mobile Land-Based Strategic Offensive Missile
                        Systems</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The proposal would impose a complete ban on the deployment of mobile land-based,
                    strategic offensive missile systems (ranges greater than 1,000 km). Missile
                    systems with such ranges carried by waterborne vehicles on inland waterways
                    would also be prohibited. Any such existing systems would be destroyed.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">IV. Mobile Sea-Based Strategic Offensive Missile Systems</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>The proposal would ban the construction of additional strategic offensive
                        missile launching submarines or of additional launchers in existing
                        submarines. This prohibition should apply to all submarines with ballistic
                        missile or cruise missile launchers. Such submarines under construction as
                        of September 1, 1968, could be completed, subject to agreement on their
                        number. There would be no limitation on the characteristics of SLBMs or
                        SLCMs, or on retrofitting missile submarines with new or larger missiles of
                        the type with which they are equipped. The fitting out of surface ships with
                        facilities for firing offensive ballistic missiles would be
                        prohibited.</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>There would be no replacement of ballistic or cruise missile submarines
                        within the first five years of the agreement. During that period the two
                        sides would undertake to reach agreement on rules governing subsequent
                        replacement of submarines. In the absence of a supplementary agreement on
                        such rules, each side may replace submarines after five years from the date
                        of the initiation of the agreement provided that replacement does not
                        increase the total number of submarines or of submarine-launched ballistic
                        missiles or cruise missiles.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">V. <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>s</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The proposal would ban the deployment of more than a set and equal number of
                    fixed, land-based anti-ballistic missile launchers and associated radars. A
                    total prohibition on deployment of mobile <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                    systems, both land-based and sea-based, would be imposed. There would be no
                    other constraints on the characteristics of the <gloss target="#t_ABM1"
                        >ABM</gloss> systems deployed.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">VI. Aircraft and Anti-aircraft Systems</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The proposal would not include limitations on aircraft or anti-aircraft
                    systems.</p>
                <pb facs="0697" n="661" xml:id="pg_661"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">VII. Technological Improvements</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There would be no prohibition of technological improvement within the constraints
                    of the agreement.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">VIII. Verification</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The limitations described in paragraphs I through V are proposed to be verified
                    by national means.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">IX. Provisions for Revision and Withdrawal</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>Either party may propose revision of the agreement if it believes that
                        conditions affecting the agreement have changed. The two parties shall meet
                        from time to time to discuss the operation of the agreement and possible
                        revisions.</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>Ten years after entry into force of this agreement the two parties shall
                        meet for a formal review of the operation of the agreement with a view to
                        assuring that the purposes of the agreement, with any revisions that may
                        have been made during the 10-year period, are being realized. In the absence
                        of agreement by the two parties on the continued operation of the agreement
                        with necessary revisions, either party may withdraw by giving six months
                        notice prior to 11 years from the day of entry into force of the agreement.
                        Otherwise, the agreement shall be automatically renewed for another ten
                        years, at which time this review procedure shall be repeated.</item>
                    <label>C.</label>
                    <item>Either party shall in exercising its national sovereignty have the right
                        to withdraw from the agreement at any time if it decides that extraordinary
                        events, related to the subject matter of the agreement, have jeopardized the
                        supreme interests of its country.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
