<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>293. Summary Notes of the 594th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-11-25T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-11-25T13:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic arms</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recadKg9AQii6mb77" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Arms talks</term>
                    <term ref="reccfPriXIHvxyBuS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Arms buildup</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-11-25T13:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-11-25T12:00:00-05:00" n="293"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d293">
                <head>293. Summary Notes of the 594th Meeting of the National Security Council<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d293fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings File, Vol. 5,
                        Tab 76, Box 2. Secret; Sensitive. Drafted by Bromley Smith.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1968-11-25T12:00:00-05:00" to="1968-11-25T13:20:00-05:00">November
                            25, 1968, noon–1:20 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of monetary issues, Vietnam, and current problems before
                    the United Nations.]</p>
                <pb facs="0776" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/>
                <p>[Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJR1">Wiggins</persName>:] d. Disarmament—The
                    issue now is the continuation of the conference of non-nuclear powers.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d293fn2">See <ref target="#d284">Documents 284</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d286">286</ref>.</note> Our position is to oppose a permanent
                    body to deal with this issue. As to the talks on strategic arms limitations, the
                    Soviets have made mention of these talks but we have been non-responsive.</p>
                <p>The President: What should we do about conducting talks on strategic arms
                    limitation? We have the Czech situation, a new Administration coming in and
                    there is uncertainty as to the possibility of achieving anything in such
                    talks.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJR1">Wiggins</persName>: We should proceed with
                    the talks. There is no problem about conducting a parallel policy—attacking the
                    Russians for their invasion of Czechoslovakia each morning and each afternoon
                    talking about strategic arms limitations.</p>
                <p>The President: The President-elect has slowed down Senate ratification of the
                    non-proliferation treaty. Can we accomplish anything in strategic arms talks if
                    we do not have the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> ratified?</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJR1">Wiggins</persName>: We can accomplish
                    something because the Russians are eager to undertake the arms talks. The
                    Russians are embarrassed by criticism of the Czech invasion. They want to
                    undertake arms talks in order to draw attention away from the Czech issue.
                    However, we should not propose a special Senate session to ratify the
                    non-proliferation treaty.</p>
                <p>The President: Ratification to the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> has a
                    bearing on the strategic arms talks. The Congressional leaders will be coming
                    here this evening to discuss whether or not to hold a special session.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d293fn3">No record of this conversation has been found.
                        However, in a memorandum to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName>, November 25 at 11 p.m., Rostow proposed talking
                        points for a message to President-elect Nixon. Among other things, Rostow’s
                        draft message indicated President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> had decided to “leave the <gloss target="#t_NPT1"
                            >NPT</gloss> to the opening days of the next session of Congress in
                        January, at the earliest. (Both <persName corresp="#p_DEMK1"
                            >Dirksen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>
                        think this would be wiser than calling a special session.)” (Johnson
                        Library, National Security File, Memos to the President, Rostow, Vol. 108,
                        Box 43R)</note> The Germans have been softened up by recent actions in the
                    monetary crisis but we have no leverage on them to ratify the <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> because we have not yet ratified. The same
                    situation is involved with Israel. We have given them the Phantom airplanes but
                    this may not be useful in getting them to accept the <gloss target="#t_NPT1"
                        >NPT</gloss> unless we have already ratified. In India and Japan, those
                    opposing the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> can argue that their countries
                    should not act on the treaty before we do.</p>
                <p>Delaying ratification until the new Senate arrives may mean that the ratification
                    of the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> is in doubt. The composition of the
                    Senate will be different. Senators <persName corresp="#p_CCM2">Clark</persName>
                    and Morse will be out and Goldwater will be in. <pb facs="0777" n="741"
                        xml:id="pg_741"/> Senator <persName corresp="#p_WJR1">Russell</persName> is
                    in doubt about the treaty and his doubts may grow. Unless we act in December, we
                    may run into trouble.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJR1">Wiggins</persName>: It is embarrassing in
                    the United Nations to be able to say only that we think we will ratify the
                    treaty. It would be wonderful if the treaty were ratified.</p>
                <p>The President: Asked for a paper summarizing the attitudes in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as reported by Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_WJR1">Wiggins</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d293fn4">Not
                        further identified.</note>
                    <persName>Bob Murphy</persName> has been told that we believe we ought to go
                    ahead with the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> now.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d293fn5">On November 15, President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> announced that President-elect Nixon had designated
                        Robert D. Murphy, former Deputy Under Secretary of State for Political
                        Affairs, to serve as his liaison with the White House and as observer at the
                        Department of State. See <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents
                            of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B.
                                Johnson</persName>, 1968-69</hi>, Book II, p. 1126.</note> It is
                    true the Senators didn’t want to come back for a special session. The Czech
                    invasion blew up earlier plans for the arms talks. We should get started even if
                    we handle the talks so as not to bind a successor. It is our hope that Mr.
                        <persName>Nixon</persName> will agree to our going ahead and we have offered
                    to have <persName>Bob Murphy</persName> as an observer on the delegation.</p>
                <p>Secretary Fowler:<note n="6" xml:id="d293fn6">
                        <persName>Henry H. Fowler</persName>, Secretary of the Treasury.</note> The
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting at Brussels changed the
                    thinking of Europeans. The European situation is different after the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting as regards their doubt about
                    bilateral or US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> arms talks.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CCM2">Clifford</persName>: It is clear that
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members do not want to return to the
                    cold war. Their concern was that a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> arms
                    buildup might upset the movement toward detente. The <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> meeting was delayed almost to the point where the Soviet
                    invasion could not be fully exploited in an effort to get them to increase their
                    defense contribution. Most of the Soviet divisions are now out of Czechoslovakia
                    and the threat to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members is, in their
                    minds, less than it was a few weeks ago. However, <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> members would welcome US-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    arms talks.</p>
                <p>The President: State Department officials had told him the arms talks would cause
                    trouble with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members. Secretary Rusk
                    believed that talks would trouble our allies. President-elect Nixon said we
                    should delay the talks because of the Czech invasion. A paper was requested
                    giving all the reasons why the talks should or should not be held which he could
                    use in a conversation with Senator <persName corresp="#p_DEMK1"
                        >Dirksen</persName>.<note n="7" xml:id="d293fn7">Not further
                        identified.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CCM2">Clifford</persName>: The Germans and
                    British want us to go ahead with the arms talk. They are prepared to have us
                    take the calculated risk that things will quiet down in Czechoslovakia. The rest
                    of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members want us to go ahead but
                    they do not want us to ask them whether we should go ahead.</p>
                <pb facs="0778" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/>
                <p>The President: <persName>Bob Murphy</persName> has been told that a meeting with
                    the Russians might persuade the Soviets to pressure Egypt on the Middle East
                    problem and Hanoi on the Vietnam problem.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CCM2">Clifford</persName>: As to whether a
                    special session on the <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> should be called, we
                    must make a very careful nose count before deciding. There is real concern that
                    the Senate might refuse to ratify the treaty. Senators would resent a special
                    session whereas to the arms talks, such talks would help advance in the <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> here and abroad.</p>
                <p>The President: We should tell the new Administration the facts of life and then
                    they will have to take responsibility.</p>
                <p>[Here follows brief discussion of other U.N. issues.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
