<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                    <head>91. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d91fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 18-3. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">Foster</persName>. This conversation took place in
                            the Hotel des Bergues.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-08-01">August 1,
                                1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>U.K. Draft Treaty</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CL2">Lord Chalfont</persName>, U.K.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_FWC2">William C. Foster</persName>, USDel/<gloss target="#t_ENDC1">ENDC</gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>At <persName corresp="#p_CL2">Lord Chalfont</persName>’s request, I received
                        him in my apartment at the des Bergues at 4:30 today. He said that the
                        purpose of his visit was to make it clear that his government felt that it
                        must table its present draft treaty with respect to the major articles on
                        nuclear arrangements. Although appreciative of U.S. attempts to find
                        compromise language which would reduce German and Italian opposition to
                        their present language, his government felt that the statements of Prime
                        Minister <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> in December were so
                        explicit on this subject that any backing away from that would be political
                        suicide. They also believed that their formulation was the best possible in
                        order truly to limit the spread of nuclear weapons. He said he recognized
                        that our position is difficult in attempting to develop a European consensus
                        and that as we had said in the Western Four meeting, our suggestions were
                        probably as far as we could go in attempting to help achieve this consensus.
                        He again stated that they had no objection to our proposed safeguards
                        clause, nor to our concern about early tabling of any assurance clause. He
                        said his government would be willing to make some concessions toward the
                        Canadian draft in order to attract Canadian support.<note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">See <ref target="#d85fn2">Document 85, footnote
                            2</ref>.</note> While he recognized our difficulties with the proposed
                        Canadian withdrawal clause including the possible submission of problems and
                        decisions to the Security Council, he felt that they could accept the
                        Canadian formulation to obtain Canadian support.</p>
                    <p>I expressed our disappointment that our suggestions could not be accepted,
                        particularly since he had heard the strong objections to the U.K.
                        formulation of the Germans and the Italians, at Paris and here.</p>
                    <p>I inquired whether some general language which avoided the specific problem
                        of <gloss target="#t_ANF1">ANF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>
                        and the majority vote would allow them to change their current position. He
                        said that they had considered this but believed that so much legal ingenuity
                        had been expended in getting where we are that there is little hope for this
                        as a promising course.</p>
                    <pb facs="0270" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/>
                    <p>He said that he and his government had perhaps misread what they thought were
                        signals as to U.S. position as set forth in my <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> article,<note n="3" xml:id="d91fn3">Foreign Affairs, July
                            1965, pp. 587-601; annotated in <hi rend="italic">Documents on
                                Disarmament, 1965</hi>, pp. 265-280.</note> the Kennedy speech<note n="4" xml:id="d91fn4">Reference presumably is to a speech by Senator
                            Robert F. Kennedy (D-NY); not further identified.</note> and what he
                        characterized as a leak of the <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName> report.<note n="5" xml:id="d91fn5">
                            <ref target="#d64">Document 64</ref>.</note> From those alleged signals
                        they had concluded that the U.S. Government was assigning top priority to
                        non-proliferation, even as against the necessity for achievement of an
                            <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ANF1">ANF</gloss>.
                        In view of that, he believed they may recently have promised too much too
                        soon in the House of Commons and with the press, all of which may have
                        caused much of the present embarrassing differences between the allies. I
                        conceded that he might be right as to the embarrassment. I also said that
                        non-proliferation continued to have top priority with us but that we also
                        continued to support our basic commitments on <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ANF1">ANF</gloss>. Until after the German
                        election, at least, any discussion in this field is very difficult for the
                        present German government. This political problem for the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> was much like his own estimate of his
                        proposal as being essential for the political health of his own
                        government.</p>
                    <p>In an attempt to find a possible way out of this dilemma, I inquired whether
                        the speculation which I had heard from some source, which source I did not
                        recall, as to their possible willingness, although admittedly reluctant, to
                        accept as amendments our Articles I, II, and IV, after a U.K. treaty had
                        been tabled. He said that this offered possibilities, and if they could
                        table their present draft with some possible Canadian amendments and
                        possibly the safeguard clause added, then we or one of our allies, or even
                        one of the non-aligned, might offer U.S. amendments and they could (in what
                        could be made to appear reluctantly) accept the amendments. They then would
                        have carried out their political commitment.</p>
                    <p>I said that this appeared to have possibilities and it might be that we could
                        advise our allies that we still did not like Articles I, II and III, of the
                        U.K. draft, as we have already informed the British. However, by agreement,
                        we could perhaps publicly commend the British for their initiative but
                        stating in low key that we would have to give more thought to their
                        formulation since it had features which we felt were not the wisest. We
                        would need to discuss such a statement with our allies before presenting it,
                        so that each could weigh the political consequences, and, indeed, we would
                        need to develop a scenario that could help answer many of our problems. I
                        said that I hoped the British had also considered the political cost of
                        appearing to diverge from a unified position with the U.S., both in <pb facs="0271" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> terms of cohesion of the alliance
                        and in terms of possible attacks from their conservative opponents at home.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CL2">Lord Chalfont</persName> said he recognized
                        this problem and hoped that any public evidence of the differences could be
                        minimal.</p>
                    <p>In concluding, he asked that our discussion and his personal tentative
                        favorable reaction to this sort of plan be kept in the closest confidence
                        while he discussed it back home as he presumed I would do also. I told him
                        that I would only discuss it with Washington and with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BG5">Bunn</persName> here in view of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BG5">Bunn</persName>’s participation in treaty activities.
                        He said that he would discuss it only with his associate, Sir
                            <persName>Harold Beeley</persName>, and that we could consult again
                        later in the week when we had word back from home.</p>
                    <p>He raised the question of the Italian position. I said we had not heard, but
                        we both agreed that if we and the U.K. and probably the Canadians, agreed
                        with the plan, and also the Germans came along, that the Italians could
                        undoubtedly be persuaded also to accept.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>