<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 116.Mr. Williamson to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="118"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                <head>No. 116.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williamson</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation in Central America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-07-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 27, 1874</date>. (Received September
                        9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 194.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your instruction No. 79, I have the
                    honor to inform you, that yesterday afternoon the council of war, composed of
                    the chief officers of the army of Guatemala, over which Ex-President Grenados
                    presided, concluded the trial of Gonzales and his confederate, Bulnes. The
                    sentence of the court was, that the former should be degraded from his rank, be
                    forever prohibited from holding any office of honor or profit in Guatemala, and
                    be imprisoned for five years. The latter’s sentence was the same in all
                    respects, except that he is imprisoned for two years. Both have appealed to the
                    supreme court of war, which is a civil tribunal for the final trial of military
                    cases, and is composed of the same judges who constitute the supreme court of
                    justice; so I am informed by the prime minister.</p>
                <p>As instructed by you, I communicated both to the minister of foreign affairs and
                    to the prime minister that the Government of the United States felt “that the
                    civilization of the age, and the immunity which the intercourse of governments
                    exacts for their representatives in other lands,” gave it the right to expect
                    the stern visitation of the law upon <pb facs="0272" n="176" xml:id="pg_176"/>
                    the perpetrators of the outrage upon Vice-Consul Magee. Both of them professed
                    to receive the declaration as an evidence of the friendly interest which the
                    United States takes in the welfare of Guatemala.</p>
                <p>To-day the prime minister told me he thought the sentence of the court was too
                    lenient as to Gonzalez. He also stated the supreme court of war had the right to
                    change the sentence and increase the punishment, and that the government would
                    use its influence to have it do so. It is perhaps a coincidence that no steps
                    (so far as I can learn) were taken to bring Gonzalez to trial until it became
                    known the British dispatch war steamer Petrel had landed at San José with
                    dispatches for the English chargé, and that the British Pacific squadron had
                    been ordered to rendezvous at Panama.</p>
                <p>The British chargé is very indignant at the sentence of the court, and has
                    expressed to me and the French chargé his determination to notify the government
                    of Guatemala that he considers the protocol annulled. He takes the ground that
                    the punishment is totally inadequate to the offense, and that the government of
                    Guatemala has shown its <hi rend="italic">mala fides</hi> by permitting the
                    smallest puishment to be imposed upon the accused that the law allows.</p>
                <p>* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>He says, moreover, that such a punishment in Guatemala would be a farce, and that
                    even if the supreme court does not reverse the sentence, or the president pardon
                    the criminals in a few months, they will become heroes, instead of being
                    degraded, in the eyes of the public.</p>
                <p>In this opinion I fully concur with him. In any country where there are
                    guarantees that the punishment would be inflicted according to the sentence, it
                    would seem to be sufficiently heavy.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. WILLIAMSON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
