<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-07-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="147" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                    <head>No. 145.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-07-07"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 7, 1874</date>.
                            (Received September 1.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to send you the documents and
                        reports (inclosures 1 to 12) connected with the recent trial at Chefoo,
                        growing out <pb facs="0371" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/> of the attack made by
                        the people of Chi-mi on an American missionary, Rev. H. Corbett, residing
                        there. I have not heretofore sent you any of the papers connected with this
                        affair, since at no time was it possible to indicate the result; and you
                        have now the whole story. Mr. Sheppard’s report (inclosure 8) furnishes so
                        full an account of the origin, progress, and results of the disturbance, and
                        of the steps taken to induce the intendant at Chefoo to bring the offenders
                        to justice, with the details of their trial and punishment, and subsequent
                        indemnity for Mr. Corbett’s losses, and his return to Chi-mi, that I shall
                        not attempt to add anything to it.</p>
                    <p>As soon as the leading particulars of the assault were received from Mr.
                        Corbett, (inclosure 1,) Mr. Cornabé, our consular agent at Chefoo, made them
                        known to the intendant, (or taotai, as he is usually called by foreigners,)
                        and continued to give him the subsequent details of outrages suffered by the
                        native Christians, at Chi-mi, urging him to uphold law and order by the
                        arrest and punishment of the guilty. I inclose only one of his replies,
                        (inclosure 4,) for the whole correspondence will not interest you; and this
                        specimen is enough to show the manner in which the simplest statements can
                        be misrepresented when it serves the end of the officials to shirk their
                        duty. The most noticeable thing in it is the charge brought against the
                        convert Wang Li-tung, of an attempt to kidnap a child for the Roman Catholic
                        Church; but this allegation was so barefaced and unfounded that it was not
                        even referred to on the trial, much less attempted to be proved against him,
                        as soon as it was found that he was a Protestant. Nothing of this kind had
                        ever been done in that region, and the local officials trumped up the
                        charge, most probably because it would be readily believed elsewhere.</p>
                    <p>As soon as the report of these things reached me, six weeks after their date,
                        (for our communication with Chefoo is slow in winter,) I brought it to the
                        notice of the foreign office, which immediately sent a copy of my complaint
                        to the governor of Shan-tung. (Inclosure 2.) As soon as more precise details
                        were received, I also desired Mr. Sheppard to take charge of the case,
                        which, it was plain, would require much patience and decision to bring to a
                        satisfactory end. (Inclosure 7.) At the first interview which they had, the
                        intendant evidently looked upon the affair as having no serious
                        importance—probably, among other reasons, because there was no loss of
                        life—and wished to regard it as already in effect settled. (Inclosure 8.)
                        This being the case, and full evidence of his disinclination to uphold the
                        treaty being received, I again brought the affair to the notice of the
                        foreign office, urging that there was no reason for this tardy action; and
                        received a reply that he would be told to attend to its adjudication, which
                        was immediately done, as he himself acknowledges in his subsequent report.
                        (Inclosures 5 and 6.)</p>
                    <p>This report of the intendant is an interesting document when read in
                        connection with his reply of February 7 to Mr. Cornabé and Mr. Sheppard’s
                        dispatch. In it he undertakes to explain away, or else admits, every charge
                        which he at first declared was unfounded. The previous portion of that
                        correspondence had probably been sent to his superiors, and it was now
                        necessary to exhibit a degree of diligence in maintaining the peace in
                        Chi-mi, by proving the falsity of some charges which were never made. His
                        proclamation (inclosure 9) will be regarded with some respect for a time,
                        and the native Christians can appeal to it as upholding their right to adopt
                        a faith so different from most of their countrymen. Since Mr. Corbett’s
                        return, though he himself is treated with respect, it is reported that his
                        brethren still suffer contumely and are <pb facs="0372" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/> shunned, but nothing worse than hard words seems to
                        have yet been experienced.</p>
                    <p>One thing is observable in this trial. No evil conduct was charged against
                        the native Christians by their countrymen, and no excuse was offered by them
                        for cutting down their fruit-trees, robbing their houses, or assaulting and
                        wounding them, except that they were followers of a foreign faith. A
                        testimony of this kind to their blameless living can hardly fail to have a
                        beneficial effect in that region, and the report of these things in other
                        parts of Shan-tung will perhaps tend to restrain future outbreaks. The
                        circulation of news is not very rapid in the inland parts of the province,
                        especially among the agricultural and laboring classes; but the notoriety of
                        the trial, and the willingness of the intendant to do justice in punishing
                        his guilty countryman for acts done to a foreigner, will, it may be hoped,
                        give this an exceptional influence for good.</p>
                    <p>Another thing may also be referred to. The intendant is very careful in his
                        report (inclosure 11), to particularize certain charges of ill-usage
                        suffered by converts at Chi-mi, contained in Mr. Cornabe’s letters to him,
                        and to state that they had all been ruled out of court as not being under
                        its jurisdiction, adding that this was done with the full consent of the
                        United States consul. He alludes to this right of the Chinese government to
                        exercise exclusive jurisdiction over its own subjects, in the proclamation
                        issued to be posted in Chi-mi; and it is a point on which the authorities
                        are becoming more and more sensitive, especially in reference to missionary
                        operations. In that proclamation he quotes the twenty-ninth article of the
                        treaty, and then sets forth most distinctly the independent jurisdiction of
                        each nation over its own subjects. This distinction appears easy enough in
                        theory, but even some of our best-informed countrymen appear to have come to
                        the conclusion that because the article says that those who peaceably teach
                        and practice Christianity shall not be molested, it involves the right to
                        compel the Chinese to take up the cudgels when their own people are molested
                        for professing Christianity.</p>
                    <p>The result which has been attained in this trial is owing mainly to the
                        decision and perseverance of Mr. Sheppard in asking only for the rights
                        guaranteed by the treaty, and convincing the intendant that he must maintain
                        them and punish the guilty before the case would be dropped. He was
                        materially assisted by the missionaries at Chetbo in translating and
                        interpreting, and the list of the men concerned in the attacks on Mr.
                        Corbett furnished by the native converts, with their evidence of the part
                        each one took in the acts of violence, was of material advantage in fixing
                        the guilt on the right persons. I would respectfully suggest that Mr.
                        Sheppard’s action in this case may receive your special approval.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Statement of Rev. H. Corbett.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-12-22"><hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 22,
                                    1873</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>On the 1st of December, as I was passing through the market-town of
                            Hwa-yin, about forty li south of the city of Chi-mi, I was followed by a
                            crowd of men attending the theatre there, who attacked me with stones,
                            crying out at the same time “Hit him,” “hit him;” and “Kill him,” “kill
                            him.” Returning in the evening, and passing by the same place, the crowd
                            rushed forward to meet me, fully occupying the road on both sides, and
                            leaving but a narrow passage for me in the middle. When I came up to
                            them <pb facs="0373" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/> I saw that several of the
                            men had stones in their hands, which they threw at me, hitting me in
                            several places and injuring also my horse. I urged my horse forward with
                            all possible speed, but the men pursued me quite outside the town. On
                            the following day I went with my passport to the local magistrate,
                            stating the above facts. He promised to investigate the matter, and that
                            he would see to it that I had no further difficulty in the future. On
                            the second day he issued a proclamation for the purpose of restraining
                            the people, which he sent to me to read. The proclamation stated that
                            foreigners had a perfect right, according to the treaty, to propagate
                            their religion in the interior. In it the district magistrate also
                            stated that he had received special instructions from his superior
                            officer to afford protection to all persons propagating their religion
                            according to the treaty. On the same day I went to the town of Hwa-yin,
                            and learned that the proclamation had not been posted. I then wrote to
                            the magistrate informing him of this fact, and begging that he would
                            attend to this matter immediately, for fear that by being neglected it
                            would grow worse, and stating that there were other villagers who had
                            formerly received me cordially who did not now dare to hold intercourse
                            with me. In consequence of this several proclamations were posted in
                            different places, the magistrate thus far fulfilling his promises, but
                            failing to apprehend or punish any one. Yesterday, on the 19th of the
                            month, I, with several native Christians, went to the yuh-hwang temple
                            fair, which is about thirty li south of the city. On approaching the
                            place a great many men ran to meet us. There was such a crowd and uproar
                            that I did not attempt to preach or distribute books, but only
                            endeavored to conciliate and quiet the people. I was suddenly attacked
                            again on all sides with stones, by which I was struck several times. I
                            then ran into the temple to escape from danger. The crowd rushed in
                            after me, filling the temple and the court, and stones were hurled at me
                            from all directions, both inside and outside. While I was in the temple
                            for a few moments, thinking how I could best escape, the mob only
                            increased, and I determined to run the risk of forcing my way, if
                            possible, through the people. As I rushed out the people followed me in
                            crowds, but fortunately for me a few men behind me fell down, thus
                            blocking up the way for a moment and giving me barely time to mount my
                            horse and gallop off. The people followed, pelting me with stones and
                            clods of earth; some of the native Christians seized hold of a few of
                            the leaders, restraining them for an instant, thus further facilitating
                            my escape. I urged on my horse and got out of the way, followed by a
                            shower of stones. After my escape the people sought out and fell to
                            beating the native Christians. One old man was severely wounded by a
                            stone, so that he could not walk, and was carried to the house of a
                            friend to have his wounds attended to, being unable to get to his home,
                            though it was not far off. Another person was knocked down by a stone,
                            which cut a large gash on his head. Others received wounds more or less
                            severe. The people continued in a state of lawlessness, and there is
                            reason to fear that the mere issuing of proclamations will be
                            insufficient to restore order.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">ministers of the foreign
                            office</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-06"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 6,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: I have heard it reported that Mr.
                            Corbett, an American missionary, who had been desired by the Christians
                            of Chi-mi, in Shantung, to come and preach to them, and had lived there
                            quietly for some months without any difficulty arising, teaching the
                            converts at their request the doctrines of the Scriptures, suddenly
                            became the object of the suspicions of the people. In December, hearing
                            that several hundred reckless men were out against him, and being aware
                            of it, he escaped with his children and got away; but the riotous people
                            then surrounded and burst into his house, destroying his books and
                            things utterly. Mr. Corbett happily reached Chefoo without suffering any
                            violence himself.</p>
                        <p>As this case is one which, if not thoroughly investigated, will, it is to
                            be feared, grow into something very serious, I make it known to your
                            excellencies, with the hope that orders may be sent to the proper
                            authorities in Shantung to fully inquire into and learn the causes of
                            this disturbance in that region, with the grounds of the popular
                            suspicion, so that the affair may be equitably judged and settled. This
                            is highly important.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself of this occasion to wish your excellencies the highest
                            happiness.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0374" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                            44.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Ministers of foreign
                                    office</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                                     gregorian" when="1874-02-24"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tungchi</hi>, 13<hi rend="italic">th year,</hi> 1<hi rend="italic">st moon,</hi>
                                        8<hi rend="italic">th day</hi>, (February 24,
                                1874.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>The members of the foreign office return their compliments.</p>
                        <p>Your excellency’s note, giving the report respecting an American
                            missionary at Chi-mi in Shantung, has been received, in which you state
                            that in December last several hundreds of reckless men were out against
                            him, but being aware of it he escaped with his children, while his house
                            was afterward surrounded and broken into, and his books and things
                            utterly destroyed.</p>
                        <p>We have now to state that orders have been sent to the governor of
                            Shantung to direct that a thorough investigation be made into this
                            affair, with a view to its equitable adjudication and settlement; and
                            when his report of the proceedings taken is received, we will have the
                            honor of again addressing you and making known what has been done.</p>
                        <p>With the present reply we take the opportunity of wishing you every
                            happiness.</p>
                        <closer>Cards of
                            <signed>WÂNSIANG</signed>,<lb/><signed>PAO-YUN</signed>,<lb/>And seven
                            other members of the foreign office.<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">S.
                                    Wells Williams</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Chargé
                                    d’Affaires</hi>.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No.
                            44.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Taotai</gloss> to <persName type="to">W. A. Cornabé</persName>, United States
                                vice-consul.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-07"><hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi> 7,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The day after starting for the provincial capital, on public business, I
                            had the honor to receive your dispatch, stating that you had been
                            informed by the Rev. H. Corbett that the people of Chi-mi had collected
                            a mob and assaulted him, and requesting me to inquire into the matter. I
                            also received your letter stating that he had further informed you that
                            the people there had collected 300 men for the purpose of injuring him,
                            and had also carried off his donkey, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>While I was purposing to investigate this affair, I received the report
                            of the magistrate of Chi-mi, stating “that on the 1st December, at the
                            market-town of Hwa-yin, during a theatrical play, a native named Wang
                            Li-tung, there present, in front of the Yuh-hwang temple, seized a child
                            of thirteen years, called Li-San-man, crying out that he wished to take
                            it to the Tien-chu-tang (Roman Catholic church) to enter the faith. The
                            child screamed, and the crowd at the theater, moved by a common
                            resentment, rescued it. Wang Li-tung then proceeded to drag from the
                            ground a man called Kiang Kwan-kih, but the crowd rushed forward and
                            pursued him, while he, leading on a number of men, resorted to violence.
                            Fortunately the men at the theater were many, and succeeded in
                            reclaiming also Kiang Kwan-kih.” Thus this native Chinese dares in open
                            day to kidnap children, and then requests that the matter be
                            investigated. (Original obscure.) I suppose that this affair is the one
                            referred to in your dispatch. What a discrepancy between these two
                            representations!</p>
                        <p>When foreign missionaries propagate their doctrines in the interior,
                            their intercourse with the natives should be peaceable, and friendly
                            relations be maintained. In the present affair it is evident that both
                            parties were to blame, and each of them has told its partial story,
                            hoping that it would be believed. Seeing that it concerns the
                            intercourse between this and foreign nations, we must carefully
                            discriminate between the false and the true, and follow up the matter
                            (to a settlement) so as to insure peace in future.</p>
                        <p>On my departure from Chefoo I designated Wang Shin-jin, an expectant
                            prefect, to go at once to Chi-mi, and, in connection with the
                            magistrate, examine the matter and report to me. On my return to
                            Lai-chau he reported to me that the origin of this affray was really
                            found to be this: A great many people were assembled at the theater, and
                            Mr. Corbett brought his three children to enjoy themselves there. The
                            people were not familiar with the sight of foreign children, and
                            gathered around to look at them, which Mr. Corbett opposed by sharply
                            rebuking them. In consequence of this the crowd increased, and he took
                            his children and left. There was certainly no such thing as attacking
                            and stoning him.</p>
                        <p>It was simply that the convert Wang Li-tung seized hold of a child at the
                            theater, named Li San-man, and was carrying him off, as he said, to have
                            him join the church. <pb facs="0375" n="279" xml:id="pg_279"/> The child
                            screamed and resisted, but Wang, holding it firmly, was running away,
                            when the people at the theater, moved by a common indignation, rushed
                            forward and rescued it. Wang then led on a company of men and began to
                            fight; both sides refused to yield, and men received wounds from each
                            other.</p>
                        <p>In regard to a mob gathering at Chi-mi, it was because the people were
                            incensed by seeing Wang Li-tung trying to force people to enter the
                            religion, and came to the city to institute a suit and stop such
                            proceedings. This affair occurred when many candidates were gathered for
                            the examination; but beside this there was no other assemblage of the
                            people.</p>
                        <p>In regard to Sü Yin-tsoh going to Ko-fau and carrying off a cow and an
                            ass, I learned that Mr. Corbett had a house there, and when he returned
                            to Chefoo he left these animals and sundry articles in charge of an
                            assistant named Lin Lung-méi. Many people in the neighborhood, hearing
                            of this attempt at forcible proselytizing, went to Mr. Corbett’s house
                            to inquire into the matter; but really, his goods were none of them
                            carried off. His cow and ass broke the ropes which held them and ran
                            away to the hills, seeking for food, but there was no such thing as
                            leading them away. The magistrate had them found and brought back, and
                            delivered to Lin. These things can all be proved by evidence. Just now
                            there is no gathering among the people to create disturbance.</p>
                        <p>In looking at this whole affair (says the Taotai) in reference to
                            foreigners going into the interior to propagate Christianity, it is well
                            understood that those who preach it and those who adopt it are to
                            receive the same protection as other people, but no permission can be
                            given them to force others to enter it. Now, when Wang Li-tung violently
                            dragged away this child he began an incipient rebellion—a thing much to
                            be detested; and such village brawls cannot be allowed to extend. All
                            the parties concerned in this affair ought to be summoned before the
                            magistrate for a thorough judicial investigation and settlement.</p>
                        <p>On my return (to Chefoo) I directed the same Wang Shin-jin to return to
                            Chi-mi and make known these instructions. I am informed that the people
                            there desire to settle this matter, and that when Mr. Corbett comes back
                            they will treat him in the most friendly manner; no similar disturbance
                            shall again arise, and they beg that further judicial proceedings may be
                            stayed. In the disturbance which arose at the theater, it appears that
                            no man took the lead; and it would be difficult to summon £he real
                            persons (who caused it.) Much of what is reported is false. Since there
                            is a willingness to settle the affair and resume friendly relations, it
                            is advisable to stop all litigation. This would be of advantage to the
                            missionaries.</p>
                        <p>I therefore make this reply; and if my proposal pleases you, may I ask
                            you to summon Mr. Corbett, and instruct him in future to earnestly
                            enjoin upon all who are connected with him that they will not be allowed
                            to create such disturbances in future? In conducting law-cases in the
                            interior, private interference (on the missionary’s part) will not be
                            allowed.</p>
                        <p>I shall issue a stringent proclamation, informing the people of that
                            district that they will not be allowed again to show disrespect to
                            missionaries, but must seek for lasting peace, stop their litigations,
                            and be sincerely friendly.</p>
                        <p>In respect to Mr. Corbett’s complaint that trees have been cut down at
                            Pan-hien, and other outrages committed at Ta-lao village and
                            Tung-kia-ngan, I have directed the district magistrate to make inquiries
                            and report, but have not yet heard from him. It is probable that mutual
                            distrust and misunderstanding have arisen from these false rumors. If
                            this affair be soon settled, the minds of people in other places will be
                            quieted.</p>
                        <p>With this reply, I take the opportunity to wish you the compliments of
                            the season.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">ministers of the foreign
                            office</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-04-04"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: I have already brought to your notice the
                            attack on Rev. H. Corbett by the people of Chi-mi, who stoned and robbed
                            him, and then received a reply stating that orders had been sent to the
                            governor of Shantung to examine into the affair.</p>
                        <p>I have since received a report from the American consul at Che Foo, who
                            has been investigating this case with the intendant there, in which he
                            complains that the latter is dilatory, and is trying to slur over the
                            whole affair of the attack and robbery of Mr. Corbett. His report leads
                            me to ask why the intendant should delay the case three whole months,
                            and then just turn around and say that he had finished it? It is not
                            easy to explain this, except by supposing that he is partial in some
                            way. If he will <pb facs="0376" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> examine the
                            11th article of the treaty he will see what is required to be done, and
                            that his report of the facts is entirely at variance with what the
                            consul has ascertained. The names of more than ten men, who were engaged
                            in the robbery, have been given in with the evidence, and yet he avers
                            that the case is already finished. I think this shows clearly that he is
                            unwilling to try it at all.</p>
                        <p>I therefore earnestly request that other orders may be sent to Shantung
                            requiring the governor to direct his subordinates to have this whole
                            matter tried in Chefoo, to which place the criminals, and all that are
                            connected with it, shall be removed, and where the intendant shall
                            summon the witnesses. Here, in conjunction with the consul, it can be
                            fully examined and decided in accordance with equity and the criminals
                            punished. It will not be difficult, under such circumstances, to get at
                            the truth; for, as the proverb says, “when the water has fallen the
                            rocks appear.”</p>
                        <p>As I write this note I improve the opportunity to wish you every
                            happiness.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No.
                            44.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Ministers of foreign
                                    office</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                                     gregorian" when="1874-04-12"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tungchi</hi>, 13<hi rend="italic">th year,</hi> 2<hi rend="italic">d moon</hi>,
                                    26 <hi rend="italic">day</hi>, (April 12,
                                1874.)</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>The ministers of the foreign office return their compliments.</p>
                        <p>We have received your excellency’s note respecting the robbery of Mr.
                            Corbett. [Here follow its leading points, and a summary of what their
                            former note contained.]</p>
                        <p>We have now, in compliance with your request, again urged the governor of
                            Shantung to enjoin upon his subordinate immediately to examine this
                            affair in accordance with justice, and punish the wrong-doers, and
                            report the conclusion as soon as possible; and now send this note in
                            reply for your information.</p>
                        <closer>Cards of <signed>PAG YUN</signed>,<lb/>MAO CHANG-HI,
                            &amp;c.</closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To <hi rend="smallcaps">S. Wells Williams</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 7 in No. 44,]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williams</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Sheppard</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-03-11"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 11,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received three dispatches from Mr.
                            A. Cornabé, United States vice-consul at Chefoo, dated 12th January,
                            28th February, and 2d March, all of them relating to the attack on Rev.
                            H. Corbett, at Chi-mi, on the southern side of Shantung promontory, and
                            detailing the action he had taken in procuring redress for this
                            violence, and compensation for the property destroyed; he also incloses
                            copies of the communications which have passed between him and the
                            Taotai upon this matter, from which it is plain that the latter is
                            disinclined to prosecute the affair to a satisfactory conclusion.</p>
                        <p>Under these circumstances I wish you would proceed to Chefoo and see what
                            further steps can be taken to bring the affair to a conclusion according
                            to the obligations of the treaty and justice. It seems from the papers
                            here that the messenger sent to Chi-mi from Chefoo, and the district
                            magistrate of that place, have given in statements to their superiors of
                            the affair which are plainly distorted and imperfect, and designed to
                            shield him from all culpability.</p>
                        <p>You will therefore find it necessary to get the evidence of the persons
                            best acquainted with all the circumstances of the affair, so as to
                            counteract these <hi rend="italic">ex-parte</hi> reports. In asking for
                            redress, the arrest and punishment of the ringleaders should be
                            demanded, as well for the future security of foreigners going there, as
                            for the maintenance of order. A careful list of the property should be
                            made out which was stolen or destroyed, with its actual value, and
                            compensation made to Mr. Corbett for his losses. When these two points
                            are obtained, the district magistrate may well be made to issue a
                            proclamation setting forth the freedom guaranteed to Christians and
                            their teachers by treaty and imperial decree, to practice their faith
                            without molestation.</p>
                        <p>I do not think it best for you to ask for any compensation for the losses
                            of the native Christians, and it will probably be best to limit your
                            action to that which concerns Mr. Corbett alone, and let the redress
                            which may be given to him be admonition enough for the security it may
                            afford to his native converts. They cannot fail to be benefited if his
                            wrongs are redressed, and we have no such liberty of action in this
                            respect that we can properly interfere in any direct way for native
                            Chinese, and it is better to say nothing.</p>
                        <p>In regard to this case, it seems, from what I now know, that this popular
                            rising was of <pb facs="0377" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/> such dimensions
                            as to alarm the district magistrate, who told Mr. Corbett that he could
                            not protect him, as the power in his hands was too weak. There was no
                            direct attack on Mr. Corbett, who, escaping by night with his children,
                            happily avoided the violence of the mob, which vented itself on his
                            rooms. It will be difficult, perhaps, in such a case to fix the guilt on
                            any individual. It is a question to be decided by the evidence whether
                            the district magistrate did what he could to warn or protect him but he
                            seems not to have been altogether silent and not at all inimical. The
                            violence of a Chinese mob soon gets beyond the control of their local
                            officials, and it is a question for us to consider how much this point
                            is to be weighed in this case, and what degree of protection we are to
                            expect. The case at Chi-mi differs from that at Yu-chan, in December,
                            1871, when Mr. Pierson was attacked, in that the latter was a simple
                            assault with robbery, in which the populace sympathized very little.</p>
                        <p>I hope you will succeed in attaining the object for which you go to Che
                            Foo. The further action of Mr. Corbett must depend on himself in a
                            manner, but no force can be regularly employed to protect an American
                            anywhere in the interior.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 8 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sheppard</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Williams</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tien-tsin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-25"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 25,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It affords me much pleasure to be able now
                            to report to you the final and most satisfactory settlement of the
                            serious disturbance, or succession of riots, which occurred last
                            December in £he district of Chi-mi, province of Shantung, and originated
                            in a feeling of hostility stirred up among the people of that district
                            by evil-disposed persons against an American missionary who had been
                            peaceably living and quietly pursuing his calling in their midst. This
                            outbreak against missionaries is the first of a serious nature that has
                            happened in the north of China since the massacre of French missionaries
                            at Tien-tsin, in 1870, and it is the only organized disturbance that has
                            occurred in the interior, far from a treaty-port, since the attack made
                            upon missionaries at Yang-chow, in 1868.</p>
                        <p>The history of this case seems, therefore, in my opinion, interesting
                            from several points of view. In the first place, it serves as an
                            indication of the progress of public opinion regarding the labors of
                            Christian missionaries in this country, since the previous disturbances
                            above referred to; it shows the peculiar causes which continue to affect
                            the peaceable residence of foreigners in the interior, and the jeopardy
                            their lives may be placed in at any hour; it also shows to what extent
                            the treaties existing between China and other nations are known and
                            respected in the country at large; and, lastly, the record of this case
                            exhibits the attitude generally assumed by Chinese officials, at the
                            treaty-ports and in the interior, when called upon to administer justice
                            in behalf of foreigners, whether it be asked under the treaties, or
                            under the plainest requirements of Chinese law.</p>
                        <p>The following brief summary of the voluminous documents composing the
                            record of this case will explain the origin, nature, and consequences of
                            the outbreak, as well as the course of action I pursued, and the results
                            attained by that course. About the 1st of September, 1873, the Rev.
                            Hunter Corbett, ah American missionary residing in Che Foo, left that
                            place, accompanied by his three children, and went to the district of
                            Chi-mi, on the sea-coast of Shantung, about four hundred li (one hundred
                            and thirty miles) south of Chefoo, for the purpose of residing
                            temporarily among the native Christians of that district, in response to
                            their earnest solicitations. He was provided with a passport, as
                            required by treaty, bearing the seals of the consular and Chinese
                            authorities of Chefoo. He took up his residence in the village of
                            Ko-fau, twenty-five li from the city of Chi-mi; and besides the native
                            converts, numbering one hundred and fifty adults, Mr. Corbett found a
                            large number of people in his vicinity desirous of professing the
                            Christian faith.</p>
                        <p>It was Mr. Corbett’s practice to move about among the neighboring
                            villages, in company with his native helpers, preaching and distributing
                            religious books to the people; and on such occasions the people had been
                            found, with few exceptions, friendly and well disposed. It was not until
                            the 30th of November that any active hostility was shown; but on that
                            day, as Mr. Corbett was passing through the village of Hwa-yin, on his
                            way to preach at a more distant place, a crowd of people, who had been
                            witnessing a theatrical performance, assailed Mr. Corbett with stones
                            and threatening language. Still later in the day, as Mr. Corbett was
                            passing through the same village on his return home, he was still more
                            violently attacked by the same people, who had remained in waiting for
                            him. Mr. Corbett, being on horseback, made his escape in <pb facs="0378" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/> safety, and the next day he complained to
                            the district magistrate of Chi-mi, and asked for protection under his
                            passport, in accordance with the treaty. The magistrate promised to
                            protect Mr. Corbett and to punish those guilty of the assault; he also
                            showed Mr. Corbett a draught, of a proclamation he proposed to issue,
                            asserting the right accorded to missionaries by the treaty to propagate
                            religion, and the protection to be extended to native converts as well.
                            But none of these promises were fulfilled; and it was not until Mr.
                            Corbett had several days afterward again begged the magistrate to take
                            action that the latter expressed his sense of duty in this matter by
                            simply issuing the proclamation. The inevitable consequences of such
                            official inaction in this country soon followed.</p>
                        <p>On the 17th of December Mr. Corbett went with some native converts to
                            preach and distribute books at a fair held in the Yuh-hwang temple,
                            thirty li south of the city of Chi-mi. On reaching the temple he was
                            soon surrounded by an immense mob hooting and throwing stones. Nothing
                            that Mr. Corbett and the native Christians could do or say would pacify
                            the raging crowd, who appeared to be bent on some bloody work. Mr.
                            Corbett took refuge in the temple, but there his position became more
                            precarious every moment. The mob surrounded the building, filled the
                            courts, and showered stones into the room where he was, one of the
                            stones striking him in the face. Seeing no way of escape, at the peril
                            of his life, and with the assistance of a few native Christians, who
                            nobly stood forth to defend him, he attempted to force his way through
                            the midst of the mob, and barely succeeded in doing so. He mounted his
                            horse and galloped off amid a shower of missiles, and with the crowd in
                            full cry after him, but he managed to make good his escape. Disappointed
                            of their victim, the mob then fell upon the Christians who had been left
                            behind, beating all of them and inflicting severe wounds upon some, who
                            had to be carried to their homes. The passions of the people were now
                            thoroughly roused, and the excitement had spread over the whole
                            district. A crisis was approaching, which might have been averted by the
                            display of firmness and energy on the part of the magistrate in the
                            discharge of his duty. But his conduct was precisely similar to that of
                            the officials during the corresponding stage of the Yang-chow affair in
                            1868, and of the Tien-tsin massacre in 1870; he was actuated by no
                            motive to sustain treaty rights, nor even, as it appeared, by the common
                            humanity of eoming promptly forward with such protection as he could
                            give to life and property imperiled by mob violence.</p>
                        <p>When Mr. Corbett the same day reached his home at Ko-fau he at once
                            reported this fresh disturbance to the district magistrate, naming some
                            of the ringleaders of the mob, and urging that immediate action be taken
                            to arrest the guilty and restore order. Meanwhile it became plainly
                            apparent to Mr. Corbett and his native friends that more mischief was
                            brewing, the excitement and commotion in the neighborhood finally
                            reaching such a degree as to lead the native Christians to urge Mr.
                            Corbett to fly from the place. On the night of December 19, fully
                            convinced of the danger of remaining where he was, Mr. Corbett, with his
                            three children, fled to the district city of Chi-mi, distant twenty-five
                            li, escorted by a small band of undaunted native Christians. On the 21st
                            of December Mr. Corbett obtained an interview with the magistrate, who
                            gravely said that the disturbance had now become too serious for him to
                            manage, and he could not answer for his own safety, let alone the safety
                            of foreigners. The magistrate repeatedly pressed Mr. Corbett to fly to
                            Chefoo, and promised to restore order after his departure. Mr. Corbett
                            wisely determined to continue his flight, and, accordingly, late in the
                            night of the 21st December, he left with his children for Chefoo, and,
                            traveling by a circuitous route, reached there in safety.</p>
                        <p>The news of Mr. Corbett’s escape, when it became known the next morning,
                            was the signal for a general uprising. Armed mobs assembled with
                            impunity and in great numbers. They were exultant in having succeeded in
                            disposing of the foreigner, with the apparent approval of the
                            magistrate, and they proceeded first to wreak their vengeance on all
                            that Mr. Corbett had left behind. They broke into and demolished the
                            interior of his house, destroyed or carried off his furniture and
                            personal effects, and took away his mule and cow. A pack-mule, loaded
                            with some of Mr. Corbett’s effects, was stopped on the road by a mob and
                            forcibly taken away from the man in charge.</p>
                        <p>Then commenced a relentless persecution of the native Christians, and
                            every day witnessed scenes of violence, pillage, and ruthless
                            destruction of property. Fruit-trees were destroyed, farming implements
                            and stock carried away, and houses stripped of their furniture. Two
                            Christians were bound and carried off; another Christian was severely
                            wounded by a weapon in the hands of a local constable, who was leading a
                            mob into his house; and many Christians fled from their homes to places
                            of concealment. The village of Tung-chia-au-tsz was wholly abandoned by
                            its inhabitants, who, being all Christians, fled from the attack of a
                            mob. Fortunately no lives were lost, for, after Mr. Corbett’s escape,
                            the rioters seemed to be more intent upon persecution and pillage than
                            the shedding of blood. A mob of about 3,000 men assembled in the suburbs
                            of the city and were becoming turbulent, when the magistrate hurried to
                            the spot, and upon his hearing and promising to consider their charges
                            against the “foreign devil,” the mob gradually dispersed. A mob also
                            collected in front of the inn where <pb facs="0379" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/> Mr. Corbett stopped while in the city of Chi-mi.
                            Threats and imprecations against foreigners, native converts, and the
                            Christian religion were heard on every side, indicating a popular
                            feeling of hostility.</p>
                        <p>Such was the course of events in the district of Chi-mi during the month
                            of December. Subsequent investigations proved that the hostility of the
                            people was aroused and their passions inflamed by the accusations so
                            long and so falsely made against foreign missionaries in China. Any
                            falsehood that can be invented to defame the foreigner and render him
                            hateful finds ready believers among the ignorant mass of Chinese; and
                            there were not wanting in Chi-mi designing persons to thus fan the flame
                            of excitement, when once it was aroused. The old story of kidnapping
                            children for mutilation was revived; but undoubtedly the hatred
                            displayed against Christian preachers and converts was mainly due to the
                            general belief in the truth of such vile and abominable charges as are
                            made against the Christian religion in the native pamphlet known as the
                            “Death-blow to corrupt doctrines.” This pamphlet, it appears, was widely
                            circulated throughout the district of Chi-mi some time ago by
                            influential men among the literati, and many assert that its
                            distribution was encouraged by the local officials themselves; it is
                            certain at least that they did not attempt to check it.</p>
                        <p>In this affair the culpability of the district magistrate seemed
                            unquestionable. From the 30th November, when the first disturbance
                            occurred, he never attempted to make a single arrest, or administer the
                            slightest punishment. This indifference was readily enough construed
                            into sympathy with the rioters, and hence the latter were emboldened to
                            continue their lawlessness. In the mean time Mr. Corbett had not
                            neglected to report the disturbance to the consular authority at Chefoo.
                            Mr. Cornabé, the United States consular agent, first wrote to the
                            customs Taotai, at Chefoo, on the 22d of December, giving an account of
                            the attack made upon Mr. Corbett at the Yuh-hwang temple on the 17th of
                            December, and the disorder it had occasioned in the district, and
                            earnestly requesting the taotai to urge the magistrate of Chi-mi to
                            apprehend and punish the guilty. The Taotai replied briefly, expressing
                            his disbelief in Mr. Corbett’s account, and stating that he would have
                            the Chi-mi magistrate investigate the matter and report. A few days
                            later Mr. Corbett arrived in Chefoo, and Mr. Cornabé was then enabled to
                            furnish the taotai with fuller particulars, and with the names of some
                            of the principal rioters.</p>
                        <p>About this time the Taotai left Chefoo on a short visit to the provincial
                            capital, and before leaving he sent a deputy official to Chi-mi to
                            assist the magistrate in his investigation. During the taotai’s absence
                            Mr. Cornabé repeatedly wrote to him, giving further details of the
                            disturbance, as they came to hand, and earnestly desiring him to send
                            such instructions as would call forth honest exertions on the part of
                            the magistrate.</p>
                        <p>At length, on the 7th of February, the taotai replied in a long dispatch.
                            He had received the reports of the deputy and the magistrate, and they
                            agreed in representing that no such disturbance as Mr. Corbett
                            complained of had occurred at Chi-mi. The taotai, following the reports
                            of his subordinates, positively denied that Mr. Corbett had been
                            attacked, and made a rambling statement, accusing a native Christian of
                            attempting to kidnap a child, thus causing a disturbance at the
                            Yuh-hwang temple; and taking all this for granted, he considered that
                            any disorder which might have existed was brought about by the
                            indiscretion of Mr. Corbett and the native converts, hence he desired
                            that Mr. Corbett should be admonished to avoid giving offense in future.
                            But the taotai betrayed his real feelings by urging that judicial
                            proceedings should be stayed, as the people of Chi-mi were now anxious
                            to settle their differences and live in peace with Mr. Corbett. Mr.
                            Cornabé replied to this dispatch, refuting its misrepresentations, and
                            asking, once for all, that an impartial investigation should be made,
                            and that the principal rioters, whose names he had given, should be
                            arrested and punished. The taotai answered by simply saying that he
                            would again send a deputy to Chi-mi.</p>
                        <p>It was evident that the taotai was bent upon shielding the fault of the
                            magistrate, and avoiding his unpleasant duty of redressing the wrongs of
                            a foreigner, as required by treaty.</p>
                        <p>On the 7th of March, when navigation re-opened at this port, I received
                            from Mr. Cornabé a dispatch setting forth the occurrences related above,
                            and informing me that notwithstanding his repeated efforts he had been
                            unable to obtain the least satisfaction from the Taotai, or even the
                            admission of any wrong in this matter, and he therefore requested
                            instructions for his guidance. Impressed by the serious aspect this case
                            had now assumed, involving, as it did, the integrity of important treaty
                            stipulations, and fully believing that the future security of foreigners
                            and native Christians in the interior of Shantung was now at stake, and
                            would be seriously affected for better or worse by the manner of
                            adjusting this difficulty, I determined to go myself to Chefoo, and
                            endeavor to bring about a settlement with the Taotai. With your approval
                            I therefore proceeded to Chefoo without delay, where I employed myself
                            for a few days after my arrival in collecting testimony from native
                            Christians and others who had come from Chi-mi; and this business having
                            been completed, with the result of fully substantiating Mr. Corbett’s
                            statements, I called upon the Taotai on the 24th of March. <pb facs="0380" n="284" xml:id="pg_284"/> From the inclosed memorandum
                            of our interview it will he seen that the Taotai was in no humor to
                            discuss the business fairly. He first threw the blame entirely upon the
                            native Christians, then upon Mr. Corbett, and finally insisted that
                            proceedings should be stopped, as the people of Chi-mi were now anxious
                            to be at peace with Mr. Corbett. He attributed the disturbance to an
                            attempt made by a native Christian to kidnap a child. When I came to
                            demand the arrest and trial of forty-two principal rioters, whose names
                            had been given, the taotai emphatically refused to comply, and it was
                            only after I had as firmly insisted upon his doing so, in observance of
                            article 11 of our treaty, that he at length yielded his reluctant
                            consent, but not, however, until I had been obliged to say that, failing
                            in his arresting these men, I would consider the question of arresting
                            them myself by virtue Of the power given to United States authorities in
                            the last clause of article 11 of the United States treaty. This was the
                            first important step toward a satisfactory adjustment, and it was taken
                            by the Taotai only after he had been obliged to abandon every one of the
                            numerous false positions he had assumed in argument. After I had
                            corrected his frequent misstatements as to occurrences at Chi-mi, I had
                            still to convince him that it was his duty to afford redress under the
                            treaty, and he would not be convinced of this until he had found and
                            read for himself the various clauses I had referred to. Our discussion
                            maybe characterized as a stubborn attempt on the part of the taotai to
                            make light of a serious matter and ignore his lawful responsibility, and
                            an equally stubborn adherence on my part to rights which have been long
                            established by treaty.</p>
                        <p>A month passed before I was informed by the taotai, through Mr. Cornabé,
                            that the accused had been brought to Chefoo. I at once went to Chefoo,
                            and upon my arrival there, on May 1, I addressed the Taotai, asking for
                            a list of the names of those brought for trial. On receiving the
                            taotai’s reply I was surprised and disappointed to find that of the
                            forty-two whose names I had handed to the taotai on the 24th of March,
                            all of whom he had repeatedly promised to arrest, only ten had now been
                            brought to Chefoo, besides four others who had not been accused.</p>
                        <p>This breach of good faith, after a month’s delay, was part of a
                            temporizing policy to which I was determined not to submit. I could not
                            consent to go to trial with but ten of the accused, without failing to
                            obtain adequate and lasting redress for the outrage committed, and my
                            desire was to impress the people of Chi-mi with the fact that such
                            lawless proceedings as had occurred in their district would not be
                            passed over lightly.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, on May 4, I called upon the taotai, accompanied by Mr.
                            Cornabé and Commander Bridgeman, of the United States gunboat Palos,
                            which vessel had been sent to Chefoo from Shanghai by Mr. Seward, who
                            considerately anticipated my need of such support as the mere presence
                            of a gunboat could afford in the settlement of this question.</p>
                        <p>The taotai was attended by the magistrate of Chi-mi and the magistrate of
                            Fuh-shan, the district in which Chefoo is situated. The appearance and
                            conduct of the Chi-mi magistrate confirmed the opinion previously formed
                            of his character. He was an elderly man, infirm and irresolute, and
                            apparently without spirit or ability. The Fuh-shan magistrate seemed
                            intelligent and energetic.</p>
                        <p>A memorandum of the interview is inclosed herewith. I first reproached
                            the Taotai with some warmth for his bad faith, whereupon he made several
                            lame attempts to excuse his delinquency, but only succeeded in exposing,
                            in a still worse light, the utter inefficiency of the Chi-mi magistrate,
                            who had, as the Taotai unintentionally proved, quite disregarded his
                            instructions. The earnestness with which I urged my views seemed to
                            convince the Taotai of the propriety of doing his duty and fulfilling
                            his promises; and so, after some further quibbling, he declared himself
                            willing to complete the arrests and bring all the accused to Che Foo for
                            trial. He deputed the Fuh-shan magistrate to carry out this business,
                            and agreed to my proposal that two weeks should be allowed to fulfill
                            the promise. During the discussion Commander Bridgeman remarked to the
                            Taotai that he had orders from the American admiral to remain at Chefoo
                            until this affair was settled, and he hoped soon to be able to report
                            its satisfactory adjustment. This remark seemed to have considerable
                            weight with the Taotai, and it undoubtedly curtailed useless
                            discussion.</p>
                        <p>It was reported by Chinese who came from Chi-mi, from time to time, that
                            the people there were determined to oppose the arrest of the rioters who
                            had been accused; and hence it appears that the magistrate was
                            intimidated and did not uudertake to arrest them, but resorted to
                            various pretexts to screen the guilty, a course fully in keeping with
                            his behavior from the beginning of this difficulty.</p>
                        <p>Having obtained from the Taotai his promise in writing that twenty-one
                            more of the rioters who had been accused should be arrested and brought
                            to Chefoo for trial before the Taotai and myself, and a day having been
                            agreed upon for the trial, I returned to Tien-tsin.</p>
                        <p>On the 20th of May, I once again proceeded to Chefoo. This, my third
                            visit in connection with this ease, occurred nearly six months after the
                            first outbreak in Chi-mi, and three months had elapsed since my first
                            interview with the Taotai regarding it. The Fuh-shan magistrate had
                            arrived from Chi-mi a few days previously, having in <pb facs="0381" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> his custody most of the rioters he was
                            sent to arrest. The whole number of rioters now under arrest in Chefoo
                            amounting to twenty-eight, I decided to proceed with the trial. On May
                            22, I had an interview with the Taotai, when it was agreed that the
                            trial should begin on the 25th and be held in the yamen, or court-house,
                            near the customhouse in Chefoo, as the most commodious room available.
                            Various preliminaries were discussed, and it was decided to put each of
                            the accused on his trial separately.</p>
                        <p>The trial began on the 25th of May, and continued for six days, the court
                            sitting from 2 o’clock to 6 p.m. daily. I inclose herewith a reliable
                            report of the ferial, published in the North China Herald of June
                            13.</p>
                        <p>The first day was wholly occupied in hearing Mr. Corbett’s statement of
                            his grievances, and when it was concluded, the Taotai expressed himself
                            satisfied with the truth of what had been said. It only remained to
                            identify the accused and establish their guilt, and the other five days
                            of the trial were devoted to the examination of witnesses for that
                            purpose. About fourteen witnesses, some of them Christians, were
                            examined, and after the most rigid and searching cross-examination by
                            the Taotai, who was especially severe when questioning the Christians,
                            the accused were fully identified and proven guilty. On the third day of
                            the trial (May 27) an unpleasant incident occurred. My official
                            messenger and several witnesses for the prosecution had been insulted
                            and struck by two soldiers of the Taotai’s guards, and Mr. Cornabés
                            messenger had been refused admittance to the yamen. Upon taking my seat
                            in court this day, I informed the Taotai of these indignities, and
                            insisted upon the arrest and punishment of the offenders before
                            proceeding further with the trial. The Taotai, after attempting to
                            exculpate them, admitted the justice of my demand and sent for the two
                            men, who were beaten in the presence of the court, whereupon the trial
                            was resumed.</p>
                        <p>This behavior of the soldiers of the Taotai’s own guard and within the
                            precincts of his yamun was a fair indication of public feeling among the
                            natives of Chefoo. From the time the first party of rioters were brought
                            under arrest to Chefoo public attention had been attracted to this case,
                            and sympathy with the rioters was expressed in various ways. During the
                            sitting of the court large crowds assembled in the vicinity of the
                            place, waiting with eagerness to hear the developments of the trial. No
                            disturbance was created, but there appeared to be a deep feeling of
                            resentment at such hitherto unheard of proceedings to vindicate the law
                            in behalf of foreigners. This feeling was soon expressed by means of
                            placards, in which the Taotai was vilified for partiality or submission
                            to foreigners, and one of these placards was daringly placed on the gate
                            of the Taotai’s office. It was, perhaps, partly due to his apprehension
                            of some anti-foreign demonstration by the people that the Taotai was
                            attended during the trial by an armed guard of over 100 soldiers.</p>
                        <p>The trial closed on the 1st of June, and on June 3 the Taotai came to the
                            consulate to arrange with me the terms of a final settlement. The United
                            States gunboat Saco had arrived on the day previous, and her officers,
                            in full uniform, were present at this interview. On being introduced to
                            the Taotai, Commander McDougal remarked that “the American admiral had
                            been much concerned on hearing of the difficulty in Chi-mi, and he was
                            most desirous that it should be peaceably and satisfactorily adjusted.”
                            The Taotai replied that “the admiral need give himself no unnecessary
                            anxiety, as a satisfactory conclusion would now probably be reached, and
                            that he saw no reason why it could not be fully and satisfactorily
                            adjusted between himself and the consul.” For a full account of this
                            interview, I beg to refer you to the inclosed memorandum.</p>
                        <p>After some discussion, the following terms of settlement were speedily
                            decided upon, viz: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Four men convicted of having been prominently engaged in the
                                    two cases of Stoning, to be beaten with the large bamboo; one of
                                    them eighty blows, two others sixty each, and one forty blows.
                                    The local constables (ti-pao) of Ko-fau and Hwa-yin to receive
                                    eighty blows each, and be dismissed from office.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Mr. Corbett’s pecuniary losses, estimated at 380 taels, to be
                                    paid within fifteen days, by the persons who entered his house;
                                    they to be imprisoned in the mean time and the Taotai to
                                    guarantee payment.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The remainder of the criminals to be pardoned at my special
                                    request.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>All of the prisoners to enter into a bond to keep the peace
                                    and guarantee Mr. Corbett’s personal safety while he remains in
                                    Chi-mi. All accusations or suits arising out of this case, or
                                    connected with it in any way, to be suppressed.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The Taotai to issue a stringent proclamation, giving a full
                                    account of this case, and how it was settled, and threatening
                                    severe punishment upon any one who may dare to engage in similar
                                    outrages in the future.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>When Mr. Corbett returns to Chi-mi, the Taotai is to furnish
                                    him with a special passport, and also with a letter to the
                                    Chi-mi magistrate.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>On the following day, June 4, I proceeded to the Taotai’s yamun,
                            accompanied by Mr. Cornabé, Commander McDougal, and several other
                            officers of the Saco. The Taotai was attended by the Fuh-shan
                            magistrate.</p>
                        <p>The Taotai now submitted for my approval draughts of his proposed
                            proclamation, and of the bonds to be signed by the prisoners. These
                            proving to be quite satisfactory, <pb facs="0382" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> the prisoners were then called into court, and the
                            Taotai proceeded to pass sentence upon those condemned to punishment. He
                            addressed them at some length, pointing out the gravity of their offense
                            and the severity of the punishment as prescribed by law. He told them
                            that I had requested, and the prosecutor also had desired, that they
                            might be dealt with leniently, and for this they should be thankful.
                            After warning them to live in peace with foreigners and native
                            Christians when they returned to their homes, he ordered them away to
                            receive their punishment.</p>
                        <p>Those who were to sign the bonds were then called up and seriously
                            admonished; and, lastly, all of the prisoners, save those condemned to
                            punishment, were brought into court, and the Taotai addressed them in
                            words of persuasion, caution, and warning. His remarks were so
                            appropriate and reasonable, and were delivered with such spirit and
                            emphasis, and the duties and responsibilities of the prisoners were so
                            clearly pointed out to them, that all who were present in court seemed
                            to be impressed by the seriousness of the occasion. Upon the conclusion
                            of these remarks, the bonds were signed and the court adjourned. The
                            prisoners condemned to punishment were then conducted to a neighboring
                            yamên, where they were beaten, as sentenced, in the presence of Mr.
                            Cornabé the officers of the Saco, and the acting interpreter, Mr. Hart
                            well. Inclosed I beg to hand you a copy of the proclamation, with a
                            translation of the same; also copies, with translations, of the two
                            bonds, and a memorandum of the proceedings of June 4.</p>
                        <p>Thus, after months of delay and long-protracted contention, this case was
                            finally brought to a successful conclusion. Preventive measures promptly
                            taken might have suppressed the disturbance in its incipient state; and
                            an honest desire to deal fairly and show justice to foreigners, when
                            once the violence had been perpetrated, would have attained immediately
                            the end which has but now been reached, and spared weeks of needless
                            discussion and inconvenience.</p>
                        <p>The progress of enlightenment and friendly feeling in this country does
                            not appear encouraging when the obligations of a treaty made in 1858 are
                            at this late day so little known or so wholly ignored in a coast
                            province of China as to give rise to such disturbances among the people
                            and such sturdy opposition on the part of the officials.</p>
                        <p>In attributing blame for such outrages, there is less excuse for the
                            officials than for the people they govern; for although officials may be
                            prejudiced against foreigners, they cannot be wholly ignorant of the
                            solemn national engagements made to secure the welfare of foreigners in
                            China. Still less can officials at the open ports be ignorant of the
                            manner in which justice has been rendered and treaty-rights vindicated
                            on occasions of popular outbreaks of similar nature during the past few
                            years. If proof be still needed, the settlement of this case abundantly
                            shows that it is the <hi rend="italic">will</hi> rather than the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> that is wanting in Chinese officials, to
                            extend protection to foreigners and obtain for them redress when it is
                            required. It is questionable whether the Taotai at Chefoo would have
                            yielded as he did, had he not received instructions to adjust this
                            matter from the governor of Shantung, who had heard from the tsung-li
                            yamên; and this action of the yamên was the good result of your repeated
                            representations to them of the importance of this case. The peculiar
                            feature in the adjustment of this difficulty is the success of my
                            efforts to have the offenders brought from the interior of the province,
                            where the law and the treaty were set at defiance, to a treaty-port,
                            where the trial could be conducted free from the intimidation of a mob,
                            and where treaty-rights are better understood and enforced. The presence
                            of gunboats at the open ports, and the interest taken by naval
                            authorities in such questions as this, is a sure, and sometimes the <hi rend="italic">only</hi>, guarantee of a speedy and equitable
                            settlement. Such co-operation of the naval with the consular officers
                            serves at once to convince the Chinese of the national character of the
                            question under discussion, as considered in the light of a treaty
                            obligation; the private wrong is thus exhibited more prominently to the
                            Chinese in its nature as a public question concerning the integrity of
                            treaties. It was to such moral support afforded by the presence in port
                            of the United States gunboats Palo’s and Saco, and the personal
                            co-operation of Commanders Bridgeman and McDougal, that the favorable
                            settlement of this case was largely due; and therefore I would here
                            express my thanks to the admiral of the Asiatic squadron for permitting
                            the vessels to come to Che Foo, and also to Mr. Consul-General Seward,
                            for having kindly represented to the admiral the desirability of sending
                            them. It is gratifying to find that, notwithstanding the apparent
                            hostility of the people to the Christian religion, this wrong, suffered
                            by an American citizen who was laboring as a missionary in the interior
                            of China, has met with adequate redress in strict conformity with
                            treaty-rights. And although the punishment prescribed by Chinese law for
                            the various offenses committed is much more severe than the punishment
                            actually administered, yet the ends of justice have been sufficiently
                            served, and the clemency shown to most of the prisoners after their
                            conviction will doubtless produce a good effect upon themselves and
                            others; and it is to be hoped that the proclamation which has been
                            issued will more effectually accomplish the object for which it was
                            intended, now that its warnings are strengthened by examples which have
                            been made of the guilty.</p>
                        <p>The real character of this disturbance has been anti-foreign and
                            anti-christian, and <pb facs="0383" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> the
                            settlement made has fully vindicated both objects of attack. Yet the
                            Chinese are so credulous in all they hear of foreigners, and so much
                            influenced by prejudice and superstition, that ill-feeling is soon
                            roused to-produce mischief; and when such instances occur wherever a
                            foreigner may be in the interior, and the local official shows an
                            unwillingness to act promptly in suppressing threatened disorder, the
                            safest course would be for the foreigner to withdraw at once from the
                            disturbed district and await the action of his own authorities.</p>
                        <p>Since returning to Tien-tsin, I have received a letter from Mr. Corbett,
                            who went back to Chi-mi. He reports that the people are very friendly,
                            and that he has met with no difficulty. This intelligence encourages the
                            hope that the adjustment of this case will have a permanent effect for
                            good, not only in the district of Chi-mi, but throughout the province at
                            large, and that missionaries will reap the benefit of the time, labor,
                            and anxiety devoted to attain the results which have now been
                            reached.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, I have to express my thanks to Mr. W. A. Cornabé, in
                            charge of the consulate at Chefoo, for the active and efficient aid he
                            has rendered throughout the case, and for the zeal he has shown in
                            behalf of the interests committed to his charge; to Mr. J. B. Hartwell,
                            who acted as my interpreter during the several interviews and the trial,
                            and to whom I am under great obligation for his constant attendance and
                            unwearied exertions; and to the several gentlemen who voluntarily acted
                            as secretaries and assistants, and who rendered valuable service as
                            such.</p>
                        <p>I am likewise under special obligation to Consul-General Seward for the
                            encouragement and support he has given me in this difficult case.</p>
                        <p>I trust that my course of action and its results, as herein set forth,
                            will meet with your approval, as well as that of the Government.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>ELI T. SHEPPARD,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in 8 in No.
                            44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of an interview between Eli T. Sheppard,
                                United States consul, and Kung, Taotai at Chefoo, March</hi> 24,
                            1874.</head>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I have been specially directed by the
                            American minister to come here and make inquiry into the cause of the
                            attack upon the Rev. Mr. Corbett, and the subsequent disturbance, in the
                            district of Chi-mi, in December last.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. What action do you propose to take?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I am informed by your correspondence
                            with Mr. Cornabé that you have been examining into the affair. I will be
                            happy to hear the result of your investigations.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I think there is fault on both sides,
                            and both parties are to blame. I find that a native Christian, named
                            Wang Li-tung, on the 28th day of the tenth moon, at the Yü-huang temple,
                            attempted to kidnap a child. He is a bad man. The Chinese child was
                            wounded. I also hear that Mr. Corbett has a Chinese woman (wife?) at
                            Chi-mi, and three children by her.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. If Wang Li-tung has committed any
                            crime, it is the duty of the local authorities to punish him for it.
                            That is none of my business, and I have no right to inquire into or
                            meddle with it. It is Mr. Corbett’s affair that I am inquiring about. He
                            had only been there a few months before he was driven away; so the story
                            of the Chinese wife and three children is incorrect.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I do not think Mr. Corbett is to blame
                            in any way. The people at Chi-mi are now petitioning for him to come
                            back and live among them.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Has anybody ever entered any complaint
                            against Mr. Corbett for misconduct?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. No; none whatever. But the native
                            Christians at Chi-mi refuse to kneel before the magistrates in
                            court.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Native Christians should be obedient to
                            their magistrates, and kneel before them just the same as if they were
                            not Christians. But I cannot interfere in matters between the
                            magistrates and Chinese subjects. I have been directed by the minister
                            to take the testimony of truthful witnesses, and, if I find Mr.
                            Corbett’s statements to be correct, to ask for the arrest and punishment
                            of the ringleaders of the mob, and for remuneration for Mr. Corbett’s
                            losses. I have here in my hand the sworn statements of fen credible
                            witnesses, some of whom are Christians, some not, who fully verify Mr.
                            Corbett’s statements. Now, as you acknowledge that Mr. Corbett has done
                            nothing wrong, I must ask you to have these men, whose names I here give
                            you, arrested at once and placed upon trial for punishment in accordance
                            with the provisions of the eleventh article of the treaty between China
                            and the United States.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Does Mr. Corbett propose to go back to
                            Chi-mi?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. That depends upon circumstances, I
                            suppose. Mr. Corbett has a passport <pb facs="0384" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/> bearing your excellency’s seal, and so long as he
                            does no harm, and continues to behave himself properly, it must be for
                            him to decide when and where he will go. Do you propose to arrest these
                            men, or not?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Why should I? Mr. Corbett came away
                            from Chi-mi of his own accord.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul.</hi> Is it possible that, after three months
                            of investigation, your excellency is still ignorant that Mr. Corbett was
                            obliged to fly to save his life from the violence of the mob?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. The people made a disturbance and Mr.
                            Corbett became timid and left, but he was not compelled to leave.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Does not your excellency know that the
                            magistrate of Chi-mi, to whom Mr. Corbett appealed for protection, urged
                            him to leave because it was unsafe for him to remain longer in the city
                            of Chi-mi?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. The magistrate told him he had better
                            leave, because the people were saying that he (Mr. Corbett) was
                            kidnapping children.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. But your excellency has just said that
                            there has never been any complaint against Mr. Corbett. Then why does
                            the magistrate make this charge?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I do not believe these things; but the
                            people at Chi-mi say so.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Does not the magistrate of Chi-mi know
                            that Tsêng Kuo-fau, in his memorial, after a full examination into the
                            charges of kidnapping children by foreigners and native Christians at
                            Tien-Tsin, declared that Christians never had been found engaged in
                            kidnapping, and that it was contrary to the Christian religion to do
                            so?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Yes; I know that it is so.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Then it is your duty to instruct these
                            people thus. If steps are not taken to suppress these idle rumors, this
                            matter will go on from bad to worse, just as it did at Tien-tsin, where
                            it resulted in a horrible massacre of a great many innocent people. I
                            must repeat my request that you arrest these men for trial and
                            punishment.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. If I should arrest all these men, and
                            Mr. Corbett should afterward return to Chi-mi, there would certainly be
                            more disturbances. The best way is for Mr. Corbett to drop it now. You
                            see the people are friendly.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I see the people have torn down Mr.
                            Corbett’s house, stoned him, called him “devil,” and robbed him, and now
                            you say they charge him with kidnapping children. I don’t think that
                            looks <hi rend="italic">very</hi> friendly.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Will you make your request in the form
                            of an official dispatch to me?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Certainly, if you are going to comply
                            with the request, I will do so; but if you are not, there is no use of
                            wasting the paper. Mr. Cornabé has frequently requested you to do so
                            before.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Mr. Cornabé has not asked the arrest of
                                <hi rend="italic">all</hi> these men. Will you arrest Wang
                            Li-tung?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul.</hi> No. But if these men are arrested, I
                            will bring Wang here. If he has done anything wrong, you can punish
                            him.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. But these men have killed nobody. They
                            have only had a fight; that is not a serious matter.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. They have violated the treaty, and they
                            have not been punished for it. Is that a thing of no consequence? These
                            men must be arrested and put upon their trial for punishment.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Wang must be arrested, too.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I will bring Wang here.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Will you write your request?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Yes, when you promise me your
                            compliance; not before, Mr. Cornabé’s requests are in writing, and they
                            have been wholly ignored. Do you intend to arrest the men?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I want your dispatch first.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. You have admitted that Mr. Corbett has
                            done no wrong, and that a large crowd has made a disturbance and
                            intimidated Mr. Corbett. I have here sufficient testimony to convict all
                            these men of a serious crime. It is your duty by the treaty, upon my
                            request, to arrest these men and punish them. If you cannot do so, or
                            will not, I must go to the viceroy and the governor of this
                            province.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Their number is too great.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Then am I to understand that when a mob
                            exceeds a score or so they are secure from arrest?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will promise to arrest the men named
                            by Mr. Cornabé.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. The fourteen additional named are
                            equally guilty, and must be arrested.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will not do it. Let me see the
                            proofs. I do not believe what you say.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Do I understand your excellency as
                            impeaching my statement? Such an insinuation is disrespectful to the
                            minister who sends me here, and to the Government whose commission I
                            bear.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai.</hi> You misunderstand me. I meant only that
                            I do not believe the evidence which you have taken.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I wish to call your excellency’s
                            special attention to the provisions of the eleventh article of the
                            treaty between China and the United States, which makes it <pb facs="0385" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/> the duty of the local Chinese
                            official, in case of a riot or disturbance in which United States
                            citizens are molested, attacked, or put in jeopardy, to disperse the mob
                            and arrest and punish the offenders. In this case fall three months have
                            elapsed, and not a single arrest has been made. I now understand your
                            excellency refuses to arrest the guilty parties. I shall report this to
                            Peking. It is my duty to inform you that it now becomes a question for
                            the consideration of the United States Government whether or not its <hi rend="italic">own</hi> officers will make these arrests, and what
                            farther measures shall be taken to obtain redress.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. There is no authority in the treaty
                            allowing you to arrest Chinese subjects.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. If your excellency will read the last
                            clause of the eleventh article, you will find these words: “Arrests in
                            order to trial may be made either by the Chinese or United States
                            authorities.” What would your excellency have me to understand by
                            that?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. That applies only to the open
                            ports.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Does it say so?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>, (after much quibbling.) Very well,
                            then; you send me an official request for the arrest of these men, and I
                            will bring them here.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Will you arrest them and put them on
                            trial?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul.</hi> How soon can you have them here?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I cannot tell that. I will use all
                            expedition, and will order the magistrate of Chi-mi to arrest them and
                            come here with them, and we will all be present at the trial
                            together.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Very well. I will in the mean time go
                            to Tien-tsin and make a report of this to the minister at Peking. I will
                            send you my official request for the arrest of these men to-morrow.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will notify Mr. Cornabé when the men
                            are here, and he can notify you.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I will send you a detailed list of Mr.
                            Corbett’s losses just as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I should like to have it.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>.—On Thursday, March 26, the Taotai, after
                            receiving Mr. Sheppard’s official dispatch of the 25th, returned Mr.
                            Sheppard’s visit, and during the interview the Taotai informed Mr.
                            Sheppard that all possible expedition would be observed in arresting and
                            bringing the men to Chefoo for trial. He also gave Mr. Sheppard a list
                            of names of persons whom he proposed to bring forward for examination at
                            the same time with reference to the matter.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in 8 in No.
                            44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of an interview between E. T. Sheppard,
                                United States, consul, and Kung Taotai at Chefoo, May</hi> 4,
                            1874.</head>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. At our interview (March 24) your
                            excellency promised me that you would use all diligence and dispatch in
                            arresting the principal offenders in the Chi-mi disturbance. Your
                            excellency has also since then informed Mr. Cornabé that you had
                            arrested the men, as you agreed to do, and you asked for me to come here
                            and attend their trial. Now I have come and find that only ten of the
                            forty-two have been brought.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I have brought fourteen of the men.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Yes; but only ten of those whom I
                            named.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I did not say I had arrested all of
                            them.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. You said you had arrested the men, and
                            you asked me to attend the trial according to our agreement, which was
                            when all of the persons named were arrested. When I come I find only ten
                            out of the whole forty-two here. The most culpable are not brought. This
                            has occasioned me great inconvenience and annoyance, and I come to-day
                            to inquire of you why you have not fulfilled your promise, and to tell
                            your excellency that my minister, to whom I must report these facts,
                            will be greatly displeased at your delinquency.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I issued an order for the arrest of all
                            these men, as you requested. But the magistrate of Chi-mi reports that
                            many of the men are absent fishing, some are sick, and some are visiting
                            relations.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. The magistrate has reported to your
                            excellency a lot of falsehoods. I have been advised as to the movements
                            and occupation of all these men, and I know that ten days ago they were
                            all at their homes, that they were not sick, and there is not a single
                            fisherman among them.</p>
                        <p>(The magistrate of Chi-mi, who was present, was so completely nonplussed
                            by this statement that he did not attempt to deny it or refute it in any
                            way whatever.)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chi-mi Magistrate</hi>. I issued warrants for the
                            arrest of all these men as soon as I received the Taotai’s order.</p>
                        <pb facs="0386" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. What day did you issue your warrants,
                            sir?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Magistrate</hi>. The 25th day of the 2d moon.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. How long does it take for an order to
                            reach you at Chi-mi from Chefoo?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Magistrate</hi>. About four days, ordinarily.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>, (to the Taotai.) When did you send your
                            orders for the arrests? <hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. On the 7th day
                            of the 2d month.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. From the 7th until the 25th is eighteen
                            days. Deducting four days for the order to reach Chi-mi, leaves just
                            half a month in which nothing whatever was done by the Chi-mi
                            magistrate. Does not your excellency perceive that this magistrate has
                            been grossly negligent? (To magistrate.) What were you doing all these
                            two weeks, that you did not issue your warrants for the arrest of these
                            men sooner?</p>
                        <p>Magistrate made no answer.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>, (to the Taotai.) Now your excellency
                            sees that there has been gross neglect of duty here. I shall have to
                            report this to my superiors.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Tell me what you want done, and I will
                            do it.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I want you to keep your promise, and
                            send and bring these men here, as you promised me you would do. If you
                            are not able to do it, I must find somebody who can.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will send the Fuh-shan hsien to make
                            the arrests.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Here is a list of twenty-one names;
                            they are a part of the original list which I sent you. The first eight
                            named are the most culpable, and must be produced before a trial can be
                            entered into. The others must also be brought, and the ten who are now
                            here must be kept until they arrive, and all can be tried together.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I cannot fix a day certain when I will
                            have them here.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Why not?</p>
                        <p>Captain <hi rend="smallcaps">Bridgeman</hi>. It is essential that the
                            Taotai fix a day certain when he will produce these men; otherwise we
                            may be kept waiting indefinitely. I have been sent here by the admiral
                            to remain here pending the settlement of this affair, and I hope soon to
                            be able to report that it has been satisfactorily adjusted.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. If I fix a day certain to produce these
                            men and fail, you will come back again as you do now.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. I do not ask for or wish your
                            excellency to perform an impossibility. I am certain these men can be
                            all brought if any reasonable effort is made to get them. They can all
                            be brought here easily in ten days or less.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. I will get them if they are there. But
                            you must send along with the Fuh-shan magistrate the five Christian
                            witnesses who are now here when he goes to Chi-mi to make the
                            arrests.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Why must the five witnesses go?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. For two reasons: first, that they may
                            point out the guilty men, and second, that they may see that the men are
                            arrested.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. That is quite unnecessary. I have given
                            you the name and place of residence of each man, and my witnesses can
                            identify them when they are brought here for trial.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. Yes, but it is also desirable to have
                            the prosecutors of this suit present when these arrests are made, so the
                            people of Chi-mi may see at whose instance it is done, and it will make
                            them more careful and obedient in the future.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. That is very true, and I quite agree
                            with your excellency. I will therefore order Mr. Corbett, who is the
                            prosecutor of this suit, to go with the Fuh-shan magistrate to Chi-mi,
                            to be present when these arrests are made.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi>. O, no! There is no need of Mr.
                            Corbett’s going. We do not want him.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Yes, your excellency, it is exceedingly
                            necessary and proper that Mr. Corbett, the prosecutor of this suit, be
                            present when these arrests are made, so that the people at Chi-mi may
                            see at whose instance it is done, and it will make them more, careful
                            and obedient in the future. I propose to send Mr. Corbett along with the
                            Fuh-shan magistrate to Chi-mi.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai.</hi> No, no! It is the native Christians I
                            want, not Mr. Corbett. Send the native Christian witnesses. I am
                            satisfied that some of the Chi-mi people are guilty.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul.</hi> No, I will not do it. You are trifling
                            with me again. If you want the prosecutor of the suit to go, I will send
                            him; or if you want a proper constabulary force to help the magistrate
                            bring the men, I can give you that; but I don’t want any more broken
                            promises.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Taotai</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Fu-shan
                                Magistrate</hi>, together. If the men are in Chi-mi or in an
                            adjoining district we will get them.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consul</hi>. Very well, I will give you fourteen
                            days in which to redeem your promise. At the expiration of that time, I
                            will return to Chefoo again to attend their trial.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—The last proposition of Mr. Sheppard was
                            agreed to, and the interview closed.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0387" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in 8 in No.
                            44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of the final proceedings, June</hi> 4,
                            1874.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chefoo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-04T10:00:00+08:05"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 4,
                                    1874—10 o’clock a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>On the consul’s arriving at the court-room he was invited by the Taotai
                            to the hall above the court-room, where was held a brief interview,
                            during which the Taotai presented for the consul’s approval the draught
                            of the proclamation he proposes to issue; and also of the bonds he
                            proposed to require the “house robber” and the “donkey robbers” to sign,
                            as well as the one he intended to have signed by all the accused,
                            binding them to keep the peace and to use their influence to preserve
                            order in the villages in their respective neighborhoods. His excellency
                            also promised to furnish Mr. Corbett, whenever he might wish it, with a
                            new special passport to return with his family to Chi-mi, and also with
                            a letter to the magistrate of Chi-mi.</p>
                        <p>Present in court, besides his excellency the Taotai and the Fu-shan
                            magistrate, were Mr. Consul Sheppard, Mr. Cornabé, Captain McDougal, and
                            Officers Wood, Breese, and Dr. Ayers, of the United States steamer Saco;
                            Dr. Nevins and Mr. Farmer, secretaries, and Mr. Hartwell,
                            interpreter.</p>
                        <p>The Taotai called before him the prisoners who had been condemned to
                            punishment for participating in the several stonings and robberies, in
                            their several groups, and announced to them that they had been found
                            guilty of the charges made against them severally. He told them they
                            deserved to be punished with great severity; that particularly those of
                            them who were advanced in years should have restrained the younger men,
                            instead of leading them on; and that most especially the local
                            constables, whose duty it was to suppress such risings, were guilty of
                            serious crime in joining in stoning and in entering the house of any
                            person, and especially of a foreigner. Such conduct could not be
                            tolerated, and they must be punished according to law. He said their
                            sentence ought to be even heavier than the law ordinarily prescribes,
                            but that Mr. Corbett, the prosecutor, through the consul, had begged,
                            and the consul himself had asked, that they might be dealt with in
                            mercy; and that they might congratulate themselves on getting off with
                            no more severe punishment. He advised them, when they should go-back
                            home, to live quietly, and to be at peace with any foreigners who might
                            be there, and with the native Christians. He then ordered them to be
                            taken away for punishment. He then called the parties against whom
                            evidence had been adduced that they had taken part in the robbing on the
                            road and at Mr. Corbett’s house, but who, through clemency, were not to
                            be beaten. After lecturing them very much as he did the former groups,
                            and assuring them that he had been in consultation with the consul for
                            days concerning them, and that it was only through mercy, at the
                            intercession of Mr. Corbett and the sincere wish of the consul, that
                            they were not to be beaten, required them each to sign a document
                            binding themselves to pay for the missing articles within fifteen days.
                            They were told they would be locked up until the money was paid.</p>
                        <p>The whole number of the accused were now brought into court, (except the
                            condemned,) and the Taotai addressed them at some lenght upon the
                            serious nature of the offense with which they had been charged, and
                            assured them that if the witnesses, had delivered their testimony, every
                            man of them would have had to be punished, but that Mr. Corbett and the
                            consul, not seeking for revenge, had declined to press the matter in
                            every case, and had urged him to exercise mercy and pardon them. He
                            repeated to them that the consul and he had been consulting over the
                            matter for days, both the consul and the prosecutor inclining to mercy.
                            He asked, “How could you know what would be the effect of your stoning?
                            Some of those stones might have? seriously wounded Mr. Corbett, or even
                            killed him, in which case several of you might have forfeited your
                            lives.” He ordered them to be peaceable and friendly with Mr. Corbett
                            when he goes back, and with the native Christians.</p>
                        <p>They were to have no fights nor quarrels with the Christians. These
                            Christians were still Chinese subjects; and if they did anything wrong,
                            the people were not to take the law into their own hands, but to make
                            their complaints to the local magistrate, and if he did not deal with
                            the matter, they might come to the Taotai and complain, and he would see
                            that the matter was properly investigated. And just so with any
                            foreigner. Mr. Corbett would not do any harm; but if any foreigner
                            should do what was wrong, they were not to attempt to redress it
                            themselves, but to complain to him, and that he and the foreign consul
                            would have the delinquent foreigner dealt with. That neither the foreign
                            consul nor himself would allow a foreigner or a native to conduct
                            himself lawlessly in the country. He made them all promise that they
                            would drop this matter and not make any more trouble about it; that they
                            would go home and live at peace with the foreigner and with the native
                            Christians. They all knocked their heads in acknowledgment of this
                            clemency; and he required each one to sign a pledge that he would not
                            only keep the peace himself, but would urge this course upon all the
                            villages in his neighborhood.</p>
                        <p>The Taotai then reminded them that if, after signing this bond, they
                            should violate it, they would be dealt with more severely than if they
                            had not signed it, and dismissed them.</p>
                        <pb facs="0388" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                        <p>The court then adjourned, and the Fuh-shan magistrate proceeded at once
                            to his temporary office in Yentia to have the sentences of the court
                            executed. Mr. Cornabé and the interpreter, Mr. Hartwell, were deputed by
                            the consul to go, in company with Captain McDougal and Officers Wood,
                            Breese, and Dr. Ayers, of the United States steamer Saco, to see the
                            punishment inflicted.</p>
                        <p>Arrived at the Yamen, the magistrate had each culprit brought before him,
                            and after a few words to each, ordered him to be beaten according to the
                            sentence of the court. The blows were administered with a stick of
                            bamboo, four feet or more in length and about two inches wide, held by
                            the lictor in both hands. As it is the summer season, eight blows were
                            counted ten, according to Chinese custom.</p>
                        <p>Kiang Kwan-kih professed to be sick, and begged that his son might take
                            his place. The son being willing, the magistrate consented, and the son
                            received nominally 80 Mows, really 64; Wang I-chin received nominally 80
                            blows, really 64; Wang Shi-Kiai received nominally 80 blows, really 64;
                            Wang Pao received nominally, 60 blows, really 48; Kiang Hwo-sien
                            received nominally 60 blows, really 48; Kiang Shau-sien received
                            nominally 40 blows, really 32.</p>
                        <p>After which the deputation from the consulate retired.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 9 in No.
                            44.—Traslation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Taotai’s proclamation, dated June</hi> 22,
                            1874.</head>
                        <p>Kung, by imperial appointment a brevet provincial treasurer,
                            superintendent of maritime customs at Chefoo, and intendant of the
                            circuit of Têng-chou Fu, Laichou-Fu, and Ching-chau-Fu, issues a
                            stringent proclamation enjoining upon all an observance of the treaties,
                            to the end that natives and foreigners may enjoy peace and security.</p>
                        <p>Among the treaties with various countries made public by the prince and
                            ministers of the tsung-li yamên, there is found a treaty with the United
                            States, the twenty-ninth article of which is as follows:</p>
                        <p>“The principles of the Christian religion, as professed by the Protestant
                            and Roman Catholic Churches, are recognized as teaching men to do good,
                            and to do to others as they would have others do to them. Hereafter
                            those who quietly profess and teach these doctrines shall not be
                            harassed or persecuted on account of their faith. Any person, whether a
                            citizen of the United States or a Chinese convert, who, according to
                            these tenets, shall peaceably teach and practice the principles of
                            Christianity, shall in no case be interfered with or molested.”</p>
                        <p>Repeated commands have been issued for the observance of this
                            article.</p>
                        <p>In the month of December, 1873, some natives of the district of Chi-mi
                            stoned the Rev. H. Corbett, an American missionary, insulted him by
                            calling him kwei-tzé, (devil,) and took away from him clothing and other
                            articles. This, though at first only a small disturbance, well nigh grew
                            into a serious affair. The case has now been taken up and justly
                            adjudicated by myself and Mr. Sheppard, the United States consul.</p>
                        <p>With the exception of the leaders in the disturbance, who are punished,
                            according to law, with the heavy bamboo, with degrees of severity
                            corresponding to their offenses, the offenders are pardoned and
                            released. All these people, in their disobedience and reckless conduct,
                            have been guilty of breaking the laws. As this is the first offense,
                            their punishment is inflicted with leniency, hoping to preserve peaceful
                            relations between natives and foreigners. All persons of whatever class
                            should give diligence to observe the treaty, that mutual friendship may
                            be perpetuated. I have, in connection with Mr. Sheppard, the United
                            States consul, agreed upon certain stipulations which axe to be
                            published in this proclamation; and fearing lest persons in other places
                            may be ignorant of the treaty and recklessly make disturbance, I print
                            this proclamation in order that it may be generally known. Hereafter all
                            persons must observe my instructions, and thus avoid the recurrence of
                            such misdemeanors, by which you will bring punishment upon yourselves.
                            This is my earnest expectation.</p>
                        <p>The following are the stipulations: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>In future, all who preach and practice the Christian religion
                                    shall receive from local magistrates the same care and
                                    protection as others, and no one will be allowed to insult and
                                    injure them. All who, according to the principles of the
                                    Christian religion, peaceably propagate or practice it, shall
                                    not therefor be molested or injured by the people.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Hereafter when natives see a foreigner they must address him
                                    as such, and are forbidden to call him kwei-tzé, (devil.) Those
                                    who disobey this injunction will be immediately dealt with by
                                    the local magistrate.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The Chi-mi suit, originating in Hwa-yin market, Yuh-hwang
                                    temple, Ko-Fau village, and other places, has now been justly
                                    settled. Hereafter you people of every place <pb facs="0389" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/> should take warning from it. If
                                    you are guilty of such proceedings again, you will incur heavy
                                    punishment.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>This case has been justly decided and administered according
                                    to truth, and without partiality. The accused, including those
                                    who have been pardoned, have signed a bond promising to return
                                    home and peacefully pursue their several callings, without
                                    making further disturbance in seeking opportunities for revenge
                                    and retaliation against witnesses and others connected with this
                                    suit. If there are other matters or lawsuits, they must be
                                    considered by themselves, and no use shall be made of this to
                                    obstruct other suits.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Native Christians are Chinese subjects, and are to be governed
                                    by Chinese laws If lawsuits arise, they are to be attended to in
                                    the Chinese courts, and foreigners have nothing to do with them.
                                    And, according to treaty, foreign missionaries are not to act
                                    for, or to shield and protect, natives. I have heard that native
                                    Christians have been guilty of going before the magistrate
                                    without kneeling, and refusing to pay taxes, and undertaking the
                                    prosecution of illegal lawsuits, and other lawless practices. I
                                    have also heard that people have endeavored to exact from native
                                    Christians contributions to the ceremony of “welcoming gods,”
                                    and to idolatrous processions, repairing temples, and theatrical
                                    plays, which exactions are expressly forbidden by imperial
                                    edict. It is now agreed upon, in connection with the foreign
                                    consul, that hereafter, if native Christians or other subjects
                                    are guilty of the aforesaid misdemeanors, complaints may be
                                    brought against them before the local magistrate. If foreign
                                    missionaries act for them and protect them, the people may come
                                    to Chefoo and accuse them by name before me and the foreign
                                    consul, and the case will be impartially attended to. You must,
                                    not take the matters into your own hands and stone people, and
                                    thus bring punishment upon yourselves.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 10 in No
                            44.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Two bonds, dated June</hi> 4, 1874.</head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">bond to keep the peace.</hi></p>
                        <p rend="center">A voluntary bond of releasement entered into by Kiang
                            Kwan-kih and others.</p>
                        <p>This bond, by which releasement is obtained, is in consequence of the
                            prosecution of the undersigned by a foreigner, Rev. H. Corbett. Having
                            had the case closely examined, it appears that Kiang Kwan-kih struck Mr.
                            Corbett with a stone; that a stone thrown by Kiang Hwo-sien struck his
                            horse, and that Kiang Shau-sien took part in the affray. These persons
                            are sentenced to receive punishment according to the seriousness of the
                            offense committed by each. All the accused are now ordered to return
                            home and peacefully attend to their several callings, and to abstain
                            from making disturbances in the future. Hereafter, if Mr. Corbett goes
                            again to Chi-mi to preach and propagate Christianity, the inhabitants of
                            the village are not to interfere with him in any way. You must not
                            oppose and injure Christians, and must not oppress your native
                            countrymen. And now you voluntarily promise to abide by this document,
                            and not disobey.</p>
                        <p rend="right">[Signed by twenty-seven persons.]</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">bond to secure indemnity.</hi></p>
                        <p rend="center">A promissory bond given to secure the payment of
                            indemnification within a limited time.</p>
                        <p>This is a promissory bond, given in consequence of a suit brought against
                            the undersigned by a foreigner, Rev. H. Corbett. This suit having been
                            carefully examined, it appears that articles were lost from Mr.
                            Corbett’s house, and the undersigned engage either to find and return
                            the missing articles within fifteen days or to pay an equivalent in
                            money. We voluntarily promise to abide by this agreement.</p>
                        <p rend="right">[Signed by five persons.]</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 11 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Prince <persName type="from">Kung</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Williams</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                                     gregorian" when="1874-06-30"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tungchi</hi>, 13<hi rend="italic">th year,</hi> 5<hi rend="italic">th moon,</hi>
                                        17<hi rend="italic">th day,</hi> (<hi rend="italic">June</hi> 30, 1874.)</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith makes
                            a communication.</p>
                        <p>In relation to the quarrel which occurred at Chi-mi, in Shantung between
                            the people <pb facs="0390" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/> and the Christians,
                            I have already informed your excellency that frequent orders were sent
                            to the governor of that province to direct the proper officers to
                            inquire into the affair with a view to its just settlement.</p>
                        <p>A dispatch has now been received from the northern superintendent of
                            trade, inclosing the report of the intendant of circuit at Chefoo,
                            wherein he slates that, in the case of this riot between the people and
                            Christians in Chi-mi, the parties have all been summoned before him and
                            all the witnesses examined. In conjunction with the United States
                            consul, the affair has been publicly investigated in the fullest manner
                            and decided, the guilty punished, and the case finished. “I therefore
                            respectfully make known the details,” he concludes, “that you may report
                            for information in the proper quarter that the case is settled.”</p>
                        <p>I have accordingly had a copy made of the superintendent’s dispatch upon
                            the case, and beg to inclose it herewith for your excellency’s
                            information.</p>
                        <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">S. Wells Williams</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Chargé d’Affaires.</hi></p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Report of the northern superintendent of trade,</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Li Hungchang</hi>,) <hi rend="italic">inclosing
                                the following de tailed report from Kung Yih-tu, intendant of the
                                circuit of Y’angchau, Laichau, and Tsing chau, prefectures in
                                Shantung, dated June</hi> 16, 1874.</head>
                        <p>On the 23d of March the governor of Shantung sent me a copy of an order
                            he had received from the foreign office, dated March 1, in which the
                            inquiry was made as to the cause of the quarrel between the people of
                            Chi-mi and an American missionary there, and directing me to see that
                            the district magistrate there examined into the affair and equitably
                            settled it. I at once sent him the order to inquire into the cause of
                            the disturbance, and let me know everything that he did, and at the same
                            time reported a summary of the affair and what I had done to the
                            governor, for him to communicate to the foreign office.</p>
                        <p>On the 20th of May I received from the governor a copy of another order
                            from the foreign office, dated April 23, in which I was urged to more
                            diligence, and directed to bring the parties to the trial all together,
                            and jointly examine them in the most careful manner, so as to elicit the
                            facts and settle the affair in accordance with justice.</p>
                        <p>I had already directed Meh, the district magistrate at Chi-mi, to
                            transfer Kiang Kwan-kih and others, parties and witnesses in this case,
                            to my court, where, with the foreign missionary, Hunter Corbett, and the
                            native Christians, Wang Li-tung and others, they could all be examined,
                            and a joint trial held with the consul.</p>
                        <p>Among the documents in the case was one dated December 22, received from
                            W. A. Cornabé, United States vice-consul, in which he told me that Mr.
                            Corbett had been assaulted at a market-place called Hwa-yin, by a crowd
                            around a theater, and struck by stones thrown in the <hi rend="italic">mêlée</hi>. Further, that on the 19th of December he was preaching
                            near the temple of Yuh-hwang, at Hwa-yin, when he was struck by stones
                            thrown at him from the crowd, and his assistants, Wang Li-tung and
                            others, also wounded in the fray.</p>
                        <p>The vice-consul further said he had heard that the inhabitants of Chi-mi
                            had assembled to the number of 300, each of whom had ten others at his
                            back, and all intended to go into the town for the purpose of injuring
                            Mr. Corbett. The magistrate was powerless to protect him, and he had,
                            therefore, fled on the 22d, and reached Chefoo. A letter had afterward
                            been received from his assistant, stating that on that day about two
                            thousand men from the southern association of villages entered the town
                            seeking a quarrel. The magistrate had gone out to disperse them, but was
                            powerless to effect anything.</p>
                        <p>In another note he alleged that on the 24th a man named Sü Yen-tsoh and
                            half a score of fellows with him, all belonging to Chi-mi, had carried
                            off Mr. Corbett’s things and a hired donkey; and in the afternoon of
                            that day they had gone to Ko-fau and carried off all his furniture and
                            effects, with his cow, cleaning everything out and breaking the windows
                            and doors of his house to, pieces.</p>
                        <p>Subsequently he informed me that a convert named Che Chung-yuen,
                            belonging to the village of Pau-hein, had had his fruit and timber
                            trees, all cut down by people of the place. On the same day, Wang
                            Yung-chun, a convert living in Ta-lao Village, had been attacked by
                            persons entering his house, who robbed it and greivously wounded his
                            left eye; also, one Sun Wan-lun, of the village of Tung-kia-ngan, was
                            robbed and ill-used by some persons, and his uncle carried off by force.
                            The vice-consul accordingly requested that these proceedings might be
                            inquired into and the evil-doers punished. I immediately sent repeated
                            orders to the district magistrate at Chi-mi to strictly inquire into the
                            matter and punish the offenders. This can all be shown by the
                            records.</p>
                        <p>While I was issuing these orders and making these inquiries, Mr.
                            Sheppard, the United States consul, came from Tein-tsin down to Chefoo.
                            At an inter view I had with him, <pb facs="0391" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> he told me that he had received directions from the American minister
                            at Peking to go down and inquire into this affair, and have all the
                            witnesses and others connected with the case brought to Chefoo, that we
                            might there jointly try and settle it.</p>
                        <p>I accordingly ordered the magistrate of Chi-mi to remove the case to
                            Chefoo. Mr. Sheppard agreed that he would cite the plaintiff, Corbett,
                            and five converts to be present, when we could thoroughly examine the
                            case. He also gave me the names of the leaders in the riotous
                            proceedings at Chi-mi, forty-two persons in all, and a full list of the
                            clothes and other things lost by Mr. Corbett, valued, all together, at
                            380 taels.</p>
                        <p>Having received these lists, I sent two messengers to Chi-mi; and on the
                            16th of May the prisoners and all persons connected with the case were
                            in Chefoo. I notified Consul Sheppard of these things, and requested him
                            to appear with the plaintiff and the witnesses on his side. On the 25th
                            the United States consul and Sung Tsoh-pin, district magistrate of
                            Fuh-shan, being present, I opened the court and began the trial.</p>
                        <p>Seeing from the first that this case was likely to be a troublesome one,
                            having many points mixed in it, while those pertaining to the foreigners
                            ought alone properly to be the, subject of this joint trial and
                            sentence; but the accusations by the converts, who were Chinese, and
                            therefore a portion of our own people, belonged only and of right to the
                            local rulers, whose duty it was to settle all such quarrels, and
                            foreigners had nothing whatever to do with them. I stated these points
                            to Mr. Sheppard, who cordially assented. There were several cases
                            brought forward by the vice-consul, viz, that of the assault and
                            wounding of Wang Lih-tung; of cutting down the trees belonging to Ché
                            Chung-yuen; of the injury done to Wang Yang-chun; a id, lastly, of
                            robbing Sun Wăn-lun; all of which were wrongs arising between natives of
                            China, with which foreigners had no concern, and were accordingly
                            referred to the local authorities for trial and punishment.</p>
                        <p>There would then remain for our joint investigation only the attack on
                            Mr. Corbett and subsequent loss of his things, and to ascertain whether
                            there was a combination among the people of Chi-mi to molest and injure
                            him. We continued the trial for successive days, bringing forward the
                            prisoners one after the other, and taking evidence carefully upon each
                            charge.</p>
                        <p>It was proved that no organized combination existed among the people for
                            purposes of plunder and sediton; and I therefore asked the vice-consul
                            what evidence he had for the assertion made in one of his letters, that
                            two thousand people had entered Chi-mi in a tumultuous manner and that
                            the magistrate was unable to disperse them. In the inquiries made as to
                            the origin of such a false rumor, Mr. Corbett testified that after the
                            attack made upon him, near the temple of Yuh-hwang, some of the converts
                            told him that during the next night the people of the farmsteads in and
                            around Ko-fau had lighted no end of their lanterns, and roamed over the
                            country, from which they feared there was a consultation going on. But
                            this was not satisfactory proof of the charge.</p>
                        <p>As to the charge that the district magistrate was unable to protect him,
                            it appeared from the testimony of the convert Lin Lung-méi, at the time
                            of the military examinations at the place, on the 22d of December, that
                            many candidates were gathered on the parade-ground, and when the
                            magistrate went out of the gates to inspect them he saw several scores
                            of people kneeling by the roadside, whom he (the convert) was told were
                            there for the purpose of complaining against the foreigner. From this
                            idle rumor came the story that two thousand men had entered the town,
                            whom the local magistrate could not control or disperse, and the other
                            charge that there was a seditious combination of the people with intent
                            to murder, against which the officials could not protect him. Inquiry
                            proved them both to be unfounded.</p>
                        <p>I then asked the vice-consul about his statements, and he acknowledged
                            that, they arose from incorrect information; and, therefore, in respect
                            to the two counts of plotting violence, and inability of obtaining
                            official protection [for Mr. Corbett,] it was needless to inquire
                            further.</p>
                        <p>In relation to the charge of twice stoning Mr. Corbett, the testimony of
                            Wang I-chin and Kiang Kwan-kih was as follows: They were at a theatrical
                            performance at Hwa-yin on the 1st of December, as Mr. Corbett rode by on
                            a horse, and some persons picked up stones and sent them flying so that
                            he was hit. How could any one tell who it was, among such a crowd, that
                            picked up the stones? Also, on the 19th of the month, a great crowd was
                            collected at tue Yuh-hwang temple to get up a procession for the gods,
                            and Mr. C. began to preach near by: some persons in the multitude threw
                            stones to hit him, but nobody could well know who it was.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Corbett, on being called on for his evidence upon this matter, was
                            unable to point out the very persons; nor could those whom he brought as
                            witnesses to identify the guilty ones, and particularize which ones
                            threw the stones, and which hit him, as if they had seen it all with
                            their own eyes, tell me, when I questioned them myself as to their
                            proof, which were the very men, or bring any trustworthy evidence.</p>
                        <p>On further carefully sifting their evidence on this point, they averred
                            that the first man who picked up a stone at Hwa-yin was Wang Pao; and in
                            reference to the charge <pb facs="0392" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/> of
                            throwing stones at the Yuh-hwang temple, they said that there were many
                            people named Kiang in that village, and this man, Kiang Kwan-kih, was
                            head man of it, was present at the time of the fracas, and could not
                            restrain the people. Two others named Kiang Shau-sien and Kiang
                            Hwo-sien, were there, too, and cognizant of the facts. These were all
                            the facts which could be proved concerning the two occasions when stones
                            were thrown.</p>
                        <p>In relation to the charge of Mr. Corbett twice losing things, the
                            convert, Lin Lungméi, testified as follows: When Mr. C. returned to
                            Chefoo he left the care of all his effects in my hands and I hired a
                            donkey of one Wang Lih-sien to carry them to Ko fau. This last named
                            says that the villagers, Sü Yen-tsoh and Tu Kwang-tsūen, carried the
                            whole away with them, by force. On cross-questioning these two men they
                            declared that Wang Lih-sien owed Tu Kwang-tsuen, who, seeing him that
                            day going off leading a donkey tried to distrain it and the load as a
                            security for his claim. He could not tell how the things came to be
                            lost, but he never had any idea of stealing them. However, after the
                            trouble taken in this examination, he was quite willing to make good the
                            loss of the things taken at their fair price.</p>
                        <p>Two men, Wang Lih-sien and Wang Lih-hai, further gave evidence that in
                            the afternoon of that day the village constable, Wang Shi-kiai, and some
                            thirty others went to Mr. Corbett’s hired house, at Ko-fau, broke into
                            it and carried off all the clothes and furniture and destroyed the doors
                            and windows. I then asked this constable about it, who said that he and
                            Li Pah, Sun Shi-tang, and three others went to Ko-fau; and hearing that
                            Mr. C. had returned to Chefoo they started off to see his chapel. They
                            urged one Wang Lih-hao to open the doors for them to go in and then went
                            out after looking about them; but half a score of other fellows whom he
                            did not know rushed in at the same time. He did not know at all what
                            things were lost, but had no intention of robbing anything, and was
                            willing to compensate for the articles lost.</p>
                        <p>Such being the facts, I judged that as Tu Kwang-tsūen led away the donkey
                            under the idea of distraining it for debt, and Wang Shi-kiai and the
                            crowd went into the house without any intention of robbing, and both
                            were willing to pay the value of the things lost, it was needless for us
                            to examine them any further. The consul also-agreed that this was
                            sufficient. These are the circumstances connnected with the double
                            robbery of Mr. Corbett.</p>
                        <p>The eleventh article of the American treaty provides that subjects of
                            China, guilty of any criminal act toward citizens of the United States,
                            shall be punished by the authorities of China according to the laws of
                            China; and I find that our statutes lay down eighty blows of the bamhoo
                            as the heaviest punishment for doing wrong without previous
                            intention.</p>
                        <p>In this case Wang I-chin and Wang Shi-kiai both hold the post of village
                            constables. When the row began they could not restrain the crowd, and
                            made no report of their violence; the last-named also led people into
                            the house, whereby many small things were lost.</p>
                        <p>The man Kiang Kwan-kih is a village elder; he was unable to restrain his
                            sons and nephews; and having been at the theater himself, he is
                            responsible for what happened there. All of these are amenable to the
                            above law, and each of them is sentenced to receive eighty blows.</p>
                        <p>Wang Pao, who threw the first stone, and Kiang Shau-sien, who was at both
                            the-frays, are each sentenced to sixty blows. Kiang Hwo-sien, who
                            participated in one of them only, is sentenced to forty blows. Tu
                            Kwan-tsūen, and the others who carried off the donkey, pretending that
                            it was for a debt, with Wang Shi-kiai, and those who entered the house,
                            whereby many things were lost, have all agreed to repay their cost. The
                            latter must, after he has done so, be dismissed from his post as
                            constable; and the two with him may receive their pardon. Seventeen
                            others, who were not proved to have joined in the riot, were liberated
                            there in open court; while those sentenced to be beaten were punished in
                            accordance therewith, and then sent home. Tu Kwang-tsūen, and those
                            ordered to pay the 380 taels for the things lost, as the list handed in
                            by the consul stated, were detained until the money was paid to Mr.
                            Corbett.</p>
                        <p>I have also issued a proclamation, stating distinctly, that whenever Mr.
                            Corbett goes to Chimi district to teach religion, and quietly attends to
                            his proper vocation, he will be protected according to the treaty. He is
                            not to be molested in any way. So there is hope that now all parties
                            will live in peace.</p>
                        <p>I now send all the papers connected with the case, the details of the
                            examination and the circumstances of the closing, arranged in order for
                            your inspection, and have the honor to request that this affair may be
                            reported to the foreign office as having been satisfactorily
                            settled.</p>
                        <p>On receiving the above, I (the superintendent of the northern ports)
                            having separated the papers in this case, now send up the clear report
                            which I have made, and have the honor to request that the conduct and
                            finishing of this case may be looked into.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0393" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 12 in No. 44.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Corbett</persName> and
                                others to Mr. <persName type="to">Sheppard</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chefoo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-04"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 4,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The undersigned, citizens of the United States of America, residing at
                            Chefoo and Tungchow, desire to express their thanks to Eli T. Sheppard,
                            esq., United States consul for Tien-tsin and Chefoo, for the energy and
                            efficiency which he has displayed in prosecuting the case relating to
                            the recent disturbance at Chimi.</p>
                        <p>The difficulties inherent in the case, together with the obstacles thrown
                            in the way by the Chinese officials, and their determined and persistent
                            opposition to take any proper action to elicit the truth, made the
                            affair an especially difficult one. Fortunately Mr. Sheppard knew his
                            rights, and firmly insisted upon having them acknowledged.</p>
                        <p>His determination to uphold and vindicate the honor of his country, and
                            the satisfactory settlement which he has received, give us a high
                            appreciation of him as a man and a worthy representative of our
                            Government in China.</p>
                        <closer><signed><list>
                                    <item>HUNTER CORBETT.</item>
                                    <item>CHARLES R. MILLS.</item>
                                    <item>C. W. MATEER.</item>
                                    <item>J. L. NEVINS.</item>
                                    <item>J. B. HARTWELL.</item>
                                    <item>S. P. CRAWFORD</item>
                                    <item>L. W. ECKARD.</item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>