<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                    <head>No. 177.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Scruggs</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogota</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-11-17"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 17, 1873</date>.
                            (Received December 18.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 19.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The State of Panama being so remote and
                        inaccessible from this capital, and the mails so infrequent and irregular,
                        that, up to this time, I have been wholly unable to advise the Department of
                        the condition of affairs there, for the reason that it was impossible to
                        obtain reliable information here.</p>
                    <p>My latest reliable intelligence from that locality is up to the 27th ultimo.
                        At that time, the political troubles seemed to be over, at least for a
                        season. General Correoso, the insurgent chief, had retreated to the
                        interior, most of his followers having forsaken him, and the supposition was
                        that he was then making his way to Costa Rica. The government of General
                        Niere seemed firmly established, and the State legislature, then in session,
                        had conferred upon him dictatorial powers. His acts have been arbitrary in
                        the extreme; nor does he now hesitate to <pb facs="0448" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/> employ to their fullest extent the extraordinary
                        powers thus conferred upon him. His government, in short, is a despotism
                        under the flattering cognomen of a republic, and yet without any of those
                        guarantees to life and property which a strong government is presumed to
                        establish. Arbitrary arrests are of daily occurrence, and while the criminal
                        code of this country humanely spares the life of convicted murderers, petty
                        officials scruple not to order any citizen to be shot who may hesitate to
                        obey their behests. Forced loans are imposed and collected at the point of
                        the bayonet. The amount thus decreed to be paid by property-owners of Panama
                        is $60,000, and this sum is now being rapidly collected. As yet, however, no
                        foreign resident has been taxed.</p>
                    <p>During the late insurrection much property was destroyed. Dwellings and
                        stores were sacked in the most savage manner. Among the sufferers are said
                        to be some American citizens, who have made application to Consul Long for
                        redress and compensation, but their names and locality are unknown to me.
                        The presence of the’ United States marines in Panama had a most happy
                        effect, and but for the prompt action of Admiral Almy, the desolation would
                        doubtless have been more general.</p>
                    <p>There has been, and is still, a general feeling of insecurity among foreign
                        residents and property-owners, especially among those interested in the
                        Panama Bail road. The federal government seems wholly powerless to afford
                        protection to foreign interests there, and even here, in Bogota, there seems
                        developing a public sentiment that the isthmus is merely a source of
                        weakness and expense.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c., * * * *</p>
                    <closer><signed>WILLIAM L. SCRUGGS.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>