<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 201.Mr. Wing
                            to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-08-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-08-28T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807" lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107724" lcsh-match="exact">Protestants</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85149842" lcsh-match="exact">Zinc</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-08-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-08-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="203" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d203">
                <head>No. 201.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wing</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Quito,
                                Ecuador</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 28, 1873</date>.
                            (Received October 2.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 326.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch 319, concerning the
                        death of William C. Doval, I desire to make the following statement:</p>
                <p>Upon my return from Guayaquil, while lying ill in Ambato, I received a copy
                        of a publication made by certain American citizens resident in Quito,
                        offering a regard of $100 for the detection of the author of a shameful
                        outrage upon the grave of the said Mr. Doval.</p>
                <p>I inclose a copy and translation, Nos. 1 and 2, of this document.</p>
                <p>So soon after my arrival in Quito as I was able to dictate a note, I
                        addressed a communication (No. 3) on this subject to the government of
                        Ecuador.</p>
                <pb facs="0481" n="385" xml:id="pg_385"/>
                <p>After a delay of several days, I received a reply, of which Nos. 4 and 5 are
                        copy and translation.</p>
                <p>On the succeeding day 1 addressed a second note (No. 6) to Minister Leon, on
                        the same subject. In reply thereto I received his note, No. 7, of date 21st
                        of August, of which No. 8 is a translation.</p>
                <p>It will be observed that Minister Leon seemed disposed to controvert my
                        statement that the outrage upon the grave of Mr. Doval was the third
                        occurrence of the kind of which I had informed him during my official
                        residence in Quito.</p>
                <p>On the succeeding day, however, I was the recipient of a note, of which Nos.
                        9 and 10 are copy and translation, which, to a considerable extent,
                        precluded the necessity of an answer to Minister Leon’s note of the
                        preceding day.</p>
                <p>On the night of the 22d of August Minister Leon called at my room where I am
                        still confined with inflammatory rheumatism, and in the’ presence of the
                        English minister resident, Hon. Frederick Hamilton, stated to me in so many
                        words that, in his note of the same day, he fully meant to admit that I had
                        previously informed him of the outrage upon the grave of Colonel Phineas E.
                        Staunton, assuring me, however, that for the time he had utterly forgotten
                        the facts in relation to the violation of the graves of Mr. Minister
                        Coggeshall and Colonel Staunton, some three or four years since.</p>
                <p>These facts, the Department will find explicitly set forth in my dispatch No.
                        29 of September 13, 1870.</p>
                <p>I likewise have the honor to inclose copy of a note addressed to me by
                        Minister Hamilton, in regard to the interview between Minister Leon and
                        myself, which incidentally occurred in his presence.</p>
                <p>Both Minister Hamilton and myself were of the opinion, upon examination, that
                        Minister Neal’s grave had likewise been desecrated.</p>
                <p>I am not sure whether the Department is aware’ of the fact that the bodies of
                        Minister Coggeshall, of the United States, and of Minister Neal, of England,
                        remained unburied for more than one year after their respective deaths,
                        having been simply stored away in a room at one of the hospitals.</p>
                <p>This sad office was performed by Minister Hamilton, upon his arrival here in
                        the beginning of 1868.</p>
                <p>On the 22d of this month the police authorities of Quito, going outside of
                        the municipal limits of the city, presumed to force the gate of the
                        Protestant cemetery, although I am the custodian of the key thereof, and to
                        again disinter the body of Mr. Doval, without any notification to
                        myself.</p>
                <p>I immediately wrote a strong note to Minister Leon on the subject. He called
                        on me, however, before I had found time to forward it to him, and at his
                        urgent request I finally withheld it, as he promised to stringently rebuke
                        the police authorities, and attributed their act entirely to an ignorance of
                        the whereabouts of the key, and the impression which would be made thereby
                        upon their part.</p>
                <p>The chief of police also called upon me and vigorously apologized for the act
                        of his subordinates.</p>
                <p>It seems that they found the coffin of&gt;en, but that the body had its
                        burial-clothes upon it.</p>
                <p>I am thoroughly convinced, however, that these were replaced at the second
                        opening of the grave, which was occasioned by the fear of the reward offered
                        by the American citizens, referred to above.</p>
                <p>In this opinion I find that all the intelligent foreigners of Quito agree
                        with me.</p>
                <pb facs="0482" n="386" xml:id="pg_386"/>
                <p>Great feeling hits been occasioned among the foreigners resident in Quito by
                        the outrage.</p>
                <p>I must candidly say that the government of Ecuador has shown great desire to
                        detect and punish the criminals, and the President has exhibited a warm
                        personal interest therein.</p>
                <p>Colonel Staunton’s tombstone, presented by the Smithsonian Institution,
                        Williams College, and Ingham University, has not yet been recovered.</p>
                <p>I have not received copies of all the evidence taken in the case, but will
                        forward it so soon as I hold it entire. Trusting that my action will receive
                        the approval of the Department,</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>RUMSEY WING.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 326.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">$100 REWARD.</p>
                    <p>We, the undersigned, offer a reward of $100 to the person who delivers to
                            us the authors of the exhumation and robbery of the grave of the
                            deceased North American, William Doval, in the Protestant cemetary of
                            the Ejido, leaving his nude body upon the ground.</p>
                    <p>Any information that can be given, will be received at the house of the
                            North American minister.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>CARLOS KAISER,</item>
                                <item>DR. WILSON,</item>
                                <item>FRANCISCO SCHMIDT,</item>
                                <item>WILLIAM SAEGER,</item>
                                <item>ARTHUR ROGERS,</item>
                                <item>FREDERICK WOODHOUSE,</item>
                                <item>FREDERICK FULLER,</item>
                                <item>S. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">De</hi> FOREST,</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p rend="flushleft">and all the North American residents of this
                                city.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-07-25">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 25,
                                        1873</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 326.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wing</persName> to Señor
                                    <persName type="to">Leon</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Quito,
                                        Ecuador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 12,
                                1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 16th of last month William C.
                            Doval, an American citizen resident in this country, died in one of the
                            hospitals of this city. On the subsequent day he was buried in the
                            Protestant cemetery. On the succeeding night the gate of the cemetery
                            was forced, the grave of Mr. Doval opened, the clothing torn from his
                            person, and his nude body left upon the ground.</p>
                    <p>In my absence, the American citizens in Quito offered a reward for the
                            detection of the perpetrators of this foul act of desecration, of the
                            publication of which I inclose a copy.</p>
                    <p>The body of Mr. Doval was again interred, and a second time was torn from
                            its resting-place.</p>
                    <p>It is with the most painful sensations that I call the attention of your
                            excellency to the fact that this is the third occurrence of the kind
                            which I have laid before your excellency during my short official
                            residence in this capital.</p>
                    <p>I am not disposed to believe that these outrages were performed by the
                            common Indians of the country, as general report has it.</p>
                    <p>I need not assure your excellency of the intense feeling which will not
                            only arise in my own country, hut throughout Europe, when a knowledge of
                            these outrages upon the bodies of Protestants deceased in Ecuador
                            becomes public.</p>
                    <p>I have been informed that certain clews had been placed in the hands of
                            the police of this city, which, if intelligently and honestly followed
                            up, would lead to the conviction of the guilty parties. I cannot learn,
                            however, that any efficient steps have been taken to that end.</p>
                    <pb facs="0483" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/>
                    <p>Moreover, I desire to add that the tombstone over the grave of Colonel
                            Staunton, one of the most distinguished scientific men of the United
                            States, was stolen from its pedestal upon the night of the second
                            desecration of Mr. Doval’s grave.</p>
                    <p>I respectfully but decidedly request the co-operation of the Ecuadorian
                            government in the detection of the parties implicated in these acts of
                            infamy, and for the future I ask that some steps be taken to prevent a
                            repetition thereof.</p>
                    <p>With assurances of my very distinguished consideration, I have,
                            &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RUMSEY WING.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His excellency Señor <hi rend="smallcaps">Francisco Javier
                                    Leon</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                                    &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No.
                                326.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Leon</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Wing</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office of Ecuador</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Quito</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 19,
                                1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, minister for foreign affairs for Ecuador, has had the
                            honor to receive and lay before His Excellency the President of the
                            republic your excellency’s esteemed note of date 12th of the present
                            month, in which your excellency informs the undersigned of the outrage
                            that on two occasions has been committed by the disinterment of the body
                            of Mr. W. C. Doval, an American citizen, who died in this city on the
                            16th of July last, and who was interred in the Protestant cemetery in
                            this city; and also that the marble tombstone on the grave of Colonel
                            Staunton was stolen from its pedestal.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned, previous to the reception of the indicated note of your
                            excellency, was informed by Mr. Arthur A. Rogers of the particulars of
                            this event, and, in virtue thereof, hastened to give the most stringent
                            orders to the police authorities to inquire into the facts set
                            forth.</p>
                    <p>In effect, these formalities having been completed, it appeared that no
                            trace whatever existed of the mentioned crime of exhumation except the
                            forcing of the lock of the door.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned, doubting the exactness of the assertion in this respect,
                            and subsequent to the reception of the dispatch which he has now the
                            honor to answer, ordered anew an examination of the facts, and the
                            direction of the “procès-verbal,” an authentic copy of which your
                            excellency will find inclosed.</p>
                    <p>As this throws no light upon the perpetrators of the grave crime now
                            being investigated, the undersigned hopes that your excellency will be
                            satisfied with the activity and zeal of the government in the
                            elucidation of the affair, which, were it certain, the government would
                            have deplored like your excellency—a scandalous act of profanation,
                            committed in the heart of a republic essentially humane and
                            respectable.</p>
                    <p>In addition, the undersigned assures your excellency that he has the
                            impression that, up to the present time, no information has reached him
                            of any act of this nature, when all possible means would have been used
                            looking to the punishment of the guilty parties.</p>
                    <p>With assurances, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FRANCISCO-JAVIER LEON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No. 326.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wing</persName> to Señor
                                    <persName type="to">Leon</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Quito,
                                        Ecuador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 20,
                                1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I had the honor to receive your
                            excellency’s note of yesterday last evening.</p>
                    <p>I am indebted for the efforts which your excellency’s government is
                            making to ascertain the perpetrators of the outrage upon the grave of
                            Mr. Doval.</p>
                    <p>I am likewise fully persuaded that your excellency’s government regards
                            such acts of sacrilege with indignation and regret.</p>
                    <p>May I request, if any further evidence is taken in the premises, that I
                            be furnished with copies thereof also?</p>
                    <p>I trust that the search for the culprits will be rigidly prosecuted, and
                            that the beautiful marble tombstone stolen from the grave of Colonel
                            Staunton will be found.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, your excellency will pardon me for referring to certain
                            circumstances which will, I am confident, recall to your excellency’s
                            memory the fact that your excellency has previously heard of similar
                            outrages.</p>
                    <pb facs="0484" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/>
                    <p>On reference to the archives of this legation, I find that in the first
                            part of the month of September, 1870, (while I was making preparations
                            for the disinterment of the body of my predecessor, Mr. Coggeshall,) I
                            was informed that previous to my arrival at this capital the grave of
                            Colonel Phineas E. Staunton had been violated, and that his body had
                            been reinterred by certain of the police authorities, and that Mr.
                            Coggeshall’s grave had also been opened.</p>
                    <p>I was in the very act of addressing an official note to your excellency
                            on the subject when your excellency did me the honor to pay me a visit
                            at the office of my legation, in reference to the arrangements for the
                            transmission of Mr. Coggeshall’s body to Guayaquil. I then and there
                            verbally made known to your excellency, through the agency of a
                            distinguished gentleman now in Quito, what I had learned in regard to
                            the profanation of the graves of Mr. Coggeshall and Colonel Staunton.
                            Your excellency immediately promised to give stringent orders to the
                            police authorities to do all in their power to ferret out the
                            perpetrators thereof.</p>
                    <p>I was afterward the recipient of a note from your excellency of date
                            September 10, 1870, in which I was informed that your excellency had
                            hastened to put a knowledge of the outrage before the superintendent of
                            police, in order that he might take the proper steps in relation
                            thereto.</p>
                    <p>Subsequently, I informed your excellency, that upon the disinterment of
                            the body of Mr. Coggeshall, it was ascertained that his wooden coffin
                            had likewise been broken open, and that a portion of the interior metal
                            coffin had been cut off and taken away, whilst the remains of the
                            coffins, with the body inclosed, had been carelessly thrown hack into
                            the grave, without any regard to position whatever.</p>
                    <p>In this matter I spoke advisedly, as I, in common with the English
                            minister and a number of other foreign gentlemen, was present on the
                            occasion.</p>
                    <p>Feeling assured that your excellency upon reflection will recall these
                            facts, and regretting that I am compelled to refer to matters so
                            unpleasant of themselves,</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RUMSEY WING.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Señor <hi rend="smallcaps">Francisco Javier
                                    Leon</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                                    &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 8 in No. 326.—T
                                ranslation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Leon</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Wing</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office of Ecuador, Quito</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 21, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I have had the honor to receive your excellency’s esteemed communication
                            of yesterday, and in reply, I am happy to inform your excellency that
                            when possible I shall not fail to forward to your excellency everything
                            that is discovered about the author or authors of the disinterment of
                            the body of Mr. Doval, as the police authorities will continue their
                            investigations.</p>
                    <p>I have as much interest as your excellency in the detection of this
                            crime.</p>
                    <p>With assurances, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FRANCISCO JAVIER LEON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 10 in No.
                                326.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Leon</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Wing</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office of Ecuador, Quito</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 22, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, minister of foreign affairs of Ecuador, has the honor to
                            address his excellency, the minister resident of the United States of
                            America, with the object of rectifying the idea contained in his
                            communication of the 19th of the present month, as he did not remember
                            at the time that other acts of violation of graves had occurred; but now
                            having inspected the archives of this department, he has seen that in
                            effect your excellency addressed the undersigned, notifying him that an
                            act of this nature had occurred in the grave of Mr. Coggeshall, and that
                            in consequence thereof the government of the undersigned used every
                            measure in its power to discover and punish the culprits, as was
                            communicated to your excellency on September 10, 1873.</p>
                    <p>Thus rectifying the idea alluded to, I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FRANCISCO JAVIER LEON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0485" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 11 in No. 326.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hamilton</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Wing</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British
                                        Legation, Quito</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 24,
                                1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In compliance with the request
                            contained in your note of yesterday, I beg to state that in the
                            interview which took place on the 22d instant between you andf Señor
                            Javier Leon, minister for foreign affairs, his excellency frankly
                            admitted that you had personally brought to his knowledge the outrages
                            perpetrated on the graves of Mr. Minister Coggeshall, and Colonel
                            Staunton.</p>
                    <p>As I was present at the disinterment of the body of Mr. Coggeshall, I
                            remember perfectly well that on arriving at the site of the grave, the
                            ground had every appearance of having been disturbed, and that upon
                            removing the earth which covered the coffin, I observed that the upper
                            outer lid was broken in several places, and that half of the top of the
                            inner zinc coffin had been completely removed and doubtless stolen, as
                            no traces of it were to be found in any part of the grave.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FREDERICK HAMILTON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rumsey Wing</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Minister Resident in Quito.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
