<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 215.Mr. Wing to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">217</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="217"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                <head>No. 215.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wing</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Quito, Ecuador</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-08-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 11, 1874</date>. (Received September
                        9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 408.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Hereto I append copy and translation (Nos. 1 and
                    2) of a recent correspondence between the fiscal agent of this government and
                    certain prominent merchants, bankers, and commercial men of Guayaquil, in
                    reference to the late financial crisis in Ecuador, which seriously imperiled the
                    monetary and business interests of the country.</p>
                <p>The effect of this correspondence, superadded to the proposed abolition of the
                    executive decree prohibiting the exportation of silver in bars and certain
                    silver coins, has been beneficial.</p>
                <p>Exchange has fallen to a decent figure, trade is reviving, confidence being
                    restored, and the Bank of Ecuador has issued a call for the payment in full of
                    its capital stock, and offers to redeem its outstanding notes whenever
                    presented.</p>
                <p>The roads (rail and turnpike) are again in course of construction also.</p>
                <p>The cost of the ecclesiastic establishments and their accompaniments in Ecuador
                    constitutes a serious and needless drain upon the national revenue, and is out
                    of all proportion to the wealth and resources of the republic.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>RUMSEY WING.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0495" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 408.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[From Los Andes, of Guayaquil, July 29, 1874.]</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the question of the day</hi>.</p>
                    <p>We have been requested to publish the following documents, through which will
                        be seen the result of the commission that has brought the under secretary of
                        the treasury, Doctor Salazar, to this city.</p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Note of Doctor Salazar.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Republic of Ecuador, Fiscal Commission</hi>,<lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Guayaquil</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-07-20">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 20, 1874</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Messrs. Alcides Destruge, José Vivero, and José
                                Rosales:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: Desirous of giving a quick and
                            efficacious solution of the matter relative to the loan which was
                            offered to be made to the government, and of the abrogation of the
                            prohibition of the exportation of silver, I believe it expedient to
                            propose to you, as representatives of the merchants of this place: <list>
                                <label>1st.</label>
                                <item>To deposit in the Bank of Ecuador the sum of $200,000, in
                                    discharge of the account known as “loans to the
                                    government.”</item>
                                <label>2d.</label>
                                <item>The deposit being made, bonds in favor of the subscribers will
                                    be issued at 1 per cent, monthly.</item>
                                <label>3d.</label>
                                <item>These bonds will be funded, receiving in payment the
                                    custom-house receipts, for which 25 per cent, will be set
                                    aside.</item>
                                <label>4th.</label>
                                <item>The loan of $500,000 being accomplished, counting the $300,000
                                    that the bank will take, a free exportation of silver will be
                                    declared, preserving solely the right of exportation according
                                    to law.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Please, gentlemen, submit this fact to the exchange, and communicate to
                            me the result thereof, so that I may consider my mission terminated.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>VICENTE LUCIO SALAZAR.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Answer.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Guayaquil</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-07-23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 23, 1874</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Vicente Lucio Salazar, esq., Fiscal Agent</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your communication of the 20th was placed in our hands yesterday, and we
                            informed the merchants who had met, with this object, last evening, in
                            the saloon of the Exchange, of the contents thereof.</p>
                        <p>Taking into consideration the matter, and unanimously resolved, we are
                            charged to inform you that the signers of the proposal, a copy of which
                            is annexed, and which, on the 8th of this month, we had the honor to
                            inform you of, that they were ready to keep their word under the
                            conditions set forth in that proposal; but aside from that, it is
                            enough, which you deemed it well to present, and the monetary crisis,
                            without exaggeration having made money scarcer every day, the merchants
                            deplore the bad state of the situation that deprives them of the
                            pleasure of accepting in full your proposal, and to improve the occasion
                            to prove to the supreme government their desire to enter into its views
                            and assist it in the measure which it, as well as the merchants, judge
                            really advantageous for all.</p>
                        <p>But if the efforts of the merchants of Guayaquil, of which you are aware,
                            having been present, have not been sufficient to give to your commission
                            the favorable result which the supreme government and the merchants
                            nattered themselves, permit us to hope from your honor and worth, that
                            when you give an account of your trust, you will manifest the good faith
                            of the merchants in this matter, as also the necessity they have to
                            improve the conditions of the market, which they are mindful of, and
                            decide favorably their petition to the supreme government of the 18th
                            ult.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>JOSÉ ROSALES.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>JOSÉ VIVERO.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>ALCIDES DESTRUGE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Proposal of the merchants.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>The undersigned agree to take the bonds of the government if they are
                            issued at 90 per cent., with 12 per cent, annual interest, redeemable
                            with one-half of the customs-dues; that is, the merchants will pay their
                            customs-dues one-half in bonds, and the other half in current money; but
                            provided, that the government will allow the free exportation of silver,
                            and suspend every privilege in respect to the change of bank-bills,
                            leaving gold and silver money at their legal value and keeping in all
                            force the existing bank-laws.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow the names of thirty-one individuals and firms, subscribing
                            in gross the sum of $125,000 (soft or Ecuadorian currency) to the
                            proposed loan.]</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
