<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 275.Mr. Fish
                            to Mr. Davis.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d277</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">277</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558" lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-11-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                <head>No. 275.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Davis</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 14,
                            1874</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 24.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your No. 33, under date of the 20th of October
                        last, narrating your interview with Mr. von Bülow at the foreign office in
                        relation to the objection interposed by the German government to allowing
                        consuls of the United States to serve as commissioners to take testimony to
                        be used in judicial proceedings pending in this country, has been
                        received.</p>
                <p>Your representations to the minister are approved.</p>
                <p>Although Mr. von Bülow stated to you that instructions on the subject bad
                        been sent to Mr. von Schlözer a fortnight prior to your interview and
                        conversation, nothing has been heard from that gentleman in this connection.
                        The objection interposed by the German government to the obtaining of
                        testimony in Germany to be used in the courts of this country is much to be
                        regretted, and as appears from the admission made to you by Mr. von Bülow,
                        the Germans whose interests led them to resist the taking of the testimony,
                        and who invoked the interposition of their government to prevent it, are now
                        known to have been in the wrong. It would have been quite as satisfactory to
                        this Government had the reply of the German government on a subject
                        presented to their consideration, through the representative of this
                        Government at Berlin, been communicated also through him, and, as is shown,
                        some delay which has occurred might have been avoided.</p>
                <p>As Mr. von Schlözer has not communicated the answer of his government, it
                        will not be amiss that you inform Mr. von Bülow that we are still without
                        any reply. You will call his attention to the fact that the suit in which
                        the testimony is sought is one in which the Government of the United States
                        is itself a party.</p>
                <p>I inclose herewith copies of existing statutes (which are embodied in
                        sections 4071, 4072, 4073, and 4074 of the Revised Statutes of the United
                        States) enacted by this Government to insure to other powers the opportunity
                        of obtaining testimony in this country in any suit for the recovery of money
                        or property depending in any court in any foreign <pb facs="0558" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> country with which the United States are at peace, and
                        in which the government of such foreign country shall be a party or shall
                        have an interest.</p>
                <p>In these enactments, which have long been in force in this country, this
                        Government has manifested its friendship to other powers, as well as its
                        desire to aid in the administration of justice in all foreign countries with
                        which it may be at peace.</p>
                <p>It is hoped that the answer of the German government may soon be
                        communicated, and that it will be such as shall evince a willingness to
                        reciprocate the very liberal and efficient provisions made in this country
                        to enable Germany, in case of need, to obtain the evidence of witnesses in
                        this country in any suit in which that government may be interested and that
                        the facilities which Mr. von Bülow says that Germany will afford in this
                        direction may prove ample and efficacious.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
