<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title>No. 281.General Schenck to Mr. Fish.</title>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <settingDesc>
                                <setting>
                                        <date notBefore="1873-07-26T00:00:00-05:00"
                                                notAfter="1873-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                                </setting>
                        </settingDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                                        <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic"
                                                category="science-and-technology"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                                        <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                                                category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                                                subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                                                lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                                        <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                                        <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic"
                                                category="uncategorized" subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                                        <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                                                >Tariffs</term>
                                        <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                                        <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                                        <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>
                        <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="283"
                                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                                <head>No. 281.<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from"
                                                  >Schenck</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                                                  >Fish</persName>.</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                                                <placeName>
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                                  States</hi>,<lb/>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                                  when="1873-07-26">
                                                  <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26, 1873</date>.
                                                (Received August 21.)</dateline>
                                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 460.]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your No. 412, inclosing a
                                        copy of a communication addressed to you by Mr. Orton, the
                                        president of the Western Union Telegraph Company, was duly
                                        received. I have also seen Mr. Orton’s letter widely
                                        published in the newspapers.</p>
                                <p>I propose now to make that somewhat remarkable paper the subject
                                        of comment, and I trust that the same publicity which has
                                        been given to it, and to my dispatch to you to which it
                                        purports to be a reply, will be given to this, my
                                        answer.</p>
                                <p>What was the information which I gave the Department for such use
                                        in the public interest as it might be deemed proper to make
                                        of it? I stated that an arrangement existed between the
                                        Anglo-American Cable Company and the Western Union Company,
                                        under which the former <pb facs="0567" n="471"
                                                xml:id="pg_471"/> company charges and collects on
                                        all messages sent from England to points west and south of
                                        New York, for that part of the service which lies within the
                                        United States, double, or more than double the rates which
                                        are charged by the Western Union Company for the like
                                        service at home, and this Mr. Orton does not deny. He makes
                                        a show of denying it; but his answer is evasive and
                                        disingenuous, and furnishes only a striking example of the
                                        way in which a person, having no good defense, may seem to
                                        escape under cover of immaterial issues, while not in the
                                        slightest degree meeting the complaint which is really made.
                                        Let us see if I state this too strongly.</p>
                                <p>1. In my communication to you I said that I believed the contract
                                        between the two companies provided for a division between
                                        them of the receipts from this land-service in the
                                        proportion of one-third to the Anglo-American and two thirds
                                        to the Western Union, and I went on to illustrate how
                                        profitable would be to the Western Union such dividing of
                                        the overcharge, inasmuch as such receipt of two-thirds would
                                        quite exceed the whole proper charge made under the home
                                        tariff of that company. Mr. Orton denies fiercely and with
                                        much ostentation that the agreement between the companies
                                        provides for a division of the charges for the service of
                                        his company in that proportion. All I have to say on that
                                        point is, that I learned, from what I supposed to be a
                                        reliable and well-informed source, that such was the nature
                                        of the agreement.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Orton himself knows, better than any outsider can, what
                                        really are now, or have been heretofore, the exact terms of
                                        the contract, and can remove all doubt, if he thinks proper
                                        so to do, by publishing the actual documentary proof. This,
                                        however, is not the question. It is not the public
                                        complaint. This is merely asserting that a mistake has been
                                        made in stating the manner of division of the spoil. It is
                                        of little consequence to the public how the parties
                                        apportion the excessive rates between them. It is of far
                                        more interest to discover that they have been imposing and
                                        collecting such exorbitant rates.</p>
                                <p>2. Mr. Orton attempts to meet the exposure of these overcharges
                                        for the land service on his lines in the United States by
                                        asking attention to the reduced rates charged by the
                                        Anglo-American Company for messages sent on government
                                        account. This, again, is avoiding the issue. On careful
                                        examination of the quarterly bills which have been rendered
                                        and paid here for ocean-cable service, I find that the rates
                                        vary, being sometimes half the tariff charge, sometimes more
                                        than the full charge, depending apparently in part, but not
                                        entirely, upon the fact whether the messages were altogether
                                        or any portion of them in cipher. But what has this to do
                                        with the rates, doubled or more than doubled, over the wires
                                        of the Western Union Company? Nothing whatever; and Mr.
                                        Orton himself furnishes that answer in his own express
                                        language, when he says, “instead of the rate of four
                                        shillings and threepence a word, London to Washington, the
                                        State Department pays only two shillings and threepence.”
                                        Thus showing that even if a reduction is made to the
                                        Government, it is only on the cable-service from England to
                                        America, and does not apply to the excessive rates collected
                                        here for the use of the lines in the United States.</p>
                                <p>As to messages coming the other way, that is, “from Washington or
                                        other points in the United States, to be transmitted by the
                                        cable to England,” I have, in my former letter to you,
                                        distinctly stated that “I have no means of knowing whether
                                        they are subjected to the same or similar overcharges or
                                        not.” Any reference, therefore, in Mr. Orton’s letter to
                                        messages from the United States to England was uncalled for,
                                                <pb facs="0568" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> and could
                                        have been introduced only for the purpose of withdrawing
                                        attention from the real issue.</p>
                                <p>So much for the plain, simple, substantive complaint embodied in
                                        my letter to you. It was a complaint first brought to my
                                        knowledge by respectable banking and commercial houses here,
                                        who had discovered that they were thus imposed on, in being
                                        compelled to pay, in addition to the heavy cost for the
                                        transmission of their telegrams across the ocean, a rate of
                                        charges for their passing over the wires in the United
                                        States so greatly in excess of the charges regularly made in
                                        America. I was asked if I could give an explanation. I could
                                        not. But I thought, as others concerned did, that anything
                                        thus injuriously and unfairly affecting easy, cheap, and
                                        rapid correspondence between countries having such
                                        necessary, intimate, and constant relations as Great Britain
                                        and the United States, was well worthy of investigation, and
                                        exposure if need be, with a view to correction of the
                                        wrong.</p>
                                <p>I am glad to find that my movement in this direction has been
                                        successful.</p>
                                <p>In replying to and denying not the essential charge, but matters
                                        entirely collateral to the main fact, the president of the
                                        Western Union Company has made admissions and furnished
                                        information showing most clearly the existence of the unfair
                                        and extortionate practice complained of.</p>
                                <p>Before proceeding to verify this, I furnish and refer to, and
                                        request to have appended and made a part of this
                                        communication, the tariffs of charges of the Anglo-American
                                        Company and of the Western Union Company, respectively, as
                                        officially published by them in this country and in the
                                        United States. I believe no change, or no material change,
                                        has been made in the rates set forth in these tables; and I
                                        have assumed them therefore as the basis of my computations.
                                        With these tariffs before you, you will be better able to
                                        follow and comprehend my comments and figures.</p>
                                <p>First, then, let us see what is actually exacted and collected in
                                        England for transmission of messages over the wires of the
                                        Western Union lines to points beyond New York. If the tariff
                                        of the Anglo-American Company be analyzed, it will be found
                                        that the whole of that service beyond New York is divided
                                        (not into three, as Mr. Orton says, but) into five rates or
                                        classes of charges. These rates are for every word,
                                        including the date, address, and names of the sender and
                                        receiver.</p>
                                <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>Threepence (being equal to 6.951 cents) for each word
                                                for all stations within the District of Columbia,
                                                Delaware, Maryland, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and
                                                all places in New York outside of the city.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>Ninepence (equal to 20.87 cents) for each word for all
                                                stations in Alabama, Georgia, Illinois, Indiana,
                                                Kentucky, Louisiana, Michigan, Mississippi, North
                                                Carolina, Ohio, South Carolina, Tennessee, Virginia,
                                                Wisconsin, Saint Louis in Missouri, and Lake City,
                                                Saint Mark’s, and Tallahassee, in Florida.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>One shilling (equal to 27.83 cents) for each word for
                                                Pensacola, in Florida.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>Fifteen pence (equal to 34.785 cents) for each word
                                                for all stations in Arizona, Arkansas, California,
                                                Colorado, Dakota, Idaho, Iowa, Kansas, Minnesota,
                                                Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New Mexico, Texas, Utah,
                                                Wyoming, and all places in Missouri except Saint
                                                Louis.</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>Two shillings (equal to 55.66 cents) for each word for
                                                all stations in Oregon, Washington Territory, and
                                                all places in Florida except Lake City, Saint
                                                Mark’s, Tallahassee, and Pensacola.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>Now, comparing these charges with those which are given in the
                                        tariff <pb facs="0569" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> of the
                                        Western Union Company for the same service, it will be seen
                                        that they are in the average, as I have averred, double, or
                                        more than double, what are paid for sending over the same
                                        lines and to the same points at home.</p>
                                <p>In considering these extortionate overcharges, it is to be borne
                                        in mind, too, as I have in my former letter explained, that
                                        the excess is made greater by the fact that names, dates,
                                        and addresses are charged for in the one case and not in the
                                        other.</p>
                                <p>But it may be claimed that these several charges per
                                        word—threepence, ninepence, one shilling, fifteen pence, two
                                        shillings—do not amount, at great distances from New York,
                                        to double the charges, or, in some instances, to even as
                                        much as the charge made by the Western Union Company at
                                        home; but, then, let it be especially noted, that the charge
                                        of threepence a word, which is very nearly seven cents,
                                        additional to the ocean charge, is imposed for all that
                                        territory which lies within the limits of the District of
                                        Columbia, Delaware, Maryland, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and
                                        all places in New York outside of the city. Within this area
                                        are included the cities of Brooklyn, Jersey City, Albany,
                                        Buffalo, Newark, Philadelphia, Wilmington, Baltimore, and
                                        Washington. Within this area is transmitted and distributed,
                                        doubtless, a very large proportion of the whole business
                                        intelligence which passes by cable from England to the
                                        United States.</p>
                                <p>The regular charges of the Western Union at home for messages
                                        within this territory are generally 25, 30, or 40 cents for
                                        the first ten words, and only 2 to 3 cents per word for all
                                        over ten words.</p>
                                <p>Take for example Philadelphia. The difference is so much that I
                                        have been informed by a leading banking-house that, instead
                                        of sending telegrams through from hereto that city, they
                                        send only to New York, and have their agent there transmit
                                        them thence to Philadelphia. This in a large business is a
                                        great saving.</p>
                                <p>But these calculations can be readily made by any one having the
                                        aid of the accompanying two tables of charges. It is not
                                        necessary therefore to repeat instances by way of
                                        illustration. My computations in this, as in my former
                                        letter, are made on the basis of 109 for exchange, and 115
                                        for gold.</p>
                                <p>The fact of such excessive charges demanded and received by the
                                        Anglo-American Company, for that portion of service
                                        performed by the Western Union Company, stands proved then
                                        beyond all question or denial.</p>
                                <p>Now, what is Mr. Orton’s defense? As I have before said, he does
                                        not controvert what is thus alleged. He undertakes to show
                                        that the Western Union is not implicated, or a sharer, in
                                        these excessive rates. He says “there are more than 6,000
                                        telegraph stations in the United States, and it being
                                        impracticable to supply European offices with a tariff to
                                        each of such stations, this country is divided into four
                                        districts, for each of which a uniform rate is established.
                                        The cable rate of $1 per word between England and New York
                                        includes 8 cents a word, payable to the Western Union
                                        Telegraph Company for their part of the service. The rates
                                        beyond New York are, for all stations in New Jersey,
                                        Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, and District of Columbia,
                                        3 cents a word. For all other territory east of the
                                        Mississippi River, including the city of Saint Louis, 15
                                        cents a word. For all other stations in the United States,
                                        west of the Mississippi River, 20 cents a word.”</p>
                                <p>It is not clear to me what Mr. Orton wants to have understood by
                                        this statement. I suppose he means to aver that the
                                        proportion of the receipts allotted to the Western Union is
                                        an allowance of 3 cents, 15 <pb facs="0570" n="474"
                                                xml:id="pg_474"/> cents, or 20 cents per word for
                                        three classes of stations at different distances west and
                                        south of New York, and 8 cents additional for each word for
                                        that company’s part of the service east of New York. This
                                        would make his classification of the allowances to the
                                        Western Union aggregate 11 cents, 23 cents, and 28 cents.
                                        And this raises the question how much, or what part, of the
                                        service is performed by the Western Union Company before New
                                        York is reached? It must add greatly to the value of the
                                        general bargain, if, without reference to New York, 8 cents
                                        per word is received for every cable message sent anywhere
                                        in New England from the point where it reaches the United
                                        States. In any view of the case it is most evident that
                                        these receipts of 11 cents, or 23 cents, or 28 cents for the
                                        share of the Western Union for every word transmitted by
                                        cable beyond New York, are quite above its own regular
                                        charges. And Mr. Orton cannot escape from this proposition
                                        by calculations relating to particular remote points,
                                        without reference to the general average of business.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Orton, in all his instances of the prevailing number of words
                                        in a telegram, and which in the case of transmission between
                                        Chicago and New York he says were during one month down to
                                        an average of six, evidently leaves out of the calculation
                                        the names and addresses of the sender and the receiver of
                                        the message, which can certainly, in hardly any case, be
                                        less than four; and this would make an average of ten words
                                        charged for under the cable system. It is true he speaks of
                                        cable messages of two words; but it would puzzle one to know
                                        what sort of a message that could possibly be when names and
                                        addresses are counted and charged for.</p>
                                <p>But this, after all, as I have already said, is quite aside from
                                        the controversy between us. I may have been mistaken as to
                                        the exact proportion of advantage received by the Western
                                        Union in the division of this overcharge for service by its
                                        lines. I am not mistaken as to the excessive and exorbitant
                                        charges, which I have helped to expose. And the whole
                                        public, I believe, will unite with me in calling on the
                                        Western Union Company, and in calling on Mr. Orton, to see
                                        to it that this imposition is no longer continued.</p>
                                <p>But Mr. Orton’s reply to this demand is that the Western Union
                                        Company is in no sense responsible for the charges made by
                                        the Anglo-American Company; that “the cable business is
                                        controlled by the cable companies, who fix the rates to be
                                        charged, and make and modify the rules governing its
                                        conduct.” And yet in the same connection he admits that the
                                        Western Union Company has agreed to apply these rates and
                                        rules to cable messages in the United States, and to accept
                                        certain fixed rates for its compensation for all services on
                                        its own lines. This is, indeed, if we are to believe it, a
                                        sad condition of servitude. Are we to understand that the
                                        managers of the Western Union Company say to the foreign
                                        cable company, “Here are our lines spreading all over the
                                        United States; we are ready to receive and distribute all
                                        messages that you will send. We stipulate only for a certain
                                        share of your charges, which we will cheerfully and
                                        submissively accept as compensation satisfactory to us, and,
                                        that being paid, we care not what or how much you charge the
                                        citizens of the United States or of Great Britain for our
                                        work that we do for you. It may be a penny a word or a pound
                                        a word. That is nothing to us.”</p>
                                <p>Who can believe that the Western Union is so completely a
                                        neutral, or so entirely subject to the rule of a foreign
                                        corporation?</p>
                                <p>Two things, at least, are certain and beyond all dispute. (1.)
                                        There is an arrangement of some kind between the companies
                                        on the two sides <pb facs="0571" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/>
                                        of the Atlantic. (2.) And under that arrangement all persons
                                        who transmit messages from England beyond New York, pay at
                                        least twice as much for the use of the American lines as
                                        they would have to do for the same service in the United
                                        States.</p>
                                <p>Perhaps I owe it to myself not to close without referring to the
                                        fact that the reply made in behalf of the Western Union
                                        Company is garnished with flings and innuendoes against me.
                                        To this form of assault I have only to answer, that it is
                                        unworthy of Mr. Orton; and I should lack self-respect if I
                                        noticed such attempt to bolster up, by gross personality,
                                        the deficiency in a statement or an argument. I have
                                        character enough, I think, to be sufficient protection
                                        against falsehoods that are put forward only by cowardly
                                        insinuations; and I rest perfectly secure in the knowledge
                                        that if slander dares to take a bolder and more definite
                                        form, there are ample proofs to meet it.</p>
                                <p>But Mr. Orton goes out of his way also to intimate the existence
                                        of some influence exercised over me on the part of persons
                                        or associations whose interests are opposed to those of the
                                        corporations with which he is connected. This is another
                                        most mistaken conjecture. I have no interest, never have
                                        had, and do not expect to have, direct or indirect, in any
                                        cable telegraph company.</p>
                                <p>I do wish to see the day arise when the business will not be so
                                        much controlled by a monopolizing and absorbing combination,
                                        but reasonably cheapened to the public by the wholesome
                                        competition of rival lines. I look upon the continuance of
                                        such a monopoly as an obstruction now in the way of the
                                        great civilizing and peaceful influence to be hoped for from
                                        the cheapest possible transmission of intelligence between
                                        the remotest as well as the nearest parts of the earth.</p>
                                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                                <closer>
                                        <signed>ROBT. O. SCHENCK.</signed>
                                </closer>
                        </div>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
