<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 378.Mr. Bassett to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d380</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">380</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-05-21T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-05-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="380" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d380">
                <head>No. 378.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bassett</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port au
                                    Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-05-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 21, 1874</date>.
                            (Received June 20.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 310.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Asking your reference to my No. 299 of the
                        17th ultimo, and to my No. 305 of the 9th instant, I have the honor to state
                        that late in the afternoon of the 9th instant, Her Britannic Majesty’s
                        gun-vessel, Sea Gull, carrying three guns and one hundred men, under command
                        of Commander Stubbs, came into this harbor, where she still remains, in
                        response to the request of my colleague of Great Britain for the presence in
                        these waters of a war-ship during the public irregularities and inquietude
                        prevailing here; that in answer to a similar request from my colleague of
                        France, the French steam-frigate. La Magicienne, carrying thirty guns and
                        five hundred men, under command of Post Captain Guepart, Rear-Admiral
                        Thomasset being on board, cast anchor in the bay of Port au Prince on the
                        morning of the 10th instant, where she remained until day before yesterday
                        and then left for Newfoundland; and that on the 15th instant, a day behind
                        time, my colleague of the German Empire received an answer to his request
                        for the presence of a man-of-war of his government pending the uncertainties
                        of the public situation in Hayti, by the entry into this port of the German
                        corvette, Augusta, which carries ten guns and two hundred and thirty men,
                        under command of Baron von Goltz. She left the 19th instant, for
                        Jamaica.</p>
                <p>While lying at anchor here La Magicienne and the Augusta exchanged civilities
                        with the authorities of this government and with each other.</p>
                <p>Although the presence in these waters of war-vessels of their respective
                        governments has, as is thus shown, been judged desirable by the
                        representatives of the great powers, the United States, Great Britain,
                        France, and Germany, I venture for myself to hope now, but am by no means
                        yet quite certain, that any actual necessity which may have existed for such
                        friendly armed presence has begun for the moment to disappear. But I learn
                        from Her Britannic Majesty’s minister resident that as the Sea Gull will
                        probably leave in a day or two, he has asked for a national vessel of his
                        government to come to the harbor of Port au Prince on or about the 7th
                        proximo, and to remain during the elections and the choice of a President of
                        Hayti, two important prospective events which are alluded to in my No. 309
                        of even date, and my colleague of France, the Count de Lemont, informs me
                        that he expects here about the same time and for the same purpose the French
                        corvette, Duchayla.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EBENEZER D. BASSETT</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
