<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 418.Mr. Bingham to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d420</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">420</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-01-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="420" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d420">
                <head>No. 418.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation, Japan</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Yokohama</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-01-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 12, 1874</date>.
                            (Received February 21.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 41.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith a copy
                        of the speech of felicitation addressed to the Tenno by the diplomatic body,
                        through their dean, Sir Harry S. Parkes, at the audience granted them by His
                        Majesty on New Year’s day, and also a copy of the Tenno’s reply.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. A. BINGHAM.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 41.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Address of the <gloss type="from">foreign
                                    representatives</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Mikado on the
                                    new year</gloss>
                        </hi>, 1874.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sire</hi>: In the name of the foreign
                            representatives accredited to Your Majesty’s court, I beg to convey to
                            Your Majesty our united congratulations on the occasion of the year now
                            commencing, and to express our sincere hope that it may be marked
                            throughout its course by much personal happiness to Your Majesty and by
                            increasing prosperity to your country.</p>
                    <p>Your Majesty will doubtless have learned with satisfaction from your
                            embassadors, who have lately returned to Japan, how friendly are the
                            sentiments which are entertained toward Your Majesty by our respective
                            sovereigns and rulers, and how cordially <pb facs="0756" n="660" xml:id="pg_660"/> they desire that, by the removal of all barriers
                            to free intercourse in the interior of your country between their
                            respective subjects and citizens and those of Your Majesty, the fullest
                            advantage may be derived from the happy relations which already exist
                            between Japan and their respective states. We feel satisfied that these
                            wishes are reciprocated by Your Majesty, and we therefore trust that the
                            efforts of Your Majesty’s government will be entirely directed to the
                            advancement of measures which are calculated to promote so desirable an
                            object, and to permit the natural expansion of those material interests
                            which form the closest bond of union between states.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 52 in No.
                                41.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Reply of the <gloss type="from">Tenno</gloss> to the
                                address of the <gloss type="to">foreign
                                representatives</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>I am highly rejoiced at the felicitations which, on the occasion of this
                            new year, have been made to me by the representatives of the friendly
                            powers on my own happiness and the prosperity of my country. I
                            felicitate the sovereigns and presidents of the freindly powers on their
                            happiness and the prosperity of their respective countries. I trust that
                            the amicable relations of my country and the friendly powers will be
                            rendered closer by the public law of mutual intercourse.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
