<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-02-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="425" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d425">
                    <head>423.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Bingham</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-23"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 23,
                            1874</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 26.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your No. 43, inclosing a copy
                        of Consul Hawes’ dispatch informing you of the trial and conviction of an
                        American, who had passed the limit within which Americans are by treaty
                        allowed to reside, and had been arrested and returned by the Japanese
                        authorities for trial.</p>
                    <p>The question being now brought to the consideration of the Department, an
                        opportunity is offered for the expression of an opinion upon the right of
                        entertaining jurisdiction in such cases, as well as upon the policy of doing
                        so.</p>
                    <p>The treaties of the United States define the limits within which their
                        citizens may reside within the empire of Japan. Beyond those limits they
                        lose the protection of the municipal laws of the United States, and become
                        subject to Japanese laws and to the rules of international law. It is
                        understood that Japanese laws forbid foreigners to go beyond treaty-limits
                        without special permits; and ho canon of international law would interfere
                        with such a mild enforcement of these laws as appears to have been made in
                        this case.</p>
                    <p>I gather from the meager account which Consul Hawes gives of the arrest and
                        return of the offender that the Japanese authorities exercised no
                        jurisdiction over the person of the offender except to arrest him in his
                        violation of law, and to return him to the consul for punishment. This they
                        evidently did under the provisions of the sixth article of the treaty of
                        1858, by which we have agreed that “Americans committing offenses against
                        Japanese shall be tried in American consular courts, and, when guilty, shall
                        be punished according to American law.”</p>
                    <p>When this offender was delivered to the principal officer of an American
                        consular court, it became the duty of that officer to try him, and, if he
                        should be found guilty, to punish him according to Amer can law. It is the
                        opinion of this Department that good faith called upon the consul to
                        endeavor to do so.</p>
                    <p>Whether the existing laws warranted the conviction and punishment, is a legal
                        question, upon which I can only express the views of the Department without
                        assuming to instruct judicial officers in the performance of their duty as
                        judges.</p>
                    <p>A treaty of the United States, duly concluded, is the supreme law of the
                        land.</p>
                    <p>The treaty in question confers upon American consular courts jurisdiction
                        over offenses against Japanese.</p>
                    <p>The statute of 1860 (§ 7) authorizes a consul to arraign and try citizens of
                        the United States charged with committing “an offense against law” in Japan,
                        and upon conviction to sentence him to fine or imprisonment.</p>
                    <p>The same statute (§§ 4, 5) authorizes the minister of the United States in
                        Japan to make regulations for the due execution of these powers.</p>
                    <p>Mr. De Long, the late minister, made such regulations, in which, among other
                        things, it is provided that misdemeanors at the common law are to be
                        punished by fine or imprisonment, or both. A misdemeanor is defined to be an
                        “offense inferior to felony, punishable by indictment or by particular
                        prescribed proceedings. In its usual acceptation <pb facs="0765" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/> it is applied to all those crimes and offenses for
                        which the law has not provided a particular name.”—(<hi rend="italic">Bouvier, Law Dict.</hi>)</p>
                    <p>In the opinion of this Department the offense in question, if proved, was a
                        misdemeanor, and was punishable as such under the “regulations” prescribed
                        by Mr. De Long.</p>
                    <p>The American policy in Japan has been the strict observance of our treaty
                        obligations towards that power as a ground for insisting upon a similar
                        observance towards us. Good policy, therefore, as well as good faith call
                        upon us to maintain the consular jurisdiction over such cases as are
                        presented by Mr. Hawes’s dispatch, unless we violate well-settled principles
                        of law by doing so.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>