<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-06-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-06-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="438" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d438">
                    <head>No. 436.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation, Japan</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokei</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-17"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 17, 1874</date>.
                            (Received July 21.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 94.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my No. 84, of date the 20th ultimo, I
                        informed you that on the 4th ultimo I received from Sir Harry S. Parkes a
                        note to the effect that he held a further installment of $5,833.33 of the
                        special compensation due the United States from the Simonoseki indemnity.
                        Since that time I have received your instruction No. 35, directing me to
                        receive from Sir Harry Parkes a like sum reported in my No. 57, of date
                        February 23, and to remit the same by bill to Messrs. Morton, Rose &amp;
                        Co., in London, to be passed to the credit of the United States.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch as your instruction substantially authorizes me to receive all the
                        unpaid balance of the Simonoseki indemnity and remit the same in like
                        manner, I have obtained a bill for the two several amounts paid to me by Sir
                        Harry Parkes of $5,833.33, each, for the gross sum of £2,479 3<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 4<hi rend="italic">d</hi>., drawn by the Oriental
                        Banking Corporation at Yokohama, on the Bank of England to my order, which I
                        have this day remitted, <pb facs="0783" n="687" xml:id="pg_687"/> indorsed
                        to the order of Messrs Morton, Rose &amp; Co., London, with request to pass
                        the same to the credit of the United States. I inclose herewith the exchange
                        voucher of the manager of the Oriental Banking Corporation.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to inform you that in further pursuance of your instruction
                        No. 35, on the 10th instant I addressed to the minister for foreign affairs
                        a communication, (inclosure No. 2,) acquainting him that the United States
                        expects to receive from Japan the unpaid residue of the Simonoseki
                        indemnity, inasmuch as the other powers interested are receiving the
                        balances due them.</p>
                    <p>With reference to your instructions touching the joint note of the ministers
                        of the other powers respecting an arrangement to travel and trade in the
                        interior, I have the honor to say that I have given the same full
                        consideration and will act in accordance therewith.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JNO. A. BINGHAM.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 94.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">exchange voucher.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Oriental Bank Corporation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Yokohama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-16"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 16,
                                1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I hereby certify that the sight-rate on London ruling in Yokohama this
                            date is 4<hi rend="italic">s</hi> 3<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. per dollar,
                            and at this exchange the sum of $11,666.66 = £2,479 3<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 4<hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</p>
                        <p>For the Oriental Bank Corporation:</p>
                        <closer><signed><list>
                                    <item>J. ROBERTSON,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Agent.</hi></item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">S. W. Thomson</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting Accountant.</hi></item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 94.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to
                                    <gloss type="to">minister for foreign
                            affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokei</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-10"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 10,
                                1874</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 48.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I am instructed by my
                            Government, under date 20th April, to inform your excellency’s
                            government that had the other Powers interested refrained from
                            collecting their portions of the unpaid residue of the Simonoseki
                            indemnity, the government of the United States would not have been
                            disposed to press for its portion remaining unpaid, but that inasmuch as
                            the other powers interested had demanded and been paid on account of the
                            remaining portion of the indemnity, the government of the United States
                            expects to be treated in the same manner.</p>
                        <p>In obedience to these instructions, I have the honor to acquaint your
                            excellency that I am authorized and ready to receive, on behalf of the
                            United States, an installment of the indemnity equivalent to the sums
                            paid to either of the other powers.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>JOHN A. BINGHAM.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>