<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 464.Mr. Foster to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d466</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">466</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="recvFVZiL6ijeo9Lc" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104428"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political rights</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="466"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d466">
                <head>No. 464.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 13, 1874</date>. (Received March
                        3.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 108.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: By an act of the Mexican Congress passed on the
                    30th of September, 1872, the President was authorized to appoint a commission to
                    inquire into the facts concerning robberies of cattle and other crimes alleged
                    to be constantly committed on both sides of the Rio Grande frontier. An American
                    commission was then in session at Brownsville engaged in the same
                    investigations, and this fact was doubtless the chief incentive to the step
                    taken by the Mexican Congress. The President, as mentioned in Mr. Nelson’s
                    dispatch No. 657, of September 30, 1872, constituted the commission in the
                    persons of Messrs. Emilio Velasco, Ignacio Galindo, and Antonio Garcia Carrillo,
                    with Mr. Agustin Siliceo as secretary. The first-named gentleman, who was the
                    leading spirit of the investigation, is a native of Tamaulipas, and has
                    represented the Matamoras district in several Congresses, including the present
                    one. He is a lawyer of extensive attainments, familiar with American history and
                    jurisprudence, and was retained by this legation as its legal adviser in the
                    claim of Messrs. Barron, Forbes &amp; Co. <hi rend="italic">vs</hi>. The United
                    States, two years since. As secretary of the State government of Tamaulipas, Mr.
                    Velasco has been long familiar with the condition of the frontier, and by his
                    speeches in Congress, and his editorial articles in the Siglo XIX, upon the free
                    zone and the border difficulties, gave such proof of fairness and impartiality
                    that several of his productions were forwarded to your Department with
                    commendation by Mr. Nelson in 1870 and 1872, and are published in the diplomatic
                    correspondence of those years. His appointment was considered by this legation
                    as a guarantee of a conscientious investigation which would be certain, whatever
                    might be his conclusions, to throw a vivid light upon the facts of the border
                    troubles. Messrs. Galindo and García Carillo are also lawyers of good repute,
                        <pb facs="0825" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/> resident, the former in Monterey,
                    and the latter in Saltillo, and consequently familiar at the outset with the
                    state of affairs they were instructed to investigate.</p>
                <p>The commission was organized at Monterey on the 14th of November, 1872, and
                    immediately proceeded to Matamoras, where it issued a set of rules on the 21st
                    of the same month, inviting the citizens of both banks of the Rio Grande to
                    present their evidence and their complaints upon the subject in question. It
                    remained in session at Matamoras and other towns on the Rio Grande for several
                    months, taking voluminous evidence, amounting to several thousand pages of
                    manuscript, and on the 15th of May of last year, forwarded from Monterey a
                    preliminary report, transmitted with this dispatch, which has just issued from
                    the press as a quarto pamphlet of 106 pages, forming one of the accompanying
                    documents to the report of the minister of foreign affairs for the past two
                    years. This result of the labors of the commission has not disappointed the
                    expectations expressed by this legation, as to the amount of close research
                    which it displays, and the apparent conscientiousness and moderation with which
                    its conclusions are stated. Whether those conclusions, which are in general
                    strikingly opposed to those of the American commission of 1872, can be relied
                    upon as a correct summary of the facts concerning the border troubles, is a
                    question which it would require much time and other sources of information than
                    those in the possession of this legation to determine. I deem it my duty,
                    however, to mention some of those conclusions, and to call the attention of the
                    Department of State thereto.</p>
                <p>The invitation extended by the commission to the Texan claimants was not accepted
                    by them, and not a single complaint was submitted by any American citizen. Being
                    obliged, therefore, to derive its facts chiefly from Mexican sources, it was
                    natural that the report should give prominence to the losses and outrages
                    suffered by Mexicans at the hands of Texan malefactors, and while presenting but
                    little in confirmation, should contain much in abatement of the large loss
                    alleged to have been sustained by American citizens. In addition to the verbal
                    testimony received by the commission, it devoted particular attention to the
                    collection of documentary evidence, and it is chiefly upon the records of the
                    courts of the frontier towns that it has relied in the formation of its report.
                    Bearing in mind that the capital question involved is that of the
                    trustworthiness of the witnesses, it took great pains to satisfy itself as to
                    their character, and rejected as unworthy of credit many accusations made
                    against citizens of Texas. There remained, however, several charges of
                    complicity in robberies of cattle, made against persons of some prominence in
                    Texas, by such a number of witnesses of different classes that the commission
                    deemed them sufficiently proved. Among these persons figure authorities of the
                    rank of judge, sheriff, and aldermen, and most of them appeared before the
                    American border commission presenting claims against Mexico for hundreds of
                    thousands of dollars in each case.</p>
                <p>The Mexican commission had in its hands the report of the said border commission,
                    and took some pains to refute its general conclusions, and especially to show
                    the falsity or unlimited extravagance of the principal claims. By reference to
                    the published statistics of the cattle owned, or upon which taxes have been
                    paid, during a series of years, in the frontier counties of Texas, it shows that
                    there has been, until the year 1871, a constant and normal increase in the
                    numbers of the said cattle; that the number of cattle alleged to have been
                    stolen from Texas in specific years is vastly in excess of the entire amount <pb
                        facs="0826" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/> ever owned in the counties in
                    question; that the entire official valuation of real estate in those counties
                    forms but a fraction of the alleged losses, and gives as specimens several
                    instances of persons who have alleged losses of thousands of cattle, when, in
                    the years in question, they either paid no taxes on cattle, or paid them upon
                    but a few scores or hundreds.</p>
                <p>The commission has given a historical sketch of the frontier troubles since the
                    treaty of Guadalupe-Hidalgo, showing the fluctuations of crime, its methods,
                    causes, and consequences, and has entered into numerous personal and
                    topographical details concerning the most notable criminal organizations. It has
                    devoted especial research to the antecedents of General Juan N. Cortina, (now,
                    1874, mayor of Matamoras,) upon whom a great part of the odium of these crimes
                    has fallen for the last fifteen years. It asserts that at the time of the famous
                    “Cortina raid” of 1859, that person was a private individual, an American
                    citizen, and a resident in Texas, as were most of his companions; that his
                    movement had a quasi-political character, being caused by the injustice with
                    which persons of Mexican origin were habitually treated in Texas; and that
                    during the recent period when Cortina exercised military command on the
                    frontier, far from protecting crime, he attacked and destroyed several bands of
                    cattle-thieves; that the numerous accusations brought against “soldiers of
                    Cortina” for robberies committed during the years 1871 and 1872 are generally
                    entirely false, and when true in some degree, the criminals did not at the time
                    belong to the forces of Cortina, but were deserters therefrom.</p>
                <p>The conclusion of the commission is, that although robberies of cattle are still
                    frequently committed on both sides of the Rio Grande, the proportions of this
                    crime are now much less than in former years.</p>
                <p>The excitement upon this subject, promoted for two or three years past by the
                    residents of the American frontier, is attributable, in great measure, to a
                    desire to involve the two republics in war, for purposes of annexation. As
                    practical remedies, the commission proposes the amendment of the penal laws of
                    Texas and of the frontier States of Mexico, so as to facilitate the conviction
                    and punishment of the criminals, and especially the revision of the extradition
                    treaty of 1861, so as to make it applicable to all cases of cattle-stealing, and
                    similar crimes on the frontier, as also to the deserters from the armies of both
                    republics. It calls attention to the fact that many of the criminals live
                    alternately, and exercise political rights on both sides of the frontier; it
                    therefore proposes that persons who thus exercise the attributes of citizenship
                    in either republic be subjected to the effects of the extradition treaty on
                    demand of the authorities thereof.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
