<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 552.Mr. Adee
                            to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d554</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">554</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-02-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-02-10T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="quarantine-blockade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919" lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807" lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-02-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-02-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="554" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d554">
                <head>No. 552.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation in Spain</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 10, 1874</date>.
                            (Received March 20.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 176.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to General Sickles dispatch No. 973,
                        in relation to the blockade of the northern coast of Spain, I have the honor
                        to forward herewith a copy of the regulations for the Peruvian blockade of
                        1864, received to-day from Mr. Sagasta in response to my request to be
                        furnished therewith. It will be remarked that these rules are framed with
                        reference to the exercise of all the belligerent rights growing out of a
                        recognized state of war between contending powers. It is extremely doubtful
                        whether they will be insisted upon. I understand, through Mr. Layard, that
                        Mr. Sagasta expressed the utmost surprise at the latitude given to the
                        decree of January 31, by the inclusion of these regulations, and stated that
                        the measure had been adopted without his knowledge.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. AUGUSTUS ADEE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ministry of state.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Regulations concerning the blockading of
                                ports held by the enemy and the capture of hostile or suspicious
                                vessels.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ministry of marine—direction of
                                armaments.—ministry of state—direction of political
                            affairs.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. A port held by the enemy is
                                considered blockaded when its entrance is guarded by a number of
                                vessels sufficient to render the passage dangerous.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. inasmuch as the blockade must be
                                effective and constant in order to be considered valid, therefore,
                                if storms or other circumstances drive or remove the blockading
                                vessels from the entrance of the blockaded port, such neutral
                                vessels as may enter or sail out during their absence shall not be
                                considered to have violated the blockade.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. A blockade shall not be
                                considered fully in force until after notice shall have been given
                                by the commander of the blockading squadron to the consuls of
                                Neutral powers, by means of a circular, summoning them to name,
                                without delay, such time as they may deem necessary, at the
                                expiration of which vessels belonging to their respective nations
                                are to leave the port; and if the time fixed by them shall seem
                                admissible, he shall so inform them, allowing free passage to such
                                vessels during the time granted.</item>
                        <item>Information of the establishment of a blockade is also to be
                                communicated to the government of Her Majesty, to the end that it
                                may give due notice, diplomatically, to the governments of all
                                neutral nations.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 4. Even after the publication of
                                this notice, the existence of the blockade is not to be considered
                                as known to any vessel that may be bound to the blockaded port until
                                after the delivery to it of the special notification, which is to be
                                placed among the papers of such vessel by the commander of the
                                war-vessel that may be designated for the purpose.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 5. After the delivery of the
                                special notification, any attempt to enter the port constitutes a
                                violation of the blockade, and the vessel having made such an
                                attempt is a lawful prize.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 6. If a vessel which has been
                                specially notified shall attempt to run the blockade, it shall be
                                captured under any of the circumstances specified below: <list>
                                <label>1st.</label>
                                <item>If it shall be surprised in the act of passing the line of
                                        the blockading vessels.</item>
                                <label>2d.</label>
                                <item>If, having attempted to do so, it shall be pursued by one
                                        of the blockading vessels, said vessel not losing sight of
                                        it; for, if this condition be wanting, or if the pursued
                                        vessel shall enter a neutral port, it shall be free.</item>
                                <label>3d.</label>
                                <item>If, after having passed the line, it shall attempt to sail
                                        out of the port, or to run the blockade again.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 7. If a neutral vessel shall appear
                                in the vicinity of the blockaded port, or <pb facs="0962" n="866" xml:id="pg_866"/> shall attempt to pass the line in the face of
                                the fire of the blockading vessels, the shots fired shall be
                                considered equivalent to the special notification, and the vessel
                                may be captured.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 8. If a neutral vessel of war shall
                                attempt to run the blockade, after having been informed of its
                                existence, it shall be driven back by force, being responsible for
                                the consequences of its aggressive act.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 9. If a vessel which is forced to
                                seek a port in consequence of stress of weather, lack of provisions,
                                &amp;c, shall appear in the vicinity of the blockaded port, it may
                                be allowed to enter, on furnishing proper evidence of the existence
                                of the causes aforesaid. But if it shall have articles which are
                                contraband of war on board, it must deposit such articles on board
                                of one or more of the blockading vessels before entering the port,
                                or pledge itself to keep them on board until its departure.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 10. Under the designation <hi rend="italic">contraband of war</hi> are comprised cannons,
                                mortars, muskets, and arms of all kinds; bomb-shells, hand-grenades,
                                balls, percussion-caps, fuses, powder, and saltpetre; articles of
                                equipment, such as uniforms, straps, belts, saddles and bridles,
                                and, in general, all instruments or articles manufactured for
                                purposes of war.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 11. The court which is to pronounce
                                sentence in prize cases shall sit at—.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 12. In case of a Spanish vessel
                                being in danger, or being captured by the enemy, aid must be lent to
                                it, and every possible effort made to recapture it, although such
                                recapture shall give no right to the captured vessel. If such
                                recapture shall have been made from a neutral vessel, it shall be
                                considered as hostile in case of having remained in possession of
                                the latter for more than twenty-four hours, unless there be special
                                circumstances, the determination of which is reserved for Her
                                Majesty.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 13. Outside of the line of the
                                blockade, and although no effort be made to run it, it is allowable
                                to capture vessels belonging to the hostile state or to its
                                citizens, together with all the property belonging to enemies which
                                may be found on board, whenever a declaration of war has preceded
                                the act of capture. The portion of neutral cargo that may be carried
                                by such hostile vessels shall be free, provided it do not consist of
                                contraband of war.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 14. Under similar circumstances,
                                any neutral vessel carrying goods contraband of war, official
                                dispatches, troops, or seamen, to the enemy or for his account,
                                shall be detained and captured; but if contraband goods do not
                                constitute more than half of the cargo, the contraband articles only
                                shall be confiscated, the remainder of the cargo, together with the
                                vessel, remaining free.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 15. Vessels whose neutrality is not
                                shown by proper papers shall also be captured.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 16. Vessels carrying double sets of
                                papers, or such as appear fraudulent, shall be considered
                                suspicious, and shall be searched. Also such as have not the papers
                                required’by the laws of the country to which they belong, and such
                                as shall not heave to, when summoned to do so by the cruiser, or
                                shall refuse to permit an examination of the compartments in which
                                it is supposed that there is contraband of war, such suspicious
                                vessels shall be treated as hostile vessels, unless the suspicion
                                attaching to them shall be removed.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 17. Neutral merchant-vessels,
                                convoyed by a neutral vessel of war, shall not be searched. It shall
                                be considered that they carry no contraband of war if the commander
                                of the convoy shall so declare.</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 18. There shall be a copy of these
                                regulations on board of each vessel belonging to the Pacific
                                squadron.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 26<hi rend="italic">th</hi>, 1864</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> A correct copy:<lb/>
                        <signed>GULLON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
