<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="555" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d555">
                    <head>No. 553.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName></hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation in Spain</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-24"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24, 1874</date>.
                            (Received March 27.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 180.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward herewith a copy
                        and translation of a decree dated the 19th instant, and published in the
                        “Gaceta” of the 20th, extending, until the 5th of March next, the time fixed
                        for the enforcement of the decree of January 31, declaring the northern
                        coast of Spain, from Cape de Penas to Fusnterrabia, in a state of
                        blockade.</p>
                    <p>The proclamation of the blockade, as at first; promulgated, was met <pb facs="0963" n="867" xml:id="pg_867"/> by energetic protests from the
                        foreign powers whose Biscayan commerce would suffer interruption and
                        hinderance by the sweeping measure proposed. These remonstrances acquired
                        additional force in view of the grave international questions which might
                        have arisen had the Peruvian blockade regulations of 1864 been applied in
                        the present instance without modification, as seems to have been somewhat
                        improvidently contemplated. The inconveniences likely to be entailed by such
                        a course led to its essential modification, and fresh regulations were
                        subsequently published for the guidance of the naval commander of the forces
                        on the blockaded coast, and for the consular officers of Spain in foreign
                        countries. Copies and translations of these, in the form of an order of the
                        minister of marine, and of a communication from that officer to the minister
                        of state, will be found appended hereto. These regulations, although
                        changing to some extent the character of the proposed blockade and relieving
                        it of the unqualified belligerent rights before assumed to exist, still
                        failed to remove the weighty objections raised by foreign governments. Their
                        representatives here pointed out the serious incongruities that remained. An
                        extended line of coast was closed to commerce, while certain of its ports
                        remained open under embarrassing restrictions. Ports not occupied by the
                        Carlist insurgents, or even likely to be menaced by them, were blockaded.
                        And the available naval force of Spain was inadequate to maintain an
                        effective surveillance over two hundred miles of tempestuous coast,
                        especially when the spring storms would constrain the blockading vessels to
                        take frequent shelter in the widely separated harbors wherein safe anchorage
                        could be found. The French government indeed gave official publication to
                        the regulations of February 11, but under certain reservations.</p>
                    <p>Under these circumstances, the government of Marshal Serrano has determined
                        to, at least partially, relinquish its contemplated purpose. As a
                        preliminary step, the blockade is postponed until the 5th of March proximo,
                        ostensibly for the purpose of giving time for an extended consideration of
                        the whole subject with a view to adopting a definitive resolution which
                        shall harmonize the many conflicting interests concerned. This is looked
                        upon as merely a prelude to the final abandonment of the scheme.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                    <closer><signed>A. AUGUSTUS ADEE.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 180.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Decree of February</hi> 19, 1874, <hi rend="italic">extending the time for the enforcement of the blockade of the
                                Biscay an coast to March</hi> 5, 1874.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translated from “La Gaceta de Madrid,”
                                February 20, 1874.]</seg></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Decree.</hi></p>
                        <p>The decree of the 31st January ultimo, declaring in a state of blockade
                            the coast of Cantabria comprised between Cape de Peñas and Fuenterrabia,
                            as a necessary measure for the isolation and prevention of the
                            introduction of outside aid for the Carlist insurgents now infesting
                            several provinces in the north, has given occasion for the presentation
                            of petitions from commerce, in good faith, both national and foreign, to
                            the government, setting forth the prejudices which necessarily will
                            accrue thereto from such a measure, by reason of the continued
                            transactions and the large interests affected thereby in the greater
                            portion of the ports of the above-mentioned coast.</p>
                        <p>The government of the republic, which, while giving heed in the first
                            instance to putting down the insurrection, does not for a moment forget
                            the importance of our industry nor the necessity of encouraging it and
                            protecting, as it should, our mercantile <pb facs="0964" n="868" xml:id="pg_868"/> transactions, has decided to take into
                            consideration the representations above mentioned, and until, after
                            subjecting them to an extended examination, a definitive resolution
                            shall be adopted which shall harmonize all interests so far as it maybe
                            possible, the government, in a council of ministers, decrees the
                            following: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>. The term established in
                                    article 6 of the decree of the 31st of January ultimo, for the
                                    commencement of the enforcement on the coast of Cantabria of the
                                    state of blockade therein ordered, is prorogued until the 5th
                                    day of March proximo.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. II</hi>. The ministers of state and
                                    of marine shall give immediate information of this resolution to
                                    whom it may concern for its full publicity, for its
                                    communication to the representatives of Spain in foreign
                                    countries, and for its exact fulfillment on the part of the
                                    naval forces of operations.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 19,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/> The President of the executive power of the
                                republic,<lb/><signed>FRANCISCO SERRANO.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>The minister of marine,<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">Juan Bautista
                                    Topete.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                180.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Order of February</hi> 11, 1874, <hi rend="italic">fixing the regulations to be observed in the blockade of the
                                Biscayan ports and coast, published February</hi> 13, 1874.</head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ministry of marine.</hi></p>
                        <p>The government of the republic, in agreement with the council of
                            ministers, has been pleased to decide that the rules and regulations
                            expressed in the following articles shall be observed by the vessels
                            ordered to cruise off the Cantabrian coast now declared in a state of
                            blockade, according to the provisions of the 7th article of the decree
                            of January 31st last.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>. The commanders of the vessels
                                detailed to cruise off the coast of Cantabria comprised between Gape
                                de Peñas and Fuenterrabia, shall take especial care to search all
                                suspicious vessels, and shall endeavor to prevent the introduction
                                of articles contraband of war into the blockaded ports.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. II</hi>. The following articles shall be
                                deemed contraband of war for the effects of the blockade: Gannons,
                                mortars, howitzers, guns, pistols, revolvers, and all kinds of arms;
                                shells, grenades, balls, caps, metallic cartridges, fuses,
                                gun-matches, powder, saltpeter, and sulphur; equipments, such as
                                uniforms, straps, and belts, harnesses, saddles, and, in general,
                                all instruments or articles manufactured for or of direct
                                application to warlike purposes.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. III</hi>. As for the exercise of the
                                right of search, especially with respect to foreign vessels, the
                                commanders of the naval vessels should bear in mind that the
                                jurisdictional maritime zone comprised within the limits of the
                                blockade extends from the line drawn from one to the other of the
                                salient points of the inlets and bays for the space of three miles
                                outward; such being the situation of the blockade coast, that only
                                those vessels bound to its ports are obliged to sail close to the
                                land, and consequently any others doing to, and having a different
                                destination, are to be deemed suspicious, except in extraordinary
                                circumstances.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. IV</hi>. Although the right of search in
                                time of war may be exercised on the high seas as well as in the
                                territorial waters of either belligerent, the government, desirous
                                of protecting, as far as possible, commerce carried on in good
                                faith, as well under the national as under a foreign flag, enjoins
                                the commanders of the forces detailed for operations on the coast of
                                Gantabria to limit the search and indispensable detention of
                                merchant-vessels to those found within the jurisdictional limits
                                specified in article 3, except in cases of justified suspicion, in
                                which they will proceed in a different manner.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. V</hi>. As for the <hi rend="italic">form</hi> of the Adsitation, when it becomes necessary, it is
                                to be performed in the terms laid down as a general rule in article
                                120, title 5, of the General Naval Ordinances of 1793; that is, the
                                cruiser shall stop, whenever nautical circumstances permit, at the
                                distance of a cannon-shot from the vessel which is to be searched,
                                sending a boat out to her, from which only one officer and two or
                                three men shall go on board, the first of whom shall limit his
                                action to examining the papers showing the nationality and the
                                nature and destination of the cargo.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. VI</hi>. Every foreign merchant-vessel
                                found within the limits of the blockade with goods contraband of war
                                shall be good prize.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. VII</hi>. Those foreign merchant-vessels
                                which come for the first time to the limits of the blockade shall be
                                especially notified that the coast is blockaded, an entry being made
                                to that effect in their log-book, in their roll, and in the register
                                or manifest of the cargo, under the signature of the officer who
                                performs the search. If, subsequently, <pb facs="0965" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/> the same vessel, with such entries on her
                                papers, he found within the line of the blockade, she shall be good
                                prize whatever may be the character of her cargo.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. VIII</hi>. The Spanish vessels which may
                                be found within the limits expressed in article 3, or which, being
                                laden in our ports for other loyal ports, may change their course
                                and make for another occupied by the rebel forces, shall be detained
                                and judged by the competent tribunals.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. IX</hi>. The blockading forces shall set
                                no impediment in the way of the continuation of the voyage of any
                                national or foreign commercial vessel which, having cleared from a
                                port in Europe, America, or Asia with the requisites and guarantees
                                expressed in a separate order of this date, may be bound direct to
                                the ports of Gijon, Santander or San Sebastian, which are excepted
                                from the blockade for this purpose alone.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. X</hi>. The commander of the cruiser
                                shall give immediate and detailed notice, at the first opportunity,
                                of all visits effected upon national or foreign vessels, to the
                                general commanding officer of the blockading forces for his
                                information and for circulation among the vessels of the
                                same.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XI</hi>. Fishery being for the present
                                prohibited along the coast of the provinces, of Vizcaya and
                                Gimpuzcoa, comprised within the limits of the blockade, the
                                commanders of the cruisers shall seize the vessels and their crews
                                which shall infringe this regulation.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XII</hi>. The general commanding officer
                                of the naval forces on the coast of Cantabria shall fix a sufficient
                                period of time for national and foreign vessels to quit the
                                blockaded ports and roads in which they may be at the time, which
                                they shall do in ballast, or with a cargo shipped prior to the day
                                of the establishment of the blockade.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>By order of the government of the republic I inform you of this for your
                            information and its circulation and exact fulfillment.</p>
                        <p>May God guard you many years.</p>
                        <closer><signed>TOPETE.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-11"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">General Commanding Officer</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">of the naval forces on the coast of
                                Cantabria</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                180.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Communication from the minister of marine to the
                                minister of state, reciting the regulations for the blockade of the
                                Biscayanports of Spain, dated February</hi> 11, 1874, <hi rend="italic">and published February</hi> 13, 1874.</head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ministry of marine.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: In compliance with the
                            precepts of articles 2 and 3 of the decree of January 31st ultimo, which
                            declares in a state of blockade the coast of Canta-bria from Cape de
                            Pefias to Fuenterrabia, with the sole exception of the ports of Gijon,
                            Santander, and San Sebastian, which for the present shall continue open
                            to lawful commerce, the government of the republic, in a council of
                            ministers, has decided upon the observance of the following rules: <list>
                                <item>First. The consuls, vice-consuls, or consular agents of Spain
                                    in foreign ports, will continue to dispatch, in the usual
                                    manner, every Spanish vessel which may be completely and legally
                                    qualified to enter the ports of Gijon, Santander, and San
                                    Sebastian, the only ones comprised in the blockaded coast to
                                    which this privilege is extended.</item>
                                <item>Second. The captains or consignors of the said vessels shall
                                    present to the consuls, vice-consuls, or agents referred to a
                                    statement of the packages, boxes, &amp;c, expressing generally
                                    or in bulk the contents thereof, which compose their manifest
                                    and entire cargo, which latter must consist altogether of
                                    articles of lawful commerce, to the absolute exclusion of such
                                    as are declared contraband of war.</item>
                                <item>Third. The said consuls, vice-consuls, or consular agents
                                    shall remit to the administrators of customs of the
                                    above-mentioned ports excepted from the blockade and to which
                                    the vessels are bound, a general note of the total cargo they
                                    carry thither, in order that they may be examined and searched
                                    for other articles not specified therein. The naval authorities
                                    in the above-mentioned ports, or their delegates, may undertake
                                    the search of these vessels, even though on passing the line of
                                    the blockade and while on the open sea they may have been
                                    already visited by the Spanish cruisers for the self-same
                                    purpose of ascertaining that they carry no prohibited articles
                                    of war, or unregistered goods.</item>
                                <item>Fourth. Merchant-vessels legally cleared from foreign ports
                                    for those of Gijon, Santander, and San Sebastian, shall, to
                                    enable them to pass the line of the blockade and be admitted to
                                    those ports, be subject in every particular to the regulations
                                    laid down for Spanish vessels in the preceding rule.</item>
                                <item>Fifth. The provision contained in the 3d rule is extended to
                                    the administrators of customs of those Spanish ports from which
                                    national or foreign vessels may clear for the three ports before
                                    mentioned excepted from the blockade.</item>
                                <pb facs="0966" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                                <item>Sixth. For the present the following articles are declared
                                    contraband of war: Cannons, mortars, howitzers, guns, pistols,
                                    revolvers, and every kind of fire or side arms; shells,
                                    grenades, balls, caps, metallic cartridges, fuses, gun-matches,
                                    powder, saltpeter and sulphur; military equipments, such as
                                    uniforms, straps and belts, harnesses, saddlery, and, in
                                    general, all instruments or articles made for or of direct
                                    application to warlike purposes.</item>
                                <item>Seventh. To the end that the measures of which the adoption is
                                    compelled by the state of war shall be least prejudicial to
                                    maritime commerce carried on in good faith and to the industrial
                                    enterprises which develop Spanish interests under the shelter of
                                    the laws, those vessels, both national and foreign, which, while
                                    the blockade lasts, may seek clearance from national or foreign
                                    ports to any of those not excepted above, and comprised in the
                                    blockaded coast, belonging to the province of Santander or
                                    Asturias, may do so, clearing, in the terms fixed in these
                                    instructions in the first, second, and third rules, for the
                                    ports of Gijon and Santander, and thereafter, if the
                                    circumstances of the war permit, they may sail for the ports to
                                    which they are bound provided with the corresponding
                                    safe-conducts which shall be issued to them by the naval
                                    authorities in conformity with the instructions they may receive
                                    to that effect.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>By order of the above-mentioned government of the republic, I have the
                            honor to communicate the foregoing to your excellency for your
                            information and for immediate circulation among the representatives of
                            Spain in foreign countries.</p>
                        <p>May God guard your excellency for many years.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-02-11"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>JUAN BAUTISTA TOPETE.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To the <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister of State.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>