<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 594.Mr. Fish to General Sickles.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d596</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">596</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="596"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d596">
                <head>No. 594.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to General <persName
                            type="to">Sickles</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-11-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 12, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 404.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You will receive by the mail of this date a copy
                    of the telegrams which have been sent to you with reference to the capture of
                    the. “Virginius,” and also of those from you relating to the same subject, as
                    they have been received and deciphered here.</p>
                <p>The first intelligence was received here late in the evening of the 5th instant,
                    from Mr. Hall, acting consul-general in Havana. I was absent from Washington the
                    6th, returning on the evening of the 6th. Your telegram was received announcing
                    the instructions of the Madrid government not to inflict any penalties until the
                    matter should have been reported there.</p>
                <p>On the 7th the public journals announced the execution on the 4th of four persons
                    who had been captured on the vessel, one of whom was represented to be an
                    American, who is said to have entered the military service of the
                    insurrectionists in Cuba, and who claimed to hold a military commission from the
                    insurrectionary authorities, and to have been in actual military service on the
                    island.</p>
                <p>The execution, as it is called, of those persons was forced on with indecent and
                    barbarous haste, and in defiance of all humanity and regard to the usages of the
                    civilized world.</p>
                <p>It was perpetrated in advance of the knowledge of the capture reaching Havana or
                    Madrid, and it would seem to have been thus precipitated in cold blood and
                    vindictiveness, to anticipate and prevent the interposition of any humane
                    restraints upon the ferocity of the local authorities from the government at
                    Madrid or its representative in Havana.</p>
                <p>This is but another instance in the long catalogue of the defiance of the home
                    government by those intrusted with authority in Cuba, and adds another page to
                    the dark history of bloody vengeance and cruel disregard of the rules of
                    civilized war, and of common humanity, which the military and other officials in
                    Cuba have but too frequently made part of the history of Spain’s government and
                    of its colony.</p>
                <p>The promptness with which the Madrid government responded to your suggestion, and
                    forwarded instructions to the captain-general to await orders before inflicting
                    any penalties on the passengers or crew of the Virginius, is accepted as
                    evidence of their readiness to administer justice, and gives promise of the
                    promptness with which they will condemn, and punish the hot thirst for blood and
                    vengeance which was exhibited at Santiago de Cuba.</p>
                <p>Condemnation, disavowal, and deprecation of the act will not be accepted by the
                    world as sufficient to relieve the government of Spain from participation in the
                    just responsibility for the outrage. There must be a signal mark of displeasure
                    and a punishment to which the civilized world can point, and which other
                    subordinate or local officials will have cause to look to as a beacon on a
                    dangerous rock, to be forever after avoided.</p>
                <p>You will represent this to the government at Madrid, and you will further very
                    earnestly, but avoidiug any just cause of offended sensibility, represent that
                    the failure of some speedy and signal visitation of punishment on those engaged
                    in this dark deed cannot fail to be regarded as approval of the act, and in view
                    of the orders given to abstain from any punishment which the home government had
                    passed upon them, will be regarded as admission of the inability of the
                    government of the <pb facs="1025" n="929" xml:id="pg_929"/> peninsula to control
                    the affairs of the island of Cuba. The omission to punish the acts of the 4th of
                    November in Santiago de Cuba, will be a virtual abandonment of the control of
                    the island, and cannot be regarded otherwise than a recognition that some power
                    more potent than that of Spain exists within that colony.</p>
                <p>You may read what precedes to the minister, and you may say that this Government
                    has confidence in the sincerity and good faith of the present government at
                    Madrid, and of its desire to have executed in Cuba the promises made in
                    Madrid.</p>
                <p>We fear, however, that unaided, Spain has not the power to control the resistance
                    to its authority under the attitude and profession of loyalty and support which
                    is more formidable than the insurrection of Yara to her continued ascendency.
                    The rebellion and insurrection of the Casino Espagnol and its pretorian
                    volunteers present the most formidable opposition to the authority of the
                    peninsula.</p>
                <p>With regard to the “Virginius,” we are still without information as to the
                    particulars of her capture. There are conflicting representations as to the
                    precise place of capture, whether within British waters or on the high seas, and
                    we have no information as to whether she was first sighted within Spanish waters
                    and the chase commenced there, or whether it was altogether in neutral
                    waters.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hall has been requested to furnish full particulars, and a vessel of the Navy
                    has been dispatched thither. Mr. Hall informs me that telegraphic communication
                    between Havana and Santiago de Cuba has been interrupted.</p>
                <p>There is also some doubt as to the right of the Virginius to carry the American
                    flag, or of her right to the papers which she unquestionably carried. This is
                    being investigated, and, of course, no admission of doubt as to the character of
                    the vessel can be allowed until it become apparent that the Government cannot
                    sustain the nationality of the vessel, while the doubt imposes on the Government
                    the necessity of caution in ascertaining the facts before making a positive
                    demand.</p>
                <p>While writing this instruction, a telegram from Mr. Hall mentions that Havana
                    papers of this morning published a statement, apparently from official sources,
                    that the captain and thirty-six of the crew of the Virginius and sixteen others
                    were shot on the 7th and 8th instant.</p>
                <p>Such wholesale butchery and murder are almost incredible; it would be wholly
                    incredible but for the bloody and vengeful deeds of which Cuba has been the
                    theater. No government deserves to exist which can tolerate such crimes. Nature
                    cries aloud against them. Spain will be loud and earnest in punishing them, or
                    she will forfeit her past good name.</p>
                <p>Your request to the government that our consul be permitted to see and to confer
                    with American citizens who may be prisoners at Santiago de Cuba was considerate,
                    and is approved; but it had been anticipated through the Havana consulate.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
