<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 67.Mr. Williamson to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026944" lcsh-match="exact">Clergy</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-09-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                <head>No. 67.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Williamson</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Legation in Central America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-09-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 28, 1873</date>.
                            (Received November 4.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 29.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that the
                        opportunity of quite a long and free conversation has been afforded me with
                        President Barrios, his chief minister, Mr. Samayoa, and the minister of
                        foreign affairs. It occurred at the house of the President. Our first
                        subject of discussion was civil marriage. Certain Swiss citizens had applied
                        to me to marry them, under the impression they had the same rights that
                        American citizens have. I informed them that according to my construction of
                        the Circular No. 15, and of international law, the citizens of Switzerland
                        in Guatemala, by reason of the act of their government in asking the
                        protection of our minister here to be extended to them, and the consent of
                        the government of Guatemala that such protection should be extended, were in
                        nowise changed in their relations to their own government or to mine; that
                        the only object sought to be accomplished, or that could be <pb facs="0196" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/> accomplished, by the asking and granting said
                        protection was that the good offices of my government should be interposed
                        in behalf of the citizens of Switzerland whenever this could be legitimately
                        done without injury to my own Government; that the right of American
                        citizens to be married at the legation, or rather the right of the minister
                        to celebrate the marriage of such citizens of his country in Guatemala, was
                        derived exclusively from that extraterritorial jurisdiction granted by
                        international comity and sentiment by consent and law. Hence I declined to
                        celebrate the marriage as requested, but promised myself to present the
                        matter to the government of Guatemala in an unofficial way, if the Swiss
                        gentleman could afford me the opportunity of doing so without impropriety,
                        by addressing a letter to the proper authority requesting that a decree be
                        issued authorizing him to be married by any civil magistrate of Guatemala.
                        The Swiss did so, and in the interview with the President and members of his
                        cabinet, which I am attempting to describe, the subject of civil marriages
                        was presented and discussed. I took the liberty of saying: In my country we
                        were opposed to all special legislation, and therefore upon principle I
                        could not advocate the issuance of a decree for the benefit of the Swiss
                        citizens whose case had given rise to the discussion, but that in our
                        opinion, which was sustained by the legislatures of the most civilized
                        countries of Europe, and by the advanced ideas lately promulgated in laws by
                        the neighboring state of Mexico, marriage was a civil contract, and should
                        be permitted to be entered into by strangers in Guatemala as any other
                        contracts, by the consent and act of the civil authorities, whether the
                        clergy were disposed or not to assist; it was a sacrament and without effect
                        unless they secured their fees by pronouncing the benediction.</p>
                <p>President Barrios expressed his hearty concurrence in these views, and said
                        he would issue the decree tomorrow authorizing civil marriages between
                        foreigners residing in Guatemala. He said he hardly thought the time had
                        arrived for him to extend this privilege of civil marriage to his own
                        people. I replied, it would in all probability soon come; * * * * that in
                        our country we considered the civil law supreme, and would neither furnish a
                        hierarchy of Romanists or Protestants to assert that its sanction was
                        necessary to give validity to a contract which the law pronounced good. * *
                        * * I then said there were three rivers in Guatemala which I thought my
                        government, with the permission of Guatemala, would be glad to have
                        explored, if the Government of Mexico would give its joint consent to the
                        exploration of one of them, the Usumacinta, which empties itself through
                        Mexican territory into the Bay of Cam peachy. The rivers alluded to, running
                        entirely through Guatemala soil, are the Motagun and Potochic, both flowing
                        eastward and emptying into the Gulf of Dolce and Bay of Honduras. Both are
                        reputed to be navigable for a considerable distance, and the former is said
                        to be navigable at all seasons for vessels drawing six feet up to a point
                        within fourteen leagues, or forty-two miles, of this city. The President and
                        ministers said the government would be glad to grant the permission, if
                        asked. I remarked that we should also, probably, wish to sound, explore, and
                        map such portions of the coast of Guatemala as were adjacent to the Gulf and
                        Bay of Dolce. They said there would be no objection, and would be gratified
                        if the United States would undertake the work. I replied, I would
                        communicate with you on the subject before opening my correspondence with
                        them in regard to it. The three rivers named, the Usumacinta, Potochic,
                        Motagun, if navigable, as reputed, are very valuable as commercial outlets
                        of the trade and products of Guatemala and the provinces of Tabasco and
                        Chiapas to the ports of <pb facs="0197" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/> the Gulf
                        of Mexico and the Caribbean Sea nearest our cities on the Gulf coast. I
                        recommend to your consideration, therefore, whether it would not be
                        advisable to address the Secretary of the Navy upon the subject of the
                        explorations mentioned, after taking the views and instructions of the
                        President thereon.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. WILLIAMSON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
