<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 764.Mr. BoJcer to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d767</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">767</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-08-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-08-25T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663" lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-08-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-08-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="767" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d767">
                <head>No. 764.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">BoJcer</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-08-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 25, 1873</date>. (Received September
                                    15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 137.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to say, in reply to
                                dispatch No. 120 from the Department of State, asking for
                                information concerning the traffic in. African slaves carried on
                                with the Levant, via Malta, that the result of my inquiries
                                convinces me that, to a limited extent, such a trade is in
                                existence. I have had sufficient assurances, both from the British
                                embassador at Constantinople and from the Ottoman government, that
                                this commerce prevails notwithstanding their best efforts for its
                                suppression. I have been further assured by the British embassador
                                that in any measures which we may take for the extinction of the
                                abominable traffic we may depend upon the hearty co-operation of his
                                government.</p>
                <p>By referring to my former dispatch on this subject, No. 81, under
                                date of March 18, 1873, it will be seen that just previous to that
                                date stringent instructions had been issued by the British
                                government to the governor of Malta concerning the transportation of
                                slaves in British vessels touching at that island. The adroit
                                precautions taken by the slave-dealers to avoid detection were also
                                mentioned. So skillful are these arrangements, that while an
                                examining officer might be morally certain that a group of slaves
                                was before his eyes, he could find no legal pretext for disturbing
                                the so-called “family “of the dealer.</p>
                <p>To anticipate the stricter scrutiny at present in force at Malta, it
                                is now the practice to provide each slave with regularly executed
                                papers of manumission, which are exhibited at Malta and at the port
                                of destination, and destroyed on the disembarkation of the slaves.
                                The <pb facs="1224" n="1128" xml:id="pg_1128"/> poor creatures are,
                                of course, no more aware of the meaning of the charter of freedom,
                                which they take and give up with equaldocility, than though it were
                                a papyrus coeval with Cheops.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the obstacles thus thrown in the way of a legal
                                emancipation of slaves transported under the protection of the
                                British flag, which the authorities at Malta may plead in abatement
                                of our indignation, the British government has lately informed the
                                governor of Malta that it is far from satisfied with the result of
                                his preventive measures, and it is hinted that there is a thought of
                                replacing him with some one who will look more to facts and less to
                                legal forms.</p>
                <p>In my previous dispatch I also mentioned the real or feigned activity
                                of the Ottoman authorities in searching for slaves in vessels
                                arriving at this port from Africa, and of the zeal with which papers
                                of manumission are thrust into the hands of every negro suspected of
                                the slightest taint of slavehood. I have somedoubts of the
                                genuineness of this ostentatious display of virtue. It is performed
                                with too much noise, too much parade, and too much is said to the
                                simple public about the matter. Ido not observe that the number of
                                slaves is diminishing in Constantinople, not even of eunuchs, which
                                latter sexless things should be on the decline were there not a
                                regular source of supply and a way of importation, which are kept
                                carefully hidden from all but the faithful.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the clamor made by the Turks over the introduction of African
                                slaves is for the purpose of leading our eyes away from the much
                                greater and more nefarious traffic in female slaves for the harem
                                which is carried on from the north by way of the Black Sea.
                                Abhorring, as all Christians must, this latter infernal trade in
                                helpless women, whose very charms and lovely sensibilities—gifts
                                which to a higher degree give them a natural right to freedom—are
                                used but to increase their price to the chaffering sensualist, I am
                                astonished that such representations have not been made to the
                                Russian government as would induce that power, in the name of our
                                common humanity, to putdown this business with the strong hand, if
                                need be. Holding the key of the Caucasus anddominating the Black
                                Sea, it would cost Russia no great effort so to set her face against
                                the commerce in women that its extinction must soon follow, and
                                besides, if the famous “traditional policy” is yet in force at St.
                                Petersburg, such a step would be in the line of Russia’s political
                                interests.</p>
                <p>While on the general subject of slavery in Turkey, permit me to call
                                the attention of the Department to that branch of it which relates
                                to trade in eunuchs, carried on between Egypt and the Levant, and
                                which, I believe, might be suppressed by a joint action of the
                                powers, the more surely at the present time while the Khedive is
                                asking the world’s indulgence for the establishment of the Egyptian
                                judicial reform.</p>
                <p>These unfortunate creatures are manufactured in Upper Egypt, not one
                                in ten surviving the barbarous operation. At an early age they are
                                brought through the whole length of Egypt, and those that are not
                                sold for the harems of Cairo and Alexandria are exported from the
                                latter city to stock the harems of the Levant. In the various
                                conversations which I have had with the Khedive and his minister of
                                foreign affairs on this subject, they have invariably replied to me
                                with complacent irony: “The eunuchs are made by Christians in a
                                region beyond our jurisdiction, and in purchasing them we greatly
                                better their condition.” These unqualified facts, facts though they
                                are, involve a fundamental lie when unexplained. Without the
                                encouragement of the harem system of the Turkish Empire, eunuchs
                                would not be made at all. The producers of them, the Copts of Upper
                                Egypt, Christians in name, <pb facs="1225" n="1129" xml:id="pg_1129"/> would disgrace any religion that was ever contrived by pagandom.
                                Over the region which the Egyptian government affects to have no
                                jurisdiction it has nevertheless perfect control; or, granting the
                                official assertion to be true, it is equally true that the trade in
                                eunuchs could not exist for a day after the Khedive prohibited their
                                transportation through Egypt. I beg the Department to consider the
                                above suggestions; for, leaving religion out of the question, the
                                horrible practice of eunuch making and selling, which exists only
                                because of the Turkish market for these maimed beings, is a reproach
                                to any organized government, whether living under the law of the
                                Bible or the Koran.</p>
                <p>While there is no denial of the fact, inquired of by the Department,
                                of transportation of African slaves in British ships via Malta,
                                lapse of time and the vague information furnished by the
                                Department’s dispatch render it impossible for me to give more than
                                a general reply to the inquiry, or to point at present to a
                                particular case in illustration of an abuse, the truth of which is
                                admitted even by the British government.</p>
                <p>If, however, the Department will instruct the consul of the United
                                States at Malta to telegraph to me the name and the destination of
                                those ships arriving at Malta which may be suspected of transporting
                                slaves for any market in the Turkish Empire, I shall take such
                                measures as will lead to the detection of the guilty parties who
                                connive at the wretched business, and in my effort I feel sure that
                                I shall have the fall co-operation of the British embassador, who
                                has already suggested to me that we should act in concert.</p>
                <p>I shall instruct the various consuls of the United States who
                                correspond with this legation, so that they may be ready to
                                investigate the case of any suspected ship that I may report to them
                                by telegraph which may arrive at their several posts. I have already
                                requested information from the agent and consul-general in Egypt as
                                to the departure of slaves from any port of the vice-royalty, and if
                                the Department will instruct, or permit me to instruct, the consuls
                                of the United States at Tangier, Tunis, and Tripoli to send me
                                telegraphic intelligence of the name, destination, and date of
                                sailing of Such vessels as are supposed to contain slaves, I fear
                                that we shall soon discover that as lively a trade in humanity is in
                                progress between Africa and the ports of the Levant, although with
                                mitigated horrors and to a less extent, as was ever carried on
                                between the Bight of Benin and the coast of Cuba.</p>
                <p>In accordance with the instructions of the Department, I shall
                                continue my investigations of the matter in hand, and report any new
                                information as soon as it may be obtained. In view of the infamous
                                traffic in women by way of the Turkish ports of the Black Sea, to
                                which I have alluded, all of which is conducted in Turkish steamers,
                                it is to be desired that the post of consul of the United States at
                                Trebizond should be filled, and that it should be made of sufficient
                                importance to secure the services of a competent American.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. H. BOKER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
