<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-01-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="775" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d775">
                            <head>No. 772.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Boker</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-01-29"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 29, 1874</date>. (Received February
                                    24.)</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 186.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor herewith to transmit
                                a copy of the new stamp-tax law recently promulgated by the Sublime
                                Porte. As this law is at present of little” interest to the few
                                citizens of the United States residing in Turkey, 1 have not thought
                                it necessary to furnish the Department with an English translation
                                of so extended adocument, as it differs very little from similar
                                laws in force in various European countries. I have inclosed two <hi rend="italic">résumés</hi> of the prominent features of the law
                                from the local newspapers, which may contain sufficient information
                                for the purposes of the Department. If, however, the Department
                                should wish to possess an English version of the entire law, I shall
                                have it prepared and forwarded without delay.</p>
                            <p>It was intended that this stamp-law should go into effect on the 1st
                                day of March next, O. S.; but at a meeting of the foreign
                                representatives, lately held at the French embassy, it was decided
                                by a majority I of the ministers that the law in question would
                                impose an additional tax upon commerce within the signification of
                                the terms of exemption <pb facs="1245" n="1149" xml:id="pg_1149"/>
                                from such burdens contained in the ancient capitulations. It was
                                therefore determined by the meeting that a sanction to the
                                enforcement of the stamp-law could not be given by the
                                representatives of the foreign powers until after it had been
                                authorized by their various governments. The Sublime Porte has been
                                notified of that decision, and requested to postpone the enforcement
                                of the law until the powers should have the opportunity of
                                expressing their opinions on the subject. To that request the
                                Sublime Porte, with its usual amiability, will probably yield
                                without an effort at self-assertion.</p>
                            <p>In view of this condition of things, one may well ask by whom the
                                Ottoman Empire is governed, since a council of foreign
                                representatives may by an intimation suspend or nullify the action
                                of any decree or law that may be issued by the Sultan or by his
                                government. So odious and dependent a state of tutelage would not be
                                borne by the humblest recognized government among the European
                                states. An appeal to the antiquated capitulations at this day seems
                                like the enaction of a solemn farce; so completely have the age and
                                the Ottoman Empire outgrown the state of things against which the
                                provisions of the capitulations were designed to guard civilized
                                nations in their intercourse with Turkey.</p>
                            <p>Why the Ottoman Empire submits to this slur upon its sovereignty,
                                this denial of its right of self-government, this continual and
                                vexatious interference with its internal affairs, can only be
                                accounted for by supposing that it is easier for an indolent people
                                to endure an abuse that has obtained the force of habit than to
                                redress it by means that might require a violent exertion or a proud
                                appeal to the justice of nations. If the latter were firmly made,
                                Ido not believe that the opinion of the world, without giving a
                                manifest wrong its sanction, could deny to Turkey the right to
                                regulate itsdomestic economy, and to treat with other nations upon
                                terms of reciprocity, and in that manner only.</p>
                            <p>None but questionable friends, or undoubted cynics, will deny that
                                the government of the Ottoman Empire is sufficiently liberal and
                                enlightened to conduct its international relations upon a footing of
                                equality, and, as between nations, to be entitled to receive all
                                that it is willing to concede. It possesses also sufficient power
                                and intelligence, and a sufficent sense of justice, to be able to
                                conduct its international public business without the constant
                                advice and the solicitous interference of those self-constituted
                                guardians who proffer friendship and coercion in the same hand. The
                                persons who are forever crying out that the Ottoman Empire shoulddo
                                something for itself, should develop its resources, should reform
                                its judiciary, should civilize and educate its people, should liken
                                itself to the nations of Europe, are the last persons to permit it
                                to take a single step without tugging at those leading-strings that
                                confine it within its ancient barbarous limits. What advancement can
                                be hoped for from a government that is deprived of independent
                                action, that sees with the eyes, hears with the ears, thinks with
                                the brain, and acts with the will of others! What scope is there for
                                natural development or for the growth of national virtues within the
                                shadow of this moral servitude? No freedom of actions that will lead
                                to the results with which this century has endowed the nations of
                                Europe can be Expected from a people that since it entered the
                                European family as a relative has not drawn a single free breath,
                                has not been permitted to pursue its own interests in its own way,
                                nor in accordance with the course marked out for it by nature. That
                                kind of indulgent thralldom which pets its object into imbecility
                                may have the same disastrous result in dwarfing character as the
                                thralldom of force. None of those national characteristics, <pb facs="1246" n="1150" xml:id="pg_1150"/> pride, patriotism,
                                self-confidence, courage, intolerence of foreign interference,
                                which, even in disagreeable excess, form the foundations of a
                                nation’s strength, can long survive in people that yields itself up
                                to be thus systematically pampered, upheld, and directed by its
                                neighbors.</p>
                            <p>Characterize the Turk as we may, he is yet a human being, the
                                descendant of a race before whose name, not many centuries ago, all
                                Eastern Europe turned pale; and I have watched with pain and shame
                                the working of the insidious policy through which the Christian
                                nations are sapping his remnant of strength, draining the last coin
                                from his treasury, delivering him over to the usurer, the sharper,
                                the swindler of their own creed; and meanwhile, fondling him and
                                smiling in his deluded face as they blindly prepare him to become
                                the easy prey to some ambitious neighbor. Ido not say that there is
                                this motive in the system, but the result will be as though there
                                were; and common wisdom should foresee and prevent a catastrophe
                                upon which the powers of Western Europe speculate with so much
                                horror, and which they have already shed their blood to avert.</p>
                            <p>The next time the sovereignty of Turkey is menaced, the horror may be
                                no less, and the bloodshed no less, bat both will be vain.</p>
                            <p>I trust that the United States will never become a party nor a
                                patient witness to the undermining process which is slowly working
                                the ruin of the Ottoman Empire; that we will concede to the Turks
                                all that we demand for ourselves; and that we will set to the other
                                friendly but shortsighted nations an example of a great and
                                magnanimous power that scorns, in spite of the temptations of
                                self-interest, to take advantage of the weakness or the pliant
                                character of a friendly people in our international relations with
                                it; and, above all, that we will refrain, either by advice or
                                dictation, from intermeddling in itsdomestic affairs, when, as at
                                present, it seems bent on making a last effort, by usual and
                                practiced means, to replenish its exhausted resources. I beg,
                                therefore, to suggest that the Government of the United States will
                                sanction, since the Sublime Porte thinks that sanction necessary for
                                its action, the new stamp-law or any other law that the Ottoman
                                government may enact for the legitimate increase of its
                                revenues.</p>
                            <p>I have, &amp;c,</p>
                            <closer><signed>GEO. H. BOKER.</signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg><lb/><dateline rendition="#center">[From the Levant Times and Shipping
                                        Gazette, Constantinople, Wednesday, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-01-07">January 7,
                                            1874</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">the new
                                    stamp-regulations</hi>.</p>
                                <p>We have just received from the Porte a copy of the regulations
                                    concerning the new stamp-system. The first article sets forth
                                    what instruments are subject to the stamp, namely, those
                                    relating to loan transactions, deeds of partnership or
                                    association, and every sort of contract, bills of exchange,
                                    checks, receipts, certificates of deposit, snares and bonds of
                                    public companies, teskeres and takrirs, hodjets, inventories,
                                    acts of authorization, judicial orders, receipts for public
                                    salaries or pensions, mazbattas of civil or commercial
                                    tribunals, extracts and copies of publicdocuments made for
                                    private individuals, placards and notices of all kinds,
                                    passports for the provinces, bills of lading and
                                    charter-parties, policies of insurance, and, generally, all
                                    deeds or writings produce-able in a court of law or before the
                                    councils of the empire; finally, newspapers, which are to bear a
                                    2–para stamp a copy, (about one-tenth of a penny.) The
                                    exceptions from the stamp aredocuments passing from one public
                                    department to another or delivered to private individuals
                                    against a receipt; receipts fordonations for the poor, to
                                    schools, religious and charitable establishments; certificates
                                    of indigence; judgments, &amp;c., of criminal and police courts;
                                    and periodical publications relative to science. For bills
                                    contracts, receipts, delegations, &amp;c, the stamp will be a
                                    proportional one, commencing <pb facs="1247" n="1151" xml:id="pg_1151"/> at 20 paras for sums from 100 to 1,000
                                    piasters, 1 piaster for from 1,000 to 2,000 piasters, and then
                                    rising 1 piaster for every 2,000 piasters up to 20,000, from
                                    which point the stamp will be at the rate of 5 piasters for
                                    every 10,000 piasters or fraction thereof, with further
                                    modifications higher up in the scale, 1,000 piasters being the
                                    amount where the sum is from 1,500,000 to 2,000,000 piasters,
                                    and above the latter figure, 500 piasters for every million or
                                    fraction of a million. Shares and scrip certificates of
                                    companies authorized by imperial decree will be subject to a
                                    stamp of 1 per cent, on the nominal capital, and all foreign
                                    stocks, loans, shares, or bonds, quoted and negotiated on the
                                    bourse of Constantinople, must also be stamped at the same rate.
                                    There will be a 10–para stamp for all receipts, &amp;c, for sums
                                    under 100 piasters, and a uniform stamp of 10 paras for checks.
                                    Placards and notices will have to bear a stamp of 1 piaster
                                    each; on bills of lading and charter-parties the stamp will be
                                    only 10 paras; for petitions to the Sultan, 2 piasters; and for
                                    an ordinary petition, 1 piaster. Provision is made for the
                                    effacement of the stamps when used, and there are heavy
                                    penalties for evading the tax. Future notice will be given as to
                                    the mode of gettingdocuments stamped or obtaining paper ready
                                    stamped, or the affixable stamps.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#center">[From the Levant Herald <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-01-09">January 9,
                                            1874</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                                <p>The first legislative enactment resulting from the programme of
                                    fiscal reform, announced two months ago by the ministry, now
                                    appears in the regulations just published for the application of
                                    the new stamp-law. There is nothing particularly original in the
                                    regulations. They are framed upon the experience of other
                                    countries, and they ordain the attachment of a stamp to
                                    instruments or publications to which such attachment is or has
                                    been required in England and in France. The regulation,
                                    therefore, is so far safe and contains nothing in itself which
                                    will militate against its successful application. The scale
                                    adopted is moderate; and while the regulations cover a
                                    sufficiently wide field to promise considerable financial
                                    results, they do not weigh oppressively in any direction so as
                                    to occasion resistance to or invite evasion of their
                                    application. We have, therefore, nothing to say against the
                                    principles which have guided the ministry in framing the new
                                    regulations.</p>
                                <p>The instruments to which an ad-valorem stamp is required to be
                                    affixed are contracts of every kind, bills of exchange and
                                    promissory notes, and every other instrument for the transfer of
                                    value. The scale adopted is half a piaster (about a penny) for
                                    sums from 100 to 1,000 piasters, and a piaster for sums over
                                    1,000 piasters and up to 2,000 piasters. Above that figure one
                                    piaster is added for every 2,000 piasters up to 20,000, and over
                                    20,000 5 piasters will be charged upon every 10,000 piasters or
                                    fraction of that sum. When the amount reaches a million and a
                                    half of piasters anddoes not exceed 2,000,000, the stamp is
                                    1,000 piasters; and over 2,000,000, it is 500 piasters for every
                                    million or fraction of a million.</p>
                                <p>Ordinary trade-receipts are to bear a stamp of 10 paras and
                                    upward in a graduated scale proportioned to the sum. Stocks,
                                    shares, and bonds negotiated on the Constantinople bourse are to
                                    take a stamp of one-half per cent. Policies of insurance are
                                    included in the above category, as well as alldocuments or
                                    writings which may be produced in evidence before any Ottoman
                                    tribunal. Passports are to bear a stamp, as also checks, which
                                    are submitted to the moderate imposition of 10 paras. Petitions
                                    to the Sultan are taxed with a stamp of 2 piasters. Bills of
                                    lading and charter-parties bear only a 10–para stamp, while
                                    placards and public notices pay 1 piaster. Newspapers are to be
                                    covered by a 2–para stamp, which seems to be scarcely enough to
                                    make this tax worth the trouble of application. A stamp of 5
                                    paras would not have sat heavily upon the better class of
                                    newspapers, and might have tended to weed the native press of
                                    publications which convey neither information nor instruction,
                                    and which serve no other end than to occupy the attention of the
                                        <hi rend="italic">bureau de la presse</hi>. In this
                                    particular the new tariff would bear modification. Roughly
                                    stated these are the principal features in the new
                                    stamp-regulations, the text of which we publish in our French
                                    columns. The point in connection with this reform, which, under
                                    present circumstances, is the most interesting is its material
                                    results to the treasury. The ministry estimates these, modestly
                                    enough, at £T200,000—modestly enough, that is to say, supposing
                                    the organization of the stamp-office to be good from the outset,
                                    and its working to be kept up rigidly to the standard of like
                                    offices in France and in England. Not only must that
                                    organization be perfect as far as regards the collection of the
                                    stamp-duties, but it must be so devised as to impose a minimum
                                    of inconvenience upon the public. It is in administrative
                                    organization that the Turks most fail. The ministry makes many
                                    good laws, and makes them in good faith, meaning that they
                                    should be carried out; but when they come to be put into
                                    execution they, in many cases, become so bemuddled, mutilated,
                                    and distorted by the indolence, incapacity, and unintelligence
                                    of the officers employed to carry them out, that the best
                                    designs of the government are defeated, and mischief arises out
                                    of <pb facs="1248" n="1152" xml:id="pg_1152"/> that which was
                                    planned for good. The object of this tax, as of every other, is
                                    general good—to promote general interests. Now it is seen, in
                                    the case of the tithe, how, by a vicious system of application,
                                    this tax so oppresses the particular interests on which it
                                    immediately bears that general interests suffer most materially.
                                    It will, then, entirely depend upon the manner in which the
                                    details of the new stamp-regulations are carried out whether it
                                    will prove to be an advantage or not. In their framing there is
                                    nothing to raise complaint. It depends upon the administration
                                    to render their application either easy and inoffensive or
                                    harassing and obnoxious. Tax-paying is not a pleasant process in
                                    itself, and it, therefore, needs to be sweetened by every
                                    possible facility to the tax-payers. This is a principle which
                                    the Turkish government has yet to apply, if not to learn. The
                                    collections of the customs due, of the tithe, of the sheep-tax,
                                    even of the royalties on mines, are all effected with a maximum
                                    of vexation, and general interests suffer most seriously
                                    therefrom. Having, then, two full months before it in which to
                                    organize the new stamp-office, it is to be hoped that the
                                    government will bestow the greatest care upon the details of
                                    that organization, so that the reform we are discussing, which
                                    is in itself sound, and which, fiscally speaking, should be
                                    inoffensive to the contributors and profitable to the treasury,
                                    may not prove a vexation to the one and a disappointment to the
                                    other.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>