<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-06-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="801" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d801">
                            <head>No. 798.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Beardsley</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate-General of the United States in
                                            Egypt</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-06-01"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 1,
                                    1874</date>. (Received June 30.)</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 202.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith
                                copies in French and English of my communication to the minister of
                                justice, announcing, in obedience to your instruction No. 120, of
                                the 28th ultimo, that the President is prepared to accept, for
                                citizens of the United States in Egypt, the jurisdiction of the new
                                tribunals so soon as he shall receive information of their
                                organization.</p>
                            <p>I am, &amp;c,</p>
                            <closer><signed>R. BEARDSLEY.</signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                    202.]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Beardsley</persName> to <persName type="to">Cherif
                                            Pasha</persName>.</hi></head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate-General of the United States
                                                in Egypt</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-05-28"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 28,
                                            1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                                <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: In obedience to
                                    instructions which I have received from my Government, I have
                                    the honor to inform you that the President of the United States
                                    is prepared to accept, during his pleasure, the project of
                                    judicial reform in Egypt whenever he shall receive information
                                    of the organization of the new tribunals, as provided in the
                                    regulations of organization.”</p>
                                <p>Until the organization of such tribunals, the existing judicial
                                    jurisdiction of United States consuls in Egypt shall remain
                                    unimpaired.</p>
                                <pb facs="1289" n="1193" xml:id="pg_1193"/>
                                <p>So soon as the President shall receive official information of
                                    the organization of the new tribunals, he will issue a
                                    proclamation suspending, during his pleasure, the judicial
                                    functions of the United States consuls iii Egypt, so far as
                                    relates to the matters which are brought within the jurisdiction
                                    of those tribunals by the regulations of organization.</p>
                                <p>I am instructed to inform you, therefore, that during such
                                    suspension of consular authority the Government of the United
                                    States will accept for its citizens in Egypt the jurisdiction of
                                    the new tribunals to the extent of the jurisdiction proposed to
                                    be conferred on the new tribunals by the regulations of
                                    organization.</p>
                                <p>I have the honor to inclose herewith, Mr. Minister, a copy of the
                                    act of Congress authorizing the President to accept the project
                                    of judicial reform in Egypt, and a copy of the proclamation
                                    which the President proposes to issue, so soon as he shall
                                    receive information of the organization of the new
                                    tribunals.</p>
                                <p>Accept, &amp;c,</p>
                                <closer><signed>R. BEARDSLEY,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Agent and
                                            Consul-General.</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>