<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-08-03T08:53:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-08-03T08:53:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                    <head>182. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d182fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                            656.9813/8–361. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution. Drafted by
                                <persName corresp="#p_LRS1">Lindquist</persName> on July 31; cleared
                            by <persName corresp="#p_MWP1">McConaughy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TWR1">Tyler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BWB1">Buffum</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis
                                Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Bell</persName>, and
                            Jenkins; and approved by Rusk. Repeated to The Hague, Canberra, London,
                            New Delhi, and Rangoon for <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName>
                            who was visiting the Far East.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-08-03T09:53:00-04:00">August 3,
                                1961, 9:53 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>126. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Over past few weeks Department, at
                        Dutch initiative, has held series searching and candid exchanges with
                        Netherlands Embassy regarding West New Guinea.</p>
                    <p>Premise our participation has been avoid role of direct stage manager or
                        go-between while at same time demonstrating our deep concern over serious
                        potentialities this dispute if left unresolved and our willingness encourage
                        and assist indirectly in search for constructive solution.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, we have not attempted obtain Dutch agreement to any specific
                        formula or method of approach. We have reviewed with them various
                        possibilities, including direct <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        trusteeship, single or multination trusteeship and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> commission. We have told them that while trusteeship concept
                        has many attractions we foresee certain obvious disadvantages such as
                        difficulty of finding acceptable and willing administering powers and
                        problem of financing. Preoccupation of <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>
                        and delicacy his present position seem additional factors against direct
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> trusteeship.</p>
                    <p>Our examination of problem, however, has led us believe that some degree of
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> participation seems essential to
                        satisfactory settlement and Dutch have been so advised. Although significant
                        elements in both Indonesia and Netherlands might prefer direct negotiations,
                        actual chances for such bi-lateral agreement now appear remote.</p>
                    <p>These considerations have led to development in Department of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> committee idea, in which five to seven nation
                        body, appointed by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>, would visit <gloss target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss>, examine prevailing situation and recommend
                        means settlement to following <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. (Subsequent
                        message contains draft of resolution which might serve introduce item to
                            <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.<note n="1" xml:id="d182fn1">Telegram
                            127 to Djakarta, August 3. (Ibid.) The draft resolution enclosed in
                            telegram 127 was the same as the second attachment to <ref target="#d181">Document 181</ref>.</note> This draft resolution has
                        not been shown Dutch and must not be disclosed <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s.)</p>
                    <p>Conversations have served considerably advance Dutch thinking by requiring
                        them focus on specific aspects of problem. It now clear Dutch recognize
                        their best interests lie in disengagement from <gloss target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss>. They assert they will not transfer territory to <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> (Dept spokesman July <pb facs="0438" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/> 28 declined Dutch request we so inform <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>).<note n="2" xml:id="d182fn2">In the
                            conversation among <persName corresp="#p_SELC1">Schiff</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_TWR1">Tyler</persName>, and others on July 28;
                            see <ref target="#d181fn1">footnote 1, Document 181</ref>.</note>
                        However, Dutch preparedness submit issue to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> treatment implies recognition that loss of sovereignty might
                        be outcome. Dutch consistently express strong concern for welfare of Papuans
                        and insist that Dutch stewardship cannot be relinquished without adequate
                        provision for ascertaining Papuan desires re future political
                        arrangements.</p>
                    <p>Having consulted with us (talks now in suspension although no decisions
                        reached nor commitments made by either side), it believed Dutch now will
                        quietly seek views of other selected nations, informing them that ideas have
                        been exchanged with US but not identifying us with any specific concept or
                        plan.</p>
                    <p>With this background, Dept believes time now ripe for similar talks with
                            <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s. Basic objective will be to seek
                        evidence and indication of extent of <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                        flexibility and encourage them, by discussion and suggestion, as in case
                        Dutch, to assess situation realistically. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>In view foregoing, Ambassador should seek earliest appropriate opportunity
                        discuss <gloss target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss> with <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_S1">Subandrio</persName>.
                        Believe initial approach can effectively employ context of <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName> visit Washington and subsequent
                        exchange with President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>. You
                        should reiterate our deep desire help find an amicable solution but at same
                        time make clear to them our belief that we can be most useful by avoiding
                        role of direct intermediary. You may wish follow with review of our
                        searching study of problem, briefly outlining concepts of direct and
                        nationally administered trusteeships, and culminating with exposition of our
                        present view that perhaps feasible approach to problem would be request to
                        UNGA for establishment <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> committee which
                        would consider how dispute might be resolved in accordance with <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter. You should emphasize that we have
                        reached no definite conclusions.</p>
                    <p>Believe statement along these lines will set appropriate stage for inquiring,
                        possibly with observation that some months have passed since Washington
                        discussions this subject, if recent <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                        study of issue has produced conclusions or considerations which they might
                        wish to discuss with us. (<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. We hopeful
                        this introduction will stimulate them to reply in other than general terms
                        and possibly orient their thinking in direction serious consideration <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> committee idea. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.) If appropriate, Ambassador may wish refer to recent
                        informal contacts with Dutch by <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> as suggesting degree
                            <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> flexibility.</p>
                    <p>If asked, you may state we have, at Dutch request, discussed problem with
                        them in general terms but reached no conclusions or undertakings <pb facs="0439" n="412" xml:id="pg_412"/> and made no commitments. Special
                        effort should be made avoid any <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                        impression we and Dutch have devised Western package.</p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> officials should be reminded of highly
                        delicate position of US and urged in best interests all concerned maintain
                        strictest secrecy.<note n="3" xml:id="d182fn3"><p><persName corresp="#p_JHD1">Jones</persName> made this démarche on August
                                8 to <persName corresp="#p_S1">Subandrio</persName> who described it
                                as a “great step forward” and showed obvious gratification that the
                                United States had taken the initiative. In a conversation later on
                                August 8, <persName corresp="#p_S1">Subandrio</persName> remarked
                                that the U.S. suggestion was very timely because <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName>, he, and others were scheduled to meet on
                                August 12 to discuss West New Guinea. <persName corresp="#p_S1">Subandrio</persName> stated he was fighting the use of force
                                and now he had better ammunition. (Telegrams 234 and 239 from
                                Djakarta, August 8 and 9; Department of State, Central Files,
                                656.9813/8–861 and 656.9813/8–961)</p>
                            <p>In a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>,
                                August 1, <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">Robert Johnson</persName>
                                attached what he described as a “bootleg” copy of telegram 126 and
                                informed <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> that “the
                                Indonesian Desk Officer points out that these instructions should be
                                helpful in preventing the Indonesians from taking a very harsh line,
                                which they might otherwise be encouraged to take, at the Belgrade
                                Conference of uncommitted states.” (Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, Countries Series, West New Guinea,
                            6/61–8/61)</p></note></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>