<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>19. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="19"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                <head>19. Memorandum for the Record<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d19fn0">Source:
                        Kennedy Library, Hilsman Papers, Chron File, 1/62–6/62. Secret. Prepared by
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-02-13">February 13, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">The Secretary’s Meeting on the State of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d19fn1">
                        <persName>Rusk</persName>’s Appointment Book indicates that the Secretary
                        met at 5:35 p.m. on February 13 with <persName corresp="#p_HWA1"
                            >Harriman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis
                            Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Cleveland</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_REE1">Rice</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PRB1"
                            >Peters</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CAJ1">Chayes</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> to discuss <gloss
                            target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> and Laos. <persName>Rusk</persName>’s
                        next appointment was at 6:10 p.m. (Johnson Library)</note>
                </p>
                <p>After much discussion in which <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> contributed
                    heavily to the discussion and had several of its recommendations adopted, it was
                    decided that the United States would propose postponing the <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> meeting, substituting a military briefing
                    of the Military Committee of the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> at
                        <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>. The Secretary would also like
                    to postpone the <gloss target="#t_CENTO1">CENTO</gloss> meeting.</p>
                <p>The United States will make a written commitment to Thailand giving them
                    bilateral assurances along the lines of those contained in the <pb facs="0077"
                        n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/> Military [<hi rend="italic">Manila</hi>] Pact and
                    similar to those in the Military Assistance Agreements with Pakistan.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d19fn2">Apparent reference to the Mutual Defense Assistance
                        Agreement, signed at Karachi on May 19, 1954 (5 UST 852), and the Defense
                        Support Assistance Agreement, signed at Karachi on January 11, 1955. (6 UST
                        501) The United States also committed to the defense of Pakistan by the
                        terms of the Agreement of Cooperation, signed at Ankara on March 5, 1959.
                        (10 UST 317)</note>
                </p>
                <p>This will be delivered immediately so as to coincide with <persName
                        corresp="#p_KRF1">Bobby Kennedy</persName>’s visit.</p>
                <p>The letter<note n="3" xml:id="d19fn3">See <ref target="#d18fn3">footnote 3,
                            Document 18</ref>.</note> will end with an invitation to <persName
                        corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName> to come to the U.S. because the President
                    wishes to make this new bilateral commitment to Thailand public and <persName
                        corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName>’s visit would provide a suitable
                    occasion.</p>
                <p>The letter will be delivered by the Ambassador, and <persName corresp="#p_KRF1"
                        >Bobby Kennedy</persName> will then reiterate and strengthen the commitment
                    by expressing the President’s wish that <persName corresp="#p_TK1"
                        >Thanat</persName> come to the U.S. so that the bilateral commitment can be
                    made public with emphasis.</p>
                <p>The letter will mention the postponement of the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> meeting; it will make commitments along the lines of the Pak
                    Military Assistance Agreement (at <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>’s
                    suggestion), it will make the point that <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    still has some utility and that the most effective way of deemphasizing <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> and reemphasizing the U.S. bilateral
                    commitment would be not to tamper at all with the voting procedure (at <gloss
                        target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>’s suggestion).</p>
                <p>It is <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s view to which all agreed
                    that <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> is important today as a device to
                    get Asian people participating if real trouble comes in Asia. We will, however,
                    reduce its political and economic role since it is not broad enough for these
                    tasks. We will leave it with a military planning role in the event of a major
                    war. All this was a result of a suggestion by <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alexis
                        Johnson</persName> that we might want to consider phasing <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> out—i.e., this suggestion was rejected.</p>
                <p>To implement the above, the following steps will be taken but without mentioning
                    our phase-down intentions to any of our allies.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>After Council Meeting, gradually decrease scale of Headquarters and other
                        non-military activities.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>But leave intact the Treaty itself. Continue, perhaps increase, military
                        exercises.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Let Headquarters Bangkok eventually have only Military Planning Office,
                        Countersubversive Section (Advisory Services Only) and perhaps a Secretary
                        General.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>After above steps have been taken British and French may find it easier to
                        withdraw from <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> without loss of
                        face.(Such withdrawals would not materially weaken <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                            >SEATO</gloss> as a deterrent or an instrument for <pb facs="0078"
                            n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> action; the repercussions, if any, would be
                        largely <hi rend="italic">within</hi> the Atlantic Community.)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>To reduce Headquarters activity: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Council Representatives meet in Bangkok less frequently (now every
                                10 days).</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Consider turning economic projects over to <gloss target="#t_ASA1"
                                    >ASA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ECAFE1">ECAFE</gloss> or other
                                regional auspices.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">RH</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
