<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>226. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Consulate General in
                    Singapore</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-02-10T20:08:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-02-10T20:08:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-10T20:08:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-10T20:08:00-05:00" n="226"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                <head>226. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Consulate General in Singapore</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d226fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 656.9813/2–1062. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>,
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LRS1">Lindquist</persName>; cleared by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Bell</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_DR1">Dungan</persName>, in draft by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGL1">Stone</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1"
                            >Harriman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CJJ1">Czyzak</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BWH2">Bundy</persName>, and in substance by
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>; and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_REE1">Rice</persName>. Repeated priority to Djakarta and to
                        The Hague, Canberra, London, and <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-02-10T20:08:00-05:00">February 10, 1962, 8:08 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>239. Attorney General visit.<note n="1" xml:id="d226fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Robert Kennedy</persName> and his wife were
                        visiting Indonesia at the invitation of Indonesian Attorney General Dr.
                            <persName>Gunawan</persName>, who extended the invitation during his
                        visit to Washington in April 1961, The <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                            >Kennedy</persName>s stayed in Indonesia February 12–18 during an
                        extended tour of world capitals.</note> Singapore for Attorney General.
                    Subject your consultation with Embassy Djakarta, we recommend that in <gloss
                        target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss> discussions with <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> you take following line: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>US remains genuinely objective toward issue. Our basic motivation is
                            help Dutch and <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s find peaceful and
                            mutually agreeable settlement. We have not taken Dutch side as
                            illustrated by our attitude re Dutch overflights<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d226fn2">See <ref target="#d242fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    242</ref>.</note> and by our continued cooperation with
                            Indonesia regarding arms shipments.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>We believe necessary ingredients for peaceful adjustment <gloss
                                target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss> problem present and resort to violence
                            would be tragic development serving no beneficial purpose. Dutch clearly
                            wish leave territory as soon as possible with some face-saving in
                            fulfillment obligation toward Papuans. Indonesians not only willing
                            grant measure internal autonomy but also, if we understand position
                            correctly, prepared permit Papuans complete freedom of choice after
                            appropriate period still to be defined; both sides have demonstrated
                            gratifying restraint publicly and it clearly evident both sides striving
                            for peaceful solution. It appears to us only remaining obstacle is find
                            framework for beginning substantive negotiations.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In these circumstances US wishes strongly counsel Indonesians agree to
                            negotiate with Dutch under aegis <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>
                            with no pre-conditions. We recognize that <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                                >GOI</gloss> agreement to do this may, because of <gloss
                                target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> public position, necessarily result
                            in secret negotiations. While we cannot guarantee that successful
                            agreement will emerge and are convinced it will require hard and perhaps
                            protracted bargaining, we believe prospects for settlement are good and
                            that in any event <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would not wish
                            leave</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>At the request of <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Dungan</persName> at the White
                    House, the Central Intelligence Agency provided a short-range appraisal of the
                    internal security situation in Indonesia that concluded that Indonesian security
                    would be capable of protecting the Attorney General. (<gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss>/OCI telegram 092157Z to the White House, February 9; Kennedy
                    Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Indonesia, Vol. II, 1
                    /62–3/62) <pb facs="0542" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/> any stone unturned in search
                    for peaceful solution. If it does not make corresponding efforts, it will deny
                    itself essential international support. You urged impress on Indonesians that
                    world opinion cannot understand <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> demand that
                    Dutch in effect surrender their position in advance and we believe it essential
                    to peaceful settlement and Indonesian international position that <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> re-examine its position and make every effort
                    agree come to negotiating table without prior conditions. FYL Although
                    substantive positions both sides very close, issue of “preconditions” could be
                    obstacle preventing settlement. We believe your visit to Indonesia provides
                    fortuitous and possibly last opportunity to impress on <persName corresp="#p_S2"
                        >Sukarno</persName> US view that cooperation, good faith and recognition
                    political realities necessary if hostilities to be avoided.</p>
                <p>Apparent impasse which has prevailed recently continues, at least on surface.
                    Basically, Dutch prepared negotiate in presence third party (preferably <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or member his staff) but insist that no advance
                    conditions be imposed. <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s on other hand
                    continue insist that advance understanding be reached that purpose of talks will
                    be discuss inter alia modalities transfer <gloss target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss>
                    administration to them. We agree with Dutch that this is in fact a
                    pre-condition. Dutch at times, however, have implied that discussion
                    administrative transfer expected to be item to be taken up in negotiations and
                    that they would be prepared deal with question constructively. In fact <persName
                        corresp="#p_VRJH1">Van Roijen</persName> expressed to Dept Feb 8 on return
                    from Hague his personal opinion is that if negotiations are started through
                        <persName corresp="#p_TU1">U Thant</persName>, an agreement can be
                        reached.<note n="3" xml:id="d226fn3">As reported in memorandum of
                        conversation, February 8, (Department of State, Central Files,
                        656.9813/2–862)</note> At other times, Dutch (For Min <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ2">Luns</persName>) have insisted that transfer administration
                    directly to Indonesia never will be undertaken by <gloss target="#t_GON1"
                        >GON</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Indonesians, partially at US urging, have moved encouragingly on issue
                    self-determination. You may be faced with <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>
                    argument to effect that since they have substantially met Dutch demands on
                    self-determination, they unable comprehend why Dutch continuing hold back on
                    transfer administration. <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s may cite Dutch
                    attitude this point as “proof that Dutch fundamentally unwilling transfer <gloss
                        target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>s, that
                    demand self-determination only smokescreen.</p>
                <p>Recent contact in London between Dutch and Indonesians may have resulted slight
                    advance toward better understanding between two parties. Details this meeting,
                    however, unclear and Embassy Djakarta will have all currently available
                    information.</p>
                <p>To best our knowledge, <persName corresp="#p_TU1">U Thant</persName> has not
                    pressed this matter for past two weeks since Dutch Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_VRJH1">Van Roijen</persName> just returned Feb 7 from <pb
                        facs="0543" n="516" xml:id="pg_516"/> week’s consultation Netherlands and
                        <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> special representative from Djakarta
                    has been out of New York for about two weeks. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                        >FYI</gloss>.</p>
                <p>With return DC-8 to Amsterdam and substitution normally used DC-7’s on regular
                        <gloss target="#t_KLM1">KLM</gloss> commercial schedule via Tokyo, troop
                    airlift issue appears have subsided somewhat, at least for present. However, it
                    can be anticipated that you may be questioned this subject during visit
                    Indonesia. Believe your response can best be in terms our public pronouncement,
                    i.e., that US not permitting special military charters as hope for negotiated
                    settlement <gloss target="#t_WNG1">WNG</gloss> issue now great with Acting
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TU1">U Thant</persName> making earnest efforts in New York
                    find basis for negotiations. With respect first flight, you may wish take line
                    that plane’s departure Holland based Dutch interpretation of Chicago Convention
                    that only normal technical clearances required. Although we consider such
                    military charters to be “state aircraft” and therefore requiring permission in
                    addition to routine technical clearances, we were unable resolve this legal
                    question prior first plane’s departure.</p>
                <p>Our public statement said military charters not being permitted “for time being”
                    while attempts for peaceful solution in progress:<note n="4" xml:id="d226fn4"
                        >Not found.</note> If Indonesian interrogators take line that this phrase
                    implies that breakdown of talks would result US assistance to Dutch with respect
                    troop movements and, therefore, means Indonesians negotiating under duress, you
                    might say that US intent in this issue is just the opposite, in sense that we
                    wish our actions contribute to peaceful settlement. However, it obvious that
                    change in situation would force US re-evaluate situation. Nevertheless our basic
                    policy goal would in any event continue unchanged: You may wish advise
                    Indonesians that our refusal permit chartered troop flights and our continued
                    shipment military equipment to Indonesia have resulted bitter charges in
                    Netherlands that we in fact not neutral. This reaction also shared by other
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies.</p>
                <p>Remind importance attached high levels Pope case especially in view Washington
                    conversations with <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName> and <gloss
                        target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Foreign Minister.</p>
                <p>Excellent press here on your trip thus far.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
