<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                    <head>28. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_FMV1" type="from">Michael V.
                            Forrestal</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                        President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BM1" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d28fn0">Source: Kennedy Library, National Security Files,
                            Meetings and Memoranda, Staff Memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName>, 4/5/62–6/62. Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-04-10">April 10,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Chester Bowles</persName>,
                            dated April 4, 1962<note n="1" xml:id="d28fn1">In an April 5 covering
                                memorandum transmitting this 54-page memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> noted that “it contains
                                recommendations that many will consider controversial. Because of
                                this, I am strictly limiting the number of copies available.”
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 790.00/4–562)</note></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I have read the above mentioned memorandum, copies of which were sent by
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName>, both to you and to
                        me.</p>
                    <pb facs="0091" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                    <p>The bulk of the memorandum is a recitation of the recent history of our
                        activities in the Far East. The tone is mildly critical of our past policy,
                        especially vis-à-vis Taiwan and the Asian Neutrals.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> suggests a
                        re-orientation of U.S. policy toward the area (beginning on page 33) but
                        also recommends that it be accomplished step-by-step and without much
                        fanfare. His major recommendations are as follows:</p>
                    <p>[Here follows a summary of <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName>’
                        recommendations on Taiwan and the People’s Republic of China.]</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">C. Southeast Asia</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Strive to stabilize the military situation in Viet-Nam to produce at
                            least a deadlock.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Make known through a third party our willingness to negotiate with the
                            Russians or others on a political solution in South Viet-Nam.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Continue efforts on the <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Souvanna</persName>
                            solution in Laos, but prepare contingency plan for de facto
                            partition.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Step-by-step dissolution of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> to
                            be replaced by U.S. bilateral guarantees.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Attempt to get Soviets and Chinese to join in guarantees (using grain
                            shipments as leverage).</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">C. [sic] Regional Cooperation</hi></p>
                    <p>Press for greater regional cooperation in the development of the Mekong
                        River, the Asian Productivity Organization, and the Association of Southeast
                        Asia (<gloss target="#t_ASA1">ASA</gloss>).</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> also discusses the
                        political implications of these recommendations. Generally he believes that
                        the domestic political impact will not be as great as one might expect. He
                        cites the change of policy in Laos without much fuss and the domestic
                        concern over our involvement in South Viet-Nam as indications of this. He
                        stresses that if the position is properly explained by a united
                        Administration, the logic of a “two China” policy could be conveyed to the
                        American people.</p>
                    <p>The memorandum is persuasive and well organized. It would, of course, be
                        political dynamite in certain quarters. For this reason, it is probably not
                        wise to have it floating around. Many of the recommendations, however, can
                        be supported on a purely pragmatic basis and quite independently of any
                        overall philosophy. My own feeling is that it is not particularly helpful to
                        cast our foreign policies in terms of a world view or overall political
                        doctrine. Much more can be achieved, I think, if we simply take the position
                        that each case will be judged on the basis of what appears to be the best
                        interests of the United States at the time the decision is taken. One way of
                        doing this is for the Administration quietly to support the view that the
                        Communist enemy is not the unchanging <pb facs="0092" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> monolith he is popularly believed to be. If the impression is conveyed
                        that the changes within the Communist bloc require corresponding flexibility
                        in our own attempts to deal with each local situation, the range of choices
                        available to the President may hopefully be increased. There is one point in
                        the <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> memorandum with which I do
                        not believe I agree: that is his suggestion that we should begin urging for
                        a political solution in Viet-Nam at this time. I particularly doubt whether
                        we should consider approaches to the Chinese or the Russians through third
                        parties. It is too early to begin on this task. It is important, I think,
                        both for domestic and foreign policy reasons, to maintain a rather strong
                        position both in Thailand and in South Viet-Nam, especially if there is any
                        hope of stabilizing the situation. It provides a counter-balance in the
                        public mind to a more flexible policy in Laos and it also avoids misleading
                        the Chinese and Viet Minh into thinking we might be preparing to disengage
                        from the area. When the security situation shows definite signs of improving
                        in South Viet-Nam, we would be in a better position to consider a negotiated
                        settlement.</p>
                    <p>[Here follows a short paragraph on Ambassadorial appointments.]</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">MVF</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>