<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="295" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                    <head>295. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1" type="from">Kennedy</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_S2" type="to">Sukarno</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d295fn0">Source:
                            Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Indonesia,
                            Vol. III, 11 /62–12/62. No classification marking. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Bell</persName> at the instruction of the
                            President after his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_JHD1">Jones</persName>; see <ref target="#d293">Document 293</ref>.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> had hoped that
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> would decide
                            that the salutation to this letter should be “Dear Bung Karno,” the
                            familiar term used by <persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName>’s
                            friends and associates in Indonesia, but the decision was left to the
                            President. (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KCM1">Kaysen</persName>, October 22; Kennedy Library, National Security
                            Files, Countries Series, Indonesia, Vol. III, 11/62–12/62)</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-11-02">November 2,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: I have recently had a long talk
                        with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JHP1">Jones</persName>, in the course
                        of which he told me of your invitation for me to visit Indonesia. Having
                        heard so much of your country from my brother, <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Bobby</persName>, and from many others who have visited or lived there,
                        I want very much to visit Indonesia.</p>
                    <p>Although I cannot accept your kind invitation at this time, I have not given
                        up hope of eventually visiting your country when my duties permit. In the
                        meantime, you have my warmest thanks for your invitation.</p>
                    <p>I am encouraged by the course of developments in Cuba since my letter to you
                        on October 22,<note n="1" xml:id="d295fn1">Not printed. (Department of
                            State, Presidential Correspondence, Lot 66 D 204)</note> although, of
                        course, much still remains to be done before we can consider the episode
                        closed. In this connection, I am aware of the restraint exercised by your
                        government throughout the Cuban crisis. It unquestionably contributed to the
                        atmosphere which made a peaceful settlement attainable. Let us hope that we
                        can now turn the perilous events of the past weeks into a real advance
                        toward the free and peaceful society for which we both strive.</p>
                    <p>From all reports, the transfer of administration in West Irian is proceeding
                        smoothly within the terms of the August 15 agreement. It took mature and
                        imaginative statesmanship both on the part of your Government and that of
                        the Netherlands in reaching agreement for the peaceful settlement of this
                        longstanding dispute, and I am glad to see a conciliatory atmosphere at the
                        start of its implementation. As you know, I have instructed United States
                        authorities to cooperate closely with the United Nations in providing
                        logistic support for the United Nations Temporary Executive Authority in
                        West Irian.</p>
                    <p>As you know, Secretary Rusk and Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> discussed economic problems
                        briefly with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_S1">Subandrio</persName>
                        in New York in September,<note n="2" xml:id="d295fn2">See <ref target="#d291fn1">footnote 1, Document 291</ref>.</note> and
                        conversations between other Indonesian and American officials are
                        continuing. I am sure that from these and other contacts an effective
                        program will emerge.</p>
                    <pb facs="0676" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/>
                    <p>You certainly face a challenging and exciting task in this great endeavor.
                        There was a time, of course, when economic matters appeared less dramatic to
                        many than political affairs, but this is certainly not true today. I can
                        think of few better measures of the greatness of a nation and its leaders
                        than their success in developing its resources for the benefit of all its
                        citizens. I know that Indonesia, under your leadership, is well embarked on
                        this adventure.</p>
                    <p>I was delighted to hear from Sargent Shriver of your long talk with him last
                        month and the enthusiastic reception you gave him.<note n="3" xml:id="d295fn3">A memorandum of the Shriver—<persName corresp="#p_S2">Sukarno</persName> discussion has not been found.</note> I
                        understand that preparations for establishment of a Peace Corps program are
                        well under way. I am convinced both that the Peace Corps can make a real
                        contribution to the continued development of Indonesia and that my country,
                        in turn, will be much the richer from the knowledge of Indonesian life and
                        culture which returning Peace Corps volunteers will bring. They will also be
                        able to learn much in the way of new, practical techniques from your
                        people.</p>
                    <p>Aside from the matter of economic development, there are a number of other
                        major issues in which our two countries share a deep interest. The various
                        forces shaping events in Southeast Asia, for example, have long been a
                        source of considerable preoccupation to both of us. In this particular
                        field, it seems to me that it would be most useful if those officials of our
                        two countries who are most directly concerned with Southeast Asia could
                        periodically exchange views on the general problems of the region and our
                        mutual interests there. If this idea appeals to you, you might wish to
                        discuss it with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JHP1">Jones</persName>.</p>
                    <p>I am asking Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JHP1">Jones</persName> to carry
                        this letter to you on his return to Djakarta,<note n="4" xml:id="d295fn4">The letter was sent to the Department of State for telegraphic
                            transmission to Djakarta.</note> and to give you the warm personal
                        regards of myself and my family.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely,<note n="5" xml:id="d295fn5">Printed from an unsigned
                        copy.</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>