<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-07-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-07-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="327" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d327">
                    <head>327. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d327fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/EAP Files: Lot 90 D 165, <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 54/59–62. Secret; Noforn. A note on the cover sheet
                            indicates that the Central Intelligence Agency; Department of State’s
                            Bureau of Intelligence and Research; and the intelligence organizations
                            of the Army, the Navy, and the Air Force participated in the preparation
                            of this estimate. All members of the U.S. Intelligence Board concurred
                            with the estimate with the exception of the representatives of the
                            Atomic Energy Commission and Federal Bureau of Investigation, who
                            abstained because the subject was outside their
                        jurisdiction.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 54/59–62</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-07-11">July 11,
                            1962</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">PROSPECTS FOR THE PROPOSED MALAYSIAN FEDERATION</p>
                    <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                    <p>To estimate the prospects for achievement of the proposed Federation of
                            Malaysia<note n="1" xml:id="d327fn1">The proposed Federation of Malaysia
                            is to be made up of (a) the Federation of Malaya, which became
                            independent in 1957; (b) Singapore, which was granted partial
                            self-government in 1959; and (c) the three British dependencies on the
                            island of Borneo: the Protectorate of Brunei and the Crown Colonies of
                            Sarawak and North Borneo. [Footnote in the source text.]</note> and for
                        its political and economic viability.</p>
                    <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>The Federation of Malaysia will probably be formally established
                            within a year; agreement on general principles may be announced as early
                            as 31 August 1962. The chief threat to achievement of the merger comes
                            from the pro-Communist Barisan Sosialis Party (BSP) of Singapore which
                            is seeking an opportunity to upset the precariously situated Singapore
                            Government and to halt further progress toward federation. (Paras.
                            5–8)</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>The projected merger is essentially the incorporation into Malaya of
                            the four other territories. Although these areas will retain a
                            considerable degree of local autonomy, the central Federation government
                            in Kuala Lumpur will assume control of internal security, foreign
                            policy, and defense. <persName corresp="#p_ART1">Tunku Abdul
                                Rahman</persName>’s moderately conservative and pro-Western
                            coalition, known as the Alliance, will probably dominate the government
                            of the new Federation in its early years. The new state will have the
                            benefit of the proven stability of the governmental and economic
                            structure of Malaya, and the support and protection of Britain,
                            Australia, and New Zealand. (Paras. 4, 9–10, 16, 20)</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>The chief threats to the new Federation will be communal antagonisms,
                            easily aroused because of the ethnic diversity found in each of <pb facs="0735" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> the component states, and the
                            opposition of Communists and other radical elements. The leftists will
                            probably find additional support within the Chinese communities, in
                            Singapore and elsewhere, which are resentful of the political
                            discrimination in favor of the Malays as announced in the proposals for
                            the new Federation. Similar resentments may emerge among the non-Malay
                            indigenous peoples of the Borneo territories. The future of Malaysia
                            will be largely influenced by whether the <persName corresp="#p_ART1">Tunku</persName> continues successfully to control these various
                            frictions. It will also depend in large measure on the economic progress
                            of the new Federation and its component territories. (Paras. 10–15,
                                17–19)<note n="2" xml:id="d327fn2">In a July 10 memorandum to <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> Director <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>, the Director of the Office
                                of Research and Analysis for the Far East, <persName>Charles N.
                                    Spinks</persName>, recommended that <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> concur with the estimate subject to two
                                revisions. Spinks’ office did not agree with a conclusion in the
                                discussion portion that “the vitality of the <persName corresp="#p_ART1">Tunku</persName>’s coalition has flagged.”
                                Spinks suggested that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>’s Office
                                of National Estimates (<gloss target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss>) would
                                challenge his objection. The final assessment of the <persName corresp="#p_ART1">Tunku</persName> coalition was a compromise
                                between <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>’s and <gloss target="#t_ONE1">ONE</gloss>’s points of view. Spinks also
                                stressed that the Philippine claim to North Borneo “was a serious
                                matter in their eyes.” <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>’s
                                estimate that it could prove troublesome to the formation of the
                                Federation of Malaysia was incorporated in the discussion section of
                                the estimate. (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/EAP Files: Lot 90 D 165, <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 54/59–62)</note></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Here follow a 6-page Discussion section and 3 maps.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>