<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>386. Letter From the Ambassador to the Philippines (Stevenson) to the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs () to the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (Hilsman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">386</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="386"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d386">
                <head>386. Letter From the Ambassador to the Philippines (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SWE1" type="from">Stevenson</persName>) to the Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HRJ1"
                        type="to">Hilsman</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d386fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> PHIL–US. Confidential; Official-Informal.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Manila</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-06-08"
                            >June 8, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Roger</persName>
                    </hi>: An important new channel with the Philippine Government, and with
                    President <persName corresp="#p_MD1">Macapagal</persName> in particular, has
                    developed here over the past few months which I think you should know about.</p>
                <pb facs="0851" n="824" xml:id="pg_824"/>
                <p>As you are doubtless aware, two people in which the President has very great
                    confidence and whom he sees almost daily are Rod Perez, Acting Secretary of
                    Finance, and Ting Roxas, Director of the P.I.A. (Program Implementation Agency).
                    We regard these two as very outstanding Filipinos, both with ability and
                    integrity Jim Ingersoll<note n="1" xml:id="d386fn1">
                        <persName>James H. Ingersoll</persName>, Director of the <gloss
                            target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> Mission in the Philippines.</note> came to
                    know them both quite intimately through various A.I.D. matters and subsequently
                    the four of us began a series of regular Friday luncheons, which are rotated
                    between our homes or occasionally held in some private dining room.</p>
                <p>At these luncheon meetings we feel free to bring up and discuss any and all
                    Philippine-American problems. I usually have a list of two or three items,
                    current ones being war damage, Cultural Foundation, Retail Trade Bill,
                    disruption of road traffic between Subic and Clark Field because of delay in
                    replacing washed-out bridge, etc. Jim and I have found our two Filipino
                    counterparts most easy to talk to and we usually see eye-to-eye on nearly every
                    problem that comes up. Better still, they give us a high degree of cooperation
                    and do their best to clear up or correct items which we present. Naturally, we
                    try to show the same cooperative attitude on our side.</p>
                <p>Since these two men are so close to the President, we know that he will hear very
                    promptly of situations about which we would like to have him aware. In some
                    cases, I can ask Perez to get the President’s reaction on a certain matter and
                    he will call me back within a few hours. In other cases, he can arrange
                    appointments with the President on short notice, which might take several days
                    through regular channels.</p>
                <p>While this arrangement which I have been describing is entirely unofficial and
                    somewhat unorthodox, it seems to be working very well and the fact that these
                    two important and busy men arrive very promptly for our luncheons and remain
                    with us as long as there are things to discuss seems to indicate that they and
                    possibly the President are pleased with the relationship.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d386fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> responded in an
                        official–informal letter to <persName corresp="#p_SWE1"
                        >Stevenson</persName>, June 19. He approved fully of the informal channel
                        idea. (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 1 PHIL)</note>
                </p>
                <p>This channel is especially satisfactory from my point of view since, as you are
                    aware, the Vice President can make very few decisions on his own responsibility
                    and hence in the long run we have to get the President’s approval or viewpoint.
                    I am sure that the Vice President knows about these luncheons and does not
                    resent them, since Roxas is a very close personal friend of the Vice President
                    as well. Also, Rod Perez was identified with the Grand Alliance, of which
                        <persName corresp="#p_PE1">Pelaez</persName> was the leader, and Roxas and
                    Perez are close friends of Senator Manglapus. In fact, they <pb facs="0852"
                        n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/> brought the Senator to a luncheon not long ago to
                    enlist his interest in trying to work out a satisfactory solution to the
                    Cultural Center impasse.</p>
                <p>On the subject of communication, I learned from our luncheon yesterday that one
                    of the reasons for Hechanova’s trip to the States later this month<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d386fn3">Philippine Secretary of Commerce and Industry Rufino G.
                        Hechanova visited the United States June 26–29 to discuss trade and economic
                        relations. Documentation on his visit, including memoranda of conversation
                        with Department of State officials, is ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 7 PHIL.</note> is to evaluate by personal “inspection”
                    whether or not he would like to be the <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>
                    Ambassador to succeed <persName corresp="#p_MA2">Mutuc</persName>. Perez
                    indicated there was a strong possibility that Hechanova will get the assignment
                    if he likes the looks of things in Washington. It is our understanding that one
                    of the reasons <persName corresp="#p_MA2">Mutuc</persName> was sent to
                    Washington was because of his Harvard background and thus the opportunity to
                    cultivate the <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Family. Presumably
                    in the <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> view, Hechanova’s youth would tend to
                    be a favorable factor in his developing contacts with the younger members of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> Administration.</p>
                <p>I told Perez quite frankly that I felt that whoever was sent to the U.S. to
                    succeed <persName corresp="#p_MA2">Mutuc</persName> should plan to remain for
                    several years. He said he agreed and that Hechanova would certainly stay at
                    least two years. Presumably, he would then wish to return to run for Senator or
                    Governor, since he has political ambitions.</p>
                <p>We have our fingers crossed on the war damage situation. Please have someone keep
                    us as up to date as possible, since there is great interest here and I am asked
                    about it by the Vice President and other officials whenever I see them.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Bill</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
