<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>397. Memorandum From Secretary of State Rusk to President to President
                    Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-02-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="397"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <head>397. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName type="from">Rusk</persName>
                    to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1" type="to">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d397fn0">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                        Security Files, Countries Series, Thailand, Vol. I, 1/61–5/61. No
                        classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-02-24">February 24, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Reaffirmation of United States Support for Thailand</item>
                </list>
                <p>On the basis of recent discussion of our policies in Southeast Asia I believe
                    that a reaffirmation of our moral and material support for Thailand would be
                    both timely and highly advantageous to our interests. With this thought in mind
                    I submit for your signature a letter to Field Marshal <persName corresp="#p_ST1"
                        >Sarit Thanarat</persName>, Prime Minister of Thailand, reiterating our
                    intention fully to honor our obligations as an ally and friend and expressing
                    our willingness to discuss with the Royal Thai Government measures designed to
                    further the security and economic progress of Thailand.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> wrote to the Prime
                    Minister on November 8, 1960<note n="1" xml:id="d397fn1">See <ref
                            target="#d396fn1">footnote 1, Document 396</ref>.</note> to assure him
                    that the preservation of the independence and integrity of Thailand was a matter
                    of the highest concern and importance to the United States and to inform him of
                    our willingness to explore with the Thai Government measures for advancing its
                    program of economic and social development. President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s letter stressed the high value
                    which the United States continues to place on its friendship and cooperation
                    with Thailand. In replying in December, 1960 Field Marshal <persName
                        corresp="#p_ST1">Sarit</persName> expressed his deep appreciation of
                    President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s assurances and the
                    gratitude of the Thai Government and people for American military and economic
                        assistance.<note n="2" xml:id="d397fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_ST1">Sarit</persName>’s note was conveyed to the
                        Department of State by the Thai Ambassador on December 28 and then sent on
                        to the White House. (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, International
                        File)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Prime Minister continues to be gravely concerned over the threat to
                    Thailand’s security posed by the troubled situation in Laos and the resulting
                    prospect of a southward thrust of Communist power in Southeast Asia. He has
                    welcomed our past assurances of our fidelity to our commitments under <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, to which, in the absence of a bilateral
                    mutual defense treaty between the United States and Thailand, the Thai
                    Government is inclined to give a de facto bilateral interpretation. The
                    importance of our relationships with Thailand is such as to warrant a
                    reaffirmation of our continuing awareness of Thai economic and security
                    requirements and of our unswerving sympathy and support.</p>
                <pb facs="0869" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/>
                <p>I believe that a personal reassurance from you in this sense to the Prime
                    Minister would be both timely and highly advantageous to our interests and I
                    therefore recommend that you sign the enclosed letter.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d397fn3">Attached but not printed. The letter was signed by
                        President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> and the text was
                        transmitted to Bangkok in telegram 1277, February 28. In telegram 1531 from
                        Bangkok, March 1, the Embassy reported that the letter was delivered to
                            <persName corresp="#p_ST1">Sarit</persName> at noon that day.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, 611.92/2–2861 and 611.92/3–161)</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that, if approved, no publicity be given to this message. If
                    approved, we shall transmit it by telegram to our Ambassador at Bangkok for
                    delivery to the Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>I enclose for your information a biographic sketch of the Prime Minister.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d397fn4">Attached but not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Dean Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
