<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>62. Telegram From the Embassy in Burma to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-10-07T05:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-10-07T05:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="reclIDTRPrn9Z53H4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94004349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCM</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-10-07T05:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-10-07T05:30:00-05:00" n="62"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                <head>62. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Burma</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d62fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 BURMA-US. Secret; Priority;
                        Limit Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Rangoon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-10-07T17:00:00+06:30">October 7, 1963, 5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>245. Presented credentials General <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName>
                    9:00 a.m. this morning (Monday). Highly pleased at frank nature our first
                    conversation but equally concerned at content his remarks. Conversation easy and
                    friendly and I found him quite likeable personally. Chief of Protocol and
                    Cabinet Secretary remained throughout conversation which lasted thirty
                    minutes.</p>
                <p>After initial small talk about my previous service west and north of Burma’s
                    borders, his apology for not receiving me sooner, the conveyance of Secretary’s
                    and <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s greetings, etc., etc., I
                    asked if it would be appropriate to turn to substantive matters. Upon his
                    request that I should always be frank and direct with him, I said wished to
                    start with my last talk with President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                        >Kennedy</persName> before departure Washington. President had seemed very
                    well informed re Burma and I would speak from notes I had made at that time.</p>
                <p>President’s first thought had been that I should convey his desire to have
                    opportunity meet <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> personally. I had
                    felt from nature his remarks that President had received reports that the
                    General’s last trip to Washington during the previous administration didn’t go
                    very well and that he seemed eager erase any past misunderstandings.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d62fn1">The 1960 visit was described as a “fiasco” by <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJB1">Dexter</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne
                            Win</persName> felt he was not given proper honor upon his arrival, his
                        wife was insulted while he was undergoing medical attention at Walter Reed
                        Hospital, and no high-ranking Department of Defense officials saw him.
                        (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_DJB1">Dexter</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>, October 11; ibid., EA/BUC Files:
                        Lot 66 D 483, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15-1, Head of State, Exec.
                        Branch (<persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName>))</note> He had said
                    he hoped that at some mutually convenient future time a meeting would be
                    possible.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> said he greatly appreciated this
                    thought from President. Said we need not be concerned over unfortunate events
                    during his last visit as relations between nations should not be affected by
                    such small <!-- start of pg 137, missing in our scan; replace @facs when restored -->
                    <pb n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/> matters, and there were indeed matters between us
                    of more serious nature. He nevertheless related in some detail, obviously trying
                    to give appearance of laughing them off, mishaps his last visit. It obvious
                    mistakes on our part during that visit are still with us, despite his
                    protestations to contrary, although as he himself said, and later proved, this
                    not our greatest problem by any means.</p>
                <p>[Here follows <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName>’s account of making
                    the three points suggested and approved in the Attachment to <ref target="#d60"
                        >Document 60</ref>.]</p>
                <p>The General listened intently during above but asked no direct questions. Said he
                    pleased at President’s interest in Burma. He said he thought the <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> administration had changed the US
                    understanding of neutral nations and their problems. He supposed President might
                    well be confused about what is happening in Burma. This would not seem unusual
                    as he felt sure even many Burmese were not really aware of what he was trying to
                    do. He hoped things would clear up in future and everyone would see that he on
                    right path. Burma had a great desire to be left alone with her problems at the
                    moment although he knew that no nation, as no individual, could really stand
                    alone for very long. The story had proven however that Burma must beware of
                    seeming friends who let her down.</p>
                <p>I said if he were speaking of the US I must ask that he be more specific. I had
                    found suspicions here and this was a cause of great personal concern to me. His
                    reaction was immediate and he spoke with feeling, saying he would tell me of one
                    of past grievances. He related the great sense of personal loss he had felt when
                    he found that some of his closest friends in the officer corps had been
                    subverted by us and were actually [garble—your?] agents. He did not mention
                    names but it obvious when he spoke of one in particular he referring to Brig.
                        <persName>Maung Maung</persName> now seconded as Ambassador to Israel.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> he would always get the
                    truth from me. I could not comment on events in past of which he spoke as I did
                    not as yet know. If what he said were true I could understand his feelings. I
                    could only tell him that I was an old-timer at the diplomatic business; that
                    nothing would happen in his country from American sources that I did not know
                    about and personally approve; and that I would give him my word that he need
                    have no concerns of this nature about the future.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> said he aware <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> was making progress in bringing total
                    US Government and activities under control—even making progress over most
                    difficult agency—but even though progress being made he had not been able fully
                    succeed as yet (this in laughing vein as if he didn’t envy President his task).
                    I replied that I knew for a fact that President had already succeeded. I
                    recalled <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName>’s remarks to <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d62fn2">See <ref target="#d53">Document 53</ref>.</note>
                    <pb facs="0165" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/> (he remembers this talk with pleasure)
                    of steps he had taken to insure against corruption of too much power in hands
                    one Cabinet member or individual. Said I not at liberty go into details but
                    President’s methods somewhat like his own, and I could assure him President now
                    fully and completely in control.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> reverted again to thought that he
                    and <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> might meet. He said he hoped
                    this could be possible. I should know however that he had been so involved in
                    internal matters that he had not even been able to accept as yet three
                    invitations in local area, i.e. India, Pakistan and Ceylon. He hoped to get
                    these out of way as soon as possible but in any event these should precede any
                    return to the US. He laughed heartily when I said I thought one idea <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> may have wished to get across was that
                    he had managed to get rid of the fellows who were in control in Washington at
                    the time of his last visit.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> if any suspicions arose in
                    future I hoped he would discuss them both quickly and frankly with me
                    personally. Said I hoped see him occasionally in any event, as I had feeling
                    Washington had felt somewhat, cut off from him personally of late. Knew of
                    course of great demands on him personally, particularly during present difficult
                    period, and would be careful not to overdo privilege seeing him personally. He
                    said would be great pleasure and we parted in mutual agreement we both would
                    have had less troubled life had we stayed in the army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> It obvious the General’s suspicions real and are
                    not going to be corrected either quickly or easily. While it disturbing find he
                    feels as he does it nonetheless gratifying that he talked about it as he did.
                    The <gloss target="#t_DCM1">DCM</gloss> tells me that he has not done so before
                    here locally and at least open grievances should be easier to deal with than
                    secret ones. Hope Dept will understand my decision at this meeting avoid denials
                    or belabor past. Have feeling had I done so would have lost credence with
                        <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName> personally even in process
                    presenting credentials.<note n="3" xml:id="d62fn3">
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> informed <persName
                                corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> on October 8 that <persName
                                corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName> “very sensibly avoided engaging
                            in an apology for or defense of past U.S. actions in Burma.” <persName
                                corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> believed it would have been
                            counterproductive and that it should not be attempted in future
                            contacts. <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> sent <persName
                                corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s advice to the Burma desk.
                            (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>, October 8;
                            Department of State, EA/BUC Files: Lot 66 D 483, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                                >POL</gloss> 15–1, Head of State, Exec Branch (<persName
                                corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName>))</p>
                        <p>On October 9, the Department commented on the “friendly and frank” tenor
                            of the conversation: “His suspicions past US activities Burma are of
                            course an old story which we recognize as important element our current
                            problem establishing satisfactory relations with him. Believe you were
                            wise not to attempt refute his accusations but to stress instead your
                            assurances regarding future. Although <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne
                                Win</persName>’s suspicions based on serious distortions of facts on
                            past US relations with one of his associates, we have always believed no
                            useful purpose would be served by debating subject with him. Our efforts
                            must now concentrate on future actions to dispel to extent possible
                                <persName corresp="#p_NWG1">Ne Win</persName>’s lingering suspicions
                            of US motives.” (Telegram 120; ibid., Central Files, <gloss
                                target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 BURMA–US)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Byroade</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
