<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-09-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                    <head>90. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Cambodia</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d90fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                            751H.00/9–762. Secret; Priority. Repeated to Bangkok, Saigon, Vientiane,
                            Paris, London, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss><gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>. There is no time of transmission on the source text;
                            the telegram was received on September 8 at 1:37 a.m.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Phnom Penh</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-09-07">September 7,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>221. Policy. This message represents our evaluation of present situation and
                        concludes with our views as to courses of action open to US which would be
                        designed meet in part <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s
                        desires without involving US in commitments we could not give nor in actions
                        damaging to our relations with our Thai and South Vietnamese allies.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s present insistent demands
                        for “guarantees” of Cambodian neutrality and territorial integrity and his
                        threat to ask for Soviet <pb facs="0228" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> and
                        Chinese Communist troops as last resort to protect Cambodian independence
                        may be large-scale blackmail. Possibility always exists however, he may do
                        just what he says in event “guarantees” or some kind of assurances affording
                        partial, if not full, satisfaction his needs are not forthcoming. To the
                        extent we ignore this possibility, we are heading on collision course
                        leading to possible disaster.</p>
                    <p>I have been struck in my round of calls by seriousness with which Cambodian
                        leaders view, or profess to view, situation. While their comments to me
                        might be part of planned campaign put <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss>
                        position in most favorable light, there is no doubt of intensity their
                        feeling and their apprehension present situation. Some of this apprehension
                        could represent their concern <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s course may be leading Cambodia toward Communist
                        camp. Underlying it all, however, is same obsession with Cambodian survival
                        as is clearly evidenced by <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>
                        himself. Prince Monireth, elder statesman <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn
                            Nouth</persName> and Queen, like other top officials, have stressed
                        Cambodian fears their neighbors, which include North Vietnamese and Pathet
                        Lao as well as Thais and South Vietnamese. They all paint picture of small,
                        weak and relatively defenseless Cambodia menaced by two powerful neighbors
                        on each side with historical record of aggressive designs against Cambodia.
                        Cambodians recall that almost 100 years ago they sought French protectorate
                        to avoid being absorbed by Thais and Annamites and with withdrawal of French
                        protection they now again consider themselves faced by same danger. They all
                        make particular point of <persName corresp="#p_DC1">Dap Chhuon</persName>
                        overthrow government and fact that <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                        representative, who expelled for participating in plot, is now Cabinet
                        minister in Saigon. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName> says
                            <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss> has in possession map showing Thai
                        and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> plans for partition Cambodian
                        territory. <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> and Cambodians
                        are evidently not unaware of Thai and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                        complicity in <persName corresp="#p_SNT1">Son Ngoc Thanh</persName> efforts
                        in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and Thailand to spark movement to
                        overthrow <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>. All top officials
                        emphasize that repeated border incidents, for which they accept no
                        responsibility and ascribe all blame to their neighbors, have led to present
                        situation and <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss> cannot continue suffer
                        this constant harassment. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName>
                        warned that when <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> says he may
                        take a certain course, this is not bluff. He recalled <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s warning re recognition Communist
                        China and his extension of such recognition when <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> troops occupied border areas Stung Treng Province in 1958.
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName> struck ominous note “I
                        have worked many years with my Prince and I know him well”.</p>
                    <p>While picture of small, weak Cambodia without means of defense against
                        organized aggression across border may be convincing one, less convincing is
                        Cambodian unwillingness accept any responsibility for border incidents or
                        for actions which have contributed to present situation. <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s constant public attacks on Thai
                        leaders and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, coupled with Cambodian
                        press campaign along similar lines, <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss>’s
                            <pb facs="0229" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> failure return <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> planes and crew of seized fishing vessel
                        are examples of <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss> intransigeance which has
                        added fuel to flame. <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>
                        recognized Cambodia’s greatest weapon is publicity and plays it to the
                        hilt.</p>
                    <p>While US economic and military aid are our best assets in present situation,
                        developments in recent months have tended to make these assets less
                        effective than previously. Private and public statements by <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> and Minister Defense and Chief of
                        Staff General <persName corresp="#p_LNG1">Lon Nol</persName> indicates some
                        dissatisfaction with volume and types US military <gloss target="#t_AID1">aid</gloss>. They compare small amount aid given Cambodia with that
                        given Thais and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and add these neighbors
                        use US material for aggression against Cambodia. General <persName corresp="#p_LNG1">Lon Nol</persName> recently observed to Chief <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Cambodia was receiving negative response
                        to its requests. He pointed to <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss> request
                        for military allowances in connection with proposed troop increase and to US
                        rejection Cambodian appeal for international conference. Belief <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> is taking steps in Bangkok and Saigon in
                        effort explore means finding solution for difficulties will help US position
                        in Cambodia to certain degree, but larger question of where Cambodia is
                        heading and what we can do to prevent its sliding into Communist camp
                        remains.</p>
                    <p>US interests are best served at this stage of developments in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, particularly in view of situation <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and in light uncertainties re outcome, of
                        efforts achieve settlement Laotian problem, by truly neutral, genuinely
                        independent Cambodia. However, only development likely impress <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> would be resounding US success in
                        area, as nothing succeeds like success with him, and specter of possible
                        Communist success in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, giving him
                        impression Communism may be wave of future, evidently has major influence on
                        his thinking. Combined US-<gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> victory in
                            <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> would contribute more than anything
                        else to US influence with <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>,
                        but even that would probably not lead to any basic change in his policy.
                        Since such victory not yet at hand, we must seek best course presently
                        available.</p>
                    <p>Recommend we go ahead full speed on effort adapt Laos Accord current
                        situation. While this in itself does not appear be enough meet needs present
                        situation, it would provide framework within which we could move to approach
                        basic question of “guarantees” or assurances for Cambodian independence.
                        Additionally, believe only way in which assurances satisfactory to both
                        Cambodians and Thais and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> could be
                        provided would be through some type observation or control group stationed
                        in area and empowered to move freely along border area in event of incidents
                        requiring investigation and action. We would hope this mechanism could be
                        established under <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> auspices, which should
                        insure neutral or impartial, international composition of observation or
                        control group, and which in effect is only mechanism offering real
                        possibility of acceptance by those concerned. (Any suggestion of extension
                        of <pb facs="0230" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> would again raise question of conference
                        and problem of body to which reports would be made.)</p>
                    <p>Bangkok’s 425<note n="1" xml:id="d90fn1">Telegram 425, September 6,
                            transmitted the text of a note from Thailand to the U.N. Acting
                            Secretary-General inviting him to send a U.N. representative to
                            investigate Cambodian charges that Thailand was threatening Cambodian
                            neutrality and independence. (Ibid., 751H.00/9–662)</note> opens way to
                        move in desirable direction. Such course should provide means of bringing
                        stability to border areas and lessen tension which has risen to such
                        dangerous peak.</p>
                    <p>Obviously, solution of type suggested, which gives <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> good part of what he has been
                        clamoring for, may reinforce his belief that public demands coupled with
                        blackmailing tactics are way to get what he wants from us. Yet, in situation
                        we now face, apparent US concessions to these demands may be price we have
                        to pay to keep Cambodia truly neutral and deny its space to Communists. And,
                        at this writing we cannot be completely certain that even this price will be
                        enough.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SPD1"><hi rend="strong">Sprouse</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>