<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1000</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1000</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-09-27T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-09-27T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-27T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-27T17:00:00-05:00" n="1000"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1000">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.115/997: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-27T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 27, 1940—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>368. Your 837, September 14, 9 a.m.,<note n="14" xml:id="d1000fn14">Not printed,
                        but see note No. 1630, September 13, from the American Ambassador in Japan
                        to the Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v01#pg_695">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, Vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 695</ref>.</note> 842, September 16, 5
                        p.m.,<note n="13" xml:id="d1000fn13">Not printed.</note> and 878, September
                    22, 2 p.m.<note n="15" xml:id="d1000fn15">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_697">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 697</ref>.</note> The Department
                    heartily approves the approach you have made to the Foreign Minister.<note
                        n="16" xml:id="d1000fn16">Yosuke Matsuoka.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0906" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/>
                <p>It seems to the Department that the continued bombing of American properties in
                    China by Japanese aircraft and the completely inexcusable multiple bombings of
                    certain property do not, unless such bombings cease immediately, warrant the
                    withholding longer from the American public full information in regard to (1)
                    the number and extent of these bombings since the beginning of the Sino-Japanese
                    hostilities; (2) the protests which have been lodged against them with the
                    Japanese Government and the unsatisfactory response which the Japanese
                    Government has made to our representations—a response whose unsatisfactory
                    nature is not only reflected in the general weakness of the explanations offered
                    but also in the continuance and repetition of the bombings; and (3) the fact
                    that although properties have been marked with American flags and otherwise and
                    the Japanese authorities have been furnished maps showing the location of
                    American properties, some properties have been repeatedly bombed to an extent
                    which makes unavoidable an assumption that these bombings were deliberate.</p>
                <p>The record of representations and replies which we have under consideration for
                    publication include this Government’s formal note to the Japanese Government
                    dated March 30, 1939;<note n="18" xml:id="d1000fn18">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_643">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Japan, 1931–1941, Vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 643</ref>.</note> oral representations
                    made May 11, 1939, to the Japanese Foreign Minister by you;<note n="19"
                        xml:id="d1000fn19">See memorandum by the Ambassador in Japan, May 11, 1939,
                            <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_646">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 646</ref>.</note> the Japanese
                    Government’s reply of May 17, 1939;<note n="20" xml:id="d1000fn20">See telegram
                        No. 238, May 19, 1939, 4 p.m., from the Chargé in Japan, <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v01#pg_649">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 649</ref>.</note> to this Government’s
                    note of March 30, 1939; this Government’s formal note to the Japanese Government
                    dated May 22, 1939;<note n="21" xml:id="d1000fn21">See telegram No. 241, May 22,
                        1939, 6 p.m., from the Chargé in Japan, <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_650">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 650</ref>.</note> Mr. Dooman’s
                    representations to the Foreign Minister of June 19, 1939;<note n="22"
                        xml:id="d1000fn22">See telegram No. 283, June 19, 1939, 7 p.m., <ref
                            target="frus1939v04#pg_342">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1939, Vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 342</ref>.</note> and your note of
                    September 13, 1940 (referred to in your 837, September 14, 9 a.m.), which the
                    Department would appreciate receiving by radio via Shanghai in full text.</p>
                <p>In view of your 878, September 22, 2 p.m., particularly the Foreign Minister’s
                    statement, as mentioned in the last substantive paragraph of that telegram, the
                    Department suggests that you wait for what you consider a reasonable time to
                    determine whether or not effective action is being taken by the Japanese
                    Government to halt the bombings; that at the expiration of such time you advise
                    the Department; <pb facs="0907" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/> and that you proceed
                    to inform Mr. Matsuoka that full information in regard to the bombings, as
                    indicated above, will be released to the public. You may say that it has been
                    the long-established practice of this Government to keep the American public as
                    fully informed as practicable with regard to events affecting American rights
                    and interests in foreign countries, that consequent upon an expression of desire
                    on the part of the Japanese Government that publication of documents and full
                    data relating to cases of bombing of American properties be withheld, this
                    Government had been encouraged to hope that effective measures of a preventive
                    character would be devised by the Japanese Government but that, in view of the
                    continuance with undiminished vigor of attacks on American properties in China,
                    the Department is reluctantly forced to the conclusion that no useful purpose
                    would be served by further delay in making available to the American public
                    information regarding the extent and character of damage inflicted upon American
                    properties in China by Japanese forces during the current hostilities.</p>
                <p>With particular reference to your 842, September 16, 5 p.m., in which mention is
                    made of the “tenth bombing” of the Methodist Episcopal mission, and for the
                    purposes of the record, it appears from the reports of the bombing of American
                    Methodist mission properties at Chungking received by the Department that those
                    properties are situated in two separate areas (one in the Daijihang—or
                    Tachiahang—section near the banking district and the other in the western part
                    of the city) and have together been bombed eleven times. It is believed that the
                    western district properties include the Suteh Girls’ school, a hospital, a
                    church (the Lewis Memorial Church?) and certain residences, and that the
                    Daijihang compound includes a hospital, a church and residences. Chungking is
                    hereby requested to clarify this aspect of the matter for your and the
                    Department’s information.</p>
                <p>Sent to Tokyo via Shanghai. Repeated to Chungking, Peiping. Shanghai please
                    repeat to Chungking and to Peiping Tokyo’s telegram 837, September 14, 9
                    a.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
