<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Shanghai ( (Butrick) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1055</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1055</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-21T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-21T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-21T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-21T04:00:00-05:00" n="1055"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1055">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">390.1115A/74: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butrick</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-21T17:00:00+08:00"
                            >October 21, 1940—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received October 21—10:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1126. Evacuation of Americans from Shanghai. The American President Lines acting
                    as agents inform me that the vessels of the <pb facs="0947" n="939"
                        xml:id="pg_939"/> Matson Line will charge $395 for minimum first class
                    accommodations, all regular first and second class accommodations will be
                    considered first class, which establishes the minimum first class rate for the
                    poorest second class accommodations; that the vessels of the United States Lines
                    will charge $450 for minimum first class accommodations, that all regular first,
                    second and third class accommodations will be considered first class which
                    establishes the minimum first class rate for the poorest third class
                    accommodations. Both ships apparently have slightly lower fares for dormitories
                    (possibly improvised, with cots).</p>
                <p>I feel that I ought to inform the Department that there exists deep
                    dissatisfaction among the Americans here with the above arrangements and that
                    the evacuation program may fail, for the present at least, unless greater
                    consideration is given to the matter of adjusting fares downward, according to
                    accommodations supplied. Some Americans can afford first class accommodations,
                    many cannot.</p>
                <p>Americans here are loyal and patriotic. They feel that the present evacuation
                    advice should be heeded because it is a part of American national policy. By and
                    large they do not feel that they are in immediate danger and they leave their
                    homes here with reluctance. Many of them are selling their motor cars, household
                    furnishings, et cetera, at a great loss. Many Americans will undergo the heavy
                    expense of maintaining themselves here and their families in the United States.
                    Many of the missionaries on returning to the United States will become public
                    charges on their missions and possibly even be dismissed. The problem for many
                    Americans is a serious one, possibly even implying at a future date loss of
                    their businesses or employment. Americans in general recall that their
                    Government over a period of years has encouraged them to come to China in the
                    furtherance of American export trade and American missionary and philanthropic
                    enterprises. This encouragement has been expressed through the maintenance of
                    the open-door policy, the system of extraterritoriality, the passage by Congress
                    of the China Trade Act,<note n="3" xml:id="d1055fn3">Approved September 19,
                        1922; 42 Stat. 849.</note> the establishment of export credits and the
                    general protection afforded Americans and American business. Local Americans
                    will pay fares that seem reasonable to them but they will, I fear, resent being
                    charged high fares at a time when they feel they are assisting the national
                    policy and their personal fortunes are being jeopardized.</p>
                <p>All career officers have read this message and concur.</p>
                <p>Sent to the Department. Repeated to Chungking and Peiping.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Butrick</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
