<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-23T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-23T04:00:00-05:00" n="1082" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1082">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">894.00/934: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-23T18:00:00+09:00">July 23, 1940—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received July 23—12:46 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>613. It is reported that the Cabinet will immediately proceed to
                            formulate its foreign policy along the lines of “strictest of relations
                            with the Axis powers and vigorous prosecution of the plan for the
                            establishment of a new order in East Asia”, and that announcement will
                            be made as soon as possible with regard to the decision reached.<note n="26" xml:id="d1082fn26">For a “summary of fundamental national
                                policies”, issued by the Konoye Cabinet on August 1, see <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_108"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                                    108</ref>.</note> While awaiting such clarification, I present
                            hereunder my provisional assessment of the present situation.</p>
                        <p>1. The selection of Prince Konoye to lead the new Cabinet depended on the
                            question whether or not the end of the conflict with China could be
                            expected to materialize within the reasonably near <pb facs="0976" n="968" xml:id="pg_968"/> future. The conflict had begun during
                            Prince Konoye’s first premiership, and it was not only his personal hope
                            but the expectation of the public that he should be in office when the
                            conflict be concluded. The belief of many of the most competent
                            observers that the choice would fall on Baron Hiranuma was based on the
                            analysis in certain official quarters of the prospects of peace with
                            China, that the reappearance at this time of Prince Konoye would be
                            premature. The selection is nevertheless, we believe, clear indication
                            that such analysis has been revised in the light of European
                            developments and that a more optimistic view prevails with regard to the
                            prospects of bringing the China conflict to an end.</p>
                        <p>2. The reasons are [<hi rend="italic">for?</hi>] the retirement of the
                            Yonai Cabinet have not been fully exposed and their nature is suggested
                            by the emphasis which is being laid on future close association with the
                            Axis and on the setting up of an economic bloc in the Far East. As the
                            Department is aware, Admiral Yonai has been persistently skeptical over
                            the benefits to Japan of close association with the Axis Powers, he has
                            been lukewarm over the new order in East Asia and he looked for
                            adjustment of relations with the United States and Great Britain. His
                            position on these matters was fairly well concealed, but the public
                            sensed nevertheless that the degree of vigor with which the Yonai
                            Cabinet approached problems directly and indirectly related to the China
                            conflict in no way corresponded with the accelerated tempo of events in
                            Europe which seemed to impel Japan toward “strengthening its relations
                            with the Axis Powers.”</p>
                        <p>A second factor was undoubtedly the desire on the part of the Japanese
                            people after a decade of almost complete isolation to grasp the hands
                            held out by nations who have demonstrated their military power. There
                            occurred therefore a force against which a Cabinet which contributed
                            little toward the fulfillment of Japanese ambitions in China could not
                            prevail.</p>
                        <p>3. The Cabinet just constituted is on the whole conservative in
                            complexion, the exceptions are Hoshino, Minister without Portfolio and
                            concurrently Director of the Planning Board, Kazami, Minister of
                            Justice, and possibly Matsuoka. Hoshino has long been a stalwart
                            proponent of the economic bloc idea, he has had an opportunity to try
                            out his hand in Manchuria and his presence in the Cabinet is therefore a
                            clear indication of intention to establish the economic bloc. Kazami has
                            been given the Justice portfolio to draft changes in the electoral law
                            and parliamentary system which would bring them more closely into line
                            with the single party principle which is now being worked out. Matsuoka
                            is an incorrigible talker and it remains to be seen whether his policies
                            will be as drastic as his recent statements would seem to promise.</p>
                        <pb facs="0977" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/>
                        <p>4. The best opinion today is that there will be no abrupt and drastic
                            change in foreign policy in the immediate future. Although the trend is
                            undeniably toward the Axis Powers, definitive and irrevocable action at
                            this juncture in that direction would appear to be effectively prevented
                            by economic considerations. The Axis Powers are not now in any position
                            to supply Japan with raw materials or to absorb her manufactured goods,
                            Japan being now largely dependent in both respects on the United States
                            and the British Empire. I would therefore expect Japan to refrain in
                            such event from entering into definite commitments with the United
                            States on any terms compatible with American policy or on the other hand
                            with Germany and Italy pending the outcome of the struggle in
                            Europe.</p>
                        <p>5. Whatever trends or developments emerge in future we must reluctantly
                            assume that through the fall of the Yonai Cabinet our efforts during the
                            past several months to create some substantial basis for an improvement
                            in Japanese-American relations have been checked by the turn of events.
                            After establishing contact with the new Foreign Minister I shall study
                            the future outlook and the desirability of recommending a new approach
                            in case some opening worthy of exploration should develop.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>