<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-15T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-15T06:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.92/22: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Thailand</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bangkok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-15T18:00:00+07:00">September 15, 1940—6
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 16—10:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>79. Referring further to the Legation’s telegrams 75, September 13, 2
                            p.m., and 77, September 14, 10 p.m.<note n="79" xml:id="d146fn79">Latter
                                not printed.</note> Further conversations today reveal that the Thai
                            Government will be willing to accede to the request of the Vichy
                            Government that the pact of non-aggression between the two countries
                            shall come into force without the usual formalities, provided both sides
                            agree first on points 1 and 2, incorporated in the text of <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, which was sent to the Vichy
                            Government by the Thai Government and which is quoted in the Legation’s
                            telegram No. 70 [<hi rend="italic">78</hi>], September 15, 4 p.m.<note n="80" xml:id="d146fn80">Not printed; the two points referred to
                                were as follows: “1, the fixation of the Mekong frontier by the deep
                                water channel and the settlement of all other outstanding
                                administrative questions as provided by the exchange of letters
                                under date of 12th June; and 2, the adoption of the Mekong as the
                                frontier between the two countries from the north to the south as
                                far as the frontier of Cambodia, involving the retrocession to
                                Thailand of territories on the right bank of the Mekong opposite to
                                Luang Prabang and Pakse.” (751G.92/21.)</note> Point 1, it is
                            understood, has already been agreed upon in principle by the two
                            Governments, only the details remaining to be worked out by the
                            Governments of Thai and Indochina. Point 2 is a new element which, it is
                            claimed, has been introduced as the result of the fear of the Thai that
                            the Japanese will march in and appear on Thai frontiers which are
                            regarded as artificial by the Thai Government. The proposed return of
                            the territories of Laos and Cambodia, as indicated in the last paragraph
                            of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, it would appear is not
                            regarded as condition for the agreement to bring into force the pact of
                            non-aggression although such an agreement on the part of the Vichy
                            Government as proposed by the Thai is earnestly desired by the Thai
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>The French Minister informed me today in strict confidence that he had
                            received official information to the effect that definite agreement has
                            been reached between the Vichy and the Japanese Governments to provide
                            for permission to march Japanese troops through the northern part of
                            Indochina into China. He believes other commitments have been made also.
                            Therefore, the French Minister pointed out, the <hi rend="italic">status
                                quo</hi> in Indochina has already been upset and this, he believes,
                            strengthens the claims of the Thai. In this connection he revealed to me
                            that in his recent conversation with the Thai Prime Minister and
                            Minister of Foreign Affairs at Lopburi (reference is made to the
                            Legation’s telegram number 72, September 8, 10 p.m.<note n="81" xml:id="d146fn81">Not printed.</note>) the Prime Minister stated
                            that the Japanese had promised to give the Thai what they <pb facs="0126" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> wanted in Indochina but that
                            the Thai Government preferred to deal with the French Government. The
                            Prime Minister, according to further revelation of the French Minister,
                            said that although Great Britain and the United States were urging the
                            maintenance of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in Indochina he
                            (the Prime Minister) had not seen any British and American warships for
                            the enforcement of same.</p>
                        <p>In a conversation today with the British Minister it was revealed that
                            the British, as result of the fear that the Japanese may establish
                            themselves in a sphere of influence in Indochina on the Thai frontier,
                            as reported today by wireless news service from Berlin, may weaken in
                            their resolve to urge and insist that the Thai adhere strictly to the
                            policy of the maintenance of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in
                            Indochina. The British Minister said the Thai Deputy Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs yesterday inquired of him as to the British view in regard to
                            the Thai proposal to the Vichy Government establishing two conditions
                            for the agreement to put into force immediately the pact of
                            non-aggression between the two countries. He said he had replied that
                            the matter was one between Thai and the Vichy Government, that the
                            British would have nothing to say if Vichy should agree to the Thai
                            proposal. I then said to the British Minister that I thought we should
                            continue to go along together in the matter of bringing all possible
                            pressure to bear in order to influence the Thai to remain out of the
                            Indochina affair on the basis of the larger and more far-reaching
                            aspects of the question, which, as he agreed, the Thai officials
                            apparently do not fully understand and appreciate.</p>
                        <p>I am beginning to fear that, as is usually the case, if I am not
                            mistaken, our policy of consistent dealing may, in this, leave us out on
                            a limb in splendid isolation while our friends compromise with the
                            issue. It looks as though the British policy of appeasement is about to
                            be applied to the Thai-Indochina affair.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grant</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>