<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-23T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-23T06:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.94/142: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-23T13:00:00+02:00">September 23, 1940—1
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 4 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>607. My telegram No. 606, September 22, 8 p.m., and previous. Chauvel
                            told me this morning that a military agreement was reached at Hanoi
                            yesterday afternoon which specifically prohibited the entry of Japanese
                            soldiers from the Kwangsi division into Indochinese territory. News of
                            the agreement was immediately communicated by General Nishihara to the
                            commander of that division but in spite of this, last night Japanese
                            troops did enter Indochina in the region of Dong-dang. They were
                            resisted by force. To add to this confusion, said Chauvel, and as an
                            example of Foreign Office coordination between various Japanese
                            governing authorities, the Foreign Office at Tokyo <pb facs="0152" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/> had immediately complained to the French
                            Ambassador that “in spite of an agreement having been reached the French
                            had created an incident[”].</p>
                        <p>He told me that the French had now approximately 100,000 troops in all
                            Indochina of which some 50,000 are north of the Red River.</p>
                        <p>He is giving me this afternoon the text of the political agreement and a
                            summary of the military accord which I shall cable immediately.<note n="94" xml:id="d172fn94">Not printed; see footnote 92, <ref target="#pg_142">p. 142</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>He remarked significantly that he personally had never for a moment
                            doubted that Japan’s ultimate objective was the occupation of and
                            control of French Indochina.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>