<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-23T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-23T03:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.94/141: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-23T17:00:00+09:00">September 23, 1940—5
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 23—8:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>880. 1. The French Embassy informs me that the official communiqué quoted
                            in paragraph 2 of our 881, September 23, 6 p.m.,<note n="95" xml:id="d173fn95"><hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi></note> was by mutual
                            agreement to have been published in Vichy, Hanoi and Tokyo this morning
                            on the entry of Japanese troops into Indochina but that owing to the
                            reported clash between Japanese and Indochinese troops at Dongdang the
                            Foreign Office informed the French Ambassador that the publication in
                            Japan of the communiqué would be delayed until the irritation aroused by
                            the clash had subsided although the Japanese Government realized that
                            the clash had occurred through delayed transmission of orders to the
                            Indochinese troops and was not disposed to hold the French Government
                            responsible. Apparently as a result of the representations of the French
                            Ambassador, a communiqué was published in Tokyo this afternoon (our 881,
                            September 23, 6 p.m., paragraph numbered 1) but the Department will
                            observe that it materially differs from the text which the French
                            Embassy informs me was jointly agreed upon.</p>
                        <p>2. The French Embassy further informs me that prior to the signing of the
                            Franco-Japanese agreement in Hanoi, the Japanese military made further
                            unreasonable demands but it is understood that these demands were
                            finally withdrawn. The present agreement according to the French Embassy
                            provides for the passage of Japanese forces through Indochina and the
                            occupation and use of three air bases with adequate Japanese personnel
                            to man the bases. The agreement is said to be exclusively military and
                            to include no commercial or economic <pb facs="0153" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/> provisions although such provisions may be the
                            subject of future negotiations.</p>
                        <p>Sent to the Department, repeated to Shanghai for Chungking.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>