<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.94/182</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-24">September 24, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Ambassador called to see me this afternoon to communicate to
                            this Government a message from the Chinese Government to the effect that
                            the Chinese army had undertaken military preparations both along the
                            Kwangsi frontier of Indo-China, as well as along the Yunnan frontier.
                            The Chinese Government wished the Government of the United States to
                            know that should the Japanese attempt to invade China through
                            Indo-China, the resistance would be far more considerable than the
                            resistance which had taken place <pb facs="0159" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> at Canton or at Nanning. The Ambassador said that the Chinese
                            Government now had under its control approximately one-third of the
                            Yunnan railway and that he believed that a very stiff resistance would
                            be put up by the Chinese troops.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador once more stressed the importance to China of the
                            reopening of the Burma Road and expressed the hope that the United
                            States would do everything possible to persuade the British Government
                            to reopen the Road.</p>
                        <p>I asked the Ambassador if he had any information as to the progress of
                            the loan negotiation. The Ambassador said that he had not today but that
                            he took it for granted that the matter would soon be concluded.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>