<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political Relations (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d225</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">225</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="225"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d225">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/32</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political
                        Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-21">October 21,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Butler called at his request. He referred to conversations which had been
                    held on the subject of possible British, American and Dutch cooperation in the
                    field of Far Eastern policy with reference especially to the making of tentative
                    “war plans” in relation to certain defense measures. He read to me parts of a
                    telegram in which the <pb facs="0197" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> Foreign Office
                    stated that they intend to have a conference at Singapore at which they hope to
                    have a Dutch representation and would like to have an American representation.
                    This conference is to begin on October 22 and they would welcome the presence of
                    an American representative about a week later. They hope that the United States
                    will exert some influence with regard to the formulation of the Dutch
                    attitude.</p>
                <p>Mr. Butler said that he understood clearly the position which this Government has
                    taken in regard to this matter and that he did not want to press anything upon
                    us. He said that he therefore was merely communicating what his Government had
                    said. He said that he would venture to offer, on his own part, a suggestion,
                    namely, that we might be willing to have our Consul General at Singapore
                    participate in the conference to be held there in the capacity of an
                    “observer”.</p>
                <p>I said that I would report upward what Mr. Butler had said.<note n="30"
                        xml:id="d225fn30">Notation on October 26 by the Secretary of State: “Consul
                        could report without acting as observer. C. H.”</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
