<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/35</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-12">November 12,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Australian Minister called to ascertain whether this Government contemplated
                    sending a good will naval mission to Australia and to other countries in the
                    southern area. I replied by reviewing all of the steps we have taken thus far to
                    deal with the Far Eastern situation, including any threatened movements by Japan
                    to the south, and then added that for the present we had other plans in mind
                    than a good will mission.</p>
                <p>I made some inquiry about the importance of increasing the number of airplanes at
                    Singapore. The Minister replied that his Government had sent 50 planes to
                    Singapore and that the British had some over 100 planes there. In answer to
                    another question, the Minister <pb facs="0215" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> said
                    that Australian plants produced about five or six planes per week and that this
                    capacity would be doubled within the next six weeks. I inquired further whether
                    his Government would consider it very important to send still other planes to
                    Singapore, and he said that he was not advised as to this. I emphasized more
                    than once about the importance of a substantial number of planes being stationed
                    at Singapore, and pointed out that we have assembled at Manila all of our ships
                    in the Far East, including a number of submarines, as well as some
                    airplanes.</p>
                <p>There was some general reference to the present conferences at Berlin<note n="46"
                        xml:id="d252fn46">Reference is to the visit to Berlin of the President of
                        the Soviet Council of Commissars (Molotov).</note> as they might affect the
                    Far East to the detriment of China at the hands of both Japan and Russia. I
                    remarked that we hoped to continue, on an increasing scale, our aid to
                    China.</p>
                <p>Before leaving, the Minister handed me a message of congratulation to the
                    President from the Prime Minister of Australia (message transmitted to
                        President).<note n="47" xml:id="d252fn47">Presumably on the result of the
                        Presidential election, November 5.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
