<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d280</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">280</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Munitions</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">United States Army</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="280"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d280">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.248/438</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-12-11">December 11,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The French Ambassador called on me this afternoon at his request.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador brought up the subject of obtaining munitions for French
                    Indochina.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador quite bluntly that after full consideration by the
                    appropriate authorities of this Government it had been found impossible to
                    permit the exportation to Indochina of the various categories <pb facs="0241"
                        n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> of munitions listed in the memorandum which he had
                    left with me some ten days ago.<note n="67" xml:id="d280fn67">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Ambassador took this without any argument. He then read to me a telegram he
                    had received from the Governor General of Indochina urging that the United
                    States be requested to sell to Indochina the ten airplanes which had been
                    destined for Thailand but which had been held up in the Philippines.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador that there could be no question of selling these airplanes
                    to Indochina since they were going to be utilized by the United States Army, and
                    that if it were found that any old planes now in the Philippines could be
                    spared, they would be sold to China. I took occasion to state that it seemed to
                    me amazing that the French Government would continue to permit the 100 new
                    military planes purchased in the United States to go to pieces in Martinique
                    when these planes would be of enormous value to Indochina in resisting
                    aggression either on the part of Japan or on the part of Thailand. I said I had
                    been very much interested in Mr. Laval’s<note n="68" xml:id="d280fn68">Pierre
                        Laval, Vice President of the French Council of Ministers (Vice
                        Premier).</note> comments on this possibility in his conversation with Mr.
                    Murphy, referred to in Mr. Murphy’s telegram of December 9.<note n="69"
                        xml:id="d280fn69">See telegram No. 1109, December 9, 5 p.m., from the Chargé
                        in Vichy, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, in section under France
                        entitled “Maintenance of Relations by the United States with the French
                        Government at Vichy.”</note> I read the pertinent portions to the
                    Ambassador.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador thereupon burst into a state bordering upon frenzy. He shouted
                    that he had sent ten telegrams to his Government on that subject insisting that
                    the terms of the armistice made possible the shipment to Indochina of the planes
                    in Martinique and that each time he had been turned down flatly with the
                    statement that the terms of the armistice would not permit. Now, he was informed
                    that Mr. Laval was taking a contrary view. He said he would immediately
                    telegraph his Government and insist that steps be taken at once to ship these
                    planes to Indochina.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
