<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations ( (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="388"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d388">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102/90½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-12">June 12,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I share Mr. Hamilton’s view<note n="62" xml:id="d388fn62">See memorandum by the
                        Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs, June 11, <ref target="#pg_349"
                            >p. 349</ref>.</note> that no useful purpose would be served by our
                    attempting to make reply to the Chinese Government. I feel, however, that we
                    should give serious consideration to points (1) and (2), and that we should not
                    entirely rule out point (3).</p>
                <p>In my opinion, the United States must, no matter what we may do or not do in the
                    field of material pressures, continue to maintain a diplomatic front on the
                    Pacific and in the Far East. I feel that, no matter what we may wish that we
                    might do, it is impossible for us to “abandon” our principles and to scrap our
                    objectives in relation to China, to Japan, to China and Japan, and in relations
                    with other countries in the Far East. The fact that there have been and are
                    hostilities in the Far East has not dissolved-out our interests and concern in
                    and with regard to that region. The fact that there is a war in Europe and that
                    we are menaced by trans-Atlantic developments does not dissolve-out our
                    interests and concern in and with regard to the Far East and the fact that we
                    are menaced by trans-Pacific developments. In the case of the Japanese-Chinese
                    conflict, we have one theater of operations in which broadly speaking the armed
                    conflict has been running in a manner unfavorable to the aggressor side. That
                    China continue to resist Japan will be to the advantage of the United States and
                    Great Britain and France. The United States and Great Britain and France should,
                    therefore, encourage and as far as possible support China’s resistance. These
                    three powers should cling to those of their “special” rights in China the
                    existence of which is now helpful both as regards their own nationals and as
                    regards China while resisting Japan. Also, they should as far as possible keep
                    open channels of communication with China. The Chinese suggestion in those
                    connections is a common-sense suggestion. True, we should at this time speak
                    gently to Japan and we should not give Japanese chauvinists new grounds for
                    argumentation that the Japanese Navy should move toward new conquests, but we
                    need not stand in our tracks as regards diplomatic pursuit of our objectives in
                    China or fear even to discuss with the British and the French, with whom we now
                    are associated in a world conflict, measures of common interest and concern in
                    the Far East as well as elsewhere.</p>
                <p>I recommend that we seriously consider making a declaration such as the Chinese
                    suggest and that we remind the British and the French <pb facs="0360" n="352"
                        xml:id="pg_352"/> Governments that we regard it important that channels of
                    communication be not closed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
