<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d403</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">403</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="403"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/1581</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-28">June 28,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British Ambassador, accompanied by the Minister of Australia, called at my
                    request. I said that I desired to make reply to the two proposals and inquiries
                    made by their two Governments on yesterday and set forth in an <hi rend="italic"
                        >aide-mémoire</hi> placed on file yesterday.<note n="86" xml:id="d403fn86">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_365">p. 365</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>One was an inquiry as to whether this Government would place an embargo against
                    Japan and send our fleet to Singapore, where it might have a base. To this I
                    said that I had replied on yesterday to the effect that we could not think of
                    sending our fleet to Singapore for the sake of peace in the Pacific area: that
                    this would leave the entire Atlantic seaboard, north and south, exposed to
                    possible European threats; and, secondly, as to the embargo proposal, I said
                    that this country has been progressively bringing economic pressure to bear on
                    Japan since last summer, now a year, and I enumerated the different steps and
                    methods, which are familiar to all, and added that our fleet is now somewhere in
                    the Pacific near Hawaii. I said that we have and are doing everything possible
                    short of a serious risk of actual military hostilities to keep the Japanese
                    situation stabilized, and that this course during the past year is the best
                    evidence of our intentions and activities in the future.</p>
                <p>As to the second proposal of a joint effort to bring about peace between Japan
                    and China, I explained rather fully what this Government has been doing during
                    the past several weeks to explore every phase of the Japanese possibilities,
                    making it clear that until the French surrender the developments were
                    increasingly interesting, but that since the surrender of the French, the
                    military group is moving in the direction of Hitler and Hitlerism with all that
                    that means in making aggravated application of their doctrine of the new order
                    in eastern Asia. The Ambassador finally inquired as to what objection there
                    could be to an effort by the British and the Australians to bring about peace
                    adjustments between Japan and China. I said that, of course, my Government would
                    have no thought or occasion to object, that we ourselves, as stated, have for
                    some weeks been exploring the situation; that if, as the Minister of Australia
                    says, Australia can make certain concessions of iron ore privileges and other
                    things to Japan in which she is much interested, and if the British can make
                    some concessions of interest and value to Japan and they desire then to call on
                    Japan and China to see what concessions they are willing to make upon the theory
                    that all of the countries must make some <pb facs="0378" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"
                    /> concessions if peace is to be brought about, this objective would be in line
                    with the desires of this Government; that this Government would only make two
                    points in that connection, one, the principles underlying the Japanese new order
                    in eastern Asia policy as it is being practiced would need negativing or at
                    least serious modifying, and, second, that no properties or interests of China
                    be offered to Japan by Great Britain or the United States, or, in other words,
                    that we do not make peace with Japan at the expense of China nor at the expense
                    of the principles which were contained in my statement to Japan and 55 other
                    governments in July, 1937,<note n="87" xml:id="d403fn87">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_325">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 325</ref>.</note> when Japan moved into
                    China for the purpose of its conquest. The Ambassador and Minister seemed to
                    understand this view and also that this Government has already moved along this
                    entire direction, especially so far as Japan is concerned.</p>
                <p>I handed the Ambassador and the Minister as an informal record of statements made
                    orally a copy of the attached statement.<note n="88" xml:id="d403fn88">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
