<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-23T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-23T22:00:00-05:00" n="470" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d470">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94119/693: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Second Secretary of Embassy in China</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Paxton</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-24T11:00:00+08:00">November 24, 1940—11
                                        a.m.</date><lb/>[Received November 24—5:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>122. This office’s 121, November 19, 4 p.m.,<note n="83" xml:id="d470fn83">Not printed.</note> Wang-Japanese
                                negotiations. The French Consul yesterday evening told of an
                                interview he had a few days ago with Hidaka, Counselor of the
                                Japanese Embassy, at which the latter said that General Abe would
                                return to this city shortly for formal signature of the treaty which
                                had received approval at Tokyo.</p>
                            <p>This morning the same informant gave an account of a conversation he
                                had just had with Chu Min Yi in which that official stated that the
                                treaty would be signed by the end of this week as the prolonged
                                delay was proving embarrassing; that German pressure had been
                                influential in accelerating Japanese approval; that Italian
                                recognition would follow Japanese action at once but that the
                                Germans were not expected to act so promptly. It was also stated
                                that the “principal terms” of the treaty would be published without
                                delay but that certain <pb facs="0452" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/>
                                economic points involving considerations of “military necessity”
                                would not be given publicity as yet and that Abe would probably not
                                continue as Japanese Ambassador to the Nanking regime after the
                                treaty had been signed.</p>
                            <p>Sent to the Department; repeated to Chungking, Peking, and Shanghai.
                                Code text by mail to Tokyo.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Paxton</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>