<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d512</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">512</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-02-05T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-02-05T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyDoZHa1V3dM762" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085173"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military communication</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-02-05T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-02-05T05:00:00-05:00" n="512"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d512">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/15659: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-02-05T18:00:00+08:00"
                            >February 5, 1940—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received February 5—2:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I have just completed a trip on the Yangtze River from the mouth of the Whangpoo
                    to Hankow and back accompanied by Military Attaché Mayer, Naval Attaché
                    Overesch, Assistant Naval Attaché McHugh and Consul Lafoon. We traveled as
                    guests of Admiral Glassford<note n="38" xml:id="d512fn38">Rear Adm. William A.
                        Glassford, Jr., Commander of the U. S. Yangtze Patrol.</note> on U. S. S.
                        <hi rend="italic">Luzon</hi> and stopped at Chinkiang, Nanking, Wuhu,
                    Anking, Kiukiang, Huangshihkong and Sankiangkow to deliver packages and mail to
                    Americans and to give us an opportunity to visit and talk with Americans.</p>
                <p>Following comments are made as a result of personal observation and conversations
                    en route:</p>
                <p>The Yangtze River from its mouth to Yochow is controlled by the Japanese Army as
                    a line of military communication. This control is exercised by means of
                    occasional small garrisons ashore, river patrol vessels and maintenance of
                    station ships. Nothing moves on the river between points mentioned except with
                    the permission of the Japanese Army.</p>
                <p>River is commercially dead, there is a complete absence of Chinese and foreign
                    shipping except for a few small junks and traveling between villages and larger
                    towns. All Chinese merchants of substance and bankers have disappeared. The only
                    shipping on the river consists of Japanese naval gunboats, army transports and
                    numerous diesel engine vessels, most of them small wood ships of a type seen in
                    the Inland Sea of Japan. At one time it was estimated that there were perhaps
                    5,000 of these on the river. They carry military supplies and cargo. All vessels
                    of whatever types are controlled by the army, most if not all of them being
                    manned by men in army uniform. Not a single naval vessel of combatant value to a
                    fleet is used on this duty. Only obsolete cruisers, gunboats, and patrol boats
                    were sighted between Shanghai and Hankow.</p>
                <pb facs="0499" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/>
                <p>Except for this very real and effective control over the river and the traffic
                    which it serves, the Japanese Army has but little control over areas [north?] or
                    south of the river, except along railroads, highways and canals, that extend
                    back from the river. Chinese life carries on as usual except that there are
                    areas on either bank in which there has been guerilla activity, and here
                    ruthless destruction has been carried out by the Japanese as punishment for
                    damage done to Japanese shipping or to Japanese personnel. The great cities of
                    Anking, Wuhu, Kiukiang, Wuchang and Hankow have been partially devastated and
                    the former enterprising population widely dispersed. In many of the towns along
                    the river Japanese military has demolished whole blocks of buildings just to
                    obtain wood for fuel. Less than 50 percent of the normal population remains.
                    Anking has been reduced from 120,000 to 5,000. Large parts of these riparian
                    towns have been staked out by the Japanese Army and Navy as military zones for
                    the exclusive use of Japanese.</p>
                <p>Currency throughout area of river is the Chinese national dollar. Japanese
                    military scrip is used almost entirely among Japanese. Scrip has been used to
                    obtain supplies and goods under forced sale but Chinese quickly dispose of scrip
                    for national currency. Japanese military are acquiring by forced sale or
                    otherwise all of the exportable material, such as cotton, silk, rice, china,
                    grass, sugar, vegetable oils, and shipping it down river in military ships for
                    their own account. Material which they are acquiring consists for most part of
                    accumulated stocks of the past year and a half. When these stocks have been
                    absorbed it is expected the Japanese will begin to find difficulty obtaining new
                    stocks unless they are prepared to offer better terms or better money.</p>
                <p>American oil companies had exhausted all stocks before Japanese obtained control
                    of river and have not been permitted to import for their own account since.
                    American buyers of Chinese products have been able to get out stocks on hand but
                    have not been able to purchase new stocks.</p>
                <p>There is evidence of a desire on the part of the Japanese Army thus far to be
                    considerate of the personal wants and comforts of Americans. American
                    missionaries furthermore have been allowed to carry on their charitable and
                    religious work. (There is, however, an atmosphere of uncertainty and uneasiness
                    about this situation and there is no tangible assurance that the attitude
                    displayed by the Japanese toward Americans to date has been genuine or other
                    than an attempt to placate public opinion in the United States and to pit us
                    against other foreigners in China who have not been treated thus.[)]</p>
                <p>Politically the Japanese military have no control whatever throughout valley
                    except in immediate neighborhood of garrisons and within <pb facs="0500" n="492"
                        xml:id="pg_492"/> rifle range of lines of communication. There is no
                    interest among local Chinese population in much discussed Wang Ching-wei plans
                    which if established will merely serve as pseudo-legal heir to business
                    monopolies now functioning as adjunct to military operations. Chinese native
                    Nationalist regime functions and collects taxes on both banks of river except in
                    neighborhood of Japanese garrisons and Chinese residents registered with the
                    Japanese military pay taxes to guerilla regimes that dot the countryside.</p>
                <p>Navigationally the river is safe for commercial shipping, and I find it difficult
                    to understand continued Japanese Army restrictions upon foreign trade and
                    shipping except on the theory that such military restrictions are maintained
                    with intent to squeeze out non-Japanese and compel them to relinquish at a
                    sacrifice trading facilities built up over long period of years. At least 60
                    small ocean-going steamers of from 2,000 to 3,500 tons were observed during the
                    voyage. Chinese booms and obstructions have been largely removed.</p>
                <p>Commercially, the Japanese attempt to dominate the Yangtze River is doomed to
                    failure. Temporary benefits are derived by the purchase of certain commodities
                    with worthless military scrip. The use of legal yen is even prohibited. To date
                    the Chinese are able to exchange this scrip back to old Chinese currency.
                    Eventually and rapidly, however, the scarcity of good currency and the
                    impoverishment of the Japanese controlled areas through seizure of goods and
                    ruthless exploitation will create a serious condition.</p>
                <p>American goods, even if permitted to be shipped in, will find neither a market to
                    absorb them nor other than Japanese controlled distributors who will, as a
                    matter of policy, discriminate against their distribution. Only the complete
                    withdrawal of the Japanese military with consequent freedom of action of Chinese
                    markets will restore either the market or distributing agencies.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Chungking, Peiping, Hankow. Peiping air mail to Tokyo.</p>
                <p>Paraphrase by pouch to Commander in Chief, Asiatic Fleet. Naval and Military
                    Attachés request their Departments be informed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
