<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-24T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="540" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.516/672a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-24T19:00:00-05:00">April 24, 1940—7
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>127. 1. There have been a number of indications that the Nanking
                                regime may soon establish a new “central bank” and issue a new
                                currency. Bearing in mind the preferential position which has been
                                afforded to Japanese commerce and enterprise in Manchuria, Inner
                                Mongolia, and north China by the currency systems, with their
                                accompanying controls of trade and exchange, which have been
                                established by the Japanese-sponsored authorities in those areas,
                                the Department has ample reason to anticipate that the establishment
                                of a new “central bank” and the issuance of a new currency in
                                central China would result in serious discrimination against and
                                consequent detriment to American trade and enterprise in the
                                important central China area. It seems likely that any new currency
                                which may be issued would be pegged to the yen and be supported by
                                exchange and trade control, thus bringing central China within the
                                “yen bloc” and establishing a fundamental discrimination in favor of
                                Japanese commerce and enterprise as compared with the commerce and
                                enterprise of the United States and other third countries.</p>
                            <p>2. The Department views the probabilities in regard to this important
                                matter with great concern.</p>
                            <pb facs="0521" n="513" xml:id="pg_513"/>
                            <p>3. The Department has noted with special interest paragraph 3 of your
                                telegram No. 256, April 17, 7 p.m.,<note n="79" xml:id="d540fn79"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_317">p.
                                        317</ref>.</note> in which you report a growing loss of
                                confidence in Japan in the conception of East Asia as a
                                self-sufficient economic unit. This development would seem to offer
                                a hope that influence could be brought to bear in Japan which might
                                dissuade the Japanese Government from making a new currency move in
                                central China. Accordingly, the Department would welcome any
                                suggestion which you may have in regard to possible action by this
                                Government which might be best calculated to contribute to the end
                                desired.</p>
                            <p>Sent to Tokyo via Shanghai. Repeated to Chungking and Peiping.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>