<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations ( (Dunn) ) to the Under
                    Secretary of State ( (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d638</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">638</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recn8b1d7iCOsszeq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100445"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum products</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="638"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d638">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894.24/1036½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-29">July 29,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I had two calls at my house over the weekend by members of the British Embassy,
                    sent by the Ambassador to lay before us considerations with respect to the
                    President’s proclamation calling for the licensing of petroleum products and
                    scrap. The Ambassador has asked that these considerations be laid before you as
                    soon as may be possible. I understand that he, himself, is asking for an
                    appointment to see you today.</p>
                <p>According to telegrams received by the British Ambassador from the Foreign
                    Office, the British Government feels that the licensing proclamation has had a
                    bad effect in Japan, and may result in bringing matters to a head in the Far
                    East. The British Government point out the vital importance of high octane gas
                    in their present war effort, and state that they are at present taking the whole
                    output of high octane gas from The Netherlands Indies. The British Government
                    are in accord with our desire to prevent large deliveries of gasoline to Japan
                    at this time, but they feel that it is best not to bring about a crisis at this
                    time, nor to have to go back on measures already taken. To sum up, the British
                    are fearful that this licensing measure may result in the Japanese taking steps
                    to insure possession and control of the petroleum products in The Netherlands
                    Indies.</p>
                <p>Another point brought up by the British Embassy is with respect to the
                    relationship between the British Government and the American oil producers and
                    exporters. The British officials have been told by American producers with some
                    heat that the British Government is responsible for the placing of restrictions
                    on exports of certain petroleum products from the United States in order to
                    benefit through the sale of these same products to the Japanese from other
                    sources, both British and Dutch. The British officials are extremely
                    apprehensive whether the picture presented as a result of the President’s
                    proclamation will not seem to justify the accusation now being made by the
                    American oil companies along those lines. The British make the statement that
                    the matter of their relationship with the American oil companies is of primary
                    importance to them in the carrying out of the war. They state that if the
                    American oil companies really believe <pb facs="0600" n="592" xml:id="pg_592"/>
                    that the British have instigated the President’s action for the purpose of
                    benefiting from the restriction of the sale of American products, the oil
                    companies can greatly hamper British action in defense of the British Isles, not
                    to speak of matters relating to the Far East and other areas. The British
                    Embassy is particularly anxious that we take steps to make known to the American
                    oil companies, both on the Atlantic and the Pacific seaboards that this action
                    of the President was taken entirely without any relationship to the British, and
                    most certainly not at their inspiration or instigation, and that it is entirely
                    based upon a strictly American policy. (This suggestion appears reasonable to
                    me: the oil companies which will be represented at your forthcoming meeting
                    regarding the Spanish Atlantic area could be informed at that time along these
                    lines, and, if you approve of so doing, I could communicate with Mr. Grady, now
                    in San Francisco, and have him drop that word to the oil companies of the
                    Pacific coast, who, no doubt, will all be represented at the meeting of the
                    National Trade Council which Mr. Grady is attending.)</p>
                <p>Another matter the British were concerned with was the question of aviation
                    gasoline and aviation lubricating oil which they now draw from the United States
                    for their requirements in Great Britain. I told Mr. Butler, Counselor of the
                    Embassy, both Saturday and yesterday, that I could assure him that there was
                    absolutely no intention whatever of restricting supplies of this kind in the
                    case of British requirements, and that as licenses will be granted for countries
                    in this hemisphere, they could always draw as much as they required through
                    their Canadian companies, and that if any difficulties arose in regard to this
                    question, we were ready to discuss them as they came up.</p>
                <p>I cannot too strongly point out the extreme importance the British Embassy give
                    to the points raised above and it appears that (1) the licensing system would
                    have most drastic results in the Far East, and (2) that it would be creating an
                    extremely adverse disposition on the part of the American oil companies toward
                    the British Government and would interfere greatly with the present British war
                    effort.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James Clement Dunn</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
