<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political Relations (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d643</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">643</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="643"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d643">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 (D) Regulations/383</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on Political
                        Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-08-15">August 15,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>At the conclusion of a conversation held this morning in Mr. Morgenthau’s<note
                        n="34" xml:id="d643fn34">Henry Morgenthau, Jr., Secretary of the
                        Treasury.</note> office in which Mr. Morgenthau, Mr. T. V. Soong,<note
                        n="35" xml:id="d643fn35">T. V. Soong, Chairman of the Board of Directors,
                        Bank of China.</note> and Messrs. Cochran,<note n="36" xml:id="d643fn36">H.
                        Merle Cochran, Technical Assistant to the Secretary of the Treasury.</note>
                        White<note n="37" xml:id="d643fn37">Harry D. White, Director of Monetary
                        Research, Treasury Department.</note> and Hornbeck participated (see
                    separate memorandum)<note n="38" xml:id="d643fn38">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_664">p. 664</ref>.</note>, Mr.
                    Morgenthau asked me to remain with him.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morgenthau said that he was interested in and concerned about the question of
                    embargoes upon exports of petroleum to Japan: he hoped to have the embargo made
                    more extensive than it now is. He asked for my views on the subject. I replied
                    that in my opinion the problem of petroleum embargoes is full of difficult
                    angles; that there would seem to be very good reasons for not attempting to
                    prevent exports of crude oil; that in any consideration of the question of
                    embargoes account must be taken of the fact that not one only but several
                    effects flow from the exportation or non-exportation of a given commodity or
                    group of commodities. Mr. Morgenthau asked whether I thought that, if our
                    petroleum embargo were made more extensive <pb facs="0606" n="598"
                        xml:id="pg_598"/> Japan would take drastic action against us or move toward
                    forceful seizure of the Netherlands East Indies. I replied that Japan could
                    purchase ample supplies of crude oil from outside the United States, even from
                    the Netherlands East Indies; that an embargo by us on crude oil would not
                    materially hurt her; that she is in no position deliberately to challenge us;
                    that I have all along believed that her policy and action with regard to a
                    possible attack upon the Netherlands East Indies will be on the side of caution
                    pending clarification of the situation in Europe; and that, not desperately
                    needing petroleum at this time, she would not proceed toward seizure of the
                    Netherlands East Indies, with the exposure of her naval position that would be
                    required, merely because of an embargo by this country nor would she act
                    drastically against us. Mr. Morgenthau said that such was also his view. I
                    referred again to the fact that Japan can get plenty of petroleum from sources
                    outside of—and not under control of—the United States.</p>
                <p>There followed some discussion of the subject of economic pressures.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
