<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d720</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">720</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-19T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-19T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-19T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-19T21:00:00-05:00" n="720"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d720">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/16249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-20T09:00:00+07:00"
                            >October 20, 1940—9 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 4:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>528. My 526, October 18, 9 p.m.<note n="90" xml:id="d720fn90">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_428">p. 428</ref>.</note> In
                    view of the importance of this and the exact sense of General Hey’s [<hi
                        rend="italic">Chiang Kai-shek’s</hi>] conversation with me of October 18
                    there follows a close paraphrase of his remarks as taken down and later
                    corrected and approved by him (but not independent of the preliminary exchange
                    of views on international topics to which I alluded in my telegram under
                    reference): <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>I apprehend that perhaps you and your Government are not being kept
                            apprised of the actual situation in this country and therefore I desire
                            at this moment to take this chance to give you the following information
                            so as [apparent omission] following closure of the Burma route not only
                            American commodities but goods promised by Russia have not reached us.
                            Moreover, the Chinese Communists are giving many indications [of]
                            forsaking completely the maintenance of [apparent omission] in North
                            Kiangsu, especially they have conducted themselves so badly as to hamper
                            the conduct of hostilities. The foregoing is one of the menaces
                            confronting China at this time. It is my desire that the American
                            Government be acquainted with this fact. After closure of the Burma Road
                            and the non-arrival of American supplies, it should be further noted
                            that the probability of Soviet aid to China became remote. No supplies
                            are being received through Sinkiang. As things are at present, the
                            lingual Communist press has not published articles critical of any [<hi
                                rend="italic">my</hi>] Government but the Communists have launched
                            verbal onslaughts. This is causing a deterioration of the people’s
                            morale which I acknowledge is not so good as it was a year ago. The
                            prolongation of hostilities is being menaced from within. I want your
                            Government to have the following confidential information which I have
                            hitherto mentioned to no person not even T. V. Soong. Since July new
                            United States loan had not been granted and if the British had not
                            before having [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] opened the Burma route our
                            economic and social situation would have deteriorated. The foregoing I
                            thus hold to [apparent omission] menace. The Japanese and their design
                            to smash our power we do not fear but deterioration of the people’s
                            morale and the Chinese Communists are truly problems of a serious
                            character. That this situation has improved during the past week is
                            attributable to the removal of restrictions on the Burma route.
                            Accordingly improvement in the Russian attitude toward China has
                            resulted. But if resistance is to be prolonged, the attitude of Soviet
                            Russia maintained, and the morale of the people sustained the positive
                            help of the United States is necessary.</p>
                        <p>China [apparent omission] air planes and economic assistance. Although
                            the route to Burma has been restored I fear that savage Japanese aerial
                            attacks may render it useless. The opening of the route resulted from
                            the support accorded the British by your President. <pb facs="0681"
                                n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> This factor I regard as the crucial
                            turning point in which defeat has been converted to victory and our most
                            threatening stage successfully passed. Our people and Government are,
                            therefore, most grateful to President Roosevelt. Nevertheless more
                            comprehensive assistance from the United States is necessary and the
                            American authorities are being consulted by T. V. Soong in this respect.
                            We will appreciate any support you can grant us in this connection. The
                            fact that China, regardless of coming developments, desires to continue
                            to concert with Great Britain and America in the Far East, I deem it
                            unnecessary to emphasize, but the element of time is of the essence. In
                            the event that the route to Burma is not usable owing to Japanese
                            bombing, American supplies can not be shipped to us. It is impossible to
                            ship goods through Siberia. A Japanese attack on Singapore would suspend
                            ocean shipping and bring about the same result. If the road is closed or
                            ocean traffic suspended, American assistance will not help us. Time, I
                            wish to emphasize, is of vast importance.</p>
                        <p>I strongly hope that before the severance of communication facilities
                            American planes can be procured in plentiful quantities. In the hope of
                            obtaining the aid of the United States in this respect, I am despatching
                            a proposal to Soong. Planes are urgently needed; we must have aircraft
                            that are already fabricated to reach China in 3 months in order to
                            uphold the morale of the civil and military population and to continue
                            the struggle. 500 to 1000 planes in a year are required by China of
                            which it is trusted 500 can reach China within the next 3 months before
                            disruption of communications. It is also hoped that American volunteers
                            will be able to aid us in carrying on hostilities. Splendid air bases
                            are possessed in Chekiang Province from which American planes could be
                            utilized to attack Japanese naval bases in Japan and Formosa. China will
                            be able to diminish Japanese naval strength materially if she can obtain
                            from America one-twentieth or one-tenth of the planes Britain is now
                            receiving from the United States. For America the supplying to China of
                            planes and volunteers is a desirable alternative to war with Japan.
                            Provided the American Air Force would work in conjunction with our Army
                            in case of an American-Japanese war, it might not be necessary for the
                            American Fleet to proceed to the Orient, by working together they would
                            be powerful enough to ruin the navy of Japan and thus effect a perpetual
                            solution of Far Eastern difficulties.</p>
                        <p>If American volunteers cannot be procured, our air force will be trained
                            to fly the new planes. But if the Government of the United States
                            consents, the procurement of volunteers in the United States should be
                            no problem.</p>
                        <p>It is not necessary for me to stress a point of which you are well aware:
                            in the matter of cooperation among America, China, and England, we will
                            follow the leadership of the United States.</p>
                        <p>We are thankful for the new loan of $25,000,000 which with other loans of
                            the past two years total $75,000,000. The results have been excellent.
                            But I trust that for further bolstering the morale of the Chinese
                            people, America will see fit to grant a single big loan rather than
                            small piecemeal credits. As I have declared above, it is not the
                            Japanese Army which we fear, because our army is able to deal with <pb
                                facs="0682" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/> it, but the defiant
                            Communists. American economic assistance plus the aid of the American
                            Air Force can stabilize our unsteady economic and social conditions,
                            thus making it impossible for the Communists to carry out their
                            schemes.</p>
                        <p>I wish you to mention yet another point to your Government. When we
                            commenced to resist Japan’s invasion, the Chinese people were informed
                            that the war would continue for a period of 3 years. Now we have fought
                            over 3 years but we have not vanquished Japan. No later than August of
                            this year Chinese planes were opposing Japanese bombers but now we do
                            not have planes adequate for this purpose. In consequence of which other
                            Japanese bombing goes unchallenged and the people are filled with
                            disquiet; businessmen ask how long we can prolong the conflict without
                            Anglo-American aid. If the American airplanes cannot reach us before the
                            severance of Indo-Chinese routes, the people’s spirit and sentiment
                            might become so disturbed as to render the situation impossible of
                            support.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Comment and interpretations in relation to the foregoing and allied topics
                    follow.</p>
                <p>Sent to the Department only.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
