<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-08-17T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-08-17T13:00:00-05:00" n="833" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d833">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102S/2194a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-08-17T14:00:00-04:00">August 17, 1940—2
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>313. It is the Department’s understanding that at the meeting of the
                                Defense Committee at Shanghai on August 15, Defense Sector B was
                                assigned to United States forces and the remaining portion of the
                                British sector assigned to Japanese forces, by majority vote, the
                                Italians abstaining from voting and the Japanese voting “no;” and
                                that the majority decision has been approved by the Municipal
                                Council; but that the Japanese reserved the right to present an
                                alternative plan and took the position that no plan should be
                                adopted unless unanimously agreed upon; that the British forces are
                                to be withdrawn upon the nineteenth. This Government approves the
                                plan for United States forces to take over Sector B, in which are
                                situated the American Consulate General and a considerable number of
                                other important American interests, and hopes that the Japanese
                                Government will approve it at least tentatively and will not oppose
                                taking over of Sector B by United States forces pending final
                                decision regarding the matter. This Government is giving
                                authorization for the Commander-in-Chief of the Asiatic Squadron or
                                the American Consul to give notification locally that (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) this Government approves the Defense
                                Committee’s and the Municipal Council’s decision and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the Commander-in-Chief is prepared to
                                proceed in accordance therewith when the British withdraw their
                                armed forces from their sector.</p>
                            <p>Please review Department’s 362, August 13, 3 p.m. to Shanghai and
                                take up this matter immediately with the Foreign Office, saying that
                                we consider the plan and procedure indicated thoroughly reasonable
                                and that we hope that the Japanese Government will take the same
                                view and will take action accordingly.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>