<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Shanghai ( (Butrick) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-09-06T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-09-06T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-06T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-06T01:00:00-05:00" n="864"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d864">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102S/2250: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butrick</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-06T15:00:00+09:00"
                            >September 6, 1940—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received September 6—12:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>881. With reference to the last substantive paragraph of my 875, September 5, 10
                    p.m., the situation at present is briefly as follows:</p>
                <p>Sector B. The agreement covering the operation of Japanese gendarmes is that
                    outlined in the Consulate General’s despatch 2033 of March 6, 1939, entitled
                    Japanese demands on the Municipal Council of the International Settlement at
                        Shanghai.<note n="40" xml:id="d864fn40">Despatch not printed, but see
                        telegrams No. 168, March 1, 1939, 2 p.m., and No. 183, March 4, 1939, 4
                        p.m., from the Consul General at Shanghai, <ref target="frus1939v04#pg_11">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1939, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 11</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1939v04#pg_15">15</ref>.</note> In general the agreement <pb
                        facs="0814" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/> is observed by the Japanese although
                    there are from time to time instances of the illegal operation of Japanese
                    gendarmes in Sector B. Approximately 28 plainclothes gendarmes are constantly on
                    duty along the water front assisting in searches for terrorists. Japanese
                    gendarmes in numbers varying from 2 to 20 are known to make their headquarters
                    at two places within the sector but they claim to be residing there in private
                    capacity.</p>
                <p>Sector D. The Commissioner of Police is still negotiating for the implementation
                    of the Fu-Franklin agreement for a joint police force. The Japanese gendarmes
                    have been operating in this and other extra-Settlement roads areas since 1938.
                    Prior to the withdrawal of the British troops they also took up billets at a
                    former gambling establishment near one of the British barracks. The Japanese
                    gendarmes now have approximately 10 places from which they operate in Sector D
                    and their numbers are estimated as having increased from about 60 prior to the
                    withdrawal of the British troops to about 500 at the present time. They have not
                    occupied the posts vacated by the British but as many of those posts were on the
                    patrols opposite Japanese posts there were no reasons for occupying them. The
                    Japanese gendarmes in this sector are much more active since the British
                    withdrawal although there were occasionally gendarme patrols, principally
                    mounted, operating during British occupation of the sector.</p>
                <p>The gendarmes operating in Sector B are plainclothes gendarmes while those
                    operating in Sector D are in uniform. There are no Japanese naval landing party
                    forces known to be in either sector.</p>
                <p>Undoubtedly there are plainclothes operatives of the Japanese special service
                    section of the army in both sectors. This is the opinion of the Shanghai
                    municipal police although they have no evidence to prove it.</p>
                <p>Sent to the Department. Repeated to Peiping, Chungking and Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Butrick</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
