<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1910-01-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1910-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to Ambassador <persName type="to">Rockhill</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-01-03"><hi rend="italic">January 3,
                                1910</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 35.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to send inclosed for your
                            information copies of dispatches of October 30, November 2, and December
                            4 from the Legation at Peking, dealing with the situation at Harbin as
                            regards the <pb facs="0338" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/> claim of the
                            Chinese Eastern Railway Co. to the possession of rights of municipal
                            administration there. There is also inclosed an outline map showing the
                            location of the land on which the railway officials propose to establish
                            an international settlement.</p>
                        <p>The department is disposed to consider Mr. Fletcher’s criticism of this
                            proposal as just. The city of Harbin—that is, all the most available
                            sites for business purposes—would still remain under the administrative
                            control of the Chinese Eastern Railway Co. and the proposed
                            international settlement would probably, owing to its location, remain
                            to a great extent unoccupied, or, if occupied, business houses there
                            would be placed at a great disadvantage. Any such arrangement, moreover,
                            would still be open to the objection which this Government has made from
                            the beginning, that the exercise of municipal powers by the Railway
                            Company is not in harmony with the convention of September 8, 1896,
                            between China and the railway company, and is in violation of the
                            extraterritorial rights of the powers and in violation also of the
                            principle of the open door and equal trade opportunity, to which the
                            Government of Russia has repeatedly committed itself.</p>
                        <p>You are so thoroughly acquainted with the views of the American
                            Government upon this question that it is unnecessary to enter upon a
                            detailed discussion of the matter. Your attention is called to the clear
                            statement made by the Chinese foreign office in the circular note, a
                            copy of which is inclosed in Mr. Fletcher’s dispatch of December 6 last.
                            It is a satisfaction to the department to find its own position thus
                            strongly supported by the Chinese Government.</p>
                        <p>I have expressed in my cablegram of this date the desire of this
                            Government to avoid embarrassing the Imperial Government of Russia,
                            which, however, it is hoped will instruct the railway company that no
                            exercise of political powers was intended in article 6 of the convention
                            of 1896.</p>
                        <p>I have to remind you again of the opinion held by the United States
                            Government that the general plan outlined in my cablegram of November 6,
                            through London, for the neutralization of railways in Manchuria, is the
                            most feasible method for the settlement of this vexed question, and I
                            trust you may be able to obtain from the Imperial Russian Government an
                            approval of the principle involved.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington
                            Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>