<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Sherrill to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1910</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1910-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1910-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1910-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1910-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 19654/9.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Sherrill</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-03-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 14, 1910</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 279.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that I have to-day
                    received from the minister for foreign affairs a note dated the 28th ultimo
                    replying to my note of July 17, 1909, sent to the minister in accordance with
                    the Department’s telegraphic instruction of July 16, 1909, and already reported
                    in my No. 30 of July 19, 1909. In accordance with the instructions contained in
                    the department’s No. 24 of September 30, 1909, I have to-day sent a note to the
                    minister for foreign affairs notifying him that the Government of the United
                    States reserves its rights in the premises and all due assertion thereof should
                    occasion arise.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Sherrill.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to Minister <persName type="to"
                            >Sherrill</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Buenos Aires</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-02-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 28, 1910</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: The contract entered into between
                        the National Executive and and Mr. John Oldman having been approved by
                        Congress, to which matter your excellency’s note of July 17 last year
                        refers, whose receipt I had the honor to acknowledge the 31st of the said
                        month, this ministry did not consider a reply thereto indispensable, but the
                        fitness of such having been intimated I am pleased to defer to that desire
                        by means of this note.</p>
                    <pb facs="0176" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                    <p>Your excellency, in the said note of July 17, states, under instructions,
                        that your Government supposes that that of this Republic had in mind the
                        treaty of 1853 with the United States and it was not its intention to
                        infringe in any way its provisions, in making a certain cable contract
                        called the “Contrato ad referendum” entered into between Executive and Mr.
                        John Oldman on behalf of the Western Telegraph Co., for the construction and
                        development of a direct cable between the Argentine Republic and the
                        Continent of Europe. Your excellency adds that you hope the Argentine
                        Government will wish to avoid all infraction of American rights under the
                        treaty of 1853 and finally calls my especial attention to articles 8, 13 and
                        17 of that contract.</p>
                    <p>The assumption of the Government which your excellency worthily represents is
                        very logical and just. This Government has not forgotten the provisions of
                        the said treaty, not only because they are obligations which it is always
                        ready to fulfill, but also because it is its greatest desire to tighten the
                        bonds of friendship which unite it with the United States.</p>
                    <p>This Government considers that the contract with the Western Telegraph Co. by
                        its very nature in no way affects the treaty of 1853, and that the
                        most-favored-nation clause therein contained can not be invoked in this
                        case.</p>
                    <p>The effect and the application of this clause is subordinate to the legal
                        principle of secundum subjectum materiam—that is to say, according to the
                        material. That clause being in a treaty of commerce, its application and the
                        favors which it brings can not be cited, except in so far as they refer to
                        commercial relations and especially regarding customs tariffs, free trade,
                        or protection, without its influence comprehending contracts on ways of
                        communication in general, whether by telegraph or railroad, these being
                        considered as public services and consequently subject to special
                        conventions.</p>
                    <p>The said principle that the most-favored-nation clause includes only the
                        regulations which govern trade relations has been adopted by many countries,
                        among them the French Republic, where the courts have, in cases submitted to
                        their jurisdiction, expressly so decided it.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, article 3 of the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce, and Navigation of
                        1853 between the Republic and the United States, which doubtless served your
                        excellency as a base for the observations which now occupy me, says “That
                        any favor, exemption, privilege, or immunity whatever, in matters of
                        commerce or navigation, which either of them has actually granted, or may
                        hereafter grant, to the citizens or subjects of any other Government,
                        Nation, or State, shall extend, in identity of cases and circumstances, to
                        the citizens of the other contracting party, gratuitously, if the
                        concession, etc.” So that its results are confined to acts of commerce and
                        navigation and the concession in question can not be considered as such,
                        since, as I have shown, ways of telegraphic communications are considered as
                        public services.</p>
                    <p>Examining this question from another point, it seems proper to add that the
                        landing of cables on one territory to connect it with another country is a
                        matter which is exclusively subject to the will of the sovereign of that
                        territory, from which it follows that the concessions for its improvements
                        are also subject to the will of that sovereign represented by the government
                        of the nation.</p>
                    <p>This theory, which may be said to be universal, has been applied by England,
                        France, Spain, Portugal, Brazil, Peru, Ecuador, Colombia, Mexico, Japan,
                        etc., in granting exclusive concessions and by the United States itself, as
                        set forth in an official report, of the Attorney General regarding the
                        landing of a cable between territory of the Union and that of the Republic
                        of Cuba. (Official opinions of the Attorneys General of the United States,
                        Washington, 1900, Vol. XXII, pp. 514 to 519.)</p>
                    <p>It says, among other things, this: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>The intention of connecting our territory with foreign territory is a
                                matter which is subject to the sovereign control of this Government
                                * * * permission to land a cable can not be given nor with held in
                                opposition to the desire of the government which exercises sovereign
                                power. The laying of cables-especially in this last quarter of a
                                century, was done at great cost and danger and it has been very
                                common among nations, including the United States, to grant
                                exclusive concessions for a term of years to-companies which raised
                                the necessary capital and were engaged in such enterprises.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>I believe that the matter is sufficiently explained to demonstrate that the
                        concession cited in no way affects the treaty of 1853, and that this
                        Government, in according it, did not desire in any manner to infringe the
                        condition thereof and that I might omit referring to articles 8, 13, and 17
                        of the contract with the Western Telegraph Co., to which my attention was
                        kindly called.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, and with the desire to be deferential to your excellency and
                        your Government, I will add in this respect, that, if indeed articles 8 and
                        13 of that contract constitute an obligation on the part of the Argentine
                        Government not to accord its assistance to another company and to employ the
                        cable of the Western for its <pb facs="0177" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/>
                        official dispatches, these obligations are compensated for by those which
                        the company incurs for the benefit of the State, and thus is decided the
                        problems of transcendental importance of direct communications with the
                        Continent of Europe and North America, freeing them from the surcharges and
                        high rates to which they are subject to-day.</p>
                    <p>With regard to article 17, the right which it establishes is simply a
                        preference and does not constitute a privilege, having reference to the
                        legitimate and reasonable purpose of assuring during a certain time the
                        interest on capital invested, and it is only under like conditions that
                        cables which could be constructed in virtue of conventions with foreign
                        powers are excluded.</p>
                    <p>I renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">V. de la Plaza.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Sherrill</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Minister for Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Buenos Aires</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-03-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 14, 1910</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt to-day of your excellency’s note of the 28th ultimo setting out that
                        in the opinion of your excellency’s Government the contract entered into
                        with the Western Telegraph Co. for the construction and operation of a
                        direct cable between the Argentine Republic and Europe does not in any of
                        its terms infringe upon the provisions of the treaty of 1853 between the
                        United States and the Argentine Republic.</p>
                    <p>While taking due note of the Argentine Government’s view of the case as set
                        forth in your excellency’s note, I am instructed to advise your excellency’s
                        Government that the Government of the United States reserves its rights in
                        the premises and all due assertion thereof should occasion arise.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Sherrill.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
