<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1909-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1909-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="400" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d400">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Northcott</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogota</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-10-29"><hi rend="italic">October 29,
                                1909</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 20.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that in accord
                            with the instructions contained in the department’s cable of October 23,
                            1909, on Wednesday last, October 27, 1909, accompanied by Secretary
                            Hibben, I delivered to Dr. Carlos Calderon, Colombian minister for
                            foreign affairs, an answer in writing to his notes suggesting the
                            abandonment of the tripartite treaties and the opening of negotiations
                            for a new treaty with the United States. A copy of my note is inclosed
                            herewith.</p>
                        <p>At the interview which took place on the delivery of the note,
                            immediately after receiving and reading it, Dr. Calderon stated
                            verbally, that the present Colombian Government could not enter into
                            negotiations of any kind with Panama, as it (the Government of Colombia
                            as at present constituted) regarded the United States as being solely
                            responsible for the separation of Panama. To which statement we replied
                            that that view was not conceded by the United States in the slightest
                            degree.</p>
                        <p>At a dinner given by the President at the palace last night, which we
                            attended, Secretary Hibben had personal and unofficial conversations
                            with Dr. Borda, the newly appointed Colombian minister to the United
                            States, and with Dr. Calderon. These conversations Mr. Hibben will
                            report to you in person.</p>
                        <p>The feeling here is still very strong against the United States, and if
                            submitted to the present Congress the treaties would, in all
                            probability, be overwhelmingly rejected.</p>
                        <p>The present session of Congress here is expected to end within two weeks,
                            and it is not now generally believed that the Colombian Government will
                            submit the treaties to the present session.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Elliott
                            Northcott.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Northcott</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Minister for
                                        Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogota</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-10-26"><hi rend="italic">October 26,
                                        1909</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: In comment upon the
                                memorandum with which your excellency presented me on the 22d of
                                September, in regard to a conversation which I had had the honor of
                                holding with your excellency as to the abandonment of the tripartite
                                treaties signed in Washington on January the 29th, last, by the
                                plenipotentiaries of the Republics of Colombia and Panama and the
                                United States of America, and in reply to your excellency’s
                                courteous note of the 2d instant, and of the subsequent personal
                                note which your excellency was good enough to send me on the 9th
                                instant, I have the honor ta reply to the proposition for the
                                negotiation of a new convention between Colombia and the United
                                States, as a consequence of the abandonment, proposed by your
                                excellency, of the present treaties, under instruction of my
                                Government, as follows:</p>
                            <p>The treaty of January 9 between Colombia and the United States was
                                negotiated in order to facilitate the negotiations between Colombia
                                and Panama, and to that end the United States conferred favors upon
                                Colombia in regard to the use of the canal and gave Colombia other
                                advantages as equivalents for the agreement between Colombia and
                                Panama, besides aiding Panama to carry out the engagements of the
                                Colombia-Panama treaty.</p>
                            <pb facs="0518" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/>
                            <p>Your excellency’s statement in the personal note to which I have
                                refer ted, that the abandonment of the Root-Cortes treaty will
                                virtually eliminate the treaty with Panama means, in effect, that
                                the considerations upon which the favors of that treaty were
                                predicated is to be treated as nonexistent, thus eliminating the
                                initial reason for a new treaty between the United States and
                                Colombia. It would be impossible for the United States to impose, by
                                independent convention with Colombia, any conditions constraining
                                the free hand of Colombia and Panama in settling their questions of
                                mutual agreement.</p>
                            <p>Whether the United States would be in any position to make any treaty
                                with Colombia would depend upon the ascertainment of the terms on
                                which Colombia and Panama may agree and the United States could only
                                consider such an agreement with Colombia as might facilitate the
                                Colombia-Panama agreement. In short, the whole tripartite agreement
                                would have to be done over again with the probability of no prospect
                                of reaching conclusions as favorable to all three parties as those
                                which your excellency’s Government proposes to set aside. Indeed, in
                                light of subsequent events it is more than doubtful if even
                                similarly favorable concessions by the United States to Colombia
                                could gain the approval of the United States Senate, as I have had
                                the honor to point out to your excellency in conversation on several
                                occasions.</p>
                            <p>For these reasons, the Government of the United States must decline
                                to acquiesce in wiping out the tripartite treaty and can not enter
                                upon a separate negotiotion with Colombia alone.</p>
                            <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Elliott
                                Northcott.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>