<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Belgian Minister.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1910</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1910-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1910-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1910-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1910-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="54"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 811B.5034.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Belgian Minister</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-05-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 2, 1910</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to transmit herewith, for your information,
                    a copy of an opinion rendered by the Attorney General, dated April 29, 1910,
                    upon the question presented by Mr. Ed. C. André, through you, as to the legal
                    right of a Belgian corporation to purchase and hold a plantation in the
                    Philippine Islands containing an area of 1,430 hectares. As will be observed,
                    the Attorney General holds that under the law no foreign or domestic corporation
                    authorized to engage in agriculture may purchase or hold lands in the
                    Philippines in excess of 1,024 hectares.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Attorney General</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Justice</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-04-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 29, 1910</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
                        of your communication o April 21, instant, in which you state: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>I have the honor to inclose copies of two notes addressed,
                                respectively, to the minister of foreign affairs at Brussels by Mr.
                                Ed. C. André, dated April 4, and to the Belgian minister at this
                                capital by the minister of foreign affairs of his Government, dated
                                April 17, and with them three letters from Mr. André, dated March 30
                                and April 4, addressed to you and handed to me by the minister of
                                Belgium for delivery to you. These documents raise the question
                                whether a Belgian corporation authorized to engage in agriculture
                                may legally purchase and hold a plantation in the Philippine Islands
                                containing an area of 1,430 hectares. The collateral inquiry is also
                                presented whether, if the answer to the foregoing question is in the
                                negative, an agricultural and commercial corporation created under
                                Philippine law may take and hold the said plantation.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>You request an expression of my opinion on both of these questions</p>
                    <p>The act of Congress entitled “An act temporarily to provide for the
                        administration of the affairs of civil government in the Philippine Islands,
                        and for other purposes,” approved July 1, 1892, is the law still in
                        force.</p>
                    <p>By the seventy-fifth section of that act it is provided: <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p>That no corporation shall be authorized to conduct the business of
                                buying and selling real estate or be permitted to hold or own real
                                estate except such as may be reasonably necessary to enable it to
                                carry out the purposes for which it is created, and every
                                corporation authorized to engage in agriculture shall by its charter
                                be restricted to the ownership and control of not to exceed one
                                thousand and twenty-four hectares of land. * * *</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The first clause of this section forbids the organization of corporations to
                        conduct the business of buying and selling real estate. The next,
                        recognizing the necessity of some corporations to hold real estate for the
                        conduct of their business, denies the permission to hold or own any real
                        estate except such as may be reasonably necessary to enable it to carry out
                        the purposes for which the corporation is created. The holding of real
                        estate, under this provision, is incidental to the main business of the
                        corporation, such as manufacturing or trading. By no intentment can this
                        apply to a corporation formed for the use or cultivation of land.</p>
                    <p>By the next clause of this section it is provided: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Every corporation authorized to engage in agriculture shall by its
                                charter be restricted to the ownership and control of not to exceed
                                one thousand and twenty-four hectares of land.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0193" n="81" xml:id="pg_81"/>
                    <p>Mr. André suggests, in one of the notes transmitted through you: “I am in
                        doubt whether this refers to the rules and by-laws of the corporation or to
                        the privilege granted to a company at being filed.”</p>
                    <p>This provision is not directory. It affects the very being of the
                        corporation. It is an absolute prohibition of the power to hold land in
                        excess of 1,024 hectares. “This limitation was placed on the act after much
                        debate and deliberation in the United States Congress, and it is repeated
                        and emphasized in all the legislation upon this subject.</p>
                    <p>These prohibitions in the organic act were embraced in the “corporation law”
                        of the Philippine Commission, enacted by authority of the United States. By
                        Article I, section 13, it is enacted: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Every corporation has power (par. 5) to purchase, hold, convey, sell,
                                lease, let, mortgage, encumber, and otherwise deal with such real
                                and personal property as the purposes for which the corporation was
                                formed may permit and the transaction of the lawful business of the
                                corporation may reasonably and necessarily require, unless otherwise
                                prescribed in this act: <hi rend="italic">Provided</hi>, That no
                                corporation shall be authorized to conduct the business of buying
                                and selling real estate or be permitted to hold or own real estate
                                except such as may be reasonably necessary to enable it to carry out
                                the purposes for which it is created, and every corporation
                                authorized to engage in agriculture shall be restricted to the
                                ownership and control of not to exceed one thousand and twenty-four
                                hectares of land. * * *</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Reversing the order in which the questions in your communication are
                        presented to me, and replying to the second inquiry, I think an agricultural
                        corporation created under Philippine law can not take and hold of the
                        plantation described, or of any other lands, more than 1,024 hectares.</p>
                    <p>By the last paragraph of this same section 75 of the act of Congress it is
                        provided: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Corporations not organized in the Philippine Islands, and doing
                                business therein, shall be bound by the provisions of this section
                                so far as they are applicable.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>And by section 73 of the “corporation law” of the Philippine Commission it is
                        enacted: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Any foreign corporation or corporation not formed, organized, or
                                existing under the laws of the Philippine Islands and lawfully doing
                                business in the islands shall be bound by the laws, rules, and
                                regulations applicable to domestic corporations of the same class,
                                save and except such only as provide for the creation, formation,
                                organization, or dissolution of corporations or such as fix the
                                relations, liabilities, responsibilities, or duties of members,
                                stockholders, or officers of corporations to each other or to the
                                corporation: <hi rend="italic">Provided, however</hi>, That nothing
                                in this section contained shall be construed or deemed to impair any
                                rights that are secured or protected by the treaty of peace between
                                the United States and Spain, signed at the city of Paris on December
                                tenth, eighteen hundred and ninety-eight.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>This act was passed under the authority delegated by the organic act. Its
                        provisions are declaratory of the limitations of that act.</p>
                    <p>The restrictions upon the ownership and control of lands in the Philippine
                        Islands by corporations are absolutely determined by this legislation. It is
                        beyond the power of the executive branches of the Governments, either of the
                        United States or the Philippine Islands, to authorize or permit corporations
                        to own or hold lands in excess of the amount so designated.</p>
                    <p>I am therefore of opinion that neither a corporation formed in Belgium to
                        acquire and possess lands in the Philippine Islands nor any other foreign or
                        domestic corporation authorized to engage in agriculture may legally
                        purchase or hold more than 1,024 hectares of land in the Philippine
                        Islands.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. W. Wickersham.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
