<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1909-12-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1909-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="595" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d595">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 22867.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Hitt</persName> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-12-06"><hi rend="italic">December 6,
                                1909</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 527.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith a
                            copy, with translation, of a note which I have received from the foreign
                            office, under date of the 4th instant, relative to one Max Runge, who is
                            being sought by the New York police under a charge of theft, and whose
                            arrest, with a view to extradition, the New York police department has
                            requested of the police president of Berlin.</p>
                        <p>It will be observed that the foreign office points out that the
                            individual in question would not seem to be extraditable, as the offense
                            against him is not included in the extradition treaty of June 16, 1852,
                            but that if he is a German subject, he might be prosecuted before the
                            German courts, if this was requested by the Government of the United
                            States and the assurance given of reciprocal treatment on the part of
                            the United States in similar cases.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">R. S. Reynolds
                            Hitt.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Inclosure—Translation.]</head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Note verbale.]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1909-12-04"><hi rend="italic">December 4,
                                        1909</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The foreign office has the honor to inform the embassy of the United
                                States of America that, under date of November 5, 1909, the New York
                                police department requested the president of police at Berlin to
                                cause the necessary steps to be taken in order that search might be
                                instituted for one Max Runge, a ship steward, born at Berlin, April
                                3, 1881, wanted in New York for theft, and that in case he should be
                                found he might be provisionally detained for the purpose of his
                                extradition.</p>
                            <p>Since the fugitive is said to have been born here it is to be
                                presumed that he was born a German subject. The question is raised
                                whether he has in the meanwhile lost his German nationality by
                                acquiring citizenship in the United States of America. In neither
                                case would his extradition come in question, since the offense with
                                which he is charged is not listed in the extradition treaty of June
                                16, 1852, between Prussia and other States of the Germanic
                                Federation on the one part and the United States of North America on
                                the other part. In case Runge should still possess German
                                nationality it could be considered whether he might not be brought
                                before the German courts to answer for the offense committed in the
                                United States. In order to do this, however, it would be necessary
                                for the Government of the United States of America to request
                                Runge’s criminal prosecution and at the same time to declare that it
                                guarantees reciprocity in reverse cases.</p>
                            <p>The foreign office therefore has the honor to request information
                                concerning the points designated from the embassy of the United
                                States of America.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>