<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1910-06-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1910-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="753" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d753">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 212.11G16/13.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Wilson</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-06-21"><hi rend="italic">June 21,
                                1910</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 101.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 86, of the 8th
                            instant, and to my telegram of to-day, I have the honor to inclose, for
                            the department’s information, copy and translation of a note received
                            to-day from the foreign office, and copy of my reply thereto, relative
                            to the provisional arrest and detention of Heliodoro Garcia, charged
                            with assault with intent to commit murder in California.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Lane
                            Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                1—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                        Affairs</gloss> to Ambassador <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-06-18"><hi rend="italic">June 18,
                                        1910</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 32479.]</seg></opener>
                            <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador</hi>: Referring to the embassy’s
                                note, dated the 8th instant, I beg leave to ask that the final
                                proofs in support of the extradition of Heliodoro Garcia be sent to
                                this department, because whatever the legal classification of the
                                offense may be, the 40 days established by the treaty for the
                                presentation of said document has expired in excess. In case that
                                the embassy has not said documents I shall be pleased to learn when
                                the same may be had.</p>
                            <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Enrique C.
                                Creel.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0838" n="726" xml:id="pg_726"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Minister for
                                        Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-06-21"><hi rend="italic">June 21,
                                        1910</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 295.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to
                                acknowledge the receipt to-day of your excellency’s note of the 18th
                                instant (No. 32479) with reference to the provisional detention of
                                Heliodoro Garcia, who is charged with assault with intent to commit
                                murder in California.</p>
                            <p>Your excellency requests to be advised whether the proofs, as
                                required by treaty, have been received by the embassy; and in the
                                event that they have not, asks to be informed when they can be
                                presented. Your excellency furthermore states that the 40-day
                                detention period, as prescribed by treaty, has expired.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the formal proofs I have the honor to advise your
                                excellency that I have this day requested the necessary information
                                from my Government, which will be communicated to your excellency in
                                due time.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the second point in your excellency’s note, I regret
                                that your excellency differs from the principles accepted by the
                                department for foreign affairs in its note of April 12, 1909, which
                                was an acquiescence in the policy of extending the 40-day
                                provisional detention period when, because of distances, unavoidable
                                delays in securing testimony, or for some other unforeseen reason,
                                it was not possible to submit the proofs within those limits;
                                because while it is true that Article X of the extradition treaty
                                does prescribe a 40-day detention period, your excellency will agree
                                that the extradition treaty was intended primarily to serve the ends
                                of justice; and if a fugitive, against whom there is a clear case,
                                is allowed to go free because of a strict adherence to this article,
                                it is apparent that the true ends of justice will not be furthered;
                                and furthermore, while the crime is of course primarily an attack on
                                society in the place where it was committed, it is nevertheless
                                certain that a criminal at large constitutes a menace to and an
                                offense against the society of any place where he may be found,
                                which goes to show, and I am sure your excellency will agree with
                                me, that justice is not confined to one community, but is
                                international; and that by extradition not only is the justice of
                                the place where the crime was committed satisfied, but also the
                                justice of the place where the fugitive may be found is
                                vindicated.</p>
                            <p>It is, however, not necessary to discuss at length the various
                                equities, acquiesced in by your excellency’s Government, of this
                                policy, because, strictly speaking, the question of an extension of
                                the 40-day period has no bearing on the case now under
                                consideration.</p>
                            <p>As your excellency will note, my request of April 15 asked for the
                                provisional arrest and detention of Heliodoro Garcia on the charge
                                of murder, on which charge he was apprehended on April 23. My note
                                of June 4, however, withdrew this charge, and asked for his
                                provisional arrest and detention on the charge of assault with
                                intent to commit murder. After a careful study of the extradition
                                treaty in force between your excellency’s and my Government, I have
                                not been able to find any provision prohibiting the rearrest of a
                                fugitive on a second charge, whether the first one was not proven or
                                whether, as in this case, it was withdrawn; and inasmuch as
                                paragraph 21 of Article II of the extradition treaty declares
                                assault with intent to commit murder to be an extraditable crime, it
                                would appear that even if the 40-day detention clause were to be
                                interpreted literally, Garcia’s detention can only be considered as
                                commencing prior to June 4, which was the date on which his
                                apprehension on the charge of assault with intent to commit murder
                                was requested.</p>
                            <p>I have entered thus fully into a discussion of this case for the
                                reason that I fear my two previous notes may not have been entirely
                                understood; and I have the honor to request the provisional arrest
                                and detention of Heliodoro Garcia on the charge of assault with
                                intent to commit murder in California.</p>
                            <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Lane
                                Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>