<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Aide-mémoire to the Russian Embassy.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1910</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d928</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">928</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1910-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1910-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1910-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1910-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="928"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d928">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 393.00/3.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire to the Russian Embassy.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1910-10-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 11, 1910</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The question of the protection of the interests of foreigners, subjects or
                    citizens of powers not having treaties with China, who might be sojourning or
                    traveling in China, is one that has frequently come <pb facs="0951" n="839"
                        xml:id="pg_839"/> before the Government of the United States for
                    consideration. The position uniformly taken by the Federal Government has been
                    that by consenting to lend its good offices in behalf of subjects of other
                    nations’, it could not assume to assimilate such subjects to citizens of the
                    United States and to invest them with extraterritorial rights which they did not
                    enjoy as subjects of the country of their allegiance. The American minister to
                    China was informed in 1895 by the then Secretary of State, Mr. Gresham, that the
                    consuls of the United States in China had never been invested with power to
                    exercise jurisdiction over citizens or subjects of another nation, and that the
                    Department of State has repeatedly so held in respect to citizens of Switzerland
                    who had, for many years, been under the protection of ministers and consuls of
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>Moreover, the Supreme Court of the United States has held that the question of
                    the jurisdiction of American consular courts in the Orient depends not merely
                    upon international law and the provisions of the treaties, but also upon the
                    statutory law of the United States which plainly provides for the exercise of
                    such jurisdiction in criminal cases over American citizens only. In civil cases,
                    also, while the statute is not so clear, the law officers of the Department of
                    State are of the opinion that the jurisdiction is doubtful.</p>
                <p>Consistently with this policy, which is determined by the limitations imposed by
                    the Federal statutes, the American minister to China was instructed in July of
                    last year,<note n="1" xml:id="d928fn1">See <ref target="frus1909#pg_69">Foreign
                            Relations, 1909, p. 69</ref>.</note> relative to the proposal of the
                    Chinese Government to issue passports to, and assume jurisdiction over nationals
                    of countries which had no treaty relations with China who might desire to travel
                    in the interior of that Empire, that the Department of State was not in a
                    position to question the right of the Chinese Government in the premises,
                    provided no interference was contemplated with the extraterritorial privileges
                    of any persons, whatever their civil status, who owed allegiance to the United
                    States, or who were entitled, by international law or by usage, to the
                    protection of the Government of the United States, as foreign seamen on American
                    ships, or as assistants or guards in legations and consulates, or as employees
                    of American citizens in China.</p>
                <p>The Department of State therefore regrets its inability to comply with the
                    request presented by the Russian Embassy to the Department of State in the
                    embassy’s aide-mémoire of September 17 last; and, while appreciating the
                    importance of concerted action in matters of common interest to the powers in
                    China, it finds itself, for the reasons given above, under the necessity of
                    refraining from participation in this present matter, so long as no action is
                    taken or contemplated that would in any wise unfavorably affect American
                    interests in China.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
