<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1002</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1002</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="1002" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1002">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Italy)/10–2945</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With reference to the State Department’s memorandum of October 25th relating to
                    the question of the publication of the Italian Armistice Terms, the Foreign
                    Office agree that the Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean, should be
                    directed to draft an agreed commentary. <pb facs="1085" n="1073" xml:id="pg_1073"/> It is suggested that he should be asked to draft it in
                    consultation with his United Kingdom and United States political advisers and in
                    such form as will make it clear which of the Armistice Terms are obsolete or
                    have never been invoked, which of them have been modified by directives from the
                    Combined Chiefs of Staff and which of them are still in force.</p>
                <p>While the Foreign Office certainly do not object to the publication of the
                    Italian Armistice Terms in the manner now suggested, they consider that this
                    should only take place after communication to the-Italian Government and to the
                    Advisory Council. In this connection the State Department will recall
                    conversations with members of this Embassy regarding modification of the
                    Armistice Terms, in which it was suggested that, in order to avoid creating a
                    precedent which could be invoked by the Soviet Government to the prejudice of
                    the American and British position in the ex-satellite States, it was preferable
                    that notification of any changes should be made to the Italian Government by the
                    Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean, rather than by the United States
                    Government or His Majesty’s Government.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Office agree that it would be preferable for the Italian: Government
                    to take the initiative by asking for publication of the Armistice Terms. They
                    consider, however, that Signor Parri’s statement to foreign journalists on
                    October 11th, a copy of which is attached,<note n="92" xml:id="d1002fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> and more particularly the report from the Italian Minister
                    of Foreign Affairs to the Council of Ministers on October 18th, as communicated
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Giornale Del Mattino</hi>, the relevant extract from
                    which is also attached,<note n="92" xml:id="d1002fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    constitute a request for publication and that the Italian Government cannot well
                    be expected to take a further initiative.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-29">October 29,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
