<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The British Prime Minister (
                        Churchill
                    ) to President Truman</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1051</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1051</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="1051" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1051">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of Defense Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Churchill</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-27">April 27,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>19. Field Marshal Alexander has telegraphed to the Combined Chiefs of Staff,
                    number Naf 932. It seems to me vital to get Trieste if we can do so in the easy
                    manner proposed, and to run the risks inherent in these kinds of
                    political-military operations.</p>
                <p>The late President always attached great importance to Trieste, which he thought
                    should be an international port forming an outlet into the Adriatic from all
                    regions of the Danube Basin. There are many points to consider about this, but
                    that there should be an outlet to the south seems of great interest to the trade
                    of many states involved.</p>
                <p>The great thing is to be there before Tito’s guerillas are in occupation.
                    Therefore it does not seem to me there is a minute to wait. The actual status of
                    Trieste can be determined at leisure. Possession is nine points of the law. I
                    beg you for an early decision.</p>
                <p>Field Marshal Alexander and his trusty lieutenant, Mark Clark, are in the process
                    of gaining quite soon an overwhelming and timely victory in North Italy. This is
                    the time to back our successful generals, as we are doing on the northwest
                    front.</p>
                <p>The plan for the Anglo-American occupation of Venezia Giulia has been hanging
                    fire in Washington for a considerable time, with the result that Field Marshal
                    Alexander is still without orders. I should therefore be most grateful if you
                    would give your personal attention to this.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
