<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="1075" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1075">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Italy)/5–1045</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary
                                    of State</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-10">May 10, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I refer to my memorandum of May 4, 1945 (copy attached)<note n="31" xml:id="d1075fn1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1138">p.
                                1138</ref>.</note> submitting the background to the dispute with
                            Marshal Tito over the <pb facs="1164" n="1152" xml:id="pg_1152"/>
                            occupation and administration of northeastern Italy (Venezia Giulia).
                            Field Marshal Alexander’s forces have entered and are in partial
                            occupation of Trieste, Monfalcone and Gorizia. Tito’s forces also occupy
                            portions of these three cities as well as, apparently, the remainder of
                            the Compartment of Venezia Giulia. While Allied forces proceeded no
                            further than the three points mentioned above, Tito has continued
                            pouring his Yugoslav troops into the entire area east of the Isonzo
                            River. He has persisted in his claim that this area is his exclusive
                            operational theater. He is now receding even from his agreement of May 5
                            to afford facilities to Alexander’s troops. His forces are setting up
                            the administration of the area and Alexander’s forces have been unable
                            to establish Allied Military Government even in the portion of the three
                            cities we have entered. The formation of a “Slovene Government” at
                            Trieste has been announced.</p>
                        <p>I feel that the implications of the developments in Venezia Giulia are of
                            such importance to the future peace of Europe and will have such
                            far-reaching consequences with respect to United States policy and
                            prestige that I should bring considerations, in addition to those
                            mentioned in my May 4 memorandum, to your attention.</p>
                        <p>The Department’s policy that Allied Military Government should be
                            extended to all of Venezia Giulia, up to the 1939 Yugoslav-Italian
                            frontier, in order to prevent the area’s becoming prejudiced by
                            unilateral action by force is based on reasons much more fundamental
                            than the Italian-Yugoslav aspects of the problem. What we must keep in
                            mind is whether we are going to uphold the fundamental principle of
                            territorial settlement by orderly processes, against force, intimidation
                            or blackmail. Tito has an identical claim ready for South Austria (a
                            large portion of Carinthia and Styria) and may have similar designs on
                            parts of Hungary and Greece, if his methods in Venezia Giulia succeed
                            (see Caserta’s telegram 2037, May 8, midnight, and 2042, May 9, 2
                                p.m.)<note n="32" xml:id="d1075fn2">Neither printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Although the stability of Italy and the future orientation of that
                            country with respect to Russia may well be at stake, the present issue
                            is not a question of taking sides in a dispute between Italy and
                            Yugoslavia or of becoming involved in internal Balkan politics. The
                            problem is essentially one of deciding whether we are going to permit
                            the Soviet Government, which operates directly on territorial
                            settlements in the case of Poland, lying in the Soviet military theater,
                            to operate through its satellite Yugoslavia in the Mediterranean
                            (Anglo-American) theater, to set up whatever states and boundaries look
                            best for <pb facs="1165" n="1153" xml:id="pg_1153"/> the future power of
                            the U.S.S.R. Yugoslav (Russian) occupation of Trieste, which is the
                            vital outlet of large areas of Central Europe, would have most
                            far-reaching consequences beyond the immediate territory involved.</p>
                        <p>Tito’s anxiety to “liberate” parts of Italy, while sizable parts of
                            Yugoslavia itself (the region between Istria and Belgrade) were still in
                            German hands can, of course, be explained by his primary interest in
                            territorial aggrandizement rather than defeating the common enemy.</p>
                        <p>Thus on the very day of victory in Europe, we see tactics being employed
                            by some of our allies which are strongly reminiscent of the methods the
                            Japanese used in Manchuria and Hitler copied in 1938–1939 to increase
                            their territories and ultimately to plunge all of Europe and the world
                            into war. At a time when we have at last achieved military victory in
                            Europe and have a force of millions of men in arms on that continent, we
                            must decide if we will acquiesce in unilateral action by force as a
                            method of drawing the future boundaries of Western Europe. (See Rome’s
                            1209 of May 8, 3 p.m. attached.)<note n="33" xml:id="d1075fn3">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1148">p.
                                1148</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>There is no doubt that Prime Minister Churchill sees the implications in
                            these developments and feels, as suggested in his message to you of
                            April 30,<note n="34" xml:id="d1075fn4">See telegram 417, May 1, 8 p.m.,
                                to Caserta, <ref target="#pg_1130">p. 1130</ref>.</note> that we
                            should not give way to Tito.</p>
                        <p>Alexander’s Chief of Staff has been authorized to endeavor to obtain from
                            Tito an agreement on a purely military basis to permit Alexander limited
                            facilities in this area. Tito’s acquiescence even to an unsatisfactory
                            minimum now seems questionable. In these circumstances we may be faced
                            with the necessity of withdrawing completely from this area, with all of
                            its consequences, or of implementing our present policy by threat of
                            force to secure complete and exclusive control of Trieste and Pola, the
                            keys to the region.</p>
                        <p>There is attached for ready reference a map of the Compartment of Venezia
                            Giulia and surrounding area.<note n="35" xml:id="d1075fn5">Not attached
                                to file copy of this memorandum.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>