<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="1112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1112">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Italy)/6–2645</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the
                                Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Molotov</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 363</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-26">June 26,
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Molotov</hi>: I have just received the
                            following message from the President to Marshal Stalin: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Personal and Top Secret for Marshal Stalin From President
                                    Truman:</p>
                                <p>“Subsequent to the receipt of your message of June 21<note n="76" xml:id="d1112fn1">
                                        <ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#pg_846">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Conference of Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Potsdam</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 846</ref>.</note> with
                                    reference to the negotiations at Trieste I have been informed by
                                    the Supreme Allied Commander that these discussions in Trieste
                                    have been concluded and a supplementary military accord signed.
                                    The sole purpose of these discussions was to implement the
                                    military aspects <pb facs="1204" n="1192" xml:id="pg_1192"/> of
                                    the political agreement reached between the United States,
                                    British and Yugoslav Governments on June 9. The June 9 agreement
                                    embodied the principle that the future disposition of the
                                    Venezia Giulia territory should be reserved for orderly
                                    adjustment as a part of the eventual peace settlement, and that
                                    nothing in the agreement would prejudice or affect the ultimate
                                    disposal of this territory.</p>
                                <p>“It was conceded, after agreement had been reached on this point,
                                    that Yugoslav administration could be established in the
                                    disputed area up to the limit of the territory necessary to meet
                                    Allied military requirements. Due regard has been given
                                    throughout the discussions, both on the government and military
                                    level, to legitimate interests of both Yugoslav and Italian
                                    populations as well as to the contribution made by Yugoslavia to
                                    the elimination of German military power.</p>
                                <p>“The Allied Commander, as I said in my previous message to you on
                                    this subject, must have adequate authority in the area entrusted
                                    to him to enable him to carry out his task and to safeguard the
                                    interests of all concerned. In a like fashion responsibility of
                                    the Yugoslav Commander has been recognized and there has been no
                                    effort to interfere with the exercise of his responsibility in
                                    the region of Venezia Giulia entrusted to him east of the agreed
                                    line. The Allied Governments must therefore insist, particularly
                                    since both commanders have agreed that they will refrain from
                                    any action prejudicing the final settlement, that there be no
                                    interference with the exercise of their responsibility west of
                                    the line.</p>
                                <p>“During the conversations at Trieste it is true difficulties
                                    arose since it appeared that the Yugoslav authorities did not
                                    fully appreciate that the fundamental principle of the agreement
                                    of June 9 was that no action could be permitted which would
                                    prejudice the ultimate disposal of the area. The Yugoslav
                                    military commander declined at first to recognize the Allied
                                    Commander’s authority which was established by Article 3 of the
                                    Belgrade Agreement over administration west of the line. This
                                    and other acts on the part of local commanders subsequent to
                                    June 9 have given rise to the impression that the full extent of
                                    the agreement reached with Marshal Tito and the Belgrade
                                    Government had not been communicated to these local
                                    commanders.</p>
                                <p>“If there should be any further aspects of the agreement which
                                    you feel should be considered, we shall have an opportunity at
                                    our early meeting to discuss this.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Will you please deliver this message to Marshal Stalin.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>W. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>