<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Italy ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-02-13T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-13T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-13T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-13T07:00:00-05:00" n="1148"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1148">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Italy)/2–1345: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-13T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 13, 1945—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 14—5:49 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>388. Section I. During last visit of Macmillan to Rome officers from G–5<note
                        n="54" xml:id="d1148fn1">Headquarters staff division dealing with civil
                        affairs.</note> AFHQ came here to discuss with AC<note n="55"
                        xml:id="d1148fn2">Allied Commission.</note> a reply to Tam 445<note n="56"
                        xml:id="d1148fn3">Not printed.</note> regarding proposed directive on
                    Italian financial matters and prepared a draft which was taken by G–5 officers
                    to AFHQ with the intention of having it transmitted from Caserta to Combined
                    Chiefs of Staff. Although discussions on this draft are apparently still being
                    carried on in G–5 where the general lines of Department’s 84, February [1] to
                    AmPolAd are known and although draft has not been submitted to offices of
                    political advisors to SACMED for concurrence I submit following paraphrase
                    thereof based on text as agreed upon in conferences in Rome:</p>
                <p>Section II. [<hi rend="italic">Begin paraphrase</hi>] This message is an agreed
                    view following consultation with Acting President and Chief Commissioner of
                    Allied Commission: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <note n="57" xml:id="d1148fn4">The numbered paragraphs were not
                                transmitted in chronological order; as here printed, they have been
                                restored by the editors to the usual numerical sequence.</note> Two
                            main proposals are made in Tam 445: (1), that the Italian Government
                            again control foreign exchange transactions; (2), that it should again
                            become the only issuing authority for all lira currency, <pb facs="1248"
                                n="1236" xml:id="pg_1236"/> including all AM lire already in
                            circulation, whether for the purpose of meeting obligations to the
                            Allies under Armistice Clause 23 or for its own use. Since these
                            proposals conform with the developing policy of the Allied governments
                            toward Italy which is to have it assume the responsibilities ordinarily
                            associated with sovereignty, I support both of them.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>In each case there is a question, however, as to when such changes
                            should take place.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Both experience and probity are required in the difficult technique of
                            exchange control and neither can easily be found at this time in Italy.
                            Some of the most expert persons are now in German controlled Italy and
                            those remaining are suspended and awaiting epuration hearings. In order
                            to obtain at least a nucleus of competent men we are trying to expedite
                            hearings but must exercise considerable care. The Italian Government
                            assisted by Allied Commission is now developing exchange control
                            machinery substantially like that of 1917–1919, that is operated by
                            Banca d’Italia as agents of Italian Treasury. So far as we know, neither
                            the government nor the public have ever requested acceleration of date
                            when full responsibility would pass to Italian hands. Furthermore, the
                            Allied governments have an interest to the extent to which they have to
                            make foreign exchange available to the Italians either now or in the
                            future in making sure that the little foreign exchange now at the
                            disposal of the Italian Government is not wasted through improper or
                            imprudent management. In telegrams Tam 136 and 398 and Tam airgram
                                24<note n="58" xml:id="d1148fn5">None printed.</note> you have urged
                            the need for exercising control in all transactions in the currencies of
                            neutral countries as well as in the operation of post liberation
                            accounts in the United States and United Kingdom and you, therefore,
                            seem to share this view. You may feel that these considerations weigh
                            against any premature relinquishment of controls. I shall meanwhile
                            continue the policy of preparation for transfer of full responsibility
                            to the Italians whenever you may so direct.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Regarding the second proposal, the Italians at some date clearly must
                            publicly shoulder the burdens which they have not had to face simply
                            because the Allied invasion came from the south and consequently for
                            almost a year the note printing facilities were not available to the
                            Allies and were found destroyed when they were reached. The Italian
                            Government was thus unable to make currency available in fulfillment of
                            its obligations under article 23. I sympathize fully with your desire to
                            make the Italians face this issue and to realize that possible escape
                            from or reduction of their obligation is an illusion. It is due only to
                            the above military circumstance that AM lire have <pb facs="1249"
                                n="1237" xml:id="pg_1237"/> had to be printed and imported and yet I
                            do not doubt that both the government (as evidenced by its recent
                            memorandum) and the public hope that the Allies might be persuaded to
                            make available sterling and dollar credits commensurate with the
                            currency thus created. This control over the issue of currency, I must
                            warn you, since it means the open assumption of an obligation of the
                            Armistice which the Government publicly has declared it is seeking to
                            avoid, may well appear to the Italians far from a welcome concession or
                            as of no advantage. Whereas the lire account proposed last autumn, if
                            carried out, would have meant a charge of some 15–18 billion lire
                            annually to the government’s budget, the new proposal would mean an
                            increase in the government’s debt to the Banca d’Italia of some 50
                            billions immediately and budget charges of some 5 billions of lire would
                            continue each month.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>In a recent memorandum<note n="59" xml:id="d1148fn6">Memorandum of
                                January 9, 1945, not printed; for summary, see despatch 858, January
                                26, from Rome, <ref target="#pg_1228">p. 1228</ref>.</note> to the
                            Governments of the United States and the United Kingdom and to the
                            Allied Commission, the Italian Government has requested the dollar
                            and/or sterling counterpart not only for all Allied military lire
                            outstanding but also to cover all payments which the Italian Government
                            has made or will make for supplies, requisitions, services and work
                            furnished to or ordered by the Allied forces. I do not think it likely,
                            but unless the two Governments propose to accept this demand, they must
                            face the question whether it is wise in the name of “decontrol” to make
                            the Italian Government and people resolutely undertake their financial
                            obligation at this particular moment. The arguments in favor of so doing
                            without further delay, I recognize, are both in logic and in equity very
                            strong: The realities should be faced by the Italians. It is the outward
                            and visible sign of a sovereign state that it issue and control its own
                            money, and they might as well do so at once since they will have to
                            swallow this bitter medicine at one time or another. In present
                            circumstance, on the other hand, it is arguable that the government is
                            weaker than it ever will be again. If the proposal in Tam 445
                            precipitated a crisis, it is possible that no government might be formed
                            at all. It took 12 days to produce a government at the last crisis.
                            Furthermore, the people in general retain what has been called an
                            uncritical confidence in the value of the lira, despite the grave
                            financial situation of the country, and I should not like to do anything
                            to destroy the present confidence in the currency. Savings are made,
                            bank deposits continue, contributions for life insurance, assistance
                            societies and the like flow in, and so far there has been no sign of any
                            panic flight from money into goods.</item>
                        <pb facs="1250" n="1238" xml:id="pg_1238"/>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>In view of these considerations, although I agree that assumption by
                            the government of responsibility for its currency is desirable, I feel
                            that I should invite your attention to the fact that in deciding this
                            question due regard should be given to the wide issues and potential
                            dangers which I have set forth. Should you determine to go ahead with
                            the proposal, however, I should like to make informal soundings as to
                            the likely reaction of the Italians before making any demands
                            officially.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>All of the same considerations apply with respect to the establishment
                            of a lira account although in a reduced form. It is technically
                            desirable but it is difficult politically.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>My experts at AC and at this headquarters have advised me in the
                            following sense with respect to the proposals concerning AFA contained
                            in Tam 445: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Allied forces in Italy regardless of their location with
                                    respect to Italian Government or AMG territory must continue to
                                    receive an adequate volume of lire currency from AFA.
                                    Consequently, if responsibility for all currency is assumed by
                                    the Italian Government, AFA should either physically draw
                                    currency from the government or obtain currency from abroad as
                                    at present for Italian Government account, but for military use.
                                    After the non-military currency arrives, moreover, the remaining
                                    stocks of AM lire should be retained by AFA and it should have
                                    the right to use them in an emergency.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Finance Sub-commission including AFA will require some
                                    months to complete the process already begun of ridding itself
                                    of financial operations such as mentioned in paragraph L–A of
                                    Tam 445. Certain operations which must be continued by AC and
                                    which are in addition to those mentioned in paragraph L–C of Tam
                                    445 include civilian supply and financial accounting and the
                                    financing of Advisory Council and AC–AMG.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The transfer of AFA to headquarters, therefore, could not be
                                    accomplished for several months and even then would require the
                                    creation of another Finance Sub-commission section to continue
                                    handling many current functions of AFA.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>The wider problem of giving “a greater measure of responsibility in
                            financial matters” to the Italian Government is dealt with only to a
                            limited extent in Tam 445. The AC is concerned at present in varying
                            degrees between advice and control with many other areas of financial
                            operations such as the following: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The AC assists the government in its own territory in the
                                    control of expenditure and finds it necessary to a certain
                                    extent to bring pressure upon the government from time to time
                                    to prevent essential communications and other services necessary
                                    to the Allied war effort from breaking down.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The AC collaborates with the government in the collection of
                                    revenue, the development of new sources of revenue, the
                                    improvement <pb facs="1251" n="1239" xml:id="pg_1239"/> of
                                    existing techniques of collection and in the effort to reduce
                                    collection costs and generally stimulate the efficiency of the
                                    revenue service.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>With regard to governmental accounting within and without the
                                    budget, the AC works with the central accounting authority in
                                    attempting to keep a close check on budget deficit, expenditure
                                    and disbursement deficit.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>With the Italian Government the AC is trying to obtain normal
                                    operations of domestic insurance, but is keeping a tight control
                                    at the same time as required by Tam 417 over insurance interests
                                    abroad.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In the field of property control and in the absence of any
                                    instruction in detail from CCS, the AC has been trying to
                                    conserve the properties of Allied nationals in Italy and to
                                    arrange appropriately for the transfer of this responsibility to
                                    the Italian Government.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>I intend to continue as heretofore until otherwise instructed. <hi
                                rend="italic">End of paraphrase.</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Section III. Without presuming to enter into technicalities, I can only say with
                    regard to the foregoing that it is an unhappy commentary on Allied policy and
                    practice in Italy if, owing to a failure to take reasonable measures to
                    strengthen the position of the Government and improve conditions in the country,
                    it is considered inadvisable to establish now financial measures which would
                    have been realistic and practical if determined months ago and which must
                    eventually be put into effect as a part of a safe economy in Italy.</p>
                <p>To my mind the liberation of the north should not be regarded as a potentiality
                    for increased strength to the present government but as an eventuality fraught
                    with fresh burdens which may prove unbearable and consequently contributory to a
                    state of disorder throughout the country similar to but greater in extent than
                    we have already witnessed in other areas. To confront the present government in
                    its present state of weakness and disillusionment with the necessity of adopting
                    measures which, taken by themselves, increase their responsibilities before the
                    country without concrete and present benefits may be found by Allied financial
                    experts here too drastic a dose but even that will not be established without
                    determining accurately the measured views of all the interested ministries of
                    the government. Some steps to that end are, I understand, envisaged.</p>
                <p>In conclusion I can not refrain from submitting however that if the Italian
                    Government can be assured that the President’s expressed views as regards food
                    and transport requirements for Italy may be regarded as in process of execution
                    and, that the American policy to substitute a more realistic status for Italy in
                    place of the present armistice regime has been accepted for implementation, the
                    Italian Government should then be able to absorb the shock of the contemplated
                    financial measures particularly in view of the fact that they are fundamentally
                    salutary and do not in themselves preclude the possibility <pb facs="1252"
                        n="1240" xml:id="pg_1240"/> of eventual credits to Italy which may prove
                    necessary and constructive. And even if that is too optimistic a view and the
                    government fails in the test outlined above it can be argued that the
                    consequences of such a revelation of weakness would be more easily dealt with
                    now than at the time of the real emergency when the north is liberated.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
