<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-13T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-13T14:00:00-05:00" n="1142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1142">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">865.51/1–1345: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-13T15:00:00-04:00">January
                                    13, 1945—3 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>66. Following is for your information on program of discussion with
                            Italian technical mission. Mission arrived in Washington <pb facs="1235" n="1223" xml:id="pg_1223"/> November 10 with letters from
                                Bonomi<note n="40" xml:id="d1142fn1">Ivanoe Bonomi, Italian Prime
                                Minister.</note> to President, Secretary and Secretary of Treasury
                            describing the mission as “fully accredited” by the Italian
                                Government.<note n="41" xml:id="d1142fn2">The mission was headed by
                                Baron Quinto Quintieri and Raffaele Mattioli and is often referred
                                to as the Quintieri–Mattioli mission.</note> In preliminary
                            discussions to ascertain purpose of visit, mission indicated desire to
                            discuss measures to stabilize and provide backing for the lira, credits,
                            return of gold seized by Germans, Allied military expenditures in Italy,
                            the centralization of the note issue in the Bank of Italy, and the
                            participation of Italy in various United Nations economic organizations.
                            They described financial and monetary questions as key to Italian
                            problems and expressed hope of learning extent to which Allied support
                            would be given in backing currency. Generally, they intend to find out
                            where Italy stands in relation to United Nations in economic and
                            financial matters.</p>
                        <p>Mission was reminded that United States is merely one of United Nations
                            and was told that some of these points could not be discussed in detail.
                            It was suggested that they direct their attention to specific practical
                            problems in Italo-American relations. They were told that discussions
                            would be carried on at technical level.</p>
                        <p>Discussions have followed two general lines. The principal discussions
                            have related to financial matters and have taken place with Treasury.
                            Italians have outlined their problems in detail and have urged (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) steps to regularize financial relations with
                            the Allies in such a way as to permit Italian Government to control
                            internal finances, to put lira on a firm basis, and to be informed of
                            what its assets and liabilities are; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that the
                            United States make available to Italy the dollar equivalent of lira
                            expenditures of our forces in Italy for purposes other than troop pay,
                            plus the dollar value of any excess of supplies and resources furnished
                            us on a requisite basis over supplies which we furnish to Italy.</p>
                        <p>Treasury is about to hand the mission a statement on these proposals
                            which will say: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We view with sympathy Italian desire to assume responsibility
                                    for entire note issue and will discuss Italian request with
                                    British, to whom Italian Government should also make known its
                                    views.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>(As reported in a separate telegram, we have already proposed
                                    this to the British in connection with the discussions in
                                    CCAC).</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>We are prepared to enter into an agreement governing financial
                                    arrangements arising out of the operation of American troops in
                                    Italy, designed to formalize present procedures. (This would
                                    transfer the troop pay arrangement from a unilateral American
                                    statement to an undertaking as part of agreed
                                    procedures.)</item>
                                <pb facs="1236" n="1224" xml:id="pg_1224"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We will take steps aiming to provide the Italian Government
                                    with full information relating to transactions affecting
                                    American-Italian relations.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>We will assist the Italian Government to mobilize its foreign
                                    assets to the maximum.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>This statement constitutes in effect an acceptance of the first group of
                            Italian proposals and rejection of the second. For reasons which have
                            been explained to you in connection with the proposed lira account (see
                            Deptel 396, November 7),<note n="42" xml:id="d1142fn3">Not
                                printed.</note> it is impossible for us to pay dollars for
                            expenditures for our forces in Italy other than troop pay. However, we
                            are asking the War Department to agree to replace free of charge any
                            goods requisitioned or purchased with lire which are in short supply and
                            use of which necessitates current replacement by importation. We have
                            given similar undertakings to the continental Allies. Although such an
                            arrangement would probably have limited practical significance in Italy,
                            it would seem to us to be of some value from a political viewpoint.</p>
                        <p>The mission has also been provided with information concerning the
                            procedures under which AM lire are issued, and figures on total issues
                            of AM lire and issues to American forces and to Italian agencies.
                            Detailed information has also been provided on standing of
                            post-liberation dollar accounts.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the financial conversations, discussions have been
                            arranged for the mission on the subject of trade, the current status of
                            Italian assets in this country, trading with the enemy restrictions, the
                            proclaimed list, etc. While the interest of the mission in these
                            subjects has been primarily in their relationship to the Italian
                            financial position, we think that the discussions have been of
                            value.</p>
                        <p>We anticipate that our conversations with the mission will end in about
                            two weeks. We plan to give them a consolidated memorandum stating our
                            position and views on the principal points covered during the
                            discussions. In addition to these specific points, we hope to give them
                            a general statement of our attitude toward Italy’s economic problems,
                            indicating our sympathy and interest but also making clear the
                            limitations on our ability to help Italy.</p>
                        <p>We also plan to issue a press release indicating in very general terms
                            the nature of the discussions, portraying them as laying the basis for
                            the resumption of normal economic relations between the two countries,
                            and suggesting that they will eventually be followed by some
                            agreements.</p>
                        <p>It would be desirable if this statement could be made a joint one with
                            the Italian Government.</p>
                        <pb facs="1237" n="1225" xml:id="pg_1225"/>
                        <p>The Department’s general attitude toward the discussions has been that
                            they would perforce be mainly explanatory and informative, but that the
                            mission should not be allowed to return home without accomplishments. We
                            will try to make the memorandum summarizing the discussions as
                            substantial as possible. The press release will necessarily be thin. We
                            see nothing to be gained from an overblown statement and think that
                            directing publicity toward the fact that we are trying to work out
                            detailed economic problems by joint discussions is the best
                            approach.</p>
                        <p>(We gather from the mission that the Italian Government has discouraged
                            press discussions of the mission, and its members have scrupulously
                            refrained from giving out information to the press here.)</p>
                        <p>Exactly what the Italian Government expected the mission to accomplish is
                            far from clear to us. We have gathered that no precise instructions were
                            given the mission and assume that it was expected to find out how
                            matters stood and to do the best it could. That the Italians had hopes
                            of obtaining something substantial would seem to be indicated by the
                            fact that the mission was armed with full powers in the face of our
                            agreement to receive it only in an unofficial capacity. We for our part
                            are convinced that the achievements of the mission, though perhaps
                            disappointing to it and to the Italian government, will have been far
                            from negligible. It has effectively served to present and explain
                            concrete Italian problems, to promote goodwill, and to lay the basis for
                            later solutions. It might be well for you to convey this thought in any
                            informal discussions with officials of the Government.</p>
                        <p>We plan to inform the British of the conversations and to show them for
                            their information the statements we will give the Italians before they
                            are handed to the mission. The mission had planned to go on to London
                            but we understand the British are not prepared to receive them at this
                            time.</p>
                        <p>A full record of the discussions has been made and copies of minutes and
                            documents are being sent you by mail.</p>
                        <p>Department would welcome any comments you may have.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>