<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative in Bulgaria ( (Barnes) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-01-04T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-04T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-04T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-04T09:00:00-05:00" n="122"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d122">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Bulgaria)/1–545:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative in Bulgaria</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Barnes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-04T15:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 4, 1945—[3 p.m.]</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 5—6:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5. The time has come I think when the Department should point[out?] to the
                    Russian authorities in Moscow in the most forceful manner possible the
                    imperative need of our delegate on the Allied Soviet Control Commission<note
                        n="14" xml:id="d122fn1">Maj. Gen. John A. Crane, U.S.A., Chief of the U.S.
                        military representation on the Allied Control Commission (ACC) for
                        Bulgaria.</note> and of this mission for a weekly courier <pb facs="0150"
                        n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/> plane linking our establishments here with
                    Washington Bucharest and Caserta. We have received one pouch, No. 3, since my
                    arrival. I point out to cite merely one handicap of this situation that we are
                    now receiving telegrams which are undecipherable due to non receipt of
                    cryptographic material.</p>
                <p>It is my belief that the Russian authorities should be informed in so many words
                    that we are here as Allies to assist in carrying out terms of the armistice and
                    that we must conclude that the Soviet Government views our presence in an
                    entirely different light if we cannot obtain a blanket permit for a weekly
                    courier plane. The so-called agreement reached between Russian Military
                    authorities in Moscow and the Allied Military Missions there as to procedure
                    covering flights of American and British planes to Sofia is so interpreted by
                    local Russian authorities as to constitute an even greater impediment to the
                    movement of our planes in and out of Sofia than formerly existed. These
                    authorities have explained to the British and to us that requests for clearance
                    under this agreement can be only made here and that each individual request must
                    contain following particulars: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Number and type of aircraft;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Individual and tailmarkings;</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Route of flight;</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Purpose of flight;</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Passenger list, numbers and particulars with respect to each person,
                            type of cargo and to whom destined;</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Expected time and date of arrival.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Each request will be transmitted separately to Moscow for decision by the
                    Commissar of Foreign Affairs<note n="15" xml:id="d122fn2">Vyacheslav
                        Mikhailovich Molotov, People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the Soviet
                        Union.</note> upon receipt of this information. Russian authorities
                    anticipate a minimum delay of 7 days in the case of each request.</p>
                <p>It is obvious to anyone who knows weather conditions here and the inadequate
                    radio installations maintained at the local airfields by Russian authorities
                    that these regulations are calculated to render virtually impossible regular air
                    communications for the British and ourselves.</p>
                <p>While the Russians from one point of view might be well pleased to have [us?]
                    shut up shop in Bulgaria, their local representatives are sufficiently
                    intelligent to know that in such an eventuality the reaction locally would
                    gravely affect their long range position in the country. Therefore, I do not
                    believe that it is necessary for us in such matters as the assurance of proper
                    communications to go begging to them with our hat in our hands. The usefulness
                    of our presence will continue <pb facs="0151" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> at a
                    minimum until this mission and our delegation on the Allied Soviet Control
                    Commission can be assured of a regular means of transport for personnel,
                    supplies and mail.</p>
                <p>This is also No. 3 to AmEmbassy, Moscow, and No. 4 to AmPolAd.<note n="16"
                        xml:id="d122fn3">American Political Adviser (Alexander C. Kirk) on the staff
                        of the Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean Theater, at Caserta.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Barnes</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
