<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative in Bulgaria ( (Barnes) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-05-24T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-24T10:00:00-05:00" n="202"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">874.00/5–2445: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative in Bulgaria</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Barnes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-24T17:00:00+02:00"
                            >May 24, 1945—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 24—4:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>269. See my No. 268 today, 11 a.m. I have discussed the Dimitrov case with the
                    Senior Regent Ganev, the Prime Minister and the Exarch.<note n="55"
                        xml:id="d202fn1">Stefan, Metropolitan of Sofia, Exarch of the Bulgarian
                        Orthodox Church.</note> The MinFonAff is out of town as it is a local
                    holiday.</p>
                <p>Both the Regent and Exarch urged upon me the need to save Dimitrov. They said
                    that any honest patriotic Bulgarian whose ideals have not been warped by
                    Communist doctrine would urge the same upon me.</p>
                <p>I told the Prime Minister the whole story of the escape as I know it from the
                    time Dimitrov left his own house until he arrived at mine. I said I had not gone
                    to the Russians as the matter appeared to be one between myself and the
                    Bulgarian Govt. I pointed out that the Allied Control Commission was here to
                    supervise the execution of the Armistice terms, that we were now in the second
                    period of the Armistice, and that, as I understood that document, the ACC was no
                    longer in principle under the general direction of the Soviet High <pb
                        facs="0234" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/> Command. I added that if the escape of
                    Dimitrov was a matter about which the Russian authorities would concern
                    themselves, it seemed to me that it was for the Bulgarian authorities to discuss
                    the subject with the Russians, rather than for me or Gen. Crane to do so.</p>
                <p>The PriMin agreed with this reasoning. He was taken by complete surprise with the
                    news as no inkling of the escape had reached him from the militia or the
                    Minister of Interior. I know that the hunt for Dimitrov has been in full cry
                    since sometime this morning. I therefore asked the PriMin to get in touch with
                    the Minister of Interior immediately to call off the search. He said that he
                    would do this at once and would also consult with other members of the Cabinet
                    as to what position the Govt should take. He agreed emphatically with me that no
                    incident involving your [<hi rend="italic">our</hi>] mission should be allowed
                    to arise and that every effort should be made to find a solution with respect to
                    Dimitrov’s future that would eliminate him as an embarrassment to the Russians,
                    the Communists and the Bulgarian Govt and that would at the same time preclude
                    arousing democratic opinion elsewhere against Bulgaria and the FF. He said that
                    of course the Govt would not consider taking any definite steps in the case
                    until I had received instructions from Washington.</p>
                <p>There can be no doubt but that our action in the Dimitrov casie will be largely
                    controlling in what the average, patriotic Bulgarian may think of us in the
                    future. While there is as yet no public knowledge of the matter, the case is
                    bound to be discussed on street corners and in every household in Bulgaria. In
                    view of this situation and the tenor of the Prime Minister’s remarks, I urge
                    most sincerely that, without taking any position on the question in principle of
                    asylum, the Dept authorize me to negotiate as best I can through the Bulgarian
                    Govt for the departure of Dimitrov from Bulgaria under the guarantee that he
                    will go to the US or to some far distant country and refrain from political
                    activity until Bulgaria again has an established and recognized Govt. So far as
                    I can ascertain from conversations with high Govt authorities and local lawyers,
                    no legal basis exists for the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> domiciliary arrest
                    under which Dimitrov has been confined to his house and from which he escaped
                    yesterday afternoon. Both the Regent and the Exarch have assured me that
                    Dimitrov is guilty of no crime against Bulgaria, its people, the Allies or any
                    moral code.</p>
                <p>Whatever may be the Dept’s instructions they should not be delayed beyond
                    tomorrow at the latest.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Moscow as No. 129, AmPolAd as No. 144.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Barnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
