<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-28T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-28T13:00:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">874.00/5–2845: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative in Bulgaria</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Barnes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-28T20:00:00+02:00">May 28,
                                    1945—8 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received May 28—9:07 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>278. Following tel is from Genl Crane to JCS sent this evening: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I called this afternoon accompanied by Black, of Barnes staff,
                                    on Gen Biryusov who has just returned from Moscow. I informed
                                    the Soviet General of the events of past 5 days with regard to
                                    Dimitrov case and explained the view of the US Govt that this
                                    was a matter primarily between the American and Bulgarian Govts
                                    and that a decision of the ACC would be accepted only if reached
                                    on a genuinely tri-partite basis. I also mentioned that
                                    negotiations on this subject were now in progress in Moscow.</p>
                                <p>To this Gen Biryusov replied that while he might have been
                                    inclined to intervene had he been here at the time of Dimitrov’s
                                    escape he would take no action now until he received
                                    instructions from Moscow and would in the meantime regard the
                                    incident as one between the American and Bulgarian Govts. He
                                    added however that he could in no case consider reaching an ACC
                                    decision on a tri-partite basis until he reed instructions that
                                    the three powers participating on the ACC had agreed on a new
                                    procedure for that body.</p>
                                <p>Gen Biryusov added that he nevertheless felt it his duty to
                                    inform me that Dimitrov had been held under house arrest for a
                                    month on a charge of being a “defeatist”, that he, Biryusov,
                                    personally believed Dimitrov to be a Fascist who had supported
                                    the German cause and that it was his own personal view that Mr.
                                    Barnes’ action constituted a “brutal interference” in Bulgarian
                                    internal affairs. This statement does not correspond with the
                                    documents in this case seen by Barnes and Black.</p>
                                <p>As regards the Soviet military posts which restricted Mr. Barnes’
                                    movements between his villa and Sofia, Genl Biryusov said that
                                    they would be removed immediately. He then repeated his view
                                    that this whole matter should remain one between the US and
                                    Bulgarian Govts until the receipt of any instructions to the
                                    contrary. The tenor of the conversation was entirely
                                    amicable.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Repeated to Moscow as 137.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Barnes</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>