<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The British Embassy to the Department of State
                    
                    Handed to the Department on January 13.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d3</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">3</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="3" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">875.01/1–1245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="21" xml:id="d3fn1">Handed to the Department on January 13.</note>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Government welcome the statement of the Department of State’s
                    policy with regard to Albania contained in the Department’s memorandum of
                    November 21st, 1944,<note n="22" xml:id="d3fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1944v03#pg_288">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 288</ref>.</note> and are glad to find
                    that the Department share the view of His Majesty’s Government that recognition
                    of the Provisional Government formed at Berat<note n="23" xml:id="d3fn3">See
                        footnote 15, <ref target="#pg_4">p. 4</ref>.</note> should not be granted
                    for the present. As for the future His Majesty’s Government agree that before
                        <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> recognition can be granted to any Albanian
                    Government it should be in a position to fulfil the conditions which the State
                    Department have put forward.</p>
                <p>There remains the question of establishing relations on a day to day basis with
                    the F.N.C.<note n="24" xml:id="d3fn4">The National Liberation Front, political
                        party created at the Congress of Berat, October 22, 1944, as a successor to
                        the National Liberation Movement (L.N.C.); officially, a mass organization
                        representing all shades of “democratic” political opinion, but actually a
                        camouflage organization for the purpose of implementing the program and
                        policies of the Albania Communist Party.</note> which is in <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control of the country. It is noted that the
                    State Department feel it may soon be desirable to establish such relations as
                    would enable them to open an office in Tirana for the purpose of protecting
                    American interests there and co-ordinating activities of representatives of
                    other American agencies who may be sent to Albania. His Majesty’s Government for
                    their part have also been considering this problem and have reached the
                    conclusion that until the time comes for the recognition of a government in
                    Albania the best course would be to withdraw the British liaison officers at
                    present in the country and to accredit a military mission to the headquarters of
                    the F.N.C. Plans have therefore been worked out for the despatch of a mission
                    under the command of the <pb facs="0018" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> Supreme Allied
                    Commander in the Mediterranean. This mission, whose duties would include the
                    provision of up to date information on political tendencies in Albania and of
                    advice on the economic and financial situation, would be headed by an officer of
                    the rank of Brigadier. He would be assisted by a Lieutenant Palmer (at present
                    senior British Liaison Officer at F.N.C. headquarters) as political adviser and
                    by two or three other officers with experience in Albanian affairs. It is
                    proposed that Military Liaison Albania (which is a joint Anglo-United States
                    organisation) would be separate from the British military mission but would work
                    in close cooperation with it.</p>
                <p>As recent military developments in Albania make it very desirable that the
                    mission should enter the country at the earliest possible moment, His Majesty’s
                    Government propose to send it in as soon as the necessary administrative
                    arrangements can be made. At the same time His Majesty’s Government would
                    welcome any information the State Department may be able to give about their own
                    plans for maintaining contact with F.N.C. during this interim period.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-12">January 12,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
