<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">875.00/8–1545</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Representative in Albania</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jacobs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 75</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tirana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-15">August 15,
                                1945</date>.<lb/>[Received September 13.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Sir: With reference to my telegram no. 57, July 1, 1945, 3 p.m.,
                            embodying preliminary findings and recommendations of the Special
                            Mission at Tirana with respect to the question of the recognition of the
                            present regime in control of Albania, I have the honor to submit
                            herewith the final recommendations of this Special Mission under the
                            title: “Summary of Findings and Recommendations with Respect to the
                            Recognition of the ‘Democratic Government of Albania’</p>
                        <p>There is, as mentioned in the Summary, a supplementary, documentary
                            report consisting of fourteen sections, the titles of which will be
                            found in Appendix II attached to the Summary. This documentary report
                            will be submitted by separate despatch<note n="18" xml:id="d35fn1">The
                                Documentary Report Supplementing Summary of Findings and
                                Recommendations With Respect to the Recognition of the “Democratic
                                Government of Albania” was transmitted to the Department in despatch
                                76, August 16, from Tirana, neither printed.</note> as it will not
                            be necessary for the higher officers of the Department considering the
                            Summary to read this supplementary report although they may wish <pb facs="0059" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> to consult certain sections of
                            it, especially Section VI—”International Relations”.</p>
                        <p>Information concerning the officers who assisted in the preparation of
                            the enclosed Summary, as well as the documentary report, will be
                            submitted in a separate despatch.</p>
                        <p>I expect to be in Washington shortly to confer with officers of the
                            Department concerning the recommendations contained in the Summary.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacobs</hi>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Service Officer</hi>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extracts]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Summary of Findings and Recommendations With
                                    Respect to the Recognition of “The Democratic Government of
                                    Albania”</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In a telegram dated July 1, 1945, the Special Mission of the United
                                States Government sent to Tirana to study conditions submitted a
                                preliminary report of its findings of facts and certain
                                recommendations with respect to the question of extending
                                recognition to “The Democratic Government of Albania”, as
                                follows:</p>
                            <p>[Here follows text of report contained in telegram 57, July 1, 3
                                p.m., from Tirana, printed on <ref target="#pg_38">page
                                38</ref>.]</p>
                            <p>Having completed its studies, there is attached a final report in
                                fourteen sections. In addition, there is set forth below a summary
                                of important facts followed by suggestions and recommendations,
                                which are essentially the same as those submitted in July and quoted
                                    above.<note n="19" xml:id="d35fn2">The Summary, which in the
                                    original consisted of 26 double-spaced, legal-sized typewritten
                                    sheets, was divided into the following sections: I. Organization
                                    of the Present Regime; II. Personnel; III. The Judiciary; IV.
                                    The Army and Police; V. Extra-Governmental Agencies and
                                    Influences; VI. Opposition Groups; VII. Nationalist Sentiment;
                                    VIII. International Relations; IX. Other Governmental
                                    Activities; X. Specific Recommendations. Only Section X of the
                                    Summary, which comprised 7 pages in the original text, is
                                    printed here.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">x. specific recommendations</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Recognition</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The present regime should be recognized by the United States, Great
                                Britain and the Soviet Union and recognition should be accorded
                                simultaneously at the earliest possible date subject to the
                                following conditions and restrictions:</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, the regime recognized shall undertake
                                to hold a general election at which the people of Albania will
                                choose representatives to a Constitutional Convention where the
                                representatives so chosen will decide whether they wish (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to continue the present form of government
                                intact, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the present form of government
                                with changes decided <pb facs="0060" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> upon by
                                them, or (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) some new form of government to
                                be organized by the said Constitutional Convention, provided that in
                                any event there shall be proclaimed in the organic law of the
                                present or any new government a Bill of Eights similar to that
                                contained in a “Declaration on the Eights of Citizens” adopted at
                                the Congress of Berat in October 1944, but apparently since
                                discarded by the present regime.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> In connection with the aforementioned
                                elections, two proposals will inevitably be made, viz: either that
                                the election be by secret ballot or that it be held in accordance
                                with the existing electoral laws of the present regime—the town-hall
                                variety of election. In view of the known attitude of the British
                                toward the regime, it is almost certain that they will try to insist
                                upon election by secret ballot. It is believed that either method
                                would be satisfactory but, as the present regime would be in control
                                in either case, the simplest procedure would he to conduct the
                                election according to existing electoral laws. A clear warning
                                should, however, be given by each of the three powers that the
                                regime must permit the election to be conducted in an atmosphere of
                                perfect freedom and that all parties and all persons whether for or
                                against the government shall be permitted to participate without
                                threats or fear during or after the elections. In giving this
                                warning, it should also be stated that the diplomatic
                                representatives of the three powers, who will be in the country,
                                will have standing instructions to observe the conduct not only of
                                the election but also of the Constitutional Convention which will
                                follow. It is believed that these safeguards should be reasonably
                                sufficient.</p>
                            <p>While the British may raise the point, it is not recommended that the
                                present regime be required to permit Albanian refugees abroad,
                                political or otherwise, to return to Albania under safe conduct
                                passes to participate in the election. These refugees constitute a
                                very small minority of the Albanian people and, while there may be a
                                few true patriots among them, there are far more persons who
                                collaborated with the Italian and German invaders and who fled to
                                escape their just deserts. It would be too much to ask the present
                                regime to permit their return without careful screening which the
                                three powers have neither time nor means to provide. There may,
                                however, be a few former Albanian leaders whom the British seem to
                                favor, such as Medmed Konitza, former Albanian Minister to London,
                                whom the present regime might permit to come into the country
                                without molestation.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, there should be an exchange of notes
                                in which the Albanian authorities shall undertake, pending
                                negotiation of treaties, to guarantee to the diplomatic consular
                                representatives of the three powers, diplomatic rights and
                                privileges usually extended under international law. In view of the
                                peculiar situation existing in Albania some of these rights
                                mentioned in Section VI on International Relations should <pb facs="0061" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> be specifically named so
                                that there will be no question about them. In addition, it should be
                                clearly provided in the exchange of notes that the diplomatic
                                representatives, including their staffs, shall be entitled to travel
                                freely about the country unaccompanied by government police or
                                guards.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Assistance to be Rendered</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In discussing the question of recognition with the British and Soviet
                                authorities, it is recommended that the subject of assistance, joint
                                or separate, which they will render to the new government especially
                                in the fields of finance and economic reconstruction, be taken up.
                                Without such assistance there can be no economic stability in the
                                country and without such stability no government can continue long
                                in power. In according such assistance, advantage should be taken of
                                the opportunity to insist, as a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>,
                                that the regime reduce the size of its Army commensurate with its
                                resources and population. This last point is highly important
                                because the budget for this year, which was only made public on July
                                28, 1945, indicates that a little over half of the one billion franc
                                estimated revenue is to be devoted to the Army.</p>
                            <p>It might also be agreed between the three powers that this subject
                                will be submitted to their diplomatic representatives in Albania for
                                joint study and joint or separate reports as the situation may
                                require. This study should begin, however, as soon as possible after
                                recognition is accorded and the diplomatic representatives arrive in
                                Tirana. As stated above UNRRA may be able to take care of emergency
                                needs pending a decision on some long range program.</p>
                            <p>In connection with financial and economic assistance referred to
                                above, it is also recommended that irrespective of other
                                considerations immediate steps should be taken by the three powers
                                to restore postal, telegraphic and ordinary private financial
                                facilities between Albania and the outside world. Such restoration
                                is of great importance to the United States because of the large
                                percentage of the population, especially in southern Albania, which
                                has friends and relatives in the United States, with whom they wish
                                to communicate and from whom they badly need remittances which were
                                formerly the main support of many of them.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">British-Soviet-Albanian
                                    Relations</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is recommended that the Department of State confer with the
                                British Foreign Office and the Soviet Foreign Office with regard to
                                their real attitude and policy toward Albania, This approach should
                                definitely be made before a decision is reached with respect to the
                                question of recognition, as the results of those inquiries might
                                change the entire character of the recommendations.</p>
                            <pb facs="0062" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, we should make a point-blank request
                                of the British Foreign Office for a clarification of its real policy
                                toward the setting up of an independent Albania and toward the
                                opposition groups in Albania and elsewhere. In other words, we
                                should know whether the British Foreign Office is really desirous
                                and prepared to support the establishment of an independent Albania.
                                We should make it clear that we know of utterances of certain
                                British officials who prefer to see the country divided up and the
                                southern part added to Greece. If the Foreign Office still supports
                                Anthony Eden’s declaration that there is to be an independent
                                Albania, that declaration should be reaffirmed and British policy
                                oriented accordingly.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, an inquiry should be made of the
                                Soviet Foreign Office with regard to its real policy toward Albania
                                and toward the Communist group in Albania. This may be a delicate
                                question but if there is to be any satisfactory solution of the
                                Albanian problems the United States, before according recognition,
                                should know whether the Russians and the Russian Communist Party
                                will refrain from exercising, through the Communist group in Albania
                                or otherwise, undue influence in forcing upon the Albanian people a
                                form of government which they do not want and a foreign policy which
                                is unacceptable to its people. In other words, we should expect the
                                Soviet Government to live up to its declaration at Yalta that the
                                Albanian people have the right to choose freely and without coercion
                                within or without the form of government under which they wish to
                                live.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Border Problems</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>There are three Albanian border problems, one with Greece (the most
                                urgent), one with Yugoslavia, and one with Italy, which should be
                                made the subject of discussions with the British and Soviet Foreign
                                Offices at the time the question of recognition is discussed.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, with regard to Greece, we should seek
                                to persuade both Foreign Offices to agree to a definite policy,
                                which should be announced publicly, to the effect that there is to
                                be no change in the southern border of Albania in favor of Greece
                                unless and until at some future time before some duly constituted
                                international organization Greek claims can be considered in a calm
                                and peaceful atmosphere and decided upon their merit. If the three
                                governments wish to decide upon a more positive policy, they could
                                agree among themselves to suggest to the Albanian and Greek
                                governments the appointment of a commission consisting of one member
                                for each of the three powers, (possibly the diplomatic
                                representatives of the three powers at Tirana) together with Greek
                                and Albanian representatives, to proceed to the border and to decide
                                upon such minor adjustments as would be necessary to make the border
                                conform more to natural topography, <pb facs="0063" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> with a provision that the boundaries, once
                                fixed, minorities on either side thereof shall be removed to their
                                own country whether they wish to or not.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, a somewhat similar discussion should
                                be had with respect to the boundary between Albania and Yugoslavia
                                in the Kossova region. As has been indicated in the section of this
                                report on Albanian international relations there are approximately
                                one-half million Albanians in the Kossova area of Yugoslavia. The
                                Albanian authorities have apparently acquiesced in Yugoslavia’s
                                position that no change in this boundary be made but it is well
                                known that this is due to the influence that the Tito faction has
                                had over the present regime. The apparent solution at the present
                                time on that basis is not a real solution as it has settled
                                nothing.</p>
                            <p>Although this problem is not urgent in view of the present regime’s
                                acceptance of the present <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>, it is
                                highly desirable that the matter be discussed with the British and
                                Soviet Foreign Offices and possibly an agreement reached that a
                                commission, possibly the same commission that would study the Greek
                                frontier problem, should study this problem with a view to making
                                recommendations along the lines of a settlement similar to the
                                settlement proposed for the Albanian-Greek frontier with the
                                exception, of course, that a larger territory in the Kossova region
                                would be ceded to Albania and populations transferred accordingly.
                                It is also evident that with respect to this matter the cooperation
                                and participation of the Yugoslav authorities would be
                                essential.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>, definite agreement should be reached
                                that the Island of Saseno lying at the entrance of Valona harbor and
                                taken by Italy in 1920 shall be returned to Albania. It is so
                                obvious that Saseno belongs to Albania that no mention was made of
                                it elsewhere in this report and it would not have been mentioned at
                                all except for the fact that only recently Saseno was the subject of
                                inquiry from A.F.H.Q., at Caserta. Hence the brief recommendation,
                                which is the only logical one to be made.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Balkan Federation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>There remains as a possible final subject for discussion the question
                                of Albania joining a Balkan federation.</p>
                            <p>It is believed that there is merit in the idea of a general Balkan
                                federation, provided that the terms of the federation agreement are
                                reached by the Balkan states concerned after a mutually friendly
                                conference of their representatives who would act and draft without
                                influence from outside powers. In other words, the three great
                                powers, the United States, Great Britain and the Soviet Union, as
                                well as France, which will also be influential in European affairs,
                                should <pb facs="0064" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> stand absolutely
                                aloof and allow the Balkan states to work out their own solution in
                                this respect.</p>
                            <p>It is believed, however, that the present is not a propitious time to
                                attempt to arrive at a federation arrangement as there is obviously
                                too much friction existing in the Balkans for any such agreement to
                                be reached. Aside from the Albanian-Greek and Albanian-Yugoslav
                                problems, there are Yugoslav and Greek problems, Balkan problems and
                                so on. Probably, therefore, it would be best for the three big
                                powers to suggest to Albania and to Yugoslavia, the only other power
                                really concerned at the moment, that this matter should be dropped
                                for the time being as there are more pressing problems for the
                                authorities of each of these Balkan states to consider than the
                                problem of a federation. In due time, however, the idea should be
                                taken up.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">xi. appendices</hi><note n="20" xml:id="d35fn3">None printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>List of Cabinet Officers.</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>List of Sections of Documentary Report attached.</item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>Table of Contents of this Summary.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>