<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Czechoslovak Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs ( (Clementis) ) to the
                    American Chargé in Czechoslovakia ( (Klieforth))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d508</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">508</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="508"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d508">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860F.014/6–545</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Czechoslovak Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clementis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Chargé in Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Klieforth</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="16" xml:id="d508fn1">Copy transmitted to the Department in
                        despatch 3, June 5, from Prague; received June 13.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Prague</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-31">May 31,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honour to address to you the following
                    information:</p>
                <p>The Czechoslovak Government has always claimed frontiers for this country which
                    were in existence before Munich, at the same time never failing to emphasize to
                    the competent bodies that this point of view must not be prejudicial to future
                    claims of rectification of frontiers to be raised at a suitable time in full
                    accord with the Allied Governments, in favour of the Czechoslovak Republic and
                    to the disadvantage of the enemy states. The period immediately following the
                    end of war operations has on our part been considered as most suitable for this
                    purpose. The Czechoslovak Government has therefore prepared proposals along this
                    line in order to lay duly substantiated claims before all Allied Governments
                    and, should such rectification concern the boundaries of the friendly
                    neighbouring Polish State, naturally also before the Polish Government.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, however, it has been brought to the knowledge of the
                    Czechoslovak Government that the territory of Kladsko was placed under the
                    administration of the Polish authorities and that, by a proclamation dated in
                    April 1945, Mr. St. Piaskowski was appointed commissioner of the Polish Republic
                    for the administrative province of Lower Silesia.</p>
                <p>This proclamation, which was addressed to the population of Lower Silesia and
                    South Brandenburg, and which having been posted also in the area of Kladsko, was
                    evidently supposed to cover this area too, asserted that this province, Slavonic
                    from time immemorial, had been taken from Poland.</p>
                <p>With respect to the arguments contained in the aforesaid proclamation, I take the
                    liberty of drawing your attention to the fact that the area of Kladsko, up to
                    the year 1742 when first annexation by Prussia took place, had been a possession
                    of Bohemia to which it belonged also ethnographically to such an extent that
                    even at the <pb facs="0526" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/> present time, after more
                    than two hundred years of forced Germanisation, entire groups of communities
                    have never been deprived of their decidely Czech character.</p>
                <p>It should be added to the statement of the Polish proclamation that the primary
                    origin of these inhabitants is Slavonic, that these primarily Slavonic
                    inhabitants used to and still do belong to the Czech branch. For this reason
                    these people applied to the Czechoslovak Government to take charge of Kladsko
                    until final determination of the frontiers should be made.</p>
                <p>Owing to the fact that Kladsko gravitates to Czechoslovakia also economically and
                    by its system of transport, it is the intention of the Czechoslovak Government
                    to take over the control of this territory, as shown in the map attached hereto
                    [encl. A],<note n="17" xml:id="d508fn2">Brackets appear in the original; map not
                        reproduced.</note> without any further delay.</p>
                <p>The Czechoslovak Government would not consider the taking charge of Kladsko as a
                    final act, being fully aware of the fact that this problem will ultimately have
                    to be solved at the Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>The Czechoslovak Government, knowing that such regulation of north-eastern
                    boundaries of Czechoslovakia in her favour may concern future Polish frontiers,
                    is determined to settle this point in amicable accord with the Polish
                    Government.</p>
                <p>I may add that the Czechoslovak Government does not consider the present note as
                    providing for all claims concerning rectification of frontiers which may have to
                    be raised in connection with ethnological, historical, geographical, economic,
                    transport and other motives.</p>
                <p>A similar note is being addressed to the representatives of the Governments of
                    Great Britain, the Union of the Soviet Socialist Republics, France and to the
                    Polish Government.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="italic">Under Secretary of State:</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr</hi>. V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Clementis</hi>
                        m.p.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
