<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-15T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-15T08:00:00-05:00" n="593" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d593">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Finland)/3–1545:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative in Finland</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi></persName>)
                                <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Helsinki</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-15T15:00:00+02:00">March 15,
                                    1945—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 8:09 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>103. I called on March 13 on Zhdanov; he had been away most of the time
                            since my arrival. I mentioned my visit to Leningrad last May and the
                            fortitude of the Leningrad people in withstanding the siege.<note n="29" xml:id="d593fn1">The siege of Leningrad was raised on January 18,
                                1943.</note> Zhdanov said they had been encouraged by the attitude
                            of freedom-loving democratic peoples throughout the world and also by
                            the tangible assistance extended by American Lend Lease. He said that
                            tactically Leningrad’s defence was more important than that of
                                Stalingrad<note n="30" xml:id="d593fn2">The siege of Stalingrad was
                                raised on February 2, 1943.</note> and was principally responsible
                            for the Red Army’s ability to push into East Prussia. Zhdanov extended
                            congratulations on forcing of the Rhine at Remagen.<note n="31" xml:id="d593fn3">March 7, 1945.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I referred to a statement made last May when I was in Moscow by the
                            Soviet scientist Peter Kapitsa<note n="32" xml:id="d593fn4">Peter
                                Leonidovich Kapitsa, Russian physicist.</note> on the presentation
                            to him of the Franklin Institute Medal. Kapitsa said that in science
                            when a theorem is correct it can be demonstrated in a number of ways;
                            and that in life, also, if our ideals are the same then even if we use
                            different methods, we need not find ourselves involved in important
                            contradictions. I remarked that the United States and the Soviet Union
                            had the same ideals of democracy and freedom for peoples each of us
                            followed different social and economic systems in attainment of those
                            ideals, the Soviet Union a Communistic system and the United States of
                            America [a] system of private capital. Each could recognize that the
                            other has a different system and yet cooperate in the common ideal. I
                            mentioned with pleasure the ever developing collaboration between our
                            countries not only in war but in building for peace. Zhdanov expressed
                            agreement and said that notwithstanding difference in systems, points of
                            collaboration were increasing all the time.</p>
                        <p>At my request Zhdanov commented about the work of the Control Commission.
                            The work had been much more difficult during October and November.
                            Thereafter, with the replacement of Castren<note n="33" xml:id="d593fn5">Urho J. Castren, Finnish jurist and former Prime Minister.</note>
                            by Paasikivi it became more satisfactory and was on the whole proceeding
                            well. The economic provisions of the armistice had been carried out <pb facs="0620" n="608" xml:id="pg_608"/> more readily than the military
                            and political. Special difficulty was encountered in connection with
                            dissolution of pro-Fascist organizations. They had finally been
                            dissolved. Their activities might still be carried on underground and
                            appearance of performance might be better than actuality. The Finns
                            tried to insist that their war against Russia was an independent one and
                            not involved with German Fascism. The Russians had proof there was
                            complete cooperation between the Finnish and German General Staffs.
                            Zhdanov said the elections were coming on.<note n="34" xml:id="d593fn6">General elections for the Finnish Diet were held March 17 and 18,
                                1945. These were the first post-war elections in Finland.</note>
                            They would be a test between reactionary and democratic forces and an
                            indication whether Finland could be accepted again in the family of
                            peaceful democratic nations. He was more favorably impressed by the Finn
                            people than he had anticipated. He had thought they would be taciturn.
                            From the way they had received Soviet singers and artists they expressed
                            their feelings as spontaneously as the Russians.</p>
                        <p>As I started to leave Zhdanov said he would like to ask for my impression
                            of Finland. I said I had been here only a little over two weeks and had
                            no adequate basis for comment. I said the shops appeared pretty empty.
                            There seemed to be a good deal of excitement and rumor. This was no
                            surprise to an American at election time, for we were familiar with
                            manifestations of that type in our elections. Zhdanov laughed and wanted
                            to know whether there was more of a rumor and excitement here than in
                            America at such times. I said it seemed about the same to me. As to
                            whether the elections here would show any real change, I was not at all
                            sure. I understood that the Finns were obdurate in their views and slow
                            to change. There were a good many new elements and perhaps there had not
                            been sufficient time for substantial changes. Zhdanov laughed. I said
                            again that I had been here for only a very short time. Referring to
                            Zhdanov’s earlier statement that the Finns seemed to be moving in the
                            right direction, I said that seemed to be the important thing.</p>
                        <p>I told Zhdanov of my recent impressions of the United States. Our country
                            was geared to all-out prosecution of war in Europe and also in Pacific.
                            He showed familiarity with our military operations both in Europe and in
                            Pacific.</p>
                        <p>Zhdanov was cordial and genial throughout the call which lasted an hour
                            and a half and as I left he hoped we would keep in close touch.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Moscow as my 32.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hamilton</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>