<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-28T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-28T19:00:00-05:00" n="638" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d638">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860D.01B11/5–2845: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the United States Representative in
                                Finland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-28T20:00:00-04:00">May 28,
                                    1945—8 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>85. Department’s 70, May 2 and 76, May 10<note n="56" xml:id="d638fn1">Telegram 76 not printed.</note> and your 71, March 2; 157, April
                                12<note n="57" xml:id="d638fn2">Telegram 157 not printed, but see
                                telegram 70, May 2, 6 p.m., to Helsinki, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> and 192, April 28. We have been giving
                            careful consideration to the several problems that have been brought up
                            by Gartz and to his repeated suggestions that a Finnish representative
                            be permitted to come to this country to discuss these questions. It is
                            believed that such discussion would be more effectively facilitated by a
                            permanent mission than by a special delegation and that the presence in
                            this country of some form of permanent Finnish representation short of
                                <pb facs="0662" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/> diplomatic representation
                            might in fact be of general usefulness in facilitating the disposition
                            of matters of current interest. We should appreciate your early comment
                            on this matter.</p>
                        <p>For your information the Department has expressed to the Hungarian and
                            Bulgarian Governments its willingness to receive from them an informal
                            governmental representation in this country without the restoration of
                            diplomatic relations. This decision was based on the view which the
                            Department has consistently maintained that the sending of
                            representatives to the three major Allied capitals by the former
                            satellite states during the armistice period is in each instance a
                            matter to be decided by the Government of the Allied country concerned.
                            There would seem to be even less objection in the case of Finland than
                            in the case of Hungary and Bulgaria. Should your reaction be favorable
                            we would be disposed to authorize you to indicate to the Finnish
                            authorities the willingness of this Government to entertain any
                            proposals the Finnish Government may wish to make regarding the sending
                            of a Finnish representative to this country. Although such a
                            representative would not be accredited officially to this Government and
                            his presence here would in no sense imply a resumption of diplomatic
                            relations between the two countries, he would have access to the
                            American authorities and such facilities as would enable him in an
                            unofficial and informal way to represent Finnish interests in this
                            country. The appointment of any particular individual for this post
                            would, of course, be subject to the approval of this Government.</p>
                        <p>Sent to Helsinki; repeated to Moscow as Department’s 1167.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>