<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversations at the White House on August 22,
                        1945, Between President Truman and General de Gaulle
                    This copy of memorandum of conversations obtained
                        from the files of the Division of European Affairs is unsigned and its
                        authorship cannot be determined. Another account of the two conversations
                        written by Henri Bonnet is printed in Charles de Gaulle’s Mémoires de Guerre, vol. iii: Le Salut, 1044–1946, (Libraire Plon, 1959) pp.
                        550–553. On August 24 President Truman and General de Gaulle met at 3:30
                        p.m. for a further conversation; for memorandum by Bonnet of this
                        conversation, see ibid., p. 553.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d683</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">683</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-08-22T15:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-08-22T15:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-22T15:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-22T15:30:00-05:00" n="683" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d683">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.00/8–2245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversations at the White House on August 22,
                        1945, Between President Truman and General de Gaulle</hi>
                    <note n="87" xml:id="d683fn1">This copy of memorandum of conversations obtained
                        from the files of the Division of European Affairs is unsigned and its
                        authorship cannot be determined. Another account of the two conversations
                        written by Henri Bonnet is printed in Charles de Gaulle’s <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de Guerre</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Le Salut</hi>, 1044–1946, (Libraire Plon, 1959) pp.
                        550–553. On August 24 President Truman and General de Gaulle met at 3:30
                        p.m. for a further conversation; for memorandum by Bonnet of this
                        conversation, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 553.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1945-08-22T15:30:00">August 22,
                        1945, 3:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>The President had two conversations at the White House with General de Gaulle on
                    August 22. The first conversation was held in the afternoon following de
                    Gaulle’s arrival, and the second after dinner that evening. The following
                    persons were present at both conversations: <list>
                        <item>M. Bidault</item>
                        <item>Secretary Byrnes</item>
                        <item>Admiral Leahy</item>
                        <item>Ambassador Bonnet</item>
                        <item>Ambassador Caffery</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The first conversation was devoted to a general discussion of French economic
                    conditions, with particular reference to the possibility of cooperation on the
                    part of the United States, with the view of bettering the economic situation.
                    The President asked General de Gaulle about the French coal situation; told him
                    of his real concern about the coal shortage in Europe and reviewed the steps
                    which the United States Government has taken to endeavor to improve the
                    situation.</p>
                <p>General de Gaulle replied by outlining the progress which has already been made
                    to increase French coal production, which he said at present is about two-thirds
                    of pre-war production. He explained the difficulties which the French have had
                    to overcome to achieve this level of production and mentioned the lack of
                    transport, the lack of pit props, the fact that French miners have been
                    dispersed throughout France and Germany, the low calorie content of the diet of
                    the French people which resulted in a decreased output of the mines, and the
                    wornout condition of much mining machinery and equipment. He said <pb facs="0720" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> that, while he is optimistic over the
                    possibility of further increasing French coal production to the pre-war level,
                    this will take a considerable time and will necessitate certain assistance.</p>
                <p>The President and the Secretary expressed to General de Gaulle the desire of the
                    United States to aid France to increase coal production, and said that French
                    requests for mining machinery and equipment should obtain a top priority. They
                    emphasized that requests for such machinery and equipment should be presented at
                    the earliest possible moment, if they had not already been made known. The
                    President and the Secretary also referred to the directions given to our
                    military authorities that all German miners within the jurisdiction of our
                    military authorities be employed in the mining industry and mentioned that those
                    who are prisoners in the United States are being returned to Germany.</p>
                <p>General de Gaulle said the French Government fully approved the directives which
                    the President had sent to General Eisenhower some time ago concerning the
                    exploitation of the German coal mines. He expressed the hope that the British
                    Government, if it had not already done so, would also approve the President’s
                    proposal. He added that for France it was a matter of vital necessity to obtain
                    German coal as reparation.</p>
                <p>Before the end of the conversation, the President said that he wished in a
                    friendly way to draw General de Gaulle’s attention to the unfortunate effect
                    which had been produced by a number of unjustified criticisms directed against
                    the United States which had appeared in the French press. He also mentioned that
                    certain American business men had complained that they had been badly received
                    by members of the French Government in Paris when they had gone there in order
                    to endeavor to cooperate with French business and industry.</p>
                <p>General de Gaulle and M. Bidault replied that they believed that the information
                    which had been received in the United States concerning press attacks directed
                    against the United States had been very much exaggerated. They also made the
                    point that the French press, which had originated with the Resistance, was still
                    very “jeune”, and that it was often severely critical of the French Government.
                    Both General de Gaulle and M. Bidault said that in reality there was a sentiment
                    of profound affection for the United States and a very real desire to cooperate
                    with the United States, whose generosity toward France was much appreciated.</p>
                <p>The second conversation, held in the evening, began with General de Gaulle and M.
                    Bidault making several broad, general statements on some aspects of the
                    political picture in France. In reply to questions, they talked briefly about
                    the forthcoming elections and the policy pursued by the Communist Party.</p>
                <pb facs="0721" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/>
                <p>The German question was then raised by de Gaulle, who said that certain of the
                    decisions taken at Potsdam, where France was not represented, had given rise to
                    an apprehension that the German danger, which had been for the moment eliminated
                    as a result of Germany’s crushing military defeat, would perhaps be reborn at
                    some future time. He mentioned that, while an important part of German territory
                    in the East had been detached from Germany, the Potsdam communiqué<note n="89" xml:id="d683fn2">For text of communiqué, see <ref target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_1499">
                            <hi rend="italic">Conference of Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Potsdam</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                        1499</ref>.</note> had given no indication that similar measures would be
                    taken on Germany’s western frontier. He said, “The Rhine means for France
                    exactly what a river would mean to the United States which separated the latter
                    from an intermediate, neighboring country equally strong.” He went on to say
                    that all invasions of French territory from the east have always come through
                    the Rhineland and that, therefore, France should have a guarantee that this
                    would not occur in the future. He said that separation of the Rhineland from
                    Germany was a necessary geographic guarantee and that it was also a
                    psychological necessity for the French people.</p>
                <p>He also expressed apprehension of certain decisions which had been taken at
                    Potsdam with respect to the administration of Germany which appeared to be a
                    prelude to the reconstruction of a central German authority. He mentioned
                    particularly the proposed Secretaries of State who will be established at
                    Berlin, and added that Prussia had always been the motivating force of German
                    imperialism Should German unity be reestablished, it would be even more
                    dangerous than in the past, because Germany might then be under the influence of
                    a strong and powerful Slav bloc which was now being constituted in eastern
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>In reply the President and the Secretary observed that the German danger should
                    not be exaggerated. They said they had recently visited Germany and had seen
                    with their own eyes the extent of the destruction throughout the country.
                    Furthermore, Germany has suffered a very great loss in manpower. With this in
                    mind, and in view of the decisions taken at Potsdam relating to the reduction of
                    German industry to the point where it will only cover the immediate economic
                    needs of the country, the possibility of a new German menace seems somewhat
                    remote.</p>
                <p>General de Gaulle, in reply, admitted that Germany had become greatly enfeebled,
                    but also expressed the opinion that, despite the loss of Silesia, a unified
                    Germany would still have an enormous industrial potential if it retained the
                    Ruhr and that, therefore, France was desirous of seeing the Ruhr
                    internationalized. He recalled that after the last war the Allies had also taken
                    steps to assure the disarmament of Germany and the control and limitation of the
                    German military <pb facs="0722" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> machine.
                    Unfortunately, differences of opinion between the Allies after the end of the
                    last war allowed Germany to escape executing the clauses of the treaty and
                    permitted Germany to regain her military power. He added that there is no
                    absolute guarantee that there will not be future dissensions between the Allied
                    powers, which Germany will take advantage of to regain her strength. De Gaulle
                    said, “The very fact that Germany is weakened makes that country all the more
                    susceptible of becoming the political instrument of other Powers.” He expressed
                    the belief that Germany certainly will be tempted to play such a game.</p>
                <p>The President replied that after the last war the Allies had acted unwisely, and
                    that the United States for its part was determined not again to commit the same
                    errors. He observed that after the last war the German war industry was
                    reestablished with the complicity of industrialists of a number of Allied
                    countries. The archives of the Farbenindustrie, which came into our possession,
                    prove the extent of the complicity of British, American and French
                    industrialists. He went on to say that the United States has no intention of
                    financing German reparations as it had done after the last war. Since the United
                    States, and presumably the other Allies, do not intend to commit the same
                    errors, the possibility of the German menace is remote.</p>
                <p>The President expressed the view that the best guarantee of French security lay
                    in devoting all of France’s energies to the reconstruction of France, and he
                    assured General de Gaulle that France could count on the friendship of the
                    United States in this task, since the United States strongly desired France to
                    become strong and prosperous once again.</p>
                <p>General de Gaulle expressed his appreciation for the foregoing remarks of the
                    President, but reverted to the question of Germany’s western frontier and said
                    that the left bank of the Rhine, which consisted of a variety of different
                    geographic regions which he said had never been united, should definitely be
                    taken away from Germany. He also repeated his desire to have the Ruhr placed
                    under an inter-Allied administration.</p>
                <p>The President and the Secretary replied to General de Gaulle that the primary
                    requisite for world security is understanding of the Allies working together in
                    an effective international organization. Furthermore, the atomic bomb will give
                    pause to countries which might be tempted to commit aggressions. The President
                    then said that above all the world needs an economic restoration. He added that
                    all countries are seeking aid from the United States, and that it is obviously a
                    physical impossibility for the United States to extend to all these countries as
                    much aid and assistance as they would like to <pb facs="0723" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/> receive. Nevertheless, the President assured General de
                    Gaulle that France will certainly receive favorable consideration.</p>
                <p>Regarding the Ruhr, the President and the Secretary mentioned that in the last
                    days of the Potsdam conversations, the USSR had on several occasions brought up
                    the question of its internationalization with participation of Russian troops in
                    the occupation of the Ruhr, but the American delegation had avoided discussing
                    the matter.</p>
                <p>The President took occasion to say that France and the United States have always
                    been friends, and the President expects this fruitful friendship to continue. He
                    told General de Gaulle that the United States believes that it is in its own
                    interest to see France restored to prosperity and well-being. General de Gaulle
                    expressed appreciation for these views, but said that France is suffering from a
                    variety of ills. The President replied, “We want to help cure them.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
