<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-16T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-16T15:00:00-05:00" n="857" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d857">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/11–545: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Representative in Hungary</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-16T15:00:00-05:00">November
                                    16, 1945—3 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>684. ReMistel 868 Nov. 5. You may say in reply to PriMin’s note of
                            November 3 on subject of Hungarian Army that regulation of strength and
                            organization of Army in interim period before conclusion of peace treaty
                            is properly matter for ACC, where Gen Key will make known views of this
                            Govt, and that you are not in a position to express to Hungarian Govt at
                            this time US views on points raised by PriMin’s note or to make specific
                            request of ACC to suspend reduction of Army as PriMin suggests.</p>
                        <p>War Dept has requested Key’s recommendations on nature of military
                            clauses for Hungarian peace treaty (Warx–80529, Nov. 1<note n="66" xml:id="d857fn1">Not printed.</note>). Question of strength of
                            Hungarian Army in interim period is closely connected with that of its
                            peacetime strength in view of Article I (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) of
                            Armistice Agreement which provided that “On the conclusion of
                            hostilities against Germany, the Hungarian Armed Forces must be
                            demobilized and put on a peace footing under the supervision of the
                            ACC”.</p>
                        <p>Preliminary view of Dept and War Dept on interim strength of Hungarian
                            Army (reMistels 851, 853 Nov 2<note n="67" xml:id="d857fn2">See footnote
                                55, <ref target="#pg_903">p. 903</ref>.</note> is that it need not
                            be any larger than is needed for the maintenance of internal order, and
                            that the ACC (all three Reps participating) should determine the size of
                            the armed force, in addition to the regular police forces, necessary for
                            that purpose. Limitations fixed now would of course be subject to change
                            by ACC at later date in light of reduction of Soviet forces in Hungary
                            or other circumstances.</p>
                        <p>This tel has been cleared with War Dept. Please make it available to Gen
                            Key.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>