<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-10T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-10T19:00:00-05:00" n="870" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d870">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">864.6363/12–1045: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Representative in Hungary</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-10T19:00:00-05:00">December
                                    10, 1945—7 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>808. Your 819 Oct 24.<note n="93" xml:id="d870fn1">Not printed; it
                                reported on a joint election manifesto of October 24 issued by the
                                leadership of the Smallholders, Social Democratic, Communist and
                                National Peasant Parties; the manifesto pledged, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, the transfer to state control of underground
                                national resources and of power producing plants
                                (864.00/10–2445).</note> When an appropriate occasion arises please
                            inform the Hungarian Govt that while this Govt of course does not object
                            to the nationalization of natural resources by a sovereign state in
                            accord with its own laws, it feels that Hungary should not take such a
                            step affecting foreign owned property while that country is under an
                            armistice regime. This consideration is specially valid in respect to
                            the substantial American investment in petroleum property in Hungary
                            which, according to Article XIII of the armistice, the Hungarian Govt is
                            obligated to return in complete good order but which it has not yet
                            restored to its American owners.</p>
                        <p>This Govt furthermore feels that if the Hungarian Govt undertakes an
                            extensive program of nationalization, subsequent to the signing of a
                            treaty of peace, should it be obvious at that time that it would not be
                            in a position to make immediate, effective and adequate compensation in
                            free exchange for American-owned property expropriated, such action
                            would inevitably present the possibility of conflict with the obligation
                            which the US Govt has to protect the interests of its nationals.<note n="94" xml:id="d870fn2">Telegram 1105, December 15, 1945, 6 p.m.,
                                from Budapest, reported that a note had been sent to the Hungarian
                                Foreign Minister in the sense of the Department’s instructions. It
                                further reported that Hungarian Government nationalization program
                                pertained to mines and sources of electrical energy but excluded oil
                                properties. No specific request for the exemption of American-owned
                                coal mines from nationalization laws was planned unless specifically
                                instructed by the Department. (864.6363/12–1545)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>