<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Representative in Hungary ( (Schoenfeld) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-12-19T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-19T07:00:00-05:00" n="874"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d874">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">661.6431/12–1945: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Representative in Hungary</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-19T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 19, 1945—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 20—2:05 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1126. PriMin Tildy called today explaining he did so as courtesy for first time
                    since taking office in that capacity. He expressed grave concern about present
                    economic situation of Hungary and alluded to currency devaluation plan announced
                    today along lines reported mytel 1109, December 17.<note n="5" xml:id="d874fn1"
                        >Not printed; it reported that a plan to accomplish devaluation of currency
                        by affixing stamps to bank notes would be announced on December 19 and
                        completed by December 31 (864.515/12–1745). Budapest’s telegram 1129,
                        December 20, 1945, 5 p.m., reported that the Hungarian Government’s currency
                        stamping program had further undermined public confidence in the Hungarian
                        currency and had caused an acute shortage of currency on the eve of
                        Christmas (864.515/12–2045).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Tildy also informed me (mytel 1108, December 17<note n="6" xml:id="d874fn2">Not
                        printed; it reported that the Political Committee of the Hungarian National
                        Assembly was scheduled to meet on December 20 to consider ratification of
                        the Soviet-Hungarian economic collaboration agreement
                        (661.6431/12–1745).</note>) that political committee of National Assembly is
                    expected tomorrow to recommend ratification of Soviet Hungarian economic
                    collaboration agreement by adopting formula approved by Voroshilov taking
                    express cognizance of Hungarian Government’s declaration that economic and
                    commercial agreements with third countries will not be affected by agreement.
                    Further Tildy said Hungarian Government would convey notes to British and
                    ourselves this week in answer to our representations as to most favored nation
                    rights under our respective commercial treaties with Hungary and would give us
                    assurance that such rights will continue in force. Tildy volunteered statement
                    that formula chosen in recommending ratification is in accord with American
                    Government objective as made known at Moscow and here of tripartite cooperation
                    in dealing with Hungarian economic situation. He added he hoped ratification of
                    agreement would give Hungary breathing spell.</p>
                <pb facs="0938" n="926" xml:id="pg_926"/>
                <p>I took opportunity of Tildy’s visit to intimate to him (urtel 823, December 13)
                    that as previously stated to Hungarian representatives, we consider it essential
                    to approach broad aspects of economic problem in Hungary on tripartite basis. I
                    added for his personal information only that we had proposed this matter be
                    considered by ACC with view to prompt creation of commission within ACC to
                    examine economic and financial position. To his inquiry whether ACC would take
                    such action I answered our proposal had been made so recently that I was not yet
                    informed of decision. I may add for Department’s information that Col. Townsend
                    informed us today he has made proposal as instructed but does not expect meeting
                    of ACC scheduled for tomorrow to take place in view of Gen. Key’s illness and
                    since recent practice has been to dispense with formal meetings of ACC. In any
                    case it would have been unliklely that this matter could be included in agenda
                    for tomorrow’s scheduled meeting.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, repeated to Moscow as 140 and to London as No. 74.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
