<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-21T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-21T13:00:00-05:00" n="876" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d876">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">661.6431/12–2145: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Representative in Hungary</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Budapest</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-21T19:00:00+01:00">December
                                    21, 1945—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received December 23—1:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1138. When handing me note quoted in mytel 1135 today ForMin said
                            Hungarian Government’s decision to proceed with ratification of Soviet
                            Hungarian economic collaboration agreement was designed to meet wishes
                            of USSR for removal of an obstacle in Hungarian Soviet relations which
                            had somewhat “chilled” those relations. Hungarian Government had
                            received assurances from Soviet Minister here that ratification would
                            clear the way for active assistance by USSR in present economic
                            distress. To my inquiry whether Soviet Minister had indicated what form
                            Soviet assistance would take for rehabilitation of Hungary ForMin
                            replied these assurances were thus far only on the political level and
                            had not been accompanied by any offer of study or recommendation of
                            concrete measures on part of Soviet economic experts. Hungarian
                            economists he said remain very skeptical that Soviet technical
                            assistance can produce desired results. There was no reason to believe
                            Soviet economists and other experts had even approached the problem of
                            Hungarian rehabilitation.</p>
                        <p>Gyöngyösi intimated definitely that Soviet Government does not favor any
                            effort to bring about tripartite examination of Hungarian economic
                            situation with view to remedial action.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department repeated to London as 76 and to Moscow as 147.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Schoenfeld</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[During the Moscow Conference of Foreign Ministers, December 16–26,
                                1945, agreement was reached by the United States, the United
                                Kingdom, and the Soviet Union with respect to the procedures to be
                                followed in preparing peace treaties with Italy, Rumania, Bulgaria,
                                Hungary, and Finland. During the Conference, the situation within
                                Hungary was also discussed, particularly at the meeting of the
                                Foreign Ministers on December 22 at noon and the meeting between
                                Secretary Byrnes and Generalissimo Stalin on December 23 at 5 p.m.
                                For documentation regarding the Conference, see <ref target="frus1945v02#pg_560">volume II, pages 560</ref> ff. For
                                the Report of the Conference of the Foreign Ministers, issued as a
                                communiqué on December 27, 1945, see telegram 4284, December 27 from
                                Moscow, <ref target="frus1945v02#pg_815">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, page 815</ref>.]</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>