<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State to President Truman</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d949</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">949</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="949"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d949">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/6–3045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d949fn1">Memorandum was approved by the President on July 1,
                        1945.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-30">June 30,
                            1945</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Revision of Italian Armistice Terms</p>
                <p>In accordance with your and President Roosevelt’s directives with regard to
                    Italy, our objective is to strengthen Italy economically and politically so that
                    the truly democratic elements of the country can <pb facs="1022" n="1010"
                        xml:id="pg_1010"/> withstand the forces that threaten to sweep them into a
                    new totalitarianism. Italian sympathies naturally and traditionally lie with the
                    Western democracies, and, with proper support from us, Italy would tend to
                    become a factor for stability in Europe. The time is now ripe when we should
                    initiate action to raise Italian morale, make a stable representative government
                    possible, and permit Italy to become a responsible participant in international
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>The anomalous status of cobelligerent and unconditionally surrendered enemy has
                    hampered every effort, both by the British and ourselves as well as by Italy
                    herself, to improve her economic and political situation. This anomaly can be
                    resolved drily through the negotiation of a definitive peace treaty which has
                    been urged by the British Government but which will require several months.
                    Meanwhile, the Italian internal situation and our own efforts would be greatly
                    facilitated by some immediate interim arrangement whereby the agencies of the
                    Allied Governments would have a clear-cut policy directive and the Italian
                    Government would be accorded tangible recognition of Italy’s substantial
                    contribution towards the defeat of Germany.</p>
                <p>Only on a military level, without reference to treaty-making bodies, does an
                    interim agreement seem immediately feasible. Revision of the armistice terms
                    after consultation with Great Britain and the USSR is suggested for that reason
                    and also because of mounting pressure for their publication which, unless
                    accompanied by an announced improvement in Italy’s status, would have a
                    demoralizing effect inside Italy, would lead to agitation by groups in this
                    country, and might well be exploited against us by certain foreign powers;</p>
                <p>It is therefore recommended that the armistice terms be revised immediately so as
                    to terminate all provisions save those required to <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Cover military requirements.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Safeguard proper settlement of territorial disputes.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Implement the tripartite pledge concerning democratic
                            government.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Safeguard Allied rights pending the final treaty.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
