<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-17T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-17T08:00:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/9–1754: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Norway</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_STRONGLC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Strong</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d67fn1">Repeated to London, Bonn, and Paris;
                                pouched to Copenhagen.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-17T14:00:00+01:00">September
                                    17, 1954—2 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>195. 1. British Ambassador queried last night re Foreign Office report of
                            Norwegian interest in possibility joining revised Brussels Pact. London
                            telegram 1317, September 15 to Department.<note n="2" xml:id="d67fn2">Not printed; it informed the Department of State that Norway
                                “surprised and greatly pleased” the British by exhibiting interest
                                in the possibility of joining a revised Brussels Agreement
                                (740.5/9–1454).</note> He opined this report based on exploratory
                            conversation at initiative Norwegian Ambassador London some days ago.
                            Since then Norwegian Government had considered possibility joining
                            revised Brussels Pact and related matters at Cabinet meeting September
                            14. British Ambassador saw <persName corresp="#p_LANGEHM1">Lange</persName> late that day and was given résumé Norwegian
                            thinking.</p>
                        <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_LANGEHM1">Lange</persName> told British
                            Ambassador basic premise Norwegian thinking was that new formula for
                            participation German Federal Republic in West European Defense system
                            must be acceptable to France. Norway believes best formula would be
                            admission German Federal Republic to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> with safeguards on German rearmament. If this
                            impracticable inclusion German Federal Republic in Brussels Pact may be
                            workable alternative. Norway foresees two possibilities here. (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) concomitant German membership in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and pact with safeguards on German
                            rearmament provided through pact arrangements and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) German adherence to pact only as transitional arrangement.
                            In either case Norwegian Government would be willing consider adherence
                            Norway to Brussels Pact if this would contribute to solution of problem.
                            Norway could not however join revised pact if revisions gave it
                            supranational character. Also, Norway would require assurance that
                            revised pact would not alter existing <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> structure providing separate northern European
                            command.</p>
                        <pb facs="0156" n="1224" xml:id="pg_1224"/>
                        <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_LANGEHM1">Lange</persName> also told British
                            Ambassador he had been unable consult Danish Government owing latter’s
                            preoccupation with economic difficulties. He thought Danes would follow
                            Norwegian lead in joining pact but if not Norway was prepared act
                            alone.</p>
                        <p>4. Later last night <persName corresp="#p_SKYLSTADRIB1">Skylstad</persName>, Secretary-General Norwegian Foreign Office,
                            was queried re Norwegian attitude toward possible resuscitation of
                            Brussels Pact as device for bringing German Federal Republic into west
                            Europe and defense system. It was not disclosed to him that this Embassy
                            already had information from British sources. He on his part did not
                            disclose that this matter had been subject of recent Cabinet
                            consideration. He did review Norwegian position along lines of paragraph
                            2 above.</p>
                        <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_SKYLSTADRIB1">Skylstad</persName> made two
                            further points. As practical matter Norwegian adherence to Brussels Pact
                            could hardly be of great significance as Norway had no military strength
                            to contribute outside its own borders. Importance if any of Norwegian
                            adherence would be psychological in terms of (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                            allaying French fears of being associated with Germans in small group of
                            nations and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) easing German acceptance of
                            limitations on its armaments which could be applied also to Norway and
                            other peripheral countries. Second point was that possibility of Norway
                            joining pact had not been discussed with Storting. <persName corresp="#p_SKYLSTADRIB1">Skylstad</persName> believes there would
                            be considerable Storting resistance to this move.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_STRONGLC1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Strong</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>