<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF
                            370</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the
                                Office of European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MOOREBT1"><hi rend="italic">Moore</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d97fn1">The source text was circulated to members of the U.S. Delegation to
                                the Nine-Power Conference as document <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> Memo 29.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-09-27">September
                                    27, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BOWIERR1">Bowie</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MOOREBT1">Moore</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HUGHESJC1">Hughes</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Colonel <persName>Richardson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ANDERSONFL1">Anderson</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary said that he would like to have General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName>’s views on the
                            problem raised by the French in their memorandum, namely an armaments
                            pool. He said that our preliminary thinking on this subject suggested
                            that there were two main purposes to be serviced by such a proposal.</p>
                        <p>One would be the delimitation of certain areas, or zones, in which
                            certain types of production would be prevented or limited, for example
                            atomic weapons. These zones would be drawn in accordance with strategic
                            and military considerations since the German territory would be included
                            in the forward area. The proposal would also serve a political purpose
                            by prohibiting or limiting German production of strategic weapons.</p>
                        <p>The second main purpose would be a rationalization of arms production
                            within the territories covered, thereby serving an economic, as well as
                            a political, purpose. The thought would be to lower costs of production
                            of certain types of equipment in efficient plants, and at the same time,
                            make it impossible for any one country to provide a balanced arms
                            program independently of its neighbor.</p>
                        <p>As we analyzed French motives at the conference, they were concerned
                            about two main points; they wished to involve the U.K. as deeply as
                            possible on the Continent and they were concerned to limit German
                            control of an independent military potential. Some form of arms pool
                            would help to meet the second preoccupation, although it was clear that
                            the British attitude was such that it would do little to meet the first.
                            It was probably true also that the French had ulterior motives with a
                            view to getting control over the allocation of arms orders for the
                            benefit of French industry. However, it should be possible <pb facs="0214" n="1282" xml:id="pg_1282"/> to arrange a scheme which
                            would provide safeguards against this danger.</p>
                        <p>In reply, General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> recounted his conversation with Monsieur
                                <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFP1">Mendes-France</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d97fn2">For a summary of <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName>’s meeting with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFP1">Mendès-France</persName> on
                                Sept. 16, see telegrams 248, 250, and 251 from Paris, Sept. 16, <ref target="#pg_1200">pp. 1200</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1201">1201</ref>, and <ref target="#pg_1202">1202</ref>,
                                respectively.</note> in which he pointed out that an arms pool was
                            not the most satisfactory method of meeting the French desire to control
                            German military strength. He pointed out to Monsieur <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFP1">Mendes-France</persName> that, in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, we had a going concern already set
                            up to provide certain safeguards for France. He listed these as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Through the Infrastructure Program, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> controlled the pipelines through which fuel
                                    for aircraft must flow in the event of future war, and without
                                    this fuel German forces would have no aircraft support and thus
                                    could not fight independently.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Under <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, a pooling of
                                    reserve supplies and stocks was being worked out, so that no one
                                    country would be able to fight for very long in the absence of
                                    control over these reserves.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> had integrated
                                    arrangements for air defense which, for military reasons, must
                                    be operated from one source through an integrated radar
                                    network.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The International command structure under <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would provide a tip-off in
                                    the event that any one Member country initiated a process of
                                    pulling out its own forces for aggressive purposes.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>He said that to improve and strengthen these controls over international
                            forces, <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> would need to have its
                            powers strengthened and defined by Council action, but that this should
                            be relatively easy to provide by international agreement. Monsieur
                                <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFP1">Mendes-France</persName> had
                            replied that a program of the kind outlined by General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> would be difficult to
                            sell politically in France. German [<hi rend="italic">General</hi>]
                                <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> said that
                                <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss>’S experience in talking with
                            various groups of Frenchmen suggested that such a program could be sold
                            if it were properly explained to the average Frenchman. He said further
                            that the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> had failed in part because
                            of opposition from French military officials. These same officials,
                            including General <persName corresp="#p_JUINAP1">Juin</persName>, would
                            support a proposal of the kind General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> had made. He said
                            that <persName corresp="#p_MENDESFP1">Mendes-France</persName> wanted
                                <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> to accept responsibility for
                            the inspection of German factories. This would be impracticable since
                                <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> had no personnel for this
                            purpose and it would be politically impossible for them to get into this
                            field.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary pointed out that, if <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> were given increased authority by Council action, the
                            Council could only remove this authority by a unanimous vote, and that
                            this should help to satisfy French fears. General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> agreed and pointed
                            out that a <pb facs="0215" n="1283" xml:id="pg_1283"/> Frenchman,
                            General <persName corresp="#p_JUINAP1">Juin</persName>, would administer
                            these <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> controls insofar as they
                            relate to ground forces in the central sector. The air force commander
                            in this sector is also a Frenchman, General <persName corresp="#p_CHARPENTIERP1">Charpentier</persName>.</p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_GRUENTHERAM1">Gruenther</persName> felt
                            that the best tactic with respect to an arms pool would be to ask the
                            French questions about their plan. The Germans, including
                                Mr.______________,<note n="3" xml:id="d97fn3">The name was left
                                blank in the source text.</note> have no knowledge of the details.
                            He said that the <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> analysis
                            suggested that the basis of the French proposal was the so-called Lapie
                            Plan, developed in 1951 to deal with the need for greater integration in
                            aircraft procurement. He suggested that this plan provided the germ of a
                            program which would be acceptable and which could be developed by the
                            experts. It was pointed out that any plan would require some formula for
                            making the basic decisions, such as the voting procedure set forth in
                            the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> Treaty. Perhaps such a formula
                            could be worked out under the Brussels Treaty. The Secretary felt that
                            it was important to develop some set of counter-proposals, possibly by
                            agreement with the <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                            countries, so that the French could not say that there was only
                            destructive criticism of their proposal. It was agreed that we needed to
                            develop promptly the principles of an effective scheme, so that we could
                            use them informally in our discussion with other Delegations.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>