<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <head>123. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JALS1" type="from">Alfred
                                Jenkins</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d123fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> Library,
                                National Security File, Country File, Korea, Vol. IV. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-07-26">July 26, 1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Bonesteel’s “Eyes Only” of July 21</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>State, Defense and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> have now all
                            agreed that a SNIE is desirable as Bonesteel recommends in paragraph 15
                            of the attached telegram. I am told that the terms of reference for the
                            SNIE should be arrived at before the week is over, that it will take
                            about two weeks to write it, and perhaps another two weeks to coordinate
                            and clear the results. We can expect the end product near the first of
                                September.<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2">
                                <ref target="#d130">Document 130</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> has requested,
                            however, that the Country Team message, also referred to in para. 15, be
                            held up until his arrival August 9.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Sam Berger</persName> was not inclined to
                            believe the situation was quite so serious as Bonesteel implies. Ben
                            Fleck observed that while the Country Team in Seoul was in substantial
                            agreement as to the seriousness of the <pb facs="0294" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/> situation, there was not full agreement as to what
                            should be done about it. Perhaps the SNIE will be beneficial to their
                            thinking as well as ours.</p>
                        <p>This seems to fit the picture of heightened tension all around Communist
                            China’s periphery. I doubt that these days North Korea is concerting its
                            plans in any way with Peking. They may, however, be taking advantage of
                            heightened tensions by acting concomitantly. In doing so, they can
                            indicate support for their Vietnamese ideological brothers, at least be
                            in line with China in its anti-American policy, and not be irritating
                            their Soviet friends in the process. They would seem to be out to cause
                            maximum trouble short of precipitating any real confrontation with
                            us.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">AJ</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment<note n="3" xml:id="d123fn3">Secret; Eyes Only. Repeated
                                    to Generals <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> in
                                    Washington; General Beach, <gloss target="#t_CINCUSARPAC1">CINCUSARPAC</gloss>, Hawaii; and General McKee in Japan;
                                    and passed to <persName>Bundy</persName> and Jorden at the White
                                    House; General Carter, Director, <gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss>; and <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>, Colby, and Jack Smith of the DDI at
                                        <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Korea</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-07-21T12:07:00+00:00">July 21, 1967,
                                        1207Z.</date>
                                </dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="strong">Telegram From the Commander in Chief, United
                                    Nations Command, Korea and the Commander of United States
                                    Forces, Korea (<persName corresp="#p_BGCHIII1">Bonesteel</persName>) to the Commander in Chief, Pacific
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName>)</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>KRA 1579. Following message passed to you for your info per <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>. Subject: Situation in Korea as of
                                mid-July 1967.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Events here since my last summary in my KRA 1374 dated 25 June
                                        1967<note n="4" xml:id="d123fn4">Not found.</note> have
                                    continued at a somewhat intensified pace.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Internal political affairs are well covered by current Embassy
                                    cables. There appears to be little hope for <gloss target="#t_DRP1">DRP</gloss> compromise with opposition and
                                    internal scars of June 8 elections are by no means
                                    healed.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In regard to North Korean actions, it becomes clearer as time
                                    moves on that a significant effort is underway to try to apply
                                    subversive war against the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>An interesting facet of this derives from review and analysis
                                    of <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> statements at Panmunjom and
                                    the parallel <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> propaganda line
                                    pushed out increasingly since last autumn for Pyongyang, Moscow
                                    and <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> embassies world wide. The
                                    theme has two parts. First is that <pb facs="0295" n="263" xml:id="pg_263"/> the imperialistic Yankees and their <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> puppets are trying to reopen
                                    the Korean War to take pressure off Vietnam and are flagrantly
                                    violating the armistice to provoke such an event—and the North
                                    Koreans are prepared for such a war so that if it occurs they
                                    will annihilate us. (Of note in this regard is that
                                    interrogations of recently captured agents reiterate <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> view I reported in my KRA 1795 of
                                    10 Nov 66<note n="5" xml:id="d123fn5">
                                        <ref target="#d99">Document 99</ref>.</note> that <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>’s evaluate US as so overextended
                                    in support Vietnam that we would be unable adequately to
                                    reinforce Korea in case of war.) The second part of propaganda
                                    theme is constant repetition of the big lie to the effect that
                                    none of the aggressive actions along <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> or in interior of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> are result of <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>
                                    activity. On contrary they reiterate monotonously that this is
                                    all due to South Koreans who are fighting to throw off Yankee
                                    yoke; i.e., it is an indigenous, Korea-style “Vietcong”
                                    activity. Absurdity of this in light repeated proof that all
                                    actions are by North Korean agent/guerrillas does not faze
                                    them.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>I consider this propaganda line the tip-off to the growing
                                    seriousness of North Korean intentions and capabilities. <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s seem seriously embarked on a
                                    large scale effort to try to develop a subversive war in <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and I think it now timely for
                                    us to conscientiously review the bidding on policies re North
                                    Korea, on how and what US and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s should be prepared to do if <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s escalate their subversive
                                    activities, and on priorities re <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>
                                    assistance to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>. North Koreans
                                    are arrogantly disavowing their flagrant and large scale
                                    violations of the armistice in what seems to be an effort to
                                    build acceptance by world public opinion for their
                                    intensification of hostile subversive acts with little or no
                                    risk to them for their de facto abrogation of the armistice.
                                    They are, in other words, carefully trying to make the US and
                                    rest of world accustomed as a matter of course to steadily
                                    increasing hostile action against <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> at no great risk to North Korea, in same way
                                    that in Vietnam the Geneva Accords and Vietnam <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> were eroded and bypassed by
                                    Communists in effort to delay timely and effective free world
                                    reaction and confuse the real issues. All this jibes with
                                    speeches and directives by Kim Il-sung from his March 65
                                    requirement for more effective espionage activities against
                                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, in context of how Mao’s
                                    Chinese Communists had “liberated” China by guerrilla action and
                                    how guerrillas in Vietnam were “successfully” carrying out their
                                    mission, through to his policy address of 5 October 1966, when
                                    he stressed the need for expanding preparations for war and
                                    adopting more aggressive tactics in anti-<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> operations to achieve earlier unification of
                                    the “fatherland.”<note n="6" xml:id="d123fn6">A discussion of
                                        the points made by Kim Il-sung in his October 1966 address
                                        is in Intelligence Note No. 94, February 2, 1968. (National
                                        Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files
                                            1967–69,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–4
                                        KOR)</note>
                                </item>
                                <pb facs="0296" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Intelligence indicates <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s have
                                    now trained in special unit schools and have available for
                                    dispatch some 1200 or more specially selected agent-guerrilla
                                    personnel. Some instructors have been in Vietnam. All are
                                    capable of conducting subversion, espionage, agitation, and
                                    supporting or carrying out militant guerrilla action. More are
                                    currently in training. In addition they have been carefully
                                    training for two years 500 subversives in each of the nine
                                        <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> provinces for guerrilla
                                    activity in a target <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    province assigned to each of the <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> provinces. This adds up to 5,000 or more
                                    specially trained thugs. We must also take into account their
                                    4,070-man reconnaissance brigade, a special-forces-type unit
                                    capable of being employed in guerrilla operations. Thus total
                                    available for future <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>
                                    subversive utilization adds up to about 10,000.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Current para-guerrilla action in interior of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> is now clearly confirmed to be
                                    test of ability to operate in current <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> environment and reconnaissance to support later
                                    large-scale real guerrilla action. We call current activity
                                    “para-guerrilla” because so far sabotage and widespread
                                    terrorism has not been practiced. One interrogated captive has
                                    said [garble—current] plan is to start active phase of sabotage,
                                    blowing up railroads, bridges and buildings, terrorism, etc.,
                                    next year but perhaps later this year if conditions permit.
                                    Another has said they may put in up to 400 agents this year.
                                        <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s appear at this time to be
                                    able to land para-guerrilla teams from their fast boats almost
                                    at will. [<hi rend="italic">5½ lines of source text not
                                        declassified</hi>]</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Detected para-guerrilla activity has now developed in three
                                    areas: Taebaek-san, West Chiri-san, and west of Ulsan. Every day
                                    there are sightings, contacts and firefights. Box score since 1
                                    January from actions in interior of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, excluding <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>
                                    and contiguous areas, is: firefights 63; North Koreans 81 KIA,
                                    33 captured; <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s (<gloss target="#t_ROKA1">ROKA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_KNP1">KNP</gloss> and civilians) 40 KIA, (including four or five
                                    farmers murdered), 88 WIA. These figures do not include another
                                    sizeable number of agents and collaborators picked up by normal
                                    police action. We have identified in action about a dozen teams
                                    of from seven to sixteen <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s each
                                    but are hard put to figure how many overall actually have been
                                    introduced so far, but might be as many as twenty. Rainy season
                                    now beginning will facilitate <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> infiltration if <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s wish to continue buildup. <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s with our support are giving
                                    them a really rough time and civil population is being
                                    extraordinarily helpful. With difficulties of getting food and
                                    of resupply, plus loyalty to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    of the people, the para-guerrilla effort so far this year has
                                    faced real difficulties.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Embassy and UNC for past year or so have taken position that
                                    internal security of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> against
                                    agent and subversive activity should be function of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> civilian security and police
                                    agencies, with <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> military
                                    supporting internal operations only when necessary while
                                    concentrating on trying to stop infiltration through <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> or by interceptions at sea. <pb facs="0297" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/> We have emphasized
                                    internal security should be prime responsibility of <gloss target="#t_ROKG1">ROKG</gloss> not UNC though we of course
                                    willing to help when needed. President Park now considers trend
                                    of <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> subversive activity
                                    potentially dangerous to sense of security of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> as well as to its economic
                                    investment programs and progress. He has in past week called
                                    together senior cabinet members a number of times and put heat
                                    on <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and Korean National Police
                                    to rapidly build up better internal security capability and to
                                    reduce required support by military. <gloss target="#t_KNP1">KNP</gloss> has long way to go, however, so I have
                                    authorized temporary use of one-and-a-third active divisions
                                    from <gloss target="#t_FROKA1">FROKA</gloss> reserve for
                                    counterguerrilla action in Taebaek-san and Chiri-san areas in
                                    effort to be so effective against <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> testing this year as to discourage next year’s
                                    intensification.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>Activities of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> 32nd
                                    division in Taebaek-san and 16th regiment of 8th division near
                                    Chiri-san in conjunction with <gloss target="#t_KNP1">KNP</gloss> has been pretty good so far but several suspect
                                    areas not covered. We are converting our annual US/<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> special forces exercise
                                    “Doksoori” from a guerrilla/counterguerrilla maneuver to a real
                                    counterguerrilla action to begin right after the rainy season
                                    and, with support from <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    troops and police, to sweep the extremely rugged parts of
                                    Chiri-san and other suspect areas. I consider this effort
                                    extremely important to assure no undetected <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> test enclaves survive the summer.
                                    Embassy [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                        declassified</hi>] and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s
                                    enthusiastically support the concept.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>Actions along <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> are also
                                    continuing with increasing viciousness with more planned,
                                    small-scale attacks being made. Firefights are occurring almost
                                    every night. A few days ago three more U.S. soldiers were
                                    killed. This year’s score along <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> to date: firefights 69; <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s 64 KIA, 2 captured; <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>/US 35 KIA, (including 6 U.S. KIA), 87 WIA.
                                    Irritating factor is that in last few weeks <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> along <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> are improving their kill ratio.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>Following show overall figures:</item>
                            </list>
                            <table cols="4" rows="7">
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="italic">1965</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="italic">1966</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="italic">1967 to date</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>DMZ incidents</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">42</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">37</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">286</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Firefights (DMZ plus interior)</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">29</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">30</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">132</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>NK, KIA</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">34</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">43</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">146</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>NK, captured after firefights</cell>
                                    <cell>not comparable</cell>
                                    <cell>35 (excludes police pick-ups)</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>ROK/US, KIA</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">40</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">39</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">75</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>ROK/US, WIA</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">49</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">34</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">175</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <list>
                                <label>13.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_MND1">MND</gloss> Kim under personal direction
                                    of President Park is effectively coordinating <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> military support to civil
                                    internal security <pb facs="0298" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                                    agencies. He repeatedly has asked our assistance to expedite
                                    deliveries of counterinfiltration materiel already programmed.
                                    He believes with me that we must be as nearly totally effective
                                    as possible in meeting this year’s testing by <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s to discourage next year’s
                                    effort, but also thinks as I do that overall <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> intentions and investment in
                                    resources are such that they will take greatly increased and
                                    classically destructive guerrilla actions next year regardless
                                    of hard time this year. He is afraid of possibility they may
                                    switch from testing to destructive action later this summer. I
                                    have told him we all are trying to speed up delivery of useful
                                    materiel such as fast boats, commo equipment, coast surveillance
                                    radar, searchlights, helicopters and miscellaneous items. He
                                    also hopes the new DD and <gloss target="#t_APD1">APD</gloss>s
                                    will be available for use against <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s 1968 activity.</item>
                                <label>14.</label>
                                <item>We are conscientiously trying to carry out instructions to
                                    keep Korean situation and <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>
                                    quiet and out of press sensationalism. But I believe increased
                                        <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> activity has reached point
                                    where this cannot be effected much longer. In fact, because of
                                        <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> propaganda theme mentioned
                                    above and their blatant violations of armistice, we should now
                                    bring it out in the open by a planned psy war and
                                    counter-propaganda campaign showing the scope and intentions of
                                        <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> action and falseness of
                                    their propaganda.</item>
                                <label>15.</label>
                                <item>Because of the Commie propaganda theme and because of
                                    clarifying intent of <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>s to
                                    energize subversive warfare, I reiterate recommendation that, in
                                    effect, an SNIE on North Korean subversive and conventional war
                                    capabilities and intentions be produced expeditiously, and
                                    additionally that <gloss target="#t_IRG1">IRG</gloss> actively
                                    review current policies regarding US/<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> collaborative effort and countermeasures we
                                    should be prepared to take. Embassy and my staff are working up
                                    a Country Team message with some recommendations in this
                                    regard.</item>
                                <label>16.</label>
                                <item>Have just heard of <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Clark
                                        Clifford</persName>’s and Gen. <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>’s mission to Asian/Pacific countries
                                    contributing forces to Vietnam.<note n="7" xml:id="d123fn7">The
                                        White House announced on July 20 that <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Clifford</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> would travel to
                                        Saigon to assess the war effort and visit the countries with
                                        troops in Vietnam for consultation and to discuss additional
                                        manpower needs. They spent August 2 and 3 in Seoul.</note>
                                    North Korean intensification of activity here may add to
                                    difficulties for <gloss target="#t_ROKG1">ROKG</gloss> to
                                    contribute significant additional combat forces to
                                    Vietnam.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>