<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>143. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v29p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recWMZ9EcUPmDYpbT" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="recco4TvraiYB3Tfh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007556"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radar</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d143">
                <head>143. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On January 6, 19678, President Pak presided over an emergency conference on
                    internal security at the Korean Army Headquarters at Wonju. In public statements
                    President Pak announced that the conference would focus on combating an expected
                    “tenfold increase in [North Korean] agent infiltration whose purpose is all out
                    guerrilla warfare.” The President reportedly called the meeting to discuss
                    counterinfiltration measures and to promote a new Civil Defense Bill scheduled
                    for legislative consideration. Approximately 160 senior officials from the
                    national and provincial governments, the military and police, and the Korean
                    Central Intelligence Agency attended the well-publicized conference. (Telegram
                    3308 from Seoul, January 9, National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59,
                    Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 23–7 KOR <pb
                        facs="0341" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>) The Embassy later reported that the meeting was
                    intended to generate a high level of publicity “to impress <gloss
                        target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> with readiness of <gloss target="#t_ROKG1"
                        >ROKG</gloss> to deal with infiltrators and other subversive activities, to
                    alert Korean people to seriousness of <gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss>
                    infiltration threat this spring, and to dramatize to Korean people preparedness
                    of Pres. Park and <gloss target="#t_ROKG1">ROKG</gloss> to protect security of
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>.” (Telegram 3447 from Seoul, January 17;
                    ibid.)</p>
                <p>In addition to furthering those objectives, the Embassy reported that the
                    government intended to use the Wonju meeting to “create public climate in favor
                    of controversial Civil Defense Bill.” (Ibid., and telegram 3308 from Seoul,
                    January 9; ibid.) The Embassy advised that the pending bill was “almost
                    unanimously condemned by press and academic groups for wide powers it gives
                    govt. and consequent fears for individual rights.” The political opposition had
                    voiced its intention to defeat the bill when it came before an upcoming special
                    session of the National Assembly. (Telegram 3308 from Seoul, January 9;
                    ibid.)</p>
                <p>The conference produced a revised counterinfiltration plan establishing
                    interagency control under the overall authority of provincial governors and the
                    Prime Minister to meet specific threats. According to the Prime Minister, the
                    program would advance Korean interests in “maintaining civilian control over
                    counter-infiltration operations” and in “limiting use of troops and their
                    contact with local population during operations.” (Telegram 3447 from Seoul,
                    January 17; ibid.) In the days following the conference the Minister of National
                    Defense outlined to the Korean press additional counterinfiltration measures,
                    including creating new rapid-response teams and helicopter and patrol-boat
                    units, installing new radar systems, as well as constructing a fence across and
                    defoliating the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. (Telegrams 3350 and 3476
                    from Seoul, January 11 and 18, respectively; both ibid.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
