<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>176. Telegram From the Embassy in Korea to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v29p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-02-12T06:47:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-02-12T06:47:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recQYPa4gvIIvO6oh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Operational control</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-02-12T06:47:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-02-12T06:47:00-05:00" n="176"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <head>176. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Korea</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Korea—<hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi>
                            Incident—<gloss target="#t_Cactus1">Cactus</gloss> IIa, <gloss
                            target="#t_Cactus1">Cactus</gloss> Seoul Cables, February 10 to February
                        28, 1968. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>; <gloss
                            target="#t_Cactus1">Cactus</gloss>. Attached to a February 12 memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>, that indicates the President saw
                        the telegram. Telegram 4178 from Seoul, February 12, also attached to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>’s memorandum is discussed
                        below.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Seoul</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-02-12T11:47:00+00:00">February 12, 1968,
                        1147Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4176. <gloss target="#t_VANTO1">VANTO</gloss> 5. Cyrus Vance, accompanied by
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>, General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGCHIII1">Bonesteel</persName>, and John Walsh, conferred with
                    President Park for <pb facs="0402" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> 5–1/2 hours today.
                    Prime Minister, Foreign Minister, Defense Minister and <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss> Director also participated.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2"
                        >Telegram 117405 to Seoul, February 18, and telegrams 117522, 117523, and
                        117531 to Seoul, all February 19, contain a detailed, five-part report of
                        this meeting. (National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central
                        Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 US/VANCE)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Lengthy session provided useful relief value for <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss> emotions. Tensions gradually eased as dialogue was established.
                    Park reiterated at length themes made familiar by reports of Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> and General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGCHIII1">Bonesteel</persName> in fatalistic and simplistic
                    terms. While the President’s sincerity was not in doubt it was evident that his
                    specific proposals were the product of emotion rather than finished staff
                    work.</p>
                <p>Park charged with deep conviction that <persName corresp="#p_KIS1">Kim
                        Il-Sung</persName> is on path of war. The rate of violation of the Armistice
                    Agreement has increased markedly. The attack on the Blue House designed to kill
                    him and his family and the seizure of the <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> were
                    acts of war. The North Koreans have thousands of trained infiltrators and
                    further serious penetrations are inevitable in the spring. They intend to harass
                    the South Korean people, disrupt the economy and, when the country is
                    sufficiently weakened, resort to all out war. They will only respect
                    counterforce. They should be warned of the consequences of further violations,
                    asked to apologize for past actions, and requested to promise not to violate the
                    armistice agreement in the future. In addition we should publicly state that any
                    future violations will be met by immediate retaliation. All courses of action in
                    the present situation are dangerous but Park did not believe that retaliation
                    would provoke the DRNK to war. Firmness and resolution are imperative in the
                    present situation. The US world position depends upon firmness in face of
                    Communist pressure. If we are weak here we will pay for it in the form of
                    Communist aggression elsewhere.</p>
                <p>On the Panmunjom issue, Park feared <persName corresp="#p_KIS1">Kim
                        Il-Sung</persName> would delay and stall the negotiations in order to
                    humiliate the US and therefore <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>. He wished to
                    know what the US would do under those circumstances in order to calm his people.
                    He was worried and displeased by the indications by high officials that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> could have been in North Korean territorial waters
                    and by Senator Mansfield’s recommendations that the issue be submitted to the
                        <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>. These statements and the absence of
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> participation at Panmunjom aroused
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> suspicions about the negotiations.
                    Nevertheless, he would not oppose the continuation of secret talks providing he
                    had an assurance that infiltration would stop.</p>
                <p>Throughout the lengthy discussion Vance calmly and sympathetically strove for a
                    dialogue with the President, probed for specificity, pointed out the weakness
                    and dangers of Park’s options, explained US <pb facs="0403" n="371"
                        xml:id="pg_371"/> policy, reiterated the commonality of US–<gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> interests, warned of the dangers of precipitate
                    and unilateral action, and sought for a common, satisfactory course of
                    action.</p>
                <p>While the jury remained out at the end of the session, the atmosphere was
                    friendly and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s appeared to recognize that
                    we would not agree to a policy of retaliation. Despite press reports to the
                    contrary, the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s did not raise issue of
                    revision of Mutual Defense Treaty or of seeking to disengage from the
                    operational control of CINCUNC. Clearly, however, we have much serious talk
                    ahead of us before we will know the outcome of this mission. We will submit a
                    draft communique tonight.<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">Telegram 4178 (<gloss
                            target="#t_VANTO1">VANTO</gloss> 7) from Seoul, February 12, stated that
                        the draft communique “will fall far short of <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                            >ROK</gloss> ambitions and a substantial wrangle is in the offing.” In
                        telegram 114006 to Seoul (<gloss target="#t_TOVAN1">TOVAN</gloss> 20),
                        February 12, the Department of State forwarded cleared language for use in
                        the communique. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 33–6 KOR N–US)
                        The Embassy later reported that “ten hours of exhausting exchanges were
                        required” to agree on the wording of the communique, with which neither side
                        was fully satisfied. (Telegram 4242 from Seoul, February 15, also telegram
                        4229 from Seoul, February 14; both ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 7 US/VANCE) The joint communique issued on February 15 is
                        in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 11, 1968, pp.
                        344–345.</note> Tomorrow morning we will meet with the Foreign and other
                    Ministers and probably in the late afternoon with the President.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
