<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="211" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                        <head>211. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_KNB1" type="from">Katzenbach</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d211fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 KOR S–US. Secret; Sensitive;
                                Nodis.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-12-23">December 23, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Review of United States Policy Toward Korea: Status Report</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Last February, upon his return from Seoul, Mr. <persName>Vance</persName>
                            recommended to you that we reassess our policy toward Korea. You asked
                            me to take responsibility for this task. This assessment has been going
                            forward under the direction and supervision of the Senior
                            Interdepartmental Group.<note n="2" xml:id="d211fn2">Reference is to the
                                study, “U.S. Policy Toward Korea,” June 15; <ref target="#d201">Document 201</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>As a result of the work, the issues are now well understood.<note n="3" xml:id="d211fn3">The <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> members met
                                to discuss the paper on policy toward Korea on September 19. A
                                September 9 Issues Paper and an undated Briefing Paper were prepared
                                in advance of the <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> meeting.
                                Copies of those documents as well as minutes of the <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> meeting are in the Johnson Library,
                                National Security File, Agency File, Senior Interdepartmental Group,
                                Vol. 7, 43rd Meeting, September 19, 1968 and National Archives and
                                Records Administration, RG 59, Senior Interdepartmental Group Files:
                                Lot 70 D 263.</note> A considerable amount of highly technical
                            analysis—economic, military and political—remains to be completed but
                            these studies, too, are now well under way.<note n="4" xml:id="d211fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> sent a memorandum
                                to <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> members on September 26
                                directing the initiation of an interagency study based on the issues
                                raised and points of agreement derived from the September 19 SIG
                                meeting. (Ibid.)</note> Thus, we should be able to present your
                            successor with incisive, well-grounded policy options and with detailed
                            program recommendations to carry out these options.</p>
                        <p>This memorandum is in the nature of an interim report—to tell you what we
                            have accomplished to date and what remains to be done.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Importance of Korea</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I need not dwell on the extent of our Korean involvement and its dangers.
                            Our intelligence both as to intent and capability needs
                                improvement,<note n="5" xml:id="d211fn5">A letter from <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>, November 30, discussing
                                options for an effective intelligence program in Korea as well as
                                similar documentation focusing on the intelligence issue are ibid.,
                                Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 KOR
                                S–US.</note> but it does seem clear that North Korea remains
                            aggressively bent on swallowing the South. Over the past year Pyongyang
                            has significantly stepped up its provocative actions. South Korean
                            patience is running thin. We are tied to South Korea’s defense by treaty
                            commitments and perhaps even more by history. Our military presence <pb facs="0488" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> in Korea still numbers over
                            50,000. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                declassified</hi>] Last year we provided some $350 million in
                            military and economic assistance (plus the special $100 million military
                            assistance appropriation you sought of the Congress).</p>
                        <p>We should be proud of our efforts in Korea. The Koreans have used our
                            assistance well. Their economy is growing at near fantastic rates and
                            the prospects for ultimate viability are excellent. Korean military
                            forces are among the best in the world, as their 50,000 troops in
                            Viet-Nam more than attest.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Our Objectives in Korea</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Our objectives in Korea are: <list>
                                <item>—To keep South Korea out of hostile hands;</item>
                                <item>—To reduce the probability of large-scale North-South
                                    hostilities;</item>
                                <item>—To maintain a stable compromise among the great powers with
                                    interests in Korea;</item>
                                <item>—To increase <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> ability to
                                    defend itself;</item>
                                <item>—To promote South Korean economic and political
                                    development;</item>
                                <item>—To encourage a greater Japanese contribution to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> security and prosperity.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Some Tentative Conclusions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The conclusion which I and the other members of the <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> draw from this record is this:</p>
                        <p>There must be no question about the strength and importance of our
                            commitment to the security of South Korea in the face of an aggressive
                            adversary. But, as time goes by, it is appropriate to reconsider the
                            question of whether our present posture decided many years ago is still
                            an optimal one for meeting our commitment.</p>
                        <p>The answer could well turn out to be that it is. But the SIG believes
                            that there is here a real and pressing question of national policy and
                            strategy which will bear further examination by the next
                            Administration.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—The Republic of Korea (<gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>) has
                                made great progress in all areas. Increasingly, she has the
                                strength—and should be encouraged—to stand on her own two
                                feet.</item>
                            <item>—Our knowledge about North Korean military capabilities is limited
                                and may not be altogether reliable. This raises questions about what
                                the military balance—with and without United States forces—actually
                                is and how, if necessary, it should be improved.</item>
                            <item>—Our present policy effectively ties down in Korea two United
                                States divisions, which are not available for use elsewhere. They
                                require substantial expenditures for support both in Korea and the
                                United States.</item>
                            <item>—Our present posture leaves us little choice as to whether and how
                                to become involved on the ground in the event large-scale
                                hostilities reoccur on the Peninsula.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0489" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                        <p>Whether or not we consciously change our strategy, the United States will
                            face important decisions in Korea over the next few years. Sooner or
                            later, the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions in Viet-Nam
                            will return home. We will have to make choices on the kinds of force
                            structures—both <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and U.S.—we should
                            maintain. The prospects for the Korean <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>—so essential to our defense policy toward Korea—are
                            uncertain and we need to consider whether to try to transfer this
                            program completely to the Defense Department budget. Some of our policy
                            options require considerable lead time (e.g. <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>), and the new Administration will have to act soon if
                            the United States wants to maintain these options.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Uncertainties</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>There are a number of uncertainties which hinder reaching definitive
                            conclusions on any changes in policy: <list>
                                <item>—First, as already indicated, our limited intelligence makes
                                    it difficult to estimate the precise nature of the threat to
                                    South Korea.</item>
                                <item>—Second, there is the even greater difficulty of determining
                                    the likely effect on North Korean, USSR, and Communist Chinese
                                    attitudes, intentions, and policies, of any change in our
                                    military posture.</item>
                                <item>—Third, the outcome in Viet-Nam may affect the general climate
                                    in East Asia including Korea.</item>
                                <item>—Fourth, the 1971 Korean Presidential election raises serious
                                    questions about the continuation of political stability in
                                    Korea.</item>
                                <item>—Fifth, our position in Japan or Okinawa—now essential to
                                    Korea’s defense—could well be eroded in coming years.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Some Key Issues</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The critical problem to resolve is whether it is possible to substitute
                            improved Korean combat forces in whole or in part for our forces now in
                            Korea and still maintain a combined <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>-U.S. strength adequate to provide deterrence and, if
                            necessary, deal with the likely military threats. This question in turn
                            raises a host of subsidiary questions.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—Is the United States combat presence, 15 years after the Korean
                                War, an irreplaceable element of deterrence against North Korean
                                attack?</item>
                            <item>—If our forces are reduced or withdrawn, will we be politically
                                able in the United States to reintroduce them should hostilities
                                again break out?</item>
                            <item>—How much of a South Korean defense is needed to replace United
                                States forces and what will it cost? What kind of United States
                                force capabilities would we want to keep in readiness against
                                certain major military contingencies such as a combined Chicom-North
                                Korean attack? [<hi rend="italic">1 line of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>]</item>
                            <item>—Is it feasible to reduce the margin of uncertainty about North
                                Korean military capabilities by a stepped-up intelligence
                                effort?</item>
                            <item>—What would be the effect of a United States troop withdrawal from
                                Korea on our position in Asia?</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0490" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/>
                        <p>In addition, there are several subsidiary questions: <list>
                                <item>—To what extent is a “trade-off” between US and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces compatible with our
                                    objectives for Korean political stability and
                                    development?</item>
                                <item>—Similarly, what share of the cost of its own military needs
                                    can we ask the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> to assume
                                    without impairing her now very favorable economic
                                    prospects?</item>
                                <item>—And, finally, how can we obtain the necessary funds to assist
                                    the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> in a multi-year program
                                    for the improvement of her forces?</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Remaining Efforts</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I have listed only some of the more fundamental problems involved in any
                            policy change. They are not easy to resolve. To deal with them in an
                            orderly manner we need a more detailed look at these and similar
                            problems. The <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss> has commissioned an
                            interagency group to assess them and to determine, as precisely as the
                            subject allows, the technical, and political feasibility, requirements,
                            costs, advantages and disadvantages, of various policy options in
                            Korea.</p>
                        <p>The end-product of our whole review effort will be alternative five-year
                            programs for <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and United States
                            forces and for United States economic and military assistance programs
                            which can serve as the basis for decision-making by the new
                            Administration.</p>
                        <p>Parenthetically, I am hopeful that the interagency study effort will also
                            shed light on how to improve our whole approach to integrated country
                            planning and programming in areas where security, economic, and
                            political considerations so greatly overlap.</p>
                        <p>The Deputy Secretary of Defense and the Deputy Director of Central
                            Intelligence concur in this memorandum.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Nicholas deB. Katzenbach</persName>
                                </hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>