<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>258. Memorandum From Secretary of State Rusk to President to President
                    Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v29p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="reccKWZw7wcZPbjV8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85111861"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Reconnaissance aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <head>258. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d258fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Korea—Pueblo Incident, Vol. Ib. Part A
                        (beginning February). Top Secret. A handwritten notation on the memorandum
                        indicates it was received on February 3. Although the memorandum is on
                        Department letterhead and is unsigned, presumably it is from <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1968-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                            notBefore="1968-02-02T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> Seizure—Possible Military Options</item>
                </list>
                <p>Attached are planning papers on four courses of action involving military
                    pressure in North Korea.<note n="2" xml:id="d258fn2">Not printed.</note> None of
                    these should be contemplated for employment in the current phase of
                    negotiations. They should be reserved for possible use after the current
                    negotiations at Panmunjom have clearly failed.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Air Reconnaissance over North Korea.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Sailing Banner into area where <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> was
                        seized.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Seizing a North Korean vessel.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Limited blockade of North Korean naval vessels.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Polish ship.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Reprisal.<note n="3" xml:id="d258fn3">The memorandum bears <persName
                                corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>’s handwritten notations. Next to
                            course of action 1, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> wrote:
                            “good sense—marginal.” Next to number 2, “risks less likely.” <persName
                                corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> wrote in numbers 5 and 6. The
                            former referred to seizure of a North Korean vessel under Polish flag of
                            convenience.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Number 3 has been cleared in the Korean Working Group; the others are still in
                    various stages of clearance.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is clear to me that each of these contemplated actions involves risks. The
                    numerical order in which they are listed above indicates a descending order of
                    preference in terms of combining minimum risk and maximum pressure.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Air Reconnaissance over North Korea is probably first in order of
                        preference, confined to the use of Black Shield. It would appear to the
                        North Koreans either as a form of pressure or as a threat of more forceful
                        action to come. They would not know which and this would increase their
                        anxiety. The risk of loss is low. The North Koreans would resent but
                        probably not publicize our intrusion into their air space unless they shot
                        down a reconnaissance aircraft.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Sailing <hi rend="italic">Banner</hi> along the North Korean coast with an
                        escorting force demonstrates our right and our willingness to do what we
                        were <pb facs="0620" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/> doing when <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pueblo</hi> was seized. We believe the risk of North Korea seizing the
                        Banner is zero; the risk of their attacking it with aircraft or missiles is
                        low. The presence of the escorting force and the knowledge (or suspicion)
                        that U.S. forces are prepared to react quickly to an attack on <hi
                            rend="italic">Banner</hi> would tend to deter such an attack and make
                        the North Koreans apprehensive. Despite the escort, however, there is a risk
                        of attack by aircraft or missiles with a possibility that <hi rend="italic"
                            >Banner</hi> would be sunk. Like the other courses of action listed, it
                        does not offer much prospect of producing the return of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pueblo</hi> and crew, but it does increase the pressure and tension in
                        the area.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>The seizure of a North Korean naval vessel is more risky since it would
                            probably be opposed by North Korean air and naval forces. It would be a
                            dramatic demonstration of our concern and determination, but it would
                            probably not greatly increase our bargaining power in obtaining release
                            of <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> and crew; in fact it would probably
                            reduce prospects of this. And unless we had exhausted the machinery of
                            the United Nations, our action could be properly denounced as
                            illegal.</p>
                        <p>If we wish to seize (or sink) a North Korean naval vessel, our best
                            chance might come during a fracas resulting from enemy attempts to
                            harass or sink <hi rend="italic">Banner</hi>.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>A limited blockade of North Korean naval vessels would quickly become a
                        “set-piece” operation on our part. North Korea could watch it, determine the
                        pattern, and pick the time and place for offensive action. If they decided
                        to do it, they could, almost certainly, sink an important US naval vessel,
                        such as a destroyer. We stand to lose much more than we gain by undertaking
                        actions which leave the initiative for counter-action to the enemy. There,
                        in his own backyard, we cannot afford to maintain enough force to prevent a
                        determined counter effort from succeeding. Even though we doubt that he
                        would risk it, we shouldn’t repeat the <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi>
                        incident, on a larger scale, by giving him the option of striking us again
                        at a vulnerable point.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Air Reconnaissance</hi>. Low key reconnaissance would be
                        designed to achieve needed information and concurrently keep the opposition
                        guessing as to our next move. This effort, limited to that reconnaissance
                        which we really need, and which the enemy will think is compatible with a
                        genuine military need, should be seriously considered. It should be of a
                        nature designed to minimize the probability of loss.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Sailing Banner</hi>. If we conclude that we must do
                            something visible at this time, sailing of <hi rend="italic">Banner</hi>
                            is probably as good as any other visible action.</p>
                        <p>If we do it, we should do it low profile, with little or no visible
                            force. A combat air patrol should be a safe distance away, in order of
                                <pb facs="0621" n="589" xml:id="pg_589"/> 50 miles, where it could
                            intervene if required but where it would be less likely to create an
                            incident. The surface escorts should be well over the horizon, clearly
                            out of sight of any vessels approaching <hi rend="italic">Banner</hi>
                            but able to intervene.</p>
                        <p>We shouldn’t undertake the operation at all unless we were prepared for
                            some significant consequences: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>If North Korea sinks or seriously damages <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Banner</hi>, we should be prepared to count this as an “Act
                                    of War.”</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>We should have plans in being, and have made a decision, in
                                    advance, to make a suitable military response to the sinking or
                                    serious damaging of <hi rend="italic"> Banner</hi>.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>These plans should include such actions as neutralization of
                                    the North Korean Air Force.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Seizing a North Korean Naval Vessel</hi>. As the attached
                        detailed planning indicates, this course is dangerous. We might fail; we
                        might suffer heavier losses than the enemy in the process. We probably
                        should not undertake this action unless we are looking for a small fight and
                        wish to use this action to cause one.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Limited Blockade of North Korean Naval Vessels</hi>. This
                        action is not recommended. It would be costly in resources, would be
                        unlikely to help retrieve the ship and crew, and leaves the US
                            vulnerable—<gloss target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> could pick the time and
                        place and hope to sink a significant US vessel such as a destroyer. It is
                        unlikely that North Korea would do this; however, if it happened, our legal
                        position for retaliation would not be particularly good and we would have
                        suffered another blow to our prestige.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
