<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-02-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                        <head>261. Memorandum From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to President <persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d261fn1">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 33–6 KOR
                                N–US. Secret; Nodis. Drafted by <persName>Bundy</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-02-03">February 3, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Second Meeting at Panmunjom</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The meeting will be held at 7:00 p.m. tonight, our time, 9:00 a.m.
                            February 4, Korea time.<note n="2" xml:id="d261fn2">The North Koreans
                                asked for a meeting on February 3. The U.S. principals countered
                                with the later time and date, which were accepted, because of
                                preparational and logistical problems created by the short notice
                                given by the North Koreans as well as uncertainty as to the latter’s
                                motives for suddenly requesting a meeting. In addition, as <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> noted, requesting a delay of
                                at least 1 day after having received an invitation was standard
                                procedure when scheduling <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss>
                                meetings. (Telegram 3917 from Seoul, February 3; ibid.) A chronology
                                of events in Washington the evening of February 2 and Seoul at the
                                corresponding time was sent to President <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>. (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> to the President,
                                February 3; Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File,
                                    Korea—<hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> Incident, Vol. Ib, Part A
                                [beginning February])</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>We have sent Admiral <persName corresp="#p_SRAJV1">Smith</persName> a
                            detailed statement for him to make.</p>
                        <p>He will again ask for the names of the injured and wounded.</p>
                        <p>The North Korean chief effort we think will be to use the alleged
                            confession of Lieutenant Harris which they issued yesterday to support
                            their case that the vessel was in territorial waters. This confession
                            includes several references to violations and one specific
                            latitude-longitude position inside their waters.</p>
                        <p>We are sending a special guidance to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_SRAJV1">Smith</persName> to handle this “evidence”.</p>
                        <p>The minimum condition the North Koreans are going to attach to the
                            release of the crew and possibly the vessel is beginning to take shape.
                            What they seem to be shooting for is a signed statement by us admitting
                            the vessel violated their waters. They may initially attach other
                            conditions, such as espionage, hostile and provocative acts, but might
                            settle for the single admission.<note n="3" xml:id="d261fn3">When
                                informed of the meeting, President Pak asked only that the United
                                States adopt a “strong posture” with the North Koreans. (Telegram
                                3904 from Seoul, February 3; National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 33–6 KOR N–US)</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>