<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>343. Telegram From the Embassy in Korea to the in Korea to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v29p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d343</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">343</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-06-25T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-06-25T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-06-25T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-06-25T05:00:00-05:00" n="343"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d343">
                <head>343. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy</gloss> in Korea to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d343fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> JAPAN–KOR <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Confidential.
                        Repeated to Tokyo and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss
                            target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Seoul</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-06-25T19:00:00+09:00">June 25, 1964, 7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1729. 1. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CICI1">Chong Il-kwon</persName>
                    told me June 25 he is now actively considering possibility achieving “limited”
                    normalization <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>-Japan relations in period
                    immediately following <gloss target="#t_LDP1">LDP</gloss> election assuming
                        <persName corresp="#p_IH1">Ikeda</persName> again elected party president.
                        <persName>Chong</persName> envisages exchange full diplomatic missions and
                    simultaneous agreement on part of Japanese to liberalize imports from
                        Korea.<note n="2" xml:id="d343fn2">In response the Embassy in Tokyo reported
                        that with regard to “limited” or “partial normalization” the Japanese
                        Government “has always favored such a step and would welcome it now.” The
                        Japanese were also willing to accept a diplomatic mission, rather than a
                        full-scale embassy, in Korea. The imports question was a problem because the
                        Japanese were reluctant “to permit increased imports Korean marine products
                        as long as Rhee Line issue unresolved and because of opposition from Diet
                        members with ties to industries concerned.” (Telegram 3987 from Tokyo, June
                        29; ibid.)</note> Once normal diplomatic relations established under such
                    arrangement full settlement pending issues could proceed in less controversial
                    manner.</p>
                <p>2. <persName>Chong</persName> expressed belief it would not be possible secure
                    full settlement this year under present procedures. He was concerned that
                    indefinite postponement normalization would lead to growth of two Koreas concept
                    in Japan and greatly weaken <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> position.
                    Therefore wanted to push ahead quickly to limited goal and hoped for US
                    support.</p>
                <p>3. <persName>Chong</persName> believes overt participation by US in such a
                    limited settlement would ensure widest acceptance in Korea.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d343fn3">The Embassy noted Japanese wariness of overt U.S.
                        participation, which would have to be credibly justified to the Japanese
                        people, advising “that generally speaking the less overt US involvement the
                        better.” (Ibid.)</note> Opposition some time ago indicated willingness
                    accept diplomatic exchange and trade expansion as short-term goal and US support
                    would simplify govt’s task.</p>
                <p>4. <persName>Chong</persName> will discuss his proposal with President Pak and
                    meet with us again on this question if latter approves. I cautioned
                        <persName>Chong</persName> against possible press leaks. I told him we would
                    consider role for US once proposal is clearly defined.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> We agree with Prime Minister’s judgment that
                    it is difficult conceive of early progress on overall normalization and favor
                    further exploration concept of limited normalization timed for late summer. At
                    this stage we would welcome Dept and Embassy Tokyo views. Are we prepared to
                    indicate our support through direct action, e.g, high level US visit to Tokyo or
                    Seoul to help achieve early limited <pb facs="0794" n="762" xml:id="pg_762"/>
                    agreement? What would be Japanese reaction to such proposal and to overt US
                    involvement?</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
