<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-03-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                        <head>35. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d35fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EAP1">EAP</gloss> Files: Lot 90 D
                                99, SNIE 10–4–65. Top Secret; Controlled Dissem; Limited
                                Distribution. According to a note on the cover sheet, the Central
                                Intelligence Agency and the intelligence organizations of the
                                Departments of State and Defense and of the National Security Agency
                                participated in the preparation of this estimate. All members of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> concurred with this
                                estimate on March 19 except the representatives of the Atomic Energy
                                Commission and the Federal Bureau of Investigation, who abstained on
                                the grounds that the subject was outside their jurisdiction.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">SNIE 10–4–65</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-03-19">March 19, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="strong">PROBABLE COMMUNIST REACTIONS TO DEPLOYMENT<lb/>OF A
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> COMBAT DIVISION FOR BASE
                                SECURITY DUTY IN SOUTH VIETNAM</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">The Estimate</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We do not believe that the introduction of one <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> combat division into South Vietnam
                                for static defense purposes would provoke Communist China, North
                                Korea, or North Vietnam overtly to invade South Korea or South
                                Vietnam. Neither do we believe that it would in itself change
                                Communist attitudes toward negotiations, or lead to a slackening of
                                the insurrection in South Vietnam.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The main question is what interpretation the Communists would put
                                on the introduction of the full <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                combat division. They would almost certainly estimate that it would
                                not in itself significantly alter the military situation. They might
                                consider, however, that it portended a substantial further buildup
                                of foreign forces—e.g., Chinese Nationalist, Thai, Philippine, and
                                US—for ground combat. Whatever their estimate on this point, they
                                would try to discourage such a buildup. To this end they would
                                increase their propaganda, and again accuse the US of recklessly
                                expanding the war. They would probably <pb facs="0097" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/> employ the theme of “US use of Asians to fight
                                Asians” and attempt to stir up troubles between the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces and the Vietnamese.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The Communists would probably supplement their propaganda with
                                some sorts of action. The North Koreans would almost certainly
                                attempt to arouse protests in South Korea against the export of
                                South Korean forces. They might make threatening military movement
                                within North Korea or along the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>,
                                designed to reinforce any doubts the South Korean or other
                                governments might have about the wisdom of thus diverting their
                                troops. We think it unlikely that North Korean ground force
                                “volunteers” would be sent to North Vietnam, though it is possible
                                that North Korean technicians or anti-aircraft personnel (possibly
                                SAM operators) might be brought in. In South Vietnam, Viet Cong
                                terrorist efforts and military harassment might be directed against
                                the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces in the hope that
                                casualties would cause discontent in South Korea and also serve as a
                                warning to other potential foreign contingents.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Communist China might attempt to scare off further US-initiated
                                strengthening moves in South Vietnam by deploying Chinese forces
                                southward toward the North Vietnam border. We do not believe,
                                however, that China would do much else. It would be unlikely to
                                counter by sending a Chinese division to the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> because it would be unneeded there and probably
                                uninvited. If it had decided for independent reasons, to send more
                                or less overt anti-aircraft or fighter plane units, it might seize
                                upon the introduction of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                division in the South as further justification for doing so.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The introduction of a <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> division
                                would add one more complication to an already difficult situation
                                for Moscow. It would provide a new occasion for the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> to put pressure on the USSR for
                                more and quicker military aid. The USSR might agree to North
                                Vietnamese requests for greater or speedier assistance, although we
                                doubt that this would take forms which substantially increased the
                                risks of direct Soviet involvement. It would also diminish somewhat
                                any USSR hopes that negotiations could still be arranged.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>