<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="367" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                        <head>367. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d367fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> JAPAN–KOR <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Confidential. Drafted by Fleck and approved in
                                    <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> on December 21. The memorandum
                                is Part II of V.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-11-29">November
                                    29, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and U.S. Relations with
                                Japan</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName>Tong Won Lee</persName>, Republic of
                                Korea</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName>Hyun Chul Kim</persName>, Korean
                                Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Nam Ki Lee</persName>, American Section Chief,
                                Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William P. Bundy</persName>,
                                Assistant Secretary for Far Eastern Affairs</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Winthrop G.
                                    Brown</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>David H. Popper</persName>, Deputy Assistant
                                Secretary for International Organization Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FBA1">Benjamin A. Fleck</persName>,
                                Officer in Charge, Korean Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>-Japan Normalization</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary said he had great personal respect for the role
                                played by the Foreign Minister in the negotiations for normalization
                                of relations between the Republic of Korea and Japan. The Foreign
                                Minister had displayed a high degree of wisdom and courage. The
                                Secretary said he understood that the ratification instruments would
                                soon be exchanged. He asked if the Minister saw any obstacles to
                                good relations between the two governments arising in the near
                                future.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The Minister replied that the instruments of ratification were
                                scheduled to be exchanged on December 22 in Seoul. He foresaw no
                                real problems arising. As he had mentioned to Mr.
                                    <persName>Bundy</persName> that morning,<note n="2" xml:id="d367fn2">A memorandum of their conversation is
                                    ibid.</note> the negotiations were now over and the Korean
                                people were trying to forget the sad memories of the past.
                                Everything now depends on the sincerity and spirit of cooperation of
                                each side. He said good relations with Japan were important to Korea
                                but the Korean people are very sensitive and there would be trouble
                                if the Japanese were too selfish.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary said that in view of the history of the last 60
                                years and the proximity of Korea, a small country, to Japan, a large
                                country, the sensitivity of the Korean people is understandable. He
                                pointed out that the United States has encountered similar feelings
                                from time to time on the part of the Canadians and Mexicans.
                                However, today’s Japan is not the same Japan as that with which the
                                Korean people had <pb facs="0830" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/> been
                                acquainted prior to 1945. Great changes have taken place in Japan
                                since then.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The Minister replied that he agreed and that his government, as
                                well as Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName>, has made great efforts to
                                convince the Korean people of this truth. However, it is now up to
                                Japan to demonstrate sincerity in its dealings with Korea.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary asked whether the Minister was suggesting that Japan
                                adopt a “low posture” toward the Republic of Korea. The Minister
                                replied that his government only wished the Japanese to adopt a
                                “normal posture.” The Secretary said the United States would help,
                                when appropriate.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Korean Proposal for Tripartite Consultations</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The Foreign Minister stated that the United States is the big
                                brother of the Republic of Korea and of Japan. The two younger
                                brothers have quarreled with each other in the past. It might be
                                useful if the elder brother would now bring the younger brothers
                                into a family atmosphere to talk over family matters. He said he was
                                not asking for a commitment or for institutionalized meetings. He
                                said that his government is confident that U.S. policy toward the
                                Republic of Korea will not change as a result of normalization of
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>-Japan relations.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary replied that in view of the great span of Korean and
                                Japanese culture and history, the Minister was extremely flattering
                                to speak of the United States as an elder brother. He said the
                                Minister was quite right in assuming that there would be no change
                                in U.S. policy. The United States has an unlimited commitment in
                                Korea. If the United States Government were to relinquish any of its
                                responsibilities in Korea, they would be turned over to the Republic
                                of Korea and to no one else.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary went on to say that the effect of World War II on
                                the Japanese had been radically different than its effect on the
                                Koreans. The Japanese Government had renounced the use of force and
                                had prohibited the establishment of armed forces. It was politically
                                impossible for the Japanese Government to emulate the example set by
                                the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government in Viet-Nam.
                                Japan was only gradually assuming the responsibilities appropriate
                                to a country of its size and strength. The United States is
                                encouraging it to do so, but the process will take a little
                                time.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>The Minister recalled that he personally had told Japanese Prime
                                Minister Sato that it is time for Japan to share some of the
                                responsibilities of the United States in Asia. Sato had agreed but
                                had said that there are legal and domestic difficulties in the way.
                                The Secretary remarked that we have been encouraged by recent
                                Japanese actions such as the decision to participate in the Asian
                                Development Bank.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0831" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Conference</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>The Foreign Minister recalled that a year ago he had invited the
                                Foreign Ministers of 10 Asian nations to attend a Foreign Ministers
                                Conference in Seoul. Most replies had been favorable but the
                                Japanese had adopted a negative attitude toward the proposal. He
                                believed, however, that the Japanese attitude was being modified.
                                Ambassador Kim Tong-cho had recently reported from Tokyo that the
                                Japanese are now indicating an interest in participating in the
                                conference. He said in his view the conference should not discuss
                                specific problems. His idea in proposing the conference was to have
                                Asian Foreign Ministers sit down together and hold a general
                                discussion of Asian affairs and seek methods of cooperation.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary asked if the Minister had any date in mind for
                                convening the conference. The Minister replied that he was going to
                                be talking with Japanese Prime Minister Sato and Foreign Minister
                                Shiina in Tokyo on his way back to Seoul. He intended to consult
                                with them concerning a specific date and obtain their views
                                regarding what type of conference should be held. He believed their
                                desires should be carefully considered.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>The Secretary observed that some subjects can be discussed more
                                effectively if the United States is not present. The Minister
                                replied that his government would remain highly dependent on
                                continued U.S. support to make the conference successful.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>