<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-01-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="108" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                        <head>108. Special National Intelligence Estimate 83.4–73<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d108fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: The estimate assessed the threat
                                        posed to Costa Rican political stability by the activities
                                        of domestic Communists and Rightists and concluded that
                                        despite rising tensions the country remained committed to
                                        its democratic political tradition.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box
                                        361, Subject Files, National Intelligence Estimates. Secret;
                                            [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not
                                            declassified</hi>]. All brackets are in the original
                                        except those indicating original footnotes, text that
                                        remains classified or that was omitted by the
                                    editors.</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-01-12">January 12, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>[Omitted here is a title page, a table of contents, and a map of Costa
                            Rica.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">OUTLOOK FOR STABILITY IN COSTA RICA</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Note</p>
                        <p>This Special Estimate, on the threats to Costa Rican political stability
                            over the next two years or so, was requested by the Department of
                            State.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusions</p>
                        <p>A. Over the past couple of years the local political pot in Costa Rica
                            has been kept boiling by the highly personalistic and contentious style
                            of administration of President Figueres. The activities both of domestic
                            Communists and rightwing zealots and of their foreign supporters have
                            contributed to the tension and uncertainty. The campaign for the
                            February 1974 election is already underway and is likely to add its own
                            unsettling ingredients. Nonetheless, Costa Rica is strongly committed to
                            the peaceful, democratic processes which have sustained it through
                            periods of political upset. We expect that the elections will take place
                            in this tradition, and that a president representing one of the centrist
                            political groups will succeed to office.</p>
                        <p>B. We do not discount the chance of a quixotic tilt at the established
                            order by small groups of political extremists. Any such attempt at <pb facs="0385" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/> antigovernment subversion or
                            violence would almost certainly be condemned by the public and countered
                            by the security forces. The existence of a number of “private armies”
                            also raises the possibility of a larger action against the government by
                            rightwing forces. But we believe there is little likelihood of such a
                            development, except under extreme conditions; i.e., a major national
                            crisis in which the established moderate leadership of the country is
                            discredited. In short, we see no serious threat to Costa Rica’s
                            stability or democratic political system.</p>
                        <p rend="center">THE ESTIMATE</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">I. Factors in Costa Rican Stability</p>
                        <p>1. Costa Rica is the most stable, socially egalitarian, and politically
                            democratic country in Central America, and perhaps in all of Latin
                            America. These achievements reflect in good part its distinctive
                            history. During the colonial period it was isolated from the centers of
                            Spanish political power and devoid of easily exploitable natural
                            resources. The sparse Indian population was all but eliminated, and the
                            salubrious climate and lack of mineral wealth discouraged the
                            importation of slave labor. The society that evolved was composed mostly
                            of industrious, independent European landholders. After independence,
                            first coffee and then banana estates produced a number of family
                            fortunes, but the aristocratic leisure class did not emerge in a
                            dominant position in Costa Rica as it did in most other countries of
                            Central and South America.</p>
                        <p>2. The Costa Rican political system came to reflect the values of its
                            relatively homogeneous and democratically inclined populace. From its
                            first free and honest election in 1889, Costa Rica has made steady
                            economic and social progress under constitutional, representative
                            governments. The public has supported a major national investment in
                            public and social institutions; the result has been relatively efficient
                            public administration and high standards of education, medical care, and
                            other social services.</p>
                        <p>3. The Costa Rican economy is basically sound. The per capita gross
                            national product of $550 is the highest in Central America and has been
                            expanding over the past decade at a steady if unspectacular pace.
                            Because of the relatively high level of social services and the fairly
                            even distribution of personal income, the population of just under two
                            million has been spared the extreme poverty that afflicts large numbers
                            in neighboring Republics.</p>
                        <p>4. Yet rapid population growth<note n="2" xml:id="d108fn2">The annual
                                rate of growth reached nearly 4 percent in the early 1960s, but
                                since has declined to 2.8 percent. [Footnote in the
                                original.]</note> and budgetary difficulties have placed strains on
                            the country’s ability to maintain the high level of so<pb facs="0386" n="343" xml:id="pg_343"/>cial services. The annual rate of economic
                            growth fell from 7–8 percent during 1965–1970, to 4–5 percent during
                            1971–1972. This decline reflected in part financial problems under the
                            incumbent government. Balance-of-payments strains have arisen from these
                            financial difficulties, as well as from depressed world market
                            conditions for bananas and coffee and the current disorganization of the
                            Central American Common Market. Nevertheless, the Costa Ricans have
                            begun some minor corrective measures and are planning a comprehensive
                            stabilization program. Over time the prospects for some recovery towards
                            the higher growth rates of past years are good, though the economy will
                            continue to be subject to periodic strains caused by fluctuating world
                            market conditions for its agricultural exports.</p>
                        <p>5. Costa Rica is strongly committed to peaceful political processes which
                            have been interrupted only once in recent times. In 1948 the
                            personalistic party of Rafael Calderón Guardia, which had ruled for the
                            previous two terms, refused to accept its electoral defeat by Otilio
                            Ulate, the candidate of a coalition of opposition parties. José
                            Figueres, an anti-Calderonist merchant and farmer, led a successful
                            armed revolt. He then headed a transitional junta that enacted a new
                            Constitution before Ulate began his four year term in 1949. Every
                            election since this short but bloody civil war has pitted Figueres’s
                            political organization against a coalition dominated by the
                            Calderonists. The electorate has alternated the Presidency between these
                            two forces, though Figueres’s National Liberation Party (<gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss>), has held a legislative majority for
                            most of the period.</p>
                        <p>6. The electorate’s voting habits reflect the strong pull of the center
                            in Costa Rica and work to discourage political extremism. The two
                            moderate groupings, the center-left <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss>
                            and the more conservative anti-<gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss>,
                            consistently command over 90 percent of the popular vote. The repeated
                            peaceful transfer of power to the opposition, in turn, serves to
                            perpetuate the sturdy “two-party” system.</p>
                        <p>7. Costa Ricans have become confident enough in the strength and
                            durability of the political center to be tolerant of the small dissident
                            elements at either end of the spectrum. Extremists—some of them
                            political adventurers and some of them committed ideologues—have in
                            general responded to the democratic atmosphere in which they operate by
                            pursuing their goals in a nonviolent way.</p>
                        <p>8. The openness of the society and widespread citizen interest in
                            political and other public affairs also lend support to the traditional
                            pattern of political behavior on the part both of orthodox political
                            activists and of fringe groups. Accessability to political leaders, even
                            including the President, is remarkably free and provides a fairly
                            continuous exchange of views between the electorate and public
                            officials. Little political news or gossip eludes the irrepressible (if
                            sometimes ir<pb facs="0387" n="344" xml:id="pg_344"/>responsible) corps
                            of newspaper and radio-television journalists; thus, partisan
                            confidences and even conspiracies rarely escape exposure.</p>
                        <p>9. Finally, the ballast of Costa Rica’s political equilibrium is the
                            population’s deep-rooted determination to preserve the distinctive
                            national character. The Costa Ricans are sensitive to developments
                            abroad and concerned that the problems that afflict other countries
                            might at some point be visited upon them. Thus, while they are tolerant
                            of <hi rend="italic">outré</hi> ideas and conduct, they typically close
                            ranks against any threat to their way of life.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">II. Current Problems</p>
                        <p>10. “Pepe” Figueres, generally considered the architect of Costa Rica’s
                            present-day institutions and stability, now is regarded by some of his
                            countrymen as a distinct threat to them. Figueres served as President
                            from 1953–1958 and began a second, four-year term in May 1970.<note n="3" xml:id="d108fn3">Figueres was ineligible to run for the
                                presidency until eight years after his first term. He chose to wait
                                an extra four years, partly in order to square off against an old
                                rival, Mario Echandi, whose presidency from 1958–1962 made him
                                ineligible until 1970. Figueres is barred from standing again for
                                the Presidency by a 1969 constitutional change limiting subsequently
                                elected Presidents to a single term. [Footnote in the
                                original.]</note> The outstanding figure in contemporary Costa Rican
                            folklore, Figueres evokes strong responses from others; loyalty or
                            antipathy to him tends to be fierce [<hi rend="italic">10 lines not
                                declassified</hi>]. Indeed, his present administration has been a
                            time of intense and protracted political agitation, and Figueres himself
                            as an object of controversy nearly overwhelms the substantive policy
                            issues he raises.</p>
                        <p>11. Figueres’s controversial policies range from efforts to make Costa
                            Rica a tax haven for international investors of dubious integrity to
                            favored treatment for the local Communist Party and promotion of the
                            establishment of a Soviet mission. The heat of the debate over these
                            issues has caused some skittish Costa Ricans to fear that the political
                            bitterness will lead the country into a period of violence. Even among
                            less alarmed citizens, confidence in the future has suffered somewhat
                            from the general climate of tension and uncertainty. General concern has
                            arisen about the seeming disarray of the party system, about the
                            weakening of governmental institutions by Figueres’s free-wheeling
                            administration of office, and about corruption. But the areas of
                            greatest concern are the activities of Communist and anti-Communist
                            extremists, the fear that the new Soviet Embassy will subvert Costa Rica
                            and use it as a base of operations against neighboring countries, and
                            rumored foreign-sponsored invasions.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Communist Issue</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>12. The Communist Party (Popular Vanguard Party, PVP), though
                            constitutionally proscribed, has traditionally operated fairly openly
                                <pb facs="0388" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> and with little success in
                            Costa Rica. But the Party seems to many Costa Ricans to be enjoying a
                            new privileged position under the Figueres government. An upturn in the
                            Communists’ political fortune in fact began under the previous
                            administration when they allied with an insignificant but legally
                            registered far-leftist party and were able to run candidates on its
                            ticket for the 1970 election. In this way the Secretary General of the
                            PVP, Manuel Mora, gained an assembly seat. The Party has since made some
                            minor inroads into municipal councils in a few towns. It has also had
                            some success in organized labor, which in Costa Rica is a small, weak
                            movement with little political potential at least over the short term.
                            The Communist front party received only one percent of the presidential
                            ballots and seven percent of the legislative vote in the 1970 election.
                            Since then the PVP has conducted a reasonably successful recruitment
                            drive. It now claims a membership of more than 5,000; we estimate there
                            are about 1,500 active, dues-paying members, which is nearly double the
                            number in 1969–1970.</p>
                        <p>13. Concern about the Communists, particularly amongst Costa Rican
                            rightists, was raised to new heights by Figueres’s determination to open
                            diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union. If any single issue has
                            dominated the Figueres administration, it is that of the Soviet
                            presence. Figueres claims that he is helping the U.S. in its policy of
                            building East-West bridges in the new era of negotiation, and at the
                            same time constructing a valuable Soviet market for Costa Rica’s surplus
                            coffee. As the government’s negotiations with the Soviets proceeded
                            during early 1971, anti-Communist organizations launched a high-powered
                            propaganda campaign that appeared for a while to have forced Figueres to
                            back down. But on 29 November 1971 the government finally accredited the
                            first two Soviet diplomats. As of the end of 1972, the Soviet mission
                            numbered 13 officers, 8 in the Embassy and 5 in the commercial
                                mission.<note n="4" xml:id="d108fn4">As a comparison, the British
                                Embassy in San José has four officers; the U.S. mission contains
                                about 30 members, including Embassy and <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> officers. [Footnote in the original.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>14. The Soviets probably view their diplomatic entry into Central America
                            as a modest triumph for their policy of expanding their presence in
                            Latin America generally. They are acutely aware of the local opposition
                            to their presence and of the hostility with which they are regarded in
                            neighboring countries, and their first interest is to promote good will
                            so as to dispel local fears. The Soviets may in time engage in some
                            low-level political action in Costa Rica and in Central America, but
                            they almost certainly will be anxious to avoid costly or risky
                            operations. They probably discern few possibilities for the Communist
                            parties in the region to make major political gains any time soon. They
                                <pb facs="0389" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/> are likely to concentrate
                            on building their respectability and influence and, over time, try to
                            take advantage of opportunities to chip away at the strong U.S. position
                            in the area.</p>
                        <p>15. Many Costa Ricans have been particularly suspicious of the
                            relationship between President Figueres on the one hand and the PVP’s
                            Mora and the Soviet Embassy on the other. Their meetings apparently
                            relate principally to various money-making schemes, [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>] though they probably include some
                            discussion of political matters as well. Some conspiratorial-minded
                            opponents of Figueres, willing and even eager to believe the worst, have
                            conjectured that his long record as an outspoken anti-Communist
                            constituted a strategem to put him “in place” to promote the Communist
                            cause at the proper time. We do not believe that Figueres’s dealings
                            with the Communists represent any “sell-out” on his part of basic Costa
                            Rican interests. Rather they are indicative of his proclivity for
                            opportunistic financial scheming with anyone who can help him cope with
                            his chronic indebtedness. He continues to meet with Mora, who is a
                            long-time personal friend, but his only known political actions in
                            support of the Communists—promotion of a Soviet presence and of
                            legalization of the PVP—are consistent with his long-held views.<note n="5" xml:id="d108fn5">Ironically, Mora’s dealings with Figueres
                                have caused dissension within the PVP, where some critics accuse the
                                party chief of a “sell-out” to the establishment [<hi rend="italic">2 lines not declassified</hi>]. [Footnote in the
                                original.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>16. The institutional checks and balances in the Costa Rican system have
                            operated to limit what Figueres could do to help the Communists even as
                            President. As a key example, Figueres has been unable to persuade the
                            legislature, dominated by his own <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss>,
                            to erase the constitutional prohibition of the Communist Party.
                            Furthermore, Figueres’s promises of a vigorous and lucrative trade
                            relationship between the Soviets and Costa Rica have not been fulfilled.
                            Soviet goods have not been competitive in Costa Rica’s open system of
                            bidding, and only small amounts of vodka and other consumer goods have
                            been sold. The Soviets have made known their displeasure with the
                            one-way direction of the trade arrangement and, now that they have their
                            Embassy, are hedging on further contracts for coffee until Costa Rica
                            reciprocates with a greater volume of purchases. Finally, Figueres’s
                            power and influence will drop off rapidly when he steps down from the
                            Presidency, and many in his own party, as well as those in the more
                            conservative parties, oppose him on the Communist issue.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Rightists</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>17. The mere fact of the Soviet presence has provided a new <hi rend="italic">raison d’être</hi> for the local anti-Communist
                            activists. Some of these have already <pb facs="0390" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/> engaged in minor harassing action against the
                            Soviets. Others have made an effort to mobilize a political force to
                            unseat the politicians responsible for the Soviet presence, either via
                            the ballot box or in some less orthodox way. [<hi rend="italic">4 lines
                                not declassified</hi>] In general, the rapidly anti-Figueres,
                            anti-Communist groups are more likely than any groups on the far Left to
                            use violence in pursuit of their cause.</p>
                        <p>18. The Communist issue has brought to public notice a rightwing zealot,
                            Jorge González Martén. A millionaire and for a while a U.S. citizen,
                            González waged a successful court battle in 1972 to regain legal
                            standing as a Costa Rican eligible for the Presidency. This effort and
                            González’s introduction of a political propaganda blitz, U.S.-style, won
                            quick fame for him as an up-and-coming personality and for his
                            minuscule, stridently anti-Communist, National Independent Party. He has
                            attracted the support of several wealthy Costa Rican businessmen
                            interested in backing a staunchly conservative anti-<gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> figure for the Presidency. He
                            apparently has also gained a measure of support from some U.S.
                            businessmen in Costa Rica. González’s political appeal is on the wane
                            now that the more moderate opposition politicians have taken to the
                            hustings, but his glib and urgent presentation of a looming Communist
                            takeover in Costa Rica has contributed to the local concern about
                            political polarization.</p>
                        <p>19. In plotting a coup, the extreme Right might seek support from several
                            paramilitary groups or “private armies” that are a fixture on the Costa
                            Rican scene. These loose organizations are accepted by the populace as a
                            hedge against the need for an armed force (there is no national army)
                            and, as a holdover from the war of 1948. The members of these groups
                            come from a wide variety of social and political elements and include
                            respected businessmen, politicians, and farmers, as well as smugglers
                            and adventurers. While most of the groups do not identify themselves
                            first and foremost as anti-Communist, they would not be uncomfortable
                            with that description, and under certain circumstances some groups might
                            be attracted to the alarmist themes of anti-Communist activists.</p>
                        <p>20. There may have been as many as a dozen “private armies” at various
                            times since the 1948 conflict, and remnants of most of them probably
                            remain. Some could probably count on the support of only 10 to 15
                            persons. The Free Costa Rica Movement, a rightwing businessmen’s group,
                            is larger and would be able to raise a militia of a hundred or so
                            persons. The single largest group is the security arm of the center-left
                                <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss>, which could count on several
                            hundred stalwarts; but few if any of these would support a rightwing
                            coup.</p>
                        <p>21. Another amplification of the danger from rightist extremists could
                            develop from their connections outside the country. Stories of impending
                            foreign invasions, arms landings, and outside funding of <pb facs="0391" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/> local subversives have abounded over the
                            past two years. In several instances a kernel or two of truth lies
                            behind the stories. The specific lines of friendships, enmities, family
                            and business ties, and the other forms of intercourse among the Central
                            Americans defy unraveling, but one general aspect is a penchant for
                            meddling in each others’ domestic politics. [<hi rend="italic">4 lines
                                not declassified</hi>] Legitimate Costa Rican politicians, too, have
                            approached foreign Embassies and businessmen to solicit support and
                            funds.</p>
                        <p>22. Outside meddling, however, rarely exceeds the talking point before
                            being exposed by rumor, by investigative journalism, or by government
                            leak. The Costa Rican public’s invariable censure considerably weakens
                            the impact of foreign interference. Although rumor and minor
                            conspiracies have added to the sense of political insecurity within
                            Costa Rica, we believe there now is no real danger to the government
                            from this kind of activity. Indeed, President Figueres has effectively
                            turned invasion scares to his own end, using the “threat” to expand
                            temporarily his base of sympathy and support.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">III. Outlook</p>
                        <p>23. Although recent issues and events in Costa Rica have raised tensions,
                            we believe that controversy will remain within the bounds of the
                            country’s sound institutional structures. The debate over the Communist
                            issue has been particularly potent in energizing small extremist groups.
                            But over the short run there appears to be very little chance that any
                            group—Left or Right—will be able to undertake action on a scale to
                            threaten the government seriously.</p>
                        <p>24. On the Left, the PVP, even under the present favorable conditions,
                            has demonstrated little potential to rise beyond the minor party status
                            it has held for decades. There are a few leftist extremists in and out
                            of the party who preach violence, but they are for the most part
                            identified and isolated. The leadership and bulk of the PVP have
                            traditionally pursued the <hi rend="italic">vía pacífica</hi>, a
                            penchant at present reinforced by Soviet diplomatic requirements.</p>
                        <p>25. On the Right, the several continually conspiring small groups possess
                            little strength on their own. We do not dismiss the possibility that a
                            small number of rightist fanatics might launch some kind of coup
                            attempt. However, we see almost no chance that such an effort would
                            prove to be anything other than quixotic. The Civil Guard and other
                            police forces, with public support, would be able to counter it.<note n="6" xml:id="d108fn6">While the 2,500-man Civil Guard, with the
                                assistance of other small police forces, is competent to meet this
                                kind of low-level threat, it could not cope effectively with
                                widespread outbreaks of violence. [Footnote in the original.]</note>
                            The existence of “private armies” raises the possibility of a larger
                            action against the government. We believe, however, that such an attempt
                                <pb facs="0392" n="349" xml:id="pg_349"/> would be very unlikely
                            except in the extreme circumstances of some dramatic nationwide crisis
                            in which the established moderate leadership was discredited (akin to
                            the effort to steal the election in 1948).</p>
                        <p>26. We doubt that the traditional center-oriented political system—i.e.,
                                <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> vs. anti-<gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> coalition—will fall apart, despite
                            various expressions of concern. The sense of “new politics” in Costa
                            Rica apparently grows out of the realization that the end of Figueres’s
                            term will mean the end of the era dominated by such leaders as Figueres,
                            Ulate, and Calderón. The large number of minor parties seeking
                            registration for the next election also promotes the perception of
                            political realignment. But recognition of the basic strength of the
                                <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> behind its likely nominee,
                            party stalwart Daniel Oduber, and the hope that the electorate will hold
                            to its practice of voting for the “outs” will probably in the end serve
                            as imperatives toward unity for most of the anti-<gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> forces. These groups have already
                            begun to consider favorably the bid for support by the respected
                            conservative presidential candidate Fernando Trejos Escalante, who is
                            likely to bring back to the center most of the early support garnered by
                            González Martén’s far rightist party.</p>
                        <p>27. In short, despite the tension and uncertainty, we expect the 1974
                            election to take place normally and to return still another moderate
                            (and likely less frenetic) administration committed to preserve Costa
                            Rica’s democratic tradition.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>