<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>122. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="122"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d122">
                <head>122. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d122fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: During a lunch conversation, the president
                                of the Costa Rican Legislative Assembly told Embassy officials that
                                Oduber had agreed not to oppose the recently passed extradition law
                                in exchange for Vesco-linked funding for his election
                                campaign.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, P740044–0780. Confidential. Drafted by <persName
                                    corresp="#p_JPB_1">Johnson</persName>. Sent as an enclosure to
                                airgram A–58 from San José, May 1. The meeting was held at the Hotel
                                Amstol Restaurant. In airgram A–52 from San José, April 19, the
                                Embassy reported that efforts to tie demonstrations against the
                                Extradition Bill to U.S. interests appeared to represent an effort
                                by political allies of the Figueres administration to discredit the
                                protests. (Ibid., P740037–0730) In a July 1 letter to Sullivan,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JPB_1">Johnson</persName> stated his view
                                that Oduber sought to create the appearance of non-involvement with
                                Vesco while enjoying the benefits of his presence in Costa Rica.
                                (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_ARACENCR_1">ARA/CEN/CR</gloss> Files: Lot
                                76D290, Chron—Letters, Correspondence from Embassy, 1974)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>San José</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1974-04-18">April 18,
                    1974</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Luis Alberto Monge, President, Legislative Assembly</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LL_1">Lyle F. Lane</persName>, Chargé d’Affaires ad
                        interim, AmEmbassy San Jose</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JPB_1">Peter D. Johnson</persName>, Political Officer,
                        AmEmbassy San Jose</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Oduber, Figueres, and Liberacion Politics</item>
                </list>
                <p>During luncheon conversation today, Luis Alberto Monge, who is uncomfortably in
                    the middle of some bitter parliamentary infighting and maneuvering between
                    political factions, took time to explain in some detail the political problems
                    implicit in processing through the Assembly the Education Bill; the Newspaper
                    Bill; the Family Assistance Bill; the Exchange Reunification Bill; and then
                    looking back two or three weeks, went into some of the politics of the
                    Extradition Bill.</p>
                <p>With regard to the last, the Extradition Bill, as much of the rest has been
                    picked up in A–52, Monge described the reaction of the Figueres administration
                    against the Embassy as an attempt to “devolver la pelota” at the Embassy after
                    having been stung by the public’s reaction to the bill. He explained that back
                    in December when the political campaign was beginning to really get expensive,
                    Daniel found himself in desperate need for $4 million. Although he had not
                    previously turned to Figueres and Vesco, Oduber found that, according to Luis
                    Alberto, money was available from this source for a price. While Luis Alberto
                    Monge was in Taiwan over the Christmas holidays, he said a deal was struck
                    between Oduber and Figueres whereby $4 million worth of Vesco money was
                    channeled into the <hi rend="italic">Liberacion</hi> campaign coffers. Monge
                    said the money was part of the funds that Vesco paid for the various government
                    bonds that he bought from the administration a year or so ago and which we in
                    the Embassy estimated totalled nearly <pb facs="0415" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/>
                    $10 million (dollars). Monge went on to say that the price Oduber was required
                    to pay for the $4 million was:</p>
                <p>1. Nomination of Gonzalo Facio to remain in the Foreign Ministry;</p>
                <p>2. A stiffened law to protect Robert Vesco from extradition attempts.</p>
                <p>3. A promise to appoint Figueres’s son-in-law, Danilo Jimenez, as president of
                    the social security institute.</p>
                <p>This deal with Figueres, Luis Alberto pointed out, explains why Oduber was not in
                    a position to fight the Extradition Bill when it was being pressed through the
                    legislature. He had already committed himself to Figueres’s scheme.</p>
                <p>Curiously, Monge made no reference whatsoever to the Embassy’s approach in the
                    Legislative Assembly, at the time of the Extradition Bill’s consideration, to
                    Edgar Arroyo, Acting President of the Assembly in Monge’s absence and probably
                    an important element in provoking Figueres’s and possibly even Oduber’s
                    irritation with the Embassy. On the other hand, Monge said he expected there was
                    nothing to the allegations by Manuel Carballo Quintana that the Embassy was
                    stimulating the Costa Rican youth to protest against the government extradition
                    projects. Monge said that the original motion presented by Manuel Carballo
                    Quintana contained allegations naming <persName corresp="#p_JPB_1">Peter
                        Johnson</persName>, but Monge, before approving the motion, convinced the
                    sponsor that the name be dropped. Monge anticipated, furthermore, that nothing
                    would come of the investigation by the Foreign Ministry except a perfunctory
                    reply indicating there was no substance to the allegations.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Liberacion Politics</p>
                <p>Monge clearly is finding himself in an increasingly difficult position as heir
                    apparent to the party presidency. The difficulty lies mainly with Figueres and
                    his cronies: Burstin—who is the grey eminence; Danilo Jimenez—who has his own
                    presidential aspirations; and Carlos Manuel Vincent former Minister of
                    Gobernacion under Figueres. Figueres has been convinced by his cronies that he
                    should take over the party, and Oduber has persuaded Monge that he should not
                    confront Figueres. Anxious himself to avoid a confrontation, Monge said, perhaps
                    unrealistically, that he believed that time might well work to his advantage.
                    Monge said the <gloss target="#t_PLN_1">PLN</gloss> National Assembly scheduled
                    for May, after the inauguration of the new administration, had been indefinitely
                    postponed on his orders because the rank-and-file as well as the party cadre are
                    solidly behind his own candidacy, but Figueres is insisting on the candidacy
                    himself. Luis Alberto says it would not be politically wise to beat Figueres,
                    even though he believes he could easily do it. So, as a temporary solution,
                    Monge has agreed to indefinitely postpone the party convention. He will, in the
                    meantime, continue as <pb facs="0416" n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/> the party’s
                    secretary-general, and there will be no party president for the indefinite
                    future.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">COMMENT:</hi> Monge is obviously unhappy with what he regards
                    as indecisive backing of his position by the President-elect, but, on the other
                    hand, by not himself providing courageous leadership, and allowing decisions
                    which directly concern him to be made by others to his disadvantage, Monge has
                    lost some ground with the rank and file. Maybe Oduber, always reluctant to take
                    on Pepe Figueres, has agreed with Don Pepe to let Luis Alberto’s star eclipse by
                    itself, leaving little alternative to a resurgence of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Figuerismo</hi>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
