<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>15. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President Nixon) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recoUaDF1UnWfstSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Multilateral Trade
                        Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="rec69a7332dc9647a0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Multinational
                        corporations</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <head>15. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>) to President Nixon<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d15fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                                    >Kissinger</persName> reported on a meeting with Latin American
                                Foreign Ministers held in Washington to continue the dialogue
                                established in Mexico City in February.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                                Library, National Security Adviser, Scowcroft Daily Work Files, Box
                                6, 4/19–30/74. Confidential. Sent for information. Scowcroft
                                initialed the memorandum for <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                                    >Kissinger</persName>. Tab A is the April 18 communiqué issued
                                at the conclusion of the Washington meeting of Foreign Ministers,
                                published in the Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                                >Bulletin</hi>, May 13, 1974, pp. 517–519. The decision to hold the
                                Washington meeting was reached at the Tlatelolco Conference in
                                February. (Ibid., p. 516) In telegram 85239 to all American Republic
                                diplomatic posts, April 26, the Department reported that the
                                Washington meeting had been a success. (National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy File, D740117–0803, D740109–0672,
                                D740098–0734) In telegram 51 from Atlanta, May 2, the Delegation to
                                the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> General Assembly informed
                                the Department that the meeting there had been “marked by a
                                pronounced optimism on the future of U.S.-Latin relations,” although
                                little progress was made in defining the role of the <gloss
                                    target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> in the inter-American system.
                                (Ibid., D740105–0151, D740104–1073)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-04-19"
                        >April 19, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Latin American Foreign Ministers Conference in Washington, and the
                            <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> General Assembly in Atlanta</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Latin American <hi rend="italic">Foreign Ministers Conference</hi> in
                    Washington ended Thursday afternoon on a highly positive note. Our objectives of
                    maintaining and furthering the cooperative spirit developed at the Mexico City
                    meeting and of beginning the process of giving some practical content to this
                    spirit and the principles of inter-American solidarity affirmed at Mexico City
                    have been advanced.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Communiqué</hi> (Tab A) issued after the Conference
                    highlights the positive tone of the Conference. It:</p>
                <p>—reaffirms our joint satisfaction over continuation of the cooperative spirit
                    begun in Mexico City at Tlatelolco;</p>
                <p>—describes the subjects discussed and general views expressed, largely on matters
                    of trade and development; specifically, it notes the U.S. reaffirmation of its
                    intention to refrain to the extent possible from establishing new trade
                    restrictions on access to the U.S. market and to promote enactment of the
                    proposed Trade Reform Act which would authorize generalized preferences,
                    including in them products of particular interest to Latin America. It also
                    notes the agreement to engage in consultations on subjects related to the
                    Multilateral Trade Negotiations and other subjects to be discussed in world
                    conferences;</p>
                <p>—describes the working groups which were set up to translate this spirit into
                    action in the fields of science and technology, and multinational corporations;
                    and</p>
                <pb facs="0099" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/>
                <p>—states that the Foreign Ministers will meet again in Buenos Aires in March of
                    1975 to continue the dialogue.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Cuban</hi> question, which the Foreign Ministers of
                    Argentina and Mexico had publicly committed themselves to raising at the
                    Conference, was handled in a manner that minimized confrontation. In private
                    meetings here with Argentine Foreign Minister Vignes and Mexican Foreign
                    Minister Rabasa, I stressed the importance of having a positive Conference which
                    avoided a confrontation or domination of the deliberations by the Cuba question
                    at the expense of other more important matters. I explained the importance of
                    holding this subject until after other business had been completed and of
                    avoiding any kind of vote or decision. We were successful in getting their
                    agreement on this.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, at the Conference Vignes raised the subject in terms of the need to
                    seek a solution but without making any specific proposals. Secretary Rabasa then
                    suggested that Cuba be invited to the next meeting of Foreign Ministers. He was
                    supported by the Foreign Ministers of Peru and Venezuela. I then proposed that
                    before the next Conference Vignes, as Foreign Minister of the host government,
                    consult with all the governments represented to get their views on the subject.
                    The consultation would also include Colombia’s suggestion that Canada be
                    represented at the next meeting. This compromise formula enabled us to defuse
                    the Cuba question, maintain the constructive direction of the Conference and
                    avoid its deteriorating into a confrontation which we could not have won in the
                    press. The Conference closed without any decision, formal or informal, relating
                    to Cuban participation beyond the general understanding that the Government of
                    Argentina will consult. Your decision enabling our agreement to issue the
                    licenses to subsidiaries of American companies in Argentina for trade with Cuba
                    was instrumental in obtaining Argentina’s cooperative attitude in achieving this
                    compromise.</p>
                <p>The constructive spirit maintained at the Washington Conference is particularly
                    important because of the carry-over effect to the <hi rend="italic">General
                        Assembly of the Organization of American States (<gloss target="#t_OAS_1"
                            >OAS</gloss>)</hi> which opens this Friday in Atlanta. We expect the
                    positive and cooperative attitude maintained in Washington to characterize also
                    the Atlanta meeting. The formal agenda of the General Assembly contains no major
                    issues, concentrating on organizational business matters such as approval of the
                    budget. It will, however, hear a report from the special committee which has
                    been set up to make recommendations on the restructuring of the inter-American
                    system. The Cuban subject will no doubt be raised in speeches in Atlanta in the
                    form of objections to the maintenance of <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>
                    sanctions against Cuba. As in the past, statements will be made on both sides.
                    We believe, however, that the combination of the announcement to license
                    subsidiaries and the brief airing of the issue</p>
                <pb facs="0100" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                <p>here in Washington will satisfy those Latins pressing for change in <gloss
                        target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> policy toward Cuba—at least enough to avoid a
                    showdown vote on the matter. Formally, a two-thirds vote would be required to
                    terminate sanctions. However, a majority expression of such a view would be
                    psychologically damaging to us. The number of countries which would support
                    termination if a vote were taken is not entirely clear, but it is uncomfortably
                    close to a majority.</p>
                <p>Thus, I believe both in Washington and at Atlanta we will have avoided a
                    breakdown in the momentum of a positive dialogue with the Latins and bought
                    ourselves time on the Cuba issue. In press briefings we are stressing the
                    positive nature of the Conference and the unaltered position of our Cuba
                    policy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
