<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>365. Telegram 1606 From the Embassy in Guyana to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-10-30T12:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-10-30T12:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recaCPsAUbblCdB8K" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-10-30T12:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-10-30T12:15:00-05:00" n="365"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                <head>365. Telegram 1606 From the Embassy in Guyana to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d365fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: In a conversation with <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName>, Ambassador King
                                forcefully denied that the U.S. Government’s decision to reduce the
                                West Indian sugar quota was a politically motivated punitive
                                measure.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, [no film number]. Confidential; Priority. Repeated to
                                Bridgetown, Kingston, and Port of Spain. All brackets are in the
                                original except “[<hi rend="italic">29</hi>?]”, added for clarity.
                                In <ref target="#d439">Document 439</ref>, the Department reported
                                on Shlaudeman’s assurances to Caribbean Ambassadors that the U.S.
                                Government would examine ways of ameliorating the effects of a
                                reduction in the region’s sugar quotas. On October 27, the
                                Department informed the Embassy that in an October 18 meeting, West
                                Indian officials had informed their U.S. counterparts that they were
                                fully aware the reduction in the sugar quota was a technical, not a
                                political, issue. (Telegram 212526 to Georgetown, October 27;
                                National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, [no film
                                number]) In telegram 1599 from Georgetown, October 29, the Embassy
                                requested information on previous cases in which Latin American
                                nations had not fulfilled their sugar quotas. (Ibid.) No reply from
                                the Department has been found. On November 8, Ramphal stated to King
                                that he thought the reduction in the sugar quota was not politically
                                motivated. (Telegram 1661 from Georgetown, November 9; ibid.)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1973-10-30T17:15:00+00:00">October 30, 1973, 1715Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>1606. Subject: Sugar Quota Problem: Talk with Prime Minister. Ref: Georgetown
                    1599.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1"
                        >Burnham</persName> and majority his Cabinet apparently convinced that U.S.
                    action to reduce drastically West Indies sugar quota for 1974 was politically
                    motivated punitive move in retribution for area’s rapprochement with Cuba and
                    aggressive implementation of non-aligned foreign policy. To this extent, they
                    considered Oct 20 <hi rend="italic">New Nation</hi> editorial accurate as to
                    facts. I attempted forcefully to convince <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1"
                        >Burnham</persName> otherwise. He said I had succeeded. <hi rend="italic"
                        >End summary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. Took occasion to seek encounter with Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName> at close of ceremonial opening of
                    Parliament today (Monday, Oct 2 [<hi rend="italic">29</hi>?]) in order ask him
                    whether October 20 <hi rend="italic">New Nation</hi> editorial reflected
                    position of his govt. He said he had not been aware of editorial before its
                    publication and considered it probably a bit unfortunate, but he nevertheless
                    assumed it correctly reflected the facts, that is that reduction of West Indies
                    sugar quota was politically motivated punitive move by <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>2. I exploded and talked probably more bluntly to <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1"
                        >Burnham</persName> than on any other occasion in the four years I have been
                    dealing with him. Told him this was utter nonsense, that he should know better
                    and so on. Reminding him I had gone over U.S. Sugar Act with Acting Prime
                    Minister during his absence in effort disprove such nonsensical allegations, I
                    reviewed it again, emphasizing non-discretionary nature of Section 202 D4 and
                    fact that West Indies had failed meet commitments to <pb facs="0990" n="947"
                        xml:id="pg_947"/> U.S. through own choice. Purpose of Act, I went on, was to
                    assure U.S. a given supply of sugar each year from reliable sources. For this we
                    traditionally paid premium prices. This year, no matter how justifiable West
                    Indies might consider priority given UK market, fact was he had been left with
                    shortage of 180,000 tons (I did not attempt to explain the reallocation of short
                    falls).</p>
                <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName> seemed genuinely taken aback
                    by strength of my reaction to his statement. He asked about Nicaragua, saying he
                    understood that country had sold sugar to Cuba and had not been penalized. This
                    had led him to assumption that allegations that West Indies political
                    rapproachement with Cuba had caused cut in its quota were correct. I said I knew
                    nothing about possible Nicaraguan sales to Cuba and did not recall that country
                    having been mentioned in rash of distorted accounts of how West Indies being
                    penalized. I was aware of certain allegations concerning Bolivia and Peru and
                    was attempting to obtain clarification. These cases seemed to have involved
                    failure notify <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> of anticipated shortfalls as
                    required, where discretion is authorized by law, but not sales to third
                    countries while failing meet commitments to U.S., where there is no
                    discretionary authority to waive prescribed penalties. I would explain it in
                    more detail to FonMin Ramphal as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>4. I stressed that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> did not operate in the
                    way Prime Minister seemed to assume, challenged his belief in the conspiratorial
                    theory of history and told him he could not have it both ways. Friendship and
                    cooperation is two-way street. We offer both, but do get tired of having our
                    motives impugned as in <hi rend="italic">New Nation</hi> editorial in question.
                    Publication of such views hardly helpful to anyone.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName> backed away, said I had
                    convinced him reduction in quota was neither political move nor punitive action
                    and promised to make this clear to “his people.” He reiterated that he had
                    mistakenly assumed the worst and said he appreciated the clarification. Maybe
                    so.</p>
                <p>6. That <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName> took this conversation
                    seriously (it took place in corner of vacated Parliament Hall) evidenced by fact
                    he waved off three reminders that President and Mrs. Chung and members of
                    Cabinet were awaiting him for tea.</p>
                <p>7. Prior to sitting of Parliament, I had asked Minister of State in office of
                    Prime Minister Christopher Nascimento if <hi rend="italic">New Nation</hi>
                    editorial reflected policy of the government. He said he had not read it. I
                    urged him to do so and let me know his reaction. Later in day he phoned me at
                    home to say that while some of language was perhaps unfortunate and while <hi
                        rend="italic">New Nation</hi> editor operated with considerable autonomy and
                    not always the best of judgment, the views expressed in a general sense did
                    reflect the thinking of the majority of the Cabinet. In other words the weight
                    of opinion in the Cabinet was that the sharp reduction in <pb facs="0991"
                        n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/> U.S. sugar quota for 1974 was politically
                    motivated punitive action in retribution for the area’s rapprochment with Cuba
                    and signs of independence in foreign affairs in general. As has everyone else
                    involved, Nascimento cited alleged nonenforcement of punitive provisions of
                    Sugar Act in cases of other Latin American countries which had failed meet U.S.
                    quota commitments as confirmation that U.S. discriminating against West Indies
                    on political grounds.</p>
                <p>8. I again reviewed nondiscretionary nature of Section 202 D4 for Nascimento’s
                    benefit, pointed out that decision to meet commitments to UK rather than to U.S.
                    created self-generated problem and pleaded ignorance on exactly what had
                    happened with respect to Bolivia, Peru and Nicaragua, which are Latin American
                    countries credited with benefiting from “selective non-enforcement.” I did give
                    him same explanation I gave to <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName>.
                    When I stressed that opinions such as those expressed by <hi rend="italic">New
                        Nation</hi> hardly gave encouragement to those in Washington who were
                    attempting, at considerable cost in time and effort, to assist West Indies,
                    Nascimento said no one here aware of such efforts. General assumption was that
                    West Indies had no quota for 1974, period. I commented that Guyana’s Embassy in
                    Washington obviously not doing its job and that Frank Noel, PermSec in MinTrade,
                    who had attended technical talks in Washington last week was well aware of
                    facts.</p>
                <p>9. Nascimento professed be pleased I had raised issue with Prime Minister and
                    said he would try to “spread the word” as I had given it to him. I doubt we can
                    count on much help from this quarter, however, since he is among those close to
                    the Prime Minister who would be predisposed assume nefarious motives on part of
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> A. Dept should not be overly surprised by
                    this interpretation of drastic reduction in quota for 1974 as political
                    punishment for rapproachement with Cuba and non-alignment. This Embassy noted
                    from the start that this would be the case and other posts in the area have
                    recorded similar views. What is rational, reasonable and justifiable in
                    Washington is not always seen in same light in country such as this, especially
                    when we do not set record straight on distortions and misinformation.
                    Furthermore, there is a certain feeling of guilt which predisposes many here to
                    assume that U.S. must be displeased with recent developments. Consequently,
                    anything the U.S. does which goes against local interests tends be interpreted
                    as calculated punitive action.</p>
                <p>B. It is fairly evident that Dpty Prime Minister Ptolemy Reid did not report our
                    earlier conversation to <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1">Burnham</persName>, or did
                    so incompletely, and that latter since his return has been listening to his more
                    radical advisers, of which he has all too many. Coming on top of his exposure to
                    Third World African leaders, such an interpretation of U.S. motives <pb
                        facs="0992" n="949" xml:id="pg_949"/> would have seemed logical to him. It
                    is disappointing, however, that sugar producers, such as Bookers’s George
                    Bishop, and his own technical people, such as Frank Noel, did not succeed in
                    convincing him otherwise.</p>
                <p>C. In any event, no question but what public airing of such views can do no one
                    any good. Hopefully, things may quiet down a bit now.</p>
                <p>D. Shall follow up with FonMin Ramphal, to whom <persName corresp="#p_BLFS_1"
                        >Burnham</persName> listens and who is one of few more moderate influences
                    around Prime Minister these days. His prolonged absence unfortunate in this
                    context.</p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Action requested.</hi> That information requested in reftel
                    be augmented by data on Nicaraguan sales. Did Nicaragua sell sugar to Cuba in
                    1973? Did Nicaragua fail to meet its quota commitments to U.S.? In either case,
                    was Nicaragua penalized in any way?</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>King</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
