<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>413. Telegram 2857 From the Embassy in Haiti to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-11-13T14:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-11-13T14:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-11-13T14:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-11-13T14:55:00-05:00" n="413"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d413">
                <head>413. Telegram 2857 From the Embassy in Haiti to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d413fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The Embassy reported that Haiti’s record on
                                human rights had improved since <persName corresp="#p_DJC_1"
                                    >Jean-Claude Duvalier</persName> became President in 1971 and
                                observed that Haitian applicants for political asylum who were
                                returned to the country did not face reprisals.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D750396–0066. Confidential; Priority. All brackets are
                                in the original except those indicating text omitted by the editors.
                                In telegram 264683 to Port-au-Prince, November 7, the Department
                                requested an update on the Embassy’s previous reporting in
                                anticipation of a November 18 congressional hearing on the human
                                rights situation in Haiti and on the influx of Haitian refugees
                                coming to the United States. (Ibid., D750388–0642) No record of the
                                November 12 telephone conversation between <persName
                                    corresp="#p_HTJC_1">Heavner</persName> and Vincent has been
                                found.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Port-au-Prince</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1975-11-13T19:55:00+00:00">November 13, 1975, 1955Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>2857. Subject: Haiti: Congressional Hearings on Human Rights/Refugees. Ref: A)
                    State 264683; B) <persName corresp="#p_HTJC_1">Heavner</persName>/Vincent Telcon
                    of 11/12/75.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> Haiti’s record on human rights observance has
                    distinctly improved in the past four years as President <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJC_1">Jean-Claude Duvalier</persName> ended the climate of
                    terror and insecurity utilized by his father, disestablished the dreaded Tonton
                    Macoutes, encouraged the return of <pb facs="1110" n="1067" xml:id="pg_1067"/>
                    exiles (except for those who still actively oppose the government), stressed
                    economic and social progress, promoted the reform of public administration, and
                    began concentrating on economic development plans. A stamp fraud trial this year
                    rejuvenated long-dormant criminal processes, including the right of defense
                    lawyers to argue effectively, and allowed the local media to criticize <gloss
                        target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> shortcomings more openly. Long-standing and
                    politically important peasant land title claims now are being adjudicated,
                    whereas in the past they were ignored and any peasant agitation was repressed.
                    Local initiatives on behalf of women’s rights are encouraged. The <gloss
                        target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> is paying greater attention to enforcing some
                    workers’ rights often ignored by employers. Contrary to common belief in Haitian
                    exile circles, claimants to political asylum deported from the U.S., Canada, and
                    the Bahamas have not encountered reprisals, based upon the cases which we have
                    monitored over the past two years, and the <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss>
                    cooperates with U.S. officials to ensure an orderly and satisfactory processing
                    of returned deportees.</p>
                <p>Haiti remains an authoritarian, non-democratic society with few effective
                    institutions and without a liberal legal tradition, the Code Napoleon further
                    restricting procedural safeguards assumed under the Anglo-Saxon legal tradition.
                    Prison conditions, although improved, remain poor, decision-making arbitrary,
                    and procedural safeguards uncertain. These factors are compounded by the
                    tradition of total secrecy surrounding political prisoners and by the
                    government’s well-founded awareness that it remains the target of Communist
                    subversion and anti-Duvalierist plotting directed from the U.S., Canada, Cuba
                    and France. Nevertheless, the current government shows a willingness to
                    reconsider its practices in the context of Duvalier’s overall reform effort, and
                    even to experiment with improvements. Duvalier and his advisors appreciate U.S.
                    human rights concerns, and within the limits of perceived security interests are
                    cautiously trying to accommodate some of them. End summary.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is the remainder of the telegram.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
