<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>139. Telegram From the Embassy in the United Kingdom to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-08-28T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-08-28T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-28T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-28T08:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <head>139. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United
                        Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d139fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 974.7301/8–2856. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution. Received at
                        12:10 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-08-28T14:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 28, 1956—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1114. Suez—From <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Henderson</persName>. For the
                    Secretary.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Since your departure we have had two meetings Suez Committee<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d139fn2">The first meeting convened in London at 11 a.m., and
                            the second at 4:40 p.m., August 27. Summary reports of these meetings
                            were transmitted in telegrams 1104 and 1105, August 27. (<hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 974.7301/8–2756)</note> and I have had
                        talks with French Ambassador,<note n="3" xml:id="d139fn3">This conversation
                            took place on August 27; reported in telegram 1102, August 27, not
                            printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn Lloyd</persName>,<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d139fn4">This conversation took place on August 27; reported in
                            telegram 1103, August 27, not printed. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi>)</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName>,<note n="5" xml:id="d139fn5"
                            >No account of a conversation between <persName corresp="#p_HLW1"
                                >Henderson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MRG1"
                                >Menzies</persName> has been found in Department of State
                            files.</note> and various other interested persons. It might be useful
                        give you in this telegram brief description atmosphere and
                        developments.</item>
                    <pb facs="0347" n="307" xml:id="pg_307"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I am far from impressed re competence Committee. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> agreeable, intelligent and
                        articulate but has not yet provided firm leadership. He has not presented
                        any plan his own for approaching Egyptians but has welcomed most of
                        suggestions we have made. Iranians and Ethiopians have thus far contributed
                        little. Their role has been to sit and listen and to express agreement or
                        disagreement—mostly agreement—with various suggestions offered. I recognize
                        importance maintaining their support. Swedish Ambassador who represents
                            <persName corresp="#p_UO1">Unden</persName> highly intelligent and
                        although somewhat protocolaire is being constructively helpful and offers
                        from time to time what seems to us to be excellent suggestions and
                        advice.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>At meeting Committee on morning August 27 <persName corresp="#p_MRG1"
                            >Menzies</persName> announced no reply yet received from Egyptians;
                        suggested we try depart Thursday morning August 30 if answer should come
                        during course day; and suggested we adjourn until afternoon. I suggested
                        that we take advantage meeting to begin discussing various points of our
                        terms of reference and that we attempt find meeting of minds with regard
                        kind of approach we should make to <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> from point of view both procedure and contents.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> agreed and we spent
                        remainder of morning in quite useful discussion. It was decided that our
                        basic task would to be to obtain from <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> agreement to enter into International Convention
                        supplementary to that of 1888 and that we should try work with him Heads of
                        Agreement for use during negotiation such Convention. While discussing what
                        Heads Agreement should embrace, we ventured suggest Committee make analysis
                        of “Operations of Canal”, endeavor break down these operations into various
                        component parts with purpose ascertaining what aspects of operations might
                        be left to Egyptian handling without threat to non-political and efficient
                        management of Canal. Swedish Ambassador suggested that British shipping
                        people might be able give us useful information re various problems
                        connected with operation and number of them were invited to afternoon
                        session.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Our discussions re various phases operations during morning meeting were
                        of general character. We hoped we could become more specific after we had
                        talked with British shipping representatives. This hope did not materialize
                        since representatives in afternoon confessed ignorance of operational
                        activities of Canal and since we had no opportunity for discussion after
                        having quizzed them. They devoted their remarks for most part to stressing
                        superiority of European pilots and personnel over Egyptian and to
                        complaining of increasing difficulties which Canal authorities and ship
                        suppliers in Canal area had been encountering from Egyptians even before
                        nationalization. Their assertions of superiority of Europeans clearly did
                        not make good impression upon Iranians and Ethiopians. Nevertheless <pb
                            facs="0348" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/> latter remained placid and
                        continued try to be helpful. Our next meeting will be this afternoon and we
                        hope then make more progress in direction working out projects for Heads of
                        Agreement.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Early yesterday afternoon I called on French Ambassador. During course
                        conversation he displayed rigidity which not at all in keeping, in my
                        opinion, with realities. In brief his idea seemed to be that Committee was
                        expected to adhere strictly to terms of reference. Although he did not go so
                        far as to say it should not even illustratively indicate to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> how it would be possible for
                        international board to control basic operations of Canal without real
                        derogation Egyptian sovereignty, he nevertheless stressed that no details re
                        relations international manager with Egyptian Govt had been worked out as
                        far as he aware and thought Committee should therefore be extremely careful
                        not to give illustrations to which France might not be able to agree during
                        course subsequent negotiations.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I was somewhat surprised at attitude of <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn
                            Lloyd</persName>. In previous encounters which I had with <persName
                            corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> he had appeared relaxed and cordial.
                        On this occasion I found him apparently in state of tension. There was touch
                        of asperity in his voice. Without bothering about amenities he commenced
                        firing rather sharp questions: “What will you do if <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> says no, but—” “Will you accept
                        qualified reply?”; “How soon will you have answer for us? <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> has promised answer by Friday.” “If
                        your committee is to be of any use to us we must have answer without delay
                        and answer must be clear-cut.” I refused to be ruffled by his abruptness and
                        he gradually became a little more friendly. Nevertheless it seemed to us he
                        not happy re Committee, had little hope that Committee would be able to
                        bring kind of answer which would satisfy him, and in fact was somewhat
                        suspicious of Committee. He like French Ambassador made clear he expected
                        Committee would keep strictly within terms of reference and would not be too
                        imaginative in advancing illustrations showing their flexibility.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Later in afternoon I touched on these conversations with <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName>. He took position that we should
                        approach Egyptians in a spirit of conciliation; that while adhering firmly
                        to position that Canal should be under international management to extent
                        necessary for guaranteeing that it would operate effectively and not become
                        political instrument of any power, we should try to convince <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> (A) that this was possible without
                        infringing on Egyptian sovereignty and (B) that if <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> agreed to negotiations on basis of
                        our terms of reference, he would find that they had high degree
                        flexibility.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Barbour</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
