<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="410" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                            <head>410. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State,
                                Washington, October 29, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d410fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                    684A.86/10–2956. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RSW1">Rockwell</persName> on October 30.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-10-29"><hi rend="italic">October 29,
                                1956</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Israeli Military Move into Egypt</item>
                            </list>
                            <list type="participants">
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Ahmed Hussein</persName>,
                                    Ambassador of Egypt</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">William M.
                                    Rountree</persName>,</item>
                                <item><gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RSW1">Stuart W. Rockwell</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss></item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hussein</persName> called at
                                Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>’s request in
                                connection with reports of a serious Israeli military move against
                                Egypt. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> explained
                                that the Secretary had wanted to see the <pb facs="0872" n="832" xml:id="pg_832"/> Egyptian Ambassador personally but that he was
                                at the moment meeting with the British Charge and the French
                                    Minister.<note n="2" xml:id="d410fn2">See <ref target="#d109"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref></note></p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> reviewed for the
                                Ambassador the events of the past few days. He mentioned the reports
                                we had been receiving of large-scale Israeli mobilization, the two
                                messages sent to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> by the President urging restraint and
                                warning against forceful Israeli initiative, the public statement
                                issued by the White House along the same lines, and the decision of
                                the United States to reduce the number of American personnel in
                                certain Near Eastern states.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> said that the
                                Secretary desired the Ambassador to know that the United States
                                viewed with deep concern the reported Israeli military move into
                                Egypt. If the reports were confirmed, the United States contemplated
                                the Security Council’s being asked to take appropriate action. The
                                situation was very serious, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>, and he expressed the hope that the
                                Government of Egypt would not take action which would jeopardize a
                                clear-cut decision by the Security Council appropriate to the
                                circumstances. It was important that there be time for the United
                                Nations to take this appropriate action.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador asked whether the Secretary had in mind anything
                                beyond recourse to the Security Council. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> replied that this was the
                                first step. Other steps would presumably be based upon the Security
                                Council decision. In response to a further question from the
                                Ambassador, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> said
                                he believed that the Council might meet as early as tomorrow.</p>
                            <p>With reference to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>’s statement concerning the need for Egypt to
                                take no action which would jeopardize a clear-cut United Nations
                                decision, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hussein</persName>
                                said Egypt’s record was good. Despite large-scale provocations from
                                Israel over the past year or so, Egypt had restrained itself. It was
                                difficult to say what the Egyptian Government would do in these
                                delicate circumstances. He assumed that the Secretary did not mean
                                that Egypt should not defend itself. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> said that this was, of course, not the
                                case. It was just that we thought that the United Nations should be
                                at once seized of the matter and that nothing should jeopardize the
                                chances of quick United Nations action.</p>
                            <p>The Egyptian Ambassador went on to say that Egypt did not think that
                                Israel was a true entity. It was an artificial state created by the
                                United Nations, or certain big powers. There were some, he
                                continued, who thought that the big powers behind Israel had not
                                really tried to restrain it. He was speaking frankly, he added. Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> asked whether
                                the Ambassador meant the United States, <pb facs="0873" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> and the Ambassador reiterated that he was
                                speaking frankly. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> mentioned the steps he had already outlined
                                which the United States had taken in an effort to stop the present
                                Israeli action. The Ambassador asked whether Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> thought that if the United
                                States, United Kingdom and France really told Israel not to do
                                something, that Israel would still go ahead and do it. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> referred to the 1950
                                Tripartite Declaration of the United Kingdom, United States and
                                France, saying this had been reaffirmed many times. The Ambassador
                                said that nonetheless the Egyptian people and Egyptian Government
                                thought that not enough restraint had been placed upon Israel. Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> replied that
                                even so, the United States position opposing the use of force in the
                                area had been made very clear. We had stressed that we would take
                                action in and outside the United Nations to oppose aggression. The
                                Secretary was at that moment discussing the matter with the British
                                and the French.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> terminated by
                                reiterating the importance which the Secretary attached to this
                                matter and the Secretary’s desire that the Ambassador be urgently
                                and personally informed of this. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hussein</persName> thanked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> and took his
                                departure.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>