<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-30T15:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-30T15:40:00-05:00" n="433" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                            <head>433. Memorandum of Telephone Conversations Between the President
                                and the Secretary of State, Washington, October 30, 1956, 3:40 and
                                3:50 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d433fn1">Source:
                                    Eisenhower Library, Dulles Papers, White House Telephone
                                    Conversations. Transcribed by <persName corresp="#p_BPD1">Bernau</persName>. Another memorandum of this conversation,
                                    prepared in the Office of the President is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Whitman File, Eisenhower Diaries. It
                                    incorrectly indicates that this conversation began at 5:24
                                    p.m.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1956-10-30T15:40:00-05:00" to="1956-10-30T15:50:00-05:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"><hi rend="italic">October 30, 1956</hi>, <hi rend="italic">3:40 and 3:50
                                            p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">TELEPHONE CALL FROM THE PRESIDENT</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3:40 p.m.</hi></p>
                            <p>The Pres. said he has a second message from <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d433fn2"><ref target="#d434"><hi rend="italic">Infra</hi></ref>.</note> with an explanation—he will send it
                                over—he read the end of it. Here is something at last he is anxious
                                for us to understand. The Pres. told <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Hagerty</persName> not to issue the paper<note n="3" xml:id="d433fn3">Reference is to <ref target="#d430">Document
                                        430</ref>. At 3:24 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Hagerty</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and told him that “the Pres. wanted it
                                    [the message] differently. H. will sit and wait till he hears re
                                    releasing it.” (Eisenhower Library, Dulles Papers, White House
                                    Telephone Conversations)</note> until the <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. saw this. The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. said it has gone to London and
                                Paris but we don’t have to release it. The Pres. does not think it
                                does any damage to let them have it but maybe instead of releasing
                                it we should say we have sent a communication urging them to use the
                                greatest caution etc. The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. said
                                now they have done it they are going to try to get us to go along
                                with them. The Pres. said they could have sent it yesterday. The
                                    <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. said yesterday we might
                                have tried to stop it. The Pres. said if we let it go along etc.
                                etc. where do we get along with them against Communism. The Pres.
                                does not want to be associated with them in the Arab world. They
                                discussed handling it and the <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>.
                                said he would call after reading it.<note n="4" xml:id="d433fn4">i.e., <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName>’s second
                                    message.</note></p>
                            <pb facs="0911" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3:50 p.m.</hi></p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. called and said he is not
                                impressed by its sincerity. The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>.
                                thinks <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Hagerty</persName> should say it
                                has been sent. The Pres. said he just told him to write such a
                                statement. The Pres. will see the <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>. gets it.<note n="5" xml:id="d433fn5">Later that
                                    day the White House issued a statement indicating that upon
                                    learning of the ultimatum, President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> sent an urgent personal message to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MG2">Mollet</persName>. It also noted the
                                    President’s hope that the United Nations would be given full
                                    opportunity to settle the controversy through peaceful instead
                                    of forceful means and that the United States continued to
                                    believe that it was possible to secure by peaceful means a
                                    solution which would restore the armistice conditions between
                                    Egypt and Israel and achieve a just settlement of the Suez Canal
                                    controversy. (Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 12, 1956, p. 749; <hi rend="italic">United States Policy in the Middle East, September
                                        1956–June 1957</hi>, p. 142)</note></p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>