<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-31T09:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-31T09:15:00-05:00" n="443" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d443">
                            <head>443. Tentative Notes of the Secretary’s Staff Meeting, Department
                                of State, Washington, October 31, 1956, 9:15 a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d443fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                    Secretary’s Staff Meetings: Lot 63 D 75. Secret. Prepared by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Howe</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-10-31T09:15:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">October
                                            31, 1956, 9:15 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><p><persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> in the
                                        Chair.</p>
                                    <p>[Here follows items 2–4.]</p></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Aid to French and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss></hi>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">Elbrick</persName> said that Defense is asking what we
                                        should do about military aid and, notably deliveries coming
                                        out of the pipeline, including whether there should be now
                                        raised a condition that such material not be used in the
                                        Middle East troubles. It was pointed out that there already
                                        is a condition that aid material cannot be used in
                                        aggression. The Secretary indicated that he saw no reason
                                        why pipeline deliveries could not be continued unchanged. He
                                        asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">Elbrick</persName> to
                                        try and find out where the Israeli received the added group
                                        of Mysteres.</p>
                                    <p>[Here follows item 6.]</p></item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Suez—<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss></hi>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> indicated a growing sentiment to call the
                                        <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> under the Uniting for
                                    Peace Resolution<note n="2" xml:id="d443fn2"><gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> General Assembly Resolution
                                        377 (V), which provided for emergency sessions of the
                                        General Assembly.</note> which would require either 7
                                    members of the Security Council or a majority of total members.
                                    He noted that the Asian-African Group and the <gloss target="#t_Jugs1">Jugs</gloss> were moving in this
                                    direction. The Secretary noted that if we seem to oppose we
                                    would appear insincere. He also thought that if it is probable
                                    that the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> would be called it is
                                    better to lead. He inclined toward Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>’s recommendation,
                                    however, that we should <pb facs="0926" n="886" xml:id="pg_886"/> vote for but not initiate. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> reported that the Egyptian
                                        resolution<note n="3" xml:id="d443fn3">Reference is to the
                                        letter from the Egyptian Foreign Minister to the President
                                        of the Security Council, dated October 30. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> doc. <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/3712) See <ref target="#d439">Document
                                            439</ref>.</note> put in last night will probably be
                                    discussed today and they may supplement it with a resolution. In
                                    this connection the Secretary noted that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-French ultimatum had not been
                                    published and he thought it was in our interest that they did
                                    become available to the press. The inaccuracy of the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> account of various
                                    information on this subject going to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AWW1">Aldrich</persName> was also mentioned. Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Henderson</persName> reminded
                                    the Secretary that although <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> is the object of aggression he is still a
                                    villain. Discussion followed on the legal basis on which the
                                    British and French have taken this action. The Secretary noted
                                    that under the 1954 treaty with Egypt<note n="4" xml:id="d443fn4">Anglo-Egyptian Agreement Regarding the Suez
                                        Canal Base, October 19, 1954.</note> the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> is not justified to move in in
                                    response to action by the Israeli. On the other hand they could
                                    be justifying it, although he does not believe they have as yet,
                                    by the 1954 treaty on the basis that the nationalization of the
                                    Canal is a breach of the 1888 treaty which is a condition of the
                                    1954 treaty.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName> Correspondence</hi>—The Secretary
                                    mentioned that the President had received from <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName> last night a request to
                                    be free to use the correspondence which they had carried on
                                    during the day since there had been considerable public
                                    reference to it; and the President had acceded.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Israel Aid</hi>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> noted that an early
                                    decision will be needed as to whether we will apply sanctions on
                                    Israel in the form of holding aid (pipeline) shipments. The
                                    Secretary asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> to consider getting the Israeli
                                    Ambassador to declare more clearly the current Israeli purposes.
                                    The Secretary noted that the question of cutting off aid is a
                                    matter of degree and of abruptness because of the pipeline. The
                                    Secretary asked that a status report on our aid shipments should
                                    be requested of <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> and a
                                    comparable report on licensing.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">US Forces</hi>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> also indicated
                                    decision was needed on Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>’s letter on the disposition of US forces
                                    in the area.<note n="5" xml:id="d443fn5">See <ref target="#d428fn2">footnote 2, Document 428</ref>. Later
                                        on October 31, <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>
                                        telephoned <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> and
                                        told him that <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        believed that it would not be wise to appear to be moving
                                        combat military forces into the area. (Memorandum from
                                            <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> to
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, October
                                        31; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>)</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> said that he and
                                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> have a
                                    recommendation on this subject.</item>
                            </list>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>