<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>591. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, November
                    19, 1956</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d591</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">591</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recfZWpZzigwQIfjx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002653"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airline</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="591"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d591">
                <head>591. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, November
                    19, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d591fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 684A.86/11–1956. Secret. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BDC1">Bergus</persName> on November 26.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-11-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 19, 1956</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Israel</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Abba Eban</persName>, Ambassador of
                        Israel</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Zev Argaman</persName>, Minister, Embassy of Israel</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Robert
                            Murphy</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BDC1">Donald C.
                            Bergus</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> referred to the wish of the Israel
                    Foreign Minister to pay a courtesy call on the Acting Secretary. He noted that
                    the Acting Secretary had been unable to receive her on November 16 or 20.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d591fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> had disapproved a memorandum
                        dated November 15 from <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>,
                        which had recommended that <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>
                        receive <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> for 15 minutes at his
                        convenience. A note, dated November 19, attached to that memorandum
                        indicates that the recommendation was disapproved “in view of our action
                        regarding <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> visits” and because of <persName
                            corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>’s heavy schedule. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid</hi>., <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NE1"
                            >NE</gloss> Files: Lot 58 D 398, Memos to the Secretary thru <gloss
                            target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> June–Dec)</note> He stated that Mrs.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Meir</persName> would be available to visit
                    Washington at the end of this week or the beginning of next and that she would
                    be remaining in the United States until the middle of December.</p>
                <p>The Israel Delegation in New York had had many discussions with Western European
                    Foreign Ministers and their representatives. Israel was encouraged by their
                    feeling on Nasserism. Israel felt it essential that Western unity be restored.
                    The longer the present situation continued, the worse it would become.</p>
                <p>There had been much public discussion about justification for Israel’s action.
                    Everything which Israel had discovered since that action demonstrated its value.
                    Great arms stocks had been discovered in Sinai and Gaza, weapons of the most
                    modern categories had been found, orders to Egyptian troops indicating that
                    their ultimate mission was to destroy Israel had come to hand. A supply of very
                    deadly poison, presumably for use in Israel wells, had been found in Gaza.
                    Interrogation of prisoners had revealed not only Soviet philosophies but also
                    Nazi doctrines. There had been copies of “Mein Kampf” in Arabic everywhere which
                    probably reflected the efforts of <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName>’s Nazi German aides. The Egyptian order of battle had
                    been offensive. Had Israel sustained an assault later, world opinion might have
                    been more favorable, but the military risk would have been much greater. Israel
                    had been justified in what it had done.</p>
                <pb facs="1199" n="1159" xml:id="pg_1159"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> asked how far Israel had
                    intended to go in Egypt. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> replied
                    that Israel’s objective had been not territory but security. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> admitted that the question would be debated
                    in history for a long time, that Israel was distressed at the divergence between
                    the United States and Israel; but felt that the issue now at hand was a solution
                    to the problem. Israel felt that a great mistake had been made by a majority of
                    the members of the United Nations when it faced an eclipse of Nasserism, when
                    his military power was broken and Arab solidarity had been shown to be a myth.
                    There were echoes of Israel’s views in the Arab states and strong feelings along
                    these lines in Western Europe. The United Nations had put <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> back on his feet. This might have been
                    a case where the end would have justified the means.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> pointed out that among other
                    things there had been a tactical problem in the United Nations. Had there been
                    no United States resolution there might well have been a <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> resolution on the subject. The other
                    statements made by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> raised the
                    whole issue of “preventive war” as a justifiable course of international
                    conduct.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> wondered how far we could go in
                    relying on the United Nations as the only and exclusive guide. If the United
                    States made this the only criterion, then the West was at a disadvantage. The
                    United Nations could curb the use of force by free countries but not by the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and probably the Arabs. Therefore the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had a monopoly of force. The numerical
                    composition of the General Assembly was such that it would not adopt a
                    resolution opposed by the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, the Arabs and
                    their Asian friends. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> stated
                    that the General Assembly had passed a resolution on Hungary. The <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had profited by Near Eastern developments. He
                    mentioned <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName>’s developing views on
                    Hungary in response to Indian public opinion on the subject.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that the General Assembly
                    would not uphold European, Commonwealth, Mediterranean, or Israel interests. The
                    United Nations Charter had been used to defend the chief violator of the
                    Charter. Mr. <persName>Argaman</persName> uttered the aphorism about he who
                    comes into equity must come with clean hands. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                        >Murphy</persName> commented that as he understood the law both intent and
                    act were factors in leading to a judgment. In this instance it appeared that the
                    only action had been Israeli.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that the main problem now was
                    the implementation of the cease-fire and withdrawal resolutions. All depended on
                    the manner of implementation. If the United Nations entered the picture and
                    Israel withdrew then <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> returned to
                    his previous positions, there would be a new explosion. It was possible to avoid
                    this if implementation were carefully handled. Had Israel withdrawn <pb
                        facs="1200" n="1160" xml:id="pg_1160"/> from Sinai prematurely, the United
                    Nations force would not now be in Egypt. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eban</persName> understood that the Security General was grateful for
                    this.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> would begin his negotiations with
                    the Secretary General on November 20. Israel was prepared to leave the Sinai
                    Peninsula if the United Nations forces occupied keypoints preparatory to a
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>-Egyptian agreement for demilitarization of
                    the Peninsula without prejudice to Egyptian sovereignty. With respect to Tiran
                    and the adjoining area, the Israel action had succeeded in opening an
                    international waterway. Israel would pose three alternatives: either leave
                    Israel in Tiran, leave the islands empty, or place a United Nations force there.
                    The same principle applied to Gaza. Gaza could not be demilitarized but all
                    Israel could say was that nothing would be less prudent than to bring <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> back to Gaza.</p>
                <p>There was a great debate going on in Israel with respect to the ultimate
                    disposition of Gaza. The territory was too small to be attractive but the
                    security aspects of the problem might well be overriding. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> asked if Israel wanted United Nations
                    forces in Sinai. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> replied yes, to
                    be followed by demilitarization. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                        >Murphy</persName> said that it seemed to him that this proposal would have
                    to be imposed on the Egyptians. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName>
                    said that would depend on what the Egyptians wanted to gain from the present
                    situation. Israel understood that if it asserted a claim to Gaza it would
                    undertake a great responsibility. Israel had stated that it did not want the
                    Egyptians to return. Israel thought that it wanted Gaza, certainly with its
                    original population. The problem of the refugees there would have to be solved
                    in terms of Israel and other capabilities to absorb them. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PL1">Pearson</persName> of Canada and some Western European
                    representatives had indicated understanding of Israel’s position on Gaza.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> inquired if Israel was in a
                    position to give the facts concerning Soviet equipment captured. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that Israel was writing a report on
                    the subject and that he had told Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen
                        Dulles</persName> that Israel would provide information. Israel had the idea
                    that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had been preparing to fight for
                    the Canal. Returning to his forthcoming discussions with the Secretary General,
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that he felt Israel’s
                    desiderata could be negotiated within the terms of the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1"
                        >UNGA</gloss> resolutions. A fourth point was the Anglo-French position on
                    the Suez Canal; the British and French were interested in what would come in
                    their place.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said that we had been
                    encouraged by the apparent willingness of Egypt to accept a United Nations force
                    to occupy the Canal zone and clear the Canal. He hoped that this would give an
                    opportunity to relax the blockade of the Canal.</p>
                <pb facs="1201" n="1161" xml:id="pg_1161"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> turned to the United Nations draft
                    resolution of November 3 on Palestine.<note n="3" xml:id="d591fn3">Reference is
                        to the U.S. draft resolution on Palestine tabled in the General Assembly on
                        November 3; see <ref target="#d485">Document 485</ref>.</note> He felt that
                    the resolution should make room for the concept of a negotiated settlement. He
                    admitted that negotiations might not be the only way to a settlement but felt
                    that they should not be excluded. He wondered whether the resolution would be
                    passed. The Arabs would oppose it, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    might, and then others in Asia and Africa would also oppose it. If it failed of
                    passage then there would be a serious setback. The United States might have to
                    amend this resolution to refer to previous <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                    resolutions. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> indicated that this
                    possibility would be distasteful to him.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said he had not seen the
                    results of any canvass of United Nations delegations. There was tentatively some
                    hope that the resolution could be passed. Some delegations would doubtless be
                    influenced by developments in the area. Some momentum had to be initiated.
                    Perhaps if the Suez resolution went through first then progress could be made on
                    the Palestine resolution. The United States was not wedded to the present
                    resolution, but felt that we must get away from the present fragile condition
                    where fighting could resume. The problems posed by the Near East crisis were
                    bigger than <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that views varied on
                    statements made by the President and others as to possible United States
                    reactions to Soviet moves in the area. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eban</persName> felt that we had created some uncertainty in the Russian
                    mind. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said that it was
                    difficult to gage Moscow thinking because of certain indications of instability
                    in the judgment of the men in power there.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that Israel would enter the
                    Hungarian debate in the General Assembly. The Soviets could not be more abusive
                    to Israel than they had already been. In the long run, the United States could
                    not hope to compete with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> in winning
                    Arab favor. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> inquired if a policy
                    had developed with respect to <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1957 economic
                    assistance to Israel. The Israelis had been informed by <gloss target="#t_ICA1"
                        >ICA</gloss> that they were ready to proceed once the Department
                    approved.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> pointed out that current
                    economic aid plans for the Near East were in suspense until we could see how the
                    situation in the area developed. It was much in the mind of the President that
                    if a long-term solution to Near East problems could be achieved that the United
                    States would want to make an important contribution to such a solution.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> mentioned El Al Israel Airline’s
                    difficulty in obtaining United States export licenses for spare parts, and the
                    cessation of <pb facs="1202" n="1162" xml:id="pg_1162"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> oil deliveries to Israel. He said that
                    while the major problems affecting the area were important, he did not feel that
                    pressures on Israel were a constructive way of achieving solutions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
