<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>75. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, August 9,
                    1956, 3:40 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-08-09T14:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-08-09T14:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-09T14:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-09T14:40:00-05:00" n="75"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                <head>75. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, August 9,
                    1956, 3:40 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d75fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, Central Files, 974.7301/8–956. Secret. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BSCJ1">Blackiston</persName>. The time of the meeting is
                        from <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’ Appointment Book.
                        (Princeton University Library, Dulles Papers)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-08-09T15:40:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 9, 1956, 3:40 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Suez Canal, Canadian Jets for Israel, Export-Import Bank Loan</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Abba Eban</persName>, Ambassador of Israel</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Reuven Shiloah</persName>, Minister
                        Plenipotentiary</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_BSCJ1">Slator C.
                            Blackiston, Jr.</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Suez Canal:</hi> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                                >Eban</persName> remarked that Israel was the only state
                            discriminated against by Egypt in the matter of passage through the Suez
                            Canal. However, the Security Council resolution of 1951 does not
                            specifically refer to Israel shipping but to the right of free passage
                            of all vessels of all nations to all ports wherever bound. Israel
                            supports the London statement confirming the right of all nations to
                            passage through the Canal. Although Israel has no financial interest in
                            the Suez Canal Company, it is naturally interested in the preservation
                            of international contracts. The discrimination by Egypt against Israeli
                            shipping began while the British were still in control of the Suez base
                            and the Canal Company in the “plentitude” of its rights.</p>
                        <pb facs="0219" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said <persName
                                corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn Lloyd</persName> had explained the failure
                            to invite Israel to the Conference on the grounds that were Israel to
                            attend, Egypt might refuse. Assuming that Egypt does not attend, could
                            not an invitation to Israel be reconsidered?<note n="2" xml:id="d75fn2"
                                >During a conversation with Assistant Secretary <persName
                                    corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> on August 4, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_SR1">Shiloah</persName> requested, on instructions
                                from the Israeli Government, that Israel be invited to the
                                forthcoming Suez Conference. <persName corresp="#p_SR1"
                                    >Shiloah</persName> said that similar representations were being
                                made in Paris and London. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1"
                                    >Allen</persName> said that he would repeat the request to
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, but advised
                                that it was not in the interest of the United States or Israel that
                                the Palestine dispute be interjected into the Suez affair.
                                (Memorandum of conversation by <persName corresp="#p_BSCJ1"
                                    >Blackiston</persName>, August 4; Department of State, Central
                                Files, 974.7301/8–456)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that invitations to countries in the third (pattern of
                            trade) category were based on a mathematical formula. Thus, in this
                            category only nations 50% or more of whose trade passed through the
                            Canal were invited. The Government of Israel intends to seek assurances
                            from the 24 nations invited to the forthcoming conference that they
                            support the 1951 Security Council resolution. These assurances were
                            being sought in a confidential manner but public expressions of support
                            would be appreciated. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                                >Eban</persName> stated that he was confident of the U.S. position
                            and had therefore informed his Government of United States support of
                            the resolution.</p>
                        <p>An assurance from the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> has already
                            been obtained. The Secretary asked whether memorandum on this subject
                            would be submitted since we wished to know how the question was
                            formulated before giving a definitive reply. Our Panama Canal
                            relationship has to be considered. The Ambassador replied that a note
                            would be forthcoming.<note n="3" xml:id="d75fn3">On August 13, the
                                Israeli Embassy forwarded to the Department of State a note which
                                contained the Government of Israel’s position concerning Israel’s
                                right to transit the Suez Canal. In paragraph 10 of the note, the
                                Government of Israel noted the verbal assurances given by Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> on August 9 that
                                the United States would continue to uphold the right of free passage
                                through the Canal by ships of all nations wherever bound, and stated
                                its assumption that the United States would insist on ensuring free
                                passage for Israeli shipping. In paragraph 11, the Government of
                                Israel expressed the confident hope that during the forthcoming
                                Conference in London, the U.S. representative “will demand the
                                abolition of the present restrictions against Israeli shipping and
                                will seek the inclusion in any arrangement of the future operation
                                of the Canal of effective guarantees to avert the recurrence of any
                                discrimination against Israel shipping and against the shipping of
                                other nations bound to and from Israel.” (<hi rend="italic"
                                    >Ibid</hi>., 974.7301/8–1356) On August 16, the Israeli Embassy
                                forwarded to the Department of State a supplementary note, which
                                quoted several U.S. statements made before the Security Council in
                                support of the Israeli position. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                974.7301/8–1656)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> expressed the
                            opinion that if <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> was able
                            to get away with his seizure of the Suez Canal, he would seek new worlds
                            to conquer. Control of the oil resources of the <gloss target="#t_ME1"
                                >ME</gloss> and the elimination of Israel were his goals. Whether or
                            not the present crisis is overcome, it has become obvious that the
                            strength of the Western <pb facs="0220" n="180" xml:id="pg_180"/> world
                            is dependent upon the whim of one man who controls the lifeline of the
                            Suez. Means to lessen this degree of dependence should be explored.
                            Suggested projects to this end include: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Increased experimentation in the field of nuclear reactors to
                                    replace the need for oil as a fuel.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Larger tankers for use on the Cape of Good Hope route.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>An alternate canal through Israel to lessen the bargaining
                                    power of Egypt. Whether or not the need is sufficiently great to
                                    justify the enormous expense of construction is the principal
                                    question.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>A pipeline from the Gulf of Aqaba through Israel to the
                                    Mediterranean with an extension to Haifa to permit the refining
                                    capacity located there to be utilized. A pipeline had been
                                    considered by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company some years ago. A
                                    somewhat prophetic report on this project was prepared in which
                                    it was stated that the continued security of the Suez route for
                                    the future was not assured and that a pipeline through Israel
                                    would be beneficial in negotiations with the Arab states through
                                    which the present pipelines pass. The report estimated that the
                                    Israel pipeline could be completed in one year and would cost
                                    £20 million. A present obstacle in the pipeline is Egypt’s
                                    control of the islands at the mouth of the Straits of Tiran. It
                                    can be assumed that a tanker with oil bound for the Israel
                                    terminus of the pipeline would be fired upon by Egyptian
                                    batteries. Such resort to force would not be sustained by public
                                    opinion and resistance to the assault would be justified.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>A discussion of the legality of Egyptian control of the Straits of Tiran
                            ensued. The Secretary wondered whether the three mile limit did not
                            constitute a legal basis for Egyptian control. Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> held that the Corfu ruling<note
                                n="4" xml:id="d75fn4">Reference is to the Corfu Channel Case decided
                                by the International Court of Justice in 1949.</note> sustained the
                            freedom of navigation of such restricted seas. Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> said that Israel hoped for a
                            peaceful solution to the Suez problem but that failure of the conference
                            might result in Western military action. The West would therefore be
                            placed in need of bases from which to operate. It was inferred that such
                            bases would be available in Israel.</p>
                        <p>To speculate that Israel will not be attacked by Egypt would not be wise,
                            said the Ambassador, since <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                                >Nasser</persName> was reckless and had displayed his recklessness
                            in nationalization of the Canal.</p>
                        <p>According to the Secretary excessive dependence on Suez has been a
                            problem which has bothered the State Department for a long time. Any
                            situation which jeopardizes the Canal is likely to jeopardize the
                            pipelines as well and thus far, we have no alternatives. The Western
                            world can get over the loss of Arab oil on a short-term basis. However,
                            the long-term effect would be critical. Although the West is dependent
                            on oil, the Arab countries are likewise dependent on oil royalties. A
                            possibility of alternatives to the Canal is however, <pb facs="0221"
                                n="181" xml:id="pg_181"/> very important. History has shown that
                            when a monopolist attempts extortion alternatives to the product of the
                            monopolist are found. It is a good idea to permit it to be known that
                            other Canal routes and new pipelines are being considered.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Canadian Jets for Israel:</hi> The Israel Ambassador
                            expressed the opinion that the implementation of the “agreement” between
                            the U.S. and Canada to permit Canadian jets to be supplied to Israel
                            should go forward in secret with the U.S. supplying the arms which would
                            justify Canadian action. If this could be done, Israel would inform
                            Canada that the U.S. had fulfilled its commitment and would seek to
                            convince the Canadians to sell F–86s without publicity.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary replied that we still felt that it would not be prudent to
                            seem to be expediting planes to Israel lest it appear as a retaliatory
                            move against <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>. The Suez
                            situation is not improved if it takes on the aspect of an Israel-Arab
                            dispute. Despite public pronouncements to the contrary, there is a
                            genuine feeling among certain influential groups in Arab nations that
                                <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s attitude gives
                            rise to fears of his ultimate intentions. We do not wish any action on
                            our part with respect to Israel to cause this opposition to <persName
                                corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> to change to support.<note
                                n="5" xml:id="d75fn5">On August 10 <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                                    >Eban</persName> forwarded to <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                                    >Dulles</persName> a letter which among other points asked that
                                the United States: (1) clarify to the Governments of France and
                                Canada that the postponement sought by the United States affected
                                publication of specific arms shipments to Israel, not the actual
                                measures toward shipment; and (2) issue normal export permits for
                                the arms requested without publication. (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Ibid</hi>., 611.84A/8–1056)</note>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Export Import Bank Loan:</hi> The Ambassador stated that,
                        according to his information, the Export Import Bank had completed its
                        report on Israel’s loan application. Israel would appreciate being able to
                        bring this matter to a satisfactory conclusion. The Ambassador hoped to be
                        able to see Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> on
                        this subject after Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> returns
                        from his vacation.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
