<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>90. Telegram From the Delegation at the Suez Canal Conference to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-08-17T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-08-17T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-17T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-17T15:00:00-05:00" n="90"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                <head>90. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation at the Suez Canal
                        Conference</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d90fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 974.7301/8–1756. Secret; Priority. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>. Received at 5:55 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-08-17T21:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 17, 1956—9 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 15. Secretary met this morning with
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PC1"
                        >Pineau</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d90fn2">According to the schedule for August 17, prepared by
                        the U.S. Delegation, the Secretary’s calls on <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1"
                            >Eden</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> began at 12:15 p.m. The chronology,
                        prepared by the U.S. Delegation for that date, indicated <gloss
                            target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 15 is the only account of these
                        conversations. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., Conference Files: Lot 62 D
                        181, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 753)</note> to discuss general
                    tactics. Understood that <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> will speak
                    this afternoon’s plenary session. <persName corresp="#p_SDT1"
                        >Shepilov</persName> also indicated to <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1"
                        >Eden</persName> that he would wish speak today. Consensus was that general
                    debate should if possible be completed Saturday, understood that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> would endeavor to be last speaker so
                    that he can draw general summary and be in position respond particularly to
                    speeches by <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, India, Indonesia and Ceylon.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> plans principal speech for
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> in course Saturday session.</p>
                <p>Secretary said he had been giving considerable thought to type of declaration or
                    resolution which should be submitted to Conference.<note n="3" xml:id="d90fn3"
                        >Draft proposals were discussed at meetings of the British-French-American
                        working group on August 14 and 16. For accounts of the discussion, see
                        memorandum by First Secretary of the Embassy in London <persName
                            corresp="#p_WEM1">Evan Wilson</persName>, August 14 (<hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid</hi>., Central Files, 974.7301/8–1556) and <gloss
                            target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MC1">MC</gloss>/17,
                        August 16 (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Conference Files: Lot 62 D 181,
                            <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 745).</note> He wanted to have ample
                    time to discuss paper. He was thinking of declaration in terms so couched as to
                    get maximum number of subscribers, consistent with basic principles for
                    settlement included in his August 16 speech. He wondered whether best procedure
                    might then be to seek the designation of committee which would be charged with
                    negotiations with Egypt pursuant to general <pb facs="0257" n="217"
                        xml:id="pg_217"/> declaration, suspending present Conference to give
                    committee time to negotiate.</p>
                <p>Consensus appeared favor this general procedure. Arrangements made for staff
                    level and then high-level US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>–France–Australian
                    meeting tomorrow to go over draft declaration which Secretary undertook provide.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> suggested that declaration
                    should not be too weak. He said that immediately after general debate Secretary
                    might table paper Saturday evening in order provide opportunity delegates to
                    study it over weekend and discuss it Monday. Secretary questioned advisability
                    US taking sole responsibility for tabling “tough text” which inevitably would be
                    watered-down. This would place US in awkward position since any subsequent
                    modification would appear represent defeat. Moreover he had been talking with
                    several delegates (this morning with Iranian and Pakistani)<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d90fn4">The conversation between <persName corresp="#p_DAW1"
                            >Dulles</persName> and Pakistani Foreign Minister Choudhury began at
                        10:30 a.m., and the one with Iranian Foreign Minister Ardalan at 11:30 a.m.,
                        both on August 17. Memoranda of these conversations, prepared by the U.S.
                        Delegation, are <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., <gloss target="#t_CF1"
                            >CF</gloss> 753.</note> who were anxious to be helpful but who had
                    domestic political preoccupations which must be met without sacrificing basic
                    principles. He did not want to ride “rough-shod” over their objections to a
                    strong line. Papers should take reasonably into account their views in order to
                    rally as much support as possible from the outset and avoid subsequent softening
                    process.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> observed that it is frequently
                    dangerous to endeavor too much of a definition, but that inclusion in proposal
                    of certain points of definition might improve prospects for general acceptance.
                    He had in mind questions of who would arrange for payment to Suez Canal Company
                    and who would arrange financing future development of Suez Canal. Answer to
                    these questions, he said might turn attitude of several countries like Pakistan
                    and India to support proposal. If international body could assume
                    responsibility, advantages to Egypt would appear very great and it obviously in
                    Egypt’s interest to accept. He strongly favored this approach in lieu any
                    indication of harsh proposition to be forced upon Egypt.</p>
                <p>Secretary thought question of payments to Suez Canal Company and investments in
                    development Canal itself were primarily matters for negotiation by committee
                    with <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> and Canal Company. He felt however that
                    international board should have responsibility for both matters. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MRG1">Menzies</persName> agreed and felt this would offer
                    advantages to <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> that government could not
                    refuse. Plan should make it clear that international board would be non-profit
                    and that arrangements would be made by international board for compensation to
                    Company and future of Canal.</p>
                <pb facs="0258" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/>
                <p>Secretary observed that financing future development of Canal, including parallel
                    Canal, might be quite feasible if Canal users could have confidence in its
                    operation. He thought oil companies and other users might be prepared put up
                    considerable capital to be amortized out of proceeds. On other hand if
                    responsibility for operation should continue rest with Egypt countries would in
                    common prudence seek alternatives to Canal which eventually would be by-passed
                    for most part and become wasting asset.</p>
                <p>Responding <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName>’s comment that offer
                    should not be too attractive so that it would appear that Egypt had greatly
                    benefited by her rash action, <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName>
                    observed that no one would think that if international control were injected.
                    Secretary agreed saying that acceptance international control by <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> would represent major political defeat
                    for him.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Pineau</persName> observed that in addition other
                    important questions, was that of who would be responsible for policing of Canal
                    under arrangements now being thought about. He said that treaty might have
                    clause to effect that any interruption in transit of Canal would be considered
                    act of aggression as defined in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter, and
                    thus provide basis for protection.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
