<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-07-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="167" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d167">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 147.]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Commissioner of
                                    the United States to China</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking,
                                    China</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-07-31"><hi rend="italic">July 31,
                            1901</hi></date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith a
                        translation of a note addressed to the dean of the diplomatic corps by the
                        Chinese plenipotentiaries on the 27th instant, giving the terms of an
                        Imperial decree creating the Board of Foreign Affairs. The Emperor gives
                        this board precedence in official rank over the heretofore” existing six
                        great ministries (or boards) of state, and appoints a president, two
                        ministers, and chiefs of bureau with the rank of vice presidents of boards
                        to it.</p>
                    <pb facs="0298" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                    <p>The decree is in absolute conformity with the requests of the foreign
                        representatives contained in the note of the dean of the diplomatic corps to
                        the Chinese plenipotentiaries of April 22 last, copy of which was sent you
                        with my No. 131 of July 9.</p>
                    <p>The president of the foreign office is I K’uang, better known as Prince
                        Ch’ing, who has been president of the Tsungli Yamen since 1884.</p>
                    <p>The two ministers, who are to be with him the responsible heads of the
                        office, are: (1) Wang Wen-shao, a native of the province of Che-kiang, a
                        member of the Grand Council of State (or Imperial Cabinet); he has held many
                        high offices of state, having been twice a minister of the Tsungli Yamen and
                        Viceroy of Chih-li; and (2) Ch’ü Hung-chi, a native of Hu-nan, formerly
                        Vice-president of the Board of ceremonies; he has recently been raised to be
                        a member of the Grand Council of State.</p>
                    <p>The two chiefs of bureau have both had experience in the diplomatic service.
                        Hsü Shou-peng was secretary of legation in Washington under Chang Yin-huan,
                        and until recently held the position of minister to Korea. He understands a
                        little English. Lien Fang is an accomplished French scholar. He accompanied
                        Anson Burlingame’s mission abroad, has been secretary of legation in France,
                        and is French secretary of Prince Ching.</p>
                    <p>On the whole, the composition of the new ministry may be considered as quite
                        satisfactory, and makes a new and most important change in our relations
                        with China, giving as it does preeminence to the foreign relations of the
                        Empire over all other branches of its administration.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Chinese
                                    Plenipotentiaries</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">de
                                    Cologan</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-07-27"><hi rend="italic">July 27,
                                1901</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: On the 22dof April we had the
                            honor to receive a communication from your excellency in which you
                            pointed out that by Article XII of the Joint Note the Chinese Government
                            shall undertake to reform the Office of Foreign Affairs.</p>
                        <p>At the time we presented the matter, as communicated by your excellency
                            to us, in a memorial to the Throne, and asked for the issuance of a
                            decree on the subject. We have now received a telegram from Si An,
                            stating that the grand secretariat on the 24th of July received the
                            following decree:</p>
                        <p>“Hitherto the appointment of officials and assigning to them the
                            performance of certain official duties was for the reason that they
                            could do what is suitable as occasion required. As the treaties are now
                            being revised and settled, the first essential is to give due importance
                            to the question of friendly intercourse among nations. To cultivate
                            friendly relations in a sincere and faithful manner we must depend on
                            our subordinates being men of the right caliber.</p>
                        <p>“The Tsungli Yamen was created for the purpose of transacting
                            international affairs. Although it has been in existence for many years,
                            the princes and ministers appointed to the charge of the duties thereof
                            have been intrusted with the discharge of many other duties, and in
                            consequence they have been Unable with their entire energies and
                            faculties to attend properly to the duties of the office. It is right,
                            therefore, that special offices be created in order to assign to each
                            incumbent his proper duty or responsibility. It is hereby ordered that
                            the Tsungli Yamen be changed to Wai-wu Pu, Foreign Office, and it shall
                            take precedence of the six Boards.</p>
                        <p>Prince Ch’ing is hereby appointed President; the Grand Secretary, Wang
                            Wen-shao, is appointed Minister, and the President of the board of
                            works, Chü Hung-chi, is transferred to the Wai-wu Pu as minister, with
                            the title of Shang shu (i. e., President of a board).</p>
                        <p>Hsü Shou-peng, director of the imperial stud, and Lien Fang, an expectant
                            director of a minor court, are hereby appointed chiefs of bureau with
                            rank of senior and junior <pb facs="0299" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/>
                            vice-presidents. As to the other officers, secretaries, etc., their
                            number and rank, the rules of appointment, salaries and grain
                            allowances, let these matters be referred to the Board of Administration
                            and board of civil office to be considered at once and a report thereon
                            presented to us.”</p>
                        <p>As in duty bound, we transmit the above decree changing the Tsungli Yamen
                            to the Wai-wu Pu to your excellency, and will thank you to communicate
                            same for the information of your colleagues.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>