<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Rockhill to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-03-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-03-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="93"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 52.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Commissioner of the United States to China</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking, China</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-03-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 29, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The diplomatic corps held a meeting to-day to
                    consider a number of pending questions relating to the negotiations.</p>
                <p>The French minister submitted the following proposition to govern in estimating
                    the claims for legation guards and volunteers, which were agreed to <hi
                        rend="italic">ad referendum:</hi>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>As regards killed or wounded soldiers, in case a claim is to be made on
                            their account it shall be fixed at the sum of the pension to be paid
                            said soldier or his family according to the laws of his country.</p>
                        <p>As regards volunteers killed or having been wounded so as to incapacitate
                            them for work, the indemnity to be asked shall be calculated on the
                            position (situation) of said volunteer and the damage resulting
                            therefrom to himself or his family.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>As, however, these classes of claims come under the heading of “Claims of
                    Governments,” according to the report of the committee of indemnities, I think
                    these propositions are of no special value or importance.</p>
                <pb facs="0126" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/>
                <p>The question was then put to the various representatives as to the acceptance by
                    their Governments of the report of the Committee on indemnities, copy of which
                    report was inclosed in my No. 42 of the 14th instant. The representatives of
                    Russia, France, Germany, and Holland informed the meeting that their Governments
                    had accepted it, conditionally, of course, on its acceptance by all the powers.
                    I stated to my colleagues that I did not expect my Government to express an
                    opinion on the subject until our proposal asking for a general lump indemnity to
                    be divided among the powers proportionately to their losses and expenses had
                    been passed upon. This proposal I communicated formally to the diplomatic corps
                    in a memorandum dated the 28th of March. I inclose a copy herewith.</p>
                <p>The British minister then asked the meeting to agree to extend the limit of time
                    for the presentation of private claims from May 1 to May 14 next. This was
                    agreed to with the qualifying words “sauf exceptions justifiées.”</p>
                <p>The German minister then proposed that the military commanders here be requested
                    to prepare a joint report on the measures to be adopted for carrying out
                    Articles VIII and IX of the Joint Note. Although nine of the representatives had
                    been instructed by their Governments to favor a conference of the military
                    representatives of only such powers as were prepared to take part with their
                    forces in the measures adopted, the Russian and Austro-Hungarian ministers and
                    myself having stated that our Governments, as signatories of the Joint Note,
                    considered that they had the right to take part in the discussion of these
                    questions, which had all a very important political side, it was therefore
                    decided to invite all the military commanders here to bring about at an early
                    date such a conference.</p>
                <p>I then read to the conference the report which I had prepared with the Japanese
                    minister as to the reforms to be introduced into the office of foreign affairs
                    and the court ceremonial for the reception of foreign representatives in public
                    audiences. The report was unanimously adopted without any important
                    modifications, except the omission of the words Tsung-li Yamen as the Chinese
                    name of the office of foreign affairs, which all the representatives, except the
                    Japanese minister and myself, wish to have changed.</p>
                <p>I regret that it was not possible to carry out better the instructions contained
                    in your telegram of December 31 last to Mr. Conger, in which you said— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">if not all on modern lines, it would be highly desirable
                            to have a minister of foreign affairs who shall speak at least one
                            European language. He should be in a position to take his orders from
                            the Emperor.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In view of the fact that the ministers who will, under the prince president, be
                    at the head of the office of foreign affairs must be men of very high position
                    in the state, wielding great power and having recognized influence, and that
                    there is no one in China at the present time with such qualifications who speaks
                    any foreign language, it was felt that to insist on your views would result, if
                    adopted, in placing men of no standing or power in positions of great importance
                    and responsibility. None of the men who have been sent abroad by China to hold
                    diplomatic positions—the only ones who know anything at all of foreign
                    languages—have rank, influence, or strength enough to hold the position of
                    minister of foreign affairs and fight with any chance <pb facs="0127" n="121"
                        xml:id="pg_121"/> of success the battle of reform which must shortly begin
                    here and in which they must take a leading part.</p>
                <p>In view of the above considerations, it was deemed advisable to only recommend
                    that at least one of the two vice-ministers which the powers seek to have
                    appointed shall know some foreign language. Some of China’s diplomatic
                    representatives abroad might fill these positions very advantageously, and later
                    on perhaps become ministers in the office of foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>I inclose copy of the report as it was finally accepted by the conference.</p>
                <p>After disposing of this work the meeting adjourned.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum</hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Government of the United States is of opinion that the amount of the
                        indemnity to be demanded by the powers of China should be as reasonable as
                        possible, and in no ease exceed the power of China to pay. Whatever be the
                        method by which it is computed this indemnity should be demanded of China in
                        one lump sum, without explanation, specifications of reasons for the demand,
                        or indication of the proportion asked by each power.</p>
                    <p>If, however, the claims of the various powers amount to a sum exceeding the
                        power of China to pay, they should be proportionately reduced so that the
                        sum of the demand should not exceed the limit indicated above.</p>
                    <p>If the powers accept this proposition, after payment by China of the sum
                        demanded, an equitable fraction calculated on the losses sustained and the
                        disbursements of each state should be allotted to each one of them, and each
                        power should undertake the indemnification of its nationals.</p>
                    <p>If the powers think that a settlement of the question of the distribution of
                        the indemnity among them on the lines indicated above presents too great
                        difficulties at Peking, the Government of the United States proposes that it
                        shall be submitted to the Arbitral Tribunal of The Hague.</p>
                    <p>In other words, the Government of the United States proposes to the powers to
                        fix among themselves a reasonable sum as a lump indemnity, to demand it
                        without details or explanations of China, and to divide it afterwards among
                        the powers proportionately to their losses and disbursements.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-03-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 28, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the commission on the reform of the Office of
                            Foreign Affairs and on the modification of court ceremonial.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Article XII of the joint note provides:</p>
                    <p>“The Chinese Government undertakes to reform the Office of Foreign Affairs
                        and to modify the court ceremonial concerning the reception of the foreign
                        representatives in the sense which the powers shall indicate.”</p>
                    <p>The representatives of the powers have charged the Minister of Japan, the
                        Plenipotentiary of the United States, who with their sanction have added the
                        Counselor of the German legation, to submit a report on the reforms which
                        they consider indispensable to attain the end which the powers had in view
                        in imposing this demand on China.</p>
                    <p rend="center">I.</p>
                    <p>As to the reform of the Office of Foreign Affairs, the commission is of
                        opinion that to put this bureau in a better condition to promptly and
                        regularly transact its business it would be necessary to place in it a small
                        number of personages of high rank <pb facs="0128" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/>
                        and having unquestionable power and influence with the central government.
                        To them should be intrusted by the Emperor the exclusive conduct of direct
                        relations with the foreign representatives. These personages should be
                        directly responsible to the Emperor for their actions and consequently be
                        members of the cabinet of the Emperor (Chun-Chi Chu), or have free access to
                        him as a result of their high rank in the state.</p>
                    <p>The commission consequently recommends that at the head of the Office of
                        Foreign Affairs there should be a Prince (Ch’in Wang), with the title of
                        President of the Office of Foreign Affairs.</p>
                    <p>As it is presumable that the other duties of the Prince President will
                        prevent him devoting all his time to the duties of the Office of Foreign
                        Affairs, the commission is of opinion that under him there should be two
                        ministers (Ta Chen), members of the Chun-Chi Chu, who could take his place
                        in case of absence, and who would have all the necessary authority to
                        transact all current business.</p>
                    <p>These three high officials only would carry on direct relations with the
                        representatives of the powers and receive the foreign ministers for that
                        purpose.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that these three high officials would either singly or
                        collectively receive the representatives of the powers and transact business
                        with them.</p>
                    <p>Although it would be desirable that the above-mentioned personages should
                        have personal knowledge of foreign affairs and of the methods now generally
                        followed by all nations of the world in conducting public business, in
                        provision, however, of their lack of experience, the commission recommends
                        that there should be in the Office of Foreign Affairs two Vice-Ministers,
                        who from their personal experience would be able to place the administration
                        of the office in greater harmony than at present with the methods obtaining
                        abroad. One of them at least should know a foreign language.</p>
                    <p>The commission is of opinion that, with the modifications enumerated above,
                        the transaction of diplomatic affairs with the Office of Foreign Affairs
                        would become easier, more regular, and more rapid.</p>
                    <p rend="center">II.</p>
                    <p>Concerning the modification of Court ceremonial relating to the reception of
                        the foreign representatives the commission has only deemed it its duty to
                        consider the question of public or solemn audiences.</p>
                    <p>The commission is of opinion that the annual audiences given the diplomatic
                        corps by the Emperor should take place in the T’ai-ho Tien, and that those
                        which may be given from time to time to a single representative should be in
                        the Chien-Ching Kung.</p>
                    <p>In every case the Emperor should receive the representatives standing and
                        speak directly to them.</p>
                    <p>On the first audience to present his letter of credence or in the case of the
                        presentation of a letter of the head of his State, an Imperial sedan chair
                        and a guard of honor should be sent by the Emperor to take the
                        representative at his residence and conduct him to the Imperial palace. The
                        representative should be taken back therefrom with the same ceremony. In
                        these audiences the representative should pass, until he has presented his
                        letters, by the central doors; on leaving the audience he should comply with
                        the custom already established in this respect.</p>
                    <p>The Emperor should receive directly in his own hands the letters which the
                        representatives of the powers may have to present to him.</p>
                    <p>As regards the banquets which may be offered by the Emperor to the diplomatic
                        corps, these should be in the Chien-Ching Kung, and the Emperor should
                        assist in person.</p>
                    <p>In going to solemn audiences the representatives of the powers should be
                        carried in their sedan chairs to in front of the hall in which the Emperor
                        is to receive them; they should take their departure in the same way.</p>
                    <p>Such are the principal points on which the commission is of opinion that it
                        would be proper to insist, so that the Court ceremonial relating to the
                        reception of foreign representatives should comply with the established
                        usages between independent and equal nations.</p>
                    <p>The ceremonial details not mentioned here which may develop in the settlement
                        of this question should all be incorporated in the protocol which will be
                        prepared with the Chinese plenipotentiaries.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jutaro Komura.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron von der Goltz.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-03-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 29, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
