<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="113" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.20/173</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-16">June 16, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear George</hi>: I have received your interesting
                            air mail letters of May 20 and 21, 1941,<note n="7" xml:id="d113fn7">Letter of May 21 not printed.</note> wherein you comment on the
                            possibility of a military alliance between the United States and Cuba.
                            You also discuss the purpose of the proposed military and naval mission
                            to Cuba.</p>
                        <p>I understand your misgivings that any efforts made indirectly by
                            President Batista or his Government to suppress talk about an alliance
                            might be misconstrued. I am of the opinion, however, that an alliance of
                            this nature would not materially assist in advancing the defense
                            arrangements of this Hemisphere; on the contrary, in some countries such
                            a move might readily be misunderstood. I still believe, therefore, that
                            this matter should be kept in the background. In view of Dr. Saladrigas’
                            remarks, mentioned in your air mail despatch no. 2061 of May 23,<note n="8" xml:id="d113fn8">Not printed.</note> and of the adjournment of
                            the Cuban Congress, this may not be as difficult as was anticipated.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the possibility of our furnishing Cuba with a military or
                            naval mission, or both, I agree with the suggestion made in your
                            despatch no. 2132 dated June 5, 1941,<note n="8" xml:id="d113fn9">Not
                                printed.</note> that for the present no action is <pb facs="0111" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> necessary and that we should await the
                            action of the Cuban Government before doing anything further.</p>
                        <p>As to what the duties of the members of these missions would be, that
                            would seem to me to be a matter principally for determination by the
                            Cuban military and naval authorities. The assistance of our military and
                            naval attachés in Cuba in this regard might be of considerable value. In
                            several cases the War Department has sent an officer, at the request of
                            the American republic concerned, to investigate the needs of that
                            country with a view to choosing the personnel of a military or aviation
                            mission. I am told that, were Cuba to request such a preliminary survey,
                            the War Department would be prepared to send a qualified officer to Cuba
                            to carry it out.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>