<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-27T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-27T16:00:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.12/1588a: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-27T17:00:00-04:00">April 27, 1941—5
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>196. Please seek an early appointment with President Avila Camacho and
                            say that the Department feels that satisfactory and rapid progress is
                            being made in the preparations for the early successful termination of
                            the general negotiations. As to the specific problems, you may make the
                            following observations:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Claims</hi>. Since the two Governments appear to be
                            substantially in agreement, the differences between our original
                            proposals and the Mexican counterproposals of February 17 should be
                            readily adjusted.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>. This Government has been favorably
                            impressed by the progress made in joint discussions and by the adoption
                            of the Convention relating to military aircraft.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Oil</hi>. Very confidentially and informally this
                            Department has been exploring through oil experts of the Interior
                            Department who are in touch with a representative of Petróleos Mexicanos
                            the possibilities of arriving at a formula for the solution of the oil
                            controversy. Progress in the studies is being made about as rapidly as
                            could be expected and it is hoped they may lead to a satisfactory
                            formula. The oil question appears to be the most difficult of those
                            under consideration.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Foreign Debt</hi>. While this Government has not been a
                            party to negotiations involving past agreements, the Department has been
                            interested to learn of resumption of discussions between Señor Suárez
                            and Mr. Lamont, and it is hoped that they will work out a mutually <pb facs="0392" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/> satisfactory solution of this
                            problem. If the Department can assist in this matter it will be glad to
                            exercise its unofficial good offices.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">International Waters</hi>. This difficult question has
                            been given much careful thought. The following statement is strictly
                            confidential but you may convey it to President of Mexico for his own
                            information: We have been endeavoring in confidential conversations with
                            certain United States interests to find a solution and expect to have a
                            response from these interests soon.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Economic Cooperation</hi>. Arrangements have already
                            been made for Treasury Department experts to begin discussions possibly
                            in the near future with Mexican representatives concerning mutual
                            monetary problems with specific reference to stabilization and
                            silver.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Quota for Importation of Mexican Oil</hi>. It will be
                            difficult to approach this problem before the two countries enter upon
                            negotiations for a reciprocal trade agreement.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Highway Construction</hi>. We expect to be prepared
                            soon to discuss the matter of cooperating in financing of Mexican
                            highway construction.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Trade Agreement</hi>. Our present feeling is that
                            public notification of intention to negotiate should be deferred until a
                            formal solution of the oil expropriations matter has been found. Our
                            preliminary studies have virtually been completed. It is suggested
                            Mexico likewise prepare for later discussions on this subject.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>