<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Panamanian Ministry for Foreign Affairs to the American Embassy in
                    Panama</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="334"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d334">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711F.1914/171</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Panamanian Ministry for Foreign
                            Affairs</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Embassy in
                            Panama</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="8" xml:id="d334fn8">Copy transmitted to the Department in Embassy’s
                        despatch No. 860, January 8; received January 11.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. The arrangement between the United States and Great Britain involving United
                    States destroyers<note n="9" xml:id="d334fn9">See <ref
                            target="frus1940v03#pg_49">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 49</ref> ff.</note> of a value of
                    several millions of balboas does not appear to represent only the fair value of
                    the privately-owned land within the leased areas. Other considerations of a
                    wider scope are those which have weighed in the minds of both Governments and
                    explain and justify the agreements signed. These considerations are very similar
                    to those which at present motivate the request made by the Government of
                    Washington of the Government of Panamá for the establishment of air bases and
                    electric detectors and searchlights at different points in the Republic; and for
                    that reason it appears logical to hope that, in fixing the rental price for the
                    areas required for such purposes, the same criterion will be applied which
                    inspired the arrangements recently effected between the United States and Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>Panamá is ready to cooperate in the general defense of the Hemisphere; but it
                    must necessarily abide by the interpretation which all the American nations have
                    given to this commitment, according to which such cooperation cannot involve any
                    obligation affecting the sovereignty or the political independence of an
                    American State.</p>
                <p>It cannot be denied that in the defense of the Western Hemisphere in which the
                    United States is so nobly engaged, the Isthmus is a beneficiary; but so is the
                    United States, in the first instance, and the remaining countries of the
                    Continent. And there is no just reason why Panamá, one of the smallest and
                    poorest of the American Republics, should bear all the burdens without any
                    appreciable benefit.</p>
                <p>The Canal defense plan, prepared by the United States War and Navy Departments,
                    represents practically the military occupation of the Isthmus by North American
                    armed forces, and this circumstance cannot be considered and accepted by the
                    Republic of Panamá as a result of the obligation incumbent upon it in the
                    defense of the Hemisphere. No Panamanian citizen would have signed a commitment
                    having such a scope and no Latin American nation would ask of Panamá such a
                    sacrifice, if they were consulted.</p>
                <p>2. Although it is true that in the last paragraph of Article 2 of the General
                    Treaty between Panamá and the United States signed in <pb facs="0425" n="417"
                        xml:id="pg_417"/> 1936 both countries “recognize their joint obligation to
                    insure the effective and continuous operation of the Canal and the preservation
                    of its neutrality”, it is also true that this obligation, as respects “the
                    utilization of lands or waters additional to those already employed” only binds
                    the Government of the Isthmus “in the event of some unforeseen contingency”. And
                    it could not be otherwise, since in the first paragraph of the same article “the
                    United States of America declares that the Republic of Panamá has loyally and
                    satisfactorily complied with the obligations which it entered into under Article
                    2 of the Convention of November 18, 1903”<note n="10" xml:id="d334fn10">
                        <ref target="frus1904#pg_543">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1904, p. 543</ref>.</note> and
                    that “in recognition thereof the United States of America hereby renounces the
                    grant made to it in perpetuity by the Republic of Panamá of the use, occupation
                    and control of lands and waters which may be necessary and convenient for the
                    construction, maintenance, operation and protection of the Panama Canal …”.<note
                        n="11" xml:id="d334fn11">Omission indicated in the original <hi
                            rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>With regard to the application of Article 10 of the General Treaty the point of
                    view of the Department of State merits the most careful attention and respect.
                    Nevertheless, the present situation, however difficult it may be, does not seem
                    yet to present an imminent threat of aggression “which would endanger the
                    security of the Republic of Panamá or the neutrality or security of the Canal”
                    justifying measures affecting the territory under the jurisdiction of the
                    Panamanian Government without adequate compensation for the consequent burdens
                    and sacrifices.</p>
                <p>The cooperation which Panamá offers the North American people “nobly and
                    sincerely”, as His Excellency the President of the Republic, Dr. Arnulfo Arias,
                    expressed it in beautiful words in his recent address, is inspired by the very
                    deep desire of giving particular effect to the “good neighbor” policy, which
                    honors so signally His Excellency President Franklin D. Roosevelt, rather than
                    by the contractual obligations to which the Isthmus and the great Nation of the
                    North are parties.</p>
                <p>3. The Government of Panamá has learned with real pain of the slight importance
                    which the Government of the United States seems to attach to the sacrifice which
                    the concession of further lands means for the Isthmus. Their intrinsic value
                    cannot serve as a basis for lease negotiations between two sovereign countries,
                    because their value is not the same in the international sphere. Panamá would
                    never grant to any country at any price the use of any part of its territory;
                    and it is only by virtue of the special relations which bind it to the United
                    States that it agrees to consider with sympathy the request made by the
                    Government of Washington.</p>
                <pb facs="0426" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                <p>It is hoped that the Department of State, in a broadly comprehensive spirit, will
                    reconsider its offer and grant to Panamá a reasonable price for the projected
                    leases more in consonance with the burdens, dangers and moral sacrifices which
                    such concessions impose upon the country.</p>
                <p>4. The jurisdiction which the United States shall exercise over the leased areas
                    must be defined precisely before the drafting of the contracts. The Government
                    of Panamá insists that the Government of the United States shall have
                    jurisdiction only over military personnel on duty in the leased areas and that
                    all other persons residing therein, whatever their nationality may be, shall be
                    under Panamanian jurisdiction.</p>
                <p>5. If the grant of new lands is made in the spirit of Articles 2 and 10 of the
                    Treaty of 1936, cited by the Department of State, we must agree that once there
                    has disappeared the “unforeseen contingency” or the “threat of aggression which
                    would endanger the neutrality or security of the Canal”, “the sites required for
                    the purpose of defending the neutrality or security of the Canal” are no longer
                    necessary and their utilization must revert to the Republic of Panamá. It is not
                    conceivable that the “unforeseen contingency” or “threat of aggression” last
                    more than six years and consequently contracts for a longer period would not be
                    justified under these clauses. However, if the “unforeseen contingency” or the
                    “threat of aggression” should still be imminent, the contracts could most surely
                    be extended. It is not possible that in cases such as these any Panamanian
                    Government would object to the extension of the contracts in question.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Panamá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-07">January 7,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
