<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-02-17T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-02-17T13:00:00-05:00" n="342" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d342">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711F.1914/183: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-02-17T13:00:00-05:00">February 17, 1941—1
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>27. Your 25, February 13, 5 p.m., and 27, February 14, 8 p.m. You are
                            requested to obtain an interview with the President of the Republic and
                            hand him an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi><note n="19" xml:id="d342fn19">Ambassador Dawson handed the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> to President Arias on February 18.</note>
                            which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Government of the United States has given careful
                                    consideration to the views expressed by the Government of
                                    Panama, as set forth in the communication handed to the
                                    Ambassador of the United States by His Excellency the Minister
                                    of Foreign Affairs on February 13. The Government of the United
                                    States has likewise received with satisfaction the assurances
                                    conveyed to the Ambassador of the United States on February 14
                                    by His Excellency the President of the Republic.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States, noting with pleasure the
                                    expression of the sincere desire of the Government of Panama to
                                    give its most ample cooperation to the Government of the United
                                    States in the general defense of the hemisphere and confident as
                                    it is of the joint desire of the two Governments to fulfill the
                                    obligations incumbent upon them by reason of the General Treaty
                                    of Friendship and Cooperation, signed on March 2, 1936, refers
                                    specifically to the second paragraph of Article II of the said
                                    treaty, which reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>‘While both Governments agree that the requirement of
                                            further lands and waters for the enlargement of the
                                            existing facilities of the Canal appears to be
                                            improbable, they nevertheless recognize, subject to the
                                            provisions of Articles I and X of this Treaty, their
                                            joint obligation to insure the effective and continuous
                                            operation of the Canal and the preservation of its
                                            neutrality, and consequently, if, in the event of some
                                            now unforeseen contingency, the utilization of lands or
                                            waters additional to those already employed should be in
                                            fact necessary for the maintenance, sanitation or
                                            efficient operation of the Canal, or for its effective
                                            protection, the Governments of the United States of
                                            America and the Republic of Panama will agree upon such
                                            measures as it may be necessary to take in order to
                                            insure the maintenance, sanitation, efficient operation
                                            and effective protection of the Canal, in which the two
                                            countries are jointly and vitally interested.’</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States likewise refers to the
                                    provisions of Article X of the said treaty, which reads as
                                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>‘In case of an international conflagration or the
                                            existence of any threat of aggression which would
                                            endanger the security of the Republic of Panama or the
                                            neutrality or security of the Panama Canal, the
                                            Governments of the United States of America and the
                                            Republic of Panama will take such measures of prevention
                                            and defense as they may consider necessary for the
                                            protection of their common interests. Any measures, in
                                            safeguarding such interests, which it shall appear
                                            essential to one Government to take, and which may
                                            affect the territory under the jurisdiction of the other
                                            Government, will be the subject of consultation between
                                            the two Governments.’</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States has reached the conclusion
                                    that, in accordance with the provisions of the second paragraph
                                    of Article II above quoted, a contingency has now arisen not
                                    foreseen <pb facs="0437" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/> at the time
                                    of the signature of the Treaty of 1936 which requires the
                                    utilization by the United States of additional lands for the
                                    effective protection of the Canal.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States has likewise reached the
                                    conclusion that, in accordance with the terms of Article X of
                                    the Treaty of 1936 above quoted, an international conflagration
                                    has broken out bringing with it the existence of a threat to the
                                    security of the Panama Canal which requires the taking of
                                    measures for the defense of the Canal on the part of the
                                    Government of the United States.</p>
                                <p>These measures of defense require the utilization of certain
                                    tracts of land within the territory of the Republic of Panama
                                    and outside of the Canal Zone, which tracts have been indicated
                                    to the Government of Panama by the appropriate authorities of
                                    the United States.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States therefore requests of the
                                    Government of Panama that, for the reasons above cited and in
                                    accordance with the provisions of the Treaty of 1936 above
                                    quoted, the Government of Panama transfer to the authorities of
                                    the United States the said tracts of land at the earliest
                                    opportunity. The Government of the United States stands ready,
                                    in accordance with the spirit of cooperation which animates both
                                    Governments, to consult immediately with the Government of
                                    Panama in order that a satisfactory agreement may be reached
                                    covering the method of transfer and the amounts to be fixed by
                                    agreement between the two Governments as equitable compensation
                                    for the lands whose utilization is now required.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States takes pleasure in stating
                                    that when and if the conditions which have now arisen and which
                                    require the utilization of the said tracts of land for the
                                    defense of the Panama Canal or for its effective protection
                                    cease to exist, the Government of the United States will return
                                    to the jurisdiction of the Republic of Panama the tracts of land
                                    in question.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In your conversation with the President of the Republic, you may make it
                            clear that the communication which you are requested to hand to him is
                            sent by direct instruction of the President.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Brin has been informed that the President will receive him on
                            February 18. At that time the President will make clear to him the
                            serious view which he takes of this continued delay on the part of the
                            Government of Panama in carrying out its treaty obligations. The
                            President will likewise emphasize his belief that while the Government
                            of the United States stands always ready and willing to consider in the
                            most friendly spirit any request which the Government of Panama may make
                            of it for economic or financial assistance, such requests for assistance
                            cannot be regarded as forming any part of the discussions relating to
                            the carrying out by the Republic of Panama of the treaty obligations
                            incumbent upon it through the provisions of the Treaty of 1936.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>