<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-02-28T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-02-28T16:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711F.1914/194: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Panama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-02-28T16:00:00-05:00">February 28, 1941—4
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 9:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>33. Department’s telegram No. 34, February 25. <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi> was handed the Minister of Foreign Relations
                            yesterday. This noon he informed me that he had studied the <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi> with the President, that the
                            Panamanian Government desires to make available the defense sites
                            without further delay, and that it has been decided so to advise the
                            National Assembly at a conference to be held Monday morning at the
                            Foreign Office. The Minister stated further that for the information of
                            the people at large it is planned to issue an appropriate press
                            communiqué on Monday afternoon. He said that as soon as these steps have
                            been taken the Government will be prepared to discuss the <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> for making the tracts immediately
                            available to our military authorities.</p>
                        <p>The Minister said that somewhat later next week he would hand me a reply
                            to the Department’s <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>. From his
                            remarks this morning I believe that he will admit [<hi rend="italic">submit?</hi>] a counter proposal for the agreement touching
                            jurisdiction and that he will also submit his comments on certain other
                            points. I shall report by air mail regarding this phase of our
                            conversation.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>