<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="449" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">833.24/67<hi rend="superscript">2/4</hi></note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Minister in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-24">January 24, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Ed</hi>: My answer to your letter of December
                                26<note n="2" xml:id="d449fn2">Not printed.</note> has been somewhat
                            delayed, as I wished to give you the latest information on the situation
                            affecting Uruguay’s request for armaments.</p>
                        <p>I can assure you that this matter is in no manner escaping our attention.
                            It forms a part of a larger problem: how the United States can arm
                            itself rapidly and at the same time furnish supplies to Great Britain,
                            China, Greece, and the American countries. In order to obtain an
                            adequate concept of the situation in so far as it affects the American
                            republics we are now, with the help of the War and Navy Departments,
                            considering all the requests for arms and munitions which these
                            countries have submitted in order to estimate the most urgent needs of
                            each country, our capacity for meeting them and the financial problems
                            involved. It was to facilitate this that we asked you to request the
                            Uruguayan Government to submit officially its request for war matériel
                            in the form described in the circular instruction of September 25,
                                1940.<note n="2a" xml:id="d449fn2a"><ref target="frus1940v05#pg_13"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 13</ref>.</note> It is in this
                            connection that programs or schedules are being drawn up for each
                            country showing how and when deliveries can be made, as well as the
                            estimated financial requirements. As we informed the Uruguayan Minister
                            in Washington,<note n="3" xml:id="d449fn3">José Richling.</note>
                            Uruguay’s need for a loan to effect armament purchases is being
                            considered in connection with this program.</p>
                        <p>When you have a convenient occasion to mention this subject to Dr.
                                Guani<note n="4" xml:id="d449fn4">Alberto Guani, Uruguayan Minister
                                for Foreign Affairs.</note> or any other appropriate official of the
                            Uruguayan Government, will you please convey to him my assurances that
                            we are keeping Uruguay’s request constantly in mind and shall not fail
                            to transmit to you or to Señor Richling at the earliest opportunity
                            information <pb facs="0558" n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> concerning the
                            dates on which supplies can be made available together with the
                            financial requirements connected therewith.</p>
                        <p>You may be interested to hear that Señor Richling transmitted to us
                            several weeks ago official copies of the list of war matériel, compiled
                            according to our circular of September 25 and forwarded to him by the
                            Uruguayan Government. These are now under consideration in connection
                            with the plan described above.</p>
                        <p>With all kind regards [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>