<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Ambassador to Colombia ( (Braden), ), Temporarily in
                    Washington</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">60</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recgNB1TfjBBo9Fg4" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041888"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Electric power plant</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recZfUQWqS4grj8JT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022006054"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">National debt</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Munitions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="60"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">821.51 Cooperation Program/3</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador to Colombia</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Braden</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in Washington</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-16">April 16,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Colombian Request for Financial Assistance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As will be recalled, President Santos on January 30, 1941, summoned me to
                    indicate that Colombia would appreciate receiving in the near future financial
                    assistance for both economic and military purposes.</p>
                <p>Following other conversations with the President and his Ministers, which were
                    reported to the Department, Dr. Santos on the morning of March 31, 1941 had
                    delivered to me a letter and memorandum, as per the enclosed copies,<note n="78"
                        xml:id="d60fn78">Not printed.</note> requesting a $10,000,000 loan for 10
                    years to be made direct to the Colombian Government (<hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                    to the Banco de la Republica with the Government’s guarantee, as was done last
                    year).</p>
                <p>The proceeds of this $10,000,000—17,500,000 pesos according to the enclosed
                    memorandum would be distributed: <list>
                        <label>I</label>
                        <item>—Military requirements 7,000,000 pesos or $3,990,000.</item>
                        <label>II</label>
                        <item>—Economic requirements (irrigation, highways, public buildings and
                            electric power plant machinery) 9,850,000 pesos or $5,614,500.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>My observations on certain details of the military requirements are given in the
                    enclosed memorandum. It is pertinent to add that I have expressed to President
                    Santos, the Minister of War and Ambassador Turbay<note n="79" xml:id="d60fn79"
                        >Gabriel Turbay, Colombian Ambassador in the United States.</note> my purely
                    personal opinion that the Export-Import Bank might be unable, under its
                    authorization, to grant credits for military purposes, but that subject to
                    priority restrictions Colombia’s necessities in these particulars probably could
                    be cared for under the provisions of the “Lend-Lease Bill”<note n="80"
                        xml:id="d60fn80">Act approved March 11, 1941; 55 Stat. 31.</note> and in
                    that case the interest rate and other terms might be more advantageous to
                    Colombia than through a straight banking operation.</p>
                <p>There is also enclosed copy of memorandum<note n="78" xml:id="d60fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> handed me by Ambassador Turbay—pursuant to Dr. Santos’
                    promise to forward further details to me. It will be noted that the amount
                    requested in this document—7,000,000 pesos—covers only the program for this year
                    of the Ministry of Public Works. The Ambassador estimates that the Ministry of
                    National Economy will need between 3,500,000 and 4,000,000 pesos for its plan of
                    irrigation and power plant construction. <pb facs="0066" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                    These last two items in the President’s memorandum total 3,638,000 pesos. The
                    Ambassador includes 1,000,000 pesos for navigation, not in the President’s
                    memorandum, increases the public building estimate by 500,000 pesos and reduces
                    the highway item in the President’s memo by 712,000; as a result his total
                    estimated requirements range from 10,500,000 to 11,000,000 pesos. The latter
                    maximum figure plus the military requirements would bring Colombia’s total
                    request to 10¼ million dollars. However, it is worthy of comment that on the
                    public works program alone the government plans to expend an additional
                    6,000,000 pesos or $3,420,000 from internal sources. This evidences good faith
                    and is in a manner a guarantee of the soundness of the loan.</p>
                <p>I also call attention to the Ambassador’s remarks pointing to the urgency of this
                    financial aid for the preservation of his country’s economic and social
                    equilibrium.</p>
                <p>Dr. Turbay mentioned Argentina having received recently an interest rate of 3½
                    percent and hopes the same may be done for Colombia.</p>
                <p>I confirmed to Ambassador Turbay the assurances given me by President Santos that
                    since he recognized the difficulties of our position certain guarantees as to
                    exchange would be given to this loan. I said that while the extension of a
                    credit perhaps should not be made contingent on these guarantees, nevertheless
                    the following should be considered coincidently: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Foreign exchange should be made quickly and readily available to our
                            exporters. Exchange permits should be issued at the same time with
                            import permits.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Exchange regulations should not be made retroactive, as has been done
                            heretofore with prejudice to American exporters.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>It should be possible to accomplish an adjustment and renewal of
                            service on some of Colombia’s foreign indebtedness, such as that of the
                            Agricultural Mortgage Bank; the City of Bogotá and the Departments of
                            Santander and Santander del Norte.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Similarly, exchange should be provided so that service on the
                            Barranquilla loan would henceforth be remitted to the
                            bondholders.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The National City–First of Boston Banking Group loan should be
                            refunded to avoid repeated renewals thereof every six months.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>More detailed comment on the foregoing and on other points is given in the
                    enclosed memorandum. I do not recommend the adjustment of these several matters
                    being exacted as a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the granting of a
                    loan but I do feel they should be discreetly called to the attention of our
                    Colombian friends.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador that President Santos on March 28, 1941, after talking with
                    me, had summoned the Manager of the Agricultural Mortgage Bank and the Mayor of
                    Bogotá to insist to them that an attempt be made promptly to accommodate their
                    respective foreign debt situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/>
                <p>Dr. Turbay acknowledged that at the time when the national debt offer had been
                    approved by the Under Secretary<note n="82" xml:id="d60fn82">Sumner
                        Welles.</note> and Messrs. Morgenthau<note n="83" xml:id="d60fn83">Henry
                        Morgenthau, Jr., Secretary of the Treasury.</note> and Jones,<note n="84"
                        xml:id="d60fn84">Jesse H. Jones, Secretary of Commerce.</note> he had
                    promised that a representative of the Agricultural Mortgage Bank would come to
                    the United States to negotiate. The Ambassador inferred that this visit had been
                    deferred because there was no one with whom he could deal, since manifestly
                    Colombia could not with dignity and self respect carry on discussions with the
                    Foreign Bondholders Protective Council, Inc.</p>
                <p>I replied that my personal suggestion, and I had no idea of the Department’s
                    views in the premises, was for some one person to be fully authorized by both
                    the bank and the Municipality of Bogotá, to come here and begin informal
                    conversations. During the course of such discussions I said perhaps a way to a
                    formal settlement would be uncovered and at least Colombia would have taken this
                    step to indicate her good faith.</p>
                <p>Respecting the Bankers Group loan, the Ambassador said the National City Bank
                    officials had displayed scant interest to negotiate when he had suggested a
                    refunding at 3 percent and amortization of $1,000,000 per year to liquidate the
                    indebtedness in approximately 15 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusion:</hi> The economic purposes to which the larger
                    part of this financing will be dedicated appear to be sound and should improve
                    the country’s productive capacity in several particulars. The servicing of this
                    credit probably will not be too great a burden on Colombian capacity to pay. For
                    us to lend assistance in this manner, from the political and diplomatic aspect,
                    is a worthwhile gesture. It is expedient for Colombian economy to be supported
                    by us in these times. Therefore, I recommend that favorable consideration be
                    given to this project.</p>
                <p>The 7,000,000 pesos requested for military ends is of course dependent on many
                    production and priority conditions here with which I am unacquainted. However, I
                    recommend that it might be beneficial to us in principle and assist in the
                    defense of the Panama Canal were special consideration to be given to the
                    following items in President Santos’ memorandum. <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Aviation 2,700,000 pesos, or $1,539,000. As per my memorandum, it
                            might even be advantageous to increase this allotment.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Repair of two destroyers, estimated at something in excess of
                            $200,000.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Munitions for rifles, machine guns and ammunition therefor. Cost to be
                            estimated.</item>
                        <pb facs="0068" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Six fast motor torpedo 70 to 80 ft. boats with equipment of torpedoes
                            and depth charges. Cost estimated at $1,365,000.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The remaining military requirements do not impress me as being essential for
                    Colombia nor of benefit to us.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Spruille Braden</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
