<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Colombia ( (Braden) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-06-25T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-06-25T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-25T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-25T16:00:00-05:00" n="8"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/892: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Braden</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-25T16:00:00-05:00"
                            >June 25, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 9:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>235. For Under Secretary. Referring to my despatch No. 1458, March 28, last
                    paragraph and Department’s telegram No. 127, paragraph number 5. By reason of
                    his uniquely influential position as a conservative leader who has closely
                    collaborated with the liberal governments of Olaya, Lopez and Santos, I have
                    long cultivated Urdaneta Arbelaez’ friendship. Among other things I have
                    encouraged his idea <pb facs="0017" n="9" xml:id="pg_9"/> that Colombia in
                    particular should emulate us in making naval and air bases available to other
                    American Republics. Simultaneously I have emphasized my inability to broach such
                    a proposal to the authorities here and instead have said it should be
                    volunteered by his Government.</p>
                <p>Urdaneta since his retirement as Ambassador to Argentina has become member of
                    Advisory Council to Foreign Ministry and is therefore thoroughly familiar with
                    staff agreements and related matters. June 20 when dining with him <hi
                        rend="italic">en famille</hi> he expounded at some length that political
                    difficulties of the American Republics such as Colombia would be greatly eased
                    were staff agreements to be formalized in a general agreement approved by
                    conference of Foreign Ministers. Despite considerations of my telegram 224, June
                        20,<note n="24" xml:id="d8fn24">Not printed.</note> paragraph No. 2, he felt
                    such a conference now would be successful, suggested Rio de Janeiro as locale
                    since Brazilians would keep Argentina under control and he believed that by
                    giving Castillo<note n="25" xml:id="d8fn25">Ramón Castillo, Acting President of
                        Argentina.</note> credit for initiative it would accommodate latter’s
                    position vis-à-vis radicals and bring Argentina into full cooperation; in fact
                    Urdaneta himself would be willing to go to Buenos Aires to work to this end. By
                    reason of Urdaneta’s influence as an outstanding possible conservative
                    presidential candidate and since Laureano Gomez and De la Vega have argued for
                    such a conference he believes Conservative Party could be estopped from attacks
                    on conference results. He concluded by offering to discuss in detail with Santos
                    to which I said I had no objection providing that he presented whole idea as
                    entirely his own and that my role was exclusively as a listener since I was
                    unauthorized even to discuss it informally. In response to my inquiry he was
                    confident through a conference of this kind utilization of air and naval bases
                    by all could be embodied in basic inter-American agreement which in practice
                    would mean our being sole beneficiaries.</p>
                <p>… I have always considered it would be unwise for me even informally first to
                    bring up topic of Colombian bases being made available to us. On the other hand
                    since we might at some time wish to enjoy these facilities I have considered it
                    advisable to encourage Urdaneta on his own to explore the situation. In fact I
                    feel that Santos’ suggestion (my telegram No. 158,<note n="26" xml:id="d8fn26"
                        >May 17, 11 p.m., <ref target="#pg_4">p. 4</ref>.</note> section (<hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>)) to formalize staff agreements by an exchange of notes
                    to be ratified by Congress was induced by Urdaneta.</p>
                <p>Last night at intimate dinner in the Embassy Urdaneta said he had a conversation
                    with Santos yesterday who requested him to tell me: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The President believes that a rapidly convened and quickly terminated
                            meeting of Foreign Ministers now would be entirely successful.</item>
                        <pb facs="0018" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Sole purpose thereof should be to establish bases of cooperating to
                            meet the new and portentous developments resulting from the war and
                            further to insure hemisphere solidarity and defense.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>A formalized multilateral agreement embodying staff conversations and
                            reciprocal use of bases would constitute conference’s main
                            accomplishment and would greatly facilitate acceptance of those
                            undertakings by congresses and public in many countries.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>He preferred to handle the matter himself and not to have it even
                            discussed with anyone including the Minister of Foreign Relations until
                            it was further advanced.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>He was most friendly in his references to me and hoped I would call
                            soon when he would discuss the entire subject.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In view of this last indication I ought to request interview with Santos within
                    the next few days. However, my conversations with Urdaneta have been so guarded
                    that I can easily without slightest embarrassment to anyone dismiss entire
                    subject as informal chats between two friends or I can with equal facility push
                    forward in whatever degree the Department may desire.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Please instruct what if anything you may care to have me do.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Braden</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
