<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-05-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Baron <persName type="from">Fava</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy
                                        of His Majesty the King of Italy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-05-11"><hi rend="italic">May 11, 1895</hi></date>.
                                (Received May 16.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State</hi>: I have the honor
                            herewith to transmit to you a copy of a dispatch whereby His Excellency
                            Baron Blanc calls <pb facs="0227" n="961" xml:id="pg_961"/> the
                            attention of the signatory powers of the general act of Brussels of July
                            2, 1890, to the provisions of that act concerning the slave trade and
                            the prohibition to introduce arms and ammunition into Ethiopia, and also
                            to the necessity of causing those international provisions to be
                            observed and respected.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased to accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fava.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Baron <persName type="from">Blanc</persName> to
                                    Baron <persName type="to">Fava</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Royal Ministry or Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Borne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-04-20"><hi rend="italic">April 20, 1895</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador</hi>: Italy, having occupied the
                                coast of the Bed Sea from Ras Oasar to the Strait of Bab el Mandeb,
                                founded the colony of Eritrea, established and proclaimed her
                                protectorate over Ethiopia and its dependencies, not only took part
                                heartily and in perfect good faith in the Brussels conference, not
                                only signed the general act of July 2, 1890, considering that her
                                honor was thereby pledged, but in the first place she included in
                                her African treaties the obligation to suppress slavery,<note n="1" xml:id="d142fn1">Treaty of amity and commerce with Sultan
                                    Mohammed Anfari, of Haussa, dated December 9, 1888 (Art.
                                    VIII).</note> and in the second place desired that all the local
                                chiefs who are her dependents on the coast of the Red Sea and on
                                those of the Gulf of Aden and the Indian Ocean from Bender Ziadeh to
                                the mouth of the Juba should conform to the provisions of that act
                                for humanitarian purposes and the promotion of civilization, and
                                should signify their acceptance of the obligations resulting
                                therefrom.</p>
                            <p>Thus, while we were directly striving to suppress the slave trade on
                                the coasts possessed by us, first Menelik and next all the sultans
                                and chiefs who have treaties of protectorate with Italy—the Dan call
                                chiefs and headmen,<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">Solemn declaration
                                    of August 2, 1893, made before the civil commissioner of Assab
                                    by Abdelrahman Sheikh Yusef and by Ahmed Dini. representing
                                    Sultan Mohammed Anfari, and by the principal Dancali chiefs and
                                    headmen.</note> the Sultan of Obbia,<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn3">Declaration of November 20, 1891.</note> the Sultan of the
                                    Migertini<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn4">Declaration of November
                                    16. 1894.</note>—assumed, under the supervision of the Italian
                                Government, the obligation to observe the provisions of the Brussels
                                act so far as it relates to the slave trade and the trade in arms
                                and spirits.</p>
                            <p>The Italian Government took care to cause that obligation to be
                                respected, and succeeded so well that not only did it free many
                                slaves and cause to be freed many others by those under its
                                protection, not only was the odious traffic brought to an end in
                                both the mediate and immediate possessions of Italy, but even
                                private natives, who derived their main income from the slave trade,
                                finally became convinced that it was best for them to abandon
                                it.</p>
                            <p>Only one of the African chiefs who are subject to Italy, after
                                abiding for some time by the obligation which he had assumed, again
                                engaged in slave hunting and the slave trade, the very things from
                                which he ought to have abstained, both because he is a Christian and
                                because he personally requested, through Italy, to be admitted to
                                the Brussels conference, at which he was represented by Italy,
                                having approved in advance all the decisions that should be
                                adopted.</p>
                            <pb facs="0228" n="962" xml:id="pg_962"/>
                            <p>This chief is Menelik.<note n="1" xml:id="d142fn5">As I have learned
                                    that a congress is to be held at Brussels, I beg your excellency
                                    to be pleased to telegraph to the Italian ambassador residing in
                                    that city requesting him to discuss in my name all questions
                                    that may concern my State, and as you know that I do not object
                                    to any reforms that may be adopted by the Christian powers of
                                    Europe, and that I do not reject anything that can benefit the
                                    Christians, I beg you to take measures to prevent my State from
                                    being deprived of the necessary arms and ammunition. (Extract
                                    from a letter from Menelik to His Excellency M.
                                Crispi.)</note></p>
                            <p>As he went on failing to keep faith with Italy he relapsed into
                                barbarism in respect to the slave trade; and, having openly declared
                                himself a rebel, he no longer pays any regard to public law as
                                established by Europe in Africa.</p>
                            <p>According to concurrent testimony from non-Italian sources,<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn6">Mr. Venderheyn, a French citizen, was
                                    expelled from Ethiopia because he had been guilty of publishing
                                    certain truths in the newspapers in relation to the affairs of
                                    that Empire and to Menelik’s slave-hunting expeditions among the
                                    Vollamo.</note> Menelik capped the climax in his last expedition
                                against the Vollamo. Leading his hordes even into territories
                                comprised within the other sphere of Italian influence, viz, that of
                                the Indian Ocean, he sought to have the Amharic invasion accompanied
                                not only by plunder and destruction, but by slavery, with all its
                                horrors. Gangs of men were counted like flocks of sheep; here
                                60,000, there 15,000. And beside those whom he has kept entirely in
                                his own possession, Menelik levies a tax of $1 officially on each
                                slave taken by his soldiers that enters Shoa, or that is sold and
                                leaves it.</p>
                            <p>The slave trade has never been carried on more extensively than it is
                                now, and the little expeditions to the coast which were first
                                attempted by the Musselmans in a timid, covert way, and which were
                                detected by the vigilance of the Italian authorities, were nothing
                                in comparison with this trade which is openly carried on on so large
                                a scale.</p>
                            <p>It is consequently not proper to permit any contravention of the
                                provisions of the Brussels act in order to please Menelik; our
                                protectorate renders it our duty to compel him to observe those
                                provisions, but it is especially the duty of all the signatory
                                powers to fulfill the duties that are entailed on all of them by
                                that act as regards Menelik, in view of the obligations assumed by
                                him, in a more solemn manner, perhaps, than by any other African
                                chief, and of the outrages of which he is guilty to a greater extent
                                than others, and also in view of the more extended sovereignty
                                conferred upon him by us, of which he avails himself in order to
                                extend those outrages in a way that is extremely disastrous to the
                                cause of civilization and humanity, to the detriment of tribes whose
                                only fault is that they are exposed to his acts of violence.</p>
                            <p>Now, it was for the express purpose of suppressing the slave trade
                                that the powers whose representatives met at Brussels determined to
                                restrict the importation of firearms (Art. I, par. 7, of the general
                                act of July 2, 1890)<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn7"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. I</hi>. The Powers declare that
                                        the most effective means of counteracting the slave trade in
                                        the interior of Africa are the following:</p>
                                    <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Par</hi>. 7. Restriction of the
                                        importation of firearms, at least of those of modern
                                        pattern, and of ammunition throughout the entire extent of
                                        the territory in which the slave trade is carried
                                    on.</p></note> and pledged themselves (Art. III)<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn8"><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. III</hi>. The Powers
                                    exercising a sovereignty or a protectorate in Africa confirm and
                                    give precision to their former declarations and engage to
                                    proceed gradually, as circumstances may permit, either by the
                                    means above indicated or by any other means that they may
                                    consider suitable with the repression of the slave trade, each
                                    State in its respective possessions and under its own direction.
                                    Whenever they consider it possible they shall lend their good
                                    offices to such powers as, with a purely humanitarian object,
                                    may be engaged in Africa in the fulfillment of a similar
                                    mission.</note> not only to repress the traffic in human beings
                                in their possessions, but to “lend their good <pb facs="0229" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/> offices to such powers as, with a
                                purely humanitarian object, may be engaged in Africa in fulfillment
                                of a similar mission;” it was for this reason that the prohibition
                                of the importation of firearms and ammunition was extended in
                                Article VIII<note n="1" xml:id="d142fn9"><hi rend="smallcaps">Art.
                                        VIII</hi>. The experience of all nations that have
                                    intercourse with Africa having shown the pernicious and
                                    preponderating part played by firearms in operations connected
                                    with the slave trade as well as internal wars between the native
                                    tribes, and this same experience having clearly proved that the
                                    preservation of the African population, whose existence it is
                                    the express wish of the powers to protect, is a radical
                                    impossibility if measures restricting the trade in firearms and
                                    ammunition are not adopted, the Powers decide, so far as the
                                    present state of their frontiers permits, that the importation
                                    of firearms, and especially of rifles and improved weapons, as
                                    well as of powder, ball, and cartridges is, except in the cases
                                    and under the conditions provided in the following article,
                                    prohibited in the territories comprised between the twentieth
                                    parallel of north latitude and the twenty-second parallel of
                                    south latitude, and extending westward to the Atlantic Ocean and
                                    eastward to the Indian Ocean, and its dependencies, including
                                    the islands adjacent to the coast within 100 nautical miles from
                                    the shore.</note> from the twentieth parallel of north latitude
                                to the twenty-second parallel of south latitude; it was for this
                                reason that severe restrictions were laid in Article IX<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn10"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. IX</hi>. The
                                        introduction of firearms and ammunition, when there shall be
                                        no occasion to authorize it, in the possessions of the
                                        signatory powers that exercise rights of sovereignty or of
                                        protectorate in Africa, shall be regulated, unless identical
                                        or stricter regulations have already been enforced, in the
                                        following manner in the zone defined in Article VIII:</p>
                                    <p>All imported firearms shall be deposited at the cost, risk,
                                        and peril of the importers in a public warehouse under the
                                        supervision of the State government. No withdrawal of
                                        firearms or imported ammunition shall take place from such
                                        warehouses without the previous authorization of the said
                                        government. This authorization shall, except in the cases
                                        hereinafter specified, be refused for the withdrawal of all
                                        arms for accurate firing, such as rifles, magazine guns, or
                                        breech-loaders, whether whole or in deatched pieces, their
                                        cartridges, caps, or other ammunition intended for them.</p>
                                    <p>In seaports, and under conditions affording the needful
                                        guaranties, the respective Governments may permit private
                                        warehouses, but only for ordinary powder and for flintlock
                                        muskets, and to the exclusion of improved arms and
                                        ammunition therefor.</p>
                                    <p>Independently of the measures directly taken by Governments
                                        for the arming of the public force and the organization of
                                        their defense, individual exceptions may be allowed in the
                                        case of persons furnishing sufficient guaranties that the
                                        weapon and ammunition are intended for their personal
                                        defense exclusively.</p>
                                    <p>All arms, in the cases provided for in the preceding
                                        paragraph, shall be registered and marked by the supervising
                                        authorities, who shall deliver to the persons in question
                                        permits to bear arms, stating the name of the bearer and
                                        showing the stamp with which the weapon is marked. These
                                        permits shall be revocable in case proof is furnished that
                                        they have been improperly used, and shall be issued for five
                                        years only, but may be renewed.</p>
                                    <p>The above rule as to warehousing shall also apply to
                                        gunpowder.</p>
                                    <p>Only flintlock guns, with unrifled barrels, and common
                                        gunpowder known as trade powder, may be withdrawn from the
                                        warehouses for sale. At each withdrawal of arms and
                                        ammunition of this kind for sale, the local authorities
                                        shall determine the regions in which such arms and
                                        ammunition may be sold. The regions in which the slave trade
                                        is carried on shall always be excluded. Persons authorized
                                        to take arms or powder out of the public warehouses shall
                                        present to the State government every six months detailed
                                        lists indicating the destinations of the arms and powder
                                        sold, as well as the quantities still remaining in the
                                        warehouses.</p></note>upon the introduction of arms and
                                ammunition, when it was authorized in the possessions of the
                                signatory powers that exercised rights of sovereignty or
                                protectorate in the zone which is defined in Article VIII; it was
                                for this reason that the aforesaid Article IX, by providing for the
                                few slight personal exceptions to the prohibition, decided (in
                                addition to the most thorough control) that the regions in which the
                                slave trade was carried on should be excluded from those exceptions;
                                it was for this reason that the right of transit was regulated in
                                Article X;<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn11"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Art.
                                            X</hi>. The Governments shall take all such measures as
                                        they may deem necessary to insure as complete a fulfillment
                                        as possible of the provisions respecting the importation,
                                        sale, and transportation of firearms and ammunition, as well
                                        as to prevent either the entry or exit thereof via their
                                        inland frontiers, or the passage thereof to regions where
                                        the slave trade is rife.</p>
                                    <p>The authorization of transit within the limits of the zone
                                        specified in Article VIII shall not he withheld when the
                                        arms and ammunition are to pass across the territory of the
                                        signatory or adherent power occupying the coast, toward the
                                        inland territories under the sovereignty or protectorate of
                                        another signatory or adherent power, unless this latter
                                        power have direct access to the sea through its own
                                        territory. If this access be wholly interrupted, the
                                        authorization of transit can not be withheld. Any
                                        application for transit must be accompanied by a declaration
                                        emanating from the government of the power having the inland
                                        possessions, and certifying that the said arms and
                                        ammunition are not intended for sale, but are for the use of
                                        the authorities of such power, or of the military forces
                                        necessary for the protection of the missionary or commercial
                                        stations, or of persons mentioned by name in the
                                        declaration. Nevertheless, the territorial power of the
                                        coast retains the right to stop, exceptionally and
                                        provisionally, the transit of improved arms and ammunition
                                        across its territory if, in consequence of inland
                                        disturbances or other serious danger, there is ground for
                                        fearing lest the dispatch of arms and ammunition may
                                        compromise its own safety.</p></note>
                                <pb facs="0230" n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/> it was for this reason
                                that Article XI<note n="1" xml:id="d142fn12"><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XI</hi>. The powers shall communicate to one another
                                    information relating to the traffic in firearms and ammunition,
                                    the permits granted, and the measures of repression in force in
                                    their respective territories.</note> provided that the
                                signatory-powers should “communicate to one another information
                                relating to the traffic in firearms and ammunition, and that Article
                                    XIII<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn13"><hi rend="smallcaps">Art.
                                        XIII</hi>. The signatory powers that have possessions in
                                    Africa in contact with the zone specified in Article VIII bind
                                    themselves to take the necessary measures for preventing the
                                    introduction of firearms and ammunition across their inland
                                    frontiers into the regions of said zone, at least that of
                                    improved arms and cartridges.</note> extended the precautions to
                                territories situated outside of the specified zone, but in contact
                                therewith.</p>
                            <p>Now, the Italian Government is responsible to the powers that have
                                recognized its protectorate over Ethiopia for the observance of the
                                Brussels act in those territories consequently while it takes
                                measures to prevent Menelik from continuing to violate the act in
                                question it is under strict obligation to call the attention of the
                                signatory powers to this condition of things, to the end that, even
                                independently of Menelik’s hostility to Italy, those powers, by
                                prohibiting the introduction of arms and ammunition into Ethiopia,
                                may enforce the observance of those international provisions of the
                                disregard of which Menelik has taken, and is still taking, advantage
                                with a view to opening up to the slave trade regions in which Europe
                                sought to abolish it.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Blanc.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>