<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-09-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="539" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d539">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Terrell</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-09-05"><hi rend="italic">September 5,
                                    1895</hi></date>. (Received Sept. 19.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 615.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith for
                            your information copy of a dispatch from Consul Gibson to Consul-General
                            Short, with copy of Dr. Christie’s report and translated copy of the
                            report of the moutessarif of Mersine, all relating to the Tarsus
                            affair.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, I would call the attention of the Department to the
                            gratifying fact that the grand vizier has kept the promise he made me on
                            August 7, viz, that he would take prompt action in the matter. This
                            action, looking to the protection of the Americans in Tarsus and the
                            arrest of the guilty parties, seems to have been taken some days before
                            the receipt, in America, of the telegrams which so greatly excited our
                            Christian press. I shall now spare no efforts at the Porte to secure the
                            punishment of the guilty parties.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. W. Terrell.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 615.]</seg></opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Gibson</persName> to Mr.
                                        <persName type="to">Short</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut, Syria</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-08-27"><hi rend="italic">August 27, 1895</hi>.</date></dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 81.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith
                                for transmission to our honorable legation copies of reports in
                                regard to the Tarsus trouble, sent at my request to Acting Consular
                                Agent Daras and by him forwarded to me. Pardon the haste shown in
                                making these copies, which have just to-day been received through
                                Mr. Daras from Dr. Christie and also from the moutessarif of
                                Mersine.</p>
                            <p>They show that his excellency the moutessarif, who has direct charge
                                of affairs in Tarsus and Namroun, has taken the necessary steps in
                                the <pb facs="0544" n="1278" xml:id="pg_1278"/> affair, but
                                unfortunately it also appears that the mudir of Namroun and the
                                acting kaimakani of Tarsus, in their sympathy for the attacking
                                party, are permitting the persons arrested to go free in the streets
                                of Tarsus and even to return to Nainroun, greatly to the prejudice
                                of the case and to American interests in that fanatical section.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas R. Gibson</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi></signed>
                            </closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>P. S.—I also have the honor to inclose for your inspection and
                                    for the information of Minister Terrell the copy of a letter
                                    just this afternoon received from the governor-general of Adana
                                    containing the gratifying news of the release of Dr. Christie’s
                                    teacher, under the general amnesty allowed by His Imperial
                                    Majesty the Sultan to Armenian political prisoners. This case
                                    was referred to in the opening clauses of my dispatch No. 79 of
                                    August 6.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>T. R. G.</signed>
                                </closer>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 1 in No.
                                615.]</seg></opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Christie</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Darras</persName>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Namroun</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-08-10"><hi rend="italic">August 10,
                                        1895</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: In reply to your favor of the
                                8th, asking for the particulars of the recent outrage, I beg leave
                                to report as follows:</p>
                            <p>I rent and occupy here three houses for family and students. One of
                                them is a three-minutes’ walk from the other two. At 9 o’clock, a la
                                Franqua, in the evening of August 1, my servant Stepan and two of my
                                pupils (Misak and Solomon) had just gone to this house and were
                                preparing to go to bed, when some one called to them from the gate
                                of the yard. Misak, thinking a passer-by wanted a drink of water,
                                went down to the gate. A Moslem neighbor was there, outside; his
                                name is Zeybek Ali. He accused Misak of throwing stones at his
                                house. On the boy’s denying it he struck at him with a heavy club
                                which he had held concealed. The gate and hedge are very slight
                                affairs. He then threw a heavy stone, which struck the lad on the
                                side of the leg and knocked him to the ground, where he lay crying
                                and unable to rise. Ali then opened the gate and came into the yard
                                and began to beat the poor boy, shouting out curses with a loud
                                voice.</p>
                            <p>My servant Stepan ran to save Misak, when Ali began to beat him. At
                                this instant a crowd of Moslems, their skirts tucked up and with
                                clubs and stones in their hands, rushed into the yard shouting and
                                cursing and helped Ali to beat the three Christians. In five minutes
                                this crowd increased to 30 men. On hearing the tumult, one of our
                                Christian neighbors (Boghos) and a dozen students ran to the scene;
                                they were without weapons of any kind, and were too much terrified
                                even to strike a blow in self-defense. These also were beaten
                                without mercy. Boghos would have been stabbed with a dagger in the
                                hands of a Moslem youth named Loutfi, had not his mother rescued
                                him.</p>
                            <p>About this time I came up from the other house, having been summoned
                                from evening worship with my children by the news of the tumult. It
                                was a scene of indescribable confusion and shouting. Parties of from
                                4 to 8 Moslems were around each young lad, beating him with fists
                                and sticks and yelling out curses upon the “giaours, the kyaffirs,
                                the pigs, the dogs,” etc., threatening them with instant death and
                                reviling their religion, their mothers, their sisters, and other
                                relatives <pb facs="0545" n="1279" xml:id="pg_1279"/> in the
                                filthiest language. At least one revolver and one dagger were freely
                                brandished. I am confident that these would have been used if the
                                poor sufferers or their friends had shown the least resistance.</p>
                            <p>I went into the midst of the throng addressing gentle words of
                                remonstrance to the rioters and especially to Zeybek Ali, the oldest
                                among them. He and several others had my servant down and were
                                beating him. On my trying to pull them off, the most shameful
                                language was used against me. There were cries of, “This is the head
                                of the giaours; beat him, stone him, kill him!” But Zeybek Ali
                                protected me. Another old man (Hadji Mehmed Agha or Kara Zeber) also
                                began now to assist in quieting the tumult. I got Stepan upon his
                                feet, when instantly the mob surged upon him again, threw him down,
                                and dragged him by the feet down the stony slope in the most cruel
                                and abusive fashion. I followed, trying to save him, for I had good
                                reason to fear for his life. A shout arose, “To the mudir with him!”
                                and the crowd rushed down the hill. By this time the beating of the
                                other boys had ceased. I shouted to Stepan to make no resistance,
                                but go to the mudir’s house, and that I would go with him. He and
                                his assailants disappeared in the darkness. I followed as fast as I
                                could, fearing what they would do to him on the way; but first I
                                turned to my boys and bade them go back at once. They started to do
                                this when a zabtieh named Ali appeared and with abusive language and
                                aiming his gun at them ordered them to come to the mudir’s. This I
                                did not see; but after I had reached the mudir’s house, a mile away,
                                this Ali brought in the boys and a teacher, saying, “Here are the
                                pigs I have brought.” About ten of the rioters were around me as I
                                went down through the gardens and vineyards to the mudir’s. These
                                continued their wordy abuse of me and all my relations. My hat also
                                came in for a share of the cursing. I don’t wonder at that, for it
                                is really a shocking bad one. Several times a fellow named Hafuz
                                Nalban Oghlon and others rushed in front of me and lifted their big
                                clubs to strike me on the head. I kept laughing at them and talking
                                with Zeybek Ali pleasantly. He always interposed to protect me. I
                                should otherwise have been badly beaten and perhaps killed. In this
                                way we got over the mile or more of the road to the house of the
                                mudir. There I found poor Stepan and the crowd around him. When I
                                appeared they abused me to the mudir as a foreigner, having no right
                                to be here at all; the head of all the giaours; and said I had
                                lifted up here the American flag, a statement wholly untrue.</p>
                            <p>The mudir took part with the rioters, Zeybek Ali being his uncle. He
                                made no effort to stop their abusive talk. He charged Stepan and the
                                students with drinking raki all night, singing vile songs, and
                                stoning the houses of their neighbors. He then promised the rioters
                                that our boys should be punished, and sent the former away to their
                                homes.</p>
                            <p>I came home with Stepan and a decent zabtieh, who stayed at our house
                                that night; he is a personal friend. I made a thorough investigation
                                before going to bed and soon saw that the charge of stone throwing
                                was wholly false.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>A stone of the weight Ali shows as having been thrown could
                                    not be hurled, even by a giant, from where our boys were to his
                                    house.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The boys had not been at the house for more than three or four
                                    minutes when the attack took place. Ali’s story makes out that
                                    the stone was thrown at least ten minutes before.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Our boys are not at all of the sort that throw stones at
                                    people’s houses, as their Moslem neighbors agree.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>There are many facts that show the attack to have been a
                                    premeditated <pb facs="0546" n="1280" xml:id="pg_1280"/> one,
                                    well planned and prepared for. Some of them are these: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) A great crowd came; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) some of the assailants were from the east side of
                                    the valley, a mile away; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) they all
                                    came well prepared with weapons; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) they
                                    all rushed in at once, at the signal of All’s loud shout; (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) they beat our boys and the neighbor
                                    Boghos without mercy, although the latter were very few in
                                    number, wholly unarmed, and making no resistance even with their
                                    lists; (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) the language used and the
                                    extreme violence displayed are ample proofs that the real ground
                                    of it all was religious and race prejudice—a most dangerous
                                    spirit, that, if not checked by prompt and vigorous action, will
                                    surely lead to most deplorable outbreaks.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>I may add that the bim bashi sent here by his excellency the
                                    moutessarif has made a careful examination of the premises, and
                                    tells me that nothing could be more absurd than the charge made
                                    by Ali.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>On Friday morning I made a formal complaint to the mudir. That day he
                                took our depositions, but in a very unsatisfactory manner. On the
                                next day (Saturday noon) I sent word of the affair to Guzneh, having
                                waited that long with the sincere desire to do everything possible
                                here for peace and wishing to let the mudir have time, according to
                                his request, to settle the affair on the ground. It was only when I
                                saw plainly that he was working to hide the truth and to defeat
                                justice that I decided to appeal to higher authorities.</p>
                            <p>In accordance with your complaint to the moutessarif, and his prompt
                                action, the head of the police (bim bashi) came two days ago. He and
                                Hibmy Effendi, the yenz bashi, have been working hard on the case,
                                but the temporary kaimakam in Tarsus is releasing the prisoners and
                                sending some of them back to Namroun as fast as the officers here
                                send them down to go to prison. I desire that complaint on this head
                                be made to the moutessarif.</p>
                            <p>We were able to secure the names of the following as having taken
                                chief parts in the outrage; they are now in Tarsus but still at
                                large: Zeybek Ali, Hafuz (Nalban), two sons of Hanna(oneof them is
                                named Zebbar Effendi), Loutfi, and Zabtieh Ali—six in all.</p>
                            <p>In addition, the officers have arrested 11 men whom the bim bashi is
                                to take to Tarsus on Monday. He promises, also, that all shall be
                                put in prison.</p>
                            <p>The action taken against the transgressors has produced a most
                                excellent effect. I have talked with most of the prominent Moslems,
                                and they all approve of the punishment of these ill-doers. Some of
                                the latter are well-known criminals, whose imprisonment will be for
                                the good of all honest people in Namroun.</p>
                            <p>I have to thank you and your dragoman, Mr. Demosthenes, for all your
                                kindness in this matter. I hope by the punishment of the guilty
                                persons our security for the future, both here and in Tarsus, will
                                be effectually maintained and that we shall have to trouble you with
                                no more such cases.</p>
                            <p>Kindly present my thanks to his excellency the moutessarif for what
                                he and his officers have already done, and at the same time show him
                                the necessity for seeing that the case is thoroughly prosecuted.</p>
                            <p>I inclose a telegram for Consul Gibson in answer to one of inquiry
                                from him received this evening. It is possible I shall visit you on
                                Monday. I shall be glad if a copy of this letter be sent to Consul
                                Gibson.</p>
                            <p>With great respect, etc.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas D. Christie</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">President of Institute.</hi></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0547" n="1281" xml:id="pg_1281"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 2 in No.
                                    615.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Moutessarif of
                                        Mersine</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">United States
                                        consular agent at Mersine</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-08-27"><hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi> 27,
                                        1895</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Esteemed Sir</hi>: We have taken cognizance of
                                your letter of July 28, 311 (August 9, 1895), in which you ask to
                                know the steps taken against the offenders who violated the domicile
                                of Mr. Christie, an American citizen residing at Namroun.</p>
                            <p>Upon the receipt of your first letter of July 23 (August 4, 1895),
                                and that of Mr. Christie sent to his wife, the mudir of Namroun was
                                requested to report the facts of this case, and an answer was
                                received from him on July 24 (August 5, 1895) to the effect that no
                                violation of Mr. Christie’s domicile had taken place, but that a
                                quarrel occurred between Mr. Christie’s cook and the companions of
                                the latter (who are living in a house situated at a distance of
                                about 150 feet from Mr. Christie’s domicile), and their neighbor
                                Zeybek Ali, on account of their casting stones on him, and that the
                                whole quarrel resulted in Zeybek Ali giving a box on the face of
                                each of Mr. Christie’s cook and companions, and that the offender
                                was sent under escort to the caimakamate of Tarsus.</p>
                            <p>Furthermore, as the letter of Mr. Christie to his wife contained
                                certain intimations respecting his desire to come to town and his
                                demand for protection, the kolaghasi of Mersine was therefore sent
                                to Namroun in order to procure him full tranquillity.</p>
                            <p>The report received from the said kolaghasi, under date of July 28,
                                311 (August 9, 1895), relates that perfect tranquillity is pervading
                                at Namroun under the auspices of His Imperial Majesty the Sultan,
                                that the dispute had taken place between the cook and his companions
                                and Zeybek Ali, and that the latter has been arrested and sent to
                                Tarsus. On the other hand, as Mr. Christie has reported in a
                                petition that other persons had also taken part with Zeybek Ali at
                                the time of the quarrel, namely, Khanli Zada Jabbar and his brother
                                Hemmet, and Kefteker Osman and Khillo Oghlon Hafez Mohammed, the
                                same have been dispatched to Tarsus under escort, and the evidence
                                of those who were present that night during the quarrel is being
                                taken from them.</p>
                            <p>From the foregoing details it plainly appears that the true facts in
                                the case consist in the storming of Zeybek Ali’s house by the cook
                                and his companions, which action gave rise to a dispute between them
                                and him and his giving them blows on the face. That Zeybek Ali was
                                arrested, together with his accomplices, and delivered to the
                                authorities to be tried in a legal way. As to Mr. Christie, he was
                                not ill-treated nor was his domicile violated, but is living in a
                                perfect condition of rest and security under the auspices of His
                                Imperial Majesty the Sultan.</p>
                            <p>With the view of bringing the true facts of the case to your notice,
                                we transmit you this responsive communication, seizing this
                                opportunity to assure you of our high esteem.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">The Moutessarif of Mersine.</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>