<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Terrell to Mr. Olney.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1895p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d567</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">567</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1895-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1895-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="567"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d567">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Terrell</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-09-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 9, 1895</hi>
                        </date>. (Received Sept. 26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 619.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on Saturday,
                    the 7th instant, I presented to the foreign minister in person the original of
                        <pb facs="0568" n="1302" xml:id="pg_1302"/> the inclosed note relating to
                    the imprisonment of Mardiros K. Mooradian, the naturalized American citizen of
                    Armenian origin about whose imprisonment I wired you on the 7th instant.</p>
                <p>The imprisonment of this class of citizens on mere suspicion has become so
                    frequent and protracted, and is in such plain violation of my agreement
                    regarding them, that a firm and emphatic protest was a necessity. The release of
                    Mooradian was demanded at once, but in view of what was known to be the
                    minister’s want of power to act without instructions, I agreed to wait until
                    to-day for a final answer.</p>
                <p>The foreign minister informed me this morning that he had instructed the minister
                    of police to surrender Mooradian on condition that I would see executed the
                    order requiring his immediate departure from Turkish soil, and would not permit
                    him to go at large while here. He has been surrendered to me, and I have sent
                    him with my cavass to a steamer which leaves this afternoon for Athens.</p>
                <p>Extracts from various letters found in Mooradian’s possession are inclosed, three
                    of which are in red ink with the red seal of the Revolutionary Society attached.
                    They leave no doubt of his character as a member of a revolutionary society—a
                    fact which he virtually admitted in stating to me that he came to this city
                    under orders which he was compelled to obey.</p>
                <p>I inclose copy of my telegram sent on his release.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. W. Terrell.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 619.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Terrell</persName> to <persName
                                type="to">Turkhan Pasha</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-09-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 7, 1895</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 82.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: A dispatch from the consul-general of the
                        United States here has informed me of the arrest in this city of Mardiros K.
                        Mooradian, which he learned from the minister of police, who doubted the
                        genuineness of the American passport of Mooradian, and in whose possession
                        he claimed to have found compromising letters. He is an American
                        citizen.</p>
                    <p>I find nothing in those letters, as translated from the Armenian language in
                        which they were written, to show that the bearer was engaged in armed
                        resistance in Turkey to the authority of the Turkish Government. The mere
                        fact that the letters create a suspicion of the man’s connection with a
                        revolutionary society which has been founded in a foreign land to aid
                        revolution in Turkey can not subject him to punishment in a Turkish court on
                        his peaceful return to Turkey. Such a suspicion may furnish a sufficient
                        reason to exclude him from the Ottoman Empire as an undesirable person, to
                        which, under general instructions from my Government, I will interpose no
                        objection; but it does not afford a sufficient reason for his imprisonment,
                        against which I now formally protest and demand his immediate release.</p>
                    <p>If Mooradian has violated any law of Turkey, except that of doing some act on
                        Turkish soil in aid of a revolution against the authority of His Imperial
                        Majesty, I claim, under Article IV of the treaty of 1830, and the laws of
                        the United States made in accordance therewith, the right to try him
                        myself.</p>
                    <p>If he has been arrested while engaged in armed resistance to the <pb
                            facs="0569" n="1303" xml:id="pg_1303"/> authority of Turkey, I would
                        concede jurisdiction of the offense to a Turkish court, and content myself
                        with demanding an impartial trial.</p>
                    <p>It is hoped that your excellency will, in this matter, conform your action to
                        the agreement made between your predecessor and myself regarding such cases,
                        and order the prompt release of Mr. Mooradian.</p>
                    <p>Receive, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. W. Terrell.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
