<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="699" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Mavroyeni Bey</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-12-26"><hi rend="italic">December 26,
                                    1895</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 61.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have had the honor to receive your
                            special No. 89, of the 17th instant, in which yon communicate to me the
                            purport of a telegram received by you from His Excellency Tevfik Pasha,
                            minister of foreign affairs, acquainting you with the substance of notes
                            addressed to him by Minister Terrell, expressing satisfaction with the
                            conduct of the Turkish authorities during the recent disorders and
                            favorably referring in particular to their efforts to protect the lives
                            and property of the miss onaries and American citizens at Harpoot,
                            Marsovan, Aintab, and Marash.</p>
                        <p>The last mail brings me a dispatch from Mr. Terrell, under date of
                            December 5, inclosing copy of a note addressed by him to the minister
                            for foreign affairs of the same date, which appears to be one of those
                            to which your communication refers. Mr. Terrell therein takes occasion
                            to mention five high officers of the Porte, military and civil, at
                            Harpoot, Marsovan, Aintab, and Amassia as, in his opinion, deserving the
                            highest praise for their conduct toward the protection of the lives of
                            American missionaries and expresses his deep satisfaction on hearing of
                            their meritorious deportment. Their names are: Mehmet Bey, alai beyi of
                            Harpoot; the kaimakam of Aintab; Beker Pasha, moutessarif of Amassia;
                            the kaimakam of Marsovan, and the colonel commanding the troops at
                            Marsovan.</p>
                        <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>