<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="10" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                        <head>10. Paper Prepared by the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                (<persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                                Center, Department of Defense, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>
                                Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 330 73 A 1250, <gloss target="#t_VIET1">VIET</gloss> 092.2 (September-October 1968).
                                Confidential. A notation on the paper reads: “<gloss target="#t_Dep1">Dep</gloss>. Sec. has seen.” An attached note
                                dated September 11 reads: “<persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark</persName>—Some days ago you asked me to think over an
                                idea of yours relative to a cessation of bombing north of 17!. I
                                have done so. The attached paper, which I wrote personally, sets
                                forth the doubts &amp; problems it raises for me. Bus.” Another
                                attached note to <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName>
                                from his military aide <persName corresp="#p_PCRE1">Robert
                                    Pursely</persName> dated October 17 reads: “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName>: You handed the attached
                                paper to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Warnke</persName> some time
                                ago. He now returns it, with the comment that he feels no action is
                                indicated at this time. REP”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-09-11">September 11, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">CESSATION OF OFFENSIVE ACTIONS AND <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>It has been proposed that, in the near future, the President would
                                make a nationally-televised speech in which he would state: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Effective one week later, he was directing the cessation
                                        of all offensive actions against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>He assumed that the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>
                                        would refrain from certain military actions and would,
                                        within 2-3 days after the cessation of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, engage in fruitful
                                        discussions leading to a just and honorable peace. (See para
                                        2 below for a hard-core listing of these actions.)</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>He assumed also that, during the intervening week, if the
                                            <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> found his
                                        assumptions unacceptable, they would so state. He would
                                        construe silence on their part to indicate consent.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The following is a listing of the hard-core items of Phase II of
                                the Phase I-II package which have been mentioned to the North
                                Vietnamese in Paris: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Restore the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. No
                                        massing of troops or supplies in or near <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>No increase in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> force levels in South
                                        Vietnam after cessation of bombing.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>No attacks on major population centers in South Vietnam,
                                        such as Saigon, Hue, and Danang.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item><p>Substantive discussions, on a “our-side your-side”
                                            basis to commence as soon as bombing stops, with either
                                            side free to raise any topics relevant to a peaceful
                                            settlement.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Note</hi>: Aerial reconnaissance over
                                                <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> is implicit in
                                            the foregoing.</p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The principal arguments advanced in favor of this procedure are: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>It removes the element of reciprocity which the North
                                        Vietnamese have declared to be not acceptable to
                                        them.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0061" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>The North Vietnamese do not have to say anything; they
                                        need only to refrain from doing certain things. (Except
                                        sub-paragraph 2d.)</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Unlike earlier, more simple proposals for unilateral
                                        cessation of offensive operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, the President is
                                        protected; i.e., if the North Vietnamese respond that the
                                        proposal is not to their liking, the order to cease <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> operations would not be
                                        issued.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>Acceptance (silence) by <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> would lead promptly to substantive
                                        discussions. Rejection would coalesce world opinion against
                                        them and in our favor.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The foregoing formulation is better in several respects than
                                others put forward earlier. However, there are certain aspects which
                                deserve further and deeper examination. Among these are: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item><p>The attitude of the North Vietnamese leaders.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> stated during his
                                            last visit that, at the outset of the negotiating
                                            sessions, the North Vietnamese were arrogant, obviously
                                            expectant that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                            representatives had come prepared to negotiate a
                                            face-saving turnover of <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.
                                            They were surprised and apparently shocked that such was
                                            not the case. His views are borne out by frequent
                                            statements in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>
                                            propaganda, exhortations to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>
                                            forces, private comments to individuals, etc., regarding
                                            the “stubbornness” of the Americans.</p>
                                        <p>It seems reasonably clear that Hanoi rejects reciprocity
                                            in order to get something for nothing rather than any
                                            obscure considerations of “face.”</p>
                                        <p>This leads to a question: Would a further unilateral
                                            restriction on our offensive actions lead to any move to
                                            peace by <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> leaders, or
                                            would it serve to confirm that our “stubbornness” can be
                                            broken and further concessions gained if they stand
                                            their ground?</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item><p>The reality of the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                            construing silence on the part of the <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> delegation as
                                            acceptance of our assumptions.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: I am informed that there
                                            are ample and sound legal precedents for construing
                                            silence as consent. However, it is not clear to me that
                                            this is necessarily true in international law and, even
                                            if it is, there is no court to so construe, find, and
                                            take corrective action. Of course, there is world
                                            opinion, for what it may be worth, in dealing with
                                                <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>. I surmise it
                                            would have little force in Hanoi.</p>
                                        <p>In other words, I conjecture that <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> could, and probably would, remain
                                            silent, permit us to cease all combat operations against
                                                <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, and count upon
                                            world opinion (which has more impact in Washington than
                                            Hanoi) to inhibit us from resuming offensive operations
                                            north of 17!.</p>
                                        <p>Furthermore, arguing legalistically, the North Vietnamese
                                            could maintain that (1) these were our assumptions, not
                                            theirs; they had never <pb facs="0062" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/> agreed to reciprocal actions, and
                                            our assumptions were reciprocity in another guise; (2)
                                            since they had not agreed to the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> assumptions, they were not bound to
                                            proceed on any or all of them, e.g., an “our-side
                                            your-side” formula; (3) however, now that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> had ceased offensive
                                            operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>,
                                            which was the central reason for negotiators convening,
                                            we should now proceed to the next item on their agenda:
                                            which is probably the withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> forces from <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>.</p>
                                        <p>Question: Could we realistically reverse our course
                                            should <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> adopt the
                                            above, or a comparable position?</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item><p>Assuming silence from <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, the soundness of the assumption that
                                            prompt and substantive discussions leading to peace
                                            would be forthcoming.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Three points are
                                            pertinent. The North Vietnamese have adamantly rejected
                                            the “our-side your-side” formula, saying that they will
                                            not deal with the “puppets” <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NCKVP1">Ky</persName>. They have stated repeatedly that
                                            restoration of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>
                                            would be equivalent to permanent partition of Vietnam.
                                            And, like other Communists, they believe in the
                                            “talk-fight, fight-talk” tactic.</p>
                                        <p>I think it reasonable to expect that, in the postulated
                                            situation, talks might begin promptly. On the other
                                            hand, they might well not be substantive and productive.
                                            Free of all military pressure against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, they could (and, I
                                            believe, would) settle down for protracted negotiations
                                            (with us—not the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>),
                                            fully expectant that <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                            war-weariness would prevent us from insisting on <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> participation,
                                            inevitably produce further concessions, and ultimately
                                            give them a Paris-type victory.</p>
                                        <p>I base the foregoing judgments on these considerations:
                                            (1) following the “talk-fight” formula, they could
                                            control the tempo and resultant costs of combat in
                                                <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>; (2) they could
                                            expect, over time, a deterioration in the <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> due to weariness,
                                            losses and knowledge that <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> was not suffering while they and their
                                            country were under attack; and (3) they could expect
                                            with high confidence that, so long as the talks
                                            continued, we would not resume our offensive against the
                                            North even under circumstances of serious
                                            provocation.</p>
                                        <p>Question: Assuming silence from <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> relative to the proposed assumptions,
                                            would the resultant situation be advantageous or
                                            disadvantageous to the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>?</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item><p>The reality of the implicit assumption that we could
                                            and would resume offensive operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> should negotiations
                                            prove to be non-productive.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: Our experience with
                                            unilateral cessations of operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> has been illuminating,
                                            but not happy. Since the facts are well-known, no
                                            purpose is served by belaboring the point. Moreover,
                                            this aspect has been discussed partially in 4c.
                                            above.</p>
                                        <pb facs="0063" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/>
                                        <p>However, I am convinced that once we cease our offensive
                                            against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, the chances
                                            of resumption are most remote.</p>
                                        <p>Question: Under what circumstances, assuming that talks
                                            following this formulation have been undertaken, would
                                            the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> resume offensive
                                            operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>?</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item><p>The value of our air and naval campaign against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.</p>
                                        <p>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: As pointed out earlier,
                                            our limited air and naval operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> comprise the only
                                            pressure which self-imposed constraints permit us to
                                            apply against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.
                                            Within the limits we have established for ourselves, we
                                            have the initiative, and we can control the tempo and
                                            destructiveness of our attacks regardless of defensive
                                            measures taken by <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.</p>
                                        <p>The contrary is true in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>. There—at a cost and within
                                                limits—<gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> can
                                            control the level of combat activity and the destruction
                                            created.</p>
                                        <p>I believe that both proponents and opponents of air and
                                            naval operations against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> have, to varying degrees and far too
                                            often, expressed their differing views in extremes.
                                            Certainly, to maintain that the air and naval campaign
                                            is the single most important factor of the war is as
                                            illogical as to maintain that the campaign is militarily
                                            valueless. In essence, war is force applied to achieve
                                            an end. The more violently and the faster force is
                                            applied, the sooner the end is achieved.</p>
                                        <p>I believe the following factors are pertinent to our air
                                            and naval campaign against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> and, moreover, are undeniably true: <list>
                                                <label>(1)</label>
                                                <item>Our limited air and naval campaign is the only
                                                  means available to us, within self-imposed
                                                  constraints, to bring pressure on <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>.</item>
                                                <label>(2)</label>
                                                <item>Without attempting to quantify physical
                                                  results, our operations are disrupting the enemy’s
                                                  war effort and hurting him.</item>
                                                <label>(3)</label>
                                                <item>Complete cessation of offensive operations
                                                  north of 17! will permit the enemy to move with
                                                  impunity forces, military matériel and supplies to
                                                  areas contiguous to the combat zone, thereby
                                                  increasing the hazard to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and Allied forces and installations.
                                                  Under these circumstances, should the enemy so
                                                  choose, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and
                                                  Allied casualties will increase to a level largely
                                                  determinable by the enemy.</item>
                                                <label>(4)</label>
                                                <item>The morale of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and Allied troops, and that of the
                                                  <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> populace,
                                                  would suffer.</item>
                                                <label>(5)</label>
                                                <item>Friend and enemy alike, military and civilian,
                                                  would construe the imposition of further
                                                  unilateral restraint on our forces as a victory
                                                  for <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>,
                                                  supporting the thesis that, if the <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> remain intransigent,
                                                  they can achieve their full objectives in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>.</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </p>
                                        <p>Question: Would a total cessation of military operations
                                            against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> create a
                                            situation, political and military, more favorable or
                                            less favorable for the achievement of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> objectives?</p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Of course, people will answer the foregoing questions in different
                                ways. My own answers can be summed up as follows: <pb facs="0064" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>I know that it is militarily wrong to make concessions
                                        from a position of strength to an enemy showing signs of
                                        increasing strain and weakness; and</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>On balance, I believe such a course to be equally unsound
                                        politically.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Wheeler</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>