<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-10-28T05:25:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-28T05:25:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                        <head>132. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d132fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss target="#t_AIM1">A/IM</gloss> Files: Lot 93 D 82, <gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss>-(Incoming)-October 1968.
                                Secret; Flash; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss> Double Plus. Received at 6:17
                                a.m.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-10-28T10:25:00+00:00">October 28, 1968,
                                1025Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>22996/<gloss target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> 885. Eyes only for the
                            Secretary from <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Pursuant to telcon with Secretary,<note n="2" xml:id="d132fn2">See <ref target="#d129fn11">footnote 11, Document 129</ref>.</note> there
                            follows the answer to the three questions he raised.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p>(A) We have raised the issues of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> and indiscriminate attacks against the major
                                    cities and what we expect on the part of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> in respect to these two matters
                                    in 12 secret meetings with the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. Often these subjects were raised more than
                                    once in those meetings. In most cases both subjects were raised;
                                    in a few cases only one was raised. The discussion of these
                                    matters began in June and have continued until the present day,
                                    so that we have been consistently presenting our position in
                                    this regard to the other side.</p>
                                <p>(B) Our demand with respect to the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> has been: there will be no firing of artillery,
                                    rockets or mortars from across and within the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>; there will be no movement of
                                    troops from, across and within the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>; and there will be no massing or movement of
                                    troops near the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> in a manner
                                    threatening to the other side. Our demand with respect to the
                                    cities has been that there will be no indiscriminate attacks
                                    against major cities. These formulations are precisely in
                                    accordance with our instructions, as most recently expressed in
                                    State 254715.<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn3">
                                        <ref target="#d65">Document 65</ref>.</note> ns for a
                                    settlement. (What <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName>
                                    is saying when he speaks in this way is that while he will never
                                    admit to past violations of <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>,
                                    he understands what will be necessary in the future.)llery fire
                                    across the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>, “you will see
                                    what will happen because our government has consistently
                                    respected the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. Reality will
                                    give you the reply.” This, <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> said, would create the favorable conditions
                                    for a settlement. (What <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> is saying when he speaks in this way is that
                                    while he will never admit to past violations of <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>, he understands what will be
                                    necessary in the future.)</p>
                                <p>(C) With respect to the indiscriminate attacks against major
                                    cities, we have not only raised this issue repeatedly in private
                                    sessions, but <pb facs="0410" n="376" xml:id="pg_376"/> made it
                                    an issue in plenary meetings. In fact, with a few exceptions,
                                    there have been none for several months.</p>
                                <p>(D) Throughout our meetings when these subjects have been
                                    discussed, at no point has the other side given us any basis for
                                    believing that they did not understand precisely what we are
                                    talking about and what is expected of them.</p>
                                <p>(E) On October 11, pursuant to instructions (State 252815)<note n="4" xml:id="d132fn4">See <ref target="#d54fn4">footnote 4,
                                            Document 54</ref>.</note> and in accordance with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>’s discussions
                                    with the Secretary, we said, “In responding to your question, it
                                    is very important there be no misunderstanding between us. It is
                                    very important to understand that we are not talking about
                                    reciprocity or conditions but simply a fact that after cessation
                                    of all bombardment the President’s ability to maintain that
                                    situation would be affected by certain elemental
                                    considerations.</p>
                                <p>“We do not look on them as a condition for stopping the bombing
                                    but as a description of the situation which would permit serious
                                    negotiations and thus the cessation to continue. You will
                                    understand, therefore, that the circumstances we have discussed
                                    in our various private meetings about military activity in and
                                    around the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> are essential to
                                    the maintenance of that situation. And, of course, you know from
                                    our various discussions that indiscriminate attacks launched
                                    against major cities would create a situation which would not
                                    permit serious talks and thus the maintenance of a cessation.”
                                    We have repeated this in equally clear terms on subsequent
                                    occasions.</p>
                                <p>(F) In addition, in four meetings with the Soviet representative
                                    in Paris, we have raised the subject of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> and attacks on the major cities
                                    and have told them that the bombing cessation could not be
                                    maintained if the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> acted in
                                    bad faith with respect to these matters. He had been in regular
                                    and frequent contact with the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> delegation. He had indicated to us that the
                                        <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> understands our
                                    position. We further understand that the Secretary has also
                                    raised these subjects with the Russians and has made our
                                    position clear.</p>
                                <p>(G) Finally, our continued refusal to include the words “without
                                    condition” in an agreed minute makes it crystal clear that
                                    although there are no “pre-conditions” there are circumstances
                                    or what some people might call “conditions subsequent,” the
                                    occurrence of which would cause us to resume the bombing.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In our judgment, the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> will
                                carry out what we have demanded of them with respect to the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> and indiscriminate attacks against
                                major cities. While we have not received direct affirmation that the
                                    <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>
                                <pb facs="0411" n="377" xml:id="pg_377"/> will abide by our
                                demand—we are convinced they understand clearly what they are
                                expected to do. As indicated above, this is confirmed by our
                                discussions with Soviets. In addition, the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> understands the consequences if they fail to live
                                up to their part of the understanding, i.e., the bombing will be
                                resumed. It is always possible that there will be some minor
                                violations such as moving small numbers of men and supplies through
                                the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. These can be judged on the
                                basis of the total circumstances in which they occur.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>As we have previously stated on several occasions, the bombing
                                should be resumed if our demands with respect to either the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> or the cities are violated.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Harriman</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>