<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-09-16T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-09-16T08:00:00-05:00" n="18" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                        <head>18. Information Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant
                                (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d18fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, National Security
                                File, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName> Files,
                                Chlodnick File. Literally Eyes Only for the President and Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-09-16T09:00:00-04:00">September 16, 1968, 9
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Mr. President:</p>
                        <p>As we consider the possible initiative with the Russians, I believe we
                            should take certain steps and plan others—in the form of a scenario—to
                            make sure all bases are covered.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">A military assessment for the next several
                                        months, say mid-September to mid-November</hi>.</p>
                                <p>This should cover: <list>
                                        <item>—enemy plans and intentions;</item>
                                        <item>—our capacity to deal with them;</item>
                                        <item>—current and prospective rates of infiltration;</item>
                                        <item>—weather and probable supply movements through the
                                            Panhandle and Laos.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>We know, in general, that the answers are: a stretched out
                                    harassing campaign, with an effort to consolidate politically in
                                    the countryside; we can cope well; low infiltration now,
                                    probably due to weather—possibly due to political plans:
                                    infiltration could rise sharply when Laos dries up from
                                    mid-October on; weather will deteriorate in Panhandle, improve
                                    in Laos. But we need an authoritative wrap-up from <persName corresp="#p_AGC1">Abrams</persName>, for which we can ask at
                                    any time.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Contingency plans for applying more pressure
                                        to North Vietnam if you should judge diplomacy has
                                        failed</hi>.</p>
                                <p>Major candidates are: <list>
                                        <item>—bombing Cambodian bases;</item>
                                        <item>—bombing up to 20th parallel;</item>
                                        <item>—bombing Hanoi-Haiphong;</item>
                                        <item>—mining Haiphong;</item>
                                        <item>—ground attacks into northern half of <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>;</item>
                                        <item>—ground attacks north of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <gloss target="#t_BusBuzz1">Bus</gloss> could be asked to work
                                    on this on a personal basis now, without staff. You may wish
                                    formally to engage Pentagon staff only if bombing halt is under
                                    way.</p>
                            </item>
                            <pb facs="0080" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Rules of engagement during a bombing
                                    halt</hi>.</p>
                                <p>We had a good talk about this in <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Nick
                                        Katzenbach</persName>’s Vietnam group ten days ago. All
                                    hands agreed we would wish to strike back in case of <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss> violations promptly, with our
                                    response local rather than general, and about three times the
                                    weight of the particular provocation; for example, three shells
                                    for every one fired across the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. But we may wish to start formal contingency
                                    planning on this.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Political</hi>. <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>If we go ahead with another message via Dobrynin, say,
                                        late today<note n="2" xml:id="d18fn2">
                                            <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> met with
                                                <persName corresp="#p_DA1">Dobrynin</persName> that
                                            evening from 6 to 7:30 p.m. He transmitted a message
                                            from <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> to
                                            the Soviet leadership that stated that, if the leaders
                                            of the Soviet Union were “prepared to advise on the
                                            basis of what now is being said” that accompanying
                                            action on the part of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> would be assured on a “de facto basis,”
                                            then the President “would take their advice with the
                                            utmost seriousness” in a decision to halt the bombing of
                                            North Vietnam. The full text of this message is printed
                                            in <ref target="frus1964-68v14#d299">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968,
                                                vol. XIV, Document 299</ref>. In a memorandum to the
                                            President, September 16, 8:10 p.m., <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> noted <persName corresp="#p_DA1">Dobrynin</persName>’s reaction: “He
                                            felt it important that, if the Soviet Union gave a
                                            positive reply to the message I had handed to him, that
                                            we not take such a reply as committing the Soviet Union
                                            to assuring the role we had envisaged for the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in negotiations.” See
                                            ibid., <ref target="frus1964-68v14#d300">Document
                                                300</ref>.</note> and we get a positive reply, you
                                        may wish, just for the record, to check with <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> and Bohlen before
                                        moving—so that Russian experts will have been
                                        consulted.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>With respect to <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell</persName>, the question may be more urgent:
                                        should he be told in general terms of the possibility of an
                                        approach via Moscow as a third party in the next several
                                            days?<note n="3" xml:id="d18fn3">The issue was discussed
                                            with <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> in
                                            several conversations on September 17; see <ref target="#d19">Documents 19</ref>–<ref target="#d21">21</ref>.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item><p>Not immediately urgent, but to be kept in mind as a
                                            checklist, if we move ahead: <list>
                                                <item>—When do we tell <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_AGC1">Abrams</persName> and how do we keep South
                                                  Vietnamese from panicking?</item>
                                                <item>—When do we tell Asian fighting allies?</item>
                                                <item>—When do we tell <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies and how do we keep them from
                                                  turning off efforts to strengthen <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>?</item>
                                                <item>—How do we reassure Israelis that we are not
                                                  going to sell them out with the Russians, while
                                                  keeping the heat on them?</item>
                                                <item>—How do we deal with the issue of
                                                  Czechoslovakia?</item>
                                                <item>—When do we talk to Congressional
                                                  leadership?</item>
                                                <item>—When do we inform the major
                                                  candidates?</item>
                                            </list>
                                        </p>
                                        <p>(The answer to a good many of these questions—in terms of
                                            substance—will come to a head in the drafting of a
                                            statement for the President announcing his forthcoming
                                            actions. Simultaneous announcement of a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting in Brussels,
                                                post-Geneva,<note n="4" xml:id="d18fn4">Reference is
                                                to arms control talks being held in Geneva.</note>
                                            and a meeting with fighting allies in Asia would help.
                                            The Czechoslovak issue <pb facs="0081" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> will be difficult, although it
                                            could be helped by a public troop withdrawal schedule
                                            before Geneva.)</p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">A final thought</hi>. If the bombing halt comes
                                just before Geneva and we wish to hold Hanoi’s feet to the fire on
                                performance in both Paris and on the ground, you may wish to keep
                                the Geneva talks going until they <hi rend="italic">do</hi> perform.
                                Much the most interesting thing said in Paris yesterday was that
                                serious discussions could begin “the next day.”<note n="5" xml:id="d18fn5">See <ref target="#d14">Document 14</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>