<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>239. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-11-27T14:24:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-11-27T14:24:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-11-27T14:24:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-11-27T14:24:00-05:00" n="239"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                <head>239. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Country File,
                        Vietnam, <gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss> Paris <gloss
                            target="#t_Todel1">Todel</gloss>-Paris <gloss target="#t_Delto1"
                            >Delto</gloss>, Vol. XVI(a). Secret; Immediate; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_HARVAN1"
                            >HARVAN</gloss> Plus. Repeated to Saigon.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-11-27T19:24:00+00:00">November 27, 1968,
                        1924Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>24609/<gloss target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> 996. 1. In the meetings between
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> since November 1st, and in particular in
                    the meetings preceding November 6th, we discussed a number of matters concerning
                    the procedural and physical arrangements for the first wider meeting which will
                    deal with the rules of procedure for the next phase. The following reflects the
                    status of these discussions and the exchange of notes verbale of November
                        5th.<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2">See <ref target="#d198">Document
                        198</ref>.</note> It should be emphasized that these discussions concerned
                    only the arrangements for what both sides have agreed would be meetings on the
                    rules of procedure for the plenary sessions (i.e., analogous to the <persName
                        corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                        >Lau</persName> meetings of May 10 and 11, 1968).<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d239fn3">See <ref target="frus1964-68v06#d230">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. VI, Document
                            230</ref>.</note> Prior to and after our resuming discussion on this
                    subject with the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>, we intend to have detailed
                    consultation with <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> delegation on which we
                    will report fully.</p>
                <p>2. Based upon the discussions which we have held with the <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                        >DRV</gloss> since November 1, the following is a summary of <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> positions
                    regarding procedure and other matters for the wider talks: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Both sides agree that the first wider meeting (with <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>
                            present) will discuss the rules of procedures, and that the subsequent
                            meetings will also be devoted to procedural questions. It is not clear
                            whether both sides agree that substantive, plenary sessions will not
                            begin until after the rules of procedure have been agreed upon.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Press. Our position is that there should be no press at the first
                            meeting in the wider format and the press should not be permitted “until
                            such time as the rules of procedure have been agreed upon” (similar to
                            last May). The <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> originally wanted
                            press at the first wider meeting. In their November 5 note verbale, the
                                <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> conceded the point “temporarily”
                            in an effort to have a meeting the following day. We may assume that
                            they will similarly yield on barring the press from the meetings on
                            procedure, while insisting on a press session at the opening of the
                            first plenary.</item>
                        <pb facs="0743" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>Language and Translation. During the November 5 <persName
                                corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                                >Lau</persName> meeting, we agreed to continue the system we have
                            used so far. This will, however, have to be determined in final form
                            during the procedural meetings; as our discussion now stands, the
                            procedural meetings will be concluded using the double translation
                            system.</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>Name of Conference. Prior to the cessation of bombing, we had told the
                                <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> that we wanted to refer to the
                            next phase as “meetings” and they had indicated acceptance. However, on
                            November 5, during a discussion which focused primarily on the question
                            of participants, we stated that “we cannot agree on what the wider
                            format will be called and that will be decided in the rules of procedure
                            as it had been done with our official conversations.”</item>
                        <label>E.</label>
                        <item>Number of People. We told <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName>
                            that we thought that each side should have about nine to ten people in
                            the room during the procedural meetings. <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                                >Lau</persName> said that he thought each delegation could send
                            somewhere between five and seven persons. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comment</hi>: Discrepancy here is not serious, as <persName
                                corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> himself said.</item>
                        <label>F.</label>
                        <item>Room. Originally, the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> wanted to
                            hold the first wider meeting in the large conference room. In its note
                            verbale of November 5, the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> conceded
                            this point and agreed to our suggestion to hold the procedural meetings
                            in the smaller room. Their agreement was, as on the question of press,
                            “temporary” in an effort to get a meeting on November 6. However, we can
                            expect the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> will agree to remain in
                            the smaller conference room in the procedural meetings.</item>
                        <label>G.</label>
                        <item>Seating. This appears to be the major unresolved question. The <gloss
                                target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> has informed the French that since
                            there will be a four-sided conference, they should prepare new seating
                            arrangements to reflect this fact; i.e., a four-side table. We have told
                            the French so far only that we do not agree with the <gloss
                                target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> suggestion and that we will let them
                            know our views later. We have agreed with the <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                                >DRV</gloss> that it would be preferable to work through the French
                            for the final arrangements subject to the agreement of each side on this
                            matter.</item>
                        <label>H.</label>
                        <item>Order of Speaking. <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> has
                            said that he does not consider this matter important. Presumably, we can
                            therefore take the initiative and propose that we speak first at the
                            first procedural meeting.</item>
                        <label>I.</label>
                        <item>Designated Spokesmen. This matter has not been adequately aired. It is
                            possible that the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> may raise a
                            problem on this point, although it is more likely that they will propose
                            that each delegation designate its spokesman or spokesmen in ad<persName
                                corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>. We will presumably want to
                            counter by proposing that each side designate its spokesmen. We would
                            intend to designate both <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and <gloss
                                target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> representatives.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Harriman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
