<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>272. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Vietnam</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-01-04T17:31:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-01-04T17:31:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-04T17:31:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-04T17:31:00-05:00" n="272"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <head>272. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d272fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss
                            target="#t_ISOIS1">IS/OIS</gloss> Files: Lot 90 D 345, Paris Peace
                        Conference, 1968-1969, <gloss target="#t_Todel1">Todel</gloss> Chron.,
                        January 1969. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss>. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_Bundy1">Bundy</persName>, cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SB1">Smith</persName> and Lowell Kilday of <gloss
                            target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>, and approved by <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                            >Rusk</persName>. Repeated to Paris as <gloss target="#t_Todel1"
                            >Todel</gloss> 1917.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-01-04T22:31:00+00:00">January 4, 1969,
                        2231Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1411. For Ambassador from Secretary.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We have reviewed the report in Paris 0038, the recommendations in Paris
                        0042, and the progress report and comments in Saigon 154.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d272fn2">See <ref target="#d268fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                268</ref>, <ref target="#d269">Document 269</ref>, and <ref
                                target="#d270">Document 270</ref>, respectively.</note> News stories
                        here reflect excellent backgrounding in Paris and some expectation of
                        progress. We believe this has improved our position somewhat for the moment.
                        Nonetheless, we continue to believe—and to surmise that Hanoi believes—that
                        their proposal for an unmarked and continuous round table appears plausible
                        and reasonable to American and significant third-country opinion.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Hence, we continue to believe that we must make every effort to resolve
                        this matter without further delay on some reasonable basis, and we accept
                        the thrust of Paris 0042 that <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s
                        concurrence in our accepting in the last analysis the unmarked continuous
                        round table is crucial. Like Paris, we reject totally any thought of
                        changing the present agreed format (Paris 110),<note n="3" xml:id="d272fn3"
                            >Telegram 110/<gloss target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> 1124 from Paris,
                            January 4. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                                target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss target="#t_ISOIS1"
                                >IS/OIS</gloss> Files: Lot 90 D 345, Paris Peace Conference,
                            1968-1969, <gloss target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> Chron., January
                            1969)</note> and likewise believe that there is no effective way to
                        cushion the effects of delay by any form of useful bilateral in Paris that
                        would not become rapidly disruptive in Saigon.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>On the table shape, our reading is that further progress is most unlikely
                        if we stay where we are. Although we can understand that the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> may well read Hanoi’s dropping of flags and
                        nameplates as proof that standing firm gets results, we note from Paris 0038
                        that the dropping of flags and nameplates remains conditional on our
                        acceptance of a continuous round table and was only put forward after we had
                        shown motion in our position on tables. We come back to the basic judgment
                        that Hanoi thinks it has a good thing going, in terms of American public
                        opinion, in resisting any physical demarcation of a round table.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>At the same time, we believe that accepting the unmarked continuous round
                        table would put us in a very strong position to get strong two-sided flavor
                        on the order of speaking. While our maximum objective <pb facs="0831"
                            n="797" xml:id="pg_797"/> in Saigon should be <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s concurrence in the full range of
                        possibilities contained in paras 9-12 of State 291645,<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d272fn4">See <ref target="#d264fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                264</ref>.</note> we are concerned that these complexities may delay
                        our next move in Paris. Moreover, we feel that—just as it is almost
                        impossible to explain our resistance to a round table—a position that calls
                        for two lots and for each side completing its presentation before the other
                        side speaks (AABB) is an extremely persuasive one for public opinion here
                        and elsewhere. It is simple common sense, conforms to the normal practice in
                        any multi-party litigation, and fits the basic fact that there are two sides
                        both in the fighting and in our concept of the arrangements for the
                        meeting.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In sum, I believe that you must seek to see <persName corresp="#p_NVT1"
                            >Thieu</persName> as soon as possible, hopefully Monday at latest, to go
                        over the situation with the following maximum and fall-back objectives: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>As a maximum objective, to get his concurrence in the full sweep
                                of authority covered by Paris 0042.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>If in your judgment he simply will not agree to this—or will not
                                do so without significant further delay—to get his concurrence to a
                                further meeting in Paris at which <persName corresp="#p_VCR1"
                                    >Vance</persName> would accept the continuous and unbroken round
                                table, contingent upon the dropping of flags and nameplates and also
                                upon Hanoi’s acceptance of a two-lot draw and an AABB order of
                                speaking. You could further suggest that Vance might open by
                                offering to let the other side speak first under a two-lot draw and
                                an AABB order, provided that Hanoi accepted the baize strips.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In seeking to get the maximum possible freedom, you should of course
                        reiterate all the arguments concerning the state of opinion here. Moreover,
                        you may make clear that we would certainly join with the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in stressing the fact that, even with the
                        unbroken and continuous round table, space would be allocated on a 50-50
                        basis—i.e., by sides—and the definitely two-sided flavor that any of our
                        proposed order of speaking arrangements—but particularly two lots and
                        AABB—would have. As we see it, the total deal would be taken not only as
                        more two-sided than anything else, but as representing a serious and sober
                        arrangement in which Hanoi backed down heavily, first on the flags and
                        nameplates and finally on its unrealistic and now public position on order
                        of speaking.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>If you should move to the position described in para 5-b above, you should
                        of course make clear that we cannot be sure this will produce agreement, and
                        that it would be necessary to consult further if it did not. In other words,
                        we must not get into a flat and final position at least at this
                        stage.</item>
                    <pb facs="0832" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>This instruction reflects discussions at highest levels today. As I am
                        sure you realize, we all feel a very great sense of urgency in getting these
                        procedural matters resolved.<note n="5" xml:id="d272fn5">In a January 4
                            meeting in the Cabinet Room of the White House, the President, <persName
                                corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CCM1"
                                >Clifford</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_Bundy1"
                            >Bundy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CGA2">Christian</persName>, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_JWTT1">Tom Johnson</persName> discussed the
                            Vietnam peace negotiations. (<persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                                >Johnson</persName> Library, President’s Daily Diary) Although notes
                            of this off-the-record meeting have not been found, <persName
                                corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> discussed it during a meeting
                            with his staff 2 days later. He noted: “We wallowed around. Pres didn’t
                            show any particular impatience, so I surmise <persName corresp="#p_RWW1"
                                >Walt</persName> &amp; <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Dean</persName>
                            had gotten to him. I only stated that I thought we ought to act promptly
                            on <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> request for decision.
                            I said I thought <gloss target="#t_LBJ1">LBJ</gloss> shld approve the
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> plan/convention. The
                            record shld show <hi rend="italic">decisions</hi> &amp; so <hi
                                rend="italic">tell</hi> Saigon &amp; order <persName
                                corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName> to get Pres <persName
                                corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s concurrence. Finally Pres told
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> to get out a cable to
                                <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName> (it did not get out
                            [until] 10:00 p.m. Sat nite).” <persName corresp="#p_CCM1"
                                >Clifford</persName> added: “<persName corresp="#p_BE2"
                                >Bunker</persName>’s answer is ‘miserable’. He’s not pressing hard;
                            it’s too bad. No movement. I had hoped we could get movement for Pres.
                            J’s record &amp; so the new administration would have something moving.
                            ‘They’ want <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> &amp; <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> &amp; so they’ll <hi
                                rend="italic">not</hi> move at all before the 20th.” (Ibid.,
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGM1">George M. Elsey</persName> Papers, Van
                            De Mark Transcripts [1 of 2])</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
