<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>284. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-01-16T09:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-01-16T09:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-16T09:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-16T09:20:00-05:00" n="284"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                <head>284. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d284fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Country File,
                        Vietnam, <gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss>-Double Plus,
                        Chronological Papers and Other Misc. Material. Secret; Flash; <gloss
                            target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. Received at 9:41 a.m. Repeated to Saigon. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RBH1">Read</persName> also reported the sequence of events
                        described in this telegram in situation reports based on telephone calls
                        from <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> at 3 p.m., 6 p.m., 6:45
                        p.m., and 10 p.m. that day. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-01-16T14:20:00+00:00">January 16, 1969,
                        1420Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>642/<gloss target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> 1160. From <persName
                        corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>. Ref: Paris 608 (<gloss
                        target="#t_Delto1">Delto</gloss> 1156).<note n="2" xml:id="d284fn2">
                        <ref target="#d282fn2">See footnote 2, Document 282</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>As Department aware from telecons during past 12 hours, our agreement with
                            <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> became slightly unglued after they
                        informed us of <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> concurrence (<gloss
                            target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>). Things are now back on the track
                        after this morning’s meeting with <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                            >Lau</persName> (<gloss target="#t_septel1">septel</gloss>).<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d284fn3">In telegram 757 from Paris/<gloss target="#t_Delto1"
                                >Delto</gloss> 1174, January 17, <persName corresp="#p_VCR1"
                                >Vance</persName> reported on the meeting he had with <persName
                                corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> in the <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                                >DRV</gloss>’s safe house in Choisy on the morning of January 16.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> proposed that, in lieu
                            of the French drawing lots or flipping a coin, his government was
                            prepared to let the United States or <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                            speak first in whatever order they desired, and then the order of
                            speaking would be reversed and rotated henceforth. <persName
                                corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> agreed to the proposal.
                                (<persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, National
                            Security File, Country File, Vietnam, Peace Talk Material for <persName
                                corresp="#p_GRN1">Ginsburgh</persName>-Hold for <persName
                                corresp="#p_GRN1">Ginsburgh</persName>)</note> The first procedural
                        meeting at the Majestic will be held at 10:30 am Paris time Saturday.<note
                            n="4" xml:id="d284fn4">January 18. Regarding the first procedural
                            meeting of the expanded talks, <ref target="#d286">see Document
                                286</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The sequence of events following yesterday’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName>, to the extent that we know them, is
                        as follows: <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> delegate <persName
                            corresp="#p_MVB1">Mai Van Bo</persName> went to see Quai Assist Direct
                        Manac’h at about 5:30 pm to inform him of our agreement. The fact that Bo
                        did this before the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> informed us at 1800
                        of <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> concurrence was contrary to what we
                        had <pb facs="0856" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/> agreed. Moreover, Bo gave
                        Manac’h an inaccurate account of what had been agreed between us. When I
                        later met with Manac’h at 7:30 pm, he said that Bo had at first suggested
                        that the meetings would be in the large rather than the small conference
                        room as agreed. Bo had also neglected to tell Manac’h that the table would
                        be a solid circle and, finally Bo had insisted that in deciding the speaking
                        order the French should draw lots in a manner which reflects the four party
                        concept.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I told Manac’h that Bo had given him an incorrect account of our agreement
                        and suggested that he contact him again promptly to set things straight.
                        Manac’h met again with Bo and the minor misunderstandings about the
                        conference room and the table were eliminated. Bo, however, insisted on his
                        version of how to determine the speaking order. After receiving Manac’h’s
                        account of his second meeting with Bo, I asked <persName corresp="#p_OV1"
                            >Oberemko</persName> to join me shortly after midnight and told him
                        where things stood. Obermeko confirmed our understanding of the agreement on
                        speaking order reached with <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> and
                        said that he had seen <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> at 6 pm
                        and <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> reported his meeting with
                        me in a manner consistent with our understanding. At my request <hi
                            rend="italic">Oberemko</hi> then met with <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                            >Lau</persName> at the Soviet Embassy and about three hours later sent
                        First Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BS1">Bogomolov</persName> to report to
                        me on the conversation. According to <persName corresp="#p_BS1"
                            >Bogomolov</persName>, there was a “misunderstanding” and it would have
                        to be cleared up directly between me and <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                            >Lau</persName> in the morning. I asked several times what kind of
                        misunderstanding there had been and <persName corresp="#p_BS1"
                            >Bogomolov</persName>’s replies were rather cryptic, but he did express
                        the view that “everything will be all right.”</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>At about 8 this morning Paris time, <persName corresp="#p_HVLDC1"
                            >Lau</persName> called us seeking an immediate meeting, and the
                        remainder of the story has been reported in a separate telegram. While it is
                        not clear what happened between yesterday’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_HVLDC1">Lau</persName> and today’s meeting, we suspect that
                        the “misunderstanding” was either Bo’s misunderstanding because of lack of
                        familiarity with the agreed procedures or the <gloss target="#t_NLF1"
                            >NLF</gloss>’s objection to the drawing of lots in our presence with
                        only one winner. Perhaps it was a combination of both.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Harriman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
