<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-10-17T15:47:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-17T15:47:00-05:00" n="86" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                        <head>86. Telephone Conversation Between President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d86fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, Recordings and Transcripts,
                                Recording of Telephone Conversation Between <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, October 17, 1968, 4:47 p.m.,
                                Tape F6810.05, <gloss target="#t_PNO1">PNO</gloss> 2. No
                                classification marking. This transcript was prepared specifically
                                for this volume in the Office of the Historian.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-10-17T16:47:00-04:00">October 17, 1968, 4:47
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>President: <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Dean</persName>, well what’s your
                            evaluation today?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Well. I think there’s about
                            one chance in three that we’ll hear from them by the end of the week.
                            That’s about the way it sounds to me.</p>
                        <p>President: Why do you make it so low?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Well, the way these fellows
                            turn around. If they have got to go to the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> has got to
                            go to their Central Committee, that sort of thing, I just think it may
                            take a little time. I think that <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Cy</persName>
                            are inclined to think that the answer will be yes, but I am not quite as
                            optimistic as that.</p>
                        <p>President: You got all of your people to quit talking?</p>
                        <pb facs="0273" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: I’ve really buttoned up the
                            fellows here. Vietnam is just a forbidden subject over here. I did try
                            to get NBC [television] today to come off of this business about we’re
                            being hung up by a great debate between us and Saigon. I just told them
                            very much on a background basis that the allies are in agreement. The
                            problem is Hanoi. Get them started in that direction instead of our
                            quarreling with Saigon. That’s not very good.</p>
                        <p>President: I don’t know why <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName>
                            didn’t call them in for a little backgrounder and say this is just a
                            deliberate untruth and there’s not anything here that’s holding up
                            anything—that we have kicked the ball and the ball is in their court,
                            and they can have peace any time they want it. Now we can’t make up
                            their minds. We have already taken action. It is up to them, and quit
                            saying anything here about Saigon. And I just think we oughtn’t send
                                <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> anymore stuff. To hell
                            with him. I don’t care. I am just tired of the son-of-a-bitch making
                            that kind of stuff. It is just awful that his Foreign Minister and all
                            that stuff just cause us all this damn trouble.<note n="2" xml:id="d86fn2">See <ref target="#d75">Document 75</ref>.</note> I
                            feel about the same way about these little jerks that have got one
                            battalion over there. I don’t think it’s necessary for us to stop our
                            bombers because some goddamn fellow is back in the back woods and this
                            son-of-a-bitch <persName corresp="#p_GJ1">Gorton</persName>—I don’t like
                            that either.<note n="3" xml:id="d86fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_GJ1">Gorton</persName> stated that he soon
                                expected <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> to make a
                                statement regarding the complete cessation of the bombing. See The
                                New York Times, October 17, 1968.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>President: You are going to have a great problem with me, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, in getting my consent to go out
                            there and do a goddamn thing except a simultaneous announcement. I’m
                            getting ready to say something at 4 o’clock—we’ll tell them at 3:30—but
                            I am not going to come in here and let them screw up this thing and give
                            us the pain and anguish and misery that they do for nothing. It serves
                            no purpose.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Well, that statement of
                                <persName corresp="#p_GJ1">Gorton</persName>’s is the worst single
                            thing that has happened, I think.</p>
                        <p>President: He is an erratic, no good fellow—I knew that the first time I
                            saw him. And I think that <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>
                            is absolutely disgraceful, but he’s got more control over his people
                            than I guess that you and I have. And I just hope—I don’t know who is
                            reading these reports back from <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell</persName>. Does that have pretty general distribution over
                            there?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Oh, no. This particular
                                <gloss target="#t_HARVAN1">HARVAN</gloss> Double Plus Series is
                                <persName corresp="#p_RBH1">Ben Read</persName>, <persName>Bill
                                Bundy</persName>, and myself, and <persName corresp="#p_HPC1">Habib</persName>, who has gone back to join the delegation in
                            Paris—he’s a member of the delegation.</p>
                        <p>President: That’s all right, but you make sure they tell me—they come in
                            everyday and tell me that State says so and so. You be sure
                                <persName>Bill Bundy</persName> is not talking to anybody.</p>
                        <pb facs="0274" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Oh, I am sure he’s not.</p>
                        <p>President: All right. What about—do you think that they’ll report back
                            before this weekend?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: I think there’s a chance
                            they could come back at almost any time because I would be very much
                            surprised if the Russians were not working on this very hard the way
                                <persName corresp="#p_DE1">Dobrynin</persName> welcomed my telephone
                            call yesterday morning<note n="4" xml:id="d86fn4">No record of this
                                conversation was found.</note> about the 2 to 3 days thing. I just
                            illustrate—I said if they will meet on Monday we could stop the bombing
                            on Friday or Saturday, and he was very glad to have that, and my guess
                            is that the Russians are working on this very hard.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of the Middle East.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>