<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 109.Mr. Kilpatrick to Mr. Blaine..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-12-02T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-12-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="109" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                <head>No. 109.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kilpatrick</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santiago,
                                    Chili</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-12-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2, 1881</date>.
                            (Received January 4, 1882.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 9.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Had I been able, I would, at the time the
                        Government of Chili determined to arrest and suspend the functions of the
                        government of Calderon, have given you the reasons as they are placed in my
                        possession by the secretary of state, and everything done to preserve good
                        faith as to promises made me here on the part of the government. But for
                        four months I have been very ill; for the last two months at the point of
                        death, unable even to write my own name. I am now just able to sit up, and
                        for your information and on behalf of the honor and good faith of Chili I
                        make this brief statement.</p>
                <p>Chili guaranteed through me to demand no annexation of territory from Peru as
                        an absolute condition of peace. This was done at your request. She agreed to
                        demand no territory if security for future peace and safe and satisfactory
                        indemnification could be secured otherwise, and in no case to annex
                        territory save where a large majority of the actual residents were citizens
                        of Chili and foreigners. She agreed to build up and strengthen the
                        government of Calderon if possible, and, if possible, to make it
                        respectable, constitutional, stable, a government with which she could treat
                        for peace. These pledges were made in good faith and would have been
                        fulfilled; but our new minister at Lima arrived. Whether true or false, he
                        has the reputation of having impressed the government of Calderon and the
                        people of Peru with the idea that the Government of the United States would
                        not permit annexation of Peruvian territory to Chili under any
                        circumstances. This was published and talked of. He, himself, emphasized
                        this in his letter to the government of Piérola. He sent messages to the
                        Argentine Republic urging them to send a minister at once to check the power
                        of Chili. The whole conduct of Calderon, befriended and sustained by Chili,
                        changed; and he is openly accused now by the Government of Chili of having
                        without authority flooded the country with his own paper currency, of having
                        gathered and collected arms, and of having organized secret forces, and
                        finally of having placed himself in communication with the belligerent
                        forces of Piérola, Montero, and Sola, and the Government <pb facs="0274" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> of Bolivia, still in open arms against Chili,
                        now threatening her outposts, and cutting, from time to time, her lines of
                        communication. And so far had he succeeded that the department of Arequipa
                        had proclaimed for him, and a promise made on the part of our own minister
                        at Lima to said belligerents, that the Government of the United States would
                        forcibly resist the disintegration of Peru and had determined to maintain
                        and sustain the government of President Calderon.</p>
                <p>These are the facts as given to me by the administration here to justify them
                        in the course they have pursued. The arrival of your messenger with special
                        and unknown instructions is beginning to create an excitement here and a
                        resentment against the United States that will not be easily calmed. Chili
                        has looked upon our country as its greatest friend; has been willing to make
                        many sacrifices to comply with your requests; but now, in view of the course
                        pursued at Lima, the threatening claims of some great Peruvian company
                        professing to be backed by the Department at Washington, of which I send you
                        a copy marked A, is creating an alarm and excitement here such as has never
                        existed in Chili. I should like to give you details, but I am unable from
                        extreme weakness to dictate another sentence.</p>
                <p>Yours truly,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. KILPATRICK.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure No. 9.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Shipherd</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Kilpatrick</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">The
                                        Peruvian Company</hi>,<lb/>10 <hi rend="italic">Spruce
                                        Street, New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-10-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 19, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith
                            official printed copies of communications on behalf of this company to
                            the minister of Peru and Chili at Washington.</p>
                    <p>Duplicates of these inclosures were filed in the Department of State on
                            the 11th instant, and the originals were personally delivered by * * *
                            our counsel at Washington, on the 13th.</p>
                    <p>I place these copies in your hands, of course, without comment, and only
                            for your early information. I have reason to suppose that you will
                            receive instructions concerning the interests involved at an early
                            day.</p>
                    <p>It may be proper to add that this company is now fully organized, with a
                            capital of $250,000,000; that it includes the best legal, diplomatic,
                            and money resources of the United States; that the title upon which it
                            relies is approved unanimously by a large staff of eminent counsel, and
                            that it has unqualified assurance of ample governmental backing. It has
                            called for the property, and you may safely rely that it has at command
                            every means of enforcing that call. I send you a recent copy of the
                            Times, which does but reflect the average public sentiment here. All the
                            papers (preliminary) in the case I sent to your address in this city
                            before you sailed.</p>
                    <p>We are prepared to treat Chili fairly, even liberally, but only on
                            condition that she recognizes our superior rights. If she raises an
                            issue she will simply get nothing. Right must rule.</p>
                    <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JACOB R SHIPHERD.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
