<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 157.Mr. Angell
                            to Mr. Blaine..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d157</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">157</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079" lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616" lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-04-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="157" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d157">
                <head>No. 157.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Angell</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-04-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 30, 1881</date>.
                            (Received June 20.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 149.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: A recent trial in Her Majesty’s supreme court
                        in China has raised certain questions which deserve the most careful
                        consideration of the government of every nation whose citizens are employed
                        as officials by the Chinese Government.</p>
                <p>Edward Page, a British subject, employed in the imperial maritime customs at
                        Canton, was arraigned upon an indictment charging him with murder and with
                        manslaughter of a Chinaman, who on the 26th of October last was shot and
                        killed, while attempting to smuggle goods into the country. Page pleaded to
                        the jurisdiction of the court because, while declaring that he was not
                        guilty, his acts on the occasion under consideration were official, and had
                        been examined, approved, and ratified by the Tsung-li Yamên as acts of
                        state. He maintained that Her Majesty’s court ought not to take cognizance
                        of the indictment.</p>
                <p>Chief Justice French * * * decided that he must plead. Accordingly he pleaded
                        “not guilty,” was tried and acquitted. On the trial several customs
                        officers, among them one or two Americans, refused as witnesses to give
                        information in their possession on the ground of privilege, maintaining that
                        their information belonged to the Chinese Government, and so could not
                        properly be communicated to the court. The judge ruled that they must
                        testify, but did not punish them for persisting in their refusal.</p>
                <p>It is not alone the British who are concerned in the issues now raised. There
                        are now in the customs service citizens of the United States and French and
                        German subjects. The case has therefore attracted the attention <pb facs="0382" n="258" xml:id="pg_258"/> of all the diplomatic
                        representatives here, and all have thought it expedient to consult their
                        governments upon the questions which this trial shows may be pressed upon us
                        at any time.</p>
                <p>I think the following is a fair statement of the questions in which the
                        consuls and the ministers of the United States may be called to act, and on
                        which therefore instructions, if the Department sees fit to send them before
                        a case with one of our citizens actually arises, would be very
                        acceptable.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>If an American citizen in the official service of the Chinese
                            Government is charged with crime, must the consul issue a writ for his
                            arrest?</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Must the accused obey the writ?</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>If he appears in court and pleads to the jurisdiction of the court, on
                            the ground that his act is official and is approved by the Chinese
                            Government, must he on showing that such is the fact, be
                            discharged?</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Shall any distinction be made between the case, when the person
                            injured or wronged is a Chinaman, and the case when he is a European or
                            American?</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Shall an American citizen in the official service of the Chinese
                            Government, if he is summoned as a witness, be permitted by the consular
                            court to refuse to give oral evidence on the grounds that he is
                            commanded by his superior to refuse, and that his information is the
                            property of the Chinese government?</item>
                </list>
                <p>It is understood that the customs authorities hold that a plan substantially
                        like the following should be followed:</p>
                <p>If a foreigner in the Chinese service is accused, his consul should ascertain
                        of the Chinese authorities whether the act complained of was done in the
                        discharge of official duty. If they reply in the affirmative, the case shall
                        go to the minister, who will adjust it with the Chinese Government. If they
                        reply in the negative, they shall also discharge the accused from their
                        service, and the consul shall take up the case judicially. If the foreign
                        employé is wanted as a witness, the summons shall be sent to him through the
                        Chinese authorities.</p>
                <p>I may say that the ministers all fully appreciate the desirableness of
                        sustaining and strengthening the foreign customs as far as possible
                        consistently with the just use of the exterritorial rights which are secured
                        by treaty, and which for the protection of our citizens we must exercise.
                        But I think none are of the opinion that we can go quite so far in waiving
                        jurisdiction as the customs authorities seem to desire.</p>
                <p>While the object of this communication is to obtain the opinions of the
                        Department rather than to argue the questions presented, still, perhaps, I
                        may not improperly indicate some of the results of my study of the subject
                        here upon the ground.</p>
                <p>I conceive that we must look upon an exercise of jurisdiction over our
                        citizens here not merely as a privilege, but also as a duty. It is a duty to
                        the Chinese, to the citizens of other nations, to our own citizens, and
                        especially to the latter. It is easy to see that if we should suffer lawless
                        American citizens to commit crime with impunity, not only should we bring
                        deserved reproach upon our name but we should furnish a provocation for this
                        people, who do not at all enjoy the presence of foreigners, to subject our
                        well-disposed citizens to annoyance, if not to peril. It is, therefore, only
                        with the greatest caution and for very cogent reasons that we should relax
                        the hold of our laws upon our citizens.</p>
                <p>Bearing this obvious principle in mind as we consider the fine questions
                        above raised, I do not see.</p>
                <pb facs="0383" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>How when an American citizen, even though he be in the official
                            service of the Chinese Government, is accused of crime, we can safely
                            relieve the consul from the duty of bringing the accused before him for
                            some kind of judicial inquiry into the facts.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It follows as a matter of course that the accused must appear in
                            response to the writ.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In civil cases, if the defendant pleads and proves that his act is
                            official and approved by the Chinese Government, I think his plea should
                            cover him. But even in such cases he should appear before the consul and
                            plead and prove his official authority for his act. The British
                            Government, in a case which arose in 1863, so instructed the British
                            minister at Peking.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>In a criminal case, if the person injured is a Chinaman, and the
                            Chinese Government approves the official act by which the injury has
                            been done, I think, on the whole, the wisest plan is in general to
                            recognize the plea of the accused that he is protected by the
                            approbation of the Chinese Government as valid, and to discharge him.
                            There may be indeed some danger that feelings of animosity against
                            foreign officials will be excited; but the Chinese are so obedient to
                            their government that the danger is not very great, and our government
                            can, if it becomes necessary, forbid its citizens from entering upon the
                            Chinese service. And possibly some limit might be set to the extent to
                            which this plea should be recognized, if it is thought that there is
                            danger of any abuse of it in aggravated cases.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>If the person injured is not a Chinaman, I do not see how we can
                            escape the duty of judicial investigation. No European government would
                            be content if one of its citizens or subjects were harmed by an American
                            citizen in the alleged discharge of his official duty under the Chinese
                            Government, and the accused were not fully tried in our consular court.
                            Nor, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis</hi>, should we be satisfied
                            without a consular trial of a European in the Chinese service who had
                            injured one of our citizens. I doubt whether in any such case the plea
                            of governmental authorization and approval of the act should be accepted
                            as sufficient ground for the discharge of the accused.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In respect to what shall be required of Americans in the Chinese
                            service, when they are called into court as witnesses, I think it must
                            be admitted that there are some things which they should not be asked to
                            disclose. They should be permitted to plead privilege to a certain
                            extent. Perhaps it must be left to the consul to decide in each case how
                            far this plea shall be extended. But in view of the inexperience and
                            lack of legal training of some of our consuls, it would be helpful if
                            the government should lay down some general principles for their
                            guidance.</item>
                </list>
                <p>It should of course be regarded as the duty of the consuls and the minister
                        to avoid in every way all unnecessary interference with the officials in the
                        Chinese service and to discourage vexatious proceedings against them. But so
                        long as we claim exterritorial jurisdiction over our citizens, we must
                        faithfully discharge the duties which it imposes upon us.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JAMES B. ANGELL.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
