<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-12-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                    <head>No. 19.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Delaplaine</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-12-06"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 6, 1880</date>.
                            (Received December 27.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 392.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received from the United States consul
                        at Buda-Pesth a note inclosing clipping from the Pester Lloyd, published in
                        that city, which I herewith append. It is a notification to British subjects
                        resident in Hungary and the territories belonging thereto from Her Britannic
                        Majesty’s consul-general at Buda-Pesth, wherein is suggested the entry of
                        their names in a register at his office, in order to avoid difficulties
                        which might arise in establishing their nationality.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Sterne informed me that the Swiss consul had published a similar notice
                        to his countrymen, and asked whether a like action on his part would be
                        advisable.</p>
                    <p>Not having received a reply from the Department to my No. 377, on the subject
                        of the law relative to Hungarian citizenship, and in view of the brief
                        interval before the law in question would come into force, it appeared to me
                        that a similar notification might be expedient and to the interest of
                        American citizens in that country. Upon consultation with Consul-General
                        Weaver on the subject, he expressed full concurrence with my opinion, and I
                        accordingly communicated the same to Mr. Sterne, at Buda-Pesth.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>J. F. DELAPLAINE.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 392.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">notice to british subjects.</hi></head>
                        <p>The undersigned, Her Britannic Majesty’s consul-general for Hungary,
                            desires to draw the attention of British subjects resident in Hungary
                            and the territories belonging thereto to paragraph 48 of Law L of
                            December 24, 1879, which prescribes that—</p>
                        <p>“Whosoever shall have resided in Hungary, or the territories belonging
                            thereto, at the time the present law came into force, (namely, the 24th
                            of December, 1879,) for a period of at least five consecutive years,
                            although at different places, and whose name has been entered in the
                            register of tax-payers in any parish within the said dominions, shall be
                            deemed to be a Hungarian subject, unless he shall prove within one year
                            from the date above referred to (the 24th of December, 1879) to the
                            magistrate of the place in which he resides, that he has retained his
                            foreign nationality.”</p>
                        <p>Under these circumstances, and in order to obviate difficulties which
                            might arise to subjects of Her Britannic Majesty in establishing their
                            nationality, the undersigned suggests the advisability of British
                            subjects resident in Hungary having their names entered in a register
                            kept for that purpose at Her Britannic Majesty’s consulate-general at
                            Buda-Pesth.</p>
                        <closer><signed>AUDLEY GOSLING,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Her Britannic
                                    Majesty’s Consul-General.</hi></signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">26 <hi rend="smallcaps">Waitzner
                                    Boulevard</hi>,<lb/><placeName><hi rend="italic">Buda-Pesth</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30,
                                    1880</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>