<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 199.Mr. Dichman to Mr. Evarts..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="199"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                <head>No. 199.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dichman</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 20, 1881</date>. (Received March
                        23.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 245.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Upon the receipt of your No. 133, of the 13th of
                    October last, referring to the treaty for the preservation of peace between the
                    Republics of Colombia and Chili, I took the first favorable opportunity for
                    bringing the sentiments contained in your dispatch just cited to the knowledge
                    of the Colombian Government, upon which the most gratifying impression was
                    produced, to the extent of eliciting the suggestion on the part of the Colombian
                    foreign secretary that I might find it convenient to embody your views in an
                    official communication in order that the Colombian Congress, at its next
                    session, might be made acquainted therewith.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, I addressed a note to the Colombian foreign secretary, a copy of
                    which I beg leave to inclose, in which I endeavored to convey to his government
                    a knowledge of the pertinent parts of your dispatch No. 133, above
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>From the accompanying copy of his answer you will be pleased to learn that your
                    sentiments, of which I was happy to be the simple instrument of transmission,
                    were received by the President of this republic with the most profound
                    satisfaction, and that the ready approval extended to this government in its
                    adhesion to the great principle of international arbitration and the acceptance
                    for the President of the United States of the office of arbitrator, the
                    interests of peace between the Spanish-American Republics have been advanced,
                    and the friendly and honorable position of the United States as their mediator
                    and counselor is fully recognized.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ERNEST DICHMAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 245.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dichman</persName> to Señor
                                <persName type="to">Santamaria</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 7, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The negotiation of the treaty for the
                        preservation of peace between the Republics of Colombia and Chili, concluded
                        between the chargé d’affaires of the latter country and yourself, having
                        been reported by me to my government, it affords me much pleasure to inform
                        you that the intelligence thus conveyed by me has been received with
                        feelings of lively satisfaction at Washington, as indicating on the part of
                        the Government of Colombia, not merely a desire to maintain and strengthen
                        the relations of peace and good will with the Government of Chili, but as
                        evincing also a concurrence with the great principle of arbitration in the
                        settlement of international disputes, by establishing in the treaty above
                        mentioned that system of appeal as between cosignatory states in all future
                        emergencies; and the designation, made in the same instrument, of the
                        President of the United States as arbitrator between them in certain
                        contingencies has been accepted as a manifestation of that confidence in the
                        impartial amity of the Government of the United States for the sister
                        republics of the American continent, which it has always been its proud
                        privilege to welcome on every fitting occasion and strengthen by its example
                        of good will and kindly interest in their welfare.</p>
                    <p>In advance of the completion of the treaty by the exchange of the
                        ratifications for which provision is made in the fourth article, or in
                        anticipation of any formal invitation by Colombia, I am pleased to be able
                        to convey to you the informal assurance that should occasion for arbitration
                        between the two countries which are parties to the treaty arise, <pb
                            facs="0475" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> the President of the United States
                        will deem himself privileged in being able to respond to the flattering
                        trust reposed in him and as evincing the interests of the people and
                        Government of the United States in all that concerns the welfare of
                        Colombia.</p>
                    <p>Before bringing this communication to a close it may also be of interest for
                        you to learn that, on the subject of the treaty between Colombia and Chili,
                        an instruction, of similar tenor to the one which has given rise to this
                        communication, has been sent by the honorable Secretary of State at
                        Washington to the minister of the United States at Santiago, who, I have no
                        doubt, will convey to the government of Chili the like sentiments of amity
                        and high appreciation which it has been my pleasant duty to express to you
                        upon the occasion.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ERNEST DICHMAN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 245.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Santamaria</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Dichman</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of Colombia, Department of
                                    Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 14, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your courteous note of the 7th instant was
                        placed by me in the hands of the President of the republic, and I have the
                        honor to inform you that its contents produced in him the most profound
                        satisfaction, although not really a surprise, since when he dictated the
                        stipulation contained in article 2 of the convention of peace between
                        Colombia and Chili he did not doubt for a moment that the President of the
                        United States would accept with good will the part of arbitrator between the
                        two republics which is therein attributed to him, and that this fact would
                        afford the government at Washington the opportunity of again manifesting and
                        of putting into practice, occurring the contingency, those sentiments of
                        impartial friendship it has ever shown in favor of its sister republics of
                        the American continent, and more especially of Colombia, to which it has
                        been bound during many years by the closest and most cordial ties through
                        their community of interests of great importance and identity of aspirations
                        and institutions.</p>
                    <p>The adherence of my government to the grand principle of arbitration as the
                        only available mode of amicably adjusting whatever international
                        disagreement or nonconformity, has been constant and firm since the
                        political emancipation of this country, and whenever it has been admissible
                        it has yielded to it in public treaties, especially with sister republics.
                        But the adherence of my government to such principles and its submission to
                        it in said treaties would be worthless if at the proper time it were not
                        provided, nothing improbable, in the event that the contracting parties
                        could not or would not agree respecting the selection of an arbitrator, in
                        which case the application of the great principle would become useless and
                        there would remain no other recourse than an appeal to arms or the most
                        abject humiliation of the contracting parties. It was to avoid this grave
                        occurrence that the head of my government caused to be introduced into said
                        convention the very excellent stipulation that in the event of disagreement
                        in the selection of an arbitrator, it would be obligatory upon the
                        contracting parties to submit to the decision of the President of the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>As you must know the convention alluded to was very well received by the
                        Government of Chili on which account it may be expected that it will be
                        approved during the year by the Congress of each republic. So that relying
                        as we may with security upon the gracious acceptance by the President of the
                        United States of the charge of arbitrator that by virtue of said stipulation
                        appertains to him it may be safely predicted without risk of equivocation
                        that the doors are forever closed to a war between Colombia and Chili.</p>
                    <p>But you are aware that although it is a cause for satisfaction for Colombia
                        that she succeeds in obtaining the assurance of living perpetually in peace
                        with Chili she will have effected very little for her future tranquillity
                        without the absolute certainty of living in like manner with her other
                        sister republics with some of which she possesses clashing interests by
                        reason of boundaries, proximity, and other circumstances. It is precisely
                        with Chili that this country least fears difficulties. The great distance
                        that separates their territories, the proper pride that Colombia has ever
                        experienced at the sight of the prosperity of this sister republic, the
                        admiration with which she has contemplated the solid peace she has enjoyed
                        and the great and sincere sympathy which has been won from this country by
                        the thinking people of Chili in their stoic struggle constant and audacious
                        in favor of those liberal principles based upon justice and toleration are
                        circumstances which would make even without the convention alluded to if not
                        impossible at least most remote, any cause for difficulty between the two
                        countries.</p>
                    <pb facs="0476" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/>
                    <p>The President regarded the matter in this light and anxiously the idea of a
                        convention of peace between Colombia and Chili when the chargé d’affaires of
                        the latter proposed it with the object of introducing in it the clause
                        alluded to and that which is contained in article 3. These two points
                        comprise what there is truly grand, practically, substantially, purely
                        American, and especially new in that document.</p>
                    <p>The said convention accepted in these terms by the American republics as may
                        be expected that it will be in the course of the year at Panama, there will
                        be a perpetual international peace upon the American continent and the
                        United States will assume the great office, as of right pertains to it, of
                        mediator and counselor among the sister republics of the New World, bearing
                        upon her banner high and secure the celebrated motto of one of her
                        Presidents: “America for the Americans.”</p>
                    <p>In the name of my government I have the honor to thank you for your
                        spontaneous solicitude in laying the subject to which this note refers
                        before that at Washington and to beg that you will deign to accept the
                        sentiments of high consideration and respect with which I subscribe
                        myself,</p>
                    <p>Your very obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>EUSTACIO SANTAMARIA.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
