<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-01-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                    <head>No. 23.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-15"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 15, 1881</date>.
                            (Received February 1.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 411.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Pursuant to your instruction No. 206
                        (referring to legation dispatch No. 367), I have to say, that in response to
                        my application to the ministry for foreign affairs for the information
                        desired, that office transmitted to me the certified protocol of the act of
                        renunciation of American citizenship by Marcus Cohn, together with other
                        information requested by me.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to transmit herewith, copies and translations of the
                        correspondence on the subject with the ministry for foreign affairs, as
                        stated below.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN A. KASSON.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 411.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName> to Baron
                                    <persName type="to">Haymerle</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-12-31"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 31,
                                    1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The undersigned, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of the
                            United States of America, referring to the from the foreign office (I,
                            1475–9), under date of August 4, 1880, announcing that one Marcus Cohn,
                            had renounced his American citizenship, and assumed that of Austria,
                            begs that his excellency Baron Haymerle, minister of the imperial house
                            and imperial and royal minister for foreign affairs, will be so good as
                            to cause the transmission to this legation, of a statement which will
                            certify the <hi rend="italic">place</hi> and <hi rend="italic">time</hi>
                            of this act of renunciation by the aforesaid Cohn, together with a copy
                            of the record of the same showing the <hi rend="italic">formal act</hi>
                            of renunciation, certificate of which appears to be required for use in
                            the United States.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned will also be glad to receive, for the information of the
                            Department <pb facs="0157" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/> of State at
                            Washington, a copy of the law, if any, under which such acts of
                            renunciation are recorded.</p>
                        <p>He avails himself of this occasion to renew to his excellency Baron
                            Haymerle, the assurance of his very distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>KASSON.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>His excellency, Baron <hi rend="smallcaps">Haymerle</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                411.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Baron <persName type="from">Haymerle</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Kasson</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-08"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 8,
                                1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>In response to the esteemed note of the 31st December last, (F. O. 68,)
                            the imperial and royal ministry for foreign affairs has the honor
                            respectfully to transmit to Mr. J. A. Kasson, envoy extraordinary and
                            minister plenipotentiary of the United States of America, the inclosed
                            protocol, taken with Marcus Cobn by the district captaincy in
                            Bischof-Teinitz, on the 16th of July, 1880, whereby the said Cohn
                            expressly renounced the citizenship of the United States of America,
                            acquired through naturalization.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the information desired by the envoy at the close of his
                            note, the imperial and royal ministry for foreign affairs, has the honor
                            to remark that in respect to the renunciation provided in article IV of
                            the convention of 20th September, 1870, by a citizen of the United
                            States of America of his allegiance, no special legal enactments exist
                            in this empire.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the renunciation of Austrian citizenship, the same is,
                            article 4 of the Austrian state fundamental law of December 20, 1867 (A.
                            G. L., No. 142), “On the part of the state, only limited by duty of
                            military service,” and accordingly, males no longer liable to such
                            service and females do not require a formal document of discharge in
                            order to be released from their allegiance. The delivery of a
                            declaration to this effect before the competent political authority at
                            first resort is sufficient, which authority, upon application, issues a
                            certificate to that effect.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned, avails himself, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>For the ministry for foreign affairs.</p>
                        <closer><signed>WOLFARTH.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>The Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United
                                States of America, Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">John A. Kasson.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                            411.—Translation]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Protocol of Marcus Cohn, taken July</hi> 16, 1880,
                                <hi rend="italic">at Bischof-teinitz</hi></head>
                        <p rend="flushleft">[50 Kreu’r stamp.]</p>
                        <p>Taken at the K. K. district captaincy, at Bischof-teinitz, on the 16th of
                            July, 1880.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">subject.</hi></p>
                        <p>The Hon. K. K. Statthalterei, in Prague, has, under edict of July 5,
                            1880, (Z. 40985) based on the present application of Marcus Cohn for
                            re-reception into relations with the Austrian state, ordered, that a
                            document shall be required and produced from him wherein he expressly
                            renounces the citizenship of the United States of America, acquired by
                            him through naturalization.</p>
                        <p>Marcus Cohn to-day appeared here and begs, in pursuance of the edict of
                            the before-mentioned Hon. Statthalterei, that protocol of the following
                            declaration, be taken: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I hereby expressly declare, that I renounce the citizenship of
                                    the United States of America, acquired by me through
                                    naturalization.</p>
                                <p rend="right">“MARCUS COHN.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Mayer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">witness.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilhelm Wurscher</hi>, <hi rend="italic">witness.</hi></p>
                        <p>Concluded and executed.</p>
                        <closer><signed><list>
                                    <item>SWOBODA,<lb/><hi rend="italic">K. K. District
                                            Captain.</hi></item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Eimer.</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">K.
                                            K. Custode.</hi></item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0158" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 411.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName> to Baron
                                    <persName type="to">Haymerle</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-15"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 15,
                                1881</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="italic">F. O.,</hi> 1,
                            70.]</seg></opener>
                        <p>The undersigned, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of the
                            United States of America, acknowledging the reception of the note from
                            the imperial and royal ministry of foreign affairs (II, 66, 7), dated
                            January 8, 1881, and returning thanks for the communication with its
                            inclosure, herewith returns the declaration of renunciation of American
                            citizenship made by Marcus Cohn, and begs to say that Mr. Evarts desired
                            the information with a view to understand the customary forms adopted in
                            such cases by the Austro-Hungarian Government.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned avails himself of this occasion to renew, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer><signed>KASSON.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>His excellency Baron <hi rend="smallcaps">Haymerle</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Imperial and Royal Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                                    &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>