<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 242.Mr. Blaine to Mr. Pomeroy..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="american-revolutionary-war" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="american-revolutionary-war">Revolutionary War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="246"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                <head>No. 242.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Pomeroy</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-07-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 404.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: At the instance of his excellency Alfred H.
                    Littlefield, governor of the State of Rhode Island, I inclose herewith for the
                    representatives <pb facs="0543" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/> of the Republic of
                    France who are to visit the United States in October next, to attend the
                    centennial celebration of the surrender of Lord Cornwallis at Yorktown, an
                    invitation to visit the State of Rhode Island, and while there to remain as the
                    guests thereof.</p>
                <p>I will thank you to transmit the inclosed documents, relating to the invitation
                    in question, to the Government of France through the foreign office.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JAMES G. BLAINE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 404.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Governor <persName type="from">Littlefield</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">State of Rhode Island, Executive
                                    Department</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Providence</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-07-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 16, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor herewith to inclose for the
                        representatives of the Republic of France who visit the United States in
                        October next, to attend the centennial celebration of the surrender of Lord
                        Cornwallis at Yorktown, an invitation to visit this State, and while in the
                        State to remain as the guests thereof.</p>
                    <p>I request that you will cause the same to be forwarded through the proper
                        channels to those gentlemen.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to remain, very respectfully, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ALFRED H. LITTLEFIELD,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Governor.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Appendix 1 to inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">State of Rhode Island, Executive
                                    Department</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Providence</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-07-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 16, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the Representatives of the Republic of France appointed
                            to visit the United States at the Yorktown Centennial:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: I have the honor, in behalf of the
                        State of Rhode Island, and acting by authority of resolutions of the general
                        assembly, passed at its session held in Newport on the 3d day of June last,
                        to invite you during your sojourn in the United States to visit this State,
                        and while within the State to remain as the guests thereof.</p>
                    <p>I herewith inclose a copy of the resolution under the seal of the State, and
                        beg the honor, of an early reply.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ALFRED H. LITTLEFIELD,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Governor.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Appendix 2 to inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">State of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">(In General Assembly, May session, 1881.)</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">resolution</hi> authorizing the governor to invite the
                        representatives of the Republic of France to visit Rhode Island.</p>
                    <p>Whereas during the Revolutionary War in the year A. D. 1778, while the
                        British controlled the entrance to Narragansett Bay, and greatly distressed
                        and oppressed the inhabitants of the adjoining territory; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas in the month of July of that year a French fleet arrived in the said
                        bay, under the command of Admiral d’Estaing, and occasioned the destruction
                        of many of the vessels of the British fleet to the great satisfaction and
                        relief of the inhabitants of the State; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas in the summer of A. D. 1780, another French fleet, bringing a large
                        land force, arrived in the waters of the said bay, and to the great relief
                        of the inhabitants remained within this State for a considerable time, and
                        afforded protection to the lives and property of the inhabitants of the
                        State; and</p>
                    <pb facs="0544" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/>
                    <p>Whereas the Government of the United States has invited the Government of the
                        Republic of France to participate in the centennial celebration of the
                        surrender of the British forces in America, to take place at Yorktown in
                        October next, and the Republic of France has signified its intention to be
                        represented at and to participate in the said celebration, therefore, as a
                        token of gratitude, and as showing the appreciation of the people of Rhode
                        Island of the services rendered this State by the fleets and armies of
                        France, it is</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That his excellency the governor be, and
                        hereby is, directed and authorized to invite the representatives of France
                        who visit the United States to participate in the celebration in October
                        next, to visit the State of Rhode Island at such time during their sojourn
                        in the United States as may be convenient to them, and while the said
                        representatives are within the State to remain the guests thereof, and that
                        his excellency is hereby requested and directed to appoint a committee of
                        such citizens of this State as he may deem proper to assist him in
                        entertaining the guests of the State while here, in such a manner as the
                        committee may believe will be most acceptable to their guests, and that his
                        excellency the governor be, and he hereby is, authorized to draw his orders
                        upon the general treasurer for the expense incident to carrying this
                        resolution into effect.</p>
                    <p>A true copy. Attest:</p>
                    <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>JOSHUA M. ADDEMAN,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
