<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="315" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                    <head>No. 311.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lowell</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-12"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 12, 1881</date>.
                            (Received March 25.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 140.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acquaint you that, on the
                        10th of February last, I received a letter from B. H. Barrows, esq., the
                        consul of the United States at Dublin, inclosing an old passport issued to
                        Michael P. Boyton (one of the traversers in the late state trials in Dublin)
                        on the 20th November, 1866, by Mr. Seward, then Secretary of State. He
                        stated that Mr. Boyton had applied to him to <hi rend="italic">visa</hi>
                        this passport, which he had refused, and that he had reported his action to
                        the Department of State, which had approved of the same, and that at Mr.
                        Boyton’s request he now forwarded the old passport to me, asking whether,
                        under the circumstances, I could issue to him a new one.</p>
                    <p>I replied to Mr. Barrows, on the 10th of February, that under ordinary
                        circumstances Mr. Boyton, upon producing his old passport, proving that he
                        is the person named therein, and taking the oath prescribed by statute,
                        would be entitled to a new passport; that if the Department of State
                        approved of Mr. Barrows’s refusal to <hi rend="italic">visa</hi> his old
                        papers upon the ground that he was one of the traversers in the late state
                        trials, this would be a reason why I should not give him a new passport; but
                        if Mr. Barrows’s action was approved because it would have been irregular to
                            <hi rend="italic">visa</hi> a passport more than two years after its
                        date, <pb facs="0636" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/> there would be no objection
                        perhaps to issuing another one, it being understood that it would be
                        necessary in such case for Mr. Boyton to present himself in person at this
                        legation, and take the affidavit required by law. I requested Mr. Barrows to
                        send me a copy of his correspondence with the Department on this
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>I received a reply to this letter from Mr. Barrows on the 15th of February, a
                        copy of which, I herewith inclose. He also sent me copies of his letters to
                        Mr. Hay, Assistant Secretary of State, dated on the 12th of November last,
                        and of Mr. Hay’s answer to the same, dated on the 2d of December last.</p>
                    <p>You will observe that Mr. Boyton stated to Mr. Barrows that he was not a
                        native-born citizen, having been born in Ireland but taken to America when
                        he was a child. He appears to have declared in his application to the State
                        Department that he was born in the State of New York.</p>
                    <p>I answered Mr. Barrows’s letter on the 16th of February to the effect that if
                        Mr. Boyton was taken to America when a child and claimed citizenship on that
                        ground, it would be necessary for him to prove that his father was
                        naturalized there. I herewith inclose a copy of my letter.</p>
                    <p>No further correspondence upon this subject took place until the 8th of March
                        instant when I received late in the evening a telegram from Mr. Boyton,
                        dated at Kildare, Ireland, in the following words: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>I am an American citizen, and protest against an outrage to which I
                                have been this day subjected by being arrested on a warrant which
                                charges no offense. I claim the protection of my government.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>I thereupon, the next day, addressed a letter to Mr. Barrows at Dublin,
                        requesting him to ascertain, in the first place, whether Mr. Boyton is an
                        American citizen, and, if this should be shown to his (Mr. Barrows’s)
                        satisfaction, then that he should examine into the grounds of Boyton’s
                        arrest, and if the facts should justify the belief that his complicity with
                        treasonable or seditious objects had not been made out, that Mr. Barrows
                        should then apply to the authorities for his discharge or to be informed why
                        he is detained. I herewith inclose a copy of my letter, to which I have not
                        yet received any answer. * * *</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>J. R. LOWELL.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 140.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Consul <persName type="from">Barrows</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Lowell</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-02-14"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 14,
                                    1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of
                            yours 10th inst, relative to the application of Michael P. Boyton for a
                            new passport. I explained to Mr. Boyton that his personal attendance
                            before you was necessary, but he first desired an expression of opinion,
                            and thereupon I sent in his application. Copies of the dispatches
                            relating to this matter are herewith submitted.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Boyton told me that he was not a native-born citizen, having been
                            born in Ireland, but taken to America when he was a child. You will
                            observe that the Assistant Secretary says the State Department records
                            state he was born in the State of New-York. I have to-day written Mr.
                            Boyton informing him that in order to make application for the reissue
                            of his passport he must appear before you in London.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>B. H. BARROWS,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">James Russell Lowell</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister, London.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0637" n="513" xml:id="pg_513"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 140.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lowell</persName> to
                                Consul <persName type="to">Barrows</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-02-16"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 16,
                                    1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your
                            letter of the 14th instant, in relation to the case of Michael P.
                            Boyton.</p>
                        <p>The fact that he has already received a passport from the Department of
                            State will not, in my opinion, entitle him to a new one, inasmuch as
                            this original passport was granted upon the supposition that he was born
                            in the United States. If, as he now declares, he was born in Ireland and
                            taken to America when he was a child, it will be necessary for him to
                            prove that his father was naturalized there; and this can only be done
                            satisfactorily by producing his father’s letters of naturalization. It
                            is well that Mr. Boyton should understand this before taking the trouble
                            to come to London.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. R. LOWELL.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">B. H. Barrows</hi>, Esq.,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Consul, Dublin, Ireland.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 140.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lowell</persName> to
                                Consul <persName type="to">Barrows</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-09"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 9,
                                1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I received last night a telegram from Mr.
                            Michael P. Boyton, stating that he is an American citizen and protesting
                            against an alleged outrage to which he has been subjected by being
                            arrested on a warrant which he says charges no offense. He thereupon
                            claims the protection of the United States Government. This telegram is
                            dated at Kildare, but I see by to-day’s Times that he has been taken to
                            Kilmainham jail, in the neighborhood of Dublin. I prefer not to
                            correspond directly with Mr. Boyton, and I must request you to see him
                            and make such inquiries into his case as will enable me to take the
                            proper action in regard to it.</p>
                        <p>It is necessary to acertain, in the first place, whether he is an
                            Americon citizen or not. By a reference to the correspondence I have
                            already had with you upon his application for a new passport, you will
                            observe that while it appears by the records of the State Department at
                            Washington that be claimed to have been born in New York, he has lately
                            stated to you that he was born in Ireland, but taken to America when he
                            was a child. I must consider, under the circumstances, this latter
                            statement to be the true one. He must, therefore, prove that he has been
                            naturalized in the United States, or that his parents have been
                            naturalized, in order to be entitled to the privileges of citizenship.
                            If the fact of his American citizenship should thus he ascertained to
                            your satisfaction, I desire then that you should carefully examine into
                            the grounds of his arrest, and if the precise facts justify the belief
                            that no substantial charge of his complicity with treasonable or
                            seditious objects can be made out, you will communicate this to the
                            authorities in Ireland and request his discharge or to be informed why
                            he is detained. You will please intimate, in respectful terms and
                            without any warmth or suggestion of threats, that you are making these
                            inquires under my instructions, and are acting precisely as British
                            consuls in the United States acted soon after the civil war, under the
                            directions of the British minister at Washington, in cases of summary
                            arrests of British subjects. It is my duty to protect, so far as I can,
                            all citizens of the United States, whether native or naturalized, who
                            are shown to be innocent of designs to subvert civil order, and I should
                            not perhaps require in such cases evidence of innocence so full and
                            conclusive as that which might be required in a court of law. At the
                            same time I shall by no means try to screen any persons who are
                            evidently guilty of offending against the criminal laws of Great
                            Britain.</p>
                        <p>I have to request that in Mr. Boyton’s case, as well as all similar ones,
                            you will be cautious and temperate and at the same time vigilant and
                            firm, and that you will promptly report your action to me.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant.</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. R. LOWELL.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Benjamin H. Barrows</hi>, Esq.,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Consul of the United States, Dublin.
                                Ireland.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>