<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 348.Mr. Evarts to Sir Edward
                                    Thornton.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-01-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="352" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                <head>No. 348.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName> to Sir <persName type="to">Edward
                                    Thornton</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-01-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 10,
                                1881</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: At the instance of my colleague, the
                            Secretary of the Treasury, I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy
                            of a letter dated the 27th ultimo, addressed by him to the collector of
                            customs at Suspension Bridge, New York, which it is desired should be
                            communicated to the customs authorities of the Dominion of Canada, for
                            their information concerning the transportation of merchandise in bond
                            from one port to another in that country, by the way of the Suspension
                            Bridge and Ogdensburg, N. Y.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. Upton, Assistant Secretary of the Treasury,
                                    to the collector of customs, Suspension Bridge, New
                                York.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Treasury Department, Office of the
                                            Secretary</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington, D.
                                            C.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-12-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 27,
                                        1880</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The department has received a
                                communication from the general superintendent of the Rome, Watertown
                                and Ogdensburg Railroad Company requesting authority to transport
                                from Suspension Bridge to Ogdensburg, in sealed cars, under entry
                                for immediate transportation and exportation, bonded merchandise
                                arriving at Suspension Bridge from one port in the Dominion of
                                Canada and destined for another port in said Dominion.</p>
                    <p>It appears from the letter of the general superintendent that in the
                                case of merchandise forwarded in the manner indicated, it is the
                                practice, under existing regulations, to require entry for warehouse
                                and transportation to be made at your port, and that upon arrival of
                                the merchandise at Ogdensburg, entry for withdrawal and exportation
                                is also required.</p>
                    <p>The Rome, Watertown and Ogdensburg Railroad Company request the
                                department to issue such instructions as will enable parties to make
                                shipment of goods in bond in the manner and between the points
                                indicated under one entry in order to obviate the expense and delay
                                attending the present method.</p>
                    <p>The department after full consideration of the subject, has decided
                                that merchandise from a Canadian port and destined for another port
                                in Canada may be entered at Suspension Bridge, N. Y., for immediate
                                transportation and exportation in bond to Canada, via Ogdensburg, N.
                                Y., and vice versa, under the form of entry and bond now required at
                                New York and other ports, in the case of foreign merchandise passing
                                in transit through the United States to or from the Dominion of
                                Canada (see Articles 20 to 33 of the regulations under the treaty of
                                Washington, $ 2171).</p>
                    <p>Especial care should be given to the requirements of Article 24 of
                                the regulations referred to relating to the sealing of cars employed
                                in conveying the merchandise from your port.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. K. UPTON,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant
                                        Secretary.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
