<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="373" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                        <head>No. 369.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Edward
                                    Thornton</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-06-06"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 6, 1881</date>.
                                (Received June 7.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your note of the 26th
                            ultimo, and previous notes, relating to incursions, made into territory
                            of the United States by British Indians from Canada, I have now the
                            honor to transmit herewith copy of a dispatch, and of its inclosure,
                            which I have received from the governor-general of Canada, from which it
                            will be seen that the Government of the Dominion is desirous of
                            obtaining all the information which can be furnished by the officers of
                            the United States calculated to lead to the identification and
                            conviction of the Indians who have been guilty of the outrages set forth
                            in your notes.</p>
                        <p>I shall therefore be glad if you will enable me to comply with the wishes
                            of the Canadian Government, and I am at the same time requested to
                            assure the Government of the United States of the desire of that of the
                            Dominion to co-operate, on its side of the boundary, in every way in its
                            power for the purpose of maintaining order and peace amongst the Indian
                            tribes, and preventing predatory incursions on either side of the
                            border.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>EDW’D THORNTON.</signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0716" n="592" xml:id="pg_592"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Lord <persName type="from">Lorne</persName> to
                                    Sir <persName type="to">Edward Thornton</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Quebec</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-06-03"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 3,
                                    1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I submitted for the consideration of
                                my government copies of your dispatches relative to the alleged
                                predatory incursion of British Indians into the territory of the
                                United States, and I have now the honor of forwarding a copy of an
                                approved report of a committee of the privy council, which contains
                                their views on the subject, and requesting that the American
                                authorities may be moved to furnish, as far as possible, the
                                information referred to, with the view to joint action for the
                                maintenance of peace and order amongst the Indian tribes on the
                                frontier.</p>
                            <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer><signed>LORNE.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Copy of a report of a committee of the honorable
                                    the privy council approved, by his excellency the
                                    governor-general June</hi> 3, 1881.</head>
                            <p>The committee of the privy council have had under consideration the
                                dispatches of Her Majesty’s minister plenipotentiary at Washington
                                to his excellency the governor-general, on the subject of the
                                predatory incursions (as is alleged) of British Indians into the
                                territory of the United States.</p>
                            <p>The Canadian Government is sensible of the great importance of
                                preventing incursions (as far as is possible) across the
                                international boundary line of Indians from either side. Canada has
                                long suffered great inconvenience and has been forced into large
                                expenditure from the unwelcome presence of Sioux and other American
                                Indians who have intruded themselves into the Canadian Northwest,
                                and therefore will willingly join the Government of the United
                                States in some concerted plan of action to prevent the recurrence
                                (as far as possible) of such migrations.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the present representations of the predatory
                                incursions of certain Canadian Blackfeet, Cree, and other Indians
                                across the border, and of their stealing and killing the cattle of
                                the American settlers, the Canadian Government will take immediate
                                steps to warn these Indians, and will enforce order on the Canadian
                                side of the border; and, with a view of punishing Indians who have
                                been guilty of the outrages mentioned in the dispatches under
                                consideration, the Canadian Government will be glad to be put in
                                possession of all information which can be furnished by the officers
                                of the United States calculated to lead to the identification and
                                conviction of those Indians.</p>
                            <p>The committee humbly advise your excellency that Her Majesty’s
                                minister at Washington be moved to request the Government of the
                                United States to furnish, as far as may be in their power, the
                                information referred to, and that he be requested to assure that
                                government of the desire of the Canadian Government to co-operate,
                                on their side of the boundary, in every way in their power, for the
                                purpose of maintaining order and peace amongst the Indian tribes,
                                and preventing predatory incursions on either side of the
                                border.</p>
                            <p>All of which is humbly submitted for your excellency’s approval.</p>
                            <closer><signed>A. CAMPBELL,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Senior
                                        Councillor.</hi></signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-06-02"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 2,
                                    1881</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>