<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 433.Mr. Smyth to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d437</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">437</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="437"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d437">
                <head>No. 433.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Smyth</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Monrovia, Liberia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 16, 1881</date>. (Received April
                        26,)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 112.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you of the result of
                    the mission of His Imperial Majesty’s ship Victoria.</p>
                <p>On the 3d of February, 1881, according to the terms of the memorandum or protocol
                    drawn up between Commander Yon Valois and the German consul of the one part, and
                    the Republic of Liberia of the other, <pb facs="0860" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/>
                    the ship Victoria, with the President of Liberia and Hon. E. W. Blyden,
                    secretary of interior, on board, steamed out of the port of Monrovia on its
                    voyage to the scene of the outrage on the Kroo coast.</p>
                <p>On arrival at Sinou an interpreter was taken on board and a Liberian military
                    officer, and the ship proceeded then to Hanna-Kroo, the place where the chief
                    actors were who took part in the robbery and cruel treatment of the captain and
                    crew of the German steamer Carlos.</p>
                <p>When Hanna-Kroo was reached a message was sent by the President to the King and
                    chiefs requesting them to come on board to talk “the palava.” The King and
                    chiefs and five men came. The King informed the President that the live men he
                    brought were engaged in the robbery, and that one of them was the leader.</p>
                <p>The President ordered all the inhabitants to leave the town with whatever of
                    property they could remove within thirty-six hours, that no lives might be lost,
                    as he purposed destroying it. One man was killed by the explosion of a shell. A
                    Liberian officer, a German officer and 120 men, fully equipped, landed after the
                    town was shelled, this being the next day, and fired the town.</p>
                <p>The culprits and the King and the chiefs were brought to Monrovia, the latter to
                    be held as hostages until the indemnity should be paid by their people, and the
                    former to abide the action of the court of admiralty.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. H. SMYTH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
