<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-04-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="440" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d440">
                    <head>No. 436.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Smyth</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Monrovia,
                                    Liberia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-04-28"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 28, 1881</date>.
                            (Received June 9.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 119.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose a paper, marked
                        No. 1, just issued by the Hon. G. W. Gibson, secretary of state of Liberia.
                        I beg to call your attention to it, because it marks an important epoch in
                        the history of missionary and other philanthropic operations in this
                        country.</p>
                    <p>A great deal of money has been spent and many valuable lives lost In the
                        effort to evangelize the natives of this country on the purely spiritual
                        line, but the experience of nearly one hundred years has shown that any
                        effort for the benefit of these tribes, apart from secular agencies, will
                        never be successful. The native must be made a productive man in the region
                        of matter. He must be taught to provide for his material wants. He must be
                        made to engage in improvements that appeal to his comprehension, to his
                        sense of self-interest. This the missionary in past times neglected, and the
                        result is that there is nowhere on this coast any missionary station which
                        has become self-supporting.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Gibson has himself been engaged in missionary work, and he writes
                        from the experience and observation of years. It is to be <pb facs="0863" n="739" xml:id="pg_739"/> hoped that missionary societies will consider
                        the failures of the past, and see whether such practical suggestions as
                        those in the circular inclosed may not help them to solve the problem of
                        dealing successfully and efficiently with the work of African evangelization
                        and civilization.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JNO. H. SMYTH.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>