<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-04-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="454" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d454">
                    <head>No. 450<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Morgan</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1881</date>.
                            (Received April 28.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 183.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 112, of the 14th of March,
                        1881, referring to cases of American citizens impressed into the military
                        service of Mexico, has been received.</p>
                    <p>In my correspondence with the Mexican Government in relation thereto, I
                        endeavored to show that their impressment was not only a violation of the
                        laws of nations, but was also a violation of the positive treaty stipulation
                        between the Government of the United States and the Government of Mexico
                        (see inclosures to my dispatches Nos. 125 and 133); and that the latter
                        government is responsible for their illegal capture, detention, and enforced
                        servitude is in my opinion free from doubt. I think also that a demand
                        should be made for damages in their behalf. If you should agree with me in
                        this opinion, I beg to be instructed as to what is to be the measure of
                        damages which I am to demand.</p>
                    <p>In my instructions contained in Department dispatch No. 71 (9th of October,
                        1880), I was directed to demand their instant release, and “that they be
                        sent unmolested to their homes in Texas or allowed to proceed likewise
                        without molestation to any point in Mexico where they have business or may
                        desire to go.” I was also directed to ask “for reasonable pecuniary
                        indemnity for the detention, annoyance, and inconvenience to which they may
                        have been thus unwarrantably subjected.”</p>
                    <p>These instructions I complied with, as you will see by reference to the
                        inclosure in my dispatch No. 125. But I have to call your attention to the
                        fact that the parties in interest have not stated to what extent they have
                        been damaged, and I am not able to determine to what amount their demand
                        should be limited, and, as the Department dispatches are silent upon this
                        subject, I respectfully ask to be instructed thereupon before communicating
                        any further upon the subject with the Mexican Government.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>P. H. MORGAN.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>