<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 477.Mr. Morgan
                            to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d481</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">481</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846" lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692" lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907" lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-09-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="481" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d481">
                <head>No. 477.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Morgan</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-09-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 22, 1881</date>.
                            (Received October 7.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 273.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On yesterday I sent you a telegram as follows:
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The President’s annual message is considered threatening toward
                                Guatemala. It announces that Mexican troops have arrived at the
                                frontier State and that others will soon join them.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Confirmatory of the threatening character of the message, I inclose an
                        editorial taken from the Monitor Republicano of the 20th instant, and a
                        translation of that portion thereof which relates to the subject before us,
                        from which you will observe that the editor is of the opinion that the
                        President’s words give reason to believe that a declaration of war is
                        imminent.</p>
                <p>Referring, now, to your dispatch No. 164 (August 24, 1881), in which I am
                        instructed to continue to transmit promptly, as events progress, all
                        information on the pending difficulties between those two countries, I have
                        to report that from the date of my dispatch No. 259 (August 25, 1881) up to
                        last evening I have not had any conversation whatever with Señor Herrera,
                        the Guatemalan minister; indeed, in that interval I had seen him but once,
                        and that was at a ball which he gave on the 15th instant in commemoration of
                        the anniversary of his country’s independence. I had declined his invitation
                        on account of the President’s illness. At his earnest instance, however, and
                        as the news had reached here that the President had been sitting up and had
                        gone to Long Branch, I went to the ball for a few moments. It is well,
                        perhaps, that I did so, as my absence might have been misinterpreted.</p>
                <p>Neither had I had any conversation with Señor Mariscal upon the subject until
                        yesterday. Although I had seen him several times in the meanwhile he
                        carefully abstained from alluding to it.</p>
                <p>Yesterday evening (21st), however, Mr. Herrera called on me. He directed my
                        attention to the President’s message, and particularly to that portion of it
                        which refers to Guatemala, and which was the subject of my telegram. He
                        appeared to be quite concerned about it. He informed me that Señor Mariscal
                        had at his (Mr. Herrera’s) house on the night of the 15th spoken with
                        several persons upon the difficulties which were pending between Mexico and
                        Guatemala; that the President of the United States had proffered his
                        services as mediator between them; that the proffer had been declined. (One
                        of the guests of Mr. Herrera had told me the same thing only a short while
                        before.) I was careful not to say anything beyond assuring Mr. Herrera that
                        the United States would view with concernment any trouble between the two
                        countries, and that they would use every amicable means to prevent it. I did
                        not, however, deem it imprudent to mention to him that I had informed you of
                        the message by telegraph.</p>
                <p>Later in the evening I received Señor Mariscal’s visit. He came in while the
                        minister from Germany was with me. The German minister was speaking to me
                        upon the subject of the pending difficulties between Mexico and Guatemala,
                        and the proposed intervention of the United States, and had stated that
                        Mexico was very angry thereat, when Señor Mariscal came in, to whom I told
                        the subject of the pending conversation.</p>
                <p>The German minister soon left, and after a few moments’ conversation upon
                        other subjects, Señor Mariscal said: “And so you were <pb facs="0931" n="807" xml:id="pg_807"/> speaking of the Guatemala question when I came
                        in?” I said, “Yes.” He asked me whether I had seen the President’s message.
                        I replied that I had read that “Napoleonic” document. He inquired of me why
                        I characterized it thus. I replied because its warlike tone, as well as its
                        manner, reminded me of the speeches which that Emperor was in the habit of
                        delivering, or causing to be delivered, from the throne, when he considered
                        himself, in some sort, the master of Europe. He asked me if I really thought
                        it was so. I answered, “To such an extent that I had said to the minister
                        from Guatemala, not long before he came in, who had spoken to me on the
                        subject, that it would perhaps have been better if he had kept the money
                        which his ball had cost to purchase powder with.” Señor Mariscal then
                        repeated a great deal of what he had said to me in our former interviews
                        concerning the grievances which Mexico had against Guatemala, adding that he
                        proposed to send to congress, with his department report, a copy of your
                        dispatch No. 138 (June 16, 1881), as well as his memorandum to me in reply
                        thereto.</p>
                <p>Alluding to your dispatch I said to him that when he came in I was
                        explaining, in reply to a remark of the German minister, that it was
                        understood that the President of the United States had offered his
                        mediation, and that he had proposed to take up the question as to whether
                        Soconusco and Chiapas belonged of right to Mexico, which had angered the
                        Mexican Government and people; that the President of the United States had
                        not, through me at least, made any such proposition. I then took occasion to
                        call Señor Mariscal’s attention to the fact that there was not a press in
                        Mexico (except the official journal) which did not contain almost every day
                        something offensive to the people of the United States, a circumstance which
                        I told him I regretted very much, as it had a tendency to engender a bad
                        state of feeling on both sides of the line, and that it was, I thought,
                        particularly to be regretted in view of the friendly and sympathetic tone of
                        the assurances contained in those of your dispatches, which, under
                        instructions, I had read to him. I cited to him particularly the Nacional, a
                        paper which was owned and published, I had been informed, by a nephew of the
                        minister of Hacienda (secretary of the treasury). Señor Mariscal was obliged
                        to admit, with some reservation, the truth of my observations, and said, in
                        regard to the Nacional, that he would take occasion to speak to the editor
                        and caution him upon the subject.</p>
                <p>I particularly directed his attention to the warnings which were daily
                        uttered against the granting of concessions, &amp;c., to Americans, and the
                        baneful influences which, it was said, American enterprise would exercise
                        upon Mexican interests, material and political, threatening as it did the
                        national existence. In the same connection I mentioned as an instance of
                        these warnings the articles which were constantly appearing in the daily
                        papers upon the subject of the branch of the Franco-Egyptian bank here to
                        the effect that the assent of Congress to the contract celebrated between
                        the President and the directors thereof, should be given, upon the ground
                        that it would do a great deal toward counterbalancing American commercial
                        influence in the country, and I inquired of him how it was possible that the
                        expenditure of, I might say, hundreds of millions of American money in
                        Mexico, giving, as it did, employment to many thousands of its citizens,
                        could be any detriment to the country. In respect of the Franco-Egyptian
                        bank, I called his attention to the suggestion which I had made to him upon
                        the subject, to the effect that I believed if the Government of Mexico
                        desired to establish a bank here, one could be organized with American
                        capital upon the basis of our own national banks; and I asked him which
                        should be considered <pb facs="0932" n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/> the safer
                        institution, the one whose circulation was secured by United States bonds,
                        or one whose circulation had, practically, no security; the one whose
                        circulation did not exceed the amount of the security therefor, or the one
                        whose circulation exceeded by three to one the amount of its nominal coin
                        deposits; the one which would bring $20,000,000 of bonds of the United
                        States—more than equivalent to that sum in gold—into the country, or the one
                        which would be enabled to take at least $60,000,000 in coin out of it.</p>
                <p>I pointed out to him what in my opinion were the inconveniences and losses
                        which would result to the government in case the proposed bank was
                        chartered. I called his attention to the fact that the capital of the bank
                        was fixed (the limit) at $20,000,000; that it was authorized to issue
                        thereon $60,000,000 in paper; that although it was proposed that no issue of
                        paper should be permitted beyond three for one of coin in hand, we all knew
                        how temporary such a security was, and how easily such a requirement of law
                        could be avoided; that while the paper of the bank was not to be a legal
                        tender from individual to individual, it was to be a legal tender as from
                        individuals to the government; that consequently all debts due to the
                        government might be paid in that currency, while the creditors of the
                        government could exact payment in coin, which they would certainly do in
                        case the notes of the bank were at a discount, as I did not doubt they would
                        be in a very short time after they were issued.</p>
                <p>As an example of the loss which would occur to the government in such a
                        contingency, I cited the case of a Vera Cruz merchant who should receive a
                        consignment of goods, the duties upon which would amount to $100,000. (It
                        does not require much of a cargo to pay that amount of duties.) He may pay
                        in notes of the bank. Should these notes be at a discount of 10 per cent,
                        the merchant will only pay $90,000. The government owes him, later, a like
                        sum. When it pays him he will exact coin. The loss on both sides to the
                        government is apparent. The public officers, the army as well, I said to
                        him, would be paid in currency. I asked did he think, if the currency should
                        be at a discount, that payment therein would be received with thanks by the
                        soldiers, particularly when they saw ordinary creditors of the government,
                        including subventions amounting to some $4,000,000, annually paid in
                        silver?</p>
                <p>In respect of the advantage which it had been suggested would result from the
                        credit which the government had of $4,000,000, I suggested that the money
                        thus loaned would be in paper, and I asked what trouble it would give the
                        bank to issue that amount of notes? And again I asked whether fostering such
                        an institution would prove wise or a successful precaution against the
                        encroachment of American commerce, or whether it did not occur to him, as it
                        did to me, that it was likely to result in financial distress to the
                        country, as well as give rise to political complications. I said it was
                        difficult for me to understand what motive the press had in thus attempting
                        to warp the judgment of the people, as well as the government, against us,
                        in the face of past events, and notwithstanding the assurances which the
                        Mexican Government had received of our friendship and sympathy.</p>
                <p>I called his attention to the fact that the government appeared to share
                        these ideas with the press, citing the fact, in evidence thereof, that it
                        had recently gone to the expense of contracting for the emigration to Mexico
                        of some one hundred Italian families, to whom a considerable tract of land
                        had been given, calling his attention to the fact that Americans could come
                        into the country as easily as Italians (or any <pb facs="0933" n="809" xml:id="pg_809"/> other Europeans) could, and that when here they would
                        be, probably, the equals of the others.</p>
                <p>Going back to the Guatemala question, I stated that the President of the
                        United States, when he consented to have it suggested to Mexico that he
                        would act as arbitrator between the two countries, had been actuated by the
                        purest feelings of friendship for both nations, and in the interest of a
                        public peace, which, once disturbed, might result in consequences little
                        dreamed of by either party. Laughingly, I said that if the Mexican appetite
                        for conquest had been excited, it was probably fortunate for us that
                        Guatemala and not Texas was the meat it craved.</p>
                <p>This is the substance of what occurred, although I do not pretend that the
                        points touched upon are given chronologically.</p>
                <p>Señor Mariscal reiterated that if there should be a war with Gautemala it
                        would be Gautemala’s fault. He admitted that the course pursued by the
                        United States was friendly in its character, although he persisted in saying
                        that the facts of the case had been misrepresented by Guatemala to you.</p>
                <p>We parted on the best of terms, but he left me more than ever convinced that
                        nothing would prevent a war between the two countries unless a positive
                        position is taken by the United States, and I venture to suggest that unless
                        the government is prepared to announce to the Mexican Government that it
                        will actively, if necessary, preserve the peace, it would be the part of
                        wisdom on our side to leave the matter where it is. Negotiations on the
                        subject will not benefit Guatemala, and you may depend upon it that what we
                        have already done in this direction has not tended to the increasing of the
                        cordial relations which I know it is so much your desire to cultivate with
                        this nation.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>P. H. MORGAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 273.—Translation from
                                Monitor Republicano, September 20, 1881.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Another dark passage in the President’s message is the one in which he
                            refers to the diplomatic relations between Mexico and the republic of
                            Guatemala. These are his words:</p>
                    <p>“With regard to Guatemala, it is painful to have to say that an equally
                            favorable disposition is not observed in the course of the government of
                            that country; on the contrary, there appears to be a certain interest
                            revealed on its part in preserving indefinitely the same vagueness and
                            uncertainty in its relations with Mexico as regards the international
                            boundaries between the two countries. The Executive, notwithstanding,
                            will make every effort to clear up a situation which is pregnant with
                            evil for our country as well as for Guatemala. If, in pursuing these
                            efforts, the intervention of Congress should become necessary, I shall
                            not fail to ask for it in proper season.”</p>
                    <p>The words with which the President treats the Guatemala question are
                            terrible; they indicate that certain of our relations with that republic
                            are very tightly drawn, and in truth, unless the official documents and
                            acts of the Government of Guatemala show, as the President says they do,
                            a special desire on its part to continue in its uncertain attitude
                            toward this nation, it may be said that the sentence above quoted from
                            General Gonzalez’s message is a bold one.</p>
                    <p>It is a clear and explicit accusation against the Government of
                            Guatemala, expressed in very harsh terms for a document such as a
                            presidential message.</p>
                    <p>The public in general were not aware that matters had proceeded so far
                            between the Mexican and Guatemalan Governments, and all methods of
                            conciliation must have been very nearly exhausted when the chief of the
                            nation speaks in such terms as these, in the face of the nation, to
                            Congress.</p>
                    <p>The answer of the president of the chamber to the paragraph which we have
                            copied upon the Guatemala question indicates in a greater degree the
                            hostile feelings which exist between the two governments. He said:</p>
                    <p>“It is with still greater pain that the Congress of the Union has learned
                            that the Government of Guatemala has not manifested a disposition
                            similar to that evinced by <pb facs="0934" n="810" xml:id="pg_810"/> the
                            United States to adjust its relations with our country, appearing, as it
                            does, to wish to maintain in its present uncertainty the question of our
                            national boundary.</p>
                    <p>“The members of both chambers hope that if in truth the cause of the
                            attitude of the government is the want of a recognized boundary between
                            the two countries, this state of affairs will cease so soon as the
                            scientific commission named to this end by the Mexican Government, will
                            have completed its labors, and that an amicable convention may end a
                            question which has been so much debated, and which may result, if
                            prolonged, in great evils to fraternal nations, which should be
                            avoided.</p>
                    <p>“In the meanwhile the representatives of the nation approve of the
                            efforts which the Executive has made to obtain an honorable solution of
                            so delicate a question, and it may rest assured that in this matter, as
                            well as in the maintenance of the dignity and rights of the republic
                            against all comers, it will have the support of the legislative
                            power.”</p>
                    <p>In our opinion this is a grave and delicate question; it is proper under
                            all circumstances to guard and defend everything required by the
                            national honor; it is proper also to bring to an end this question of
                            boundary, which has for such a length of time agitated the two
                            countries, but this should be done with the circumspection and prudence
                            which a matter of such a nature demands.</p>
                    <p>The words of the President to the chamber has made us believe that we
                            were near to a declaration of war; that is to say, that the methods of
                            conciliation had been exhausted.</p>
                    <p>When diplomatic reserve shall permit, the republic will have the right to
                            know what has taken place, for that which has been done in this
                            direction looks toward the breaking up of the friendly relations between
                            the two nations who have always traveled together in the best
                            harmony.</p>
                    <p>We have no data upon which to express an opinion upon this grave
                            emergency; we follow day by day the current of political events, and
                            without a doubt, notwithstanding something has transpired with reference
                            to this matter, we were far from believing that there was a threatened
                            difficulty between Mexico and Guatemala; for the same reason, without
                            more information upon the subject than we have gathered from the few
                            words of the President, we can neither judge nor venture an opinion; we
                            must wait for events; we must wait also for some word which the Diario
                            Official may think proper to say, to throw some light upon this
                            question, which is the most important one as regards our diplomatic
                            relations.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
