<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-06-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="565" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                    <head>No. 561.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Christiancy</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima,
                                Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-06-28"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 28, 1881</date>. (Received July
                            18.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 322.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch No. 320, I have now
                        the honor further to say that I have been carefully considering the question
                        of the recognition of the provisional government therein referred to, and
                        having received nothing by the last mail in any way modifying your dispatch
                        No. 143, and knowing that I had kept you fully informed of all the facts
                        necessary to a decision, and seeing that the question whether the Calderon
                        government was a government <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> was not
                        expressly made a condition, and that the fact of your having already
                        received Mr. Elmore as the confidential agent of that government, which I
                        take to be a clear indication that you would expect me to recognize that
                        government if I found the facts you had stated as hypothetical to be true,
                        but more especially hearing a rumor here as having come from the United
                        States that my successor would not come here until peace was settled, and,
                        therefore, fearing that my neglect to make the requisition might be
                        construed as a design on my part to delay his coming, I finally concluded,
                        on the 26th instant, to recognize the provisional government as such, and I
                        here inclose copy of my letter to Mr. Galvez, minister of foreign affairs,
                        making the recognition.</p>
                    <p>I must confess that, if left to act entirely on my own judgment, I should not
                        have recognized this provisional government until it should have become a
                        government <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>, or until it should have
                        succeeded in assembling a quorum of Congress, nor until we could have seen
                        whether this Congress or that of Piérola (national assembly) at Ayacucho
                        should represent the most of the people of Peru. But I claim no right to set
                        up my own judgment against that of my government, believing strict obedience
                        to the wishes of my government my first and sole duty.</p>
                    <p>In making the recognition, I have thought it best to place it on the precise
                        grounds indicated by your instructions, believing that it would have a
                        better effect in aiding this incipient government by a clear intimation that
                        our government was more inclined to encourage constitutional than
                        dictatorial government, and that they wished to aid in restoring peace
                        between these belligerent republics.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>I. P. CHRISTIANCY.</signed></closer>
                    <pb facs="1044" n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 322.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Christiancy</persName> to
                                Señor <persName type="to">Galvez</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima, Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-06-26"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 26,
                                1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur le Ministre</hi>: My government, having
                            been informed of the organization at Magdalena of what, in your circular
                            note to me of April 30 last, is styled a provisional government under
                            the presidency of Señor Doctor Don Francisco Garcia Calderon, has given
                            me instructions, in substance, that if I find, 1st, that such
                            provisional government is supported by the weight of character and
                            influence of Peru; 2d, that it is endeavoring to restore constitutional
                            government, with a view both to internal order and negotiations with
                            Chili for peace, then I am to recognize it as a provisional
                            government.</p>
                        <p>Believing, from the best evidence I can obtain, that each of these
                            hypothetical propositions is sufficiently established in the
                            affirmative, I therefore formally express such recognition on the part
                            of the Government of the United States.</p>
                        <p>Please accept the assurance, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>I. P. CHRISTIANCY.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>