<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 577.Mr. Hurlbut to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d581</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">581</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HPZNpQil9Rnjj" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-civil-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026387"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil Service</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="581"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d581">
                <head>No. 577.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hurlbut</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lima, Peru</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-10-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 31, 1881</date>. (Received November
                        25.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 24.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The events which I indicated in my last dispatch
                    (No. 23), in relation to the recognition of the Calderon government by the
                    interior <pb facs="1070" n="946" xml:id="pg_946"/> of this country, have
                    actually transpired. Montèro, commanding the north of Peru, has formally and
                    officially proclaimed adhesion to this authority, with the hearty assent of the
                    army and people.</p>
                <p>Cacères, commanding the center, has undoubtedly followed, but official notice has
                    not yet been received. The southern department, headquarters at Arequipa, led
                    off in this peaceful revolution on the 8th day of October. Thus the fact which I
                    deemed of primary consequence, the unity of Peru under a constitutional head,
                    has been attained, and it has been attained in deference to the wishes of the
                    United States, and in distinct opposition to the European legations, as well as
                    to the pretensions of Chili.</p>
                <p>Not a drop of blood has been shed, not a life lost in obtaining this result.
                    Whatever may be the final settlement of affairs with Chili, I feel that this
                    consolidation of public sentiment in Peru is a successful issue of one object of
                    my mission here.</p>
                <p>It is a matter of very deep regret to me that Mr. Kilpatrick has not been able to
                    bring any influence to bear upon the Chilian administration at Santiago in favor
                    of the recognition and support by Chili of the Calderon government.</p>
                <p>I understand, by certain paragraphs in his “instructions,” that through Mr.
                    Osborn the United States had received substantial assurances from Chili of
                    favorable action by that republic toward the Calderon government, and that Mr.
                    Kilpatrick was directed, on proper occasion, to strengthen and confirm such
                    purposes.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately my colleague has not written me a single dispatch, and I can only
                    guess at his actions from events. The process of military suppression of the
                    Calderon government by Chili has been given you heretofore, and in Mr.
                    Balmaceda’s note to Mr. Kilpatrick of 8th October he evidently chose to consider
                    this Calderon government as utterly dissipated, for he uses the term “<hi
                        rend="italic">ya fenecido</hi>” (already dead) as descriptive of its
                    condition.</p>
                <p>It has seemed to me that the whole conduct of Chili in this matter has been in
                    bad faith.</p>
                <p>Having given the pledge referred to to Mr. Osborn, they have violated it without
                    excuse. I find their reason for so doing in the known fact that they could not
                    obtain from Calderon a pledge of cession of territory, and therefore determined
                    to destroy his authority. In this they have signally failed, and have in fact
                    contributed to his present popularity in Peru. The commissioners, Altamirano and
                    Novoa, have been in this city some six days. As yet, no approach has been made
                    toward negotiation. I learn from various sources, of different degrees of
                    credit, that they are considering the propriety of indefinite armed occupation,
                    the establishment of Chilian civil service, and the consequent reduction of Peru
                    to a Chilian province. This is undoubtedly what they would prefer. Their
                    principal fear seems to be that Chili has not population enough to overrun and
                    hold Peru. The idea next in favor is to demand cession of Tarapacá, Tacna, and
                    Arica as condition precedent to consideration of peace, and as a <hi
                        rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> of entertaining any negotiations. They say
                    that public opinion in Chili is united and resolute to keep these territories at
                    all hazard, and that a failure so to do would overthrow their government.</p>
                <p>It is probable that within ten days one or other of these propositions will be
                    decided upon. At present they utterly ignore Calderon and his government, and I
                    am of opinion that they will soon command him to leave their lines. This, of
                    course, they have the right to do, and he is ready to go when they say so, and I
                    should not be surprised <pb facs="1071" n="947" xml:id="pg_947"/> in that case
                    if they should interfere with the legations established here, or at least with
                    those which recognize Calderon.</p>
                <p>The straightforward and manly course for them would be to acknowledge the known
                    fact of Calderon’s lawful presidency, sustained by an overwhelming popular
                    sentiment, and frankly to open negotiations with him on the subject of peace on
                    terms of equality. But for the very reason that this course would be manly and
                    straightforward, I judge that it will not be adopted. On the contrary, I have
                    full reason to believe that they are now secretly treating with agents of
                    Piérola.</p>
                <p>I have already several times presented the apparent impossibility that Peru can
                    receive the least courtesy, to say nothing of justice, in this controversy so
                    long as she stands alone, and I continue to wait with patience the action and
                    decision of the Executive at home.</p>
                <p>There are many insolences in the official Chilian paper in this city, the only
                    one allowed to be published, and there have been wrongs done to American
                    citizens which for the present I do not forward to you, in the hope, though I
                    fear a vain one, that the military authorities may correct these abuses.</p>
                <p>As to the articles in the press I take no notice, but the others are more
                    serious, and if not soon properly adjusted I shall be compelled to send them
                    forward for your consideration. The situation is not pleasant, and requires of
                    me an unusual forbearance, and a careful consideration of such steps as I may
                    find necessary to maintain the rights of our citizens.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S. A. HURLBUT.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
