<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="586" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d586">
                    <head>No. 582.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Hurlbut</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30,
                            1881</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 21.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You have already been made acquainted, by my
                        No. 19, of the 22d instant, with the determination of this government to
                        send a special mission to South America for the purpose of adjusting
                        whatever questions, growing out of the contest between Chili and Peru and
                        Bolivia, may affect the relation of the United States to the three
                        belligerent powers, or conduce to the restoration of good understanding
                        among them.</p>
                    <p>I have now to inform you that William Henry Trescot, esq., of South Carolina,
                        has been commissioned as special envoy, with the rank of minister
                        plenipotentiary, to the Republics of Chili, Peru, and Bolivia, and will
                        forth with set out upon his mission.</p>
                    <p>The commission which Mr. Trescot receives will not supersede the ordinary
                        duties of yourself and your colleagues at Santiago and La Paz; but all
                        communications and negotiations connected with the settlement of the pending
                        difficulties between Chili, Peru, and Bolivia, so far as this government may
                        deem it judicious to take action, will be transferred to Mr. Trescot’s
                        charge.</p>
                    <p>Under the instructions which have been given to Mr. Trescot, he will place
                        himself in direct communication with the several governments to which he is
                        thus specially accredited. It is, however, expected that he will learn from
                        you and your colleagues the exact condition of existing political relations,
                        and receive such suggestions as your recent experience may enable you to
                        submit for his consideration. The action he may take, however, must be
                        decided upon his own responsibility and in the exercise of his independent
                        authority.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Trescot will be accompanied on this important mission by the Third
                        Assistant Secretary of State. As it may be necessary to consult <pb facs="1078" n="954" xml:id="pg_954"/> the representatives of the United
                        States in Chili, Peru, and Bolivia at the same time, or to conduct a
                        simultaneous negotiation with those governments, Mr. Trescot is empowered by
                        the President of the United States to authorize Mr. Walker Blaine to
                        represent the United States at any point where this necessity may occur.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JAMES G. BLAINE.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>