<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-04-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="650" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d650">
                    <head>No. 646.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Reed</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States.</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-04-07"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 7, 1881</date>. (Received April 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 61.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to Mr. Evarts’ instruction No. 111,
                        I have now the honor to inclose herewith, for your information, a copy of my
                        note of the 26th ultimo to the minister of state, on the question of
                        jurisdictional limits, and of a copy and translation of his reply thereto,
                        dated the 4th instant.</p>
                    <p>The minister of state confines himself to the question of jurisdictional
                        limits in time of peace, or, in other words, to the jurisdictional limits
                        established by Spain, within which Spanish <hi rend="italic">guarda
                            costas</hi> may detain and search merchant vessels with a view to the
                        prevention of smuggling, claiming, as did his predecessor, that inasmuch as
                        peace had been restored in Cuba at the time of the detention of the American
                        vessels Ethel A. Merritt, Eunice P. Newcomb, George Washington, and Hattie
                        Haskell, the question must necessarily be governed by those limits. Those
                        limits are, as will be seen by his excellency’s note, six miles from the
                        coast.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>DWIGHT T. REED.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 61.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Reed</persName> to the
                                Marques <persName type="to">de la Vega de
                            Armijo</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-26"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 26,
                                1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>On the 24th January last your excellency’s worthy predecessor addressed a
                            note to this legation giving the resorts of the investigation ordered by
                            His Catholic Majesty’s Government of the circumstances under which the
                            American vessels Ethel A. Merritt, Eunice P. Newcomb, George Washington,
                            and Hattie Haskell were fired upon and visited by Spanish gunboats off
                            the coast of Cuba, in the months of May, June, and July, 1880.</p>
                        <p>A copy of the above note was sent to Washington for the information of
                            the Government of the United States, and as it seemed to contradict all
                            of the material allegations of the masters and officers of the several
                            vessels, as to the distance of said vessels from the Cuban coast at the
                            time of the firing on and visitation by the Spanish officials, the
                            Department of State addressed each one of the representatives of the
                            vessels in question, contrasting their statements (which had been
                            accepted by the Department of State after the most searching methods had
                            been adopted to arrive at the truth of the facts according to the rules
                            of evidence in such cases) with the statements presented in behalf of
                            His Catholic Majesty’s Government, and asking them if they had any
                            corroborative evidence to offer as to the exactness of their former
                            affirmations, and also what they had to say in regard to the allegations
                            that the vessels were out of their course, and so liable to
                            suspicion.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, the Government of the United States would be pleased to
                            receive the views of that of His Catholic Majesty in regard to the
                            question of jurisdictional limit. The position of the Government of the
                            United States on this question was fully and clearly set forth in the
                            instruction of the Secretary of State to this legation of the 11th
                            August last, a copy of which was left with his excellency Señor Elduayen
                            on the 13th September, and I need not now occupy the time of your
                            excellency with a repetition of the views therein set forth further than
                            to state that it still adheres to the three-mile rule as the
                            jurisdictional limit.</p>
                        <p>The note of Señor Elduayen of the 24th January last does not appear to
                            meet the question of the jurisdictional limits within which the
                            visitations now under discussion were effected, and the wide
                            contradiction between the several statements does not suffice to bring
                            the position of at least three of the vessels within the customary
                            nautical league.</p>
                        <p>While the Government of the United States fully and frankly accepts the
                            disclaimer of that of His Catholic Majesty, that no intention of
                            discourtesy was intended in the visitations referred to, it insists on
                            the importance of a clear understanding of the jurisdictional limit. It
                            also insists on the distinction, between the verification (according to
                            the usual procedure of revenue cruisers), within a reasonable range <pb facs="1178" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/> of approach, of vessels
                            seeking Spanish ports in due pursuit of trade therewith, and the arrest
                            by armed force, without the jurisdictional three mile limit, of vessels
                            not bound to Spanish ports.</p>
                        <p>The considerations of my government on the above points, as advanced in
                            its instruction to this legation of the 11th August (already referred
                            to), do not seem to have attracted from His Catholic Majesty’s
                            Government the attention due to their precise bearing, and I am
                            therefore instructed to invite, through your excellency, an expression
                            of its views on the subject, and at the same time to express the hope
                            that such views may be furnished at as early a day as may be convenient
                            and practicable.</p>
                        <p>I avail, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>DWIGHT T. REED.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                            61.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <persName type="from">Marques de la Vega de
                                    Armijo</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Reed</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of
                                    State</hi>, <lb/>
                                <placeName type="venue"><hi rend="italic">Palace</hi></placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-04-04"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1881</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: I have read attentively your note
                            of 26th ultimo, in which you inform me that, having sent to the
                            Government of the United States the one addressed by this ministry to
                            the legation on the 24th January last, giving the result of the
                            investigation instituted by order of the superior authority of Cuba in
                            regard to the circumstances of the detention of the American merchant
                            ships Ethel A. Merritt, Eunice P. Newcomb, George Washington, and Hattie
                            Haskell, the Department of State had deemed it proper to transmit to the
                            representatives of said ships the contents of the same, in case they
                            might have new proof to offer, corroborating their former affirmations,
                            or wish to refute the charges imputed to them that their vessels were
                            out of their course, and so liable to suspicion.</p>
                        <p>You say further that meanwhile the Government of the United States
                            desires to know the views of that of His Majesty on the question of
                            jurisdictional limit, as closely connected with the question at
                            issue.</p>
                        <p>In the note of the 24th January last my predecessor in this ministry
                            plainly stated the official character of the service intrusted to the
                            gunboats Canto and Blasco de Garay when the detention of the American
                            ships occurred, remarking that the insurrection in the Island of Cuba
                            being happily terminated, the vigilance in those coasts was actually
                            directed to the prosecution of maritime smuggling and the enforcement of
                            our fiscal laws.</p>
                        <p>This statement made, it is my duty to say to you that the jurisdictional
                            limits within which the government of His Majesty understands itself to
                            have exercise, necessarily refers to those established by our special
                            legislation of customs and the reglamentary dispositions for the
                            prevention of smuggling, which covers an extension of six miles
                            (equivalent to 11.111 kilometers) from the coast to the high sea.</p>
                        <p>These limits were designated in 1775, repeated in 1830, and also in the
                            royal decree of 20th June, 1852, relative to the prevention of
                            smuggling, and finally in article 42 of the general customs ordinances
                            of July, 1870, and as there exists no treaty which conventionally
                            modifies these dispositions, and as no power has protested against them
                            in the period of so many years, the Spanish Government, apart from the
                            right which corresponds to Spain, in the use of its sovereignty, and in
                            conformity with the regulations admitted by international law to fix the
                            extension of its fiscal zone, deems it its duty to maintain and to cause
                            them to be respected.</p>
                        <p>I avail, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer><signed>EL MARQUES DE LA VEGA DE ARMIJO.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>