<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                        <head>No. 66.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Nuñez del
                                    Prado</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Relations of Bolivia</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">La Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-02-01"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1, 1881</date>. (Received May
                            10.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: This ministry has the honor to inform your
                            excellency’s government of Bolivia’s unshaken determination to defend
                            her rights and to repel the doctrines of absorption and conquest which
                            are sustained by Chili.</p>
                        <p>This attitude, which is the only one that my government considers
                            compatible with the dignity and lawful privileges of an American nation,
                            is in accordance with the conviction which it entertains, that the vast
                            proportions which the war on the Pacific is daily assuming affect not
                            only the territorial integrity of the allied nations, but even their
                            future autonomy and the permanent interests of America in a serious
                            manner.</p>
                        <p>In order to defend this idea, Bolivia has sacrificed her bravest sons,
                            and is anxiously waiting for every American country to protest against
                            the acts of that nation which has originated this sanguinary
                            conflict.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile the allied forces, whose arms have been attended with very ill
                            success during the course of the struggle, have just met with another
                            reverse near Lima.</p>
                        <p>The loss of that maritime city, and the total destruction of the allied
                            fleet, oblige the government of the undersigned once more solemnly to
                            declare to the friendly nations of this continent that it is resolved
                            unflinchingly to persevere in the defense of its autonomic integrity and
                            in that of American interests.</p>
                        <pb facs="0214" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/>
                        <p>The occupation of Lima, far from shaking the determination of this
                            republic, has stimulated its patriotism, and it is now prepared to
                            continue the struggle with Chili at any sacrifice.</p>
                        <p>This resolution is strengthened by the remembrance of an act which will
                            be condemned by all America. The war, which was inaugurated by the
                            forcible occupation of the maritime districts of Bolivia, is not a
                            dispute concerning a right that is more or less doubtful among the
                            belligerent powers; it is one for the settlement of serious and highly
                            important questions. Chili, confiding in the strength of her navy,
                            hoists the standard of conquest and of territorial annexation. Bolivia
                            and Peru reject these doctrines and offer their blood and treasure in
                            behalf of the triumph of the principle of right.</p>
                        <p>There is, then, an immense chasm between the objects aimed at by the two
                            contending parties; and peace with Chili, which is at the present moment
                            impossible, cannot be restored save by the absolute triumph of the one
                            and the utter overthrow of the other.</p>
                        <p>The justice of the cause which Bolivia is defending is in itself a
                            powerful stimulus to maintain the contest, and the cheering conviction
                            which she entertains, viz, that in sacrificing herself in her own
                            defense she is sacrificing herself for the great interests of America,
                            increases her warlike enthusiasm and adds fuel to the flame of her
                            patriotism.</p>
                        <p>My government feels persuaded that by resolutely accepting this situation
                            it furnishes evidence of its good faith towards its ally and of its
                            devotion to the principles which it professes.</p>
                        <p>If the final result shall be unfavorable to her, Bolivia will have the
                            glory of having sacrificed herself in defense of her rights in
                            preference to accepting the galling yoke of the conqueror.</p>
                        <p>Such, most excellent sir, are the declarations which my government
                            desires to make to friendly nations, inasmuch as they are watching with
                            increasing interest the prolonged struggle on the Pacific coast, and as
                            for the continuance of that struggle it relies upon the favorable
                            opinion of your excellency’s enlightened government.</p>
                        <p>This occasion affords to the undersigned, minister of foreign relations
                            of Bolivia, the high honor of offering your excellency the assurances of
                            the esteem and respect with which he subscribes himself, Your
                            excellency’s obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>DANIEL NUÑEZ DEL PRADO.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To his excellency the <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister of Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">of the United States of North America,
                                    Washington</hi>.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>