<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 684.Mr. Fish to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1881</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d688</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">688</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1881-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1881-03-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107622"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prostitutes</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-03-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="688"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d688">
                <head>No. 684.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 31, 1881</date>. (Received April
                        15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 383.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my Nos. 372, 373, 375, 376, 377, and
                    378, I have now the honor to inclose herewith copies of two notes which I have
                    addressed to this government respecting the action of the commune of Böttstein
                    in sending Fridolina Vögelin and Theresa Hauser, notorious prostitutes, to the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>In the first of these, dated and sent on the 29th instant, I informed the Federal
                    Council of the arrival of the Suevia at New York on the 28th instant, and
                    renewed the expression of the hope that they will cause the women to be returned
                    as promptly as possible, and that in future similar action on the part of the
                    local authorities in this country may be prevented.</p>
                <p>As I had not heard from the Federal Council in answer to my note of the 23d
                    instant, and I desire to give both the federal and cantonal authorities every
                    opportunity to effect the return of the women by the Suevia, if possible, I
                    suggested to Consul Mason to enter a formal and forcible protest with the
                    cantonal governments of Argovie and Basle against the shipment of the women, and
                    sent him drafts of notes to be addressed to those governments. In the one to
                    Argovie the complaint was set forth in the body of the note, and the consul—
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Forcibly protested against the unfriendly, unpardonable, and outrageous
                            action of the authorities of Böttstein in sending to the United States
                            these notorious prostitutes, who, if permitted to land, must without
                            fail increase the number of prostitutes there, or, in their destitute
                            condition, become a burden to the public charity there. It is solely by
                            reason of the assistance furnished by the commune that they were able to
                            reach the United States.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned therefore entertains the hope that the high cantonal
                            government will take immediate measures, by cable, to prevent these
                            women from longer polluting the soil of the United States by their
                            presence, in case they should have eluded the vigilance of the
                            authorities of the United States. He also entertains the confident <pb
                                facs="1253" n="1129" xml:id="pg_1129"/> hope that the parties guilty
                            of this infringement of the comity existing between Switzerland and the
                            United States, and of the laws of both countries, may be severely and
                            promptly punished.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Accompanying the note were copies or English translations of all the inclosures
                    accompanying Mr. Mason’s No. 32 to the department, as specified in my No.
                    377.</p>
                <p>In his protest to the government of Basle Ville, he transmits the same inclosures
                    as in his note to Argovie, and in addition to the protest he says— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>He confidently hopes that the high government of Basle Ville will at once
                            co-operate with that of Argovie in effecting the return of these women,
                            and that it will severely punish the guilty parties concerned therein
                            who may be within its jurisdiction. The undersigned likewise hopes that
                            efficient measures may be promptly taken to prevent in the future any
                            objectionable emigrants being forwarded from Basle to the United
                            States.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>These notes of Consul Mason were sent to-day, marked “to be de-delivered
                    immediately”, the one to Basle should have been in the hands of the government
                    before 5.30 this p.m.; and the one to Argovie should be delivered to it in Aaran
                    not later than 8 p.m.; which, by New York time would be before 2 p.m. of this
                    Thursday. The latest New York papers announce the Suevia as sailing on Saturday,
                    April 2. There is, therefore, ample time for the government of Argovie to cable
                    to New York to secure the return of the women by the Suevia, if they have not
                    already done so, in case they desire to repair the damage done the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>My note of this date was delivered at the federal palace at 6 p.m., and was
                    marked on the envelope “Cito! très-pressé!” and the messenger who took it was
                    directed to say that it should be delivered at once to the President, or, in his
                    absence, to the vice-president of the Confederation. In my note I carefully
                    avoided characterizing the action of the Böttstein officials in the language of
                    the Consular Regulations (§ 286), owing to their exception to my so doing in
                    Zimmermann’s (Trasadingen) case. I, however, felt it incumbent on me to state:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>It is unnecessary for the undersigned to designate the unpardonable
                            action of the commune council by the language which it merits. The views
                            of the Government of the United States concerning this and shipments of
                            a similar nature are sufficiently well known to the High Federal
                            Council.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">See Secretary of State to Mr. Rublee, Nos</hi>. 114, 127, <hi
                        rend="italic">and</hi> 134, <hi rend="italic">and Mr. Rublee’s Nos</hi>.
                    142, 149, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 155, <hi rend="italic">and my Nos</hi>.
                    180, 181, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 261.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">I have protested “against this unfriendly action of a Swiss
                        commune towards the United States,” and express the hope</hi>— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>That the High Federal Council will at once take measures that these women
                            may be immediately removed from the soil of the United States, which is
                            now polluted by their presence, unless the vigilance of American
                            officials shall have prevented them from landing. Their return by the
                            vessel bringing them would have a salutary effect in deterring other
                            communes from committing similar offenses, and is greatly to be
                            desired.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>If the measures of the legation and consulate at Basle in this case are
                    unsuccessful in securing the return of these women, it will, in my opinion, be
                    useless hereafter for them to try to carry out §§ 241 and 286 of the Consular
                    Regulations, and I respectfully recommend in the interest of economy, both of
                    labor, time, and money, that they should be instructed to take no further
                    measures to execute these paragraphs of the Regulations.</p>
                <p>I respectfully and urgently request your approval of the action of the legation
                    and the consulate at Basle in this case. The position of the <pb facs="1254"
                        n="1130" xml:id="pg_1130"/> Swiss Government in previous cases of a like
                    nature renders it important that our action should be sustained promptly and
                    strongly, or that it should be disapproved. In the latter case I ask that the
                    disapproval may entirely rest on my shoulders as being the party responsible for
                    and dictating the action of the consulate.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>NICHOLAS FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 383.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Droz</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 29, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, chargé d’affaires of the United States of America, has the
                        honor, referring to his note of March 23, 1881, respecting the shipment of
                        Fridolina Vögelin and Theresa Hauser, notorious and depraved prostitutes,
                        whose journey was paid to New York by their native commune of Böttstein,
                        canton Argovie, to inform his excellency Mr. Droz, President of the Swiss
                        Confederation and the High Federal Council, that the steamship Suevia
                        arrived yesterday at New York.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned renews the expression of the hope that the High Federal
                        Council will cause these women to be returned to Switzerland as promptly as
                        possible, and that in future similar action on the part of the local
                        authorities in this country may be prevented.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned avails himself of this occasion to renew to his excellency
                        Mr. Droz, President of the Swiss Confederation, and to the High Federal
                        Council, the assurances of his most distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>NICHOLAS FISH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 383.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Droz</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-03-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 31, 1881</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned, chargé d’affaires of the United States of America, has the
                        honor, referring to his notes of March 23 and 29, 1881, to inclose herewith
                        to Mr. Droz, President of the Swiss Confederation, copies or English
                        translations of the documentary evidence of the charge contained in the
                        aforesaid notes against the commune of Böttstein, canton of Argovie, of
                        having assisted to emigrate to the United States two notorious and depraved
                        prostitutes, Fridolina Vögelin and Theresa Hauser, earning their living by
                        their shameless calling.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned regrets his inability to furnish the High Federal Council
                        with the German text of all these documents, but this omission, so far as it
                        relates to the extracts from the register of proceedings of the commune
                        council of Böttstein, and from that of the church council of Leuggen, can
                        doubtless be obtained at those places, the reference to the volume and page
                        of those registers being in each case given. Should the High Federal Council
                        desire it, the undersigned, will be happy to ask his government to furnish
                        authenticated copies of the originals of the remaining documents.</p>
                    <p>The inclosed documents furnish an unbroken and unbreakable chain of
                        unimpeachable evidence as to the action of the commune council in forwarding
                        these vagrant and abandoned women to the United States. It is unnecessary
                        for the undersigned to designate the unpardonable action of the commune
                        council by the language which it merits. The views of the Government of the
                        United States concerning this and shipments of a similar nature are
                        sufficiently well known to the High Federal Council. It suffices for the
                        present that the undersigned, in bringing the proof of the guilt of the
                        commune and their unblushing admission of the same to the notice of the High
                        Federal Council, should, on behalf of the Government of the United States of
                        America, forcibly protest against this unfriendly action of a Swiss commune
                        towards the United States, and express the hope that the High Federal
                        Council will at once take measures that these women may be immediately
                        removed from the soil of the United States, which is now polluted by their
                        presence, unless the vigilance of American officials shall have prevented
                        them from landing. Their return by the vessel bringing them would have a
                        salutary effect in deterring other commanes from committing similar
                        offenses, and is greatly to be desired.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned, while reserving to his government the further discussion of
                        this <pb facs="1255" n="1131" xml:id="pg_1131"/> question, avails himself of
                        this occasion to renew to his excellency Mr. Droz, President of the Swiss
                        Confederation, and to the High Federal Council, the assurances of his most
                        distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>NICHOLAS FISH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
