<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1881-12-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1881-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="755" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d755">
                        <head>No. 751.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Morton</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1881-12-16"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 16,
                                    1881</date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 74.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have deferred a reply to the note
                            addressed to yon by M. Barthélemy St. Hilaire on the 15th of September
                            last, concerning the debt of Venezuela to France, until the extreme
                            pressure of public affairs attending the death of the late President and
                            the inauguration of his constitutional successor should cease. I now
                            proceed to answer the note of the French minister, as transmitted in
                            your No. 37, of the 17th of September last.</p>
                        <p>As I understand M. Barthélemy St. Hilaire’s response to my
                            representations of the 23d of July, he does not meet the equities of the
                            question, or the practical solutions proposed. He seems to limit his
                            consideration of the matter to the literal terms of the conventional
                            agreement of 1864 between France and Venezuela, on which he rests, as
                            constituting more than a mere priority of indebtedness in point of time,
                            because involving a specific security for the payment thereof, namely, a
                            hypothecation of ten per cent, of the gross revenues of the
                            custom-houses of Laguayra, Puerto Cabello, Maracaibo, and Ciudad
                            Bolivar. As those revenues constitute the only practicable guarantee on
                            which the debt of Venezuela to all the creditor nations rests, I infer
                            that the contention of the French Government is that France claims, in
                            effect, to hold a first mortgage, to which all other foreign claims must
                            yield preference, even to the extent of permitting the engrafting on the
                            original debt of the later stipulations of 1867 and 1868, in favor of
                            France in the matter of interest. The indisposition of the Venezuelan
                            Government to accede to this view in prejudice of the rights of its
                            other foreign creditors is, as it appears from the declaration of M.
                            Barthélemy St. Hilaire, <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The true cause of the attitude which we [France] have been
                                    obliged to assume reluctantly, and which does not permit us, so
                                    long as it shall be maintained, to practically consider
                                    propositions which involve the renewal of relations between the
                                    two countries.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I should be unwilling to regard this declaration as a bar to any
                            settlement of the dispute save at the expense of the other creditor
                            nations, whose joint claim far outbalances that of France, but it is
                            difficult to interpret it otherwise than as a refusal to enter into any
                            negotiations with Venezuela looking to a modification of the attitude of
                            France, so long as Venezuela shall ask a modification of that attitude,
                            or, in effect, a refusal to negotiate at all. I am, however, happy to
                            perceive that the alternative of force is not presented by M. Barthélemy
                            St. Hilaire, who says, in reference to the good interposition of the
                            Government of the United States, that “it has never entered into our
                            [the French] mind to wish to forestall the effect of its kind services
                            by a premature action.” This last declaration is received by this
                            government with profound satisfaction, as indicating only a pacific
                            policy on the part of <pb facs="1351" n="1227" xml:id="pg_1227"/>
                            France. And this, indeed, was to have been expected from her intimate
                            friendship with the United States and the mutual interest of both
                            countries in the general question of Venezuela’s foreign
                            indebtedness.</p>
                        <p>After the careful examination, which was due to M. Barthélemy St.
                            Hilaire’s statements, I am constrained to express the conviction that
                            the United States, in common with all the other governments, creditors
                            of Venezuela, is no more called upon, in law or equity, to recognize the
                            supremacy of the guarantees of the Franco-Venezuelan convention of 1864
                            than it is required to defer to mere priority in point of date of
                            recognition of the debt.</p>
                        <p>The indebtedness of Venezuela to France, like that of Venezuela toward
                            other foreign governments, including the United States, ante-dated the
                            conventional recognition thereof.</p>
                        <p>Pending the adjustment of the respective claims all stood alike on an
                            equal plane of right as against Venezuela. Properly regarding its
                            foreign debt as an aggregate obligation of honor on its part, that
                            republic was not in a position to discriminate in favor of any one among
                            many creditors. Neither was any one of the creditor nations in a
                            position of right or equity to assert preference for its claims against
                            the common interests of the other creditor governments. The mere
                            circumstance that France, while other nations were likewise negotiating,
                            was successful in securing an earlier settlement of her claim, and also
                            a material guarantee for its payment, does not, in the opinion of this
                            government, interpose a rightful bar to the equality of the claims of
                            other creditor nations.</p>
                        <p>In private affairs the adjustment of one debt among many, <hi rend="italic">pendente lite</hi>, to the detriment of the rights of
                            the others, is void 5 and in international jurisprudence no less just
                            rule of procedure can be admitted. So far as the share of the United
                            States in the mass of the Venezuelan debt is concerned, this government
                            must frankly declare that it would regard any persistent reliance upon
                            the Franco-Venezuelan convention of 1864 in bar of the equal claims of
                            the United States against Venezuela as retroacting in such a degree as
                            to make the very conclusion of that convention an act in derogation of
                            the rights which the United States then possessed in common with
                            France.</p>
                        <p>I have been thus explicit in presenting the true merits of the question
                            because I observe that M. Barthélemy St. Hilaire has, naturally perhaps,
                            fallen into a misconception of the scope of my note of July 23, and has
                            regarded it as controverting the French claim of priority of date rather
                            than that of alleged superiority of right. The declarations of that
                            note, however, extend to the very essence of the conventional
                            transactions between France and Venezuela. You will accordingly so bring
                            them to the attention of M. Gambetta. Pending his consideration thereof,
                            I am unable to regard the note of Mr. Barthélemy St. Hilaire as meeting
                            the position which the United States is constrained in common justice to
                            assume, or as conveying more than a very gratifying assurance of the
                            good will which the French Republic bears toward the United States, and
                            of its resolve to take no premature step which might forestall the
                            effect of the kind services of this government. I need hardly assure the
                            French Government of the heartiness with which this sentiment of good
                            will is here reciprocated.</p>
                        <p>Beyond and above the pecuniary interest involved, either for France or
                            the United States in the matter of the Venezuela claims, there lies a
                            consideration which appeals with equal force to the two leading
                            republics—France and the United States. That consideration is, the
                            fraternity of feeling and the harmony of relations which should be
                            maintained between all the republics of the world. It would, in the
                            opinion <pb facs="1352" n="1228" xml:id="pg_1228"/> of this government,
                            be a deplorable spectacle to see hostilities against Venezuela initiated
                            by the great European republic, and it would be an evil to France, for
                            which her share in the Venezuelan debt would afford no compensation
                            whatever. You will remind M. Gambetta that the question at issue is not
                            whether France shall surrender the amount owed her by Venezuela, but
                            whether she will have it paid in installments at the same ratio of the
                            other creditor nations, or in a larger ratio not acknowledged by the
                            United States to be equitable.</p>
                        <p>This government is convinced that, speaking as its representative, you
                            can readily persuade M. Gambetta that the position of the United States
                            in the controversy is one founded on the principles of justice, and you
                            should further pursuade him that the solicitude of this government has
                            not been so much for the protection of its pecuniary interests as for
                            the higher object of averting hostilities between two republics, for
                            each of which it feels the most sincere and enduring friendship.</p>
                        <p>You will take an early occasion to bring the whole matter, in connected
                            shape, to the attention of M. Gambetta, adverting especially to the
                            condition of the question at the time when the previous representations
                            of this government were made. In doing so you will read this dispatch to
                            M. Gambetta, at the same time leaving with him a copy.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>JAMES G. BLAINE.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>