<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Secretariat Files</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Report by the National Security Council</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d146fn1">At its 19th meeting on September 2, the
                                Council considered a draft report on this subject (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 28, not printed) and adopted it in
                                this revised form. The Conclusions here printed were approved by the
                                President on September 4, 1948.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-03">September 3, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 28/1</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Position of the United States With Respect to
                                Scandinavia</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">conclusions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>9. It is in the security interests of the United States that Norway,
                            Denmark and Sweden remain free from Soviet domination.</p>
                        <pb facs="0251" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                        <p>10. The United States should endeavor by all appropriate measures: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>To strengthen the present tendency of Norway and Denmark to
                                    align themselves with the Western Powers.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>To make perfectly clear to Sweden our dissatisfaction with its
                                    apparent failure to discriminate in its own mind and in its
                                    future planning between the West and the Soviet Union: to
                                    influence Sweden to abandon this attitude of subjective
                                    neutrality and look toward eventual alignment with other Western
                                    Powers in such form as may be found collectively acceptable; and
                                    at the same time to refrain from forcing Sweden into an attitude
                                    which would be unnecessarily provocative toward the Soviet
                                    Union.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>11. As one means of implementing the policy stated in the preceding
                            paragraph, the United States should explore with the members of Western
                            Union the problem of increasing the security of Norway, Denmark, and, if
                            appropriate, Sweden, through their integration into or association in
                            some form with the Brussels Treaty system or otherwise.</p>
                        <p>12. The United States should continue to support Norway and Denmark by
                            measures such as the following: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Extension of economic aid by means of favorable U.S. foreign
                                    trade policies.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Providing equipment first to strengthen Norway and Denmark’s
                                    military posture as a deterrent to Soviet armed aggression, and
                                    second to enable the Norwegian and Danish forces to resist
                                    actively an actual attack. A small amount of equipment should be
                                    furnished promptly as an immediate measure of encouragement to
                                    the Norwegian and Danish Governments.<note n="*" xml:id="d146fn2">Action on these two matters will be delayed
                                        pending the negotiation of matters with respect to Greenland
                                        and Spitzbergen. [Footnote in the source text. This footnote
                                        was deleted by action recommended in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 32/1, “Current Position of the US
                                        Respecting Base Negotiations with Denmark and Norway,”
                                        approved by the President on December 3, 1948, not
                                        printed.]</note> Further provision of equipment should be
                                    dependent upon their participation in the Western Union or some
                                    similar collective defense arrangement, consistent with over-all
                                    availability and with priorities to be established for other
                                    Western European nations.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Aggressive combatting of Communist propaganda by a vitalized,
                                    highly selective and intensified U.S. information
                                    program.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>13. With respect to Sweden, the United States should follow for the time
                            being a policy of according priority, on the limited amount of available
                            military aid, to those countries and regional groupings envisaged by
                            Senate Resolution 239 of June 11, 1948 (Vandenberg Resolution). Sweden’s
                            requirements would be considered only after those of countries which
                            have given indication of intention to cooperate with the U.S. or
                            Brussels Treaty signatories in security arrangements.</p>
                        <pb facs="0252" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/>
                        <p>14. It is essential that present U.S. base rights in Greenland be
                            retained and extended as rapidly as politically expedient.</p>
                        <p>15. United States security interests in the Spitsbergen Archipelago lie
                            in supporting Norway in maintaining her sovereignty over these islands
                            and preventing their military use by a hostile power.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>