<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Norway (
                        Bay
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-02-06T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-02-06T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="trade-unions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073951" lcsh-match="exact">Trade unions</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-06T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-06T10:00:00-05:00" n="15" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.00/2–648: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Norway</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bay</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-06T16:00:00+01:00">February 6, 1948—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>62. I asked Foreign Minister Lange yesterday how Norway views Bevin proposal
                    Western European Union, whether Norway has been asked to cooperate, and if so
                    what action will Norway take. Foreign Minister stated Norwegian Ambassador
                    London called at Foreign Office after Bevin speech and was informed Scandinavian
                    countries intentionally excluded in Bevin’s proposal for procedural reasons and
                    to avoid embarrassing Scandinavian States through forcing them to declare
                    attitude before program further advanced; that Bevin plan envisages as first
                    step agreement by England, France with <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> countries, second step Italy and Portugal; after which,
                    depending upon progress of plan, discussions with Scandinavian countries.</p>
                <p>Lange stated Bevin proposal sound and constructive but Norway should defer open
                    discussions and certainly any decision pending discussion among Scandinavian
                    Governments.</p>
                <p>Replying my question whether Stockholm meeting Scandinavian Prime Ministers
                    February 7 would discuss Bevin plan Lange said visiting <pb facs="0039" n="21" xml:id="pg_21"/> Prime Ministers invited remain additional day to discuss
                    Scandinavian matters general interest including undoubtedly Bevin plan.</p>
                <p>Lange feels Soviet Government unusually allergic at present regarding Norway and
                    best avoid any possible new irritant. As example sensitive reactions eastern
                    bloc Lange said representative Yugoslavia and another Soviet-dominated state
                    called Foreign Office protesting his recent mildly pro-western Storting speech
                    (despatch 47 January 22<note n="1" xml:id="d15fn1">Not printed.</note>). Lange
                    added Norway also desires avoid friction this particular time because presently
                    discussing several unsettled issues involved Norway-Soviet border agreement,
                    specifically question fishing and floating rights border river and manner
                    protecting newly established border. Also Lange stated minority but sincere
                    element Norway trade unions still harbor faith and friendship toward Russia
                    based on old traditional concept Soviet Socialism. Thus any precipitate or
                    enthusiastic response by Norway to Bevin plan might alienate this group
                    increasing Communist strength Norway.</p>
                <p>Lange concluded Norway feels definitely aligned to west and must increasingly fix
                    those ties. He stated belief Norway’s tragic position beginning of war partly
                    accounted for by earlier failure join with democracies and Norway must avoid
                    this mistake in future planning. I told him it was refreshing and encouraging to
                    hear this frank statement and will keenly watch for its activation.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 62, repeated London as 1, Paris 4 and airmailed Moscow,
                    Copenhagen, Stockholm.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bay</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
