<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-30T15:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-30T15:30:00-05:00" n="158" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">857D.20/9–3048: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-30T21:30:00+01:00">September
                                    30, 1948—9:30 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>5130. For Lovett and Hickerson from the Secretary. Foreign Minister Lange
                            Norway called last evening and brought up Hickerson’s suggestion to
                            Norwegian Chargé Washington that discussions be held regarding subject
                            regional defense arrangements.<note n="1" xml:id="d158fn1">The
                                suggestion referred to here presumably stems from Hickerson’s
                                conversation with Nygaard on September 23 when he summarized the
                                September 9 paper, stating at one point that “It contemplates that
                                other countries in the North Atlantic area should be consulted prior
                                to drafting the pact …” See airgram A–175, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, particularly the fifth and last paragraphs,
                                including footnote.</note> I was impressed by the frankness and
                            sincerity of his presentation.</p>
                        <p>Lange stated unequivocably Norway desired have such discussions but faced
                            difficult problem of timing. They have just agreed hold discussions with
                            Swedes and Danes regarding Scandinavian defense. For following reasons
                            Lange feels important these discussions take place before talks with us: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Sweden is only military factor in Scandinavia. In elaborating
                                    this point, said Swedes might be able develop trained ground
                                    forces of 600,000, their navy in Baltic only slightly weaker
                                    than Soviets, although air force small it is only air strength
                                    in Scandinavia, and Swedish industrial potential. He stressed
                                    vulnerability of Denmark and short distance narrow waters
                                    separating Danes from Russians at Lübeck. He stressed long
                                    borders of Norway, sparse population, and general military
                                    weakness. He is fully conscious of importance to West of
                                    southern Norwegian coast.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>Lange reasons from above background Norway alone too weak <pb facs="0275" n="257" xml:id="pg_257"/> military way to
                                    contribute anything except brief delaying action, but if Sweden
                                    could be brought in something more substantial might be created.
                                    Lange is convinced, however, Scandinavian arrangement itself
                                    insufficient and must be tied to a broader regional arrangement.
                                    He questions advantage to Norway of tie with present Brussels
                                    group and, at least by implication, seems to favor the North
                                    Atlantic regional concept. Norway, therefore, in Scandinavian
                                    talks wishes to convince Swedes of advantages outside tie. He is
                                    under no illusion this will be easy matter, but feels must try
                                    for reasons just set forth, and</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Because of public opinion in the Labor Party and elsewhere in
                                    Norway which might not be prepared accept what would amount to
                                    break of traditional ties with Sweden until every avenue of
                                    cooperation painstakingly explored. Norway has insisted on
                                    termination date for these discussions, which he once stated end
                                    of January, and later as end of February.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>Lange also raised Department’s injunction not inform Swedes
                                    our approach. He does not know whether or not it would be wise
                                    to do so, but visualizes possibility it might be useful some
                                    stage Scandinavian discussions.</item>
                                <label> </label>
                                <item>Lange put two questions to me: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Would it be possible, considering broad world-wide
                                            situation, to defer talks with us until completion
                                            Scandinavian talks?</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Would we be willing grant him discretion on question
                                            informing Swedes our approach?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>I replied I would like to think over both questions. Please telegraph me
                            promptly recommendations as to replies I should make with summary
                            reasons therefor.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Oslo as 17.</p>
                        <p>Signed Marshall.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>