<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in France (
                        Caffery
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d19</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">19</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-02-19T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-02-19T12:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="alliance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="collective-security" subject="collective-security" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119471" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Collective defense</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="economic-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-19T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-19T12:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.00/2–1948: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-19T18:00:00+01:00">February 19, 1948—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>919. There follows verbatim text of <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                    note being given French (and presumably British) Governments today.<note n="1" xml:id="d19fn1">The American Chargé in Belgium, Millard, informed the
                        Department in his telegram 371, February 19, not printed, that Spaak had
                        given copies of the <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> note to the
                        British and French on receipt of their proposal (840.00/2–1948).</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>“I. The Governments of Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands have
                                examined the British and French proposals of which Mr. Bevin, the
                                Foreign Secretary, constituted himself the interpreter, on January
                                22 last, in his address in the House of Commons on the subject of
                                the union and the consolidation of Western Europe.</p>
                            <p>“The three Governments have received these proposals with great
                                sympathy. In fact, they view with particular satisfaction all
                                efforts towards the consolidation of peace, the reinforcement of the
                                security of the countries of Western Europe and the strengthening of
                                the bonds which already unite them, and they are prepared to make an
                                effective contribution thereto.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>“II. The three Governments realize that full accomplishment of these
                            aims will require a considerable work of planning. They wish <pb facs="0045" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/> to participate in that work
                            collectively. Therefore, they intend to be represented in the
                            negotiations by a joint delegation, made up of representatives of the
                            three countries. These negotiations should lead to the conclusion of a
                            treaty between the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, Luxembourg and the
                            Netherlands, which would be signed by the representatives of each of
                            those Governments.</item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“III. The three Governments have decided on the broad outline of
                                their joint attitude with respect to certain of the basic problems
                                raised by the Franco-British proposals, and they consider it
                                advisable to inform the British and French Government thereof.</p>
                            <p>“In the first place, it does not seem to them sufficient to take as a
                                model the Treaty of Alliance and Mutual Assistance between Great
                                Britain and France signed on May [<hi rend="italic">March</hi>] 4,
                                1947 (Dunkerque Agreement). In fact, that Agreement contemplates
                                basically mutual assistance in case of armed aggression by Germany
                                or in case of hostilities resulting from concerted action to put an
                                end to the threat constituted by the resumption of a policy of
                                aggression by that country. Now, these hypotheses no longer fully
                                correspond to the realities to which the British Foreign Secretary
                                has alluded.</p>
                            <p>“That is why the three Governments believe that an agreement modeled
                                on the Dunkerque Agreement would constitute an inadequate basis for
                                the achievement of the aims to be reached. The pursuit of these aims
                                leads, rather, in their opinion, to envisaging a regional
                                organization of Western Europe under the United Nations Charter.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“IV. Not only does this solution have the advantage of being based on
                                a general treaty to which all the principal Powers of the world are
                                parties but it also presents, thanks to the provisions of Articles
                                51, 52 and 53 of the Charter, all the necessary scope and
                                flexibility. Article 51 permits the organization of legitimate
                                collective defense of the members of the group in case of armed
                                aggression against one of them. Article 52 sanctions regional
                                agreements or bodies intended to settle matters which, affecting the
                                maintenance of international peace and security, lend themselves to
                                action of a regional character encouraging peaceful settlements
                                through such agreements or bodies. Article 53 provides for their use
                                in the application of enforcement measures. These latter require
                                prior authorization by the Security Council, unless they are
                                directed against the resumption by an enemy State of a policy of
                                aggression.</p>
                            <p>“A regional organization which strengthens the ties uniting its
                                members, therefore, not only can ensure peace and security within
                                the group but can also guarantee the security of the group with
                                respect to the outside.</p>
                            <pb facs="0046" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                            <p>“This solution has the advantage of permitting, under the United
                                Nations, the achievement of the various ends which form the basis of
                                the Franco-British proposals.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“V. There are, to be sure, among these aims some which appear
                                attainable at this time and others which can be attained only
                                gradually.</p>
                            <p>“Among the objective[s] which may be achieved immediately, we should
                                envisage first of all an agreement on the political level,
                                consisting in a promise of mutual assistance.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“A. By recognizing that the security of each of the members of
                                    the regional group concerns that of all, we can lay the
                                    foundation for a possible collective application of Article 51
                                    of the Charter. On this point, the Inter-American Treaty of
                                    Mutual Assistance concluded at Rio on September 2, 1947
                                    established the principles in Article 3, paragraph 1, that an
                                    armed attack by any State against an American State will be
                                    considered as an attack against all the American States, and
                                    that, consequently, all the contracting parties undertake to
                                    oppose the attack in virtue of the right of individual or
                                    collective self-defence recognized by Article 51 of the United
                                    Nations Charter.</p>
                                <p>“In the opinion of the three Governments, this mutual aid in case
                                    of armed aggression, authorized by Article 51, must be automatic
                                    and immediate.</p>
                                <p>“B. In addition, the agreement should provide for concerted
                                    action in case of resumption of a policy of aggression on the
                                    part of Germany or of any State acting directly or indirectly
                                    with that country. It should ensure the automatic launching of
                                    mutual aid in case such concerted action should involve any one
                                    of the contracting parties in hostilities with Germany or with
                                    any State joining in her action directly or indirectly.</p>
                                <p>“C. Lastly, any action or any situation constituting a threat to
                                    the peace or security of Western Europe should immediately give
                                    rise to consultations with a view to averting it by mutual
                                    agreement. A system of regular and periodic consultations on all
                                    problems of common interest should also be instituted. Such a
                                    system becomes necessary as soon as mutual aid is made the rule.
                                    However, the three Governments do not believe that they should
                                    propose the procedure for such consultations at this time. This
                                    is the substance of the principal provisions which should
                                    comprise the political agreement to be concluded.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>“The three Governments cannot conceive of a regional organization of
                                Western Europe without their taking part in working out the policies
                                to be followed and the measures to be taken with respect to
                                Germany.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>“VI. The political agreement which has just been considered ought to
                            be supplemented, if it is to have full value, by military agreements on
                            the one hand and by economic agreements on the other hand.</item>
                        <item>“VII. The military agreements govern the implementation of the
                            political agreement. The three Governments do not intend to go into <pb facs="0047" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/> the details with respect to what
                            such military agreements should contain. That question should be studied
                            directly by the general staffs of the countries concerned.</item>
                        <item>“VIII. The three Governments deem it indispensable to cement any
                            agreement of a political character by agreements of an economic nature.
                            In this connection, the ultimate goal for which the regional group
                            should strive is full economic and customs union. If the three
                            Governments consider that such a union cannot be achieved immediately,
                            they nevertheless consider it essential immediately to make the economic
                            policies of the members of the group convergent and to take all possible
                            measures for increasing the prosperity and ensuring the economic
                            security of the group. In view of the importance attached by the three
                            Governments to giving a solid economic basis to the regional group, they
                            think that an early conference of its members should study the measures
                            of coordination to be taken, in particular the establishment of
                            permanent organization permitting continuing consultation to be held on
                            all questions connected with their economic relations, in the study of
                            which consideration would be given to the resources of their over-seas
                            territories.</item>
                        <item>“IX. The proposals of the British and French Governments discussed in
                            the address of the British Foreign Secretary have brought forth a great
                            hope, which it is important not to disappoint. The idea of a strong
                            Western Europe to ensure peace, but without cherishing any aggressive
                            thought against anyone, is an idea which opens up a way full of
                            promise.”</item>
                    </list>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
