<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of Defense (
                        Forrestal
                    ) to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Lovett
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d202</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">202</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9wzMIGHUgT4FsE" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" subject="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092473" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">North Atlantic Pact</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="collective-security" subject="collective-security" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119471" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Collective Security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="202" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/12–3148</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Forrestal</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-12-31">December 31,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Bob</hi>: I am forwarding herewith, on an informal
                    basis at this time, a copy of a memorandum which has been submitted to me by the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff covering the subject of “Base Rights for the United States
                    in return for Military Aid to Foreign Nations”.<note n="1" xml:id="d202fn1">Memorandum signed by Leahy, dated December 21, 1948; for text, see volume
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>.</note> This memorandum suggests the
                    adoption of a policy under which, in normal cases, the granting of military aid
                    would be coupled with negotiations for consideration of United States base
                    rights requirements.</p>
                <p>From a military standpoint, the recommendations of the Joint Chiefs of Staff are,
                    in my opinion, completely sound. However, as they indicate, overriding political
                    considerations may make the application of such a policy impracticable generally
                    or in given instances. However, it seems to me that the political considerations
                    when dealing with the matter of military aid, are very different from those
                    which may be involved in handling economic aid. If the purpose of the North
                    Atlantic Pact and other arrangements under which aid may be furnished is to
                    develop the concept of collective security, it seems to me reasonable, at least
                    as a general proposition, to couple the granting of such aid with the securing
                    of reciprocal advantages which the recipient of the aid may be in a position to
                    provide.</p>
                <p>We have talked at length about the dependence of our strategic plans upon the
                    acquisition of rights at certain bases at various parts of the world. You are
                    only too familiar with the difficulties which have been encountered in efforts
                    to obtain such rights. It therefore seems to me that we should not let this
                    opportunity pass.</p>
                <p>I have advised the Joint Chiefs of Staff in accordance with their request in the
                    last paragraph of their memorandum that they should proceed to make the further
                    detailed studies therein suggested. I believe that these studies in themselves
                    will be of substantial assistance in determining the practicability of applying
                    the policy which they recommend.</p>
                <p>I welcome your own thoughts as to the political feasibility of proceeding along
                    the lines suggested by the Joint Chiefs of Staff and will be glad to discuss
                    this matter with you further at your convenience.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Forrestal</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
