<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-27T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-27T16:00:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">840.00/2–2248: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-27T16:00:00-05:00">February
                                    27, 1948—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>615. In connection Bidault’s reference to some form of US association
                            with Anglo-French-<gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> group
                                (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 980, Feb 22) see <pb facs="0052" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/> topsec letter Hickerson to
                            Caffery, Feb 10,<note n="1" xml:id="d23fn1">Not printed.</note> and
                            particularly enclosures 5, 9 and 10. We would now like you to convey our
                            views to Bidault along following lines:</p>
                        <p>We have made clear privately and publicly our hearty support for Bevin’s
                            idea of closer association of western European countries in political,
                            military and economic fields. As was case with <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> initiation and development of western European security
                            program is responsibility of western European Govts. We have
                            considerable doubt that treaties along Dunkirk model would be either
                            adequate or suitable as basis. <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> notes of Feb 19 seem to us to offer sound basis for
                            such program, a basis much more realistic than Dunkirk approach. We
                            agree with Spaak’s views as indicated Brussels 371, Feb 19.<note n="1" xml:id="d23fn3">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>This country has heartily welcomed Bevin’s initiative to mobilize moral
                            and material forces of free peoples of western Europe to maintain their
                            moral and physical independence. We should not be asked to consider
                            associating ourselves with such program until picture of what western
                            European Govts themselves are going to do about it is much clearer.
                            Recovery and security are obviously interrelated.</p>
                        <p>As regards security against Germany we consider four-power formula
                            practically dead but we will continue to seek in association with
                            French, British and <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                            appropriate means of preventing western European security again being
                            threatened by Germany. We recognize French public desire for something
                            directed explicity against Germany but feel <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> formula including Article 53 and explicit mention
                            of Germany should meet it.<note n="2" xml:id="d23fn2">In response to an
                                inquiry from the Netherlands Embassy for the Department’s views on
                                Bevin’s proposal for a Western Union, Hickerson communicated to it
                                the substance of this telegram 615 (840.00/3–248).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Paris as 615; reptd London for Ambassador and Reber to indicate to
                            British our views on <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> formula
                            as 673; and Brussels as 284.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>