<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="323" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860S.00/3–2248: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cannon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-22">March 22,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>333. Foreign Minister at 12 noon handed me following note numbered 47517,
                            dated March 22: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Fed. People’s Republic of
                                    Yugoslavia has the honour to acknowledge to the Embassy of the
                                    US of America the receipt of a copy of the memorandum presented
                                    by the Government of US of America to the Government of the
                                    USSR.</p>
                                <p>“The Government of the Fed. People’s Republic of Yugoslavia most
                                    emphatically protests against the way in which the Government of
                                    the US of America, in agreement with the British Government and
                                    the French Government, has proposed to raise the question of a
                                    modification of the provisions of the Italian Peace Treaty
                                    regarding the future of the City of Trieste, since while in the
                                    proposal the necessity of Italy’s agreement had been stressed,
                                    no mention was made of the need for an agreement of the most
                                    directly interested Allied country—Yugoslavia.</p>
                                <p>“Such an attitude provides the reason for the opinion that the
                                    aim of this proposal was not to find out a better solution of
                                    the Trieste issue and the normalization of relations between two
                                    nations in south Europe, but that it had a propagandists
                                    character not contributing to the consolidation of peace in the
                                    world.</p>
                                <p>“On this occasion, the Government of the Fed. People’s Republic
                                    of Yugoslavia considers necessary to recall the following facts
                                    in connection with the Trieste issue: <list>
                                        <item>“1. It was the Government of the US of America, the
                                            British Government, and the French Government which had
                                            engaged themselves for such a solution of the Trieste
                                            question as was mainly inserted, at the end, into the
                                            Peace Treaty.</item>
                                        <item>“2. The Government of the US of America, the British
                                            Government, and the French Government were, in fact,
                                            making efforts that no direct agreement between Italy
                                            and Yugoslavia as regards Trieste should be reached
                                            although the possibility for the solution of the issue
                                            by agreement was clearly evident.</item>
                                        <item>“3. The Government of the US of America, the British
                                            Government, and the French Government were in the
                                            Security Council systematically impeding any agreement
                                            on the choice of the person of the Governor of
                                            Trieste.</item>
                                        <item>“4. The American-British Military Government, while
                                            giving full liberty to Fascist and Chauvinistic Italian
                                            elements, hindered the appeasing in the Free Territory
                                            of Trieste, thus poisoning the relations between
                                            Yugoslavia and Italy.</item>
                                        <item>“5. The American-British Government in Trieste has, by
                                            introducing an absolute totalitarian military regime,
                                            lacking any cooperation <pb facs="0538" n="520" xml:id="pg_520"/> with the people, deprived the
                                            people of Trieste of all basic democratic rights and of
                                            all liberty. The American-British zone of the Free
                                            Territory of Trieste is the only area in liberated
                                            Europe where up to this very day no elections whatsoever
                                            for the autonomous bodies have been held.</item>
                                        <item>“6. By the new proposal of the US of America, Great
                                            Britain, and France, the appeasing in the Free Territory
                                            of Trieste has been rendered even more difficult since
                                            the democratic will of the Trieste population has been
                                            fully disregarded and—on the other hand—still more
                                            difficult has been made any agreement between the Fed.
                                            People’s Republic of Yugoslavia and the Italian Republic
                                            on the Trieste question, what would doubtlessly be the
                                            best contribution to good neighbourly relations between
                                            the peoples of the two countries.</item>
                                        <item>“7. Finally the Government of the Fed. People’s
                                            Republic of Yugoslavia considers that the presenting of
                                            such a proposal during the pre-election campaign in
                                            Italy can serve exclusively to the inflaming of
                                            Chauvinistic hatred towards the Yugoslav peoples and on
                                            the other hand, to a sharpening of the internal
                                            political relations in Italy, neither being in the
                                            interest of the Italian people themselves or in that of
                                            the consolidation of peace in this part of
                                            Europe.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>“The Minister of Foreign Affairs avails, etc.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Department 333; repeated Moscow, London, Rome, Paris, Trieste.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cannon</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>