<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-05-27T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-27T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-27T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-27T18:00:00-05:00" n="332"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860S.00/5–2048: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-27T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >May 27, 1948—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1843. Subject <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 2678 May 20<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d332fn1">In this telegram, not printed, Caffery reported that the
                        British Embassy in Paris had proposed that France, the United States and the
                        United Kingdom again approach the Soviet Government for a reply to their
                        communications of April 16 (860S.00/5–2048).</note> discussed with Brit Emb
                    here. We have now agreed to transmit to Soviet Emb Washington on Tuesday, June 1
                    at 3 p. m. GMT for release to press 2 hours later<note n="2" xml:id="d332fn2"
                        >The note, dated June 1, is printed in the Department of State <hi
                            rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 13, 1948, p. 778.</note> following
                    note which is substantially same as text note Brit will deliver simultaneously
                    in London: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Secretary of State presents his compliments to His Excellency the
                            Ambassador of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and has the honor
                            to refer to his note of April 16, 1948<note n="3" xml:id="d332fn3">See
                                    <ref target="#pg_525">p. 525</ref>, and footnote 3.</note>
                            regarding the proposal <pb facs="0545" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> that
                            the Free Territory of Trieste be returned to Italian sovereignty. In
                            that note the Soviet Government was informed that the Government of the
                            United States would welcome any suggestions which the Soviet Government
                            might desire to propose concerning the procedure for drafting the
                            necessary protocol to the Treaty of Peace with Italy to effect the
                            return of the Free Territory to Italian sovereignty.</p>
                        <p>“As the Government of the United States is convinced that the protection
                            of the rights and interests of the people of the Free Territory requires
                            the very early resolution of the problem, it is hoped that the Soviet
                            Government will communicate its views at an early date concerning the
                            procedure to be followed for the joint consideration of the matter by
                            the powers concerned.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>While, in event Soviet rejection or failure reply new representations, Dept in
                    general in agreement Brit proposal further statement reaffirming intention
                    remain US/UK zone pending a just settlement Trieste problem, we consider final
                    determination next move must await developments during period 3 or 4 weeks
                    subsequent delivery June 1 note.</p>
                <p>Dept most desirous French continue support joint position re Trieste and hope
                    French will be prepared address new note to Soviets simultaneously with US and
                    UK on June 1. We shd also be grateful for French support of any further US/UK
                    statement re our intentions remain in Trieste until satisfactory settlement. We
                    shall of course consult with French re all further moves which we may
                    contemplate in order satisfactorily resolve Trieste problem. Dept most
                    appreciative close collaboration FonOff this matter.<note n="4" xml:id="d332fn4"
                        >In telegram 2870, May 29, not printed, Caffery reported that the French
                        would on June 1 at 3 p. m. GMT transmit to the Soviet Embassy a note
                        substantially the same as that of the Department (860S.00/5–2948). <p>In
                            despatch 841 of June 2, not printed, Caffery forwarded the text of the
                            French note (860S.00/6–248).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Paris 1843 rptd London 1953, Rome 1494, Trieste 267, Moscow 606.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
