<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Italy ( (Dunn) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-07-03T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-07-03T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-03T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-03T07:00:00-05:00" n="358"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50 Recovery/7–348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-03T14:00:00+02:00"
                            >July 3, 1948—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2879. Following are specific comments with respect proposals contained <gloss
                        target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 1747 dated June 25,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d358fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                    </note> transmitted to British: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Proposal to divide foreign exchange proceeds lira expenditures of
                            US–UK military equally between <gloss target="#t_AMG1">AMG</gloss> and
                            Italian Government might be useful compromise in view probability
                            Italian Government likely to oppose strongly any proposal decreasing
                            flow of current foreign exchange earnings from Anglo-American zone
                                <gloss target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss>. In view of obligation to supply
                            local currency and foreign exchange requirements Italian Government
                            likely to find proposal somewhat inconsistent.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Proposal regarding blocked assets held by Triestini does not take into
                            account varying nature of such assets, particularly those in form of
                            real estate holdings and participation in income from estates.
                            Desirability of liquidating income-earning assets not clear. Perhaps
                            same program adopted by Italian Government might be put into effect in
                            Anglo-American zone <gloss target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss>. This would make
                            possible pooling <pb facs="0585" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/> liquid assets
                            and also provide flexibility regarding handling less liquid forms of
                            assets held in US otherwise, incentive would exist to evade <gloss
                                target="#t_AMG1">AMG</gloss> control and to enter under Italian
                            program.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Proposal in Paragraph 2 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) for period July 1
                            to September 3, 1948 not entirely clear since it would appear tint while
                            Anglo-American zone <gloss target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss> would be
                            operating outside the commodity allocations “recommended by <gloss
                                target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> or established by”, financing of
                            allocations recommended might take place after <gloss target="#t_FTT1"
                                >FTT</gloss> admission to <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>.
                            Time sequence not clear.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Subparagraphs (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic"
                            >g</hi>) should be integrated since it is provided for use of local
                            currency proceeds for investment or working capital for “<gloss
                                target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> industries” on one hand, and on other
                            hand an expenditure of 25 billion lire under currency agreement of March
                            1948 which it is apparently recognized may be excessive. Moreover,
                            provision of lire for shipbuilding is treated separately. Net effect of
                            such apparently uncoordinated lire expenditures may be to increase
                            substantially deficit financing in Anglo-American zone and considerably
                            beyond any level which would be acceptable to Italian Government on
                            basis of its obligations and undertakings.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Embassy feels that approach indicated in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 1747 may not be consistent with premises underlying foreign
                    exchange and currency agreements, and appears to constitute a step towards the
                    economic and financial separation of the Anglo-American zone from the remaider
                    of Italy. The broad language of the foreign exchange and currency agreements
                    would appear to provide the basis for a viable economic and financial policy of
                    the zone. Department will appreciate that Italian Government has every interest
                    in promoting prosperity of the zone from political point of view.</p>
                <p>Type of program proposed in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1747 will
                    not be convincing to Italian Government. On basis of outstanding agreements
                    Italian Government waives all claims to any benefits from direct grants or aid
                    to <gloss target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss>. Under proposed plan it would (<hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>) waive 50% of current foreign exchange earnings
                    deriving from troop pay and services, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) agree to
                    separate programming of import requirements within framework of independent
                    economic policy premised upon ultimate autonomy from Italy, and (<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) force liquidation of blocked assets in US held by
                    Triestini, with accrual to <gloss target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss> pool perhaps for
                    immediate expenditures of proceeds. At same time Italian Government is required
                    to supply (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) current foreign exchange requirements on
                    terms no-less-favorable than in Italy, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) all local
                    currency requirements which, incidentally, are spendable in Italy for essential
                    imports. Program appears to lack inner consistency and generally understates the
                    possibility of solving economic and financial problems of Anglo-American zone
                    through close cooperation with Italian Government in the spirit of foreign
                    exchange and currency agreements, as well as the tripartite declaration.</p>
                <pb facs="0586" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/>
                <p>Incidentally, Embassy has never received copy of Stopford–Hawes report.</p>
                <p>Inform Treasury from Tasca.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dunn</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
