<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d406</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">406</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="406"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d406">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/8–1748</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-17">August 17,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Ambassador<note n="1" xml:id="d406fn1">Henri Bonnet, the French
                        Ambassador.</note> called at his request in connection with the report of
                    Generals Clay,<note n="2" xml:id="d406fn2">Gen. Lucius D. Clay, U.S. Military
                        Governor for Germany and Commander in Chief, European Command.</note>
                        Robertson<note n="3" xml:id="d406fn3">Gen. Sir Brian Hubert Robertson,
                        British Commander-in-Chief and Military Governor in Germany.</note> and
                        Koenig<note n="4" xml:id="d406fn4">Gen. Marie-Pierre Koenig, French
                        Commander in Chief in Germany.</note> on dispositions to be taken by the
                    Allied Forces in Germany in the event of an emergency. His Government had two
                    preliminary requests to make. It understood that the British and US Governments
                    would consider the report in the Combined Chiefs of Staff and if this was
                    correct the French wished to participate in any considerations of it by the
                    Combined Chiefs. The second request was that the three governments, individually
                    and together, consider the report as quickly as possible.</p>
                <p>I said that I would check to make sure that no meeting of the Combined Chiefs was
                    contemplated but that it had not met for at least two years and that I doubted
                    that any meetings were contemplated. One reason it has been allowed to lapse was
                    that it complicated our relations with other countries. To admit any other
                    country, as we had been under great pressure to do during the War, would have
                    opened the gates to others and a War could not be run by a sort of international
                    parliament. I also said that after the report had been considered separately by
                    the three national Chiefs of Staffs it might well be considered by the permanent
                    Military Committee in London since it would be impossible properly to plan
                    dispositions east of the Rhine except in connection with plans for dispositions
                    west of it. I said that I would also check on this point and let him know
                    tomorrow. He agreed not to telegraph his Government until I communicated these
                    two answers to him.</p>
                <p>He said that he himself had the impression that the Combined Chiefs of Staff were
                    not functioning but that his Government suspected that it was. It would be
                    helpful to remove these suspicions.</p>
                <p>He said that although he had not intended to raise the matter, his Government
                    would attach three conditions to its acceptance of a North Atlantic Security
                    arrangement. One was a satisfactory agreement on the report of the Commanders in
                    Chief in Germany. The second would <pb facs="0662" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> be
                    immediate US assistance in rearmament of the French forces. The third was
                    assurance that in the event of war in Europe the US would send ground forces to
                    help in the defense of France.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
