<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Caffery) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d517</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">517</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-03-03T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-03T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoqCbjAGyIdhyPL" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Consular agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-03T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-03T14:00:00-05:00" n="517"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d517">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">865.00/3–348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-03T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 3, 1948—8 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1148. Departments 662 March 2<note n="1" xml:id="d517fn1">Same as 721 to London,
                            <ref target="#pg_837">p. 837</ref>.</note> just received (Department’s
                    663 March 2)<note n="2" xml:id="d517fn2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_628">p. 628</ref>.</note> and
                    I will discuss the Italian question at once with Bidault. The following
                    information obtained today from high Foreign Office official is of interest as
                    an indication of latest French thinking:</p>
                <p>Foreign Office continues to view the situation in Italy with utmost gravity (my
                    1061 February 27)<note n="3" xml:id="d517fn3">See footnote 2, <ref
                            target="#pg_838">p. 838</ref>.</note> and feels that while US, UK and
                    French Governments may each independently be able to take certain steps to
                    strengthen the present Italian Government, the combined efforts and cooperated
                    action of the French, British and US Governments in certain questions is
                    essential.</p>
                <p>The following measures which the French can take themselves without tripartite
                    cooperation being necessary or even desirable have been approved by the
                    government: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In addition to accepting Military and Naval Attachés (on the condition
                            they are not Communist, my 250 January 15<note n="4" xml:id="d517fn4"
                                >Not printed.</note>) French have informed Italians they may now
                            also accredit consular representatives to France and consular agreement
                            will soon be signed.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The French Government will retrocede certain territories acquired
                            recently from Italy as a result of the peace treaty. The delimination of
                            such areas is being worked out by the National Defense Minister.</item>
                        <pb facs="0858" n="840" xml:id="pg_840"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Bidault has accepted Sforza’s invitation to visit Turin for the
                            signing of the Franco-Italian customs union agreement. While definite
                            date not yet fixed he envisages about March 10. As former President of
                            the National Council of Resistance he will decorate Italian resistance
                            heros and will also make a speech where he will announce that French
                            will retrocede certain territories. He will also announce France is not
                            demanding full compliance with naval protocol of Italian treaty insofar
                            as repairing Italian ships is concerned which will assist Italian
                            economy and that France will not take all vessels allocated her.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>While my source said that the above measures may be helpful to De Gasperi
                    Government the French believe that they are of very secondary importance
                    compared with the vital question of the colonies and to lesser extent the
                    question of Trieste. Foreign Office believes Italian people are more interested
                    in the fate of the colonies than anything else and that Communists as a result
                    of Moscow’s stand on Italian colonies are making much hay. He said French
                    believe that it is imperative that the US and UK join with the French in some
                    tripartite formula which “must be announced before March 25 if it is to do any
                    good,” which would place three governments in support of principle of Italian
                    sovereignty over colonies. He expressed hope that US would go along with the
                    French on this, and would also work on the British, who, he believes, are the
                    main stumbling block for any such action.</p>
                <p>Foreign Office is also seriously concerned about Communist exploitation of
                    Trieste. According to Foreign Office’s information the Soviets have through
                    Belgrade put forward some feelers to the Italians indicating that if the
                    Americans and British will get out of zone A Moscow would not be opposed to
                    Italy re-acquiring sovereignty over zone A. He said Italian Communists are
                    spreading the story publicly and in governmental and parliamentary circles in
                    Italy that Moscow is not opposed to the reestablishment of Italian sovereignty
                    over Trieste (implying all of Trieste) and that it is the US, France and UK who
                    wish to deprive Italy of the area. While French thinking on how to combat this
                    propaganda has not yet fully crystallized, the present thought of Foreign Office
                    is that the US, British and France would counter this by stating that they do
                    not oppose the return of all of Trieste to Italy. Foreign Office appears
                    convinced that the Soviets have no intention of ceding zone B to Italians and
                    that they would be obliged to come out and say so thereby putting themselves
                    squarely on the spot and knocking the props from under their propaganda.</p>
                <p>In conclusion our informant expressed again the “imperative necessity” for
                    tripartite action in the colonial question and to lesser extent on Trieste.</p>
                <pb facs="0859" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/>
                <p>Repeated to London 143, to Rome 94, to Moscow as 73, to Berlin as 80, and to
                    Belgrade as 13.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
