<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-16T12:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-16T12:55:00-05:00" n="526" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d526">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50 Recovery/3–1648: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-16T19:55:00+02:00">March 16,
                                    1948—7:55 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1165. Several Rome papers March 16 report McDermott’s<note n="1" xml:id="d526fn1">Michael J. McDerrnott, Special Assistant to the
                                Secretary for Press Relations.</note> statement on continuation of
                                <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> shipments to Italy should
                            Communists win elections.<note n="2" xml:id="d526fn2">The “Memorandum of
                                the Press and Radio News Conference, Monday, March 15, 1948, 12:30
                                noon” reads as follows: <p>“Mr. McDermott …</p>
                                <p>Q. There was a story in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>
                                    by Sulzberger—</p>
                                <p>A. I saw that John.</p>
                                <p>Q. It says that the United States is going to make some sort of
                                    an announcement of barring aid from Italy if the Communists take
                                    over.</p>
                                <p>A. There is no such decision reached by the government of the
                                    United States. Cy Sulzberger says this Government will make an
                                    announcement and then I am saying this: No such decision has
                                    been reached by the Government of the United States. The story
                                    may well have originated from the Senate debate on <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> in the course of which the
                                    intent of the Senate was pretty clear. The Communists in Italy
                                    have said they don’t want <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>
                                    and if the Communists should win, which we cannot believe will
                                    be the case, knowing the spirit and feeling of the Italian
                                    people, there would be no further question of assistance from
                                    the United States.</p>
                                <p>Q. The decision apparently was made to make the announcement. Who
                                    is making the statement?</p>
                                <p>Q. This confirms the story.</p>
                                <p>Q. This confirms the decision.</p>
                                <p>Q. This makes the announcement.</p>
                                <p>A. It is a comment on the story. It is not an announcement.</p>
                                <p>Q. Mac, has not the Senate Bill made it clear—</p>
                                <p>A. The reason I made it, there is a definite line of demarcation
                                    here. I have been asked about a question about a story written
                                    out of Paris and I just cannot let that story go without making
                                    an answer.</p>
                                <p>Q. You mean you had no plans to issue this statement until we
                                    asked?</p>
                                <p>A. This is not a statement. This is my answer to your
                                    question.</p>
                                <p>Q. If the story had not been published, you would not have made
                                    this comment?</p>
                                <p>A. Absolutely not. I am answering your question.</p>
                                <p>Q. Is this a State Department answer?</p>
                                <p>A. You can attribute it to me, if you want.</p>
                                <p>Q. …”</p>
                                <p>(Daily News Conferences—Office of the Special Assistant to the
                                    Secretary in Charge of Press Relations—Department of State, 111,
                                    1948)</p>
                            </note> All reports something at variance with radio bulletin version of
                            McDermott’s remarks.<note n="3" xml:id="d526fn3">In telegram 1189 of
                                March 17, not printed, Dunn reported that the Communist organ, <hi rend="italic">Unità</hi>, of March 17 stated: “<gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> hurried yesterday to publish
                                official text of declaration (State Department’s declaration) … on
                                aid. In text it is affirmed ‘spokesman of State Department denied
                                yesterday news from Paris according to which US Government intended
                                to declare that American aid to Italy … would be interrupted if
                                Communists won elections.’” (840.50 Recovery/3–1748)</note> Saragat
                            Socialist <hi rend="italic">Umanità</hi> and Independent Rightist <hi rend="italic">Tempo</hi>, in similar dispatches, quote McDermott as
                            stating that if in elections Italians vote Communist it will not benefit
                                <pb facs="0872" n="854" xml:id="pg_854"/> further from economic help
                            from United States. Both say McDermott stated that <gloss target="#t_PCI1">PCI</gloss> had signified it did not wish <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> and therefore if Communists win “the
                            United States will suspend all assistance to Italy.” <hi rend="italic">Tempo</hi> features article in middle of front page with large
                            headline “America Will Suspend Aid If Front Wins Elections.” <hi rend="italic">Umanità</hi> prints item in inconspicuous back page
                            report headlines “Grave American Declaration. No Help To Italy In Event
                            Of Communist Victory.” <hi rend="italic">Tempo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Messaggero</hi> also publish McDermott’s denial that
                            President Truman has given me special powers to order marines to Italy
                            if Communist coup seems imminent before election. Independent
                            Conservative <hi rend="italic">Messaggero</hi> in conspicuous front-page
                            article headlined “America Will Suspend All Aid If Communists Win In
                            Italy” says that while McDermott statement regarding aid refers only to
                            Marshall Plan it has been learned from “authoritative sources” that
                            Communist government in Italy would not receive aid of any kind from US.
                            Leftist <hi rend="italic">Paese</hi> in small page four article reports
                            McDermott’s statements regarding aid in article entitled “Electoral
                            Maneuver. No More American Aid To Italy In Case Of Communist Victory.”
                            After reporting McDermott’s statements on aid, however, <hi rend="italic">Paese</hi> says it has learned from other sources that
                            Republican circles opposing Truman’s policy have other plans and that in
                            event of victory of Front, economic and commercial relations with Italy
                            would not be ruptured or slowed down.<note n="4" xml:id="d526fn4">In
                                telegram 1223, March 19, not printed, Dunn mentioned that
                                McDermott’s statement had not been adequate to survive Communist
                                distortion and forwarded a suggestion by Sforza for a new
                                declaration by the United States along the following lines: “If the
                                Communists were to come to power in Italy, in view of the declared
                                opposition of the Communist-controlled countries to American
                                assistance toward European recovery, the United States would
                                reluctantly have to withdraw assistance to Italy in that case and
                                apply its assistance to other non-Communist countries whose
                                governments were cooperating in the efforts to provide economic
                                improvement in Europe.” (840.50 Recovery/3–1948)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dunn</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>