<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Deputy for the Former Italian Colonies of
                        the Council of Foreign Ministers (
                        Gallman
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d564</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">564</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-11T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" n="564" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d564">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">865.014/3–1148: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy for the Former Italian Colonies of
                        the Council of Foreign Ministers</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gallman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-11T18:00:00+00:00">March 11, 1948—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1004. <gloss target="#t_Itcol1">Itcol</gloss> 117. Twenty-fourth meeting <gloss target="#t_Depitcol1">DepItcol</gloss> held yesterday afternoon with Gallman
                    presiding. Record twenty-third meeting approved.</p>
                <p>Deputies considered French proposal for scheduling hearing of interested
                    governments without reaching any agreement. Prior to meeting Embassy officer
                    obtained British support for US position as instructed <pb facs="0922" n="904" xml:id="pg_904"/> in <gloss target="#t_Colit1">Colit</gloss> 62.<note n="1" xml:id="d564fn1">Not printed; the French proposal suggested that hearings
                        begin March 17 and end May 14. <gloss target="#t_Colit1">Colit</gloss> 62
                        instructed the U.S. Deputy to delay all hearings until May 1, since the
                        satellites would support the Soviet position, while the other interested
                        governments might embarrass the Western Powers with their views
                        (865.014/3–948).</note> At meeting Zarubin, while agreeing in principle to
                    French proposal, refused agree paragraph seven that proposal and insisted all
                    hearings should be completed by April 7. UK and US deputies noted that Soviet
                    had not changed position nor made any new proposal. In view Soviet
                    intransigeance French plea for reconsideration was ineffective and US and UK
                    deputies maintained position that no hearings should begin until May 1 in order
                    allow interested governments receive reports on Eritrea and Italian Somaliland.
                    Deputies decided to report their inability agree on timetable of hearings to
                    their respective governments. Thus question was temporarily shelved although it
                    remains on agenda for consideration at some future meeting deputies.</p>
                <p>Recent note from Italian Government to deputies<note n="2" xml:id="d564fn2">Not
                        printed.</note> concerns subject of hearing views of Italian refugees from
                    former colonies now in Italy. Last November deputies asked commission for its
                    views on this subject and commission postponed its decision until reaching Libya
                    (document <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> 85).<note n="2" xml:id="d564fn5">Not
                        printed.</note> Deputies decided to inform Italian Government that they
                    agreed in principle to hearing views Italian refugees and were consulting with
                    commission on best means obtaining those views. Deputies also decided to ask
                    commission its view of Soviet proposal to hear Italian refugees by sending one
                    representative each delegation in commission to Italy for that purpose after
                    commission completes work in Libya. All deputies expressed general approval this
                    proposal subject to receiving views of commission on its practicality.</p>
                <p>Secretary General yesterday received memorandum from Italian Government
                    presenting its views on Libya. Since deputies had previously sent similar
                    Italian memoranda on Eritrea and Italian Somaliland to commission it was agreed
                    send this memorandum on Libya to commission also.<note n="2" xml:id="d564fn6">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Deputies considered recent letter from commission concerning security of persons
                    testifying before commission. Letter refers to requests made by several
                    political organizations in Mogadishu to have commission leave observer in
                    territory to see that public order was respected and that reprisals were not
                    taken against any persons or groups. Since this matter was outside scope of
                    commission it advised deputies of requests. Deputies agreed matter was outside
                    their functions and powers as well and that maintenance of public security was
                    responsibility of government administering territory. Therefore, deputies <pb facs="0923" n="905" xml:id="pg_905"/> decided forward letter to British
                    Government for its information without any comments. Commission will be informed
                    that its letter this subject is being forwarded British authorities.</p>
                <p>English text commission’s report on Eritrea received by Secretary General few
                    days ago and was circulated to deputies March 9.<note n="3" xml:id="d564fn3">Not
                        printed; for text, see <hi rend="italic">Four Power Commission of
                            Investigation for the Former Italian Colonies, Official Reports</hi>, 3
                        vols., 1947–8.</note> French and Russian text will not be received and
                    reproduced before March 20. Since commission has not yet agreed on appendices to
                    be included in report copy English text appendices may not be sent deputies for
                    about three weeks. French and Russian translations appendices will have to be
                    done in London and since they comprise some 200 pages Secretary General
                    considers entire job translation and reproduction may not be completed until
                    about May 15. US, UK and French deputies generally agreed that report as
                    received should be sent all interested governments as soon as French and Russian
                    translations ready in order allow interested governments as much time as
                    possible to study report before presenting views. They also thought appendices
                    should be distributed whenever they are completed. Zarubin took contrary view
                    and declared report should not be sent to any other interested government until
                    all of report, including appendices, had been received and translated. Zarubin
                    used paragraph five, document <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> 29<note n="4" xml:id="d564fn4">Not printed.</note> as argument for saying reports should
                    not be distributed until they were completed, and pointed out that secretary of
                    commission, in letter covering report, stated “no date can be given for
                    completion of appendices to Eritrea report as agreement has not yet been reached
                    regarding materials to be included.” In view delay appendices, Zarubin
                    contended, interested governments would not receive report before hearings even
                    if hearings did not begin until May 1. Faced with this pronounced disagreement,
                    deputies postponed further discussion re distribution report until after
                    deputies and their governments had studied report.</p>
                <p>Deputies did not discuss chapter of Eritrea report on results of investigation
                    wishes of inhabitants on which commission was unable to agree. Secretary General
                    has received draft texts this disagreed chapter with statements delegations in
                    commission which are being reproduced for circulation to deputies. Copies will
                    be forwarded to Department as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>Gallman, as chairman, summarized discussion and noted items retained on agenda:
                    hearings interested governments; hearing Italian refugees; and report on
                    Eritrea. Gallman then stated next meeting could be held after deputies have
                    further considered these subjects and have consulted their respective
                    governments, and thus next meeting could be held whenever the deputies desired.
                    Zarubin objected such <pb facs="0924" n="906" xml:id="pg_906"/> procedure might
                    postpone next meeting for weeks or months. But French deputy, who will be next
                    chairman, stated they would request meeting next week.</p>
                <p>French informed us privately they want deputies at next meeting to instruct
                    commission to investigate boundary questions concerning French territories and
                    Libya in regions of: west of Nalut, Gadames, west of Gat, Tummo, and northern
                    Tibesti.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
