<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-05T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-05T19:00:00-05:00" n="631" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d631">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.515/2–548: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Portugal</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-05T19:00:00-05:00">February
                                    5, 1948—7 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>68. Reur <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> 87, Feb. 4. In response
                            to specific Congressional inquiries concerning US policy regarding
                            foreign held assets in connection with <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> Snyder transmitted letter to Vandenberg reading in part
                            as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Spanish and Portuguese assets are still blocked pending the
                                    completion of the current negotiations with Spain and Portugal
                                    covering looted gold and German assets. If these negotiations
                                    are successfully completed before the public deadline date,
                                    arrangements can promptly be made for the unblocking of these
                                    assets; on the other hand, if the negotiations are not completed
                                    by that date, these assets would likewise be covered in the
                                    transfer to the Office of Alien Property and would remain
                                    blocked pending the conclusion of the negotiations.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Above was only reference to Spain or Portugal in eight page letter
                            explaining US Govt policy as determined by <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> action re remaining <pb facs="1015" n="997" xml:id="pg_997"/> blocked assets of all countries with approval of
                            executive departments concerned. Full text of letter<note n="1" xml:id="d631fn1">Not printed.</note> follows via pouch.</p>
                        <p>Emb attention directed to significant differences in letter as compared
                            with quote from French press release as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Spain and Portugal are not singled out in Snyder’s letter
                                    since many other European countries are also mentioned. Some
                                    linkage of Spain and Portugal—which has no political
                                    significance whatsoever—inevitable since lack of settlement on
                                    looted gold and German assets places them in identical positions
                                    as only two blocked neutrals for whose assets no unblocking
                                    procedure has been established.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Should be made clear to Portuguese that transfer Portuguese
                                    assets to OAP is purely administrative move in US Govt connected
                                    with termination Foreign Funds Control without implication that
                                    vesting will follow. On basis your recent reports we strongly
                                    hope negotiations can be satisfactorily completed and funds
                                    unblocked well before transfer date about June 1.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Continued blocking pending conclusion negotiations on looted gold and
                            German assets has been applied to all neutral countries and thus no
                            discrimination against Portugal. Emb has previously been authorized
                            bring this to attention of Port Govt and even without formal
                            notification Dept assumes Port Govt aware this policy which has been
                            made known publicly heretofore as in case of Switzerland and
                                Sweden.<note n="2" xml:id="d631fn2">For the texts of the agreements
                                with Sweden and Switzerland on German assets and looted gold and a
                                discussion of the negotiations leading to the agreements, see
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 30, 1946,
                                p. 1101, and July 27, 1947, p. 155.</note> Emb advised in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 47 of Jan 26<note n="1" xml:id="d631fn3">Not printed.</note> that Dept did not wish letters
                            enclosed Dept instruction 473 Aug 21 to be presented pending further
                            instructions.</p>
                        <p>With further reference unblocking, for your strictly confidential info
                            Dept already discussing with Treas and OAP possibility of unblocking
                            Port on basis similar to that proposed by you but after reaching
                            satisfactory gold settlement.</p>
                        <p>Dept regrets timing of release but Emb will appreciate that executive
                            branch of Govt had to respond to insistent Congressional demand for
                            statement US policy with respect to foreign held assets in relation to
                                <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Emb may, at its discretion, inform Portuguese that letter constituted a
                            statement of existing policy and did not represent in so far as Port is
                            concerned any tightening of this policy or discrimination against
                            Port.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>