<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="667" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d667">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/11–1048</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-10">November 10,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">No. 414</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my despatch no. 352 of
                            September 21, 1948, and my airgram no. A–319 of September 14, 1948,<note n="1" xml:id="d667fn1">Despatch 352, <ref target="#pg_1050">p.
                                    1050</ref>, gave another account of the meeting between Don Juan
                                and General Franco. Airgram A–319 is not printed.</note> I have the
                            honor to enclose a memorandum of conversation dated November 2 between
                            Don Juan, Pretender to the throne of Spain, and Mr. Theodore Xanthaky,
                            Attaché of this Embassy and Special Assistant to the Ambassador.</p>
                        <p>The Department will note that the Pretender spoke to Mr. Xanthaky with
                            apparent frankness concerning his meeting with General Franco at San
                            Sebastian last summer and also concerning recent rumors of an agreement
                            between the Spanish Royalist and Socialist parties. The gist of his
                            remarks would seem to be that he feels his meeting with Franco has been
                            of real use to him, particularly in dispelling certain misconceptions on
                            the part of the Caudillo, and that any understanding between adverse
                            Spanish political groups should be in the public interest.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lincoln MacVeagh</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Theodore Xanthaky</persName>, Special Assistant
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Ambassador in Portugal</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-02">November 2, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>On Saturday, October 30, I met Don Juan, the Spanish Pretender,
                                casually at the Golf Club in Estoril. At that time he told me he had
                                sent for his son, the Prince of Asturias, who was in Switzerland,
                                and that after a few days in Estoril with his family the young man
                                will proceed to Madrid to begin his studies there. (Embassy’s
                                airgram No. 365 of November 1, 1948).<note n="2" xml:id="d667fn2">Not printed.</note> I expressed interest and Don Juan <pb facs="1078" n="1060" xml:id="pg_1060"/> said he would get in
                                touch with me sometime during the ensuing week to tell me the real
                                story of his interview with Franco, the Spanish Chief of State. Last
                                night Viscount Rocamora, the Pretender’s Aide, telephoned making an
                                appointment for me with Don Juan at his home in Estoril today. Don
                                Juan greeted me by saying that his son had arrived from Switzerland
                                the night before and was leaving for Madrid about November 10. He
                                then pitched into the following story of his encounter with
                                Franco.</p>
                            <p>For some time past, the advisability of a meeting with the Caudillo
                                had been suggested to him, but nothing ever came of it. Early last
                                summer Julio Danvila, a staunch monarchist and a Director of the
                                Bank of Spain, (representing the private shareholders), visited Don
                                Juan in Estoril and told him he had occasion to see Franco quite
                                often and volunteered to arrange a meeting. Don Juan agreed but
                                thought it would go the way of previous similar efforts. Very much
                                to his surprise while in England last July, where he had gone with
                                his friend, Galindez, on the latter’s yacht <hi rend="italic">Saltillo</hi> for the Olympic Games, he received a telegram
                                from Danvila informing that the encounter had been arranged.</p>
                            <p>At the appointed time and place,<note n="3" xml:id="d667fn3">The
                                    interview took place on August 25 off the coast of San
                                    Sebastian.</note> Franco came on board the <hi rend="italic">Saltillo</hi>. They talked alone for over three hours. Franco
                                immediately launched into the Pretender’s past mistakes. Don Juan
                                countered by saying that he, Franco, had also made plenty of those
                                and the past was the past and they had better talk about the present
                                and the future. Franco took this goodnaturedly and said that perhaps
                                he was right. Franco then assured the Pretender that he had always
                                been and continued to be his candidate for the throne (Don Juan
                                remarked to me that he had not forgotten that Franco last year was
                                considering other names). Franco then brought up the subject of the
                                education of the young Prince of Asturias in Spain. Don Juan replied
                                that he was agreeable to this but that he would have to receive
                                certain commitments before he would consent, such as (1) political
                                amnesty for monarchists at present under arrest; (2) guarantee that
                                monarchists would not be persecuted by the authorities; and (3)
                                freedom of monarchical press activity in the newspaper “ABC”. Franco
                                said that he would give consideration to these points and believed
                                there would be no difficulty in this respect. (Don Juan remarked to
                                me that Franco is now in the process of meeting all three <hi rend="italic">desiderata.</hi>) Don Juan then emphasized to
                                Franco that he wished to make it perfectly clear that by sending his
                                son to Spain he did not renounce any of his rights to the throne.
                                Franco was in entire accord and said that he would allow a statement
                                to this effect to be published in Spain. Don Juan wanted the
                                Caudillo <pb facs="1079" n="1061" xml:id="pg_1061"/> to make the
                                statement but the latter hedged and said he thought it would be
                                better if it came from Don Juan. During the conversation, Franco
                                gave Don Juan his impressions on what the monarchy should be like.
                                Don Juan thought these decidedly archaic. For example, Franco talked
                                of Philip II and very much in the vein of an absolute monarchy. The
                                Pretender reminded Franco that he continued firmly to hold ideas on
                                this subject which he had already publicly espoused, i.e. a
                                constitutional monarchy along democratic lines. By that, he said, he
                                did not mean that the political system of another nation should be
                                taken and bodily implanted in Spain; Spanish traditions and
                                temperament would have to be taken into consideration. Don Juan said
                                that never once during the conversation did Franco mention that he
                                intended to turn over the government to him at a given date. As a
                                matter of fact, he said, Franco repeatedly talked in terms of
                                20-year periods, which he thought significant inasmuch as Franco is
                                57. As an illustration, Franco mentioned that he expected his
                                economic planning would bear fruit within 20 years, etc. Therefore,
                                Don Juan got no impression that Franco is contemplating
                                relinquishing power voluntarily in the foreseeable future. He
                                stated, however, that in his opinion this initial contact has been
                                useful to him. Among other things he believes he has dispelled from
                                Franco’s mind certain misconceptions which he had reason to believe
                                Franco entertained concerning him. Commenting on the Caudillo’s
                                political position, he said that Franco could not be overthrown by
                                external pressure and that his internal hold on Spain was very
                                solid. Only a period so distressing economically as to drive the
                                country to desperation could unseat him. Although the economic
                                condition of Spain is far from good, it has not reached the breaking
                                point and Franco could always resort to palliatives at least
                                temporarily to avert such a situation. He said that several times
                                during the conversation, Franco spoke of his friendship for Don
                                Juan’s father, Alfonso XIII, with tears in his eyes. Franco was
                                extremely voluble and it had been very difficult for Don Juan to get
                                in his counter arguments. Plow-ever, he had been rehearsing in his
                                mind for many years exactly what he would say to Franco when they
                                met and he believed that he had gotten over his points. The
                                Pretender said that although there had probably been a
                                predisposition of dislike on both sides, the interview had found
                                both mutually “simpatico”. During the conversation Franco always
                                addressed Don Juan as “Alteza” (Highness). Franco complained about
                                the treatment he was getting in the international sphere, to which
                                Don Juan retorted “what could you expect from the victory of the
                                democracies after your attitude toward the Fascist states?” Franco
                                then said he did not believe there would be a war for another two or
                                three years. Don Juan told me that he contradicted and challenged
                                    <pb facs="1080" n="1062" xml:id="pg_1062"/> Franco’s statements
                                repeatedly and it has come back to him from Artajo, the Minister for
                                Foreign Affairs, via a mutual friend, that Franco not only did not
                                resent this but apparently was impressed. Don Juan found Franco very
                                hazy on economic subjects and that, though by no means a fool, he
                                was an <hi rend="italic">hombre primario.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Pretender said he has no illusions about Franco. He remarked,
                                however, that up to the time of his interview he was making no
                                progress and he now feels that at least he has “gotten his foot in
                                the door”. Don Juan mentioned to me that Alfonso XIII had been best
                                man at Franco’s wedding and therefore a few days ago on the occasion
                                of the Caudillo’s silver wedding anniversary, he sent him a message
                                of felicitations. Don Juan showed me Franco’s handwritten reply
                                which he had just received. It was addressed “Mi Principe” and
                                terminated “conlealtad y afecto” (with loyalty and affection), and
                                stated what a great honor it had been for him and his wife to have
                                received his message and that he owed his happiness to Don Juan’s
                                father, Alfonso XIII.</p>
                            <p>Don Juan then spoke of the recent publicity in connection with a
                                so-called agreement between the monarchists and the socialists. He
                                said that as the monarch he considered it his duty to be above
                                political factions. He believed, however, that any understanding
                                between adverse political groups tending to harmonize differences of
                                opinion would be useful and in the public interest. He said that
                                last year Gil Robles and Saenz Rodriguez<note n="4" xml:id="d667fn4">Saenz Rodriguez, a leading Spanish Monarchist in exile.</note>
                                drafted some of the clauses of a document in this sense which was
                                being discussed between the monarchists and the socialists. He said
                                it was more in the nature of a set of political principles rather
                                than an operating agreement between parties and that as he
                                understood it, no signatures were required. In any event he said it
                                was an old story, as Robles had told the British all about it last
                                year. Now the Socialist Leader, Indalecio Prieto, perhaps aided and
                                abetted by an irresponsible monarchist named Ansaldo, who has a
                                house at St. Jean de Luz, had chosen unilaterally to give unwelcome
                                publicity to what was intended to be a confidential matter.</p>
                            <p>Don Juan also mentioned that when he visited London last November for
                                the royal wedding, King George arranged an interview for him with
                                Bevin at Buckingham Palace. On that occasion he told Bevin that
                                their pinpricking policy against Franco was <hi rend="italic">contra
                                    producente</hi> and getting him, Don Juan, nowhere. Bevin
                                replied, “Well, we withdrew our Ambassadors from Madrid for you” to
                                which Don Juan replied, “Yes, and that was a great mistake.” Don
                                Juan also told Bevin that if he thought they were going to restore
                                the monarchy in order to make the socialist Indalecio Prieto Prime
                                Minister, they were very much mistaken; Prieto would probably be
                                shot if he as much as showed <pb facs="1081" n="1063" xml:id="pg_1063"/> up in Madrid. Bevin laughed and said, “Well,
                                my boy, carry on as best you can. You know that we are for you” and
                                at the same time strongly implied that the British would do nothing
                                practical towards his regaining his throne. Don Juan remarked to me,
                                “I believe, therefore, that the British cannot be too upset by my
                                meeting with Franco.” Don Juan then terminated our interview and
                                promised to keep me currently informed as to developments.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>