<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>112. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-12-07T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-12-07T11:23:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries">OPEC</term>
                    <term ref="recmuOYE0cUMJaVom" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">North-South dialogue</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-12-07T11:23:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-12-07T10:00:00-05:00" n="112"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                <head>112. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d112fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National
                        Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversations, Box 21. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. The meeting was held in the Oval
                        Office. Brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1976-12-07T10:00:00-05:00" to="1976-12-07T11:23:00-05:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">December 7, 1976, 10–11:23
                            a.m.</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Ardeshir Zahedi</persName>, Ambassador of
                        Iran</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>, Assistant to the
                        President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GA_3">Alan Greenspan</persName>, Chairman of the
                        Council of Economic Advisors</item>
                </list>
                <p>[There is a brief discussion of the weather here and in Iran, hydro-electric
                    projects in Iran, the Helmand River project. etc.]</p>
                <p>The President: Let me extend to the Shah my personal regards. I have great
                    personal regard and affection for him. I hope that in the future years the close
                    relations we have between our two countries will continue. There is a strong
                    feeling in the United States for the Shah and Iran.</p>
                <p>But I want to talk about an issue which troubles me—the Doha meeting<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d112fn2">The meeting of <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> Oil
                        Ministers was held in Doha December 15–17. See <ref target="#d113">Document
                            113</ref>.</note> and a possible oil price increase. I have read the
                    Shah’s letter<note n="3" xml:id="d112fn3">See <ref target="#d110fn3">footnote 3,
                            Document 110</ref>.</note> very carefully. I both agree and disagree
                    with it. I agree wholeheartedly with his points about conservation. The
                    industrial world has not done enough, and it is essential. I have proposed a
                    conservation plan which the Congress has not yet accepted. We are searching and
                    we need to do more with respect to alternate sources of energy. I do disagree
                    with him <pb facs="0430" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/> on the issue of oil price and
                    its relation to industrial prices. These are honest differences between
                    friends.</p>
                <p>But let me talk about the impact that an increase will have. There is unanimity
                    among my advisers that the world economic health is not good. Any increase in
                    the price of oil would have a serious impact on the world financial structure.
                    Its precise impact is hard to predict accurately.</p>
                <p>An increase would also have a serious impact on our capability to help the
                    developing countries. If economic conditions here don’t improve, the American
                    people will ask how they can continue helping the developing world when we have
                    such serious difficulties at home. If our economic situation improves—I am an
                    optimist, but we do have this pause, which I feel will be resolved in the
                    direction of stable growth—we will be able to continue and expand our efforts
                    toward North-South cooperation. The other industrial countries are lagging
                    behind now the United States, and the resources for North-South cooperation
                    simply wouldn’t be available if economic progress halted.</p>
                <p>I am a strong supporter of the Shah. I think he has done great things for his
                    country and is a strong force for moderation and stability in the Middle East. I
                    spoke out publicly during the campaign in support of the Shah. I want to
                    continue my participation in public affairs after I leave. I want to continue my
                    support of Iran—I would like to visit there at some time. It would help me
                    greatly in my efforts if the Shah could exercise a moderating influence in the
                        <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> meeting. I understand his position
                    and I agree with part of his position. But we have to look at it in a broader
                    perspective now and I think an increase would have a serious impact on the world
                    economic structure.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: It is a great honor for me to
                    meet with you, Mr. President. I want you to know how greatly you are admired by
                    the Shah and by my people. I say that from the heart on his behalf and my
                    behalf.</p>
                <p>I don’t want to take your time, but two years ago when prices were going up I
                    talked to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWE_1">Simon</persName> and would have gone to
                    the area right then and would have helped. But the past is past.</p>
                <p>Again, the meetings on the North-South dialogue have not gone well. There are
                    people in this government who are not sympathetic. Then under President Johnson
                    and early in the <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Administration,
                    when I was Foreign Minister, we proposed that oil resources be set aside to buy
                    industrial equipment on a swap basis. The Congress objected to that too and it
                    never came to fruition.</p>
                <p>The decision on holding this meeting in December was accidental, based on a
                    number of countries’ budgets. But I have been talking to other Ambassadors about
                    postponing the meeting. I talked with His Imperial Majesty about it, but it is
                    almost impossible. Had I known of <pb facs="0431" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/> your
                    letter to His Imperial Majesty, I would have urged that it be held earlier or
                    not at all. The timing was not good.</p>
                <p>The Shah told me how much respect he has for you and he would like to do whatever
                    he could. But he said he could not propose a change of date for the meeting but
                    would accept it if others do.</p>
                <p>On the question of price, he said it is inevitable there would be an increase but
                    he proposed that it be a moderate one. Our industrial import costs are going up
                    rapidly. The price of services has risen tremendously. The price per month has
                    gone up from $3–4,000 to $12,000–16,000.</p>
                <p>But we do understand the problem, and we have been thinking of only a 10 percent
                    increase. We thought about setting aside 10 percent of each barrel to help the
                    needy countries. This failed, and we compromised on $600 million of which we—the
                    Arabs—gave 40 percent. Again, on the agricultural fund, we have contributed
                    about $400 million and the developed countries haven’t done too well. Then
                    bilaterally we have set aside about 7 percent of our Gross National Product to
                    help the developing world and our neighbors. [He listed some who are being
                    helpful.]</p>
                <p>We do understand the problem. The recommendations for the proposed increase range
                    from Algeria who is proposing 40 percent—that would be irresponsible—to Saudi
                    Arabia which publicly says 5 percent but they are trying to be the white knight.
                    There will be an increase. What would be moderate?</p>
                <p>The President: The only way we can reassure the world economy is to have no
                    increase.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: That is not possible.</p>
                <p>The President: I am telling you the facts. Any increase would jeopardize the
                    economy and no increase would be a shot in the arm. The next best would be a
                    delay. Is that possible?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: Now, it is almost impossible. If
                    it were done early in the fall—when Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> and I were joking about it—if you had asked for March,
                    it would have been easy. But Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said wait until after the election.</p>
                <p>I know how you spoke up for Iran and the Shah is deeply grateful. I don’t believe
                    any of the <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> countries would agree to a
                    delay because it would look like they were forced to.</p>
                <p>The President: That’s why I asked you to come in quietly. I want to have no
                    confrontation, and that is why this meeting is private. You say a delay or no
                    increase is out of the question. Start with the Nigerian 40 percent. That would
                    be catastrophic.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: Most of them are talking of 20–25
                    percent.</p>
                <pb facs="0432" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/>
                <p>The President: That would also be catastrophic. Alan, maybe you can address it in
                    more detail.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GA_3">Greenspan</persName>: I think it is a fact that the
                    world has not yet adjusted to the earlier increase.<note n="4" xml:id="d112fn4"
                        >See <ref target="#d82fn4">footnote 4, Document 82</ref>.</note> The early
                    very sharp increase was very destabilizing. It was possible to accommodate as
                    well as we did because there was considerable lending flexibility, both among
                    borrowers and lenders. Now, however, that flexibility has vanished. The
                    international financial structure is now stretched thin. What is wrong in the
                    strong industrial countries is a lack of confidence. That is the basic reason
                    for the pause. The reason for the confidence gap is the huge increase in debts.
                    The overhang of an oil price increase adds greatly to that lack of confidence.
                    No price increase would have a very beneficial psychological effect around the
                    world. It would bring us together and help the world economy to move again.</p>
                <p>I agree with the Shah that oil is scarce and has to be priced against competing
                    fuels. It is a matter of time. Alternate sources take time and tremendous
                    investment.</p>
                <p>Since it is a matter of psychological confidence, there is no such thing as a
                    moderate increase. And the psychological benefit of no increase, in the face of
                    all the current fears, would be substantial.</p>
                <p>The President: There is just one more thing. The situation, in several countries,
                    is very serious. Take Italy. They are having serious economic problems but at
                    the bottom it is political. If the government can’t cope, there will be
                    Communists in the government. In France, the situation is potentially serious,
                    with strong Communist forces. In Portugal, the situation is very tenuous with
                    the government just hanging on and the threat of a collapse. In Spain also, they
                    are making great progress, but it is still fragile. That is why I come back to
                    no increase or a delay. Any increase adds to the danger of a financial crisis,
                    to failure in some governments, even to the danger of military crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: I think there is no doubt there
                    will be an increase, especially after the steel price increase in this country.
                    Many newspapers are now speculating there will be a 7–15 percent increase. We
                    would not accept a big increase. There will be an increase, but we are concerned
                    about the security situation in Europe. We know more than most how important
                    Europe is and the dangers of being isolated. That is why we are giving bilateral
                    help to European governments. The price of oil is about one-half percent in the
                    United States and about one or one-and-a-half percent in Europe. Unless people
                    get a shock, they won’t realize we have to switch from oil. We have plenty of
                    coal.</p>
                <pb facs="0433" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/>
                <p>I spoke in Mexico with President <persName corresp="#p_LPJ_1">Lopez
                        Portillo</persName>. What a great love he has for you.</p>
                <p>The President: He is very impressive.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: We cannot let Mexico collapse.
                    Some are going to help them. Our Minister of Finance is going there in
                    January.</p>
                <p>I think if nothing unusual happens—and the Shah hasn’t told me so I am
                    guessing—it would be about ten percent. The highest would be 15 percent and we
                    would fight anything over 15 percent. Less than ten percent, I don’t know, but I
                    honestly don’t think so. The Shah said I could promise you he would be moderate
                    and very moderate.</p>
                <p>I will report this conversation also. But the Shah understands; he has great
                    feeling for you and for the United States. And I feel very strongly about the
                    United States and our relationship. Anything I can do, I would like to.</p>
                <p>The President: I appreciate that and I know it is true. That is why I thought we
                    could talk together this way as close friends. Please express to him my
                    admiration and affection for him. I hope that the great influence he has will be
                    directed toward a moderate increase.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZA_1">Zahedi</persName>: I will tell him again. You and
                    Mrs. Ford have an invitation to visit Iran. I hope you come as many times as you
                    can and stay as long as possible. You are a great man and we love you, whether
                    you are in or out of office.</p>
                <p>The President: I am very grateful and we would at some time like to take
                    advantage of your very kind offer.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
