<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>158. Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence Turner to Secretary of
                    Energy to Secretary of Energy Schlesinger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3jq56tRRiAvPzT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85043147"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Energy policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85141276"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Uranium</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recKJAN9jjd9CGYNt" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00001972"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCI</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="158"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                <head>158. Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_TS_1">Turner</persName> to Secretary of Energy <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR_1">Schlesinger</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d158fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                        Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_SJR_1">Schlesinger</persName>
                        Papers, Box 1, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Documents, File Four.
                        Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-08-14">August 14, 1978</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Jim,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Attached is a very short report on the role intelligence might best play in
                    supporting U.S. energy policy and planning. This was prepared by my Science and
                    Technology Advisory Panel. After you have an op<pb facs="0542" n="505"
                        xml:id="pg_505"/>portunity to read it, I would like very much to get
                    together with you to discuss this report and any other ideas you may have on how
                    we can be supporting you better. May I invite you and two or three of your
                    assistants to come to the Agency for luncheon with me and our top people
                    involved in collecting and analyzing energy information.</p>
                <p>Yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TS_1">Stansfield Turner</persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d158fn2">
                            <persName corresp="#p_TS_1">Turner</persName> signed “Stan” above this
                            typed signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d158fn3">The report is dated June 1978.</note>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">Proposed Intelligence Activities in Support of <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Energy Policy and Planning</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Observations and Conclusions</p>
                    <p>1. A number of studies have indicated clearly that a driving force in the
                        strategic position of the major powers in the 1980s–1990s will be the
                        availability and price of major energy resources. In this time frame, oil,
                        natural gas, coal, and uranium are the only resources that need be
                        considered. At present, a number of agencies and departments—<gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DOE_1">DOE</gloss>,
                        Defense, Treasury, and State—have limited efforts to examine the present
                        situation and are making limited extrapolations of what might happen over
                        the next 10 years or more with the emphasis on the shorter term
                        projections.</p>
                    <p>2. There is a high probability of continued increases in the price of oil and
                        a possible severe shortage of oil relative to the demands of the world
                        economy by the end of the coming decade. The “crunch” will be massive under
                        the almost certain condition that the Soviets will no longer be a net energy
                        exporter. The situation will be even worse if <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                            >CIA</gloss> forecasts of the Soviet need to become a substantial
                        importer are valid. Alternative sources of energy will simply not be
                        available in practical economic terms in the necessary volume by that
                        time.</p>
                    <p>3. The implications of this situation in itself and for the actions of
                        governments as it becomes closer and more salient are numerous, critical,
                        and complex. With the probable exception of the nations of arid Africa, the
                        consequences of the impending energy crunch will impact heavily on most
                        governments and thus on most major international economic issues; on the
                        stresses felt by existing alliance systems (<gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                            >NATO</gloss> and Warsaw Pact); on regional power balances and emerging
                        regional powers; and on perceptions of the need for and incentives to use
                        military forces. Without engaging in overstatement, the energy fac<pb
                            facs="0543" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/>tor will have at least as much
                        impact on the role of the United States in the world in the coming decades
                        as nuclear weapons have had in previous decades.</p>
                    <p>4. Relative to nuclear weapons, the energy factor will create far more
                        difficult requirements for information and thus tasks for the <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> intelligence and policy analysis
                        communities. The implications cannot be adequately grasped simply through
                        concentration on a very small number of foreign countries, on military as
                        distinct from economic matters, and on meeting the problem through
                        unilateral <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> procurements or dispersal of
                        technology.</p>
                    <p>5. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> energy policy community now has on
                        its agenda a large number of relevant issues and action programs. These
                        developments are relatively recent and fluid in terms of the division of
                        executive branch responsibility and focus on coordination. Nevertheless, the
                        policy community is well ahead of the current production capacity and
                        institutional priorities of the Intelligence Community on energy and
                        energy-related matters. Without substantial increases in the resources
                        allocated to intelligence production pertinent to the energy factor, the gap
                        will grow.</p>
                    <p>6. Scientific and technical development will greatly influence the pace of
                        energy resource recovery and production in countries throughout the world.
                        Much of this information is in the open literature or available from easily
                        accessible sources. At one time, the Intelligence Community maintained
                        almost routine coverage of these engineering (non-nuclear) developments.
                        Shifting emphasis to assumed higher priority items has vastly degraded the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> capability in monitoring technical
                        developments in many areas of fossil fuel recovery, conversion, and use. For
                        example, our knowledge of technological possibilities of the use of the high
                            <gloss target="#t_BTU_1">BTU</gloss> gas production developed in East
                        Germany is extremely limited. Our knowledge of the South African technology
                        for the development and use of Solvent Refined Coal is similarly limited. A
                        list of comparable examples is virtually limitless. The failure to maintain
                        cognizance of technical developments in the non-nuclear energy area will
                        severely limit technical developments in the use of fossil fuels in the
                        United States.</p>
                    <p>7. Many of the policy alternatives now under active consideration and
                        increasingly detailed formulation call for syntheses of two kinds. First,
                        they require the integration of political, economic, and scientific and
                        technical intelligence. Second, they require the integration of estimative
                        intelligence on the policy intentions, capacities, and responses of numerous
                        governments in <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>, in <gloss
                            target="#t_CEMA_1">CEMA</gloss>, and in the developing world.</p>
                    <p>8. Unfortunately, these two sorts of syntheses are precisely what the <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Intelligence Community is poorly organized
                        to provide. Given <pb facs="0544" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> other production
                        burdens and historically established interagency and interoffice divisions
                        of labor, it is unrealistic to expect these syntheses to be generated in the
                        absence of high-level guidance and demand. There clearly exists competence
                        among individual analysts as demonstrated by a superb <gloss
                            target="#t_ORPA_1">ORPA</gloss> report on the political economics of
                        energy in the Warsaw Pact.</p>
                    <p>9. Analyses which synthesize across types of information and pertinent
                        nations obviously can be no better than the descriptive intelligence
                        information and “single discipline” and “single country” analyses on which
                        they can draw. The activities being undertaken and the priority questions
                        identified for production are by and large commendable and necessary. They
                        are in no way sufficient, however, to the scope of the problems posed by the
                        energy factor.</p>
                    <p>10. It would obviously be inappropriate to assume that the sole provider of
                        information pertinent to energy and energy-related policy issues will or
                        should be the Intelligence Community. However, there is little evidence of a
                        thorough assessment of which information needs should be met by the
                        Intelligence Community, which would be best provided by analysts working
                        under other public and private sector auspices, and how these streams of
                        production should be organized to complement each other efficiently.</p>
                    <p>11. An examination of these efforts to understand (a) the energy policy of
                        the Soviet Union, (b) the implications of the energy shortages to the LDCs,
                        and (c) the significance of these developments to the future of the United
                        States convinces us that <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> efforts in this
                        area fall far short of what is needed. In our view, the availability of
                        energy will <hi rend="italic">determine</hi> the economic situation in the
                        world in the 1985–2000 period. There is at present no <hi rend="italic"
                            >unified</hi> effort to understand the long-term view of the Soviets
                        regarding their energy policy or even their assessment of the <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> policy. Limited efforts are under way to
                        understand Soviet <gloss target="#t_RnD_1">R&amp;D</gloss> developments. We
                        believe that these are relatively weak attempts which reflect an evaluation
                        of Soviet <gloss target="#t_RnD_1">R&amp;D</gloss> in terms of our own
                        programs.</p>
                    <p>12. The rapid evolution of requirements for intelligence on energy systems
                        poses two kinds of important problems. First, our lack of experience will
                        hinder the developments of the kind of analysis important in the 1985–2000
                        time period. Second, the users of intelligence analysis will also require
                        experience as to the kind of analysis that will be of greatest aid in the
                        formulation of policy. The development of the appropriate analytical
                        capabilities and the acquisition of the means to use analysis will require
                        the close cooperation of the analytic and policy making communities.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations</p>
                    <p>1. The <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> should charge his staff to
                        develop a community-wide plan for the production of energy and
                        energy-related intelligence and <pb facs="0545" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/>
                        the identification of the additional resources necessary to support the
                        framing and evaluation of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> policy choices.
                        The plan should also identify the focus of leadership responsibility to
                        ensure that the synthesized analyses mentioned earlier will be
                        forthcoming.</p>
                    <p>2. The <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> and his representatives should
                        clarify with the Secretary of Energy and his representatives the information
                        needs of the latter and the contributions each will make to the provision of
                        needed analyses. Resolution of their relationship is important for getting
                        on with the substantive intelligence needs posed by the energy factor.
                        Failure to do so is likely to result in unproductive hassles about control
                        of the turf and additional intelligence resources.</p>
                    <p>3. While all necessary work cannot be done at once, the Intelligence
                        Community should pursue major synthesized analyses of, and devote ongoing
                        intelligence attention to, a small number of particularly crucial questions
                        and problems facing <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> policymakers. These
                        include:</p>
                    <p>• Preparations to maintain the safety of oil transport by sea to the United
                        States, Western Europe, and Japan.</p>
                    <p>• Feasible and acceptable <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> initiatives to
                        enhance the non-nuclear energy alternatives available to the developing
                        countries (and in particular to potential nuclear proliferators).</p>
                    <p>• Alternative adaptations by major <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>
                        nations to the coming energy crunch, including their responsiveness to
                        collective action proposals in cooperation with each other and the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>• Clarification of the extent and the economic and technical conditions for
                        feasible exploitation and use of energy mineral endowments on a worldwide
                        basis (in particular oil, natural gas, uranium, and coal).</p>
                    <p>• Alternative strategies to create sufficient interdependence between major
                        energy exporters and importers to induce the latter to sharply boost
                        extraction rates in time of emergency and to acquire the facilities on a
                        standby basis which will make that possible in a timely fashion.</p>
                    <p>• Development of institutional techniques that will facilitate the rapid
                        application of energy technologies developed outside the United States but
                        knowledge of which may have been obtained through intelligence analysis.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
