<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-11-20T06:04:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-11-20T06:04:00-05:00" n="21" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                        <head>21. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d21fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files, D740335–0877. Confidential; Priority; <gloss target="#t_Limdis_1">Limdis</gloss>. Repeated to Bonn, Brussels
                                for the Embassy and <gloss target="#t_USEC_1">USEC</gloss>,
                                Copenhagen, Dublin, Luxembourg, London, Rome, The Hague, and Tokyo
                                for the Secretary.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-11-20T11:04:00+00:00">November 20, 1974,
                                1104Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>27637. Subject: <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-French Energy
                            Relations.</p>
                        <p>1. Summary: We recommend that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                            propose tradeoff to <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> on current
                            energy issues which would balance <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            acceptance in principle of producer-consumer conference in mid 1975
                            against <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> acceptance of close
                            preparation for such conference within <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss>, and support for <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            recycling proposal.<note n="2" xml:id="d21fn2">See <ref target="#d15">Document 15</ref>.</note> Consultations should begin soonest if
                            this <pb facs="0119" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> agreement to be formally
                            reached, as it best would be, by two Presidents at Martinique. End
                            summary.</p>
                        <p>2. While initial French reaction to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s speech<note n="3" xml:id="d21fn3">See <ref target="#d17fn4">footnote 4, Document
                                    17</ref>.</note> has been to downplay differences between <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and French positions, it appears clear
                            to us and undoubtedly to <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> that
                            serious differences remain over tactics and timing for a future oil
                            conference. French efforts to convince other invitees to accept <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> ideas for such a conference may now
                            run into stiffer resistance as result of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> reaction, and may cause rift among <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> members.</p>
                        <p>3. We believe French are unlikely to abandon conference idea readily.
                            This is not solely because of pride or because Giscard’s opponents from
                            both ends of political spectrum would jump on him for bowing to American
                            pressure, but also because <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> firmly
                            believes that dialogue with producers is required and should start as
                            soon as possible; French balance of payments situation is such that
                                <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> cannot afford new oil price
                            increases while negotiating situation ripens. We believe however that
                            French would be prepared to be flexible on timing if they were to know
                            that oil negotiations would indeed take place before too long.</p>
                        <p>4. As seen from Paris, a <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> clash over this issue would not be in
                            our interest. It would prevent any real success at Martinique and would
                            probably usher in a period of embittered relations with the new French
                            Government. More importantly, it would split Europe on an issue which as
                            we see it most European governments would rather see bridged over, and
                            would also divert the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> from taking
                            those joint energy policy steps—setting goals for reduced oil
                            consumption and increased energy production—which are basically
                            supportive of our goals in the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss>.
                            Finally, it would probably provoke a French reversion to an aggressively
                            independent energy policy and because of France’s key role in the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>, energy cooperation among consuming
                            countries will continue to be much more workable with than without
                            France.</p>
                        <p>5. We believe that a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> confrontation can be avoided, and that
                            we have the elements of a compromise which can both strengthen the
                            consumer cooperation in <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> and ease
                            French fears that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> intends to use
                            the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> to prepare for a confrontation
                            with the oil producers. The settlement we propose could be struck at
                            Martinique in a way which moreover could open the way to more
                            cooperative and productive <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–French
                            relations. Our proposal would consist essentially of trading <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> agreement in principle to the holding of
                            a producer-consumer conference (possibly during the summer of 1975)
                            against French agreement to cooperate and consult fully with the members
                            of <pb facs="0120" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/> the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> in preparing a common consumer position for such a
                            conference, and to support our recycling proposal. Such an exchange
                            would give Giscard the conference he wants—but only after a reasonable
                            delay in which the consumer position could be further consolidated. In
                            return, France would have to associate itself much more closely with the
                            formulation of that consumer position within the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> and, if possible, commit itself to
                            joining the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> in due process.</p>
                        <p>6. To reach this objective, preparation through high-level discussions
                            with the <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> must begin immediately.
                            Giscard has put the question of <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>
                            support for French conference proposal on the agenda of the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> Summit which will probably take place
                            December 9–10. It is essential that we have at least a tacit
                            understanding with <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> and adequate
                            consultations with our major <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss>
                            partners before that date if we are to avoid a harmful clash between
                            France and the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> 8, or to bring this
                            proposed deal to a conclusion at Martinique. If the Department agrees
                            with this proposal, I recommend that the process of consultation begin
                            without delay.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_RK_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Rush</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>