<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>28. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in West
                    Germany</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-12-24T17:28:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-12-24T17:28:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-12-24T17:28:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-12-24T17:28:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <head>28. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in West Germany<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d28fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1"
                            >Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, Presidential
                        Correspondence with Foreign Leaders, Box 2, Germany (<gloss
                            target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>)—Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_SH_2"
                            >Schmidt</persName> (1). Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Katz</persName>
                        and approved by <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1974-12-24T22:28:00+00:00">December 24, 1974,
                        2228Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>281378. Subject: Presidential Message to Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_SH_2"
                        >Schmidt</persName>. Embassy requested transmit following message from
                    President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> to Chancellor <persName
                        corresp="#p_SH_2">Schmidt</persName>:</p>
                <p>1. “Dear Mr. Chancellor: As I mentioned in my previous letter,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d28fn2">On December 16, <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                        sent a letter to <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Schmidt</persName> to inform
                        him about his talks with Giscard in Martinique. (Telegram <gloss
                            target="#t_Secto_1">Secto</gloss> 21 to Bonn; ibid.) The memorandum of
                        the December 15 meeting between <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                        and Giscard is <ref target="#d24">Document 24</ref>.</note> we and the
                    French reached some understandings in Martinique on the elements of consumer
                    country collaboration necessary before we can move on to subsequent steps.
                    Progress on financial cooperation is of particular concern to us at this time.
                    In all frankness I must tell you that I do not believe that the United States
                    will be in a position to participate in a consumer-producer meeting until the
                    consumers have established their solidarity in the financial field.</p>
                <p>2. The Group of Ten Working Group has made some progress on resolving the issues
                    necessary to enable us to make a final decision on financial cooperation among
                    participating <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> countries. As I mentioned
                    in Washington, however, I am convinced that a satisfactory outcome depends very
                    much on the fullest possible exchange and understanding of views between your
                    government and mine.</p>
                <p>3. I hope, therefore, that we can remain in close contact on the remaining major
                    issues that need to be resolved to assure that any new facility meets its
                    objective of underpinning the economic health and cooperation of the industrial
                    democracies. I have particularly in mind the questions relating to the size of
                    the facility, the respective national quotas and the form of national
                    commitments (loans, guarantees or some combination of the two).</p>
                <p>4. I would like to have <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Arthur Burns</persName>
                    discuss these questions with you on my behalf and would be grateful if you could
                    meet with Arthur in Bonn for this purpose during the early part of January.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d28fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Burns</persName> met with <persName
                            corresp="#p_SH_2">Schmidt</persName> in Hamburg on January 11, 1975, and
                        reported that the Chancellor accepted entirely the political concept
                        underlying the U.S. plan for a financial safety net and would endorse it.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Schmidt</persName> also felt that “speedy
                        movement” on the plan was necessary. (Telegram 42 from Hamburg, January 11;
                        National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                        Policy Files, P850104–1539)</note> With regard to this task of effective
                    financial cooperation, as well as related en<pb facs="0145" n="108"
                        xml:id="pg_108"/>deavors to secure the strength of our economies and our
                    alliance, you can be assured of my fullest cooperation in the pursuit of
                    solutions that serve our mutual interests. With warm regards, <persName
                        corresp="#p_FGR_1">Gerald R. Ford</persName>.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KHA_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
