<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>30. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-08-13T10:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-01-13T19:24:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001184"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Magazine</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="prices" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518" lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-01-13T19:24:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-08-13T10:15:00-05:00" n="30" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d30">
                <head>30. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On January 3, 1975, <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> reported that
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, in
                    an interview with <hi rend="italic">Business Week</hi> magazine shortly before
                    Christmas, said that he could not rule out the use of force against
                    oil-producing nations. He made clear, however, that such action “would be
                    considered only in the gravest emergency.” “I am not saying that there’s no
                    circumstances where we would not use force,” he said, “but it is one thing to
                    use it in the case of a dispute over price; it’s another where there is some
                    actual strangulation of the industrialized world.” Asked about the interview,
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> remarked: “I have said it
                    would not come to that point, and that the oil problem would be dealt with by
                    other methods,” but he reiterated that “there’s no circumstances where we would
                    not use force.” The December 23 <hi rend="italic">Business Week</hi> interview
                    was reprinted in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> January
                    27, 1975, pp. 97–106.</p>
                <p>The Embassy in Saudi Arabia reported that King Faisal and the Saudi Government
                    were “disturbed” by the “threatening implications” of the statements that
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> made during the <hi
                        rend="italic">Business Week</hi> interview. A Royal adviser told Ambassador
                    James Akins: “This represents a complete change in American policy and we must
                    therefore revise <pb facs="0146" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/> our own policy toward
                    the United States.” Akins responded that there was “no change” in U.S. policy
                    and that he “had made the same statements” himself in a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Affairs</hi> article 2 years before. He also reminded the adviser
                    that he had declared, both publicly in the United States and privately in Saudi
                    Arabia, that “invasion would be madness but when countries are reduced to
                    desperation they take ‘mad’ actions.” To help alleviate Saudi concerns, Akins
                    requested additional information from the Department or a message from the
                    Secretary. (Telegram 32 from Jidda, January 4; National Archives, <gloss
                        target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                    D750004–0636)</p>
                <p>The Ambassador sent another telegram the following day informing the Department
                    that Minister of Petroleum <persName corresp="#p_YSAZ_1">Sheikh Ahmad
                        Yamani</persName> told him that the King was “depressed and worried by
                    ‘American threats’ against Saudi Arabia.” <persName corresp="#p_YSAZ_1"
                        >Yamani</persName> also said that he had never seen the King “so worried and
                    so questioning of his relationship with the United States.” Later that day, the
                    King himself told Akins that he was “extremely disturbed” by the “series of
                    ‘American threats’ against Saudi Arabia” that culminated in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Business Week</hi> interview. As for the prospect of occupying
                    the Saudi oil fields, <persName corresp="#p_YSAZ_1">Yamani</persName> said that
                    doing so would be “very difficult,” that the fields could be “sabotaged easily,”
                    that a “‘quick surgical operation’ would be impossible,” and that the result
                    would be the “loss of Saudi production for years.” Akins believed, however, that
                    Saudi officials would “calm down” once they digested the Arabic translation of
                    the complete text of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s
                    statements. That said, he also thought that the Kingdom would be “stirred up
                    again” when the next newspaper or magazine article reported that the United
                    States proposed occupying Saudi Arabia or any other oil-producing country.
                    (Telegram 67 from Jidda, January 5; ibid., D750004–0773)</p>
                <p>On January 8, the Department instructed Akins to tell the Saudi Government that
                    the question about military action “arose with specific relation to oil prices,”
                    and that the Secretary “made it clear that we did not consider military action
                    to be an appropriate response to oil prices.” The Department also instructed the
                    Ambassador to point out that the question itself was a hypothetical one
                    regarding a “deliberate attempt” by oil producers to “strangle the
                    industrialized world”—the “gravest emergency”—which <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said did not apply to the “present situation,” adding
                    that he “did not foresee such a situation arising.” The Department told Akins to
                    point out that <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> never mentioned
                    the possibility of an invasion of Saudi Arabia in particular, and that he had
                    highlighted the “importance of maintaining the relationship of friendship
                    between Saudi Arabia and the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>.” (Telegram 1955
                    to Jidda; ibid., D750004–0717)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> replied personally in a note
                    to Prince Sultan regarding the <hi rend="italic">Business Week</hi> interview
                    (telegram 7266 to Jidda, January 11; ibid., <pb facs="0147" n="110"
                        xml:id="pg_110"/> P850106–2309), a gesture for which the Prince expressed
                    “deep appreciation.” Sultan also said that he hoped that the Secretary’s note,
                    and a similar note from President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                    to King Faisal (telegram 7265 to Jidda, January 11; ibid., P850106–2304) would
                    result in “calming passions” in other Arab capitals. (Telegram 283 from Jidda,
                    January 14; <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National
                    Security Adviser, Presidential Country Files for Middle East and South Asia, Box
                    29, Saudi Arabia—State Department Telegrams to SECSTATE–NODIS (3))</p>
                <p>Although U.S.-Saudi tensions over the interview had dissipated by mid-January,
                        <persName corresp="#p_YSAZ_1">Yamani</persName> warned Akins that the Saudi
                    National Guard “had orders to prepare to blow up certain sensitive sections of
                    the Saudi oil fields and to fire certain wells should there be concrete plans to
                    invade and occupy them.” <persName corresp="#p_YSAZ_1">Yamani</persName> added
                    that “there had been inter-Arab discussion on the matter and any invasion would
                    be followed by cutoff of all Arab oil.” (Telegram 251 from Jidda, January 13;
                    ibid., P850106–2311)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
