<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="63" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                        <head>63. Memorandum From the Acting Executive Director of the Council on
                            International Economic Policy (<persName corresp="#p_DJM_1">Dunn</persName>) to the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d63fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security
                                Adviser, Presidential Subject File, Box 4, Energy (9).
                                Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-05-15">May 15, 1975</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>United States Preparedness to Withstand an Oil Embargo</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Our staffs have discussed several issues that deserve examination
                            relating to our preparedness to handle another oil embargo. These issues
                            include:</p>
                        <p>a. a review of international petroleum allocation mechanisms that would
                            be available in the event of either the absence or failure of <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> allocation mechanisms;</p>
                        <p>b. an assessment of the likelihood of <gloss target="#t_OAPEC_1">OAPEC</gloss> using the “financial weapon” to augment any oil
                            supply disruption, and measures we might employ to counter;</p>
                        <p>c. a review of the current drawdown of worldwide petroleum stocks—causes,
                            implications and policy options available to encourage supranormal stock
                            levels if deemed necessary or desirable;</p>
                        <p>d. a review of the current military fuel stock situation.</p>
                        <p>Normal peacetime military stocks are said to be more than four million
                            barrels short now. This review should be joined with estimates of
                            military offtake from available national petroleum supplies in the event
                            of an embargo.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> establish an adhoc
                            group to examine generally United States preparedness to withstand
                            another embargo including the items outlined above. We feel that such a
                            group should include representatives from <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FEA_1">FEA</gloss>, Treasury, State,
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIEP_1">CIEP</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d63fn2">No record of this group
                                has been found, but a reference to a similar group formed in
                                February is in <ref target="#d72">Document 72</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_DJM_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_DJM_1">J.M. Dunn</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>