<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-07-14T19:18:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-07-14T19:18:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                        <head>70. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Belgium<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d70fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files, P850036–2610. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>; Stadis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BS_1">Bosworth</persName>, cleared by Roger A.
                                Sorenson (E) and <persName corresp="#p_PEH_1">Preeg</persName>, and
                                approved by <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName>. Repeated
                                Immediate to <gloss target="#t_USOECD_1">USOECD</gloss>
                                Paris.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-07-15T00:18:00+00:00">July 15, 1975,
                                0018Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>165677. Subject: Status of Preparations for Resumption of
                            Producer-Consumer Dialogue.</p>
                        <p>1. Please pass following message to <persName corresp="#p_DE_1">Davignon</persName> from Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName>.</p>
                        <p>2. I want to give you our assessment of the current state of play on the
                            resumption of the dialogue following our talks with the French during
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s visit to
                            Paris last Thursday.<note n="2" xml:id="d70fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sauvagnargues</persName> in Paris on July 9.
                                They agreed that by the end of August, before the next <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> meeting and before the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Session, they should
                                announce that they recommended the resumption of a producer/consumer
                                dialogue. They also discussed establishing one commission to tackle
                                commodity issues, which <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> said the United States preferred “except
                                for energy.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> also
                                said that by the time of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                                meeting, the U.S. Government would overcome internal differences and
                                settle on a unified commodity policy. (Ibid., Records of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, Lot 91D414, Box
                                11, Classified External Memoranda of Conversations, July 1975)
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> also met with
                                Giscard, and their discussion is described in telegram 17951 from
                                Paris, July 10. (Ibid., Central Foreign Policy Files,
                                P840084–1763)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. The French now agree that the dialogue should resume with a second
                            meeting of the Kleber group. This meeting would be followed by a
                            conference at Ministerial level of the 27 countries tentatively agreed
                            upon in April. Both meetings would be short, thoroughly prepared, and
                            with the purpose of establishing 3 commissions on energy, raw materials,
                            and development.</p>
                        <p>4. On the question of timing, the French have come around to the view
                            that it is not feasible to try to reconvene the preparatory meeting
                            before the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Session. They
                            showed some initial preference for a meeting before the September <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> session, but I believe they now
                            agree that this is also impracticable and that we should aim for early
                            October. They would share the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> view
                            that there should be some announcement of the reconvening of the
                            preparatory meeting and subsequent timetable before the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Session, i.e. before the end of
                            August. On this basis, we would announce within the next several weeks
                            that the preparatory meeting would reconvene in early October. The
                            Ministerial meeting would follow within approximately 60 days and the
                            commissions could begin their work before the end of the year.</p>
                        <p>5. On the basis of our bilateral talks with the Iranians, Saudis,
                            Venezuelans, and Brazilians, we are confident that this general approach
                                <pb facs="0282" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> on procedure and timing
                            will be acceptable to them. However, there are still some key points
                            which remain to be resolved both with the French and with the Seven. On
                            the question of participation, the French are somewhat vague about our
                            earlier understanding reached in April that the 19 LDCs represented at
                            the conference of 27 would include 8 <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> members. We believe this is an important condition and
                            one which we must nail down before convening a second <gloss target="#t_Prepcon_1">Prepcon</gloss>. The French also want to leave
                            the question of membership on the commissions themselves in the hands of
                            the two groups (the 8 industrialized representatives and the 19 LDCs).
                            We continue to prefer objective criteria for determining membership on
                            the commissions, and have received tentative endorsement of this
                            approach from Venezuela.</p>
                        <p>6. On the critical question of the autonomy of the commissions and
                            whether they will report back to a second conference of the 27, the
                            French are now talking in terms of a “stock taking” meeting of the 27
                            some 6 months after the first meeting and the launching of the
                            commissions. They argue that this second meeting can be kept both short
                            and procedural in nature. We continue to have reservations on this
                            score. If the large conference can meet every six months, soon it will
                            be meeting for six months at a time and will have practically preempted
                            the dialogue, thereby condemning it to sterility. But we recognize that
                            pressure is building for some kind of a schedule, and this is a key
                            issue we will want to discuss at the next Governing Board meeting.</p>
                        <p>7. The role of the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> in the resumed
                            dialogue is also still at issue. In our view, agreement to reconvene the
                            preparatory meeting in the same format means by definition that the
                                <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> will be present as an observer.
                            We can seek through previous negotiation to establish the cosmetics of
                            this presence in such a way as to minimize the possibilities for
                            confrontation with the Algerians. But we can not agree to exclude the
                                <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> from the preparatory meeting.
                            As for the Ministerial meeting of 27, we should consider in the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> whether in fact <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> presence is required since the scope
                            of that meeting would cover all economic relations between
                            industrialized and developing countries. On the other hand, the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> must be present as an observer with
                            the right to speak in the energy commission.</p>
                        <p>8. The French have told us that they plan to circulate soon to the Group
                            of Ten a paper<note n="3" xml:id="d70fn3">Not found.</note> laying out
                            what in their judgment could be a basis for resuming the dialogue. This
                            would be the vehicle through which agreement among the Ten would be
                            crystallized and assurance obtained against another failure. If we
                            receive the French paper before the July 28 Governing Board meeting, we
                            would not plan to respond to <pb facs="0283" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/>
                            it formally until after we have had an opportunity for full <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> consultation at that meeting. In the
                            meantime, we will continue our bilateral contacts with the Seven, and
                            Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> now
                            plans to visit Algeria during the week of July 21.</p>
                        <p>9. At the July 28 Governing Board meeting, I think we should try to reach
                            agreement on the timetable as well as the basic questions of format and
                            procedure. In particular, I think we will have to reach a position on
                            the “reporting back” issue which I view as the key unresolved
                                point.<note n="4" xml:id="d70fn4">According to a message from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, at the July 28 <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> Governing Board meeting,
                                “consultations with other members” of the Board on resuming the
                                producer/consumer dialogue “went according to plan.” “No substantive
                                objections” were raised to the proposals that the United States had
                                given to France, <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName>
                                wrote. He added that the “main focus of discussion” was the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss>’s role in the dialogue, and that
                                the Board agreed with the U.S. position that 1) the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> “should be present” at the new
                                prepcon on the “same basis as before,” but “would not ask to speak”;
                                and 2) the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> would “be asked to
                                participate as an observer in the energy commission” with the “right
                                to speak.” Japan and Italy worried that the United States had not
                                mentioned <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> participation in
                                consultation with oil producers and wanted to be sure that <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> participation would not become a
                                “make-or-break issue” upon the dialogue’s resumption. (Telegram
                                19570 from <gloss target="#t_USOECD_1">USOECD</gloss> Paris, July
                                28; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy Files, P840125–2598)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>10. I will be sending you another message later this week on our
                            proposals for moving ahead at the July 28 meeting on both long term
                            cooperation and the emergency system. I believe it is particularly
                            important on the former that we make steady progress toward our December
                            1 date, narrowing each of the key issues in each meeting as we did
                            during the <gloss target="#t_ECG_1">ECG</gloss> negotiation of the
                                <gloss target="#t_IEP_1">IEP</gloss> itself.<note n="5" xml:id="d70fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_DE_1">Davignon</persName> replied that “in
                                general” he agreed with the U.S. position and that he was
                                “particularly pleased with the Department’s views on <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> participation at the second
                                preparatory meeting and on the energy commission.” (Telegram 6417
                                from Brussels, July 15; ibid., P850081–2024)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_IRS_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_IRS_1">Ingersoll</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>