<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-01-13T19:24:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-08-13T10:15:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                        <head>90. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>The Conference on International Economic Cooperation met at the
                            Ministerial level in Paris December 16–18, 1975, and established four
                            commissions to deal with issues related to energy, raw materials,
                            development, and finance. Participants agreed to schedule a meeting on
                            January 26, 1976, of conference and commission co-chairmen to “prepare
                            the work of the four commissions” within “the framework of the general
                            guidelines” established at the October <gloss target="#t_Prepcon_1">Prepcon</gloss> (see <ref target="#d85">Document 85</ref>). As for
                            the energy commission, which, along with the other three, would hold its
                            first meeting in Paris on February 11, 1976, the Department of State
                            believed that it should concentrate on two areas: 1) analyzing “the
                            relationship of energy supply, demand, and prices to the development of
                            the global economy in an effort to seek to narrow the differences in
                            perceptions of this relationship among the participants”; and 2)
                            promoting “cooperative endeavors among producers and consumers to
                            develop new energy supplies, to accelerate and smooth the integration of
                            the producing countries into the global economy, and to facilitate the
                            transfer of energy-related technology and expertise to the non-oil
                            developing countries to help relieve their energy burdens.” Stephen
                                <persName corresp="#p_BS_1">Bosworth</persName>, Director of the
                            Office of Fuels and Energy, would head the U.S. delegation as the
                            industrial country co-chairman of the energy commission. (Telegram 9962
                            to all diplomatic posts, January 16; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                            D760018–0154)</p>
                        <p>On December 19, 1975, the International Energy Agency Governing Board met
                            in Paris and concluded an agreement on a Long-<pb facs="0364" n="327" xml:id="pg_327"/>Term Energy Cooperation Program, which included “a
                            minimum safeguard price of $7.00 <gloss target="#t_FOB_1">FOB</gloss>”
                            for Persian Gulf oil in addition to a “commitment to implement it” in a
                            way that was “acceptable” to the United States. The agreement also
                            included a “provision for large joint projects, improved international
                            access to energy investments, and all other elements of an overall
                            package that we have considered essential.” Until the Governing Board
                            convened in January to “conclude the definitive agreement,” had the
                            status of a “Governing Board recommendation to governments,” but it was
                            “understood and accepted” that negotiations had ended. (Telegram 33322
                            from <gloss target="#t_USOECD_1">USOECD</gloss> Paris, December 20;
                            ibid., [no film number]) Telegram 33526 from <gloss target="#t_USOECD_1">USOECD</gloss> Paris, December 23, contains the complete text of
                            the draft. (Ibid., D750445–0901) See <ref target="#d94fn2">footnote 2,
                                Document 94</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>