<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" n="1032" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1032">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24522/52: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-02-01T18:00:00-05:00">February
                                    1, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received February 2—12:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>102. My telegram number 59, January 23, 11 a.m. In conversation this
                            afternoon the President<note n="36" xml:id="d1032fn36">Carlos A. Arroyo
                                del Río.</note> brought up the Galápagos Agreement. He stated that
                            the Ecuadorean Congress wished an agreement to be signed without delay
                            and inquired regarding its status. I informed him that I had promptly
                            sent the text of the new draft agreement to the Department but that in
                            view of the many changes the counterdraft<note n="37" xml:id="d1032fn37">Copy transmitted to the Department in despatch 925, January 11,
                                1944, from Quito, not printed.</note> required considerable study.
                            The President admitted there were various changes but said these were
                            really in language and not in substance. I replied that although this
                            appeared to be true in general there had been a definite change in
                            article 2 regarding duration. He stated that in his opinion the revised
                            article did not represent any change of substance, as under the previous
                            draft a new agreement would have to be arrived at between the two
                            Governments if we wished to remain after the war. He added that the
                            revision of this article had been made at the insistence of the
                            Committee for Foreign Relations of Congress and said that he himself
                            preferred that it be accepted in its present form as the previous
                            wording created the impression that we wished to stay indefinitely. I
                            did not discuss the question further but merely told the President that
                            I was awaiting instructions.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotten</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>