<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Diplomatic Representatives in the
                    American Republics Except Argentina, El Salvador, Honduras, and
                    Nicaragua</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1099</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1099</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-17T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-17T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-17T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-17T23:00:00-05:00" n="1099"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1099">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">814.01/11–1844: Circular telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives in the American Republics
                            Except Argentina, El Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-18T00:00:00-04:00"
                            >November 18, 1944—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Reference Deptel circular November 4, 7 p.m. You are requested in strict
                    confidence to inform the Foreign Minister of the Government to which you are
                    accredited that from the information available to the Department, the situation
                    in El Salvador still appears obscure.</p>
                <p>Department’s information indicates general strike has subsided but Mortgage Bank,
                    a center of political controversy, has not yet reopened. The mass of public
                    opinion appears opposed to present government, and newspapers are critical.
                    Thus, while Aguirre régime appears to hold control of machinery of Government
                    there <pb facs="1124" n="1110" xml:id="pg_1110"/> is open popular resistance and
                    the stability of the regime appears to be by no means assured.</p>
                <p>While there is no evidence to establish that the overthrow of Menéndez was
                    inspired by the Axis as such, Aguirre himself and several of his Cabinet are
                    considered in El Salvador to have totalitarian sympathies. Menéndez has recently
                    issued a statement declaring he was made to resign by force rather than because
                    of ill health as was alleged.</p>
                <p>Although Aguirre régime has indicated its intention to co-operate in the war
                    effort, it has not as yet agreed fully to assume all of its international
                    obligations.</p>
                <p>Molina has established a self-styled government in exile in Guatemala and is
                    seeking recognition. He has recently been joined there by Arturo Romero, leading
                    civilian presidential candidate.</p>
                <p>In their replies to the Department’s previous telegrams concerning recognition,
                    the American Republics while agreeing (except for Honduras and Nicaragua which
                    have already recognized the Aguirre régime) that action should be withheld for
                    the moment, are not in full accord as to the basis on which it should be
                    extended. Some countries hold that recognition should not be granted to other
                    than a democratic régime, although this attitude would perhaps imply a departure
                    from hemisphere undertakings regarding non-intervention and a broadening of the
                    scope of the consultations envisaged by Resolution 22 of the Montevideo
                    Committee. Other countries have been more disposed to follow the principle of
                    the Estrada doctrine.<note n="56" xml:id="d1099fn56">Doctrine concerning
                        governmental recognition set forth by Mexican Minister for Foreign Affairs
                        Genaro Estrada, in 1930; see <hi rend="italic">American Journal of
                            International Law</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xxv</hi> (1931), pp.
                        719–723. See also Institute Americano de Derecho y Legislación Comparada,
                            <hi rend="italic">La Doctrina Estrada</hi> (Mexico, 1930).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Please convey the above comments to the Foreign Minister and request an
                    expression of his views, as the Government of the United States is desirous of
                    determining its attitude in full consultation and in solidarity with the other
                    nations of the hemisphere.</p>
                <p>Montevideo please inform Sanders. The foregoing telegram has been sent to all the
                    American Republics except Argentina, El Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua (the
                    latter two having already extended recognition). Repeated to Buenos Aires, San
                    Salvador, Tegucigalpa, and Managua for information. Tegucigalpa and Managua may
                    at their discretion convey the substance of the above to their Foreign Ministers
                    for information.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
