<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Messersmith) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1191</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1191</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="1191"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1191">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.24/11–1744</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 21,390</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">México</hi>, D.F.</placeName>, <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-17">November 17,
                        1944</date>.<lb/>[Received November 23.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to place before the Department
                    for its consideration a matter of prime importance to the success of the
                    Mexican-American Commission for Economic Cooperation and which will determine in
                    a large measure whether or not the Mexicans will judge the Commission as a
                    success or a partial failure. At a time when the work of the Commission is on
                    the verge of drawing to a close, it would be very unfortunate for us to permit
                    the failure to grant two priorities on Commission projects to deprive us of the
                    good will and real benefits of the effective work which has been done by the
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>The Department is quite familiar with the procedure of the Commission which
                    established the Minimum Program for 1944 containing twenty-one projects. This
                    program was approved by the Department, the War Production Board and the Foreign
                    Economic Administration. The authorities of these departments are to be very
                    highly complimented on the effective cooperation which they have given the
                    Commission and which allowed all 1944 Minimum Program projects to receive
                    satisfactory priorities with the exception of two. These two exceptions are the
                    Celanese and Jorge Luis Baz Textile projects, and they are both extremely
                    important from the Mexican point of view. Earlier in the year the War Production
                    Board indicated that it would probably be in position to rate the two projects
                    in September of this year, but as that was not done, they have remained
                    pending.</p>
                <pb facs="1225" n="1211" xml:id="pg_1211"/>
                <p>In the meantime, word has been received by the Embassy and the Commission of the
                    new policy of the War Production Board whereby projects not directly connected
                    with the war effort will not be considered for priorities. As a result, Celanese
                    and Baz still remain without priorities, and the Mexican importers have been
                    advised to place their unrated orders with United States manufacturers on the
                    best possible commercial basis. In the case of the Baz Textile project, the
                    owner was informed by the manufacturers of textile machinery that delivery could
                    not be expected before late 1945 or early 1946 because the backlog of priority
                    orders and unrated orders would not permit earlier despatch.</p>
                <p>The Resident Commissioner of the Mexican-American Commission for Economic
                    Cooperation is writing a report to the two Washington Commissioners, wherein he
                    recommends, after full consultation with and approval of the Ambassador, and Mr.
                    Machold, the resident representative of Messrs. Rockefeller and Taylor, that the
                    work of the Commission be terminated and the Commission itself dissolved after a
                    report of its activities has been prepared and submitted to the two Presidents.
                    This recommendation is being made because the Mexican members of the Commission
                    have from the beginning viewed the effectiveness of the Commission by its
                    success in securing licenses and priorities for Mexican importers. The
                    Ambassador, the Mexican Commissioners, Mr. Machold, as representative of the
                    Washington Commissioners, and the Commissioner resident in Mexico fully realize
                    that the new policy of the War Production Board in not rating projects not
                    directly connected with the war effort will eliminate practical assistance which
                    might be given by the Commission to Mexican importers and, therefore, the
                    Mexicans will sidestep the Commission and go direct to United States
                    manufacturers.</p>
                <p>Under the circumstances, the Ambassador, the Mexican Commissioners, Mr. Machold
                    and the Resident Commissioner have reached the conclusion that it would be
                    better to terminate the activities of the Commission after delivery of the
                    report of its accomplishments to the two Presidents. The President of the
                    Commission, Licenciado Primo Villa Michel, is now conferring with the President
                    of the Republic and the Foreign Minister in order to make the foregoing
                    suggestion to them. But, the principal accomplishment of the Commission is the
                    1944 Minimum Program, and the Commission feels that its responsibilities under
                    that program will not be fulfilled until the two remaining projects are given a
                    priority rating by the War Production Board. The President of the Republic has
                    talked to the Ambassador on several occasions concerning his interest in the
                    Celanese project. His interest in it is not personal, but due to his belief that
                    Mexico urgently heeds such an industry. There are prominent industrialists and
                    government <pb facs="1226" n="1212" xml:id="pg_1212"/> officials who are
                    personal investors in the project and, therefore, the failure to receive a
                    priority would destroy much of the good will which has been created by the
                    Commission. The Baz Textile project is somewhat in the same status, and the
                    reaction against the Commission would be quite strong if we should fail to rate
                    this and the Celanese projects.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Therefore, the Department is urgently requested to use its full weight and
                    influence with the War Production Board in order that the two remaining projects
                    of the 1944 Minimum Program may receive a priority rating from the War
                    Production Board. Such action would permit the Commission to make its report to
                    the two Presidents on the basis that its primary work had been successfully
                    completed with every project in the Minimum Program having received a favorable
                    priority. This announcement will make a favorable and lasting impression upon
                    the Mexican people and permit the United States to receive the credit and good
                    will which it deserves through a fuller appreciation and understanding by the
                    Mexican people of the accomplishments of the Commission. The Mexican
                    Commissioners and Government officials, including the President of the Republic,
                    feel that the Commission has been a success. Their prime interest has rested in
                    the completion of the 1944 Minimum Program. After all the work and effort which
                    our Government has given to this Commission, we should not be robbed of its
                    richest fruits by our failure to give priorities to the two remaining projects
                    of the 1944 Minimum Program, the Celanese and the Baz Textile projects. It would
                    not be keeping the faith with the two Presidents if everything possible is not
                    done to bring the work of the Commission to the most successful and beneficial
                    conclusion possible. Under the circumstances, the Department is asked to lend
                    its most potent assistance in aiding the Commission to obtain the two priorities
                    in question and, thus, conclude successfully its work.<note n="56"
                        xml:id="d1191fn56">
                        <p>In a letter of December 6, 1944, the Secretary of State requested supply
                            assistance from the War Production Board for the Celanese and the Baz
                            Textile projects. In his reply of December 28, Mr. J. A. Krug, Chairman,
                            War Production Board, explained to the Secretary of State his inability
                            to assign priority ratings to these two projects, but assured him that
                            efforts were being made through textile manufacturers to give these
                            requests special preference among unrated orders. (812.24/12–2844).</p>
                        <p>For the concluding exchange of letters concerning the Commission between
                            Presidents Roosevelt and Avila Camacho, both dated January 20, 1945, and
                            for text of the final report of the Commission, dated January 1945, see
                            Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 4, 1945,
                            pp. 155 ff.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lockett</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy<lb/>for Economic Affairs</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
