<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="1190" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1190">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.50/10–644</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The President of Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Avila Camacho</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico City</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-06">September 6,
                                1944</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I take great pleasure
                            in acknowledging receipt of your kind letter of May 11 last which was to
                            have been delivered to me by Mr. Donald M. Nelson, Chairman of the War
                            Production Board, who, because of the commission which you decided to
                            entrust to him in China,<note n="55" xml:id="d1190fn55">A confidential
                                mission involving the survey of China’s war-production potential and
                                assistance in establishing a Chinese War Production Board,
                                preparatory to the stepping up of major military operations in the
                                Far East.</note> was obliged to postpone his visit to this
                            capital.</p>
                        <p>Considering the exceedingly high opinion which I, as well as my immediate
                            collaborators, have formed of the notable personality of Mr. Nelson, I
                            trust that, upon his return from China, you will decide to reiterate
                            your recommendation that he come to Mexico, since I am firmly convinced
                            that his visit will be truly beneficial to the development of economic
                            ties between our two countries.</p>
                        <p>In regard to these, I am sincerely pleased that our opinions regarding
                            the work of the Mexican-American Commission for Economic Cooperation
                            coincide. Like you, I am convinced that this organization—interpreting,
                            with a realistic spirit, the plans which, on this subject, we formulated
                            in complete agreement when I had the pleasure of deceiving you in
                            Monterrey—has realized a magnificent work which <pb facs="1224" n="1210" xml:id="pg_1210"/> makes it possible to view with optimism its
                            labors on behalf of commercial intercourse between our two
                            republics.</p>
                        <p>I desire, at the same time, to take this opportunity to congratulate you,
                            in your capacity as Commander in Chief of the American armed forces, for
                            the splendid victories which they have obtained not only in Europe but
                            also in the Pacific, and that not only correspond to the justice of the
                            cause of the United States but also are a clear demonstration of the
                            decisive manner in which the American nation is defending the most noble
                            principles of our civilization.</p>
                        <p>With my best wishes for the growing prosperity of the United States and
                            for your personal well-being, I take pleasure in assuring you of my
                            unchanging friendship.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Avila Camacho</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>