<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="1204" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1204">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">612.116/9–2044</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 6283</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-20">September 20,
                                1944</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: …</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>If you perceive no objection you may, in your discretion as to time and
                            circumstances, discuss with the Minister of Foreign Affairs and with the
                            President this Government’s concern at the apparently’ irreconcilable
                            attitude of Mr. Suárez and officials of his Ministry toward the matter
                            of easing international economic controls, and express the hope that a
                            way will be found for Mexico to cooperate fully in giving effect to the
                            foregoing principles.</p>
                        <p>The Department views with considerable concern the fact that the Mexican
                            Government has, for the purpose of controlling imports of <pb facs="1245" n="1231" xml:id="pg_1231"/> a single commodity, decided
                            to bring into effect at this time the decree of April 15 providing for
                            the control of imports into Mexico.<note n="83" xml:id="d1204fn83">On
                                July 27, 1944, the Ministry of Finance and Public Credit published
                                in the <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi> Circular No. 309–2–82,
                                listing hog lard as merchandise subject to the import restrictions
                                authorized by the decree signed April 15, as published in the <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi> on May 12
                                (612.116/8–344).</note> Now that the decree has been made effective,
                            presumably it will be utilized more readily for the control of other
                            imports. It is hoped that the Finance Minister will, in accordance with
                            his informal agreement with you, as mentioned in despatch no. 18369 of
                            June 24, consult with you before placing additional import controls in
                            effect, with a view to ascertaining whether other means of solving
                            current problems may be found. Favorable results of consultation are of
                            course somewhat doubtful because of the attitude toward economic
                            controls evidenced by the Finance Minister and his associates.</p>
                        <p>The application of import controls to lard, and the imminent institution
                            of additional controls, is most discouraging in view of the efforts
                            which this Government has made to make products of various kinds in
                            short supply in the United States available to Mexico with a view to
                            assisting the Mexican Government to provide Mexican consumers with
                            larger quantities of goods at lower prices, and to control its current
                            inflationary problems. A continuing trend in that direction will
                            undoubtedly react unfavorably in further consideration of efforts by
                            this Government to assist the Mexican Government in its general supply
                            problems.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>A. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Berle, Jr</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>