<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Paraguay ( (Frost) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="1385"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1385">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">834.6363/209</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Paraguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Frost</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1913</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Asunción</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-21">March 21,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received March 29.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform the Department that
                    Mr. H. A. Metzger, a representative of the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey,
                    has recently visited Paraguay and has made formal application of the Government
                    for permission to send into this country a geologic exploration party. Mr.
                    Metzger’s request has been based upon the fact that the exclusive exploration
                    rights given by the Paraguayan Government to the Union Oil Company have now
                    expired. In this connection, I wish to refer the Department to the Embassy’s
                    various telegrams regarding the activities of the representatives of the Union
                    Oil Company of California in Paraguay and to my two despatches Nos. 1523 of
                    November 12, 1943, and 1624 of December 9, 1943.<note n="39" xml:id="d1385fn39"
                        >Neither printed.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1488" n="1474" xml:id="pg_1474"/>
                <p>It would appear very likely that Mr. Metzger who visited Paraguay several times
                    during 1943, in the interests of his company, learned in Buenos Aires that the
                    exclusive exploration rights granted the Union Oil Company have now expired
                    without this Government and the subject American company having come to any
                    definite exploitation agreement. Prior to his departure from Buenos Aires, Mr.
                    Metzger prepared a memorandum, a translation of which is attached to this
                    despatch as enclosure No. 1.<note n="41" xml:id="d1385fn41">Not printed.</note>
                    It is understood that this memorandum was forwarded by the Paraguayan Consul
                    General in Buenos Aires to President Morínigo in anticipation of Mr. Metzger’s
                    arrival in Asunción on March 9th. It was possible for Mr. Metzger to visit the
                    President on March 15th, at which time the memorandum was discussed and
                    reportedly the President indicated to Mr. Metzger his interest and suggested
                    that Metzger present a formal application to the Minister of Public Works. A
                    formal letter of application was, accordingly, prepared and delivered personally
                    by Mr. Metzger to the Minister of Public Works on March 17th. A translation of
                    this letter of application is attached to this despatch as enclosure No. 2.<note
                        n="41" xml:id="d1385fn42">Not printed.</note> The letter was signed by Mr.
                    William Kaser, the manager of the Asunción branch of the West India Oil Company,
                    purely as a matter of convenience and in anticipation of Mr. Metzger’s departure
                    before a formal acknowledgment and reply could be expected. At the suggestion of
                    the Minister of Public Works, Mr. Metzger also visited the Minister of Finance
                    on March 18th, verbally reviewing his conversations with the President and with
                    the Minister of Public Works.</p>
                <p>In conversations with a representative of this Mission, Mr. Metzger explained
                    that his company, the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, has no desire
                    whatsoever of infringing upon any prior claim or right which the Union Oil
                    Company may have in this country. He has reportedly stated to President Morínigo
                    and the Ministers of Public Works and Finance that his company believes it to be
                    to the advantage of this country to not grant exclusive exploration rights to
                    one organization but rather negotiate with and possibly conclude exploitation
                    contracts for definite areas with different organizations. This position as held
                    by Mr. Metzger as a representative of the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey
                    would seem to be in strict keeping with the policy established by the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger has stated that his conversations with the Minister of Public Works
                    were highly satisfactory and it is expected that a reply to the application for
                    exploration permission will be forwarded to the Asunción office of the West
                    India Oil Company late this week, probably on Thursday, March 23rd. Mr. Metzger
                    will by that time <pb facs="1489" n="1475" xml:id="pg_1475"/> have returned to
                    Buenos Aires but if the reply is satisfactory he expects to send at least one
                    geologist from the Buenos Aires headquarters of his company to Paraguay and
                    presumably he will suggest that several other qualified geologists be sent
                    immediately from the United States.</p>
                <p>I have gained the impression that at least for the time being the negotiations
                    between the Paraguayan Government and the Union Oil Company have reached a
                    stalemate. Mr. Chester Cassel is still in Asunción representing the Union Oil
                    Company, but there is some possibility that he may return to the United States
                    in the near future, particularly in view of the fact that while the Paraguayan
                    Government accepted, in principle, Mr. Rubel’s invitation that three Paraguayans
                    visit Los Angeles, this invitation is now said to have been refused by two of
                    the intended guests, the Minister of Public Works and Dr. Carlos Pedretti, the
                    President of the Bank of the Republic. It would appear likely, therefore, that
                    the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey may be permitted to send an exploration
                    party into Paraguay under the conditions described in the letter of application
                    dated March 17th (enclosure No. 2). Of particular interest has been the
                    statement of Mr. Metzger that if the Paraguayan Government feels that it has a
                    prior commitment with the Union Oil Company in so far as the Chaco territory is
                    concerned, this will not prejudice the proposal for the new exploration party.
                    Mr. Metzger indicated that from his casual knowledge of the country superficial
                    signs are more encouraging in the areas east of the Paraguay river and he stated
                    that his company would be willing to confine its work to the east of the river
                    sections and would be perfectly willing to leave the entire Chaco to the Union
                    Oil Company.</p>
                <p>I shall not fail to let the Department know as developments occur, particularly
                    in view of the fact that this application on the part of the Standard Oil
                    Company of New Jersey would appear to bear promise of the realization of the
                    policy which the Department has established as regards petroleum exploration
                    work.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wesley Frost</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
