<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Peru ( (White) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1447</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1447</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-06T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-06T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064651"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Import control</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-06T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-06T17:00:00-05:00" n="1447"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1447">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">823.24/7–644: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Peru</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">White</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-06T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >July 6, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 12—8 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–651. Reference Embassy’s telegram Nos. 862 and 881 of June 28 tad July 3,<note
                        n="95" xml:id="d1447fn95">Neither printed.</note> respectively, regarding
                    the Peruvian import control project.</p>
                <p>The following supplementary information concerning the subject is being forwarded
                    in view of the Department’s interest and the importance of the subject:</p>
                <p>Statements by Finance Minister East, representatives of the Chamber of Commerce
                    and prominent businessmen indicate that the leading importers have convinced the
                    Finance Ministry and its counselors that the imposition of a comprehensive
                    import licensing program at this time is detrimental and unnecessary.</p>
                <p>The representatives of the Chamber of Commerce and businessmen energetically
                    protest against revealing the details of their import “business to a public
                    office where the information is available to competitors and insist that under
                    the prevailing conditions in Peru the Government is not justified in dictating
                    what or how much an importer shall acquire abroad. They have also referred to
                    the decision of the Finance Ministry as diametrically opposed to the principle
                    of free trade toward which the Allied and associated nations are striving, and
                    emphasized the fact that the Ministry’s decision is especially inopportune at
                    the very moment when the nations carrying the burden of the war are endeavoring
                    to remove restrictions.</p>
                <p>The France Minister, having stated at the beginning that the control would be
                    mild and would take into consideration all legitimate interests, has experienced
                    no embarrassment in acceding to the majority <pb facs="1556" n="1542"
                        xml:id="pg_1542"/> of opinion prevailing among business men. He had prepared
                    a communiqué for publication in the newspapers of July 4th or 5th announcing
                    that importers would be required to submit to the Ministry only notices, which
                    might also be termed applications, showing the quantities, values, etc. of
                    merchandise ordered abroad. There would be two copies, one of which would be
                    stamped immediately and returned to the importer who could forward his order
                    forthwith. The Peruvian diplomatic and consular officers abroad would not
                    intervene in any way—all administrative action would be taken in Lima.
                    Representatives of the Chamber of Commerce and businessmen explained that this
                    decision on the part of the Finance Minister was made in order to avoid a
                    protest meeting which had been announced by the Chamber of Commerce, to be
                    followed, if necessary, by direct appeal to President Prado. The same
                    representatives reported they would be satisfied with this simplified form if
                    their continued efforts to abolish the whole plan are unsuccessful. However,
                    they are still working toward that objective, and Mr. East’s failure to release
                    the communiqué for publication on the 4th, 5th, 6th or 7th of July indicates
                    they may be making some progress.</p>
                <p>The subject has been discussed several times with the Commercial Secretary of the
                    British Embassy and the Canadian Government Trade Commissioner who report that
                    British and Canadian businessmen also have protested against every type of
                    import control which is not absolutely necessary. They stated that the
                    authorities in London and Ottawa have not replied to their reports which were
                    sent out simultaneously with the Embassy’s telegram No. 782, dated June 13, 11
                    a.m., 1944. This leads them to the conclusion that the British and Canadian
                    Governments are opposed to the scheme, or at least prefer to withhold comments
                    on the subject. In the absence of instructions they describe themselves as in
                    full agreement with the Department and this Embassy.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">White</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
