<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Diplomatic Representatives in the American
                    Republics Except Argentina</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="1457"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1457">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 RP/3</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives in the American Republics
                            Except Argentina</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-07">December 7,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: During the past years this Government has
                    inaugurated many programs directed at implementation of economic warfare against
                    the Axis in the American republics. One such program, which to some extent has
                    overlapped the matter of Proclaimed List and related questions, has been the
                    program for replacement of Axis economic interests throughout the other American
                    republics. As you are aware, the objective of this program has been to encourage
                    the development of local controls and by this method to cut off those spearheads
                    of the Axis political-economic structure which have been responsible for
                    espionage, sabotage, and other less spectacular but equally dangerous activities
                    which characterized Axis operations in the years since the advent of Nazi
                    power.</p>
                <p>These spearheads of Axis economic power have most often been enterprises in
                    fields where technical skill was necessary and where dependence upon German
                    supplies was marked. Implementation of our campaign against these companies has
                    therefore made it both necessary and desirable to offer technical assistance,
                    managerial help and supplies from American companies, within the limits of the
                    war effort. Further, the Third Meeting of the Ministers of Foreign Affairs at
                    Rio de Janeiro<note n="9" xml:id="d1457fn9">For correspondence concerning the
                        Meeting, see <ref target="frus1942v05#pg_6">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>,
                            pp. 6</ref> ff.; see also Pan American Union, Congress and Conference
                        Series No. 36: <hi rend="italic">Report on the Third Meeting of the
                            Ministers of Foreign Affairs of the American Republics, Rio de Janeiro,
                            January 15–28, 1942</hi> (Washington, 1942).</note> and the
                    Inter-American Conference on Systems of Economic and Financial Control at
                        Washington<note n="10" xml:id="d1457fn10">Concerning this Conference, held
                        June 30–July 10, 1942, see <ref target="frus1942v05#pg_58">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 58</ref> ff.; see also Pan American
                        Union, Congress and Conference Series No. 39; <hi rend="italic">Final Act of
                            the Inter-American Conference on Systems of Economic and Financial
                            Control</hi> (Washington, 1942).</note> have made it clear that the
                    United States would assist the other American republics in the implementation of
                    the local control measures which might be adopted, both by offering technical
                    and managerial assistance and by making available certain financial
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>It has been recognized, however, that it would be highly undesirable to allow
                    economic warfare to become economic penetration, and to substitute domination by
                    the United States for domination by the Axis. It has been the Department’s
                    consistent policy that the local controls should be used by the other American
                    republics in such a <pb facs="1568" n="1554" xml:id="pg_1554"/> way as both to
                    eliminate the Axis spearheads and to take advantage of the opportunity thus
                    presented to establish nationalized industries which would be beneficial to the
                    local economy and in which local nationals would have the greater interest. For
                    this reason, the Department’s previous instructions have emphasized that
                    American participation in the reorganization of these firms should be limited to
                    a minority financial participation or a management fee contract. Moreover,
                    consistent with this policy that economic warfare measures should not be used to
                    achieve American domination of these industries, the Department has at all times
                    discussed the general principles underlying the replacement program with other
                    governments having an interest in the matter, particularly with the British.</p>
                <p>In this connection, it has been recognized by all parties that implementation of
                    economic warfare measures at the present time requires, to a large extent, the
                    use of United States companies. It has been recognized that use of these
                    companies does not imply any intention to bar desirable companies which are
                    nationals of other countries. In recent discussions which have taken place in
                    Washington between members of the British Embassy and officials of the
                    Department, it has been stated to the Department that the Ministry of Economic
                    Warfare is “in agreement with the general principles which they understand that
                    the State Department are pursuing in carrying out the replacement of enemy firms
                    in Latin America.”</p>
                <p>It is highly desirable that this general agreement should be fostered by
                    consultations between the representatives of the two governments on matters of
                    mutual interest. It is, of course, understood that close consultation between
                    American and British missions is presently the rule in all countries in
                    connection with listing matters. It is understood, also, that replacement
                    matters are closely related to and often directly grow out of the operations of
                    the Proclaimed and Statutory Lists. The Department believes that such
                    consultation between the American and the British missions on matters of
                    replacement policy which are of mutual interest is desirable, and wishes to
                    confirm the understanding on this matter which, it is believed, already
                    exists.</p>
                <p>It will be understood that such consultation need not affect the manner in which
                    the purely commercial functions of the missions are presently carried out.
                    Moreover, it is not intended that the missions should discuss matters of
                    commercial arrangements with American companies arising out of replacement
                    programs in such detail as to violate any confidences of American business
                    concerns. Rather, such matters as general programs, the nature of the
                    arrangements being made to insure a freely competitive market, and so forth,
                    would be proper subjects for consultation.</p>
                <pb facs="1569" n="1555" xml:id="pg_1555"/>
                <p>The Department will be glad to receive such comments on the subject of this
                    instruction as the missions may care to make.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
