<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Peru ( (White) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1476</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1476</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recxmLIT5ymFOK58D" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Commodity Credit
                        Corporation</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="1476"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1476">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">823.51/1550</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Peru</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">White</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 285</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-11">May 11,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received May 20.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit herewith a
                        memorandum<note n="53" xml:id="d1476fn53">Not printed.</note> reviewing the
                    principal topics in the sixth meeting on the dollar debt discussions being
                    carried on by Finance Minister East and Mr. James G. Rogers, representing the
                    Foreign Bondholders Protective Council, which took place on May 8 at 4:30 p.m.
                    in the Central Reserve Bank.</p>
                <p>Preceding despatches of the series are cited as follows for convenient reference:
                    Nos. 87, 143, 185 and 240,<note n="54" xml:id="d1476fn54">Despatches 87 and 240
                        not printed.</note> dated April 17, April 24, April 27 and May 5, 1944,
                    respectively.</p>
                <p>Despatches Nos. 239<note n="53" xml:id="d1476fn57">Not printed.</note> and
                        252,<note n="55" xml:id="d1476fn55">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1522">p. 1522</ref>.</note>
                    dated May 5 and May 8, 1944, respectively, pertaining to the Finance Minister’s
                    insistence on renewing the Overall Metals and Minerals Agreement, contain
                    appropriate supplementary information on the subject.</p>
                <p>As had been anticipated in the despatches described above, Mr. East concluded his
                    presentation with a proposal to reduce the principal of 92,602,584 dollars to an
                    equal number of soles or, in other words, to pay one sol for one dollar.…</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Though some argue that the Peruvians are more friendly with the British, Italians
                    and Japanese than with the Americans, citing in evidence the fact that the
                    Peruvians served the guano loan and paid the British in cash for the Marconi
                    communications system and the Paita dock, which were taken over by the Peruvian
                    Government from the British, that payment in cash was made to the Italians upon
                    expropriation of the Caproni airplane factory, and that payment of the 1940
                    Japanese claim for damages was effected promptly, I do not believe that this is
                    a correct deduction from Peruvian performances in regard to our various claims.
                    Many reliable American business men of long experience in Peru consider that
                    many, perhaps most, Peruvians feel closer to the United States than to any other
                    non-Latin nation.</p>
                <p>It seems more probable to conclude that the Peruvians were attentive to the
                    representations of those nations, because all of the interested persons and
                    officials seemed to be acting harmoniously as though they believed in
                    reciprocity of treatment. In other words, they knew where the governments of
                    those countries stood.</p>
                <pb facs="1593" n="1579" xml:id="pg_1579"/>
                <p>Their failure to know the true policy and attitude of the United States is not
                    hard to discover, particularly during the last three or four years. But even in
                    1936, 1937 and 1938 Peru’s sugar quota was increased after clamorous
                    demonstrations by the Peruvians, without requiring any conditions favorable to
                    the United States except that we did acquire a commercial commodity which could
                    be used. There is no effort at bargaining of the sort which was then and always
                    is expected by the Peruvians.</p>
                <p>Is it to be wondered at that Messrs. East and Dasso, to name only two, upon
                    various occasions have manifested evidence of their inability to determine where
                    we stand? Practically all of the following examples have been brought to our
                    attention by Peruvians at one time or another: Messrs. Dasso and East have
                    advised against loans and advances to Peru, but Americans of importance have not
                    only recommended but have insisted that they be accepted; the Commodity Credit
                    Corporation has made efforts to purchase canned fish and the Coordinator’s
                    representative has discouraged the exportation thereof; American property has
                    been expropriated with the support of the Rubber Development Corporation while
                    the Embassy opposed such action; the Embassy, in administering the conservation
                    program of the Foreign Economic Administration, has refused to certify import
                    recommendations for certain merchandise, even when the Peruvian governmental
                    departments have offered to pay cash, and the Lend-Lease authorities have
                    supplied the same material without cost to Peru; the United States Commercial
                    Company, at least toward the beginning, encouraged flax production and the
                    Coordinator’s Food Mission discouraged it; the Embassy pressed for the
                    liquidation of Welsch y Cia. and Radio Internacional, and the Coordinator’s
                    Office issued propaganda through Radio Internacional simultaneously with
                    advertisements by the Proclaimed List firm Welsch y Cia.; officers in Washington
                    insisted upon matching clauses to provide better conditions for mine workers
                    when even the Peruvian Director of Labor considered the program inadvisable; in
                    like manner they insisted upon a labor clause in the Overall Metals and Minerals
                    Agreement as well as in private agreements when the Peruvian Government
                    prohibited the former and discouraged the latter; the Coordinator’s Food Mission
                    has gone on record with the statement the Peruvians “…<note n="56"
                        xml:id="d1476fn56">Omissions indicated in the original despatch.</note>
                    simply are not capable of understanding why we would be niggardly in our support
                    of an undertaking which we initiated.…”; upon different occasions
                    representatives of the United States Government have insisted on spending every
                    cent of an appropriation because, among other considerations, if unused in whole
                    or part it would adversely reflect on those who made the estimate and also <pb
                        facs="1594" n="1580" xml:id="pg_1580"/> make it more difficult to convince
                    Congress of the need of consecutive appropriations for the purpose.</p>
                <p>There are other illustrations of this general category which, together with the
                    foregoing, may be annotated or omitted, depending upon whether we prefer or
                    dislike to contemplate some of the questions which come up in the minds of the
                    Peruvians.</p>
                <p>While presumably no permanent injury has been inflicted upon Peruvian-American
                    relations as a result of the foregoing instances of inconsistency, it would
                    appear that these relations have been less smooth and less beneficial to both
                    parties, both at present and in the long run, than they would have been had all
                    of the departments and agencies of the American Government performed with
                    precision as a single unit, without expressing contradictory opinions and
                    policies. These last have confused the Peruvians in recent years and at the same
                    time enabled them to escape their obligations and avoid reciprocity. We can get
                    adequate consideration for the debt problems and other American claims only when
                    the United States is able to unite its interests, demands and favors in a single
                    program, centrally executed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">White</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
