<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Secretary of War ( (Stimson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="1492"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1492">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">833.24/1204</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Secretary of War</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stimson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-14">April 14,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: You will recall that in my
                    letter of January 17 and Mr. Stettinius’ communication of February 12<note
                        n="22" xml:id="d1492fn22">Neither printed.</note> the <pb facs="1612"
                        n="1598" xml:id="pg_1598"/> hope was expressed that the War Department would
                    give sympathetic attention to the possibility of delivering to the Government of
                    Uruguay an additional quantity of the military equipment requested by that
                    Government under the provisions of the Lend-Lease Agreement concluded in
                    1942.</p>
                <p>Since then the Uruguayan authorities have renewed their requests. The Uruguayan
                    Ambassador has submitted to me, under instructions from his Government, a note
                    dated April 3,<note n="25" xml:id="d1492fn25">Not printed.</note> a copy in
                    translation of which is enclosed, stating that it is urgently necessary to equip
                    Uruguay adequately in order to enable that country to assist the United Nations
                    in maintaining political stability in this hemisphere.</p>
                <p>I have reached the conclusion that for important reasons of policy it is
                    essential to render appropriate assistance to the Government of Uruguay which,
                    notwithstanding the immediate neighborhood of a stronger nation in which
                    activity opposed to the United Nations and to hemisphere defense continues to
                    exist, has maintained a consistently friendly and cooperative attitude. In view
                    of this situation I should greatly appreciate it if the War Department would
                    give prompt and favorable consideration to the Uruguayan request with a view to
                    furnishing such military equipment as can be used to best advantage by that
                    country.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
