<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-01-13T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-01-13T13:00:00-05:00" n="248" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d248">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">835.50/139: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Armour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-01-13T15:00:00-03:00">January
                                    13, 1944—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 7:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>105. Personal for the Secretary. I have carefully studied the various
                            approaches to Argentine policy outlined in your telegram 39, January 8,
                            11 p.m. and I venture to suggest that in addition to the three courses
                            of action mentioned therein, the following be considered: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>A statement along the lines mentioned in my telegram 99,
                                    January 12, 9 p.m.<note n="54" xml:id="d248fn54">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_229">p.
                                            229</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>An export embargo to be placed on shipments from Great Britain
                                    and the United States to Argentina except for consignments to
                                    industries directly engaged in war effort. Brazil to continue
                                    embargo on rubber and add pig iron; Chile to embargo sulphur,
                                    pig iron and copper; Venezuela, Peru and Ecuador to discontinue
                                    petroleum shipments (these shipments are mainly controlled by
                                    Shell and Standard interests). Sweden to discontinue shipment of
                                    steel products and other materials essential to Argentine
                                    industry.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>It is felt that this policy would effectively disrupt
                                    Argentine industry within a period from 3 to 6 months and have a
                                    profound effect on present Argentine prosperity. It is, of
                                    course, an extreme step and as I have stated before while I feel
                                    that Argentine Government would find it impossible to refuse to
                                    sell meat or export surpluses of fats and oils, linseed, wheat
                                    and quebracho in retaliation for any economic sanctions adopted
                                    by the United Nations an alternative policy exists. This would
                                    be to embargo shipments of all products essential to Argentine
                                    economy from Great Britain and the United States along with the
                                    other suggestions mentioned in the first paragraph of number 2
                                    above.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>American ships to call at Argentine ports only for outbound
                                    cargo; British ships to follow course resulting from decision
                                    made in connection with number 2 above; Flota Mercante<note n="55" xml:id="d248fn55">Argentine Government-controlled
                                        shipping organization.</note> to continue if desired to
                                    handle northbound movement of products.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Consignee control to be handled from Washington and
                                    certificate of necessity system in Argentina eliminated. This
                                    will be necessary under whatever policy is adopted since present
                                    system has no elasticity.</item>
                                <pb facs="0305" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>All procurement except meat, eggs, sunflower seed oil and
                                    peanuts (which are covered by government to government
                                    agreements) to be confined (as is actually the case at present)
                                    to private purchases and every effort made to restrict purchases
                                    in Argentina to products which are essential to the war
                                    effort.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Orders to be issued by both American and British Governments
                                    to the effect that all statements emanating from official
                                    sources and referring to Argentina should be cleared through
                                    Foreign Office and State Department to preclude further
                                    references by procurement officials to the importance of
                                    Argentina in supply picture. Cooperation of press associations
                                    should also be sought to prevent transmission of similar
                                    statements appearing in such internationally known publications
                                    as the <hi rend="italic">London Financial News</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Wall Street Journal</hi>.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>The American and British Ambassadors to be recalled and the
                                    staffs of both Missions reduced to absolute minimum consistent
                                    with need for observation and reporting.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Argentina to be subjected to strict neutral controls covering
                                    shipping, communications, and finance by both Great Britain and
                                    the United States.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Whatever policy is decided upon I believe that the economic functions of
                            the Embassy should be transferred to Washington insofar as may be
                            possible. The present situation wherein the Embassy is expected to
                            request favors of this Government one day and take punitive action the
                            next is untenable.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Armour</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>