<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="296"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d296">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 E. W./8–344: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-03">August 3,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received August 3—2:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6191. Following is official Hansard text of passage concerning Argentina and
                    post-war policy towards neutrals which Mr. Churchill included in his speech in
                    House of Commons yesterday: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In the Mediterranean theater of war I mentioned that we have recently
                            had the satisfaction of welcoming as our comrades in arms <pb
                                facs="0352" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/> a finely equipped
                            expeditionary force from Brazil, and there are more legions to come from
                            this great land which for a long time has been rendering valuable war
                            service to the Allied cause both in the air and on the sea. As an
                            Englishman, I may be pardoned at this moment for thinking of another
                            South American country with which we have had close ties of friendship
                            and mutual interest since her birth to liberty and independence. I refer
                            to Argentina. We all feel deep regret and also anxiety as friends of
                            Argentina that in this testing time for nations she has not seen fit to
                            declare herself wholeheartedly, unmistakably and with no reserve or
                            qualification upon the side of freedom and has chosen to dally with the
                            evil, and not only with the evil but with the losing side. I trust that
                            my remarks will be noted, because this is a very serious war. It is not
                            like some small wars in the past where all could be forgotten and
                            forgiven. Nations must be judged by the part they play. Not only
                            belligerents but neutrals will fold that their position in the world
                            cannot remain entirely unaffected by the part they have chosen to play
                            in the crisis of the war.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
