<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Argentina ( (Reed) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d343</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">343</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-06T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recIMvblVMopWEA1k" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019002541"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Anti-Semitic</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-06T16:00:00-05:00" n="343"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d343">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.20235/7–644: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Reed</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-06T18:00:00-03:00"
                            >July 6, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 10:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1739. Following comments submitted on points enumerated your 1079, July 3, 7
                        p.m.<note n="45" xml:id="d343fn45">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_279">p. 279</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>(5) (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) All data on arrests of Axis spies available to
                    Embassy have been fully reported. Only the six spies in Napp case have been
                    “brought before the courts”. Four of them were sentenced on June 21 (Embassy’s
                    1583 June 21),<note n="46" xml:id="d343fn46">Not printed.</note> a year and a
                    half after they were first denounced by the Embassy; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                    of the other persons whom Argentine authorities consider to be Axis spies,
                    Embassy has official knowledge of those named in official communiqués only (see
                    Embassy’s despatch 13955, February 21, telegram 585, February 29, 8 p.m. and
                    despatch 14520, April 18).<note n="47" xml:id="d343fn47">Telegram 585 and
                        despatch 14520 not printed.</note> It is believed the Argentine memorandum
                    referred to in telegram under reference affords opportunity to request of
                    Argentine Government official lists of (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) person
                    arrested for Axis espionage, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) fugitives and(<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) those still being held. This would provide something
                    more substantial to go on in commenting on <pb facs="0404" n="390"
                        xml:id="pg_390"/> Argentine assertion that many such persons have [been]
                    brought to book.</p>
                <p>In the meanwhile, there is submitted herewith an approximate tabulation of
                    espionage arrests, representing a considered evaluation of all information
                    available through both official and confidential sources and prepared with
                    assistance of Legal Attaché. It should be borne in mind that these lists include
                    only such individuals as could properly be termed espionage agents or legitimate
                    suspects. Diplomats and other Axis Embassy officials, Argentine nationalists and
                    casual suspects rounded up for questioning have been omitted: (<hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi>) persons denounced by American and/or British Embassies: 60; persons
                    so denounced, reported arrested: 24; persons so arrested, reported released: 9;
                    still held: 15; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) persons denounced by American and/or
                    British Embassies, wanted by Argentine Government but still fugitive: 5; (<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) persons not denounced by Embassies, reported arrested
                    at instance of Argentine Government: 28; persons so arrested, reported released:
                    8; still held: 20; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) totals: arrested for espionage:
                    52; released: 17; still held: 35; fugitives: 5. Among the 60 persons denounced
                    are, of course, included the 25 individuals named in the Embassy’s memorandum to
                    the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of February 9 (see Embassy’s despatch No. 13866,
                    February 12). The remainder were denounced on various opportunities by the
                    British. In this connection, it will be recalled that at time of submitting
                    above mentioned list this Embassy and British Embassy made it known to Argentine
                    authorities that it would be perfectly acceptable for Argentina to take credit
                    for arrests if it wished, and that American and British Governments did not
                    intend to make their memoranda or information which they contained public.</p>
                <p>Since cessation of official relations subsequent to first wave of arrests,
                    Argentine Government has been proceeding largely on its own initiative, and it
                    is evident that few new developments have occurred. Any information obtained by
                    Embassy has been acquired with difficulty by confidential means, for which
                    reason it is not possible to appraise effectiveness of Argentine Government’s
                    action. Nevertheless, although German spy ring is by no means broken, as clearly
                    shown by certain indications known to Department, the Legal and Military
                    Attachés and British feel that German espionage in Argentina has suffered a
                    decided setback.</p>
                <p>Suspension of <hi rend="italic">La Fronda</hi> fully reported by despatches
                    15113, June 16 and 15141, June 20.<note n="48" xml:id="d343fn48">Neither
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>6. Argentine Government officials have on several occasions declared
                    discrimination against or ill treatment of Jews not permitted, however Jews
                    continue to feel uneasy in view of general orientation of <pb facs="0405"
                        n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> present regime. Authorities appear to have done
                    nothing to restrain anti-Semitic propaganda in <hi rend="italic">Clariquada
                        Cabildo</hi> and other periodicals. As far as can be ascertained those
                    responsible for acts in Entre Rios have not been punished.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Reed</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
