<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Argentina ( (Reed))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="368"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d368">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.35112A/6–3044</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Reed</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 6351</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-16">December 16,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary of State refers to the Embassy’s despatches no. 14974 of June 6,
                    1944 and no. 15244 of June 30, 1944,<note n="84" xml:id="d368fn84">Neither
                        printed.</note> concerning the ownership, control, and activities of
                    Transradio Internacional, Cía. Argentina de Telecomunicaciones, and encloses
                    herewith a copy of a memorandum<note n="85" xml:id="d368fn85">Not
                        printed.</note> containing the significant information in the Department’s
                    files with regard to this company.</p>
                <p>It will be noted from the enclosed memorandum that according to the Consortium
                    Agreements (<ref target="#pg_112">page 112</ref>), copies of which were
                    furnished the Embassy with instruction no. 5751 of May 9, 1944,<note n="85"
                        xml:id="d368fn88">Not printed.</note> the trust constituted by the
                    Agreements was to terminate on February 26, <pb facs="0423" n="409"
                        xml:id="pg_409"/> 1945, at which time the trustees were to distribute the
                    property equally among the four contracting parties.</p>
                <p>The Department is presently giving consideration to the advisability of
                    discussing with the appropriate officials of the United States member of the
                        Consortium,<note n="86" xml:id="d368fn86">Consortium Trust Affiliates,
                        composed in prewar days of British, American, French, German, and Italian
                        interests; controlled Transradio Internacional Argentina and Transradio
                        Internacional Chilena.</note> the Radio Corporation of America, the action
                    which is contemplated in February 1945 in the event that the original agreement
                    was not subsequently extended by the contracting parties. These discussions
                    might also refer to the arrangements with the general manager, the assistant
                    manager and the traffic manager of Transradio whereby these persons have
                    received substantial bonuses based directly on the company’s gross income.
                    Before doing so, however, the Department would appreciate receiving the
                    Embassy’s comments on the advisability of the proposed action and any additional
                    information concerning the activities of this company which has been received by
                    the Embassy subsequent to June 30, 1944. The Embassy’s suggestions as to any
                    other questions which it may be considered desirable to discuss with the Radio
                    Corporation of America, such as continued banking transactions by Transradio
                    with Proclaimed List banks, would also be appreciated.<note n="87"
                        xml:id="d368fn87">The trust constituted by agreement among the participants
                        in the Consortium was continued until the end of the war by action of the
                        majority interests in February 1945.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
