<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Bolivia ( (Woodward) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d493</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">493</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-06-27T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-06-27T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-27T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-27T16:00:00-05:00" n="493"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d493">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.24112 RP/6–2744: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Woodward</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">La Paz</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-27T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 27, 1944—5:00 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 5—2 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–292. Reference is made to the Department’s instruction No. 1049 under date of
                    October 4, 1943,<note n="44" xml:id="d493fn44">Not printed.</note> which
                    enclosed copies of notes exchanged <pb facs="0537" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/>
                    between the Department and the Bolivian Ambassador in Washington<note n="44a"
                        xml:id="d493fn44a">Notes dated September 16 and October 4, 1943, <ref
                            target="frus1943v05#pg_604">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 604</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1943v05#pg_605">605</ref>, respectively.</note> regarding
                    financial assistance to be extended by the Export-Import Bank of Washington in
                    connection with the replacement of Axis firms in Bolivia.</p>
                <p>This Embassy has every expectation that the question of the status of the notes
                    under reference and the question of financial assistance in connection with the
                    replacement of Axis firms will shortly be raised by the newly-recognized
                    Bolivian Government.</p>
                <p>In anticipation of the Bolivian Government’s raising the question, this Embassy
                    should greatly appreciate the Department’s reviewing the subject of financial
                    assistance in connection with the proposed replacement program with the
                    Export-Import Bank and informing it of the policy to be adopted in respect of
                        (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the status of the notes, and (<hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi>) the broad general question of financial assistance. The essential
                    question would seem to be whether the offer made to the Peñaranda Government
                    redounds to the benefit of the Villarroel Government in the event the latter
                    fulfils the necessary conditions enumerated in the Department’s note, or whether
                    the failure of the Peñaranda Government to fulfil the necessary conditions may
                    be asserted as a sufficient reason to consider the offer as having lapsed. Until
                    guidance on these questions has been received, the Embassy does not feel that it
                    is in any position to discuss the question of financial assistance and this may
                    delay the formulation of a method of implementing the proposed replacement
                    program as it is certain that the majority of the responsible members of the
                    Bolivian Government who are interested in the replacement program believe in the
                    necessity of financial assistance.</p>
                <p>As of possible assistance to the Department in reviewing this subject, the
                    following points are made: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It appears entirely possible for the Bolivian Government to execute an
                            effective replacement program without United States financial assistance
                            (see this Embassy’s telegram 515 of February 19, 1944), but it is highly
                            probable that it will not do so, unless concrete financial help is
                            provided by our Government.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Although no encouragement has been given to the present Bolivian
                            Government, it appears to assume that the offer of financial assistance
                            made to the Peñaranda Government will redound to its benefit. It
                            understands, of course, that certain conditions and standards prescribed
                            by the Bolivian Development Corporation must be met. If the conditions
                            and standards of the Development Corporation are met there is a very
                            strong possibility that an effective replacement program will be
                            executed.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The present Bolivian Government is in no position to accept or to
                            implement the Department’s offer of financial assistance and has done
                            nothing to implement the expropriatory features of the expropriation
                            decree-laws promulgated by it (see this Embassy’s despatch No. 3692
                            under date of May 8, 1944). If, however, the Department’s <pb
                                facs="0538" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/> offer is stated to apply to
                            the present Government, it is believed that there is a strong
                            possibility that the Government will sponsor in the Congress which will
                            evolve from the forthcoming Constitutional Convention in August the
                            legislation necessary to establish the legality of the expropriation of
                            Axis interests and to guarantee the repayment of such Export-Import Bank
                            credits as may be used to finance such expropriatory action.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Although a number of small Axis enterprises have been replaced on a
                            voluntary basis (which raises no legal problem and no problem of United
                            States financial assistance), it is very improbable that the large Axis
                            “spearheads” may be replaced in this manner. Firms such as Zeller de
                            Mozer y Cía (PL), Kyllmann, Bauer y Cía (PL), Juan Eisner y Cía (PL),
                            Schweitzer y Cía (PL), and Ferreteria Findel (PL) have already served
                            notice that they intend to resist expropriation and replacement. It
                            appears that the only method in which such large and entrenched firms
                            may be replaced is for them to be expropriated under legal process and
                            for their assets to be sold. It appears very unlikely that the Bolivian
                            Government will undertake such far-reaching action unless it has what it
                            terms as the “moral support and the concrete support of the United
                            States” in the form of some type of financial assistance.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Although conversations have not been held on the subject with the
                            Bolivian Development Corporation and will not be held until the
                            Department’s reply is received, it is believed that the Corporation is
                            willing to proceed to administer any Export-Import Bank credits extended
                            in connection with the proposed replacement program on the same basis as
                            formulated in the discussions held last year. It is known that Alberto
                            Crespo, president of the Corporation, believes the proposed replacement
                            program impossible of accomplishment without United States financial
                            assistance.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Embassy studies reveal that the “barebones” value of Axis assets
                            encompassed within the proposed replacement program considerably exceed
                            US$4,000,000.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodward</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
