<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Bolivia ( (McLaughlin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d495</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">495</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-21T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-21T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-21T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-21T18:00:00-05:00" n="495"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d495">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.24112RP/7–2044: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">McLaughlin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-21T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 21, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>765. Reference your telegram no. 1405, July 20, 7:00 p.m. The Department is
                    clearing, in consultation with the Eximbank an instruction with respect to
                    financial assistance and the replacement and expropriation program. The subject
                    of financing is being discussed with the Eximbank, and the detailed instruction
                    expanding the following points is expected to be sent within the next few days.
                    In the interim, the Department’s views are as follows.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Department considers it highly desirable that Bolivia proceed to carry
                        out the expropriation and replacement of the important Axis firms. The
                        Department has believed it to be the intention of the Bolivians to take such
                        a step after recognition.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The procedures previously suggested in the Embassy’s telegram no. 515,
                        February 19, 1944, with regard to a method of financing should be suggested
                        to the Bolivians as desirable and feasible. The Department feels, as was
                        indicated in the Department’s airgram A–545, June 15, 1943,<note n="45"
                            xml:id="d495fn45">
                            <ref target="frus1943v05#pg_598">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 598</ref>.</note> that a financing
                        procedure involving a double financing operation would be highly
                        undesirable.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>With reference to the Embassy’s airgram no. A–292, June 27, 1944, and to
                        point no. 1 therein, the Embassy is authorized to state that this Government
                        is willing to renew the assurances contained in the exchange of notes of
                        October, 1943, should the Embassy consider that such a statement would impel
                        the Bolivians to take action in connection with the replacement program. The
                        Embassy should note the conditions and limitations set forth in the exchange
                        of notes of October, 1943. The Department will inform the Embassy prior to
                        July 26 if Eximbank should feel that this previous commitment should not now
                        be again extended to the Bolivians.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>With reference to paragraph no. 3 of the Embassy’s airgram no. A–292, June
                        27, 1944, the Department feels that present Bolivian legislation is not
                        satisfactory to give clear title to a purchaser and therefore to serve as
                        the basis for an extension of credit. The Department feels that measures
                        should be taken by the Bolivians to prove both their ability and their
                        sincere desire to carry out a replacement program before negotiations
                        looking toward the establishment of any credits from the United States are
                        begun.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>An answer along the above lines may be made to inquiry by the Bolivians on
                        this question of financial assistance. It will be desirable, however, if the
                        Embassy’s answer is brief and general, and if the <pb facs="0540" n="526"
                            xml:id="pg_526"/> Embassy clearly explains that further detailed
                        instructions are expected shortly, after which fuller discussion may be had
                        with the Bolivians.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
