<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Diplomatic Representatives in the
                    American Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-20T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-20T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-20T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-20T18:00:00-05:00" n="57"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d57">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Consultation (4)/11–2044: Circular
                    telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives in the American
                            Republics</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-20T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >November 20, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>For your personal and confidential information there follows a summary of views
                    expressed to date by other American Republics with respect to meeting of Foreign
                    Ministers on war and post-war problems and Argentine request for meeting to
                    consider Argentine situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Bolivia</hi>. Will be guided by position adopted by Chile and
                    Paraguay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Brazil</hi>. Entirely approves United States position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>. Foreign Minister has expressed agreement with our
                    position and stressed point that any consideration of Argentine case should come
                    at conclusion and not at beginning of meeting of Foreign Ministers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Colombia</hi>. Colombian Government announced publicly on
                    October 31 that it favored acceptance of Argentine request. No reply yet to
                    Mexican proposals or to our memorandum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Costa Rica</hi>. Firmly opposed to acceptance of Argentine
                    request. No comment yet on Mexican proposals or our memorandum.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Cuba</hi>. Strongly approves our position, characterized by
                    Foreign Minister as “sound, rational and perfect.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Dominican Republic</hi>. Our Embassy reports that Dominican
                    Government will undoubtedly adopt our position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ecuador</hi>. Favors acceptance of Argentine proposal. No
                    reply yet to Mexican proposals or to our memorandum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>. Will support our position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Haiti</hi>. Will support our position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Honduras</hi>. Is in entire agreement that a meeting should be
                    held of the Foreign Ministers of American Republics which have cooperated in
                    war, in conformity with terms expressed in our memorandum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Nicaragua</hi>. In complete accord with our views.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>. In memorandum handed to chiefs of American
                    missions in Panama on November 16 the Foreign Minister proposed alternative
                    procedure both to Mexican proposals and to procedure suggested in our
                    memorandum. Panamanian proposal is that meeting of Foreign Ministers be
                    scheduled for indefinite date; that 15 days prior thereto the American Republics
                    consult to determine whether or not Argentina should be permitted to
                    participate; that if no unanimous affirmative decision is reached, consideration
                    of Argentine problem at meeting be confined to resolution expressing hope of
                    eventual reincorporation of Argentina in American family of nations and stating
                    conditions with which she must first comply. Foreign Minister agrees with
                    Padilla that open discussion of Argentine situation in meeting of ministers
                    would involve risk of dangerous dissension. Our Embassy reports that Foreign
                    Minister is making statement today to rectify press report that Panama favors
                    recognition of Farrell regime.<note n="46" xml:id="d57fn46">For an amplification
                        of this explanation, see telegram 641 from Panama, <hi rend="italic"
                            >infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Paraguay</hi>. Foreign Minister has expressed opposition to a
                    discussion of Argentine situation at a meeting of ministers, and has suggested
                    that an investigating committee representing the other American Republics be
                    empowered to visit Argentina to investigate situation on the spot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>. Foreign Office has indicated opposition to
                    discussion of Argentine situation at meeting of Foreign Ministers and general
                    support of United States position. No definitive reply as yet to Mexican
                    proposal or to our memorandum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Uruguay</hi>. Foreign Minister has informed our Embassy that
                    Uruguay favors meeting requested by Argentina. Has promised reply to our
                    memorandum within a few days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Venezuela</hi>. Originally concurred with Colombia in favoring
                    acceptance of Argentine request for meeting. After preliminary study of our
                    memorandum Foreign Minister considers our views not incompatible <pb facs="0072"
                        n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> with possible solution of Argentine problem. He
                    feels strongly that conversations on Argentine question should be continued and
                    no irrevocable decision be hastily taken even though conversations might be
                    prolonged.</p>
                <p>Mexican position is, of course, as stated in Department’s circulars of November
                    12, 6 p.m.,<note n="47" xml:id="d57fn47">Not printed, but see footnote 26, <ref
                            target="#pg_39">p. 39</ref>.</note> and November 16, 6 p.m.<note n="48"
                        xml:id="d57fn48">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Up to now we have proceeded slowly and carefully in order to avoid any appearance
                    of seeking to impose our views. The other American Republics have had every
                    opportunity to express their opinions and to suggest procedures. In stating our
                    own position we have emphasized an attitude of cooperation and avoided giving
                    the impression of intransigence. We now feel, however, that the time has come to
                    press our views directly and energetically in an effort to obtain general
                    agreement with the other American Republics on our position. This was the
                    purport of our circular telegraphic instruction of November 17, 3 p.m.<note
                        n="48" xml:id="d57fn49">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
