<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Chile ( (Bowers) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d694</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">694</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec2WdyKi8trpNQBA" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Refinery</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="694"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d694">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Chile/653</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 9693</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-12">May 12,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received May 23.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that negotiations for
                    the termination of the United States-Chilean agreement for the control of copper
                    exports have culminated successfully in accordance with the several instructions
                    from the Department, with particular reference to telegram No. 418 of April 10,
                    1944. There are enclosed<note n="40" xml:id="d694fn40">Enclosures mentioned in
                        this despatch not printed.</note> copies of the Embassy’s Note No. 2385 of
                    April 26, 1944 and of the Confidential Note from the Ministerio de Relaciones
                    Exteriores No. 26 of May 3, 1944, together with translation thereof. Also
                    enclosed are copies of instructions, in Spanish and English, by the Ministerio
                    de Economia y Comercio to the Consejo Nacional de Comercio Exterior outlining
                    special procedure to be followed in the issuance of export permits for copper
                    and copper base alloys to Argentina, and a letter from the Ministerio informing
                    the Embassy of instructions given to the Chilean diplomatic missions in the
                    other American republics to consult with our missions concerning the
                    desirability of proposed consignees before approving any certificates of
                    importation for Chilean copper.</p>
                <p>It should be noted that the exchange of notes provides only for outright
                    termination of the existing agreement, and that safeguards for future shipments
                    of copper from Chile, although collateral to the exchange of notes, have been
                    provided for in a less formal manner. The Embassy believed this segregation
                    advisable as the Chileans showed a disposition to modify the agreement rather
                    than cancel it completely on the theory that its existence could be used as a
                    springboard to a discussion in Washington of future marketing arrangements for
                    Chilean copper and copper manufactures. It was pointed out that any such
                    discussion would probably be better received once the subject agreement was in
                    the category of finished business.</p>
                <p>With regard to future shipments of copper, Chile proposes no quantitative
                    limitation of exports of copper manufactures and inasmuch as import
                    recommendations are required by the other American republics, it proposes to
                    have these authenticated by its diplomatic representations as a condition
                    precedent to the issuance of export permits in Santiago in which process our
                    missions will be consulted. Although the same procedure will be followed for
                    shipments of raw copper, there is less desire to approve its export.</p>
                <p>As instructed in the Department’s telegram under reference, the Embassy has
                    suggested to the Brazilian and the Uruguayan Ambassadors that diplomatic
                    representations might be in order to seek for <pb facs="0744" n="730"
                        xml:id="pg_730"/> Brazil and Uruguay, respectively, quotas of copper
                    refinery shapes representative of their minimum essential requirements, and our
                    missions in those countries have been so informed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bowers</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
