<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="80" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">810.24/554</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Statement of Policy of the State, War, and Navy
                                Departments and the Joint Chiefs of Staff Concerning the Supplying
                                of Lend-Lease Materials to the American Republics</hi><note n="11" xml:id="d80fn11">Sent under cover of a circular instruction dated
                                June 24, 1944, not printed, to the Chiefs of Mission in Chile,
                                Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba, Honduras, Haiti, Nicaragua, Peru,
                                Paraguay, Uruguay, Venezuela, Guatemala, Ecuador, El Salvador,
                                Dominican Republic, and Bolivia.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-24">June 24, 1944</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>(For the <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi> use and guidance of United
                            States representatives in conversations with representatives of the
                            other American republics in regard to procurement of material in the
                            United States. Not to be shown or quoted to representatives of the other
                            American republics.)</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The defensive phase of the war against the Axis has passed, and
                                the United Nations are on the offensive throughout the world. Axis
                                submarine operations have been substantially reduced and any large
                                threat to the security of the Western Hemisphere has been largely
                                removed.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Offensive action demands large expenditures of men, money,
                                materials, and equipment, with the result that the United States war
                                effort must be thrown into the offensive to the exclusion of the
                                defense.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Huge quantities of materials and equipment are being constantly
                                demanded from the war fronts to such an extent that the amount and
                                type of equipment available under Lend-Lease credit, on Lend-Lease
                                cash reimbursement, or direct contract for cash must of necessity be
                                modified.</item>
                            <pb facs="0112" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In view of the necessity for concentrating all productive
                                capabilities in backing up the United Nations’ offensive,
                                procurement under Lend-Lease credit shall in the future be approved
                                in general only for the following purposes, and within the period
                                ending June 30, 1945: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The development and preparation of such ground, naval, and
                                        air forces, with their supporting establishments and
                                        installations, as may be required for <hi rend="italic">Joint operations</hi> with United Nations forces within
                                        this hemisphere.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The training and equipping of such American republic
                                        forces as may be employed in conjunction with forces of the
                                        United Nations in offensive operations overseas.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The repair and maintenance of existing equipment essential
                                        to the war effort where facilities do not exist for making
                                        repairs locally.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The shipment of limited amounts of certain armaments and
                                        material deemed essential to the successful carrying on of
                                        the programs in which United States military and naval
                                        missions are engaged.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Certain raw materials, semi-finished, and finished products, which
                                are not procurable under the provisions set forth in paragraph four
                                above may be furnished on a cash basis; provided that no material
                                considered as arms, ammunition and implements of war, as enumerated
                                by Presidential Proclamation #2549, dated 9 April 1942 (56 Stat.,
                                1948), shall, without previous approval of the State, War and Navy
                                Departments, be furnished to any American republic except those
                                mutually agreed upon by the three Departments.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The procedure to be employed with respect to the procurement of
                                munitions of war or material destined for the armed forces of the
                                other American republics is as follows: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>No such munitions of war or material shall be procured in
                                        the United States without first having been screened and
                                        approved by the appropriate agencies of the War and Navy
                                        Departments.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The requirements which are clearly for Navy use, although
                                        procured by the United States War Department, should be
                                        presented to the United States Navy Department, which will
                                        negotiate with the War Department as to procurement;
                                        similarly, those clearly for Army use, although procured by
                                        the United States Navy Department, should be presented to
                                        the United States War Department, which will negotiate with
                                        the Navy Department as to procurement.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>All requests for materials which are destined for the use
                                        of the armed forces of the American republics and which are
                                        procurable by agencies other than the United States War and
                                        Navy Departments, should first be presented to the War or
                                        Navy Department, as indicated in paragraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi> above, and the service having cognizance will
                                        process for procurement through the prescribed
                                        channels.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>No American republic shall retransfer any munitions of war
                                        or material capable of use by armed forces which it has
                                        received from the United States to any other government or
                                        agency without first having obtained the approval of
                                        appropriate United States authorities.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>