<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Colombia ( (Lane))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d830</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">830</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-20T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-20T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-20T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-20T19:00:00-05:00" n="830"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d830">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.733/9–944: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lane</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-20T20:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 20, 1944—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1128. Department seriously concerned over Colombian Government proposal for
                    formation of official company to consolidate telecommunications and eliminate
                    All America Cables by declining to renew its present concession which expires in
                    February, 1945 as reurtel 1558 September 9.<note n="32" xml:id="d830fn32">Not
                        printed.</note> Obviously consolidation of telecommunications within
                    Colombia into a single company is a purely domestic matter <pb facs="0877"
                        n="863" xml:id="pg_863"/> with which Department is disinclined to intervene.
                    However, international traffic is a matter which deeply concerns this Government
                    as well as United States users of international facilities. The right of control
                    by Colombia of its own termini in the international service is fully recognized
                    but the Department must advert to the long and effectual service rendered by All
                    America Cables and Radio in the maintenance of effective international
                    telecommunications between the United States and Colombia and to the fact that
                    in spite of the handicap of Colombian terminal charges its service has been
                    sufficiently effective to attract from sixty to eighty percent of the
                    international traffic. In the efforts of the United States and Colombia to
                    faciliate trade and encourage an adequate exchange of information to the benefit
                    of both countries, this effectiveness should not be disregarded. It is for these
                    and other reasons that the Department instructs you urgently to request the
                    Colombian Government to delay the carrying out of its proposals as they affect
                    international telecommunications and that it give further study to this entire
                    problem. The Department will be glad to lend every appropriate assistance for
                    the purpose of this study.</p>
                <p>You may in your discretion also impress upon the appropriate Colombian
                    authorities the desirability of placing in effect at an early date the
                    northbound rate schedule negotiated between Colombia and the United States by a
                    recent exchange of notes.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
