<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="861" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d861">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">818.51/12–644</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Eugene LeBaron of the Export-Import
                                Bank</hi><note n="14" xml:id="d861fn14">Transmitted to San José in
                                instruction 779, December 6, 1944, not printed.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-29">November 29, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Dr. Francisco de P. Gutiérrez, Costa Rican Ambassador, called this
                            morning with regard to our Amendatory Agreement of September 28,
                                1944.<note n="15" xml:id="d861fn15">Agreement between the Government
                                of Costa Rica and the Export-Import Bank; not found in Department
                                files.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0900" n="886" xml:id="pg_886"/>
                        <p>The above-mentioned Amendatory Agreement would postpone by one year the
                            payment of the installments of principal on the loan made to Costa Rica
                            by our Agreement of July 9, 1942. The entire $2,000,000 under that line
                            of credit was disbursed. Interest only was payable to August 1, 1944.
                            All interest payments to that date were promptly made. The first
                            installment of principal, equivalent to 5% of the entire loan, will
                            become due and payable on February 1, 1945. Under the Amendatory
                            Agreement interest only would be paid on February 1 and August 1, 1945
                            and the first installment of principal would become due and payable on
                            February 1, 1946. The Amendatory Agreement “shall enter into effect only
                            on publication in the <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi> of the law
                            of approval adopted by the National Congress” of Costa Rica.</p>
                        <p>The President of Costa Rica submitted the Amendatory Agreement to
                            Congress and requested legislative approval thereof. The Congressional
                            Committee to which the bill was referred declined to report but issued a
                            statement, a copy of which is attached,<note n="16" xml:id="d861fn16">Not attached to file copy of memorandum.</note> calling upon the
                            Executive to request Export-Import Bank to postpone the payment of
                            installments of principal until one year after the establishment of
                            “world peace”.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador told me this morning that the President of Costa Rica has
                            not been able to effect the fiscal and monetary reforms which he had in
                            mind at the time he was inaugurated and which were outlined to us by Don
                            Julio Peña in May. The various Ministries are still spending money in
                            excess of requirements and probably in excess of sums appropriated in
                            the national budget. Taxes already on the statute books are not being
                            collected. Governmental economies have not been effected. Certain steps
                            have been taken to reform control of Government accounting and
                            disbursements but these reforms apparently have been of no avail to
                            date.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador says that any drastic steps to put Costa Rican finances on
                            a sound basis would result in an overthrow of the Picado Administration
                            either by peaceful or violent means. Apparently Don Julio’s usually
                            sound judgment was colored by his desire to aid the Picado
                            Administration when he informed us by cable on August 29 that the fiscal
                            changes previously discussed had been adopted. It was on the basis of
                            Don Julio’s cable and his recommendation that we agreed to postpone
                            payment of installments of principal by one year.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador stated that Costa Rica will be just as badly off in August
                            1946 as it was last August—that the situation cannot improve and that
                            any change will only be for the worse. Notwithstanding his frank
                            appraisal of the present situation in that country, the Ambassador is
                            anxious to obtain from Eximbank a revision of the Amendatory Agreement
                            improving its terms, from the Costa Rican <pb facs="0901" n="887" xml:id="pg_887"/> point of view, even though he may not be able to
                            obtain all the Congressional Committee wants. The Ambassador’s efforts
                            are due to (1) the declination of the Congressional Committee to
                            recommend legislative approval of the Amendatory Agreement in the hope
                            that more liberal terms could be obtained from Export-Import Bank and
                            (2) instructions to the Ambassador from the President.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador asked me to look into the above possibility informally and
                            to let him know whether or not Eximbank was prepared to review the terms
                            of the Amendatory Agreement. In the event of an affirmative answer, the
                            Ambassador will then file a formal request with us along the foregoing
                            lines. If our reply should be negative, he would so advise his
                            Government so that the Costa Rican Congress could then be requested
                            promptly to approve the Amendatory Agreement in its present form.</p>
                        <p>The tobacco tax, which is pledged further to secure our loan, produced
                            during the semester ending July 31, 1944 the sum of ¢1,199,771.62,
                            equivalent to $213,500. The installment of principal due February 1,
                            1945 is $100,000. Interest due will amount to $40,000. Total due on
                            February 1 will be $140,000. If the tobacco tax should produce between
                            August 1, 1944 and January 31, 1945 the same revenues it did during the
                            preceding semester, the sum thus deposited to service our loan would
                            leave an excess of approximately $73,500. During the month of August
                            1944, the only month for which we have any figures, the tobacco tax
                            produced ¢214,741.97. If this rate were maintained throughout the
                            present semester, revenues from this tax would produce ¢1,285,000,
                            equivalent to $215,000, or slightly in excess of the yield during the
                            preceding semester.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as the Bank was probably misinformed and should not postpone
                            amortization of principal for a vague or indefinite period, it is
                            recommended that consideration be given to withdrawing the Amendatory
                            Agreement of September 28 and allowing matters to proceed on the basis
                            contemplated at the time we made the loan in July 1942 and in accordance
                            with the Agreement of that date.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>