<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic Representatives in the
                    American Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d87</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">87</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="87"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d87">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/8–144</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives in the American
                            Republics</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d87fn2">The diplomatic representatives in Peru, Chile, Cuba,
                        Colombia, Venezuela, Uruguay, and Ecuador. The instruction to Ecuador was
                        slightly reworded. A similar circular was addressed on August 26, 1944, to
                        Guatemala, Honduras, El Salvador, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic,
                        Haiti, Paraguay, and Bolivia.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-01">August 1,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: Reference is made to the first paragraph of
                    Department’s secret circular instruction of June 24, 1944, subject “Statement on
                    Procurement of Military Material” (File no. 810.24/554).<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d87fn3">Instruction not printed, but for policy statement enclosed
                        therewith, see <ref target="#pg_97">p. 97</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Enclosed herewith is a draft of a note<note n="4" xml:id="d87fn4">Not
                        printed.</note> which you are requested to address to the Foreign Minister
                    of the country to which you are accredited. You will observe that the note
                    proposes that bilateral staff conversations be undertaken with a view to laying
                    the foundations for continued military collaboration between the American
                    Republics in the post-war period, and that if it is agreeable to the government
                    of the country to which you are accredited the United States will send officers
                    to undertake such conversations. You will recall in this connection that similar
                    conversations were undertaken in the summer and fall of 1940. Substantial
                    modifications in the understandings then reached must already be envisaged as
                    necessary in the post-war era. It is of course intended that these preliminary
                    conversations shall be conducted in the light of the fact that the establishment
                    of a general international organization with security functions is
                    anticipated.</p>
                <p>In presenting this note you are requested to emphasize orally that this
                    Government is anxious that its proposal to hold these conversations be treated
                    in the strictest confidence.</p>
                <p>In certain of the countries to which this circular is directed the armed forces
                    of this Government enjoy operational facilities granted for the duration of the
                    emergency. It is not proposed that the staff <pb facs="0120" n="106"
                        xml:id="pg_106"/> conversations suggested to the other governments concern
                    themselves with the post-war status of these facilities. In your discretion you
                    may so orally inform the Foreign Minister of the country to which you are
                    accredited if you feel there is any likelihood of the proposed staff
                    conversations’ being considered as pertaining to that question.</p>
                <p>You are requested to inform the Department by telegram of the reply which you may
                    receive to your note. Further instructions will be sent to you in the event that
                    you receive a favorable reply to your note. These instructions will not only
                    inform you of the contemplated date of arrival of the United States officers
                    assigned to undertake the conversations but also will make certain general
                    comments with regard to the manner in which the conversations should be carried
                    out.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>E. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
