<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Cuba ( (Braden) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d931</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">931</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-12-22T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-12-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-22T18:00:00-05:00" n="931"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d931">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.61351/12–2244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Braden</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 22, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 23—1 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1076. This afternoon I communicated the nonconfidential part of Department’s
                    telegram No. 952 December 21, 5 p.m. to Seiglie. He proposes immediately to
                    inform his Mission colleagues, telling them it is now incumbent on them to
                    decide whether they will accept the 3-cent price and then to call upon and
                    inform the President of their decision.</p>
                <p>Seiglie reiterated his often expressed conviction that, in one way or another, we
                    will obtain the sugar as needed and declared that in his last conversation with
                    Grau the President expressed appreciation for our having raised price for
                    political reason to 3 cents and said under no circumstances would he permit us
                    to be “held up”. Nevertheless the Cuban Government does not wish to appear as
                    putting pressure on industry nor to have United States Government appear to be
                    pressing Cuba.</p>
                <p>Seiglie explained that while at meeting, reported in my telegram No. 1068
                    December 14,<note n="58" xml:id="d931fn58">Not printed.</note> consensus of
                    Cubans was to insist on sale of two crops (Casanova and Santiesteban having
                    declared they would refuse flatly to consider sale of only one crop) he
                    nevertheless felt solution might be reached through sale of 1945 <hi
                        rend="italic">zafra</hi> alone. Wherefore as an entirely personal matter in
                    order that he might better advise the President as to how best to maneuver in
                    this situation he hoped I could ascertain and inform him, in strict confidence
                    whether or not we would be content to contract for the 1945 <hi rend="italic"
                        >zafra</hi> alone, the agreement in general to be the same as for 1944
                    excepting that price would be 3 cents and there would be included the security
                    clause, with such relatively minor alterations as he feels confident could be
                    agreed upon between two Governments; this agreement would also include the same
                    stipulations as to price and otherwise in respect of molasses and alcohol as in
                    the 1944 agreement and there would be included 250,000 long tons for local
                    consumption and 150,000 long tons for free market.</p>
                <p>I told him I did not like the idea myself and did not know whether the United
                    States Government agencies would even be willing to express an opinion. I added
                    that after all the next move was really up to the Cuban Mission; in this he
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>Please advise me whether or not you feel such an arrangement as Seiglie suggests
                    would be feasible and what, if anything, I may advise him in connection
                    herewith.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Braden</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
