<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="137" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d137">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.417/796</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-02-14"><hi rend="italic">February 14,
                                    1928</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Japanese Ambassador called upon me this morning at twelve o’clock and
                            referred to the conversation which I had with him on January 7
                            concerning the question of fur seals and the proposal which the
                            Government of the United States had made informally to him on <pb facs="0259" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> November 29, 1926 for a joint
                            Japanese-American scientific investigation into the migrating and
                            feeding habits of fur seals. It will be recalled that replying to that
                            proposition the Japanese Ambassador had stated that his Government
                            accepted the suggestion of the United States Government but desired that
                            experts of Soviet Russia and Great Britain be asked to participate with
                            experts of the United States and Japan in making the proposed
                            investigation, and that in the conversation which I had with him on
                            January 7 we had demurred to the suggestion that the investigation be
                            participated in by Russians and British on the ground that the question
                            to be investigated was one that particularly concerned the habits of the
                            American herd which was charged by the Japanese with becoming a menace
                            to the Japanese fishing industry.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador stated that he had not failed to telegraph at once the
                            reply which we had made to the Japanese suggestion to his Government and
                            that he now had received a reply from his Government stating that the
                            Japanese Government was very anxious to have Russians and British
                            experts participate in the proposed investigation, in view of the fact
                            that the data to be investigated would be used in a conference which
                            might be called in connection with a revision of the Convention which
                            the Japanese desired very much to have revised, and that if we failed
                            now to have the British and Russian experts present at this
                            investigation the matter might be delayed a long time in order that the
                            investigations made by the Japanese and Americans could be checked up by
                            the British and Russian investigators after the present investigation
                            had been completed.</p>
                        <p>He said that the Japanese Government was being very much pressed by
                            Japanese interests concerned to accomplish something in this matter, as
                            they were very much dissatisfied with the present situation and that the
                            Japanese Government was very much embarrassed by this pressure,
                            particularly at this time when the whole question was getting into the
                            political situation, and that the Japanese Government while appreciating
                            our position vis-à-vis Soviet Russia in any conference that might be
                            called, felt that there could be no real objection on our part to
                            participation by Russian and British scientists in an investigation
                            which would be limited solely to fact-finding and that the Japanese
                            Government hoped that we would reconsider our position in this matter
                            and that we would give a favorable reply to their suggestions,
                            particularly as such favorable reply would assist the Japanese very much
                            under present conditions.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that I would bring this matter to the attention of
                            the Secretary and that as soon as I learn the decision I would
                            communicate it to him.</p>
                        <closer><signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohnson</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>