<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-10-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.60p2/42</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Latvia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sussdorff</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Riga</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-10-15"><hi rend="italic">October 15,
                                1928</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received October 27.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5616</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Department’s Instruction No. 539, of July 10, 1928, transmitting the
                            President’s instrument of ratification of the Treaty of Friendship,
                            Commerce and Consular Rights between the United States and Latvia,
                            signed at Riga on April 20, 1928, for exchange by the Legation for a
                            similar instrument of ratification of the Treaty by the President of
                            Latvia. In the last paragraph of the Instruction under reference, the
                            Department informed the Legation that the United States Government will
                            be willing to accord the privilege of free entry of personal property
                            during their incumbency to Latvian consular officers in the United
                            States by administrative action whenever it receives assurances from the
                            Latvian Government in writing that the same privilege will be accorded
                            to American consular officers in Latvia.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, I have the honor to transmit herewith copies of a
                            Note which the Legation addressed to the Latvian Foreign Office on July
                            24, 1928,<note n="54" xml:id="d172fn54"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>,
                                    <ref target="#pg_227">p. 227</ref>.</note> concerning the
                            interpretation given by the Government of the United States to the
                            most-favored-nation clause with respect to consular privileges and
                            immunities, together with copies of a Note dated October 5, 1928, from
                            the Latvian Foreign Office <pb facs="0339" n="229" xml:id="pg_229"/>
                            stating that, in view of the fact that the United States Government is
                            willing to accord the privilege of free entry of personal property
                            during their incumbency to Latvian consular officers in the United
                            States on condition of reciprocity, consular officers of the United
                            States in Latvia during their incumbency shall enjoy the privilege of
                            free entry of personal property, beginning on October 15, 1928.</p>
                        <p>The substance of the Foreign Office Note of October 5, 1928, was
                            transmitted to the Department in the Legation’s telegram No. 87, on
                            October 12, 4 p.m., 1928, with the request that the Department telegraph
                            to the Legation the date on which similar privileges will be accorded to
                            Latvian Consuls of career in the United States.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Louis Sussdorff</hi>,
                            Jr.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Latvian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Balodis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American
                                    Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sussdorff</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Riga</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-10-05"><hi rend="italic">October 5,
                                        1928</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring myself to the note of His
                                Excellency the American Minister dated July 24th, 1928, I take
                                notice of the interpretation given by the Government of the United
                                States to the most-favoured-nation clause in respect of consular
                                privileges and immunities.</p>
                            <p>In view of the fact that your Government is willing to accord the
                                privilege of free entry of personal property during their incumbency
                                to Latvian consular officers in the United States on condition of
                                reciprocity, I have the honour to state in the name of my Government
                                that consular officers of the United States in Latvia during their
                                incumbency shall enjoy the privilege of free entry of personal
                                property.</p>
                            <p>I desire to point that the aforesaid privilege shall apply only to
                                State consular officers (<hi rend="italic">consules missi</hi>).</p>
                            <p>The present agreement shall become effective as from October 15th,
                                1928.</p>
                            <p>I beg [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed>A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Balodis</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>