<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Morrow) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="266"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.404/895<hi rend="superscript">2/9</hi>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morrow</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">México</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-07-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 23, 1928</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received July 30.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Kellogg</hi>: As you are already aware Mr. Olds
                    and I have kept up a personal correspondence during the past year with reference
                    to the religious controversy in Mexico. My letters to him of December 9, 1927,
                    February 21, March 16 and April 10, 1928, set forth in some detail the situation
                    down to and including the first visit of Father John J. Burke and Mr. Montavon
                    to Mexico City on April 3rd to 5th. Due to Mr. Olds’ departure from Washington
                    it appears desirable for your information that I should review very briefly the
                    earlier events and in some detail the developments in the situation since the
                    date of my last letter mentioned above.</p>
                <p>Before I came to Mexico last October I talked in Washington with Father John J.
                    Burke, the General Secretary of the National Catholic Welfare Conference, who
                    was sent to me by Judge Morgan JO’Brien and Cardinal Hayes. Subsequently, in
                    January during my visit to Havana for the Pan-American Conference, Father Burke
                    again called on me for the purpose of discussing the religious situation in
                    Mexico. As a consequence of these talks Father Burke requested me to ascertain
                    whether President Calles would receive him if he asked for an interview and came
                    to Mexico for that purpose. After my return to Mexico I ascertained that
                    President Calles would receive Father Burke and communicated the fact to the
                    latter. At this juncture publicity was given in the United States press to the
                    probability of such an interview. As a result of this publicity, the President
                    felt that no good purpose could at that time be served <pb facs="0437" n="327"
                        xml:id="pg_327"/> by Father Burke coming to Mexico. Subsequently the
                    difficulties caused by this incident were smoothed away and Father Burke,
                    accompanied by Mr. Montavon, the legal adviser of the National Catholic Welfare
                    Conference, came to Mexico and on April 4th in Veracruz, where the President was
                    spending a week’s holiday, the former had a long interview with the President,
                    lasting throughout the day. President Calles and Father Burke appeared to make
                    an excellent mutual impression one on the other and were able to discuss the
                    situation in a broad and liberal way and without rancor. They exchanged letters
                    which, if they had been ratified by Father Burke’s superiors, would have led to
                    a prompt resumption of public worship in the churches and might well have laid
                    the basis for a later modification of the objectionable laws.</p>
                <p>Father Burke on his return home had an unfortunate and untimely illness. Instead
                    of the matter being reported promptly to Rome by cable, as had been anticipated,
                    it was delayed apparently for the purpose of obtaining an expression of opinion
                    on a possible method of settlement from a group of Mexican Bishops. A meeting of
                    Mexican Bishops was held in San Antonio the latter part of April. I am not clear
                    whether this meeting was specially called to consider the possibility of a
                    settlement. At all events, Archbishop Ruiz, who upon the death of Archbishop
                    Mora y del Rio became the senior prelate of the Mexican Church and as such
                    presided at this meeting, was the only person present who knew of the exchange
                    of letters between the President and Father Burke. There were ten bishops at
                    this conference and they unanimously expressed a willingness to return to Mexico
                    under the present administration, and to leave the decision unconditionally to
                    the Holy See, but did, however, make some suggestions as to the terms that
                    should be included in any adjustment.</p>
                <p>Mr. Olds’ cables of May 9th and 10th, and his letters of May 5th and 9th,
                    informed me of the results of the San Antonio conference. Father Burke also
                    wrote me on May 9th covering the same ground and enclosing a letter signed by
                    himself and addressed to President Calles, in which he expressed the hope that
                    the President might give certain additional and more explicit assurances than
                    those contained in his letter of April 4th. After receipt of Mr. Olds’ cables,
                    but prior to the receipt of his and Father Burke’s letters, I talked with the
                    former by telephone. He agreed with me that it would be very difficult, if not
                    impossible, to get any further assurances from President Calles and that in any
                    event it would be quite useless to take the matter up with him by letter. I
                    suggested that it would be wise for Father Burke to make another visit to Mexico
                    and to bring with him Archbishop Ruiz. Although the latter had become the <pb
                        facs="0438" n="328" xml:id="pg_328"/> senior Mexican prelate, this, of
                    course, did not mean that he had any authority over the other Mexican bishops
                    and archbishops, nor authority to deal finally with the question of a
                    settlement.</p>
                <p>Mr. Olds, after a conference with Father Burke, telephoned me that Father Burke
                    and Archbishop Ruiz would be glad to come to Mexico. I at once tried to arrange
                    with President Calles for permission to have them come. President Calles was
                    absolutely opposed to Archbishop Ruiz coming. He stated that it would be
                    impossible for him to come without getting into discussions with Mexican
                    prelates and with prominent Catholic laymen in Mexico, and that publicity would
                    consequently result, as there was a small but powerful element in Mexico who had
                    steadfastly opposed any adjustment and would welcome the opportunity to impede
                    the work that Father Burke was trying to do. When I reported this to Mr. Olds by
                    telephone he conferred with Father Burke. Father Burke asked Mr. Olds to explain
                    that he would be greatly embarrassed if he were unable to bring Archbishop Ruiz
                    with him. I, therefore, made another effort with President Calles, and he
                    reluctantly assented to Archbishop Ruiz accompanying Father Burke.</p>
                <p>Father Burke, Archbishop Ruiz and Mr. Montavon, after being again met at the
                    border by the President’s representative, Mr. A. F. Smithers, proceeded as far
                    as Tacuba, a suburb of this city, on a private car which I had arranged to have
                    awaiting them at Laredo. From Tacuba they were taken by motor to the house of
                    Captain McBride, a member of the Embassy staff, where they remained from their
                    arrival on the morning of May 17th until their departure on the evening of May
                    19th. During this time they held no conferences except with the President and
                    with myself and in fact talked with no one else except those immediately
                    concerned in these conferences. It was, of course, desired to avoid premature
                    newspaper publicity and to defer to the wishes of the President as indicated in
                    the previous paragraph.</p>
                <p>On the day of their arrival I conferred at length with all three individually and
                    collectively. This conference lasted from 8 o’clock until 4, when I called on
                    President Calles and discussed the situation with him, after which at 5 o’clock
                    he received Father Burke, Archbishop Ruiz and Mr. Montavon, and myself. As at
                    the previous conference in Veracruz, Mr. James Smithers and Mr. A. F. Smithers
                    were also present, the former acting as interpreter. Father Burke presented the
                    suggestions of the Mexican Bishops as made at the San Antonio meeting. The
                    President answered and explained briefly why he could not comply with these
                    suggestions. Archbishop Ruiz then made a short statement to which the President
                    replied. Archbishop Ruiz expressed himself as willing to address a new letter
                        <pb facs="0439" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/> to President Calles in
                    substantially the form of the letter written by Father Burke to President Calles
                    on March 29, 1928, with the important addition that a special reference was made
                    to a public speech made by Dr. Puig Casauranc, Minister of Education, on April
                    15, 1928, at Celaya, which speech had been pleasing to the Church. It was
                    contemplated that this letter of Archbishop Ruiz should be answered in some such
                    form as that in which the President had already answered Father Burke, and that
                    when the proper authority had been received the two letters should be made
                    public and the priests then should be directed by the proper authorities to
                    return to their churches.</p>
                <p>In anticipation of the reaching of such an agreement as was reached, Mr. Olds and
                    I had arranged that he should remain available in Washington all of the night of
                    May 17th, so that any message we sent him by cable should be delivered during
                    the night to the office of the Papal Delegate in Washington, and cabled over to
                    Rome immediately so that an answer might be received as soon as possible. Father
                    Burke’s message to his associates was transmitted by me to Mr. Olds late in the
                    evening of May 17th. As the message indicates, it was contemplated that an
                    answer would be received from Rome in time to open the churches on Sunday, May
                    27th, which is the day celebrated as the Feast of the Pentecost.</p>
                <p>Father Burke, Archbishop Ruiz and Mr. Montavon had planned to wait here until
                    they received the answer from Rome. On the 19th, however, a telegram was
                    received directing their immediate return to Washington for the purpose of
                    proceeding to Rome. They accordingly left Mexico City that evening. For some
                    reason, that neither Mr. Olds nor I have understood, it was apparently decided
                    that Archbishop Ruiz alone should go to Rome, despite the fact that Father Burke
                    had been the one who had carried on the negotiations from the outset. Archbishop
                    Ruiz, unaccompanied either by Father Burke or Mr. Montavon, accordingly left New
                    York for Rome on May 26th on the S. S. <hi rend="italic">Leviathan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>When Archbishop Ruiz reached Paris the fact of his journey to Rome became known
                    through a cable to the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> of June 1. A day or
                    two later when Archbishop Ruiz reached Rome there was considerable publicity, a
                    portion of which got into the Mexican press. From the messages which came from
                    Archbishop Ruiz to Father Burke I was fully satisfied that Archbishop Ruiz had
                    been misquoted. The fact remains, however, that his visit to Rome became known,
                    and that this fact led to a great deal of pressure being brought upon the
                    authorities in Rome by those associated with the Church in Mexico who bitterly
                    opposed a settlement.</p>
                <pb facs="0440" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/>
                <p>While I was ill the North I had several conferences with Father Burke, at some of
                    which Mr. Olds was present. The matter by this time was quite out of Father
                    Burke’s hands. Through Father Burke, Mr. Olds and I met the Papal Delegate,
                    Archbishop Fumasoni Biondi, twice. Our first talk with the delegate was in the
                    early part of June, and our second talk was almost the last of June. Apparently
                    the only official action at Rome was the reference of the subject to the
                    Congregation on Extraordinary Foreign Affairs. Such personal communications as
                    had come from Rome to Father Burke indicated, however, that while no definite
                    decision had been reached, the Vatican was very reluctant to authorize the
                    delivery of the letter which Archbishop Ruiz had prepared and left for delivery
                    when the proper authority was received. This reluctance of Rome to act seemed to
                    be due partly to representations which came from Mexico opposing any settlement,
                    and partly due to representations from Mexico that it would be better to await
                    and make the settlement with General Obregon, and partly due to the
                    unwillingness of the authorities at Rome to proceed without more specific
                    assurances than those provided in the interchange of letters.</p>
                <p>I got back to Mexico on the evening of July 3rd. I saw the President on the
                    morning of the 7th of July for an hour and a half and discussed the whole
                    question with him. James Smithers acted as interpreter. I told the President
                    about my talks with Father Burke in the United States, and explained some of the
                    difficulties. I further told him that I was certain that Archbishop Ruiz had not
                    expressed the opinions attributed to him in the press. I told him further that
                    Father Burke was still hopeful of a favorable outcome, but that there was no
                    doubt that some pressure was being brought upon the Vatican authorities to make
                    no adjustment until General Obregon came in, or to make no adjustment unless
                    further and more definite assurances were given. President Calles reviewed the
                    whole course of the negotiations with me with care and with accuracy. He
                    expressed a very high opinion of Father Burke. He said that he had never
                    expected any favorable outcome after he heard that Father Burke, himself, was
                    not going to Rome. He stated that when the matter became public the Government
                    had received inquiries from its foreign representatives in many countries. They
                    also had received inquiries from priests in Mexico as to whether they could go
                    back into the churches. They also had received criticism from prominent
                    supporters of the Government objecting to what was called surrender to the
                    Church. All of this had been very embarrassing to his Government. He had thought
                    at first that it was his duty to make a statement, but he had concluded that the
                    advice I had sent him through Mr. Clark was wise and that he would make no
                    statement <pb facs="0441" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> until the Vatican announced
                    its decision, that when that decision was announced it would be necessary for
                    him to make a statement, at which time he would probably state exactly what he
                    had done, probably making public the correspondence already exchanged.</p>
                <p>He further stated that while the number of people in Mexico opposing the
                    adjustment was small, they were people who had been very influential in the old
                    regime and that if they were to direct the activities of the Church when it came
                    back he should much prefer that the Church should not come back.</p>
                <p>On Monday, July 16th, Governor Aaron Saenz of Nuevo Leon, formerly Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs in the Cabinet of President Calles, and long time intimate
                    friend of, and recently campaign manager for, General Obregon, informed me that
                    President-elect Obregon, who had arrived in Mexico City the preceding day,
                    wanted to have a long talk with me. I made an appointment to meet General
                    Obregon the next afternoon, Tuesday, at 5 o’clock. On Tuesday morning Governor
                    Saenz came to the Embassy and talked with me at considerable length about
                    governmental matters, including the religious question. He assured me that there
                    was absolutely nothing in the story that General Obregon was interfering in any
                    way with the proposed adjustment, that President Calles had consulted fully with
                    General Obregon about it, and that General Obregon was hoping that the <hi
                        rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> might be worked out as soon as possible to
                    the end that a later readjustment of the laws might be made during the era of
                    peace which he hoped would prevail during his administration. Governor Saenz
                    left me to go to the luncheon at which General Obregon was shot.</p>
                <p>The foregoing is a rough review and record of the actual course of events and the
                    conversations and principal correspondence which I have had in regard to the
                    religious situation here. This seems to have been necessary because I think that
                    both Father Burke and myself are in danger of getting somewhat off the track and
                    that others concerned directly or indirectly in any possible settlement are
                    perhaps gravely in error in regard to the real facts of the situation. There is
                    no doubt that certain Catholics here and elsewhere believe that President Calles
                    is seeking some sort of peace. They do not know that Father Burke’s letter of
                    March 29, 1928, asked for the interview of April 4th, which President Calles
                    agreed to with some reluctance, and that the subsequent talk with Father Burke
                    and Archbishop Ruiz was brought about on their initiative and was agreed to by
                    the President with still greater reluctance. The President, ever since his
                    answer of August 19, 1926, to the Mexican Episcopate, has been consistent in
                    expressing his inability to initiate or promise any changes in the Constitution
                    or laws, at least under existing conditions. I <pb facs="0442" n="332"
                        xml:id="pg_332"/> believe Father Burke is fully aware of these facts and
                    understands the conditions from which they arise. It was his clear grasp of the
                    situation which not only permitted him to discuss the question with the
                    President in such a broad minded and liberal spirit as to obtain from him a more
                    sympathetic response than had previously appeared possible, but also enabled him
                    to convince some of his associates, both of the American and of the Mexican
                    church, with whom he has had opportunity to discuss the matter. It is for these
                    reasons that I have felt strongly the desirability of his being able to place
                    the case personally before those with whom rests the final authority.</p>
                <p>To show how widely different the feeling of Father Burke and some of the Mexican
                    prelates is, I am enclosing a translation of a memorandum which came to me
                    through Mr. Amor.<note n="47" xml:id="d266fn47">Not printed.</note> The author
                    of the memorandum was Bishop Mora. Mr. Amor called on me the other day to talk
                    about his San Gabriel property. During the course of the talk he referred to the
                    Church question and said that I ought to talk with Bishop Mora, that he
                    understood the situation better than anybody else. I told him that I should
                    consider it improper to discuss the Church matter with Bishop Mora, that the
                    matter was one which the State and the Church should settle between themselves,
                    and that there was nothing the United States Government could do in the matter;
                    that I, as a person, was entirely sympathetic with both sides and regretted that
                    they could not get together, but that if men like Bishop Mora would assist the
                    efforts of Archbishop Ruiz instead of trying to impede them, it might be
                    possible that the Church and the State could work out some <hi rend="italic"
                        >modus vivendi</hi>. A day or two later Mr. Amor called and left with Mr.
                    Alan Winslow<note n="48" xml:id="d266fn48">First secretary of the Embassy in
                        Mexico.</note> a memorandum in Spanish, of which the enclosed is a
                        translation.<note n="47" xml:id="d266fn50">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I am also enclosing you a translation of an anonymous document purporting to be
                    the June Bulletin of the “National League for the Defense of Religious
                        Liberty”.<note n="47" xml:id="d266fn51">Not printed.</note> Similar
                    bulletins are issued from time to time anonymously. It is probable that
                    bulletins of this type, which actually take credit for the derailing of trains,
                    are put out by the most irresponsible type of person. The Government, of course,
                    is able to obtain copies of all these documents, and naturally associates this
                    “League” with the “Federation for the Defense of Religious Liberty” which is
                    referred to in terms of approbation in the Encyclical of November 18, 1926.
                    While the “League” may, and in all probability has, no connection whatever with
                    the Church, this confusion in names does, however, add to that distrust of
                    church authorities inside and outside of Mexico which people in the Government
                    undoubtedly have.</p>
                <pb facs="0443" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/>
                <p>In considering the situation at the present moment I must revert to my letter of
                    March 16, 1928, in which I wrote: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In stating that I am satisfied that such a letter can be secured from
                            the President, I am assuming that the conditions will not substantially
                            change before the effort is formally made to get President Calles to
                            give such assurance. Mr. Lagarde<note n="49" xml:id="d266fn49">M. Ernest
                                Lagarde, secretary of French Legation in Mexico, transferred to
                                French Foreign Office.</note> is in my opinion correct in stating
                            that ‘all of the conditions at this moment are favorable, and that delay
                            may spell loss of an opportunity which may not soon come again’. It must
                            not be forgotten that actual military operations are now going on in the
                            field and that they are believed by the Government to be incited,
                            financed and led by the Church. Something may happen any day which would
                            make it impossible for one party or the other to act”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>You will note that the foregoing is a quotation from my letter of March 16th.
                    March 16th is now more than four months away. The letter that President Calles
                    signed and delivered to Father Burke is dated April 4th. April 4th is now more
                    than three months away. The visit of Archbishop Ruiz here was on May 17th.
                    Before he went to Rome he left a letter signed in escrow for delivery to
                    President Calles when the proper authority was received. It was almost two
                    months ago that that letter was delivered in escrow. Meanwhile, however,
                    something has happened. President-elect Obregon has been assassinated. At the
                    present time it would be very difficult, if not impossible, for President Calles
                    to go ahead with the adjustment as arranged between Father Burke and himself,
                    even if the Church were now ready to go ahead. A member of the Catholic Church
                    in Mexico with whom I talked yesterday—a person who has been earnestly desirous
                    of an adjustment—told me that in his opinion no Government could make any
                    adjustment of the controversy at the present time without falling from power;
                    that he thought the killing of Obregon put off any adjustment for at least a
                    year. He deplored this fact greatly and stated that he thought those Catholics
                    were very unwise who had thought that it were better to postpone an adjustment
                    until General Obregon came in. He stated that he had always felt that President
                    Calles would be able to make an adjustment more favorable to the Church than any
                    successor of his would in the near future be able to make. He further stated
                    that the authorities in Rome had constantly been deceived as to the strength of
                    the feeling against the Church in Mexico.</p>
                <p>I do not concur in the foregoing statement so far as it means that an adjustment
                    must be postponed for a year. I do concur, however, that it is absolutely futile
                    to discuss the question at the moment.</p>
                <p>Of course the assassination of General Obregon throws a very <pb facs="0444"
                        n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> heavy burden upon President Calles. I am satisfied
                    that he does not, himself, want to continue in the presidency longer. If he goes
                    out, who is to take his place? It is too early to say what the outcome will be.
                    I have seen him but once since the assassination, and then only for a few
                    moments. I regret the form of some statements that have been issued here and in
                    Rome. It is, of course, not easy for either side to see the point of view of the
                    other, or even to believe in the sincerity of the other. The remarkable thing to
                    me about Father Burke’s two visits was that he had succeeded in presenting a
                    point of view of the Church which President Calles had not theretofore known,
                    and he had also succeeded in getting a point of view of the Government which I
                    am sure he could have made clear to the high authorities of the Church if he had
                    had an opportunity to do so. But all this discussion is inopportune for the
                    moment. Some of the work that Father Burke has done may have to be done over
                    again. How soon we can begin to do it over again, we do not know.</p>
                <p>One of the tragic things about the present situation is that Father Burke came
                    down to Mexico to prove to President Calles that it was desirable that President
                    Calles deal directly with Rome because Rome would be wiser and more conciliatory
                    than the Mexican hierarchy. I think he did succeed in convincing President
                    Calles of that fact. Unfortunately, however, we were not able to find out
                    whether Rome really desired to make the kind of an adjustment with the Calles
                    administration which Calles was willing and able to make. Before Father Burke
                    proceeds further along the line of the existing adjustment, I think it is only
                    fair that he should know what the position of Rome actually is upon this
                    question. President Calles is likely to be much more interested during the next
                    few weeks in the vital problem presented to Mexico by the death of Obregon.
                    Important as an adjustment of the religious controversy is to the future of
                    Mexico, it is a minor problem here during the next few weeks. The problem of the
                    succession is the vital problem.</p>
                <p>I hope this letter will not seem too pessimistic. Political changes come quickly
                    in Mexico. It is possible that the time may come sooner than we expect when the
                    religious question can be taken up again. If that time should come it is
                    imperative that those who seek an adjustment on behalf of the Church should know
                    just what the ultimate authorities of the Church are ready to do. I feel that I
                    have already pressed President Calles to a point which is perhaps beyond that to
                    which his own judgment would lead him. I cannot afford to press him any further
                    unless there is some reason for thinking that we are working to a practical end
                    that the authorities of the Church really desire.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dwight W. Morrow</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
