<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-01-17T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-01-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/5276: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Chargé in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Munro</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-01-17T11:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">January 17,
                                        1928—11 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>17. [Paraphrase.] Your telegram No. 30, January 16, 2 p.m.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>In response to your recommendation, we authorize you, at your discretion,
                            to present the following note to President Diaz: [End paraphrase.]</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Various rumors have come to the attention of the Department of State
                                to the effect that its present attitude is being misrepresented to,
                                and possibly misunderstood by the Government of Nicaragua. In order
                                that there may be no doubt on this subject the Department has
                                instructed me to state: <list>
                                    <label>1st.</label>
                                    <item>That the policy and attitude of the United States in
                                        relation to Nicaraguan affairs has undergone no change or
                                        modification whatever.</item>
                                    <label>2nd.</label>
                                    <item>That the agreement entered into by Colonel Stimson as the
                                        personal representative of the President of the United
                                        States, and evidenced by the exchange of communications
                                        between the Presidents of the two countries, is regarded as
                                        a subsisting obligation in all its integrity, that the
                                        United States fully intends to carry out its pledges and
                                        obligations thereunder, and expects the Government of
                                        Nicaragua similarly to carry out its pledges and obligations
                                        thereunder.</item>
                                    <label>3rd.</label>
                                    <item>That the objection to the pending legislation is, in the
                                        judgment of the Department, absolutely untenable as a
                                        proposition of constitutional law.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0535" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/>
                                    <label>4th.</label>
                                    <item>That a refusal to enact the legislation can only be
                                        considered by the Department as a breach of faith pledged in
                                        a solemn agreement entered into by the Government of
                                        Nicaragua with the President of the United States.</item>
                                    <label>5th.</label>
                                    <item>That the powers conferred by the proposed law upon the
                                        electoral board constituted as therein provided, are deemed
                                        to be absolutely essential to the execution of the agreement
                                        and to the holding of the fair election, which this
                                        Government has pledged itself to supervise and fully intends
                                        to carry out.</item>
                                    <label>6th.</label>
                                    <item>That further delay would not only create a most painful
                                        impression here, but would compel this Government to
                                        consider seriously what other measures it can and should
                                        take in order to meet the obligations which it has
                                        definitely assumed with respect to all parties
                                        concerned.”</item>
                                </list></p></quote>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Olds</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>